<text id="autogum_academic_doc134" title="The Legal Boundaries of ‘Public Purpose’ in India and South Africa: A Comparative Assessment in Light of the Voluntary Guidelines" shortTile="legal-boundaries" author="Björn Hoops, Nicholas  K. Tagliarino" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-445X/8/10/154/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. The Public Purpose/Public Interest Requirement in South African Law</head>
<p>
Section 25(2) of the South African Constitution of 1996 only permits an expropriation for a public purpose or in the public interest and based on laws of general application. Section 2(1) of the Expropriation Act empowers the Minister of Public Works to expropriate property for public purposes. The first part of the following analysis discusses the definition of ‘public purpose’ and ‘public interest’ in South African law. The second part then analyses the extent to which the legislature and the courts define ‘public purpose’ and ‘public interest’, and the remaining discretion of the competent authority to define the expropriation’s purpose. The third part evaluates whether South African law complies with VGGT 16.1. </p>

<head> 4.1. The Definition of ‘Public Purpose’ and ‘Public Interest’</head>
<p>
In the pre-constitutional era, under the Apartheid regime, until the Interim Constitution entered into force in 1993, expropriation was only possible for a ‘public purpose’. The courts defined ‘public purposes’ as all purposes that pertain to and benefit the public (in contradistinction to private individuals). This definition is very abstract and appears to cover an endless variety of purposes. Accordingly, the courts approved expropriations for the security and privacy of the Prime Minister, urban development, the maintenance of the national telecommunication system, the preservation of vegetation, and the maintenance of water quality. A project even served a public purpose if it only indirectly contributed to these purposes, for instance through the provision of housing for technicians who would then maintain the telecommunication system. In the famous <hi rend="italic">Van Streepen</hi> judgment, Smalberger JA held that also the ‘public interest’ could justify an expropriation and found that while it did not serve a public purpose, even the private supply of strategically important products served a public interest that could justify an expropriation. Only projects that solely benefited private individuals could not justify an expropriation. </p>

<p>With the constitutional era came new uncertainties. The definition of the newly introduced ‘public interest’ remains unclear; Section 25(4)(a) of the Constitution only clarifies that property may be expropriated for land reform purposes. What seems settled is that ‘public purpose’ is a narrower category that in its entirety forms part of the greater category ‘public interest’, and that the drafters of the Constitution intended to provide a broad constitutional authorisation for expropriation. The Constitutional Court has yet to provide clarity on the meaning of ‘public purpose’ and ‘public interest’. To shed light on the meaning of these terms this sub-section analyses the applicable jurisprudence of the High Court and the Supreme Court of Appeal. As both public purposes and the public interest can justify an expropriation, this contribution does not deal with the distinction between these two terms any further. </p>

<p>The analysis shows that the courts have adopted the abstract definition of ‘public purpose’ from the pre-constitutional era and construe ‘public purpose’ and ‘public interest’ very broadly. Even indirect economic benefits of private business projects may validly justify an expropriation. In <hi rend="italic">eThekwini Municipality v Sotirios Spetsiotis</hi>, the KwaZulu-Natal High Court decided that an upgrade of the Durban beachfront for the 2010 soccer World Cup constituted a public purpose. Urban development for a global sports event is thus a public purpose. While the upgrade could still directly benefit the public through the improvement of private infrastructure, <hi rend="italic">Bartsch Consult (Pty) Limited v Mayoral Committee of the Maluti-A-Phofung Municipality</hi> concerned the construction of a private shopping complex. Ebrahim J considered for the Free State High Court that it was the responsibility of the municipalities to ensure their economic viability and prevent rising unemployment and poverty. He found that the shopping complex would provide strategic economic advantages to the municipality in the form of greater financial returns, which would then result in a healthier and wealthier environment. Therefore, Ebrahim J held the shopping complex to be in the public interest. </p>
</text>
