<text id="autogum_academic_doc655" title="Magnesium Intake Predicts Bone Turnover in Postmenopausal Black South African Women" shortTile="magnesium-intake" author="Hattie  H. Wright, Marlena  C. Kruger, Willem  D. Schutte, Edelweiss Wentzel-Viljoen, Iolanthe  M. Kruger, Herculina  S. Kruger" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6643/11/10/2519/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The ethnic differences in bone mineral density (BMD) and fracture risk have been described in both high-income, and low- and middle-income countries. In South Africa, black populations have been reported to have a higher overall BMD and a lower fracture risk compared to white populations. However, evidence point towards a lower than expected BMD in black South African women and an increased risk for poor bone health and fractures. Reduced BMD among black South African women may be associated with the predominance of environmental exposures over genetic factors. </p>

<p>Earlier studies identified that the migration of black South Africans into urban areas significantly affects their health status with an increase in the incidence of obesity and non-communicable diseases related to urbanisation, the nutrition transition, and decreased physical activity. A high body mass index (BMI) has been suggested to protect against low BMD by some, while others have found excessive fat mass to be associated with low BMD and not protecting against osteoporosis. Similarly, lean mass and not fat mass strongly correlated with bone health in black South African women. Therefore, the high prevalence of obesity among black South African women may be a contributing factor to a lower BMD in this group. In addition to high fat mass levels, increased circulating inflammatory cytokines in obese individuals have also been linked to a low BMD. </p>

<p>Diet is a known modifiable risk factor for optimal bone health, with the value of specific nutrients such as dietary calcium and vitamin D well established. More recently, a holistic approach acknowledging the interaction between foods, nutrients, and food components on health outcomes, including bone health, was proposed to investigate the association of dietary patterns with the markers of bone health. The dietary patterns associated with reduced bone health are characterised by the high intakes of refined cereals, processed meats, fried foods and sweet foods, while patterns high in fruit, vegetables, and a prudent diet pattern are positively associated with bone health. In the Northwest Province of South Africa, an accelerated nutrition transition among black Africans resulted in a shift from a plant-based diet to an animal food-based diet which is energy-dense but nutrient poor and therefore, may negatively impact bone health. </p>

<p>Therefore, the purpose of this prospective study was to investigate the association between nutrient intake and dietary patterns (exposures) with changes in bone turnover and BMD (bone health outcomes) in postmenopausal urban black South African women over two years. </p>
</text>
