<text id="autogum_academic_doc218" title="Information Contained in Molecular Motion" shortTile="information-contained" author="J  Gerhard Müller" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1099-4300/21/11/1052/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The concept of entropy was introduced by Clausius in the nineteenth century into the evolving science of thermodynamics. In this context a change in entropy  was defined as the amount of heat, , reversibly exchanged between two macroscopic bodies maintained at an absolute temperature :

(1)

</p>

<p>Later, this macroscopically measurable quantity was explained in the context of statistical mechanics as molecular disorder contained in a macroscopic body. According to Boltzmann, entropy is related to the number  of microscopic states of motion which are consistent with the limited macroscopic knowledge about the molecular system:

(2)

</p>

<p>One of the most striking facts about entropy is its tendency to increase in an irreversible manner within an isolated system. This tendency was interpreted early on as arising from the statistics of motion of large numbers of particles rather than from any irreversibility in the underlying laws of motion of the individual molecules themselves. Considering the intrinsic reversibility of the basic mechanical laws it was argued by Maxwell that a being <hi rend="italic">“whose faculties are so sharpened that it can follow the course of individual molecules”</hi> should be able to operate a trap door, inserted into a vessel homogeneously filled with gas, to produce either temperature or pressure differences inside the gas that would allow mechanical work to be extracted from a single macroscopic heat reservoir, maintained at a finite temperature . Such a gain in energy, clearly, would be in sharp contrast with the postulate imposed by the second law of thermodynamics and thus create a paradox. Since its invention in 1871, Maxwell’s demon paradox has fascinated researchers up to the present day. A good coverage of the historical developments can be found in the books of Rex and Leff. </p>

<p>A decisive step forward in the analysis of Maxwell’s demons´ paradox was made by Leo Szilard in 1929. Considering the motion of a single atom, enclosed in a finite volume  and in contact with a heat reservoir of temperature , Szilard showed that knowledge about the location of the atom can be used to extract mechanical work from a single-molecule gas. This example showed that work extraction from a thermal reservoir is not for free but that it has to be paid for in terms of a new “currency”, called information. The other important achievement was that Szilard’s analysis established a connection between the physical concepts of entropy and abstract information, showing that 1 bit of abstract information corresponds to  units of entropy. This definition of a bit as the unit of information is generally regarded as the starting point of modern information theory.  </p>

<p>A further important step in the analysis of Maxwell’s demon paradox was the realization that the information gained in a physical measurement is burdened with an energy cost that overwhelms the energy gained in operating a Maxwell’s demon device. Brillouin’s initial analysis, which claimed that this energy cost is associated with the measurement process itself was later challenged by arguments that reversible measurements might in principle be conceivable. Even later it was argued that operating a Maxwell’s demon device entails storage of the information intermittently obtained, and that the energy cost of information ultimately needs to be paid when this information is erased again. It was argued that this latter step of erasure is unavoidable to arrive at a fully cyclic process of information gain and work extraction and that therefore the energy cost of information erasure is a more inescapable necessity than the energy cost of measurement and information gain. This latter resolution of Maxwell’s demons’ paradox became known as Landauer’s principle. Brillouin and Landauer both agree in that ultimately an energy of at least  needs to be expended to gain one bit of information and to ultimately conserve the validity of the second law. </p>

<p>Following discussions of Maxwell’s demon’s paradox, it can be observed that some authors express discomfort with the idea of thermodynamic information as the processes of gaining, receiving and maintaining information through measurement either explicitly or implicitly assume the involvement of intelligent beings. It is argued that such an involvement introduces an element of subjectivity into the definition of entropy, which is unacceptable if entropy is to be considered as an element of physical reality that exists independent of the existence of human beings and of human observation.  </p>
</text>
