<text id="autogum_academic_doc360" title="Integrated Water Quality Governance and Sectoral Responsibility: The EU Water Framework Directive’s Impact on Agricultural Sector Policies in Norway" shortTile="integrated-water" author="Sissel Hovik" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4441/11/11/2215/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Results</head><head> 4.1. The Participants’ Assessment of the Water Governance Arrangements</head>
<p>
The Norwegian Water Regulation introduced cross-sector and multi-level networks at the RBD and SD level. Their main task is to formulate and agree upon RBD Management Plans and Programmes of Measures. Since the management plan is not legally binding for either state sector authorities or municipalities, compliance is supposed to be ensured through participation in the entire process of formulating the plan (from identifying and characterizing water bodies, through identifying crucial matters and defining environmental goals, to the formulation of the plan and program) and through agreement on the content of the plan and program. Surveys to the members of the RBD boards revealed strong support for this system of water governance among all groups of actors. The RBD board members were optimistic regarding the system’s ability to improve the ecological status of water and its ability to protect and safeguard the water environment. Furthermore, they appreciated the fact that actors representing different policy sectors meet at the RBD and SD boards, and that the River Basin Districts are the units for cross-sector coordination. However, they recognized several shortcomings and challenges. A crucial problem was the ability to balance different national sector policy goals and solve conflicts of interests among such goals. The planning process makes the different actors’ interests and objectives visible but does not resolve conflicts of interest among the actors (p. 87). Agriculture is one of the sectors that quite a few of the RBD board members found hard to reach agreement on, together with fish farming and hydroelectric power production (see <figure>Figure 2</figure> below).  </p>

<p>Interestingly, more RBD members reported problems reaching agreements in 2015, the year for finalizing the management plan and program of measures, than in 2013. This indicates that the network cooperation process had not managed to solve conflicts of interest. These conflicts became more apparent when the time came to agree on measures. Informants representing the farmers’ organizations claimed that it was impossible to combine the national goal of increased food production with the ambition of no discharges to water from farming. An informant representing the regional agricultural authority (the county governor’s office) claimed that there were limits to the environmental demands they can impose on the farmers and still expect increased food production (p. 170).  </p>

<p>As mentioned above, agriculture has been identified as one of the three main pressures on Norwegian waters. In the two RBDs of Vest-Viken and Glomma, discharge of nutrient from agriculture land (particularly grain fields and vegetable fields) causing eutrophication was the main problem related to agriculture. In these districts, measures targeting agriculture were the most numerous. The main body of measures aim to target diffuse sources of nutrient loss. The listed measures were efforts to optimize fertilization, to avoid plowing in the autumn, to lay out vegetation belts along rivers and streams, and to construct hydro-technical installations and coffer dams. There were also some measures targeting point source discharges of nutrients, such as manure storages, silos, and green houses.  </p>

<head> 4.2. The Agriculture Sector Policy Objectives and Instruments</head>
<p>
Norway introduced legal policy instruments that aimed to regulate pollution from agriculture in the 1970s. Initially, the regulations mainly aimed to target point source pollution. Later, the focus turned towards diffuse sources of nutrient discharges, partly because of Norway’s responsibilities in accordance with the North Sea Declaration. For example, regulation of manure storages was introduced in 1977. A major revision of this policy came in 1989. The main changes aimed to regulate the amount and time of manure spreading. These regulations were accompanied by grants supporting and motivating farmers’ investments in manure storages and silos, and regulations demanding fertilization programs at each farm. Additional measures and efforts were introduced in heavily polluted lakes and rivers, combined in task programs. These were voluntary measures, backed up by economic incentives. The policy regime logic determining the agriculture sector’s policy objectives and instruments was built on a preference for voluntary measures backed by public- supported consultancy and economic incentives.  </p>

<p>During the 2003 agricultural negotiation, the Ministry of Agriculture and Food and the farmers’ organizations agreed to introduce a National Environmental Program in 2004. This program gathers the policy sector’s environmental efforts and has been revised regularly since its inception. The program lists the national goals and identifies the measures and instruments targeting the industry’s pressures upon the natural environment. It is formulated by the Norwegian Agriculture Agency, and approved by the Ministry of Agriculture and Food, after consulting the farmers’ organizations. The amount of money allocated to this program is settled through the annual negotiations between the ministry and the farmers’ organizations.  </p>
</text>
