<text id="autogum_academic_doc614" title="Evolution of a Landscape Phage Library in a Mouse Xenograft Model of Human Breast Cancer" shortTile="evolution-landscape" author="James  W. Gillespie, Liping Yang, Laura  Maria De Plano, Murray  A. Stackhouse, Valery  A. Petrenko" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1999-4915/11/11/988/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion and Conclusions</head>
<p>
In this study, we considered the following two major factors that could influence the evolution of the f8/9 landscape phage library in mice: (1) its multidisperse characteristics as revealed in soft agar electrophoresis and (2) organ- and tumor-specific targets for phage binding interactions that can arise from organ- or tissue-specific gene expression. We showed that modified p8 proteins displaying a fusion peptide along the length of the filamentous phage particle would create vastly different particles, each containing unique physicochemical features and supporting complex interactions within a defined microenvironment. As reflected in our in vitro migration study, the presence of random fusion peptides with charged amino acids in landscape phages results in significant changes in the ionization state of the phage particle leading to differences in surface charge and their subsequent ability to migrate through an agarose gel, demonstrated previously with isolated clones. This unique, emergent feature of landscape phages cannot be translated to p3-type libraries as the occurrence of p3 in only five copies limits the ability of a displayed fusion peptide to significantly change the physicochemical properties of the entire particle. It can be envisioned that local changes in pH within a tissue microenvironment may modify the surface charge of landscape phage particles, exposing a previously hidden binding epitope or also hiding a previously accessible binding epitope allowing enhanced penetration or retention within a particular microenvironment. </p>

<p>Following an extensive meta-analysis study of nanoparticle biocompatibility in vivo, it was concluded that functional nanocarriers had a slightly negative surface charge, moderate to high solubility, and particle sizes in the range of ~100–200 nm in diameter. Given that landscape phage libraries display peptide fusions that can dramatically alter the surface profile of the phage, we hypothesized that libraries of phage particles represent ideal nanoparticle systems to test the effects of a displayed peptide on tissue-selective accumulation within the local microenvironment while maintaining other critical parameters like particle size and shape. In our study, we observed similar trends of tissue accumulation as reported previously for p3-type libraries. Analysis of 3-mer frequency in each tissue revealed that a significant portion of motifs were shared across all tissues, leading to nonspecific uptake and clearance or had very low occurrences. We were able to identify several families of motifs that were enriched in a tissue-selective manner. Some of the identified motifs corresponded with previously identified tissue-selective motifs. However, we identified many motifs that were not reported, suggesting that the type of peptide display will have a significant effect on tissue accumulation or pharmacokinetics. </p>

<p>The underlying hypothesis in our in vivo evolution study of landscape phages is based on the assumption that tissue-specific gene expression provides a context-dependent pathway for development of tissue specificity. These tissue-specific gene expression profiles provide transcriptional and translational control for tissue-specific synthesis of corresponding proteins and their underlying protein-domain networks. It was suggested that components of these protein-domain networks could be identified through in vitro or in vivo targeted evolution of EBU/SLiM-harboring phage displayed peptide libraries such as the multivalent landscape phage library used in this project. In accordance with this hypothesis, we identified the following three major types of EBU motifs: (1) motifs common for all tissues; (2) motifs specific for organs with functionally related tissues and similar correlated patterns of co-expressed genes; and (3) motifs unique to single tissues with unique functions, which may be related to tissue-specific gene expression profiles within the tissues or to specific physical features of the local microenvironment. Here, we demonstrated that the frequencies of several 3-mer motifs are shared across all tissue types (<figure>Figure 5</figure>A, black arrow) and can be representative of interactions with protein products of “housekeeping-like” genes expressed at constant levels across all tissue types, such as those involved in metabolism. Similar patterns of motif enrichment could be identified in tissues with functionally-related roles and gene expression patterns. This can be visualized by enrichment of similar motifs patterns between the liver and spleen with 25 significantly enriched motifs being shared between both tissues (<figure>Figure 5</figure>A). These organs are expected to contain cell types or structures within the local microenvironment that have common biological functions, representing a theoretical construct for targeting to a multi-organ system. Finally, we demonstrated motif enrichment within single tissues, including the tumor xenograft, which suggests there are tissue-specific genes that are overexpressed or structures in the microenvironment that allow for tissue-selective accumulation of phages. This is demonstrated by 3-mer motifs like “MYW” that are only enriched within the tumor microenvironment and suggested to play a role in selective binding of a tumor-specific marker. </p>
</text>
