<text id="autogum_academic_doc428" title="Evaluating the Sustainability of Microfinance Institutions Considering Macro-Environmental Factors: A Cross-Country Study" shortTile="evaluating-sustainability" author="Wei Xu, Hongyong Fu, Huanpeng Liu" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5947/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
According to the recent disclosure of the World Bank, the total volume of people who are still struggling to meet basic needs was 3.4 billion in 2018, which is almost half the world’s population. This demonstrates the magnitude of the challenge of worldwide poverty reduction and the significance of work in this field. Various strategies and tools have been proposed to address this severe and serious issue. Among these strategies and tools, the microfinance institution (MFI), which distinguishes itself from traditional financial institutions, such as the commercial bank, by operating small loans to “unbankable poor people and small businesses”, is not only considered an effective way for the poor to manage their finances and take advantage of economic opportunities while managing risks, but also an important way to promote economic development, employment and growth, through the financial support of small businesses. The MFI has attracted tremendous interest from both practitioners and academic researchers for its significant role in poverty reduction, by bridging the gap between formal financial institutions and low-income groups or individuals. </p>

<p>In order to make full use of MFIs in poverty reduction, various MFIs have been set up all over the world since the 1970s, especially in developing countries and regions. To date, in terms of amount of customers served, the MFI is poised to become the largest banking market in the world. At the same time, MFIs are also suffering from fierce competition and rapid changes in the business environment. It is hard to sustain their success into the future in an increasingly complex business climate. Given the significant role of MFIs in poverty reduction, it is important to operate MFIs effectively and efficiently to achieve sustainable financial development. It is generally believed that it is better not to have any MFIs than to have unsustainable ones. Therefore, it is important to scientifically evaluate the sustainability of MFIs in the complex business environment. </p>

<p>Generally, sustainability is the ability to meet the needs of the present without compromising future generations. It is composed of three pillars: environmental, economic, and social. However, given the features of MFIs, the definition of sustainability is a little different in the early related literature. The sustainability definition of MFIs has focused on two pillars. One is financial (economic) sustainability. This emphasizes the financial self-sufficiency of MFIs, and a reduction in reliance on donor funds. The other is social sustainability, which focuses on social outreach. In recent years, in addition to social and financial sustainability, more and more studies have paid attention to the environmental sustainability of MFIs, analyzing the green environment performance of MFIs. A financially sustainable MFI is required, in order to achieve social and environmental sustainability. Therefore, this paper focuses on evaluating the financial sustainability of MFIs. In other words, we attempt to evaluate the financial self-sufficiency of MFIs. </p>

<p>To evaluate the financial sustainability of MFIs, previous studies have adopted accounting ratios and corporate governance factors as criteria. However, as well as the traditional financial system, MFIs are also a part of the social economy system, shown in <figure>Figure 1</figure>. More and more research has recognized that the performance of MFIs is not only influenced by internal factors, but also impacted by their external macro-environment, including the finance sector environment, macro-economic environment, and information technology environment. Meanwhile, given the negative influence of failed MFIs, some mathematical models have been proposed for evaluating the financial sustainability of MFIs, such as the order preference by similarity to ideal solution (TOPSIS), and the data envelopment analysis operating frontiers model (DEA-OF),. Prior studies have established a solid foundation for evaluating the financial sustainability of MFIs. </p>

<p>However, to the best of our knowledge, the majority of prior studies evaluating the financial sustainability of MFIs adopted accounting ratios and corporate governance factors as criteria, in the context of one country. Macro-environmental factors have received little attention to date. There has been no study evaluating the financial sustainability of MFIs integrating this many factors as criteria, especially ones accounting for the interaction between MFIs and their external operating environment. In practical terms, this interaction includes the externality of MFIs to their environment and the influence of uncontrollable environmental factors on the financial sustainability of MFIs. It should be noted that neglect of macro-environmental factors may lead to an overestimation of the financial sustainability score of MFIs, and have implications for managerial decision making, which should contribute to effective MFI performance. </p>
</text>
