<text id="autogum_academic_doc024" title="Parturition and Its Relationship with Stillbirths and Asphyxiated Piglets" shortTile="parturition-relationship" author="Pieter Langendijk, Kate Plush" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-2615/9/11/885/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Parturition and Neonatal Oxygenation</head>
<p>
Oxygen deprivation during parturition, as the main cause of stillbirth, may be caused by stretching and even rupture of the umbilical cord during stage II (expulsion of piglets) of parturition. However, the cumulative effect of repeated contractions compressing the placenta and reducing blood flow to the foetus is probably more important. Obstruction of blood flow to the foetus induces a temporary drop in heart rate, which in itself is probably harmless and an adaptive mechanism of the foetus to reduce its oxygen consumption. Repeated episodes of obstructed blood flow, however, can result in anaerobic metabolism, the cumulative effect of which is an increasing lactate level in foetal blood and a decreasing foetal blood pH as buffering capacity is exhausted. This was demonstrated by van Dijk, et al., who clamped the umbilical cord of unborn piglets for 5–8 min during caesarean section, to simulate the cumulative effect of oxygen insufficiency. In observational studies with no interventions, the cumulative effect of oxygen deprivation is reflected in the profound effect of birth order on asphyxia symptoms, with piglets later in the birth order showing increasingly higher lactate and lower pH in umbilical cord samples at birth. In a more recent study, the total duration of farrowing was shown to exacerbate the effect of birth order on measures of asphyxia and on the risk of stillbirth. This explains why stillbirth rate increases with birth order (<figure>Figure 2</figure>), especially in sows that experience a prolonged duration of farrowing. From this, it is questionable whether birth intervals contribute to stillbirth, as is sometimes suggested. In fact, a recent study showed that risk of stillbirth only started to increase significantly when birth interval exceeded 90 min, whereas the duration of farrowing increased the risk cumulatively with every 2 h that elapsed. The importance of the cumulative effect of contractions is supported by observations from Zerobin and Kündig, showing that inhibition of contractions at the start or just before parturition, using a tocolytic, prolonged parturition without increasing stillbirths. </p>

<p>It is not clear how exactly the mechanics of foetal expulsion work in the pig. Both tubo-cervical and cervico-tubal contractions occur during parturition, the first obviously serving to transport foetuses to the birth canal. The function of the latter is less clear, but have been proposed to shorten the uterine horn and to prevent accumulation of foetuses at the caudal end, thus reducing the premature rupture of the umbilical cord. In this respect, we do not know whether before being expelled, foetuses gradually travel through the uterine horn, or remain positioned at their implantation site and only travel to the birth canal once it is their turn. These two scenarios have different implications for the oxygenation for the foetus. In prolonged parturitions, placentae may also start to detach, since van Rens and van der Lende reported that in contrast to short parturitions where placentae are expelled after the last piglet has been born, in prolonged parturitions the first set of membranes are expelled while some piglets are still to be born. </p>

<p>With the cumulative duration of farrowing and birth order being the predominant factors determining the risk of stillbirth, other piglet-related factors that increase this risk are a ruptured umbilical cord, breech position and meconium staining. It is interesting to note that the percentage of piglets born with a ruptured umbilical cord varies widely from around 20% to 70%, and also that in some studies this percentage increases with birth order, whereas in others it is constant. Around 50% or more of stillbirths are associated with a ruptured umbilical cord, which suggests that this is an important risk factor. However, when expressed as the relative risk, a ruptured umbilical cord increases the risk of stillbirth approximately three-fold. This is much less compared to birth order and length of parturition. In short parturitions (&lt;3 h for example), stillbirth increased ten-fold between the first and the last piglets in the birth order; in long parturitions, stillbirth increased forty-fold (from 1% to 37%) between the first and the last piglets. The same applies to meconium staining which occurs frequently and increases the relative risk by around three-fold. With meconium staining it is also difficult to assess whether it is a consequence of asphyxia, or whether it contributed to the factors leading up to stillbirth. According to Randall, posterior delivery is a physiological condition in pigs and not associated with increased risk of stillbirth. </p>
</text>
