<text id="autogum_academic_doc154" title="Effect of Sodium Borate on the Preparation of TiN from Titanomagnetite Concentrates by Carbothermic Reduction–Magnetic Separation and Acid Leaching Process" shortTile="effect-sodium-borate" author="Wen Yu, Xiaojin Wen, Jiangan Chen, Qiongyao Tang, Wen Dong, Jingen Zhong" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2075-163X/9/11/675/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Titanium nitride is an important technological material due to its excellent characteristics such as high melting point (2950 °C), extreme hardness (8–9 on the Mohs scale), high chemical and thermal stability, gold color, and good thermal and electrical conductivity. This material has been considerably applied in various fields such as wear-resistant coatings on machine tools and bearings, and nontoxic exteriors on medical implants. Several physical and chemical methods have been reported in the literature for synthesizing TiN such as direct nitridation of metallic Ti, carbothermal reduction in TiO2 in N2 atmosphere, microwave-assisted or direct carbothermic reduction–nitridation of FeTiO3, self-propagating high-temperature synthesis, and microwave plasma synthesis. However, these processes require costly raw materials, high temperatures, long reaction time, and/or costly equipment. Therefore, affordable processes using low-cost materials for the preparation of TiN are needed. </p>

<p>The Panzhihua titanomagnetite deposit accounts for more than 90% of the Ti reserves in China. Titanomagnetite concentrates (TMCs) are currently used to produce molten iron through the blast furnace process in the Panzhihua. Nearly all amounts of Ti were concentrated into the slag after smelting in the blast furnace. As a result, more than three million tons of the slag containing 22–25% TiO2 are produced annually. However, no appropriate and economical method to process this slag is available to date because of the dispersed distribution of Ti in various fine-grained (&lt;10 μm) mineral phases. Thus, this slag is treated as a solid waste and stored; this process not only wastes Ti resources, but also poses a threat to the environment. Therefore, many studies have been devoted to develop a cleaner production process than before for comprehensively utilizing Fe, Ti, and V compounds of TMCs such as the direct reduction-smelting process, and the direct reduction–magnetic separation process. Among these, iron oxides are first reduced to metallic iron, whereas titanium oxides are rarely reduced. The reduced products are then separated by smelting or magnetic separation to produce DRI and titanium slag. However, the subsequent process of extracting titanium from the titanium slag is very complicated and is not environmentally friendly due to its high impurity content and low reactivity. Moreover, several studies have been conducted on the preparation of iron-based wear-resistant material from TMCs through the carbothermal process, in which iron oxides are reduced to metallic iron while titanium oxides are transformed into TiC or Ti(C,N). However, all impurities contained in the TMCs and reductant remain in the prepared material, which may degrade its performance. </p>

<p>In our previous study, a new process was proposed to prepare TiN and direct reduced iron (DRI) from TMCs. In this process, the TMCs were first reduced by anthracite to metallic Fe and TiN, and then magnetically separated to produce DRI and impure TiN. This process provides a way to realize the high value utilization of iron and titanium simultaneously from the TMCs. Our results showed that the Ti component was nearly completely transformed into TiN under the conditions of reduction temperature of 1300 °C, the anthracite dosage of 26%, and the reduction time of 90 min. Moreover, the separation results revealed that metallic iron and TiN can be separated precisely through grinding and magnetic separation. Therefore, the purification of impure TiN is the key technology of this process. Traditional beneficiation methods including flotation, magnetic separation, and gravity separation are unsuitable for purifying impure TiN because the particle size of TiN is generally less than 10 μm. The acid leaching process can be used to remove impurities from impure TiN given that TiN has excellent acid resistance. However, large amounts of MgAl2O4, which are difficult to dissolve in acid solution, are observed in the roasted product. Magnesium aluminate spinel is also concentrated in the impure TiN after magnetic separation and will thus hinder the purification of TiN by acid leaching. Therefore, the formation of MgAl2O4 should be inhibited during the reduction roasting process. </p>

<p>Sodium roasting is a commonly used technique to convert acid-resistant substances to soluble substances in extractive metallurgy. Sodium borate can promote the carbothermic reduction of titanomagnetite and ilmenite. Herein, sodium borate was used as an additive to inhibit the formation of MgAl2O4 during reduction to create a convenient condition for purifying TiN. The effects of sodium borate on the carbothermic reduction of TMCs, the magnetic separation of the reduced products, and the acid leaching of impure TiN were also studied. </p>
</text>
