<text id="autogum_academic_doc580" title="Dropping Counter: A Detection Algorithm for Identifying Odour-Evoked Responses from Noisy Electroantennograms Measured by a Flying Robot" shortTile="dropping-counter" author="Bluest Lan, Ryohei Kanzaki, Noriyasu Ando" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1424-8220/19/20/4574/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Discussion</head>
<p>
In this study, we developed a simple EAG detection algorithm for flying robots. The conditional EMA filter and D-Counter provide a unique algorithm that can be adopted for handling different cases or changing the sensitivity by adjusting the smoothing factor <hi rend="italic">α</hi>, window size <hi rend="italic">swin</hi>, and threshold <hi rend="italic">th</hi>. Compared with the simple fixed threshold detection, the D-Counter conferred a high accuracy of detection (quantified using a cross-correlation coefficient between the detection output and stimulus input signals). Moreover, applying the conditional EMA filter with an appropriate smoothing factor <hi rend="italic">α</hi> can reduce the individual differences even if it is applied to signals with variable signal amplitudes and the baseline. The individual diversity in bio-sensing technology has been the major problem as each individual has different characteristics. Such diversity is caused not only by the native difference of individual moths but also by the differences among antenna preparations. Therefore, the reduction in response diversity is also the advantage of our algorithm. In addition to the development of signal processing, our simplified and easy-to-set up experimental technique using an antenna holder can unify the conditions of antenna preparations and reduce the individual differences. How to minimise the effect of the individual differences is the great challenge when utilising insect antennae for practical use as chemical sensors. Improvements in both signal processing and experimental procedure are required. </p>

<p>The odour-evoked EAG response encodes multiple information of an odour filament. The fast response onset indicates the timing of odour arrival, the amplitude indicates odour concentration, the duration of a negative potential indicates the duration of odour contact, and the waveform of a single response can be altered by different odourants. However, all the information would be available only when an odour is applied under a well-controlled condition and the EAG is obtained using the same preparation. In particular, unlike gas sensors, it is difficult to estimate the absolute odour concentration from the amplitude of EAGs because the amplitude of an EAG to a certain odour concentration varies by individual preparations and their conditions, and the signal decays even if the antenna is in a continuous odour flow. Although our algorithm only tells us the onset and offset of each odour response, this will not be a problem for odour tracking. Because the duration of a single odour contact for flying insects is short (several hundred milliseconds or less), the detection of the odour onset and offset would be more reliable than odour concentration. Therefore, as long as we use odour-searching algorithms of flying insects in which the behaviours are triggered by odour onset or offset, our algorithm of signal processing will be effective. However, our algorithm cannot be used for a searching algorithm based on the concentration gradient of odour, such as osmotropotaxis, in which an insect turns to the side of higher odour concentration (i.e., the side of an odour source if the odour flow is continuous). However, whether flying insects during manoeuvres avail the odour gradient during such a short period is still in question, even though they are capable of detecting it. </p>

<p>Not only the odour concentration, but the timing of response onset also tells us the side of an odour source if bilateral information is acquired by two organs spatially separated. It has been reported that sharks and silkmoths turn based on the time difference of odour arrivals between their left and right olfactory organs. Because the timing of response onset of the EAG and its temporal dynamics are highly reproducible, the time difference in EAG onsets between two antennae spatially separated can be used to determine the side to turn. Kanazaki et al. implemented the time difference of EAG responses between two antennae to the network model on an antennae-loaded land robot. Furthermore, whether the timing of different odour arrivals is synchronised or not is supposed to be a cue for insects to recognise the odourants as mixed or not. Therefore, the timing of odour onset is solely meaningful, and how to utilise it for efficient searching should be investigated in the future. </p>

<p>The time necessary for processing signals in our algorithm is mainly constrained by the window size <hi rend="italic">swin</hi>, whereas the computational load for the algorithm itself is low. We showed that either <hi rend="italic">swin</hi> = 0.1 s or 0.2 s can output an accurate estimation of the olfactory input, which correspond to 0.1 s or 0.2 s of latency if the algorithm is operated in real time. Although the time delay should be as minimised as possible, it is worth noting that the response delay of a surge (the upwind flight triggered by an odour contact) is approximately 0.2 s in moths and flies. The allowance of response delay for successful odour source localisation was estimated to be 0.4 s, which was investigated employing a silkmoth-driven land robot. Altogether, considering the time required for sensory-motor control of insects, the time delay for signal processing in our algorithm does not prevent us from availing odour-searching algorithms of insects for the drone. </p>
</text>
