<text id="autogum_academic_doc067" title="The Role of Aberrant DNA Methylation in Misregulation of Gene Expression in Gonadotroph Nonfunctioning Pituitary Tumors" shortTile="role-aberrant-dna" author="Paulina Kober, Joanna Boresowicz, Natalia Rusetska, Maria Maksymowicz, Agnieszka Paziewska, Michalina Dąbrowska, Jacek Kunicki, Wiesław Bonicki, Jerzy Ostrowski, Janusz  A. Siedlecki, Mateusz Bujko" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6694/11/11/1650/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Discussion</head>
<p>
Genome-wide DNA methylation patterns and methylation abnormalities in pituitary tumors have been reported previously. To date, however, the impact of aberrant CpG methylation on gene expression in NFPAs has not been investigated by a multi-omics approach. In this study, we combined the results of methylome and transcriptome profiling of 33 gonadotroph NFPA samples to investigate whether DNA methylation at particular CpGs that are aberrantly methylated in gonadotroph tumors correlates with the expression levels of the corresponding genes. </p>

<p>Gonadotroph NFPAs exhibited an increase in DNA methylation relative to normal pituitary sections, and a large number of differentially methylated CpGs have been identified. In our analysis, approximately 85% of CpGs that are differentially methylated in NFPAs and associated with known human genes were hypermethylated in tumors. </p>

<p>Our correlation-based analysis revealed that methylation of a major fraction of CpGs that are differentially methylated in gonadotroph adenomas and pituitary sections did not correlate with the expression of the annotated genes. This has also been observed in a similar analysis of other human cancers. We observed a correlation between DNA methylation and gene expression in approximately 11% of gene-associated CpGs with aberrant DNA methylation. </p>

<p>These CpG sites are located in or near genes for which methylation and expression were previously reported to be correlated in pituitary adenomas, including <hi rend="italic">STAT5A</hi>, <hi rend="italic">RHOD</hi>, <hi rend="italic">GALNT9</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">RASSF1</hi>, as well as genes with previously described aberrant methylation in pituitary tumors, including <hi rend="italic">CDKN1A</hi>, <hi rend="italic">TP73</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">STAT3</hi>. A correlation between aberrant DNA methylation and the expression level was also observed for <hi rend="italic">HMGA2</hi>, which plays an important role in the pathogenesis of pituitary tumors. </p>

<p>GSEA revealed that genes whose expression was related to the methylation level of differentially methylated CpGs were enriched in pathways and processes important for tumor development. For most CpGs whose methylation was related to gene expression, the relationship was an inverse one: For these sites, hypermethylation and hypomethylation corresponded to a decrease and increase in gene expression, respectively. These results are generally in line with the idea that in tumors, elevated methylation is associated with transcriptional silencing, providing a mechanism for inactivation of genes with tumor-suppressor function. On the other hand, hypomethylation may result in the activation of potential oncogenes. </p>

<p>To simplify the interpretation of the results, we distinguished two classes of aberrantly methylated CpGs: Those in promoters, i.e., located in the 5’ promoter gene region, which includes regions from 1500 bp upstream of the TSS up to the first exon of the gene, and those in gene bodies, including exons, introns, and 3’UTR sequences. For 81% of the CpGs located in promoters for which methylation and expression were correlated, the correlation was negative, in concordance with the overall model. </p>

<p>Approximately one-third of all methylation/expression-correlated CpGs were positively correlated, i.e., hypermethylation and hypomethylation were associated with increased and decreased expression, respectively. Among these CpGs, most are located in gene bodies, whereas only 22% are located in promoters, consistent with previously published reports. Gene body methylation has been observed in active genes, implying that it may have the opposite effect on gene expression to promoter methylation, i.e., increased DNA methylation in gene bodies may promote transcription. </p>

<p>In this study, we compared the expression profiles of NFPAs and normal pituitary sections without evidence of neoplastic features, obtained by Rathke’s cleft cyst surgery. This allowed us to identify DEGs and investigate which of these genes exhibits methylation-dependent expression. When we compared the list of genes with methylation/expression correlation and the list of DEGs, most genes were hypermethylated with a fold change in expression corresponding to the sign of the correlation, e.g., a gene with negative methylation/expression correlation that was hypermethylated and downregulated in tumors. In a subset of genes, however, the fold change in expression was inconsistent with the difference in DNA methylation and the sign of the correlation, e.g., a hypermethylated gene with negative methylation/expression correlation that was upregulated in tumors. These genes were excluded from the functional GSEA. We believe that the differential the expression of these genes in NFPAs and pituitary tissue was due to a mechanism distinct from aberrant DNA methylation, despite the fact that the expression levels of these genes were methylation-related. In general, our analysis showed that in gonadotroph NFPAs, the expression of 9% of DEGs is correlated with aberrant methylation. </p>
</text>
