<text id="autogum_academic_doc036" title="Influence of the Physical State of Spray-Dried Flavonoid-Inulin Microparticles on Oxidative Stability of Lipid Matrices" shortTile="influence-physical" author="Guibeth Morelo, Begoña Giménez, Gloria Márquez-Ruiz, Francisca Holgado, Patricio Romero-Hasler, Eduardo Soto-Bustamante, Paz Robert" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3921/8/11/520/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Lipid oxidation is one of the major causes of food deterioration, leading to the loss of nutrients and bioactives, off flavors development, and could also form potentially toxic compounds. The use of synthetic antioxidants, such as butylated hydroxytoluene, butylated hydroxyanisole, or n-propyl gallate to delay lipid oxidation is currently questioned due to their possible harmful effects on human health, and the use of natural antioxidants is of growing interest. In recent years, flavonoids have been used to improve the oxidative stability of foods. The main mechanisms by which flavonoids act against lipid oxidation involve transferring a hydrogen atom or electrons to a peroxyl radical and metal chelation. Free flavonoids, mainly quercetin, myricetin, morin, (+)catechin, (−)epigallocatechin, (−)epicatechin, and kaempferol have been incorporated in different lipid systems with varying degrees of success in terms of oxidative stability. The incorporation of free flavonoids in lipid systems may have some drawbacks since these phenolic compounds have limited solubility and stability, together with unpleasant flavors in some cases. </p>

<p>Encapsulation of flavonoids is a technology which could enhance the stability of flavonoids. Among the encapsulation methods, spray-drying is the most widely used for the encapsulation of bioactive compounds in the food industry. Inulin is a linear fructo-oligosaccharide composed of fructosyl units (β (2→1) linkage) and usually contains one terminal glucose moiety per molecule. β-linkage makes inulin resistant to hydrolysis by human gastrointestinal enzymes and it is classified as colonic delivery biopolymer. Although inulin is moderately water soluble, it is used as an encapsulating agent by spray drying due to low viscosity and colorless solutions. However, there are few studies focused on the effect of the incorporation of microencapsulated flavonoids on the oxidative stability of lipid systems. In previous studies undertaken by our research group, flavonoids were microencapsulated with inulin (lipid-insoluble polymer), where channelizing agents (lipid-soluble polymer) were incorporated. These microparticles were able to release the encapsulated flavonoids and improve the oxidative stability of methyl linoleate and vegetable oils, which was attributed to the formation of channels inside the microparticles, favoring the diffusion of flavonoids.  </p>

<p>In general, powders obtained by spray-drying are amorphous. However, in the case of inulin, process variables of spray-drying such as feed temperature and inlet air temperature have been reported to influence both the morphology and the degree of crystallinity of the microparticles. When the flavonoid-inulin microparticles are incorporated into a lipid system, the physical state of these microparticles (semi-crystalline/amorphous) may influence the oxidative stability of the system, but this still has not been addressed.  </p>

<p>The objective of this research was to design flavonoids (epicatechin and quercetin) microparticles with inulin as encapsulating agent and to evaluate the influence of the physical state of spray-dried flavonoid microparticles (semi-crystalline/amorphous) on the oxidative stability of lipid systems. </p>
</text>
