<text id="autogum_academic_doc178" title="Emissions Control Catalysis" shortTile="emissions-control" author="Ioannis V. Yentekakis, Philippe Vernoux" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4344/9/11/912/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Special Issue Contributions and Highlights</head>
<p>
The present “Emissions Control Catalysis” Special Issue was successful in collecting 21 high-quality contributions by several research groups around the world, which covers recent research progress in the field of the catalytic control of air pollutants emitted by mobile or stationary sources, not limited only to the abatement of pollutants but also including research dedicated to cyclic economy strategies. These papers among others are ranging from the synthesis and physicochemical-textural-structural characterization of the materials, activity–selectivity–durability evaluation under environmentally important reactions, fundamental understanding of structure–activity relationships or other metal–metal and metal–support interactions on the multifunctional materials involved. In particular, three comprehensive review articles covering several major topics and directions in emissions control catalysis subject were published in this special issue. The review of the guest editors (Yentekakis I., and Vernoux P.) and co-workers concerns mainly the of CO, CHs, and NOx emissions abatement from stoichiometric, lean burn, and diesel engines exhausts, addressing the literature that concerns the electropositive promotion by alkalis or alkaline earths of platinum group metals (PGMs) that have found to be extremely effective for the related three-way and lean-burn reactions and catalytic chemistry. The review of Smirniotis P. and co-workers concerns the selective catalytic reduction of NOx with NH3 (NH3-SCR of NOx) focusing to low temperature applications that is a highly desirable perspective, and finally the review of Bogaerts A. and co-workers covering a hot recent trend in emissions control implicating cyclic economy strategies, that is the conversion and utilization of CO2 for the production of value-added chemicals. On the other hand, a major part of contributions (9/21) concerns original research on nitrogen oxides reduction processes, reflecting the fact that this topic still remains hot among the targets of environmental catalysis. Five out of 21 studies concern CO and hydrocarbons oxidation processes while the remained 4/21 concern CO2 capture/recycling processes under the view of cyclic economy. </p>

<head> Review Contributions</head>
<p>
Alkali metals as surface-promoters of platinum group metals (PGMs) have shown remarkable promotional effects on the vast majority of reactions related to the emissions control catalysis either they are applied by traditional routes (e.g., impregnation) or electrochemically, via the so called, concept of the electrochemical promotion of catalysis (EPOC) or non-faradaic electrochemical modification of catalytic activity (NEMCA effect). In the comprehensive review of Yentekakis et al. published in this Special Issue, more than 120 papers on the subject were collected and discussed comparatively after classification in groups, on the basis of the specific reaction promoted, e.g., (CO, HCs, or H2)-SCR of NOx, and CO or hydrocarbons oxidation. The authors also present and analyze, by means of indirect (kinetics) and direct (spectroscopic) evidences, a mechanistic model for the mode of action of electropositive promoters, which consistently interprets all the observed promoting phenomena. Concluding, they claim that this very pronounced (in some cases extraordinarily) alkali-induced promotion in emissions control catalysis prompts to the development of novel catalyst formulations for a more efficient and cost-effective control of the emissions of automotives and stationary combustion processes. </p>

<p>Since the emission standards for NOx are becoming more stringent to keep our atmosphere clean and severe pollution regulations being imposed around the world, the challenge of a cost-effective, i.e., low-temperature, selective catalytic reduction (LT-SCR) of NOx by NH3 with a combination of high NOx activity and N2 selectivity in a wide operation temperature window and good resistance to SO2/H2O have attracted paramount attention. Supported and mixed transition metal oxides have been widely investigated for LT-SCR technology. However, these catalytic materials have some drawbacks, especially in terms of catalyst poisoning by H2O or/and SO2. Hence, the development of catalysts for the LT-SCR process is still under active investigation throughout seeking better performance. Extensive research efforts have been made to develop new advanced materials for this technology. The comprehensive review of Smirniotis and co-workers collected and comparatively analyses more than 140 publications in the topic, covering the description of the influence of operating conditions, materials, and promoters on the LT-SCR performance, as well as active sites, reaction intermediates, and mechanistic implications evidenced by using isotopic labeling and in situ FT-IR studies. </p>

<p>Global climate change as a result of the greenhouse effects of the increasing emissions of the so-called greenhouse gases, with CO2 to be the most representative one, is of major concern currently. CO2 capture, conversion, and utilization is one of the possible solutions to reduce CO2 concentration in the atmosphere. Among other methods, this can be accomplished by direct catalytic hydrogenation of CO2, producing value-added products. In their comprehensive review, Bogaerts A. and co-workers, focused mainly in the last 5-years progress on the topic summarized the literature research (~125 papers) and the current priorities on CO2 hydrogenation to CO, CH4, CH3OH, DME, olefins, and higher hydrocarbons value-added chemicals by heterogeneous catalysis and plasma catalysis. Although, its energy efficiency is still deterring for commercialization, plasma catalysis has currently attracted sufficient attention, due to its simple operating conditions (ambient temperature and atmospheric pressure) and unique advantages in activating inert molecules; its potential advantages and current limitations on CO2 hydrogenation process have been accounted in the review. </p>
</text>
