<text id="autogum_academic_doc604" title="Consumer Preferences and Sensory Profile Related to the Physico-Chemical Properties and Texture of Different Maize Tortillas Types" shortTile="consumer-preferences" author="Mădălina Iuga, Víctor  D. Ávila Akerberg, Tanya  M. González Martínez, Silvia Mironeasa" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2304-8158/8/11/533/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Maize is one of the most cultivated crops in America, Europe, and Asia, being largely consumed in Latin America. Maize is a key element in the Mesoamerican diet; however, only in Mexico is it mainly consumed in the shape of “tortilla”—a flat 12 to 18 cm disc made of nixtamalized maize flour, cooked over a hot comal or skillet. Maize tortilla is one of the most popular foods in Mexico, and it is strongly related to the Mexican identity and considered a cultural heritage. It presents very different organoleptic parameters among Mexican territories, with the average daily consumption per capita being 180 g in urban areas and 300 g in rural zones of the country. The materials used to obtain maize-based products, the processes, and equipment influence the nutritional value via loss of components. Nixtamalization, a word coming from the indigenous Nahuatl linguistic root nixtli—meaning ashes or lime—and tamalli, a maize dough, is an ancient treatment (since 400–500 a. c.) used for maize grains. It involves grains boiling in approximately 5% lime water (calcium hydroxide) which enhances maize quality by softening the pericarp of the seed while increasing protein quality and the availability of niacin and calcium. This treatment also promotes flavor development and improves tortillas’ consistency, while reducing the effects of fumosin, aflatoxin, deoxynivalenol, and zearalenone, all major contaminants of maize.  </p>

<p>Tortillas are unfermented flat maize breads, with a soft, flexible, and easy to fold and roll structure and of various colors, depending on the flour and maize source. In Mexico, there are more than 52 species and more than 350 cultivars/colors per species; they are called natives and are cultivated in traditional peasant farming systems, such as the cornfield, as well as genetically improved maize hybrids cultivated in intensive production systems with less costs. Today, most of the commercial maize products consumed in Mexico are obtained from industrially grown maize imported from the United States, but in the center of Mexico native maize is still consumed. The quality differences among the tortillas on the market appear due to the fact that some artisanal tortillerias incorporate industrial maize flour gradually. The traditional method of tortilla making involves maize grain nixtamalization to obtain the nixtamalized maize dough; however, nowadays, this procedure has been replaced by industrial nixtamalized maize flour. Maize tortillas are a good source of proteins, providing important caloric intake. Taking into consideration peoples from Africa and Latin America, maize consumption is between 15% and 56%. The chemical and physical parameters of nixtamalized maize and flour tortillas are influenced by the grain’s properties. The conditions of the nixtamalization process and the milling method also play an important role.  </p>

<p>In rural households, the perception of quality, which is considered as “a good tortilla”, is closely related to the artisanal process, which also includes cooking in a wood-burning stove and clay dish. Consumers’ preferences regarding tortillas depend on the region of the country. In urban areas, tortillas of industrial origin are more readily accepted, while in rural areas, artisanal manufacturing, still dominated by women, is preferred. Nowadays, traditional tortillas handmade by women tend to be replaced by the use of electric machines and gas combustion. </p>

<p>People’s choices regarding tortilla products is important for producers, especially from the product quality enhancement point of view. In rural areas, traditional agricultural practices registered substantial changes, mainly due to the free-trade policies which caused an increase in imported crops. A commercial-scale production of tortillas implies changes to the traditional processes which lead to products with different sensory parameters. Some studies revealed that tortilla purchase intent is influenced by appearance, textural properties, and taste. Industrialized tortillas, sold in self-service stores and mechanized tortillerias, tend to be much thinner, become hard quickly, and have a slightly sweet taste of maize which is almost imperceptible, while a lime flavor predominates. These industrial tortillas are made with flours from large business monopolies, with imported maize that, due to the fact of their practicality, accessibility, shelf-life, and price, displace the original meaning of freshly made tortillas with their market model. Food perception and choices are different between women and men as a result of distinct energy needs, depending on their activities. Men consume foods with a higher energy density, while women prefer diets rich in vegetables, fruits, and fibers. Regarding eating styles, men take bigger food bites and eat faster than women. Different food preferences among the two groups are related to the response at stimuli, such as visual image, gustatory information, emotions, hormonal changes, and weight status.  </p>
</text>
