<text id="autogum_academic_doc713" title="The Effect of the Adoption of International Accounting Standards No. 12 (IAS No. 12) for Firms Reporting Losses: Evidence from Korea" shortTile="effect-adoption-international" author="Nanhee Hong, Junyong Shim" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5732/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 6. Conclusions</head>
<p>
As acknowledged by the Commission of the European Communities (2007, 18), “accounting for deferred taxes … is very burdensome for companies in general,” whereas “it has been confirmed by preparers and users, e.g., credit institutions and rating agencies, that deferred tax information (whether recognized in the balance sheet or provided in the notes) often is not considered a relevant input for the decisions to be taken”. </p>

<p>We examine the incremental effect of IFRS relative to the usefulness of information content of deferred tax balance for loss reporting firms using evidence from Korea. We expect that if IFRS adoption allows a firm greater flexibility in recognizing as deferred tax balance, then deferred tax disclosures will provide little information about the potential earnings sustainability. </p>

<p>We develop a classification scheme that uses deferred tax expense according to Dhaliwal et al. (2013). We also first examine whether IFRS adoption affects the information about loss reversal or loss persistency, including multiple determinants of tax categories, and their control variables. Both the loss reversal model and the loss persistence model results show that tax categories provide incremental information before IFRS, but after IFRS information about loss reversal or loss persistency disappears in its usefulness. </p>

<p>Finally, we extended previous research on the pricing of tax information. Our results suggest that investors generally underweight their deferred tax balance before IFRS, but after IFRS adoption, investors cannot obtain buy-and-hold returns by buying GN firm-years and selling BN firm-years. However, this is not because investors understand the information of DTAs, but because the usefulness of the information of DTAs deteriorates after IFRS adoption. </p>

<p>Our study has two important limitations. First, although we try to control the various effects associated with adopting IFRS, our research is probably not free of endogeneity issues. Second, our tests are based on only 4 years of post-adoption data. The information effect we suggest may not persist in the long period as user’s familiarity with the implementation of standards increases and/or the quality of financial reporting improves due to the monitoring effect of users of financial information. </p>

<p>We believe our findings have implications for the application of IFRS. First, although existing research analyzes the overall impact of introducing IFRS, our research focuses on specific issues related to tax accounting. Specifically, this study shows that the flexible interpretation of accounting standards related to tax accounting can reduce the quality of information. </p>

<p>We use a unique setting because, under IAS No. 12, only the recognition criteria related to the tax information were relaxed in Korea, while the estimation method for deferred taxes remains unchanged. We suggest that our setting provides evidence regarding the inherent flexibility of IFRS.
 </p>
</text>
