<text id="autogum_academic_doc176" title="Asatone and Isoasatone A Against Spodoptera litura Fab. by Acting on Cytochrome P450 Monoxygenases and Glutathione Transferases" shortTile="asatone-isoasatone" author="Ruimei Ling, Renyue Yang, Ping Li, Xiongfei Zhang, Tunkai Shen, Xiaowen Li, Quan Yang, Lirong Sun, Jian Yan" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1420-3049/24/21/3940/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Most plants have evolved a range of defense systems to protect themselves when they are infected by insects. Constitutive and inducible secondary metabolites may increase after being fed upon by insects to prevent further damage. Metabolites that were induced in damaged plants could prove useful for preventing and controlling insects. Some extracts from plants can inhibit growth of <hi rend="italic">Spodoptera litura</hi> Fab. larvae or kill them. </p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Asarum ichangense</hi> is a species of the genus <hi rend="italic">Asarum</hi>. Yi et al. reported that all parts of <hi rend="italic">A. sieboldii</hi> caused 100% mortality in both <hi rend="italic">Lycoriella ingenua</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Coboldia fuscipes</hi> larvae. Essential oil from <hi rend="italic">A. sieboldii</hi> was toxic to the house dust mite <hi rend="italic">Dermatophagoide sfarina</hi>. It was determined that a type of neolignane asatone and isoasatone was reported from the genus <hi rend="italic">Asarum</hi>, and that asatone has proved to be a potent antifeedant to papilionid butterfly, <hi rend="italic">Luehdorfia puziloi</hi> larvae. Asatone and isoasatone A have seldom been investigated for its toxicity to caterpillars, such as <hi rend="italic">S. litura</hi>. <hi rend="italic">S. litura</hi> is a harmful insect which is widespread in many countries, as it causes significant damage to crops every year. It feeds on 181 plant species that belong to 39 families, which include maize (<hi rend="italic">Zea mays</hi>), sunflower (<hi rend="italic">Helianthus annuus</hi>), sorghum (<hi rend="italic">Sorghum bicolor</hi>), and chickpea (<hi rend="italic">Cicer arietinum</hi>). </p>

<p>Many secondary metabolites demonstrate a number of different mechanisms to control pests. For example, quercetin negatively affected the mid-gut of <hi rend="italic">S. litura</hi> from <hi rend="italic">Euphorbia hirta</hi> L, and flavonoids, ginkgolide, and bilobalide from <hi rend="italic">Ginkgo biloba</hi> inhibit the metabolic enzymes in <hi rend="italic">Hyphantria cunea</hi> larvae by glutathione transferases (GSTs), acetylcholinesterase (AChE), carboxylesterase (CarE), and mixed-functional oxidase (MFO). Insect cytochrome P450 monooxygenases (P450s) are well-known for their roles in the oxidative metabolism of xenobiotics such as insecticides and plant allelochemicals in pest insects. They have been divided into four clades: CYP2, CYP3, CYP4, and the mitochondrial CYP clade. The clade CYP3 is further subdivided into different CYP families. The CYP321A, CYP6B, and CYP9A subfamilies play a role in the metabolism of xenobiotics and insecticide resistance. The products of P450-mediated reactions (phase I reactions) can be metabolized by phase II enzymes, such as GSTs, which lead to the production of hydrophilic compounds that can be excreted by phase III transporters. </p>

<p>Here, we report that asatone and isoasatone A analyzed from <hi rend="italic">A. ichangense</hi> can be potential defensive compounds against <hi rend="italic">S. litura</hi>. The anti-insect mechanisms of both compounds are described using mid-gut histopathology, P450s, GSTs, and AChE of <hi rend="italic">S. litura</hi>. </p>
</text>
