<text id="autogum_academic_doc237" title="Automatic Wireless Signal Classification: A Neural-Induced Support Vector Machine-Based Approach" shortTile="automatic-wireless" author="Arfan  Haider Wahla, Lan Chen, Yali Wang, Rong Chen" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2078-2489/10/11/338/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Simulation Results and Discussion</head>
<p>
In this section, the performance of the proposed scheme is investigated against several non-ideal channel conditions such as frequency offset, phase offset, timing offset, varying symbol number as well as different Doppler shifts. An analytical comparison is also provided with previously proposed different learning-based modulation classifiers. </p>

<head> 4.1. Dataset</head>
<p>
In this paper, the following  modulation schemes were considered. The transmitted bit-stream was generated randomly to ensure each has equal probability. The received signal was pre-processed at the receiver end to obtain a complex based-band signal. The In-Phase-Quadrature (I-Q) samples of the received signal were sampled simultaneously to a frame of length N. They are combined later in a 2 X N matrix and input to CNN for feature extraction. In this study, the value of <hi rend="italic">N</hi> is 2048 but some experiments are performed with <hi rend="italic">N</hi> = 1024, 512. This is done by varying the number of symbols in the frame. A segment has the same results as that of a full observation. In this way, the proposed classifier would be independent of N. The range of AWGN noise with signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) = −8 dB to +8 dB in the dataset. For each modulation scheme and SNR values, 10,000 realizations of the received signal are generated according to the model described in Section 2. The rest of the parameters are summarized in Table 1 in detail. </p>

<head> 4.2. Training and Validation Performance</head>
<p>
In the following experiment, the proposed classifier NSVM, which is a hybrid combination of CNN and SVM is trained and validated by using offline deployment. In order to analyze the performance, the accuracy and loss curves of training and cross-validation are plotted in <figure>Figure 5</figure>. Similar experiments are performed with a traditional CNN model with the softmax classifier in its last layer, and the results are plotted in <figure>Figure 6</figure>. The CNN settings used here are the same in both cases, as shown in <figure>Figure 4</figure>, expect one is trained with Gaussian SVM and the other one is trained with softmax as the decision classifier. The performance of NSVM is better than the traditional CNN model as the accuracy and loss converges to their minima and maxima quickly. Along with that, these results show that it smoothens as training progresses, which shows the effectiveness of the proposed scheme. This also reduces the cost of training for the proposed model. However, in the case of CNN with softmax, the classifier performance is hardly stable and satisfactory, as can be seen in <figure>Figure 6</figure>. </p>
</text>
