<text id="autogum_academic_doc501" title="Evaluation of the Filming and Protective Properties of a New Trehalose and Ceramides Based Ingredient" shortTile="evaluation-filming" author="Letteria Greco, Salviana Ullo, Luigi Rigano, Marco Fontana, Enzo Berardesca, Norma Cameli" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2079-9284/6/4/62/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Discussion</head>
<p>
The statistical analysis of the collected data at each visit shows a very good trend for hydrogel containing trehalose and ceramides based ingredient at each visit: </p>

<p><b>Evaporimetry (Transepidermal Water Loss (TEWL))</b> </p>

<p>Evaporimetry was used to detect any influence on the water barrier function of the skin following application of ceramides and trehalose based ingredient hydrogel and placebo hydrogel.  </p>

<p><b>Corneometry (Hydration)</b> </p>

<p>In order to measure the amount of water present in the stratum corneum and the skin barrier condition, hydration has been evaluated through Corneometry.  </p>

<p>Moreover, the T-test applied to hydrogel containing ceramides and trehalose based ingredient and placebo formula gave a statistically significant difference between them at each visit, always showing better results for the hydrogel containing ceramides and trehalose based ingredient. </p>

<p>The double-blind, placebo-controlled study was performed to assess, by corneometry and evaporimetry, the barrier normalizing efficacy of a topical product containing trehalose and ceramides to alleviate skin dryness on limbs. </p>

<p>The study results show a significant moisturizing effect of the ingredient at each visit, both versus baseline and versus the placebo control (<hi rend="italic">p</hi> &lt; 0.01).  </p>

<p>For the application site of topical cosmetic formula containing a trehalose and ceramides based ingredient: </p>

<p>(1) Transepidermal water loss (TEWL) value shows a reduction of −54% after 4 weeks (<figure>Figure 2</figure>). </p>

<p>(2) Hydration shows an increase of 102% after 4 weeks (<figure>Figure 3</figure>). </p>

<p>Such results point out the significant moisturizing effect after using the cosmetic under examination and go well with the rationale of the formulation, based on ingredients able to moisturize rapidly the skin and recover the cutaneous barrier to allow it to better hold the water present into its outer layers. </p>

<p><hi rend="italic">In vivo</hi> evaluation of the efficacy of a formulation for atopic and very dry skin (Xerosis) was done. </p>

<p>An example of one topical formulation for atopic dermatitis (Table 1) based on trehalose and ceramides based ingredient is reported below for illustrative and non-limiting purposes. </p>

<p>Purpose of the test: To provide active substances through a form that allows a prompt release and an effective amount in atopic dermatitis, characterized by a deteriorated functionality of the barrier, an increased transepidermal water loss (TEWL) and a significant xerosis, as well as in the case of pathologies associated with a local subcutaneous microcirculation disorder. The efficacy of a topical cosmetic formulation containing trehalose and ceramides in comparison to a placebo has been evaluated. </p>

<p>Mean values, standard deviations, and variations were calculated for each set of values. </p>

<p>Following the results of normality test (Kolmogorov–Smirnov test), the instrumental data (T0, T4 weeks) and the variations (T4 weeks-T0) were statistically compared by means of <hi rend="italic">t</hi>-test for parametric and dependent data. </p>

<p>In all cases, the groups of data were considered statistically different for a probability value <hi rend="italic">p</hi> &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>Protocol of double-blind study: the product containing trehalose and ceramides ingredient and the placebo was applied on the forearms by 20 volunteers of either sex (1 male and 19 females with an average age of 50 years) with atopic and very dry skin (xerosis), twice a day, for 4 weeks. </p>

<p>During the study, subjects were instructed to wash their body using their current skin care regimen and to not apply the tested products on any other site than the prescribed ones. For the whole duration of the test, the subjects were not allowed to use different products on the forearms and instructed to avoid UV exposure. </p>

<p>Furthermore, the side of application (left or right forearm) of the two formulations (cream containing trehalose and ceramides based ingredient and placebo) were randomized among the volunteers. Each sample was labeled “right” or “left”, indicating the side of application of the product. The assignment of subject number and subsequent placement on the randomization chart were made in order of appearance at the study center on the first day. The products were given to the subjects in anonymous containers which did not provide any information about the treatment. </p>

<p>The comparisons evidenced statistically significant differences between studied ingredient and placebo for both parameters (hydration and TEWL). </p>

<p>This means that the improvements observed in the active area were statistically higher than the improvements observed in the placebo area. </p>

<p>Instrumental measurements of skin hydration and transepidermal water loss (TEWL) were performed on a selected area (9 cm2) of the forearms at the baseline and after 4 weeks of treatment. </p>

<p><b>Skin Hydration</b> </p>

<p>A statistically significant increase in the mean basal values of skin hydration was evidenced after 4 weeks of application of both the ceramides and trehalose based ingredient cream and the placebo product (Table 2). </p>

<p>A statistically significant difference between ceramides and trehalose based ingredient cream and placebo product was detected after 4 weeks of treatment (<figure>Figure 4</figure>). </p>

<p>The cream containing trehalose and ceramides based ingredient is able to improve skin hydration if compared to placebo. </p>

<p><b>Transepidermal Water Loss (TEWL)</b> </p>
</text>
