<text id="autogum_academic_doc443" title="Detecting Patterns of Vegetation Gradual Changes (2001–2017) in Shiyang River Basin, Based on a Novel Framework" shortTile="detecting-patterns" author="Ju Wang, Yaowen Xie, Xiaoyun Wang, Jingru Dong, Qiang Bie" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-4292/11/21/2475/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Discussion</head><head> 5.1. Strengths and Limitations of the Framework</head>
<p>
Timeseries products present different temporal scales components, such as seasonal variations, long-term and short-term fluctuations. Their high temporal resolution offers the opportunity to define time profiles of vegetation dynamics. Although many methods have been developed to explore vegetation dynamics at a global or regional scale, quantitative methods that could automatically address where, when and how vegetation change are still lacking. Trajectory-based change detection is an inevitable choice to do this work by constructing a ‘curve’ or profile of full temporal records for each pixel. Nowadays, the method has been successfully applied in forest-related change analyses, land use classification, and cropland variations. </p>

<p>The framework we proposed in our study is a trajectory-based change detection method. It has several desirable properties compared with other fashionable methods. Firstly, unlike the widely used trend analyses which hypothesize that ecosystems/vegetation always change linearly in a direction, our framework could detect the non-linear change patterns in vegetation. All patterns in the framework can be interpreted from unambiguous biophysical standpoints. Secondly, unlike DBEST and BFAST, our framework automatically generalizes processes of vegetation gradual changes into different patterns without setting any parameters. Furthermore, the patterns between different pixels or areas could be compared easily. Although DBEST and BFAST could also track vegetation gradual change by a piecewise linear model on the pixel scale, the number of breakpoints must be set by users when the method was extended to the regional scale. For example, de Jong detected the short-term greening or browning periods within long-term timeseries by dividing the trend component in BFAST into four segments which were separated by three breakpoints. Then, the duration of the significant greening and browning segments, the magnitude of change in NDVI, and the abrupt changes could be compared between pixels subsequently. Lastly, trajectory-based change detection only functions when the process of vegetation change matches well with the hypothesized trajectory. Temporal trajectories of vegetation changes in different pixels may be different. Therefore, many mathematical models are needed to fit the trajectories. However, just a logistic model is used to simulate all the non-linear monotonic patterns in our framework. </p>

<p>Drawbacks of our framework are obvious. Firstly, only four monotonic patterns and eight types are presented. All the patterns are associated with only one disturbance event within the timescales of the observation period (<figure>Figure 4</figure>). Generally, changes in vegetation are complicated and difficult to be generalized by a single function. Therefore, patterns that are composed of the general categories in our framework, or patterns that vegetation gradual changes were stalled or reverse by abrupt events, were not discussed in this study. New models that could detect both the monotonic and the non-monotonic patterns are needed to be induced in future. Secondly, the smoothed treatment implemented on the NDVI timeseries makes the framework unsuitable to detect subtle changes or abrupt changes. However, it makes the framework unspecific to the MODIS timeseries products which do not suffer from the problem of data discontinuity. The data discontinuities which may be caused by changes in different sensors, orbital drift in the satellite overpass times, variations in sun-sensor-viewer geometry or differences in the atmospheric conditions (i.e., water vapour content, aerosols) are common in other timeseries products, such as datasets from AVHRR, Landsat and VEGETATION. </p>
</text>
