<text id="autogum_academic_doc210" title="Impact of Fabric Properties on Textile Pressure Sensors Performance" shortTile="impact-fabric-properties" author="Luca Possanzini, Marta Tessarolo, Laura Mazzocchetti, Enrico  Gianfranco Campari, Beatrice Fraboni" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1424-8220/19/21/4686/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Conclusions</head>
<p>
This work investigates the physical mechanisms controlling the performance of textile pressure sensors directly fabricated onto different fabrics realized with natural and synthetic fibers. It presents a detailed study of how the fabric type, weaving and structure influences the pressure sensors performance in dynamic operation mode. It demonstrates how the mechanical properties of the fabric substrates affect the textile pressure sensor fabricated onto them. </p>

<p>We studied the mechanical and sensing features of textile based pressure sensors directly fabricated onto four different types of textile substrates such as polyamide (A and B), polyester (C) and cotton (D), and with different structures. </p>

<p>The elastic properties of the fabric used to realize the textile pressure sensor resulted in having a relevant impact on the sensor performance. Fabrics with good elastic properties and wide dynamic strain range during compression result in a highly sensitive sensor (fabric A and B). </p>

<p>However, also fabrics with poor elastic features can be used to realize good textile pressure sensors that, indeed under compression respond with a lower strain dynamic range and thus have a limited sensitivity, but guarantee a high reliability and stability in dynamic operation mode (fabric C). </p>

<p>Textile pressure sensor A, based on a three-knitted layer of polyamide, shows good performance and high sensitivity in an high dynamic range (30%) due to its elastic behavior. Sensors based on fabric B show a lower reproducibility for each cycle due to the intermediate elastic properties of the pristine fabric. In this case, the macroscopic geometrical change during compression and decompression affects the sensor performance in terms of reliability even if it presents the highest sensitivity value. Sensor C, based on polyester, is the fabric with the worst elastic properties and it shows a very good stability, except for the first compression cycle. After the first compression, the thickness of fabric C varies under stress with a very low dynamic strain range (10%) that, however, results in a reasonable electrical output signal. Its sensitivity is lower with respect to sensor A, but it can still be very useful for real life applications. Fabric D, the elastic cotton fabric, shows similar mechanical properties along the vertical direction to fabric C but sensors D and C exhibit a very different behavior. In the case of sensor D, it may be the microscopic level which affects the performance and, as suggested from the conductance plots in <figure>Figure 7</figure>, after each cycle delamination or cracks occurring in the coating may lead to a deterioration of the PEDOT:PSS on the surface. We thus conclude that textile sensors, fabricated onto fabrics with good elastic properties in the vertical direction, indeed show a greater sensitivity but could be less reliable if compared to similar sensors deposited onto a stiffer fabric. </p>

<p>We also assessed the effects of varying the conductive polymer formulation. Textile pressure sensors realized onto four fabric substrates (A, B, C and D) with a PEDOT:PSS formulation containing ethylene glycol show on average a higher sensitivity, associated with a lower stability and lower reliability with respect to comparable pressure sensors fabricated onto identical fabric substrates but with a pristine PEDOT:PSS formulation. </p>

<p>In summary, the results we report in this work underline how to understand and validate the performance of textile pressure sensors in a dynamic operation mode. The sensitivity is not the only parameter that must be taken into account and the sensor’s response after multiple, repetitive compression cycles should also be considered. Fully textile pressure sensors are complex systems and in order to optimize them for real life applications it is important to consider several aspects, from the macroscopic to the microscopic scale. Reliability is an important and fundamental issue that should drive and guide the research and development of textile pressure sensors towards actual needs. We believe the results reported here open the way to a full optimization of textile pressure sensors in terms of most suitable fabrics, the range of linear pressure responses, sensitivity and dynamic operation behaviors to better fit the requirements of a large variety of dedicated real-life applications.
 </p>
</text>
