<text id="autogum_academic_doc406" title="How Abusive Supervision Affects Employees’ Unethical Behaviors: A Moderated Mediation Examination of Turnover Intentions and Caring Climate" shortTile="abusive-supervision" author="Shubo Liu, Qianlin ZHU, Feng Wei" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4187/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Theoretical Background and Hypotheses</head><head> 2.1. The Mediating Role of Turnover Intentions</head>
<p>Abusive supervision refers to a destructive leadership style where employees perceive treatment from their supervisor as hostile verbal and/or non-verbal expressions, such as ridiculing, yelling at, and intimidating subordinates; taking credit for subordinates’ achievements; and attributing undesirable outcomes to subordinates’ personal factors. Based on previous studies, we argue that psychological contract theory provides a new perspective in explaining subordinates who display unethical behavior in abusive organizational situations.  </p>

<p>Psychological contract theory is deeply influenced by the social exchange theory. Further, it has been proposed that reciprocity is central to explaining the relationships between the evaluation of the psychological contract and employee attitudes and behaviors. According to psychological contract theory, employees hold a specific set of beliefs regarding their relationship with the organization, which includes the reciprocal obligations of each party. As noted by Robinson, “psychological contracts refer to employees’ perceptions of what they owe to their employers and what their employers owe to them”. Researchers have shown that psychological contracts include both transactional and relational components. The transactional component involves the more static aspects of the exchange relationship, such as pay and benefits. The relational component involves the more flexible aspects of the exchange relationship that presume a long-term relationship with the organization, such as training and development opportunities, promotion opportunities, and support from supervisors.  </p>

<p>Employee turnover is defined as the cessation of membership in an organization by an individual who has received monetary compensation from the organization. The turnover research has paid attention to the intentions and reasons behind turnover and to its consequences. For example, Mobley provided a comprehensive explanation of the psychological process underlying turnover. In the process of making a withdrawal decision, individuals first evaluate their current jobs and experience satisfaction or dissatisfaction based on these jobs. A turnover intention can be formed if psychological attachment is decreased.  </p>

<p>Previous studies have clearly established that leadership can play an important role in construction and maintenance of employees’ psychological contract. For example, when supervisors show abusive supervision behaviors to subordinates, subordinates will regard it as disrespect, contempt and humiliation to themselves. This is contrary to the expectation or belief that one should be treated fairly. It violates the exchange principle and ethics of “equality and reciprocity” between the two parties in the relationship, damages the positive image of the supervisors in the eyes of subordinates. That is, abusive supervision creates a low-quality relationship between supervisors and subordinates, which decreases the subordinates’ attachment and loyalty to the supervisor and organization. In this case, subordinates who do not feel that their supervisors care about them are unlikely to feel obliged to remain within the organization. Moreover, subordinates are concerned about whether supervisors can provide them with sufficient learning and development opportunities and a just climate. As abusive supervisors struggle to meet subordinates’ expectations, the relational contract between subordinates and supervisors or organization will be difficult to maintain. Similarly, a number of empirical studies have confirmed the positive relationship between abusive supervision and the turnover intentions of subordinates Therefore, we hypothesize <b>H1:</b></p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Abusive supervision will be positively related to subordinates’ turnover intentions.</hi> </p>

<p>Turnover intentions signal that the relational contract between subordinates and the organization has been breached. It stands to reason that, if an individual feels that this relationship has been breached, then they will develop strong intentions to quit. A subordinate with strong turnover intentions has effectively quit before officially leaving the organization and is emotionally disconnected from other employees and the organization, but such individuals should be less likely to be concerned about what their employer owes them or what they owe their employer in a relational sense. Not only will such subordinates be less likely to help others, we argue that they will be more prone to behaving in ways that are counter to organizational policies, practices, and norms. Recent research reveals that turnover intentions result in increased incidents of negative work behavior. We accordingly propose that turnover intentions impact subsequent unethical behavior and ultimately serve as a critical mediating mechanism explaining the relationship between abusive supervision and unethical behavior. Therefore, we hypothesize<b>H2:</b></p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Turnover intentions is positively related to subordinates’ unethical behavior.</hi> </p>

<p>We hypothesize a positive association between abusive supervision and subordinates’ turnover intentions. We also hypothesize that there is a positive relationship between turnover intentions and subordinates’ unethical behavior. Together, these hypotheses suggest that turnover intentions mediate the relationships between abusive supervision and subordinates’ unethical behavior. These mediated relationships are in line with research on psychological contract theory which has support the relationship between leadership and subordinates’ behavior. Therefore, we hypothesize<b>H3:</b></p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Turnover intentions mediate the positive relationship between abusive supervision and unethical behavior.</hi> </p>

<head> 2.2. The Moderating Role of Caring Climate</head>
<p>There is reason to believe that the mechanism proposed in the above hypotheses may vary in its strength. Psychological contract theory argued that organizational characteristics (e.g., organizational climate) affect how individuals cope with decreased psychological contract. Here, we propose that organizational climate will play critical roles in shaping the violation-behavior relationship. </p>
</text>
