<text id="autogum_academic_doc626" title="Obesity in the Liver Transplant Setting" shortTile="obesity-liver-transplant" author="Carlos Moctezuma-Velazquez, Ernesto Márquez-Guillén, Aldo Torre" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6643/11/11/2552/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Obesity Before Liver Transplantation</head><head> 2.1. How Should Obesity be Defined in Patients with Cirrhosis Considered for LT?</head>
<p>
The first obstacle is to define obesity in this population. Elamparast et al. recently summarized the most commonly used definitions in this group of patients:  </p>

<dl class="html-bullet"><dt id="">-</dt><dd>
BMI ≥ 30 kg/m2 (Asian population: ≥25 kg/m2);</dd><dt id="">-</dt><dd>
Percentage of fat mass ≥28% in men and ≥40% in women;</dd><dt id="">-</dt><dd>
Waist circumference ˃102 cm in men and ˃88 cm in women (Asian population: A waist circumference ˃90 cm in men and ˃80 cm in women);</dd><dt id="">-</dt><dd>
Visceral fat area ≥100 cm2 on abdominal computed tomography.</dd></dl>

<p>The use of BMI has several limitations in patients with decompensated cirrhosis, as reflected by the fact that sarcopenia outperforms BMI as a predictor of outcomes after LT. First of all, a high BMI may be due to fluid overload/ascites, and not obesity per se, as exemplified in a study in which adjusting BMI for the liters of ascites drained at the time of LT resulted in moving one-fifth of patients from one BMI category to a lower one. Also, BMI gives no information about body composition: It cannot tell the difference between muscle, subcutaneous, or visceral adipose tissue, which have different implications. Studies looking at body composition on cross-sectional imaging have found that sarcopenia and low subcutaneous adipose tissue, but not BMI, are associated with mortality in male and female patients with cirrhosis, respectively. Excessive visceral fat when associated with sarcopenia, a term known as sarcopenic obesity, is also associated with increased mortality. In the case of living donor liver transplant (LDLT) patients, sarcopenia, myosteatosis, and the visceral-to-subcutaneous-adipose-tissue ratio, but not visceral or subcutaneous tissue on their own, have been associated with mortality. This reinforces the fact that more than the size of a patient, which is what the BMI stands for, it is the composition that matters. For the same reasons, waist circumference is not the best method to assess obesity in these patients. Trying to circumvent some of these limitations, the European Association for the Study of the Liver guidelines for nutrition in patients with cirrhosis recommend to adjust the BMI for the confounding effect of fluid retention (i.e., dry-BMI), though there is no perfect correlation between BMI and ascites, and in fact, BMI corrected for ascites drained at the time of LT failed to predict relevant outcomes after LT. Likewise, a modified BMI calculated by multiplying BMI (kg/m2) by serum albumin (g/L) with the intention of compensating for volume overload was found of no use to predict clinical outcomes. </p>

<p>In conclusion, when available, we suggest obesity be defined according to the visceral fat area on body composition analysis, especially in the research setting, because the impact of obesity on LT may be modified by the coexistence of sarcopenia, myosteatosis, and/or low subcutaneous adipose tissue.  </p>

<head> 2.2. Should Morbidly Obese Patients be Listed for LT?</head>
<p>
Some LT programs consider morbid obesity a relative contraindication for LT based on the latest recommendations from the American Association for the Study of the Liver. However, evidence evaluating the role of obesity on outcomes after LT is conflicting. When needed, patients with severe and morbid obesity do benefit from LT, meaning they live longer than they would do without it, and LT in these patients strays far away from being futile, with five-year survival rates well above 50%. Evidence so far does not support using a strict BMI cutoff to deny someone candidacy for LT, however obesity is frequently associated with other conditions that may be contraindications for LT such as cardiovascular disease, cancer, renal dysfunction, and pulmonary hypertension. Also, obesity is a risk factor for NAFLD, which though traditionally considered to have similar post-LT outcomes to those of other etiologies of liver disease, may in fact have lower one-year survival due to cardiovascular and cerebrovascular diseases. In summary, more than obesity itself, it is the sum of the comorbidities of the individual patient that determines LT outcomes and as such, morbid obesity should not be considered on its own a contraindication for LT, but in turn should trigger a rigorous pre-LT assessment to carefully select potential recipients, as discussed below.  </p>
</text>
