<text id="autogum_academic_doc155" title="Evaluating the Power Grid Investment Behavior in China: From the Perspective of Government Supervision" shortTile="evaluating-power" author="Yanbin Li, Feng Zhang, Yun Li, Bingkang Li, Zhen Li" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/21/4192/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Power grid investment behavior (PGIB) is the core business of power grid enterprises, the basis of the stable operation of power systems, and also an important guarantee for social and economic development. The scientific supervision of PGIB can contribute to rationalizing the transmission and distribution price system, as well as reducing the price of electricity consumption, thereby promoting the optimal allocation of resources and stimulating the vitality of the real economy. </p>

<p>In March 2015, a new round reform of power system in China was launched, which established the reform plan of “promoting the marketization of generation and sale side, and strengthening government supervision of the power grid link”. For PGIB, the task of “strengthening the supervision of investment behavior, cost, and investment operating efficiency of power grids” was clearly presented. Since the implementation of the new power reform, the process of the power market construction steadily advanced, and obvious marketization effects was achieved on the power generation side and power sale side. However, the supervision of the monopoly link to the power grid is insufficient. </p>

<p>After the new power reform, scholars chose different subjects and perspectives to study the related issues of the development of China’s power industry. There were many studies focused on the marketization of the power industry. Around the theme of irrationality in the electricity pricing mechanism, Reference used the fundamental theory of electricity economics to analyze the pricing methods and the forms of China’s power market with the reform of electric power industry, and pointed out the characteristics and main problems of China’s existing tiered electricity pricing. Reference proposed an inter-regional electricity transaction model to illustrate the new pricing mechanism. Reference constructed transmission reliability indices and a unified cross-regional transmission pricing model based on the cross-regional electricity trading, electrical regime, and price polices in China. There were also many scholars that studied the theme of transaction mode and operation strategy of the power retailers and generators in the electricity market. Reference constructed a master–slave game model considering bilateral contract transactions between multiple generators and large consumers, and gave the solution of Nash equilibrium solution of the game, such that both generators and consumers can benefit from participating in the game. Reference considered China’s new electricity reform and related policies as a prerequisite, carried out a depth analysis of the power generation and sales companies bidding model, and put forward a game strategy of a single sales company and multiple power producers that considered network constraints based on the principle of dark auction in game theory.  </p>

<p>In addition to the marketization of power industry, as the main cost of power grid enterprises, PGIB has an important impact on the approval of transmission and distribution prices, which should be strictly monitored by the government. However, at present, whether from the perspective of government or academic research, attention to the supervision of PGIB is relatively limited. Specifically, from the perspective of government functions, the supervision of the electric power industry in China is mainly carried out by the National Development and Reform Commission (NDRC), the State-Owned Assets Supervision and Administration Management Commission of the State Council (SASAC), the National Energy Administration (NEA), and other auxiliary departments. Among them, the SASAC is the owner of the power grid enterprise assets; thus, its supervision aims at maintaining and increasing the value of state-owned assets, and does not involve industrial supervision. As a national macro-control department, the NDRC’s supervision of the power industry is mainly based on industry strategic planning and terminal supervision such as electrovalence, but does not focus on the PGIB. The NEA is responsible for the formulation and implementation of industry specific policies, but there is no systematic regulatory document for the regulation of PGIB. However, the above-mentioned regulatory authorities are yet to form a synergistic supervision of PGIB. In addition, China’s power grid enterprises have high administrative level and monopoly status, which increase the information asymmetry between the government and enterprises, bring many obstacles to the implementation of regulatory policies, and lead to the high cost of power grid enterprises and the difficulty of rationalizing the pricing mechanism of power transmission and distribution. </p>

<p>From the perspective of academic research, the studies were mainly related to the macro description and analysis of the current situation and development direction of supervision. Reference pointed out that the current situation of China’s energy legislation could not meet the requirements of coordination of economic, security, and ecological objectives of power regulation. Reference argued that China’s regulatory capacity should be comprehensively enhanced from three aspects: (1) strengthening the incentive supervision of transmission and distribution links, (2) vigilance against market forces, and (3) strengthening the overall planning of electricity reform and environmental policies. The abovementioned researches did not provide a feasible regulatory approach for the supervision of PGIB. </p>
</text>
