<text id="autogum_academic_doc650" title="Associations between Witnessing and Perpetrating Online Hate in Eight Countries: The Buffering Effects of Problem-Focused Coping" shortTile="associations-between" author="Sebastian Wachs, Michelle  F. Wright, Ruthaychonnee Sittichai, Ritu Singh, Ramakrishna Biswal, Eun-mee Kim, Soeun Yang, Manuel Gámez-Guadix, Carmen Almendros, Katerina Flora, Vassiliki Daskalou, Evdoxia Maziridou" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/20/3992/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Hatred directed at members of groups due to their origin, race, gender, religion, or sexual orientation is by no means new. Comparatively new, however, is the practice of online hate, which has increased recently against the background of the proliferation of social media. Online hate can be expressed through offensive, insulting, or threatening texts or speech online, such as posts, comments, text messages, videos, and pictures. It directly or indirectly targets social groups based on gender, sexual orientation, disability, race, ethnicity, nationality, or religion, or individuals representing a certain group. Online hate, as a specific form of online aggression, has similarities and differences to other forms of online aggression, such as online bullying. Both online hate and online bullying are used to intentionally harm and devalue a person or group using information and communication technology (ICT). Online bullying, however, is often described as a repeated activity that occurs over a longer period of time, whereas online hate may be a single act. Whereas online bullying can be directed at an individual, online hate is necessarily based on prejudicial views about social groups. Given these conceptual similarities, some research has found an overlap between involvement in online hate and online bullying among adolescents. However, this overlap is not complete; some adolescents engage in online hate but not in online bullying. Thus, to understand why some adolescents are involved in online hate, more research is needed.  </p>

<p>Online hate might be an especially important topic for adolescents because adolescents use ICT for the accomplishment of developmental tasks (i.e., identity formation and development of personal moral values and political opinions). Online hate might interfere with these processes; initial research on online hate and research in related fields, such as offline and online discrimination, showed that such experiences impact adolescents’ wellbeing and psychological functioning. Since witnessing online hate is one of the most common ways to experience it, and past research has shown that even witnessing (online) aggression can negatively affect bystanders’ social relationships, resulting in toxic stress, and is correlated with perpetration, research on bystanders is important. Problem-focused coping strategies mitigate the detrimental effects of experiencing stressful situations on adolescents’ mental health. The way in which bystanders manage stress and the negative emotions associated with online hate might influence whether adolescents are more or less likely to react aggressively, thereby becoming perpetrators themselves. However, no study has investigated whether problem-focused coping strategies moderate the association between being a bystander and perpetrator of online hate. In this study, we explored this relationship in detail. The results might help with developing intervention programs to reduce online hate among adolescents and mitigate its potential negative effects. The results might also help us to understand how adolescents can be supported to manage this emerging online risk. </p>

<head> 1.1. Associations between Being a Bystander and Perpertrator of Online Hate</head>
<p>
Adolescents can be directly involved in online hate, as victims or perpetrators, or indirectly involved as bystanders who observe online hate without being personally targeted by hateful material, comments, or posts. Initial research on the prevalence rates of different forms of involvement in online hate suggests that the most common way to experience online hate is by witnessing it as a bystander. For example, in one study among 3500 adolescents and young adults from four countries, approximately 53% of American, 48% of Finnish, 39% of British, and 31% of German participants said they had witnessed cyberhate. In the same study, 16% of American, 10% of Finnish, 12% of British, and 4% of German participants reported that they have been personally targeted by cyberhate. More recently, a study with French participants aged 11 to 20 years found that around 57% of participants had been exposed to online hate, approximately 10% were victimized through online hate on social networking sites, and 5% published or shared online hate material.  </p>

<p>Several reasons support the suggestion that bystanders of online hate are more likely to be perpetrators of online hate. From a theoretical point of view, Bandura’s social learning theory posits that humans learn in part by imitating models, and that the status of models increases the likelihood that their behavior will be imitated. Consequently, online hate perpetration might be explained by observational learning. Online hate is often conducted with the aim of influencing values within a peer group and establishing group identity. Thus, when adolescents observe that their peers spread online hate and learn that online hate is appropriate or admirable behavior that can increase their social status and acceptance, bystanders might be more likely to participate and share, post, or forward hateful or denigrating online material against social groups. This assumption also seems reasonable because some research on (cyber)bullying has shown that being a bystander can increase moral disengagement and negative attitudes toward victims and reduce empathy for the victim. Some empirical evidence shows that individuals tend to use more aggressive expressions in their online communication and interactions when their peers behave aggressively. We therefore assumed that bystanders to online hate have higher odds of being perpetrators of online hate.  </p>
</text>
