<text id="autogum_academic_doc722" title="Sustainable Public Procurement—External Forces and Accountability" shortTile="sustainable-public" author="Rob Vluggen, Cees  J. Gelderman, Janjaap Semeijn, Marc van Pelt" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5696/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Literature Review</head>
<p>
This research uses the public procurement system to understand the impact of external stakeholders on sustainable public procurement. The concepts of sustainable public procurement and accountability are presented, against which the role of external stakeholders is positioned, and to what extent they are able to hold public organizations accountable. </p>

<head> 2.1. Sustainable Public Procurement</head>
<p>
Public procurement represents a large portion of annual public spending and has been estimated to be around 20% of the GDP across all EU member states. Public procurement is the process by which central, regional, and local governments, governed by law and regulations, purchase goods and services. The public procurement process has generally been intended as a rigid process narrowly aimed at the basic principles of European tendering policies. However, given its economic significance, public procurement has the potential to influence markets in terms of sustainability development. As a result, the public sector, through procurement, is able to contribute to sustainable objectives such as social equity, economic development, and ecological advantages.  </p>

<p>Sustainable public procurement has been debated through theoretical and specific case study papers. According to Brammer and Walker, sustainable public procurement has been mainly considered by the public sector in order to stimulate the private market towards sustainability and creating awareness on the subject. In sustainable public procurement, the Triple Bottom Line is used to affect a balance in goal setting between economical, ecological, and social aspects of the goods and services procured. Strategic sustainable goals in public procurement can be grouped into two categories, ecological and social, and according to Glas et al. the integration of a broader concern for social and environmental issues is considered to be strategic within public organizations. In daily practice, achieving these more strategic goals seems to be quite difficult. Glas et al. show that the size of an organization has an influence on achieving goals. Large organizations are more capable of creating the right incentives for implementation of sustainable procurement. While small organizations often struggle to facilitate the necessary incentives. Furthermore, the internal discussion between purchasers, deputy managers, and the city council on the cost allocation of a more sustainable procurement policy is a major influencer. This refers to the need for efficient spend of tax payer’s money and accountability within municipalities. </p>

<p>Procurement departments need to extend traditional considerations to include the triple bottom line in organizational decision-making criteria and drive positive impacts in these areas through what they procure. The ability for public procurement departments and private organizations to influence each other across a range of areas covering strategic and attitudinal issues, highlights the impact that parties can have on public and corporate sustainability. </p>

<p>Notwithstanding this reciprocal relationship, there remains a paucity of research on external actors participating and influencing public sector sustainability. </p>

<p>A study by Walker et al. shows external drivers and barriers influencing environmental initiatives. Regulation has been found to be a major external driver of green procurement. Environmental legislation is the backdrop for other drivers such as value champions’ endeavors or risk minimization efforts. Other external drivers are customer pressure, competitive advantage and pressure by NGO’s. External barriers include regulation, as it also can inhibit sustainable practices, lack of supplier commitment, and industry specific barriers.  </p>

<p>Despite many available tools and good initiatives, there is no consistent positive view on the results of sustainable public procurement. Reasons could be the missing ambition, the limitation to minimum green requirements in tenders, the lack of maturity in strategy and execution and/or the perceived additional costs of sustainability. One way to promote sustainable procurement is by adopting more sustainable selection criteria in EU tenders. Support comes from the EU Buying Green Handbook 2016, the 2012 Procurement Law in the Netherlands (effected in 2016), and sustainable guidelines from the government (PIANOo) for many product categories (<ref target="http://www.pianoo.nl">www.pianoo.nl</ref>). However, these criteria lack legal status and as a result remain non-committal. Nevertheless, more and more municipalities use a strategic approach to make their procurement activities more sustainable, by preferably buying local and as sustainable as possible, despite all difficulties in legislation, government criteria, and complex stakeholder management.  </p>
</text>
