<text id="autogum_academic_doc549" title="The Future of Hyperspectral Imaging" shortTile="future-hyperspectral" author="Stefano Selci" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2313-433X/5/11/84/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Contributions</head>
<p>
Hyperspectral imaging offers great opportunities, but it requires careful handling of information obtained in order to have a clear vision of the spectroscopic signatures that might become hidden within a huge amount of data. Moreover, different sources of signals can be obtained simultaneously to each other and a problem arises in how to meaningfully merge the different contributions. </p>

<p>Therefore, there are contributions related to fuse different spectral bands or deal with signals originating from diverse decay channels (e.g., luminescence and Raman). </p>

<p>Likewise, in order to reduce the effort, various compression strategies in the spectroscopic realm are well illustrated. </p>

<p>More theoretical smart tools are then introduced and reviewed that are sophisticated and at the same time versatile so as to better investigate the intricacies of HIS hypercube in searching for specific spectroscopic signatures. </p>

<p>Various specific applications are presented as well. Aside from their specific application areas, their practical realization requires a high skill level from the technical set-up to the data analysis, to make the presentation more widely interesting. </p>

<p>In particular, there are experimental and theoretical contributions for time series observations, compression, and specific signatures, which are a very firm step toward 4D representation and usage of HSI data. </p>

<p>In Radi et al., data spectral fusion is shown as coming from a Visible and Near Infrared VIS/NIR spectroscopic system and from a VIS/NIR hyperspectral imaging systems used respectively in interactance mode and in reflection mode with the aim of acquiring the spectral information of whole tubers for predicting the primordial leaf count of potatoes. In particular, the HSI unit uses an optical fiber to illuminate a large portion of the sampled potato with the imaging spectrograph directly attached to a CCD camera, acquiring spectral information along a line of the potato that is held by a scanner system, therefore in push broom modality. </p>

<p>Results inferred from this study, with the aid of partial least squares (IPLS), initiate the possibility of developing a portable or stationary electronic system aimed at obtaining a rapid and accurate prediction of the sprouting activity of stored potatoes. Future steps could be in testing more growing seasons for many cultivated varieties (cultivars), as well as improving the robustness and reproducibility of the prediction models. Furthermore, an increase in the productivity of the method could be achieved through improved data elaboration, for instance reducing the number of selected wavelengths, and other IPLS models, such as moving average IPLS, synergy IPLS, backward/forward IPLS, or else a genetic algorithm. </p>

<p>In Bonifazi et al., a HSI set-up is used to evaluate the stability against light and UV ageing of several painting materials, in particular powder pigments and commercial watercolors to be used in retouching. In order to obtain HSI data, a pushbroom commercial system acquires hyperspectral images in the short-wave infrared region, in the spectral wavelength interval between 1000 nm and 2500 nm. The pixel resolution by scanning the sample is between 30 micron and 300 micron, building the image one line at a time while the sample is scanned on a moving sample tray in front of the camera. The paper shows the possibility of evaluating minute spectral variations due to ageing times well before the eyes can detect changes: The classification techniques based on principal component analysis (PCA) and k-nearest neighbor (KNN) of hyperspectral data are effectively capable of monitoring the changes occurring in the painting layers. Therefore, HSI coupled with a chemometric approach allows one to monitor ageing modifications of paint layers, showing the possibility of detecting damages before its irreversibility, a result of great relevance in the field of cultural heritage and particularly useful in monitoring artworks and restoration interventions over time at a lower cost compared to similar methods. Future research lines are suggested, for instance in studying other restoration materials, like synthetic resins, or the classification and forecast of material behavior involved in cultural heritage artifacts. </p>

<p>In Bachmann et al., hyperspectral image sequences are considered for the detection and tracking of vehicles realizing low-rate video hyperspectral imaging systems. The vehicles are assumed to be driving through the parking lot and passing behind various occlusions within the scene, such as trees in the background and parked cars, at a specified maximum speed. The set-up includes an integration of a high rate data acquisition hyperspectral line scanner with a high-speed maritime pan-tilt unit that contains position and pointing information. Then, the realization of digital elevation models (DEM) is devised: HSI time series imagery after integration onto a telescopic pole system from multiple vantage points, stereo hyperspectral views, and the definition of bi-directional reflectance distribution function can all be derived. Two examples of the low-rate hyperspectral video approach are shown, that is the imaging of the dynamics of the surf zone in a coastal setting and moving vehicle imaging in the presence of many occlusions. For future, the authors propose further improvements in hyperspectral image acquisition rates by reducing the size of the across-track spatial dimension or the adoption of already commercially available sensors with on-chip spectral binning. </p>
</text>
