<text id="autogum_academic_doc473" title="SAR-mediated Similarity Assessment of the Property Profile for New, Silicon-Based AChE/BChE Inhibitors" shortTile="sarmediated-similarity" author="Andrzej Bak, Hana Pizova, Violetta Kozik, Katarina Vorcakova, Jiri Kos, Jakub Treml, Klara Odehnalova, Michal Oravec, Ales Imramovsky, Pavel Bobal, Adam Smolinski, Zdeněk Trávníček, Josef Jampilek" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1422-0067/20/21/5385/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Finding critical in vitro and/or in silico parameters (descriptors or properties) of the hit→lead→seed→drug route is still a long-term aspiration and monumental challenge in drug discovery projects, mainly due to the intrinsic multidimensionality of the problem. In concert with the medicinal chemist’s intuition (or serendipity), the computer-assisted molecular design (CAMD) approaches are regarded as an integral method for the exhaustive transformation of the compound topology or topography and/or the electronic properties into the property-based chemical space. The systematic observational of trends of structural chemical modifications that produce corresponding changes in the biological responses for a congeneric series of molecules are fundamental for the multidimensional quantitative structure–activity (mD-QSAR) studies. Moving from complex biological relationships to simple QSAR models seems to be a ‘triumph of hope over experience,’ since modelers sometimes are playing a ‘glass bead game.’ The quantitative mapping of experimental/calculated properties/descriptors into the ADMET-driven molecular potency is frequently a ‘hit-or-miss affair.’ Therefore, some structure–activity relationship (SAR)-mediated guides are urgently needed at the ‘pre-synthesis’ stage.  </p>

<p>Molecular similarity is unarguably at the core of many SAR-based methods, assuming that small variations in structure lead to small changes in activity. In other words, the working tenet of QSAR is that molecules with high similarity share common effects (similarity principle); however, the validity of the assumption is still questionable—there is no absolute standard (or metric) of similarity. In fact, similarity is a subjective concept directly related to aspects of human cognition; this phenomena is sometimes called ‘psychological proximity’. Maggiora’s provocative statement that, “Similarity, like pornography, is difficult to define, but you know it when you see it,” is probably a better illustration of cognitive aspects of similarity. Despite the presence of fluid scientific boundaries, e.g., some similarity metrics exhibit size-dependent behavior—similarity quantification is still a powerful concept that allows us to specify (with some confidence) the shared host–quest interactions. In fact, the idea of specifying a numerical measure of the intermolecular similarity based on the degree of the resemblance between two objects, each described by a number of attributes, has been widely applied in chemical information systems. A set of characteristics might be denoted by a bit-string representation, sometimes augmented with the weighting factors, assigning varying importance to the particular descriptors to calculate a quantitative measure of the structural resemblance between objects, for instance Tanimoto coefficient. Obviously, a crucial question that confronts drug ‘hunters’ is, which properties or features should be employed in the receptor-dependent (RD) methods that rely on the principle of complementarity or in the receptor-independent (RI) ones that are mainly based on the principle of similarity? Hence, many attempts have been undertaken in order to implement some rough guidelines, sometimes called ‘rules of thumb’ for both the ligand and structure-based in silico protocols; however, even meeting the rules does not guarantee the final success of drug discovery projects. </p>

<p>A confusing aspect of many SAR analyses is that the ‘fragile event’ can occur, when even small structural changes (colloquially termed ‘magic methyl’) can result in a boost of potency for the target, or in a more detrimental manner, can completely destroy biological response—a phenomenon known as activity ‘hotspot’ or activity ‘cliff’ in structure-activity landscape. In other words, finding the optimal balance between ADMET-related properties and desired drug potency (‘sweet spot’) can be rationalized graphically by extension of the 2D similarity-based projection with activity data in the form of a ‘biological response surface’ or SAR landscapes. Intuitively, we feel that the structure–activity landscapes are heterogeneous in nature with unevenly distributed regions that are reminiscent of Tolkien’s Misty Mountains with gently slopes, steep cliffs and stony bridges. Geographically, a successful voyage (or exploration) requires a map indicating smooth and flat regions that are easy to navigate or jagged parts that are tough to traverse. Chemically, gently sloped hills pinpoint areas where gradual structural variations are accompanied by moderate changes in activity, whereas in flat SAR landscapes, the biological data varies little over the wide modifications in the compound structure—further substitutions are not likely to result in more potent molecules. In fact, disallowed structural modifications can be highlighted in the sharply non-uniform regions where chemically related compounds are characterized by huge response variations, forming steep cliffs in the activity landscape. Moreover, chemical bridges can be observed with molecules connecting different local SAR models. The detection of the activity hotspots provides reasonable hints to the key question of medicinal chemistry regarding the impact of molecule rearrangement on the activity profile. The numerical quantification of activity cliffs is frequently performed using a variety of fingerprint representations or similarity metrics; for instance, the structure–activity landscape index (SALI) has been proposed to evaluate SAR smoothness. </p>
</text>
