<text id="autogum_academic_doc420" title="Impact of Educational Stage in the Application of Flipped Learning: A Contrasting Analysis with Traditional Teaching" shortTile="impact-educational" author="Santiago Pozo Sánchez, Jesús López Belmonte, Antonio  José Moreno Guerrero, Juan  Antonio López Núñez" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5968/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
The literature review carried out in this study allows us to confirm that applying flipped learning is a booming research field. Its benefits within the educational field have been verified by several authors, even though the effects of its application depend largely on the student typology in which they are put into practice. </p>

<p>The results obtained in the descriptive analysis allow us to verify that the results of its application vary, according to the educational stage in which the teacher performs their function, with a directly proportional trend observed between the effectiveness of the approach and the stage of student education. </p>

<p>In this way, a general analysis of the study variables shows positive results in the application of flipped learning in primary education and secondary education compared to traditional teaching methods. This is a trend seen in other similar studies. </p>

<p>The results obtained are similar to those found in the scientific literature, such as high motivation rates when participating in the teaching and learning process as well as during high levels of self-regulation and flexibility of the training process and notable improvements in interaction and collaboration with colleagues. The results also show greater capacity for decision-making and resolution of the problems raised, and achievement of the curricular objectives. </p>

<p>However, the results obtained in the analysis of applying the flipped learning approach in preschool education reflect the difficulties in adapting this model to the needs of the students of said stage. This is a fundamental requirement when considering the relevance of the methodology in question. The poor results obtained in the application of the flipped learning model originate from the absence of significant differences with respect to the results obtained with the traditional pedagogical model. This is a paradoxical fact that increases if we consider that the flipped model represents a genuine alternative and is optimized for pedagogical traditionalism. </p>

<p>Based on the literature analyzed, these results can be assigned to the characteristics inherent in preschool students. This typology of students may be considered an obstacle for the application of the flipped learning approach when faced with situations with a difficult resolution. For students of these age ranges, the requirement for certain levels of abstraction during the application of the approach and the limited manageability of digital teaching platforms could be a significant impediment. </p>

<p>Based on the analysis of the effectiveness of a traditional approach, in the three stages analyzed, this approach enhances one’s interaction with the contents and achievements of the learning objectives. The temporary use of a session is especially important in primary and secondary education. Self-regulation and creativity are the least empowered skills in preschool education, while interaction with the teacher and critical thinking are the least empowered in primary and secondary education. Of the eleven variables analyzed, only six of them in the preschool stage, four in the primary education stage, and three in the secondary education stage exceed the central score. </p>

<p>Regarding the analysis of the effectiveness of flipped learning, the access and choice of materials and content together with achieving learning objectives are the most potent variables in preschool education. High interaction with the teacher in primary and secondary education is encouraged, which highlights the temporary use of the session during this last stage. Of the eleven variables analyzed, eight in primary education and all in the elementary and secondary stages passed the central score. The results for students who followed a flipped learning methodology are higher than those for students who experienced traditional pedagogy in the elementary and secondary stages. Although this trend is maintained in preschool education, the difference between the results of both methodologies is much smaller. </p>

<p>When comparing the effects of flipped learning and a traditional methodology, flipped learning is only more effective in preschool education for the individualization of learning. In the primary education stage, the effectiveness of flipped learning materializes in the students’ autonomy, critical thinking, individualization, and interactions with teachers and classmates. In the secondary education stage, all skills (attitudinal, mental, interactive, and effective) are enhanced to a greater extent with the flipped learning approach, which highlights all the interactions between the students, peers, and teachers. </p>

<p>Regarding the comparison of the effects of flipped learning according to the educational stage in which it is put into practice, in preschool education, critical thinking is boosted more profusely, while self-regulation, autonomy, and interactions with peers stand out in their application more strongly during the primary stage than during the preschool stage. Secondary education achieves (compared to preschool education) superior results in self-regulation, autonomy, interaction with teachers and peers, the use of session time, and the individualization of learning. The effects in the primary and secondary stages are similar, with only a greater use of time during the secondary stage. </p>
</text>
