<text id="autogum_academic_doc509" title="Promising Prognosis Marker Candidates on the Status of Epithelial–Mesenchymal Transition and Glioma Stem Cells in Glioblastoma" shortTile="promising-prognosis" author="Yasuo Takashima, Atsushi Kawaguchi, Ryuya Yamanaka" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4409/8/11/1312/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The World Health Organization (WHO) classifies gliomas into four categories based on malignancy and overall survival (OS). Glioblastoma is the most malignant form of astrocytoma that is fast-growing (grade 4 glioma). The median OS of glioblastoma is 9–15 months and the five-year survival rate remains less than 5%. Radiotherapy with six cycles of concomitant temozolomide, an oral alkylating agent with minimal additional toxicity, is the standard treatment after surgery in glioblastoma patients. Thus, there is an immediate requirement for the early diagnosis and precise prediction of the prognosis for treatments of glioblastoma. </p>

<p>The invasiveness of glioblastoma depends on its high infiltration potential to invade the basement membranes of surrounding tissues. Glioma cells are reprogrammed to have increased motility via weakened cell adhesions and a dysregulated cytoskeleton; this is known as epithelial–mesenchymal transition (EMT). EMT is a biological process that polarized epithelial cell sheets undergo, wherein multiple biochemical changes culminate in mesenchymal phenotypes. Cells display altered morphology, resistance to chemotherapy, and <hi rend="italic">anoikis</hi> (a form of programmed cell death of cells detached from the basement membranes). EMT is also involved in other biological processes, including implantation and embryo development, wound healing, tissue regeneration, and neoplasia associated with cancer progression. During invasion in cancer, phenotypes also change as EMT is mainly induced by hypoxia and the transforming growth factor (TGF)-β released from glioma stem cells (GSCs), mesenchymal stem cells (MSCs), and myeloid cells recruited by hypoxia. The reverse is also essential for the formation of distant or disseminated tumor nodules. </p>

<p>Stem cells, including cancer stem cells (CSCs), are pluripotent and capable of self-renewal, like induced pluripotent stem (iPS) cells induced by the transcription factors Oct3/4, Sox2, c-Myc, and Klf4 or OCT4, SOX2, NANOG, and LIN28. The expression of OCT4, MYC, and KLF4 increases with increasing malignancy in astrocytomas, whereas MYC expression slightly decreases in recurrent glioblastomas. Exposure to temozolomide (TMZ) increases the expression of KLF4 and reduces the expression of Nanog and OCT4 in glioma cells, indicating that stem cell factors, especially KLF4, play pivotal roles in GSCs. The most common GSC marker CD133, also known as prominin-1 (<hi rend="italic">PROM1</hi>), is used to isolate GSCs by fluorescence-activated cell sorting (FACS) in primary glioma tissues and the cell lines U87 and T98G. There are changes in metabolism in glioma and oxidative phosphorylation, glycolysis, and glutaminolysis replace redox balance, bioenergetics, and biosynthesis, respectively. Tumor progression is enhanced by inflammation, which is an emerging hallmark of cancers that depends on the balance of glioma cell proliferation, migration, and escape from the immune system. However, the correlation between EMT and GSCs in glioblastoma has not been reported to date. </p>

<p>In this study, we focused on EMT and GSCs and performed multivariable analyses using the expression data and OS in patients with glioblastoma. To determine the distribution of survival of glioblastoma patients, we composed prognosis prediction formulae for the following components: epithelium (EPI), mesenchyme (MES), glioma (GLI), GSC, molecular target therapy (MTT) genes, and potential glioma biomarkers (PGBs). Consequently, several candidate genes were identified as promising glioblastoma predictors. </p>
</text>
