<text id="autogum_academic_doc475" title="New Molecular Insights into the Inhibition of Dipeptidyl Peptidase-4 by Natural Cyclic Peptide Oxytocin" shortTile="new-molecular-insights" author="Veera  C. S. R. Chittepu, Poonam Kalhotra, Tzayhri Osorio-Gallardo, Cristian Jiménez-Martínez, Raúl  René Robles-de la Torre, Tzayhri Gallardo-Velazquez, Guillermo Osorio-Revilla" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1420-3049/24/21/3887/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Proteases are associated with many signaling biological pathways, and it is has been proven that the number of diseases like cancer, HIV, infectious diseases, and diabetes are treated by inhibiting proteases. Pharmaceutical companies develop commercial drugs to inhibit aspartyl proteases, serine proteases, and cysteine proteases. Among several protease inhibitors, serine protease inhibitors received significant interest in various applications focused mainly in therapeutics. Serine protease inhibitors shown in Table 1, are used in treating diseases like immune-related disorders, inflammatory, respiratory, AIDS, neurodegenerative, and metabolic disorders. </p>

<p>Features like therapeutic potential, good binding affinity, low toxicity, and quickly cleavable by proteolytic enzymes, make cyclic peptides potential future therapeutics. Most of the cyclic peptides approved by the FDA (shown in Table 2) are used in bacterial and fungal infections, oncology drugs, gastrointestinal disorders, and anemia. Recently, cyclic peptides were proven to inhibit HIV-1 protease (aspartyl proteases) and elastase, shedding light onto the use of cyclic peptides as protease inhibitors. </p>

<p>Phage display technology, Incretin-based cyclic peptide, cyclic peptides from mRNA display, and split-pool synthesis are some of the tools used to develop cyclic peptide compounds. Recently computer-aided drug design technologies like molecular docking simulations are applied to identify, design rationally (called as de novo developed), and develop cyclic peptide ligand as leads to therapeutic drug targets of interest. Till today, cyclic peptides as therapeutics in regulating glucose metabolism by inhibiting proteases have not been reported for the treatment of diabetes mellitus. </p>

<p>In Mexico, approximately 11.5 million people live with diabetes mellitus (DM), which is the main leading cause of acquired blindness, non-traumatic lower-limb amputations, and chronic kidney failure diseases. Human dipeptidyl peptidase-4 (DPP4) is a serine protease, well known FDA-approved therapeutic drug target for regulating blood glucose metabolism and treating diabetes mellitus. Sitagliptin, Vildagliptin, Anagliptin, Saxagliptin, and Alogliptin are the main clinically used chemicals for human dipeptidyl peptidase-4 (DPP4) inhibition despite their side effects as pancreatitis, nausea, and anemia. It is well known that incretin hormones glucagon-like peptide 1 (GLP-1) and glucose-dependent insulinotropic polypeptide (GIP) are responsible for insulin release and glucose regulation. These hormones are inactivated by a serine protease human dipeptidyl peptidase-4 (DPP4). Since natural cyclic peptides are proven to inhibit various proteases, and to consider the beneficial aspects of cyclic peptides in comparison to small chemicals, like less toxicity, no accumulation in organs, and rapid degradation of peptides, we hypothesized that cyclic peptides from natural sources could be an alternative source of therapeutics to inhibit serine protease DPP4 for treatment of diabetes mellitus. </p>

<p>Among various naturally occurring cyclic peptides, oxytocin (natural cyclic peptide) was chosen in this study to prove our hypothesis that, cyclic peptides possess serine protease inhibition activity, and specifically inhibit DPP4. To demonstrate our hypothesis, activity atlas and field-based models of DPP4 inhibitors from natural origin were utilized to elucidate molecular insights of oxytocin peptide into DPP4 inhibition. In addition, molecular docking simulations were used to understand the binding poses and interacting residues responsible for inhibitory activity. Also, the stability of water molecules at the binding site of oxytocin was studied using 3D reference interaction site model (3D-RISM) to gain deep insights into the binding of the cyclic peptide at DPP4 druggable region. Finally, fluorescence assay was used to demonstrate the potential role of oxytocin as a DPP4 inhibitor experimentally. </p>
</text>
