<text id="autogum_academic_doc034" title="New Tricks in the Preparation Design for Prosthetic Ceramic Laminate Veeners" shortTile="new-tricks-preparation" author="Luca Ortensi, Tommaso Vitali, Roberto Bonfiglioli, Francesco Grande" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2673-1592/1/1/5/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The advent of adhesive restorative materials has introduced minimal intervention principles in restorative dentistry and prosthodontics. The necessity of making undercuts in the dental tissue has been abandoned due to new adhesive techniques that allow for the reconstruction of the cavities without excessive preparation for macromechanical retention. Also, the correct use of ceramic and composite materials with rigorous adhesive procedures allows a sound tissue preservation because of the minimally or even noninvasive (additive) approach, which is innovative, highly esthetic, and predictable in terms of both result and long-term prognosis. The aesthetics have also improved because of the high level of biomimetics of these new adhesive materials, which also allow for a better function within the oral cavity. Because of the hydrophobic characteristics of these materials, the correct use of adhesive techniques requires an effective moisture control in order to promote the bonding of the restorative materials and then to reduce failure rates of dental restorative treatments. Therefore, a performing isolation system that creates a barrier from the rest of the person’s mouth is necessary before executing adhesive procedures in order to control the moisture and microbes. Using a rubber dam can isolate the teeth and this allows the teeth to be restored dry and with relatively less exposure to intraoral bacteria. Other advantages of the use of a rubber dam include superior isolation of the tooth to be treated from the saliva in the mouth, improved visibility, reduced mirror fogging, enhanced visual contrast, soft tissue retraction, protection of the person by preventing ingestion or aspiration of instruments, materials and preventing oral soft tissues from contact with harmful materials used during operative procedures, such as phosphoric acids. </p>

<p>However, some problems related to the use of the rubber dam could be faced during prosthetic treatments, especially when rehabilitation of the anterior regions of the oral cavity has to be done with different indirect aesthetic restorations such as composite or ceramic laminate veneers (lithium disilicate, feldspathic ceramics). Incorrect rubber dam clamps placement may occupy a space that is needed for the restoration, besides possible damages to the marginal gingiva around the teeth. In addition, the use of the rubber dam leads to a loss of esthetics landmarks such as the midsagittal line, with subsequent difficulties for the correct placement of the veneers on the teeth. The small holes made in the sheet could disagree with the position of the teeth that have to be treated. In addition, inaccuracy in the reproduction of the position of the interdental contact points in the gypsum model during indirect restorations could lead to errors in the future positioning of the laminate veneers. The aim of this article is to present a clinical case report demonstrating an accurate operative protocol using different fine intraoperative maneuvers and tricks for the realization of prosthetic ceramic laminates in order to solve the problems mentioned above. </p>
</text>
