<text id="autogum_academic_doc512" title="Autonomic Stress Response and Perceived Effort Jointly Inform on Dual Tasking in Aging" shortTile="autonomic-stress" author="Giancarlo Condello, Roberta Forte, Pablo Monteagudo, Barbara Ghinassi, Angela Di Baldassarre, Laura Capranica, Caterina Pesce" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3425/9/11/290/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
With aging, gait seems no longer automated and walking becomes cognitively demanding. This is particularly evident when older individuals perform a concomitant cognitive task while walking, as indicated by the larger decrement in gait performance from single-task (ST) to dual-task (DT) conditions compared to younger adults. Furthermore, the performance decrement from ST to DT is proportional to the extent to which DT walking is perceived as stressful. In turn, acute stress seems detrimental to the ability to shield performance of a primary task when a secondary one must be performed concurrently. This is attributed to reduced efficiency of the cognitive control mechanisms responsible for resource allocation needed for successful DT performance. Indeed, these mechanisms rely on frontal-dependent cognition—the executive control network—some of which functions, as working memory is impaired by stress. </p>

<p>There is a range of subjective and objective approaches and tools to assess stress-related responses, resource allocation and effort in coping with physically and/or mentally challenging tasks. Subjective indexes of the perceptual and cognitive responsiveness to task performance, such as the rating of perceived exertion (RPE), may complement physiological measures for a comprehensive understanding of the responses to physical-cognitive DT performance.  </p>

<p>Among objective and non-invasive measurement, saliva sampling provides biomarkers relying on the two main systems that jointly contribute to psycho-physiologic stress responses: cortisol and α-amylase. Cortisol is secreted from the adrenal cortex via the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis, whereas α-amylase is secreted by the parotid gland in response to adrenergic activity.  </p>

<p>Salivary α-amylase (sAA) seems a more sensitive and generalizable stress response marker than cortisol, as it reacts more pronouncedly and rapidly to different types of stressors and returns to baseline levels immediately after the end of the stress bout without the carry-over effect observed for cortisol. Thus, sAA has been increasingly used as a valid biomarker of autonomic stress response within the sympathetic adrenomedullary system. Its stress responsiveness has been proven in different age groups throughout the lifespan including older adulthood. Aging tends to heighten the sympathetic tone, as revealed by a higher sAA global output than in younger adults, without attenuating the autonomic response to stress, as revealed by similar stress-related increases of sAA in younger and older adults.  </p>

<p>Studies of sAA response to physical stressors have mainly investigated the impact of physical exercise bouts of long duration (&gt;20 min) and moderate-to-high intensity (&gt;50% maximal oxygen consumption), showing that they acutely elevate sAA. Instead, the few studies on physically low demanding exercise (e.g., light self-paced walk) did not show any significant increase in sAA concentration.  </p>

<p>On the other hand, sAA response to physical exercise tasks has been rarely studied in relation to task difficulty and task-related cognitive challenges under ST and DT conditions. This is surprising, since there are neural commonalities between cognitive control in dual-tasking and biological acute stress responses, which become particularly relevant in aging. The cognitive control processes responsible for DT performance and task prioritization have been located in the prefrontal cortex. Prefrontal neurons, and particularly those engaged in working memory, are influenced by the activation of the two main stress axes responsible for an increased release of catecholamine and cortisol. This is relevant to the present study, because working memory seems more relevant to gait efficiency and resource allocation during DT walking in aging than the other core components of prefrontal-dependent cognition.  </p>

<p>Moreover, there is evidence that habitual physical activity and/or fitness may positively influence the ability to cope with dual-tasking. Habitually highly active and fit individuals also show, in the majority of studies, reduced physiologic stress responses. This is consistent with the hypothesis that regular physical activity may lead to physiological adaptations that buffer the effects of stressors in physical and non-physical domains (the cross-stressor adaptation hypothesis). However, the most used bio-physiological indicators of stress response were cortisol concentration or cardiovascular parameters of autonomic activity. The evidence on sAA is inconsistent and limited to young and middle-aged individuals’ responses to social-evaluative stressors. A recent study failed to find moderation of the acute sAA response to stressors by habitual physical activity levels. </p>

<p>Thus, in consideration of the above lack or inconsistency of evidence, the aim of the present study was twofold. The first aim was to investigate how aging individuals cope with locomotor-cognitive dual-tasking by analyzing complementary information on their autonomic response to DT performance and cognitive effort. Given the relevance of working memory for gait performance of older individuals, it was hypothesized that a working memory task would compete for shared resources with the walking task. We expected a higher objective response and subjective effort perception to the locomotor-cognitive DT as compared to the locomotor or cognitive task performed in isolation. Most aging research on locomotor-cognitive dual-tasking included participants aged above 60 years with comparison groups mostly aged below 40, whereas middle age is relatively understudied. To extend the evidence base to the transition to older adulthood, we included both late middle-aged and older adults.  </p>
</text>
