<text id="autogum_academic_doc118" title="Father’s Use of Parental Leave in Organizations with Different Institutional Logics" shortTile="fathers-use-parental" author="Lisa Vaagan Moen, Elin Kvande, Kine Nordli" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-0760/8/10/294/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 6. Conclusions</head>
<p>
The father’s quota which reserves part of the parental leave for the fathers has played an important role in getting more fathers to use parental leave. Earlier research has shown that there has been a lower use of leave among fathers in career jobs. The lower use in this group has been explained by the fact that these fathers are in jobs where career logic indicates the need to be always available and to be seen as irreplaceable. We have chosen to use the two-concept pairs ‘replaceable and irreplaceable’ and ‘available and unavailable’ to analyze the fathers’ use of the father’s quota in two different work organizations in order to see how different institutional logics impact the use of the father’s quota. </p>

<p>The findings show that the terms ‘replaceable and irreplaceable’ and ‘available and unavailable’ work somewhat differently among male managers in the engineering industry and male brokers in the financial industry. The managers in the engineering industry experience that it is possible to be unavailable and replaceable at work, thus they also choose to make themselves unavailable for work when they use the father’s quota. It is important for the male managers to set a boundary concerning work when they are on leave. By making themselves unavailable, they become replaceable at work because the organization has to find solutions without them.  </p>

<p>The brokers in the finance industry feel that they are irreplaceable at work and they want to be available for work at all times. The brokers have close contact with clients and they think being away on leave for three months is too long a period. Halrynjo et al. (2019) found that parental leave and absence from work are especially pinpointed as risks in Front End Finance. This is because one has a lot to lose in terms of customers, salary development, bonuses, and career opportunities. In their study, the focus is on mothers and that mothers are at a greater risk of losing their customers and “moving back to start.” The findings show that this is also the case among fathers in our study. In theory, it is not problematic among the fathers in this study to give up clients to colleagues, but then one has to start all over again when one is back from leave. Unlike the male managers, they experience that there is a risk to using the father’s quota when it comes to work and career. Thus, they make themselves available for work and they continue to be seen as irreplaceable.  </p>

<p>This shows that the institutional logics are closely linked to the concepts ‘available’ and ‘unavailable’. To be unavailable during leave time seems to be the logic for the male managers in the engineering industry. This is the type of culture and practice that is encouraged in the financial industry. At the same time, the managers are concerned that the father’s quota is available for all the male employees. This sets the framework for which practice and choices other employees should use when it comes to parental leave. To be available for work is important for the male brokers in the finance industry. In spite of a positive attitude regarding the father’s quota on the party of the brokers, they still hesitate to use it. By not taking the father’s quota or just parts of it, they make themselves more available for work, and this becomes the general practice and the institutional logic within the organization. </p>

<p>One of the brokers stands out and experiences leave as particularly important for creating a good father and child relationship. He does not care what co-workers might think about him taking long leave. This informant is the youngest in this study, and it is possible that a new generation is joining the finance industry and will contribute to a gradual change in the institutional logic when it comes to the use of the father’s quota. This is similar to the use made by one of the managers of the father’s quota as a protest against the workplace and the prevailing ‘old-boys culture’.  </p>

<p>We found that the working logic is different in the two groups and organizations studied. The leaders in the engineering industry work as a team—as opposed to the brokers who work more individually. In other words, organizational institutional logics provide guidance on what practices one can have within the given organizations. That is, even if one wishes to use the fathers’ quota, it is not necessarily the case that the work is experienced as compatible with practice.  </p>
</text>
