<text id="autogum_academic_doc686" title="A Joint Control Model Based on Emission Rights Futures Trading for Regional Air Pollution That Accounts for the Impacts on Employment" shortTile="joint-control-model" author="Shijie Wang, Laijun Zhao, Yong Yang, Chenchen Wang, Jian Xue, Xin Bo, Deqiang Li, Dengguo Liu" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5894/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 6. Conclusions</head>
<p>
Against the background of severe air pollution and rigorous government policies to mitigate the problem, it has become necessary to reduce pollutant control costs without adversely affecting employment. To accomplish these goals, we developed an emission rights futures trading model for joint air pollution control that accounts for employment, and then examined SO2 control in our study area in 2017 as a case study of the model. The results show that under the JCM, whether or not we accounted for employment affected both the cost of pollution control and employment. When we accounted for employment, the JCM both increased employment and reduced pollution control costs compared with the JCM results without accounting for employment. Furthermore, compared with the TCM, the JCM both increased employment and decreased the control cost. </p>

<p>The JCM in the present study can help polluted regions balance environmental control with economic development to ensure that residents of the affected areas can earn a living whilst also having a healthier environment. The model also accounts for differences in the cost of pollution control among the cooperating regions, and uses futures-based trading methods to achieve a “win-win” effect, thereby increasing the ability to achieve sustainable development. Although we focused on pollution control within a single region of a country, it should be possible to extend the method to encourage countries to cooperate in regional air pollution control. The trading model for emission rights futures proposed in this paper can not only effectively stimulate cooperation among regions in pollution control and decrease pollution control costs, but also represents a financial instrument that can be traded in financial markets, thereby increasing the variety of financial instruments available, and improving the flexibility of financial markets to deal with risks. The United States and other developed countries have begun trading emissions future and options, and have achieved some success. For example, the Chicago’s Climate Futures Exchange started the SO2 futures trading in 2003, and the European Climate Exchange began the emission rights futures and options trading for major atmospheric pollutants in 2005. However, because the financial markets of developing countries such as China are immature and the associated financial regulations are strict, these countries have not yet adopted emission rights futures and options trading. However, the emission rights futures trading model proposed in this paper is effective enough to encourage developing countries to test their ability to promote joint air pollution control. Furthermore, the JCM proposed in this paper can be used for additional pollutant control measures in other countries. This model has a high potential to improve air quality and fight climate change.
 </p>
</text>
