<text id="autogum_academic_doc528" title="Automated Inspection of Railway Tunnels’ Power Line Using LiDAR Point Clouds" shortTile="automated-inspection" author="Ana Sánchez-Rodríguez, Mario Soilán, Manuel Cabaleiro, Pedro Arias" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-4292/11/21/2567/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Nowadays, the interest of having a digital model of real-life scenarios is increasing. This model can be used to update and track the behaviour of an infrastructure through its whole life cycle. In the railway field, with the arrival of the high-speed train and the high request for its maintenance and inspection, research concerning technical and technological improvements has increased. One of the main concerns of the railway industry is the irregularities affecting the rail track layout, as well as the perfect state of the catenary to fulfil the requirements of gauge, among others. These elements have a big repercussion in the security of the whole railway system. Hence, railway companies invest their resources for the optimal inspection and maintenance of the infrastructures. This is where laser scanning systems come into consideration. In recent years, the applications for laser scanning technology have increased. Until now, the main applications involving this type of data were dimensional control, 3D modelling, urban planning, and, more recently, BIM (building information modelling). The main characteristic of laser scanners is their capacity for obtaining large amounts of data with high accuracy in a short period of time. Usually, this information was processed manually or semi-automatically. The monotony of this task called for the necessity of automatically process the generated three dimensional (3D) point clouds. </p>

<p>This work arises due to the lack of specific methods for classifying and inspecting railway point clouds, and especially railway power lines. It is focused on the automatic classification of MLS point clouds of the aerial contact line system from railway tunnels, and its later inspection. The aerial contact line is a set of overhead cables on top of the railway line. They provide electrical supply to electric trains. These cables are placed over the vehicle’s superior gauge limit, being the electrical supply provided through pantographs. The system is composed by three different categories of cables: (i) Contact wire, from which the pantograph takes the power for the train; (ii) suspension or catenary wire, which resists and supports the catenary weight and keeps the contact wire in a constant height; and (iii) droppers, which are vertical elements that help to maintain the contact wire in that constant height, and are fixed in between the suspension and the contact wire. These three types of elements are hanged over the train’s car with poles or cantilever arms. </p>

<p>The present paper is divided into the next sections: Section 2 presents a review of the literature related with this work; Section 3 explains the methodology, which is in charge of the classification of points conforming both the contact and the suspension wires, and the inspection of these cables; Section 4 describes the equipment used for the data gathering; Section 5 exposes the results obtained for the datasets on disposal; and, lastly, the conclusions to this research together with future lines of work to be considered are exposed in Section 6. </p>
</text>
