<text id="autogum_academic_doc301" title="A High-Accuracy Indoor-Positioning Method with Automated RGB-D Image Database Construction" shortTile="highaccuracy-indoorpositioning" author="Runzhi Wang, Wenhui Wan, Kaichang Di, Ruilin Chen, Xiaoxue Feng" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-4292/11/21/2572/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Nowadays, position information has become key information in people’s daily lives. This has inspired position-based services, which aim to provide personalized services to mobile users whose positions are changing. Therefore, obtaining a precise position is a prerequisite for these services. The most commonly used positioning method in the outdoor environment is the Global Navigation Satellite System (GNSS). In most cases, however, people spend more than 70% of their time indoors. Therefore, accurate indoor positioning has important practical significance. Although GNSS is a good choice for outdoor positioning, due to signal occlusion and attenuations, it is often useless in indoor environments. Thus, positioning people accurately in indoor scenes remains a challenge and it has stimulated a large number of indoor-positioning methods in recent years. Among these methods, fingerprint-based algorithms are widely used. Their fingerprint databases include Wi-Fi, Bluetooth, and magnetic field strengths. Although these methods are easy to implement, construction of a fingerprint database is usually labor-intensive and time-consuming. Moreover, it is difficult for their results to meet the needs of high-accuracy indoor positioning. </p>

<p>Given that humans use their eyes to see where they are, mobile platforms can also do this with cameras. A number of visual positioning methods have been proposed in recent years. These positioning methods are divided into three categories: image retrieval based methods, visual landmarks-based methods, and learning-based methods. </p>

<p>Image retrieval based methods treat the positioning task as an image retrieval or recognition process. They usually have a database that are augmented with geospatial information, and every image in the database is described through the same specific features. These methods perform a first step to retrieve candidate images from the database according to a similarity search, and the coarse position information of the query image is then obtained based on the geospatial information of these candidate images. So the first step, similar image retrieval process, is critical. The brute-force approach, which is a distance comparison between feature descriptor vectors, is often used for similarity search. Some positioning methods based on feature descriptors adopt brute-force comparison for the similarity search process of image retrieval. However, it is computationally intensive when the images of a database are described with high-dimensional features, limiting its scope of applications. Azzi et al. use a global feature-based system to reduce the search space and find candidate images in the database, then the local feature scale-invariant feature transform (SIFT) is adopted for points matching in pose estimation. Some researchers try to trade accuracy for rapidity by using approximate nearest neighbor search, such as quantization and vocabulary tree. Another common way to save time and memory of similarity search is principal component analysis (PCA), which has been used to reduce the size of feature vectors and descriptors. Some works use correlation algorithms, such as sum of absolute difference (SAD), for computing similarity between query image and database images. In recent studies, deep learning-based algorithms are an alternative to aforementioned methods. Razavian et al. use features extracted from a network as an image representation for image retrieval in a diverse set of datasets. Yandex et al. propose a method that aggregates local deep features to product descriptors for image retrieval. After a set of candidate images are retrieved, the position information of the query image is calculated according to the geospatial information of these candidate images through a weighting scheme or linear combination. However, because this position result is not calculated by strict geometric relations, it is rough in most cases and difficult to meet the requirement of high-accuracy positioning. </p>

<p>Visual landmarks-based positioning methods aim to provide a six degrees of freedom (DoF) pose of the query image. Generally, visual landmarks in the indoor environments includes natural landmarks and artificial landmarks. The natural landmarks refer to the geo-tagged 3D database, which is represented by feature descriptors or images with poses. This database could have been built thanks to the mapping module of simultaneous localization and mapping (SLAM). Then the pose of query image is estimated by means of re-localization module and feature correspondence. Although the results of these methods are of good accuracy, it takes a long time to match the features of query image with geo-tagged 3D database, especially when the indoor scenes are large. In addition to natural landmarks, there are also positioning methods based on artificial landmarks, e.g., Degol et al. proposed a fiducial marker and detection algorithm. In reference, the authors proposed a method to simultaneously solve the problems of positioning from a set of squared planar markers. However, positioning from a planar marker suffers from the ambiguity problem. Since these methods require posting markers in the environments, they are not suitable for places such as shopping malls that maintain a clean appearance. </p>
</text>
