<text id="autogum_academic_doc023" title="HOXA9 Transcriptionally Promotes Apoptosis and Represses Autophagy by Targeting NF-κB in Cutaneous Squamous Cell Carcinoma" shortTile="hoxa-transcriptionally" author="Shuo Han, Xue Li, Xiaoting Liang, Liang Zhou" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4409/8/11/1360/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Cutaneous squamous cell carcinoma (cSCC) is the second most common type of cancer with an annual incidence of over one million globally. Chronic ultraviolet (UV) exposure was suggested to be responsible for DNA damage of normal keratinocytes in the epidermis, which leads to the development of skin cancers including cSCC. However, the detailed underlying molecular mechanisms for this transition still need to be fully elucidated. </p>

<p>Apoptosis is one type of programmed cell death, which is initiated by intrinsic or extrinsic signals and finely-tuned by many factors including BCL-2 family proteins. BCL-2 family members, including both anti-apoptotic and pro-apoptotic BCL-2 family proteins, govern mitochondrial outer membrane permeabilization (MOMP) to regulate apoptosis. When apoptotic cell death program starts, MOMP releases cytochrome c to cytosol and activates caspase-family proteases for initiating apoptotic events. Tumors develop effective mechanisms to resist apoptosis and thus become one of the hallmark features of cancer. The lead member BCL-2 and its homologue BCL-XL (BCL2L1) are featured by the presence of four conserved BH domains, three of which, BH1, BH2, and BH3 domains, are responsible for their antiapoptotic role mainly by interactions with other proapoptotic members of the BCL-2 family. Inhibiting the activities of anti-apoptotic BCL-2 members by drugs or neutralizing by BH3 peptides to prime cancer cells to death has been regarded as effective therapeutic modalities. In another way, transcriptionally or post-transcriptionally repressing the expression levels of anti-apoptotic BCL-2 members in cancer is also promising. However, the mechanism regulating the expression of BCL-2 family members still remain unclear. </p>

<p>Autophagy is an evolutionarily-conserved catabolic process, during which “useless” proteins and damaged organelles are sequestrated into autophagosomes and fused with lysosomes to form autolysosomes for bulk degradation of embedded components. Except the dysregulated autophagic process defined as type II programmed cell death, autophagy is generally regarded as protective cellular process. The recycled peptides, nucleotides and lipids together with the energy are critical to the maintenance of cellular homeostasis and support tumor cells to survive under stressful environment. Autophagy-related genes (ATGs), including ULK1 (ATG1), ATG3, and ATG12 etc., are involved in the distinct stages of autophagy: initiation, autophagosome nucleation, autophagosome membrane expansion, fusion with lysosome and the intravesicular components degradation. Signaling pathways or critical factors are involved in regulating ATG genes, including Class III PI3-kinase complex I, mTORC I complex, mTORC II complex and Beclin1 et al.. However, the transcriptional regulation of the ATG genes is not fully explored. </p>

<p>In our previous study, Homeobox A9 (HOXA9) was significantly downregulated and identified as tumor suppressor in cSCC tumors and cells. HOXA9 functions in repressing the proliferation, migration and invasiveness, while promoting apoptosis of cSCC cells. However, the mechanisms about how HOXA9 regulate apoptosis has not been explored and remain to be elucidated. In this study, we found RELA (p65 subunit of NF-κB) is transcriptionally repressed by HOXA9. In cSCC, RELA transactivates <hi rend="italic">BCL-XL</hi> to antagonize apoptosis and ATG genes (<hi rend="italic">ULK1</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ATG3</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">ATG12</hi>) to promote autophagy. Our study highlights a HOXA9-NF-κB axis regulates both the apoptosis and autophagy to promote tumor development in cSCC, which may suggest novel intervention targets for cSCC therapy. </p>
</text>
