<text id="autogum_academic_doc116" title="Firm Constraints on the Link between Proactive Innovation, Open Innovation and Firm Performance" shortTile="firm-constraints" author="Nguyen  Thanh Liem, Nguyen  Vinh Khuong, Thai Hong  Thuy Khanh" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2199-8531/5/4/88/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Conclusions</head>
<p>
In a globalization context, innovation plays a critical role in improving firm competitive edge in a sustainable manner. Proactive innovation could bring first-mover advantage, but this approach requires substantive resources. For SMEs, the decision to opt for innovation is more complex, since they suffer from higher constraints which thwart their resources and capabilities to innovate. This study uses a sample of 3504 firms in Vietnam, and aims to fill the gap whether proactive or reactive innovation is better for SMEs, and whether proactive/reactive innovation is better for SMEs firms with higher or lower constraints.  </p>

<p>Our findings suggest that technological innovations in general are beneficial to firm performance, as this increases firm sales and profits. We continue to dig further by filtering innovations into two categories: proactive and reactive, and examine which is better for firm performance. The result shows that reactive innovation brings negative effects to firm performance, consistent with the view that proactive entrepreneurial behavior is a highly sought-after characteristic or a valuable resource for a firm. Finally, our result indicates that if firms have sufficient resources, then proactive strategies should be the choice rather than reactive one to improve firm performance.  </p>

<p>The findings of this research add significantly to the literature in two aspects. First, it examines the constraint—innovative performance linkage in a developing country setting. While there are a number of extant studies dealing with this link, the samples only comprise of firms in developed economies. Since SMEs in developing countries tend to experience a stronger impact of constraints, the study on the link between constraint–performance is critical in Vietnam. Second, this study found that constraints a firm faces play a role in the decision of innovation strategies, specifically the choice between proactive and reactive orientation. </p>

<p>Proactive innovation is beneficial towards firm performance, but it requires planning and resources and new ideas. Those factors could be obtained through open innovations, which could significantly help in the case of SMEs in developing countries due to their insufficient resources. It is suggested that individualism boosts open innovation thanks to its strong association with creativity, but the complexity from the collaboration with external parties should be controlled to some extent to ensure the stability of the business. Additionally, complexity from open innovation if well managed could be an enabler for successful serial entrepreneurs. Furthermore, open innovation should also be well handled due to its complicated nexus under the micro- and macro-dynamic viewpoints. </p>

<p>This research suffers from two major limitations. First, the data have some missing observations, are short and have not been updated since 2015, while innovations are the term that should be analyzed in the most current setting possible. Second, the mechanisms/factors to relieve the constraint impact on firm innovation adoption have not been studied in the current research. Therefore, future studies could seek to update the data and examine the solutions to tackle the negative impact of constraint on firm innovation.
 </p>
</text>
