<text id="autogum_academic_doc554" title="The New Empirical Equation Describing Damping Phenomenon in Dynamically Loaded Subgrade Cohesive Soils" shortTile="new-empirical-equation" author="Emil Soból, Andrzej Głuchowski, Alojzy Szymański, Wojciech Sas" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/9/21/4518/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The shear modulus <hi rend="italic">G</hi> and the damping ratio <hi rend="italic">D</hi> are the key soil parameters in geotechnical issues in which the soil is subjected to dynamic loads, for example, machines foundation, city tram and subway traffic, driving of sheet pile or precast pile, or mechanical soil compaction at the bottom of the excavation. These two mentioned parameters are also used in the soil-structure interaction when a large area of soil is employed to interaction with construction, e.g., in diaphragm walls’ construction, tunnel housing, or subway stations. Each one of the abovementioned geotechnical problems should be solved based on geotechnical parameters obtained in small and medium strain range, in which soil behaves like an elastic and elastic-plastic medium. Reliable evaluation of the stress–strain response of the soil, leading to a correct prediction of ground and structure deformations under static and dynamic loading and is directly dependent on the accurate assessment of the dynamic properties. </p>

<p>However, when energy dissipation is small, undamped analysis can be employed. Nevertheless, every abovementioned geotechnical problem is connected with significant damping, so its effect should be included in the dynamical analysis. Damping is used to describe the ability of subsoil or structures to dissipate energy during dynamic loading. However, the damping process relates to several possible processes, not to a unique process, so it is challenging to model it properly. The value of damping depends on many factors, like vibration amplitude, material properties, structural configurations, fundamental periods of vibration, mode shape, etc.. In engineering practices, several types of damping are used, i.e., hysteretic damping, viscous damping, damping caused by wave scattering, radiation damping, numerical damping, and damping as an alternative. From the geotechnical point of view, the most important are hysteretic and viscous damping. There are two types of viscous damping: external damping and internal damping. External damping is caused by the interaction between the considered body and outside of the system. Internal damping is caused by the difference of the internal velocity between moving particles. </p>

<p>This paper focuses on the internal viscous damping ratio (<hi rend="italic">D</hi>) of Quaternary cohesive soils from Warsaw and factors determining this parameter in studied material. It presents a literature review of the most important factors affecting the damping ratio. Moreover, the authors discuss the influence of identified factors on their results. For the damping ratio of cohesive soil in small and medium shear strain range obtained from resonant column tests, the authors created the new empirical model. A comparison with other models from the literature is also included in the paper. Conclusions from conducted research are drawn at the end of this work. </p>
</text>
