<text id="autogum_academic_doc052" title="Suitability Mapping for Managed Aquifer Recharge: Development of Web-Tools" shortTile="suitability-mapping" author="Jana Sallwey, Robert Schlick, José  Pablo Bonilla Valverde, Ralf Junghanns, Felipe Vásquez López, Catalin Stefan" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4441/11/11/2254/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Implications from Reviewing GIS-MCDA Studies</head>
<p>
This section is based on an already published review on MAR suitability mapping and focusses on analyzing the relevant parameters and methods for the comprehensive approach to GIS-based suitability mapping by Rahman et al.. Their approach divides suitability mapping into four main steps. It follows the scheme of (a) problem definition, (b) screening of suitable areas (constraint mapping), (c) suitability mapping including the classification of thematic layers or criteria, standardization, weighting of the criteria, and layer overlaying by decision rule, and (d) sensitivity analysis. </p>

<p>Problem definition is the basis of choosing relevant GIS maps and weighting their importance for solving the problem statement. As this part of the approach is highly problem-specific, no general statement or implications could be formulated from the review. </p>

<p>Constraint mapping identifies the parts of the study area that are not suitable for the application of MAR or need to be excluded from the analysis as they are, for instance, natural reserves or private land. This is achieved through threshold values for the GIS criteria and by applying Boolean logic to clip respective areas from the final map. Half of the analyzed studies used constraint mapping as a tool to exclude unsuitable areas. As this methodology is widely used, options to constrain single GIS datasets or complete areas from the resulting map were envisaged for the web GIS tool. </p>

<p>Suitability mapping is the core of the MCDA process as it ranks the study area based on its suitability for the application of MAR. This step comprises the standardization of GIS maps, the assignment of weights to every map, and the combination of the weights and the standardized maps by decision rule. The most commonly used weight assignment methods are the rating method, the ranking method, the multi-influence factor (MIF), and the pairwise comparison. The rating and ranking methods are very simple methods comprising manual weight assignment on a predetermined scale. MIF is a graphical weight assignment method where linkages between GIS datasets are drawn, and the weights are calculated based on the number and the importance of linkages between the criteria. Pairwise comparison is the most used method for GIS-MCDA in the context of MAR. The weights are calculated through a matrix-based comparison of pairs of criteria. The methods range from simple (rating method) to more complex (pairwise comparison). The advantage of the simple methods lies in the easiness of use, whereas the complex methods, such as pairwise comparison, offer a coefficient indicating the consistency of the decision-maker’s choices. To account for the advantages of both the simple and more complex methods, the rating and ranking method, MIF and pairwise comparison were chosen to be incorporated into the web tool. </p>

<p>The decision rule states how the standardized datasets and their weights are combined to obtain the suitability map. This integration can be based on threshold values (Boolean logic) or more elaborate integration rules, such as weighted linear combination (WLC). WLC comprises the summation of the weighted and standardized criteria and is the most commonly used decision rule. It has been developed further to its derivative analytical hierarchical process (AHP). AHP is the more structured approach that categorizes the GIS maps into hierarchical levels before aggregating und summing up the weighted criteria. It is used to solve more complex decision problems. The two most used methodologies, WLC and AHP, were chosen to be incorporated into the web tool. </p>

<p>To verify the obtained map, a sensitivity analysis should be conducted. It is used to display the effect of different standardization and weights on the final suitability map and indicates the robustness of the obtain suitability map. While this is an important factor for strengthening the reliability of suitability maps, only 21% of the reviewed studies conducted this step. </p>

<p>All reviewed studies used desktop GIS software for their analysis. Some studies created their own tools for the analysis, e.g., Rahman et al. developed the GIS-based Gabardine desktop decision support system. Other studies used tools available through standard software, e.g., an AHP tool has been implemented as an extension for ArcGIS, which has been applied by Anane et al.. </p>
</text>
