<text id="autogum_academic_doc550" title="AR Graphic Representation of Musical Notes for Self-Learning on Guitar" shortTile="ar-graphic-representation" author="Marta  Sylvia Del Rio-Guerra, Jorge Martin-Gutierrez, Vicente  A. Lopez-Chao, Rodolfo Flores Parra, Mario  A. Ramirez Sosa" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/9/21/4527/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Results</head>
<p>This section contains the results of the experimental study for each of the aforementioned independent variables. <figure>Figure 5</figure> displays the mean time (in seconds) taken to perform tasks, displaying findings for both methodologies. <figure>Figure 6</figure> shows the success rate for each task by learning methodology. All participants successfully performed the tasks of playing C major, D major, E major, and F major (all 32 in each group). However, participants in both groups encountered greater difficulty performing the tasks G major, A major, and B major, as finger placement was more complex. In particular, the B chord proved the most difficult as it is a bar chord. This means participants had to press five strings simultaneously across the fret with their index finger. It should be remembered that participants were complete beginners and this was their first contact with the instrument; as such, a chord was recorded as successful if it was performed correctly in under two minutes. </p>

<head> 4.1. Analysis of Results</head>
<p>Although the number of successful tasks was not an explicit variable in this study, it has been included to support the acceptance or rejection of the null hypotheses. Fisher’s F test was used to compare variables. The results obtained had a <hi rend="italic">p</hi>-value of 0.88. As this was greater than 0.05, it indicated that there was no significant difference in the success rates for either methodology. </p>

<p>A two-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) was performed to analyze effects on task completion times. The two independent variables were training methodology and gender. The combination of both factors was also analyzed to observe whether interference between them produced any effects on the time taken to perform tasks. </p>

<p>As seen in Table 2, the <hi rend="italic">p</hi>-values obtained for each factor were &gt;0.05; thus, the two null hypotheses proposed in Section 3 could not be rejected:
<list>
<item>The time taken to learn the basic musical chords on the guitar did not depend on the methodology used.</item>
<item>The gender of participants did not affect the time taken.</item>
</list>
</p>

<p>Based on these findings, it is possible to state that there was no significant difference between the two methodologies with regard to learning times. It can also be stated that there were no differences in learning by gender within the group itself or between different methodologies. </p>

<p>Observational findings indicated that each methodology had its own set of advantages and disadvantages. </p>

<p>Table 3 shows a t-student analysis (paired series) of the variable “time” for each task, in order to identify whether there was a significant difference in the execution time of each chord by learning method.  </p>

<p>These results show in detail the result of Table 2. In this case, we can see that all tasks (except Task 7 “Play B major chord”) showed no difference in the time of execution (one method or another of learning). Task 7 required more time from the participants of the AR methodology group. </p>

<head> 4.2. User Feedback</head>
<p>Once the experimental study was completed, participants filled out the usability scale (SUS) questionnaire to establish the usability of the ad-hoc app that had been developed to teach guitar chords using AR technology. The questionnaire consisted of 10 questions evaluated on a “ikert scale (“strongly disagree”–“strongly agree”). The score obtained for this usability questionnaire was 82.5. This indicator was higher than the average of 68. Scores higher than 68 indicate a good usability for software. </p>

<head> 4.3. Observational Findings</head>
<p>Group 1 participants were surprised by how easy it was to follow the instructions provided by the ad-hoc AR app. In-app feedback messages (red cross—“try again”, green tick—“well done!”) proved motivation and encouraged participants to follow the instructions explaining how to play chords. They did not experience the stress associated with waiting for instructions or feedback from a human instructor. However, some did state they would have preferred to receive feedback and reassurances from a human instructor to confirm whether they had played a chord correctly or not. Participants appeared relaxed as a result of studying autonomously. Upon completing a task they were often heard to exclaim, “How easy”, “Excellent”, “Awesome”, or “Bring it on!” (next task). These comments served as self-motivation. The last task, which involved playing the B major chord, created confusion. Users did not understand that the same color superimposed across multiple strings on the same fret was an instruction to bar the fret with a single finger. The majority of participants took a while to understand that they needed to use the entire length of the index finger to bar the fret. Having completed all tasks, the participants declared their interest in learning to play guitar using AR assistance and that they wished to continue using this methodology. Some stated that this type of learning could be enhanced by contact with a music teacher to ensure their technique was correct. </p>
</text>
