<text id="autogum_academic_doc738" title="Modeling Public—Private Partnerships in Innovative Economy: A Regional Aspect" shortTile="modeling-publicprivate" author="Tatiana Anopchenko, Olga Gorbaneva, Elena Lazareva, Anton Murzin, Gennady Ougolnitsky" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5588/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Materials and Methods</head>
<p>
For a multifaceted assessment and selection of the best PPP mechanism from the point of view of risk diversification, the authors developed a software product that allows public and private partners to use the proposed MCDM model to monitor the degree of compliance with their interests and make managerial decisions. </p>

<p>This article develops the research, which describes the methodology and the model toolkit for managing the sustainable development of the region. The proposed methodology was based on the idea of combining econometric, simulation, and expert modeling methods into an integrated system for managing the sustainable development of a territory. Regional information–analytical support system is creating to implement the sustainable management methodology. This system has a hierarchical structure, and the subsystems at the lower levels of management can be used independently. </p>

<p>The simulation subsystem of the analytical block implements the modified well-known Solow growth model using data from the regional data warehouse. This model sets important constraints in solving optimization management problems. The optimization and expert subsystems of the analytical unit provide a solution to the problem of harmonizing public and private interests in the sustainable economic management. </p>

<p>The processes of coordination of public and private interests are based on a fairly wide range of mathematical tools, mainly optimization. At the same time, the practice of making management decisions by economic entities allowed to outline the main features of such tasks: Multidimensionality, the need to simultaneously take into account when choosing alternatives of several targets, the need to evaluate alternatives from the perspective of a fairly wide range of criteria, difficulties (sometimes impossible in principle) to form conditions for implementing alternatives, factors criteria, and goals in quantitative form. Among the circumstances that complicate decision-making is the presence of a sufficiently large number of decision makers. These circumstances make it difficult to use the already traditional mathematical methods. </p>

<p>Due to this, the traditionally used mathematical methods for matching interests have been supplemented by authoring tools developed on the methodological foundation of the hierarchy analysis method by T. Saaty as a recognized method of supporting management decision-making through the hierarchical composition of the problem and multi-criteria rating of alternatives. </p>

<p>The advantages of the toolkit in terms of supporting the process of harmonizing public and private interests are as follows:</p>
<list>
<item>The hierarchical structure of the method reflects the interrelationship of alternative solutions with the factors on which they depend, as well as with the criteria for rating them, which visualizes the participants’ views on the situation of decision making;</item>
<item>The use of tools requires a focused collection and grouping of information that provides a decision-making process, and also allows you to assess the quality (accuracy and consistency) of data;</item>
<item>As a result of modeling the decision-making situation, it is possible to more adequately assess the influence of one or another factor on the priorities of decisions by identifying the most significant factors;</item>
<item>The use of the method makes it possible to identify the “boundaries” of the stability of the ratings and to determine the likely situations of change in the decision.</item>
</list>

<p>
The hierarchy analysis method (HAM) is a systematic procedure for the hierarchical representation of the essential elements of a problem situation, the resolution of which is aimed at making the management decision by the subjects—public–private partnership participants. This procedure consists in the decomposition of a specific problem into more and more simple components (from the goal to the comparable solutions to the problem—alternatives) and further processing of the sequence of decision judgments by pairwise comparisons. As a result, the relative degree (intensity) of interaction of elements in the hierarchy can be expressed. These judgments are then expressed numerically. The hierarchy analysis method includes procedures for synthesizing multiple judgments, obtaining priority criteria, and finding alternative solutions. </p>

<p>The hierarchy analysis method is based on the principles of: Identity and decomposition, discrimination and comparative judgments, and the principle of synthesis. </p>

<p>The principle of identity and decomposition involves structuring problems in the form of a hierarchy or a network, which is the first step in the application of the method. The hierarchy is built from the top (goals), through intermediate levels (primary factors, subjects, and criteria on which subsequent levels depend) to the lowest level (which is a list of alternatives). </p>

<p>The decomposition of the problem consists in dividing it into hierarchy levels so that the elements of the lower level of the hierarchy are comparable in pairs to the elements of the next level up to the top of the hierarchy (the law of hierarchical continuity). Thus, subject to the law of hierarchical continuity, all elements of one level are identical to each of the elements of the next level. </p>

<p>The principle of discrimination and comparative judgments comes into effect after the hierarchical/network reproduction of the problem and provides for a pairwise comparison of the elements of the hierarchy. During the survey, the elements of the task are compared in pairs to their effect (“weight”, or “intensity”) on their common characteristic. </p>
</text>
