<text id="autogum_academic_doc241" title="Amplitude Distribution of Partial Discharge Signals on Tunnel-Installed High-Voltage Cables" shortTile="amplitude-distribution" author="Yong Qian, Xiaoxin Chen, Yiming Zang, Hui Wang, Gehao Sheng, Xiuchen Jiang" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/9/21/4595/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Cable Model</head><head> 2.1. Distributed Parameters of Tunnel-Installed Cables</head>
<p>
The three-phase cable can be regarded as a transmission line system consisting of 6 conductors. The propagation characteristics of the voltage and current on the conductors are determined by the distributed impedance matrix <b><hi rend="italic">Z</hi></b> (unit: Ω) and the distributed admittance matrix <b><hi rend="italic">Y</hi></b> (unit: S). The skin effect in the metal sheath is enhanced at high frequencies and the current is bound to the inner surface and outer surface of the sheath, which makes the transfer impedance decrease rapidly and it can be ignored. In this case, the distributed parameter matrix <b><hi rend="italic">Z</hi></b> and <b><hi rend="italic">Y</hi></b> of the three-phase cable are as follows:

(1)

(2)

where <hi rend="italic">zcc</hi>, <hi rend="italic">zss, zss</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">zmu</hi> represent the self-impedance of the inner conductor, self-impedance of the metal sheath, and mutual impedance between the conductors, respectively. <hi rend="italic">yss</hi> = <hi rend="italic">yse </hi>+ <hi rend="italic">ycs </hi>+ <hi rend="italic">2ymu</hi>, where <hi rend="italic">ycs</hi>, <hi rend="italic">yse</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">ymu</hi> are the admittance of the inner conductor, admittance of the metal sheath to the earth, and mutual admittance between the metal sheaths, respectively. The formulas to calculate the impedance and admittance of directly buried cables have been given in. The calculation of the admittance of tunnel-installed cables is the same, but the self-impedance <hi rend="italic">zs</hi> and mutual impedance <hi rend="italic">zm</hi> used to obtain the impedances <hi rend="italic">zcc</hi>, <hi rend="italic">zss zss</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">z</hi>mu need to be calculated by Tylavsky’s high-frequency formulas. </p>

<p><figure>Figure 2</figure> shows the structure of the tunnel-installed cables, where <hi rend="italic">R</hi> represents the radius of tunnel, <hi rend="italic">b</hi> represents the distance from cable to the tunnel center, <hi rend="italic">d</hi> represents the center spacing of the cables, <hi rend="italic">θ</hi> represents the included angle between two cables, and <hi rend="italic">r</hi>1, <hi rend="italic">r</hi>2, and <hi rend="italic">r</hi>3 represent the radius of the inner conductor, insulating layer, and metal sheath respectively. In this paper, the unit of all the length variables is meter and that of the angle is rad. Then the self-impedance <hi rend="italic">zs</hi> and mutual impedance <hi rend="italic">zm</hi> of the cable-ground loop are:

(3)

(4)

where <hi rend="italic">ρ</hi> (unit: Ω∙m) and <hi rend="italic">μ</hi>e (no units) are the resistivity and the relative permeability of the earth respectively, <hi rend="italic">ω</hi> (unit: rad/s) is the angular frequency, <hi rend="italic">m</hi> = (<hi rend="italic">jωμ</hi>e<hi rend="italic">μ</hi>0/<hi rend="italic">ρ</hi>)1/2 and <hi rend="italic">Kn</hi> represents the <hi rend="italic">n</hi>-th order second modified Bessel function. To simplify the calculation, assume that the three cables are completely symmetrical, that is, the structure parameters of each cable are the same, and the distance and angle between any two cables are equal. In this case, <hi rend="italic">d</hi> and <hi rend="italic">b</hi> are represented by the geometric mean distance of the actual distance. </p>

<head> 2.2. Cable Characteristic Admittance Model</head>
<p>
The conductors are coupled to each other in a three-phase cable system, and therefore the voltage and current on each conductor is affected by the voltage and current on other conductors. The three-phase cable system can be transformed into a number of independent two-conductor transmission lines by using a modal transformation, then the characteristic admittance matrix <b><hi rend="italic">Y</hi>c</b> can be obtained from the distributed parameter matrix <b><hi rend="italic">Z</hi></b> and <b><hi rend="italic">Y</hi></b>:

(5)

where <b><hi rend="italic">λ</hi></b> is the propagation constant matrix of each mode after decoupling and <b><hi rend="italic">T</hi>V</b> is the voltage transformation matrix. <b><hi rend="italic">λ</hi></b> and <b><hi rend="italic">T</hi>V</b> are the eigenvalues and eigenvector matrix derived from the diagonalization of the matrix product <b><hi rend="italic">ZY</hi></b>, that is:

(6)

</p>

<p>Similar to the two-conductor transmission line, the characteristic admittance matrix <b><hi rend="italic">Y</hi>c</b> characterizes the relationship between the voltage and the current on the multi-conductor transmission line. Based on the assumption that the cable is completely symmetrical, the extended matrix of the Clarke transform matrix can be used as the voltage transform matrix <b><hi rend="italic">T</hi>V</b>. Equations (1), (2), and (6) are substituted into Equation (5) and simplified to obtain <b><hi rend="italic">Yc</hi></b>:

(7)

where:

(8)

(9)

(10)

where <hi rend="italic">Ycs</hi> is the coaxial characteristic admittance, namely, the reciprocal of the characteristic impedance of a single coaxial cable. <hi rend="italic">Ycs</hi> is only related to the structure of the cable, usually between 0. 025 S and 0.1 S. <hi rend="italic">Yse</hi> is the characteristic admittance between the cable sheath and the earth, and <hi rend="italic">Yss</hi> is the characteristic admittance between the sheaths of the cable. <hi rend="italic">Yse</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Yss</hi> are affected by the external environment of the cable system. If <b><hi rend="italic">Yc</hi></b> is regarded as a nodal admittance matrix, it can be expressed in the form of self-admittance and mutual admittance, as shown in <figure>Figure 3</figure>. </p>
</text>
