<text id="autogum_academic_doc703" title="Rethinking Institutional Knowledge for Community Participation in Co-Management" shortTile="rethinking-institutional" author="Ayonghe Akonwi Nebasifu, Ngoindong Majory Atong" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5788/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Discussion</head>
<p>
We have identified the paradox of co-management, which is an unrepresented local input in the system. Furthermore, in elaborating on the fieldwork results, we identified observations, stressing on the one hand the concerns of local people, and on the other hand the role of small institutions. In previous studies, critiques of participation examined the undesirable outcomes of state-led participatory systems without much analysis of how institutional knowledge could better acknowledge the development needs of local people in co-management. To bridge this gap, the results of our study suggest three factors for advancing the existing literature on the critique of participation. </p>

<p>First, as to the legal basis for participation between institutions and local people, there are opportunities we can exploit for improving co-management despite its paradoxes. Previous studies have shown that the dominant model of centrally driven participation compromises the effectiveness of conservation projects. In such modeling, capitalist elites tend to remake biodiversity landscapes for capital accumulation. Even so, in spite of decentralizing power, shady practices do exist that lead to the inefficient performance of institutions. While we agree with these assertions, our study suggests that legislation for participation should have pragmatic provisions that can be customized to enhance community involvement. Examples of such laws include Cameroon’s 2004 decentralization law that formalized the role of subdivisional councils in supporting local communities, Cameroon’s 1996 decentralization law on freedom of association that permits NGOs to have a hand in environmental protection, and the 1994 state forestry law for the inclusion of indigenous people in forestry. The pragmatism of these laws indicates that placing local knowledge that arises from the human‒environment relationship at the core of participation will avoid politicizing or imposing development on locals. This type of knowledge would include the convictions by which local people have lived; as partners with the environment, they have been using it traditionally for much longer than MCNP has existed. That is why respecting the opinions of local people has great potential for ensuring effective participation. </p>

<p>Second, regarding the paradox of co-management and the concerns of local people, the results revealed that many respondents in the focus groups had little awareness of forestry laws and the regulations for biodiversity conservation. They knew little about the results of data collected from villages and the content of conservation development agreements (CDA). Consistent with these findings, the existing literature has assessed the mixed success of the NGO sector in engaging with participatory methodologies. Previous studies have proposed that, despite inequalities in such sectors, enhancing the political rights of marginalized groups in participatory development can help provide the transformative change needed in wider power structures. Furthermore, called for a reconsideration of development practitioner roles in implementing participation among people. The case of MCNP, however, suggests that such practitioner roles in the hands of institutions, as well as the political rights that local people need in participation, could be amended through accountable and transparent forms of communication. That is, participation should be based on a two-way, open system of information exchange wherein locals can question institutional assistance, and institutions must justify their actions. </p>

<p>Third, in acknowledging the development needs of local people, MCNP showed that smaller institutions aiming to promote biodiversity conservation have difficulties with providing alternative livelihoods for locals. Similar issues have been addressed in studies about broader governance structures that do not always lead to local empowerment and control. Nevertheless, our inquiry on the subdivisional level of governance revealed the willingness of institutions to engage in dialogue about the local use of forests in making decisions for preserving biodiversity. What we recommend, therefore, is that such eagerness for dialogue between locals and smaller institutions be utilized to create what call adaptive social‒ecological systems. In these systems, institutions cooperate with locals to come to decisions about community projects and provide locals with first-hand information about how they intend to promote local knowledge of the environment. Such knowledge, being a conflation of ideas, should culturally and ecologically link to real-life practices recognizable by differences between the needs of locals who live in remote villages and those living closer to urban areas. These are different experiences of the use of the natural environment that institutions need to take into consideration to meet development needs.  </p>
</text>
