<text id="autogum_academic_doc694" title="International MOOC Trends in Citizenship, Participation and Sustainability: Analysis of Technical, Didactic and Content Dimensions" shortTile="international-mooc" author="Emilio  José Delgado-Algarra, Isabel  María Román Sánchez, Eva Ordóñez Olmedo, Antonio  Alejandro Lorca-Marín" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5860/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Research Design</head><head> 2.1. Problems and Objectives</head>
<p>
Through the main exploratory to factorial approach, we will respond to the following research questions:
</p>
<list>
<item>“What is the technical dimension of MOOCs in terms of citizenship and sustainability in Coursera, Edx and MiriadaX?”</item>
<item>“What is the didactic dimension of MOOCs in terms of citizenship and sustainability in Coursera, Edx and MiriadaX?”</item>
<item>“What are the main trends of MOOCs regarding the citizenship and sustainability contents?”</item>
<item>“What are the trends of MOOCs regarding the interaction between citizenship and sustainability?”</item>
</list>

<p>
These research questions are related to the following research objectives:
</p>
<list>
<item>Objective 1: Determine the technical dimension of MOOCs in citizenship and sustainability in the Coursera, Edx and MiriadaX platforms.</item>
<item>Objective 2: Determine the didactic dimension of MOOCs in citizenship and sustainability in the Coursera, Edx and MiriadaX platforms.</item>
<item>Objective 3: Access MOOCs trends in citizenship and sustainability contents.</item>
<item>Objective 4: Understand the MOOCs trends in the relationship between contents in citizenship and sustainability.</item>
</list>
<head> 2.2. Research Methodology, Sample and Data Collection </head>
<p>
The methodological approach of this research is quantitative. The sample consists of the 2019 MOOCs on citizenship and/or sustainability; allowing a selection of 161 MOOCs from Coursera (38), Edx (117) and MiriadaX (6) that can be divided into five macro reference areas (<figure>Figure 2</figure>): Experimental Sciences (38), Health Sciences (9), Technical Teachings (5), Social and Legal Sciences (85) and Humanities (24). The search bars from the respective platforms were used to define the sample. Keywords for searching were “citizen”, “citizenship”, “sustainability” and “footprint”, in all languages of the European Union (EU). </p>

<p>Regarding the didactical and technical dimensions of MOOCs, the data collection tool is adapted from the <hi rend="italic">Questionnaire for the evaluation of teaching</hi>, <hi rend="italic">technical and educational aspects of teaching sites</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Questionnaire</hi> to measure the quality of a MOOC; maintaining, with exceptions, the ’Yes’ and ’No’ scale. In relation to the specific citizenship and sustainability blocks, items for data collection are related to the theoretical background described above, focusing on main elements of the different types of citizenship and fingerprints for sustainability; including the following scale: With, "not worked", "indirectly worked", "explicitly worked". </p>

<p>The instrument consists of three items for classification (massive open online course (MOOC) platform, educational institution, macro reference area), followed by a series of items that have been grouped based on a four-part system related to the categories system. </p>

<head> 2.3. Categories System and Data Analysis</head>
<p>
Once the problem is defined and after the bibliographic review, a system of categories whose specific structure is adapted from several proposals is designed. This system consists of four categories: Didactic dimension (Table 1), technical dimension (Table 2), citizenship (Table 3) and sustainability (Table 4). </p>

<p>After categorization, prior to the analysis and with the support of the “SPSS” statistical program, the data are entered. Subsequently, descriptive methods (exploratory analysis) are applied for all categories and correlational (factor analysis) for 16 items of the specific categories of citizenship and sustainability that allow us to discover the latent relationships between variables.  </p>
</text>
