<text id="autogum_academic_doc080" title="A Quantitative Analysis of Socio-Economic Determinants Influencing Crop Drought Vulnerability in Sub-Saharan Africa" shortTile="quantitative-analysis" author="Bahareh Kamali, Karim  C. Abbaspour, Bernhard Wehrli, Hong Yang" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/6135/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The current world population has already reached 7 billion, and by 2050 it is estimated to increase to 9 billion, with the most significant increase concentrated in South Asia and Sub-Saharan Africa (SSA). A number of studies show that if no drastic actions are taken in consumption patterns, shifting diets, and reducing wastes, meeting the world’s food demand will require doubling food production and this will unavoidably exert extreme pressure on agricultural and natural resources. On the other hand, climate change has exacerbated the situation by increasing drought risks and flood events around the globe with significant impacts on agricultural production. As agriculture in most SSA countries is primarily rainfed, SSA is at the core of this threat. Achieving food security in SSA is an enormous challenge given the currently weak institutions, poor infrastructure, population, unfavorable weather conditions, and high social dependence on declining natural resources. Therefore, to better cope with the consequences of droughts and mitigate their effects, it is essential to incorporate socio-economic information in the analysis of drought vulnerability in SSA. </p>

<p>Drought is a natural disaster, and the degree of its impacts is well recognized in terms of the magnitude of vulnerability. Various definitions have been proposed for vulnerability. The Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) defined vulnerability as a function of exposure, sensitivity, and adaptive capacity. The fifth assessment report focused on socio-economic aspects and prioritizing adaptation interventions. Adaptive capacity is the ability of a system to cope with the consequence of drought and represents the potential to implement measures that help reduce potential impacts. Quantification of adaptation capacity is a challenge for two reasons. First, adaptation is the intrinsic property of a system and only manifests itself when the system is exposed to a shock. Second, adaptation is heterogeneous over space and time, and therefore, it is challenging to generalize a set of universal factors that enhance adaptive capacity in different regions over time. </p>

<p>Several studies have attempted to incorporate adaptive capacity in the vulnerability assessment using approaches such as aggregated quantitative indicators or semi-structured interviews. Indicators of adaptive capacity were also grounded in sustainable livelihood theory as a set of different forms of assets to which people have access, such as financial, human, resource, or physical assets. This approach calculates a composite index for each constituent asset. During the last two decades, many studies also attempted to employ the sustainable livelihood concept in their analysis of vulnerability.  </p>

<p>The use of indicators is one of the most common ways to define factors influencing vulnerability. Despite the extensive research, improvement is required to identify and choose driving forces and indicators that more accurately determine the relationship between socio-economic factors and vulnerability. Detailed studies along these lines have been recently conducted at the European, Australian, and in few cases at global scales, but the issue has not been thoroughly addressed in SSA countries. Naumann et al. calculated composite indicators that reflect different aspects of vulnerability and adaptive capacity at the Pan-African level. Their study, however, lacks an empirical and analytical framework that can clearly explain the direction and magnitude of effectiveness (or influence) of individual factors on vulnerability. This limitation impedes policy development to mitigate the vulnerability. Several studies have used regression models to analyze the relationship between the socio-economic variables and crop drought vulnerability in some individual countries or regions in SSA. However, these studies are case-specific, and it is challenging to upscale their findings to the whole of SSA.  </p>

<p>In assessing the factors influencing vulnerability to drought, most studies have not considered the temporal variations in different countries. Multivariable regression models used for these analyses often take the prevailing situation of individual countries over a specified time period. In reality, vulnerability is time-dependent and varies with the severity of the drought. It is, therefore, important to consider changes in vulnerability and factors that influence it on temporal dimension. As data is increasingly becoming available in developing countries, panel data analysis at the national level provides a more significant basis for modeling the complexity of socio-economic factors influencing vulnerability. Panel analysis is a statistical method to analyze two-dimensional data collected over time for the same entity. However, such an analysis exceeding a single cross-section of time has so far not been conducted in the context of crop drought-vulnerability assessment in SSA.  </p>

<p>In the literature, most studies quantifying drought vulnerability are based on some arithmetic aggregation of several representative components. Very few studies have quantified the drought vulnerability by comparing the expected crop yield under certain climate conditions with the recorded yield. The magnitude of the difference between modeled and recorded yield is an indicator of resiliency of a region to drought occurrence. Process-based crop models are practical tools to model how yield changes in response to climate variability or drought. Linking the drought vulnerability defined as the distance between the expected and recorded yield with socio-economic variables may, therefore, enhance the choice of management options. </p>
</text>
