<text id="autogum_academic_doc041" title="Profiling Bacterial Diversity and Potential Pathogens in Wastewater Treatment Plants Using High-Throughput Sequencing Analysis" shortTile="profiling-bacterial" author="Cecilia Oluseyi Osunmakinde, Ramganesh Selvarajan, Bhekie  B. Mamba, Titus  A.M. Msagati" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-2607/7/11/506/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Waterborne infections emanate from the transmission of pathogenic microorganisms (bacteria, viruses, protozoa) by both direct and indirect ingestion of polluted water. Most water-borne pathogens are spread through the fecal–oral route, and find their way to wastewater treatment plants (WWTPs) through excreted feces in raw sewage from infected people or in drinking water, or by eating food exposed to contaminated water, which could lead to serious health complications. In recent years, bacterial pathogens have been recurrently identified in wastewater plants, based on the impression that WWTPs are a major reservoir for the growth of numerous pathogenic microbes. Regardless of tremendous efforts by governments and water management facilities to improve and sustain the quality of water treatment systems, the occurrence of waterborne infections remains rampant worldwide. Bacteria, which are abundant in WWTPs, play significant roles, such as breaking down organic matter, being a source of nutrients, and facilitating energy flow and biogeochemical cycling as well as disease transmission. Traditionally, the main treatment processes in WWTPs include primary, biological (secondary), and tertiary treatment. Primary treatment is a preliminary stage which makes use of bar screens to remove large solid objects from water. It can also include the use of sedimentation basins to separate solid from liquid waste by means of natural gravity. The floating materials are removed while the remaining liquids are laid open for the secondary stage of treatment through the use of biological methods (either aerobic or anaerobic) to break down the organic waste matter. The organic matter in the waste are removed through the use of a bed of stones (trickling filter beds) or the activated sludge process. Finally, effluents from the secondary treatment tank are then disinfected with chlorine, which is assumed to kill all pathogenic organisms and reduce odor, before being discharged into distribution channels and receiving water bodies. There has been a significant effort by water management authorities to adopt new techniques in treatment plants such as UV and membrane treatment technology, mechanical (ultrafiltration, reverse osmosis, nano-filtration), ultrasonic (ozonation), biological (active filters and enzymes), adsorption (activated carbon), and combinations of these processes to eliminate and partially remove microbes in wastewater. Despite all these approaches, the existence of pathogenic microbes in raw and treated wastewater is still considered a potential hazard and health risk to the public. At present, most WWTPs assess the quality of water based on biological indicators, such as the total coliforms and fecal coliforms, as well as physical and chemical indicators. However, these assessment techniques do not directly classify the variety of the mixed bacterial populations present in WWTP systems. </p>

<p>Several molecular methods have been reported for the identification of bacterial species in environmental samples. There is, however, another challenge with regard to the species identification of microbes, in that a widespread selection of these environmental bacterial species cannot be cultured. Over the years, molecular technologies such as polymerase chain reaction (PCR), quantitative real-time PCR (qPCR), microarray, and other techniques have been widely used to target microbial species in environmental samples. All of these molecular techniques have both strengths and weaknesses, but these approaches are always delegated to specifically target the identification of a pre-selected group of microbes or virulence genes. The main limitation of these technologies is that they can only specifically detect certain pathogens, and cannot provide comprehensive insight into the potential pathogens in the environment. </p>

<p>Current approaches in microbial detection (such as next-generation sequencing) have made it possible to extract DNA directly from environmental samples and sequences for identification, diversification, diagnostic, clinical, and monitoring purposes. Recently, high-throughput next-generation sequencing methods applied to the 16S rRNA gene have produced complete descriptions of bacterial communities in various environments, due to the increased number of sequence reads that can be obtained and analyzed. A number of investigations have been performed into the microbial diversity and pathogenic indication of environmental genomes in WWTPs by sequencing of the 16S rRNA gene amplicon using different high-throughput techniques. In this study, we investigated the abundance and diversity of the bacterial communities in influent and effluent wastewater samples from three WWTPs in South Africa, using a targeted amplicon-based sequencing approach. The study evaluated the potential biomarkers and abundance of bacterial communities that were removed after treatment processes to identify pathogens (including those not conventionally checked during quality assessment). </p>
</text>
