<text id="autogum_academic_doc039" title="Mahout Perspectives on Asian Elephants and Their Living Conditions" shortTile="mahout-perspectives" author="Hannah  S. Mumby" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-2615/9/11/879/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Asian elephants (<hi rend="italic">Elephas maximus</hi>) in captivity can live in a wide range of different settings. These include, but are not limited to zoos and safari parks, elephant camps that are primarily for tourism activities, camps associated with timber extraction, in areas linked to transportation or wildlife observation functions, such as nature reserves, and in areas linked to religious and cultural functions, such as temples. Although we often describe settings in terms of in-situ (within the current or historical range of wild elephants) or ex-situ (outside of this range), the enormous variation within both of those categories makes blanket statements about welfare challenging to make and almost impossible to apply. One aspect that elephants may experience across many of the captive settings is a keeper, handler, or mahout. The responsibilities and activities of these individuals vary but may include feeding, cleaning, or bathing elephants, treating some minor medical conditions, participating in training, and riding elephants in order for them to achieve specific tasks, such as transportation of materials, religious functions, or tourism activities. </p>

<p>The term mahout is sometimes used interchangeably with elephant handlers, or with the term linked to their linguistic context, such as oozie in Myanmar. Mahouts themselves often translate their title as “elephant driver”, perhaps indicating the centrality of that aspect of their occupation. The practices of mahouts vary across south and southeast Asia, but one defining characteristic is their relationship with a single elephant or small group of elephants and the associated activities linked to that individual elephant or those few individuals. The mahout system originated in Asian elephant range countries, although aspects of it have existed in ex-situ settings. For example, mahouts from the Indian sub-continent were sent to accompany elephants given as gifts to rulers in Europe. Equally, there are historical examples of African elephants living in captivity and having individual handlers. However, these historical interpretations of mahout-elephant interactions should be used with caution in interpreting current interactions, given the changing landscape of mahoutship. Understanding current practices requires research into the practices taking place now. Given the shifting roles of mahouts in other parts of Asia, this study aims to specifically address the issues at a single camp in Nepal. </p>

<p>A mahout is more than just an elephant handler, as they may come from an area, a family, or a social group associated specifically with elephants and the practice of being a mahout. The context of mahoutship has been of interest to generations of visitors, administrators and officials, scientists, and ethnographers. These have offered interpretations of the role of mahouts both in human-wildlife interactions, and the economies and societies in which they operate. Mahout perspectives, roles, and the dynamic nature of the mahout-elephant relationship have gained increasing prominence in a range of fields including animal welfare and animal behavior. This study aims to specifically address mahout perspectives on enclosures, interaction with elephants, and providing the best environment for captive elephants, because these are currently important topics in Nepal, where elephant tourism is changing in response to the preferences of tourists. </p>

<p>In linking the perspectives of mahouts to elephant welfare, the issue of the role of what is sometimes termed “traditional knowledge” or “local knowledge” in animal welfare is raised. The terms themselves and their use are subject to debate, but are broadly used to describe bodies of knowledge and practices constructed, maintained, and developed by people or peoples who have histories of interaction with an environment. It may form part of a complex or group of related practices, including language, naming and classification systems, land-use practices, and spiritual and religious practices. Recognizing the existence of these complexes and their implications is relevant for welfare. For example, mahouts and other individuals, who work closely with elephants on a day-to-day basis, are pivotal in applying welfare practices, as they are often the ones who will implement strategies that might have been developed by managers, veterinarians, or scientists. However, their experience and skills are not only relevant in this “end-stage” of following recommendations to improve welfare. Instead, they are also a rich source of ideas, knowledge, and observations about the animals they work with and the environment they inhabit. Whilst perspectives of other stakeholders such as tourists, visitors, and other observers of mahout-elephant interactions are also pertinent in gaining human perspectives on welfare, mahouts represent an opportunity to co-produce, generate, discuss, participate in, form, test, and appraise methods linked to welfare as they are involved in the lives of the elephants on a daily basis. This avenue of research is timely, as the science of animal welfare continues to grow, and the particularly compelling case for welfare presented by elephants living in captivity is explored, including the welfare implications of their long lives, complex social interactions, and prolonged infant dependence. </p>
</text>
