<text id="autogum_academic_doc062" title="Iodine Supplemented Diet Positively Affect Immune Response and Dairy Product Quality in Fresian Cow" shortTile="iodine-supplemented" author="Marco Iannaccone, Andrea Ianni, Ramy Elgendy, Camillo Martino, Mery Giantin, Lorenzo Cerretani, Mauro Dacasto, Giuseppe Martino" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-2615/9/11/866/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Micronutrients are essential to orchestrate all physiological functions. Among them, iodine (I) plays a unique role because it is the main component of the thyroid hormones, i.e., thyroxine (T4) and triiodothyronine (T3). Since the thyroid gland regulates many metabolic processes, the extent of I requirement strongly depends on the age and stage of development of the individual. Thus, when the I demand is not satisfied, reduced functionality of the thyroid gland could occur (hypothyroidism) with negative consequences for proper mental development, body growth, and fertility. For these reason, diet is often integrated with I supplements, generally provided through iodized salt. For infants, milk constitutes the only I source; therefore, the dietary calibration of this micronutrients in dairy animals assumes relevant importance in order to obtain I-rich milk without inducing variations in animal performances. </p>

<p>In animal husbandry, I supplementation as calcium iodate, sodium iodide, and other iodine compounds is needed since the native iodine content of plant straight feed-stuffs is low; moreover, the increasing use of rapeseed meal (RSM) in livestock diets is associated with the intake of glucosinolates, which are known to be iodine antagonists inhibiting the activity of sodium iodide symporter. For this reason, the European community has recently brought to 5 mg/kg the maximum level of I supplementation for milk-producing ruminants (milk intended for human consumption), while it remained at 10 mg/kg of complete feed for other ruminant categories. Consequently, several studies have been carried out to evaluate the productive performances in animals fed the I supplementation. Weiss et al. showed that I concentration increased in serum but not in milk after supplementation of this element in diets of dairy cows. In contrast, studies performed in small ruminants showed that I supplementation doubled the milk iodine content when compared with the control group, even though no evident effect was observed in the milk gross composition. I supplementation showed also beneficial effects on healthy status. Indeed, early study on feedlot cattle demonstrated an increased resistance to foot rot, which is due to improved phagocytic cell function. Moreover, it was shown in lambs that high-dose potassium iodide supplementation can be effective to decrease the severity of airway viral infections, supposedly through the augmentation of mucosal oxidative defenses. </p>

<p>Recently, the RNA-sequencing approach was shown to be useful to elucidate which molecular pathways are affected by I supplementation in sheeps and showed the positive effects of olive pomace-supplemented diet on inflammation and cholesterol in laying hens. However, to date, little is known about the effects of I supplementation on transcriptomic profiles in dairy cows. Moreover, we tried to correlate the information concerning the signaling pathways influenced by I supplementation, with the qualitative parameters of milk and derivatives, taking into account those studies in which it was shown that dietary iodine supplementation in ruminants contributes to an improvement in the quality of dairy products. </p>
</text>
