<text id="autogum_academic_doc227" title="Utilizing a Building Information Modelling Environment to Communicate the Legal Ownership of Internet of Things-Generated Data in Multi-Owned Buildings" shortTile="utilizing-building" author="Behnam Atazadeh, Hamed Olfat, Behzad Rismanchi, Davood Shojaei, Abbas Rajabifard" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2079-9292/8/11/1258/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Review of Relevant Literature</head>
<p>
Digital Twins emergence is an endeavor to create intelligent adaptive machines by generating a parallel virtual version of the system along with the connectivity and analytical capabilities enabled by IoT. The Digital Twin technology is moving towards creating a digital representation of a real-world object (e.g., a car, a machine tool, a factory, a person) and the spatio-temporal relations between the objects represented by a subgraph of nodes and edges. <figure>Figure 2</figure> illustrates this concept. For example, a car “T37BTT” is represented by multiple nodes and edges in a subgraph, of which its nodes represent the car’s CAD design, the service records, its current state (where it is, its speed, etc.), and its manufacturing information (where it was produced, by which machines, etc.). </p>

<p>Building objects in Digital Twin can be represented using 3D digital models. <figure>Figure 2</figure> illustrates a BIM IFC file existing in the Victorian Government Digital Twin platform. It enables the Digital Twin users to access different physical elements of the building (e.g., ceiling, wall, roof, window) as well as its cadastral (title boundaries) information. Similar to the abovementioned car “T37BTT” example, the nodes of a building can consist of CAD floor plans, utility map, occupancy/ownership/spaces/ temperature information, and camera footage. </p>

<p>Several researchers have already worked on integrating BIM and IoT; however, this research domain is still in nascent stages. Isikdag proposed an architecture, based on GIS, for integration and visualization of information coming from BIM objects and IoT nodes. Rowland proposed an informational city model including BIM geometry, real-time data via IoT, multiplayer online gaming based platform and an Augmented Reality interface. Teizer et al. focused on an IoT approach that integrates environmental and localization data in a cloud-based BIM platform, aiming at making performance, environmental and localization data of workers available in an indoor work environment. Dave et al. proposed a framework for integrating BIM and IoT using open standards to provide information about energy usage, occupancy and user comfort. Tanga et al. provided an in-depth review of BIM and IoT devices integration in the AEC industry from domain application and integration methodologies perspectives. </p>

<p>Smart buildings are predicated on the appropriate integration of IoT datasets and 3D BIM models. IoT devices could collect data during the construction (structure monitoring) and operation (energy meters). The purpose of these devices is to monitor the health and safety of the building which will benefit all occupants. Integration of BIM and IoT has been adopted and used for various applications. These include construction operation and monitoring, health and safety management, construction logistics and management, facility management, energy management, and disaster and emergency response services. Here, we will review the recent investigations and initiatives that studied the integration of IoT datasets and 3D BIM models for supporting smart building management in different application domains. </p>

<p>In the construction operation and monitoring domain, the integration of BIM and IoT datasets provides new opportunities to integrate real-time datasets such as environmental data and localization data to support management and operations of construction activities. Since incorporating data sourced from IoT sensors into BIM models can facilitate real-time exchange and communication of data, monitoring construction activities would benefit from this in several aspects including on-site monitoring of the construction environment, monitoring of resources and labor behaviors, real-time communication and collaboration, and monitoring progress and performance of construction activities.  </p>

<p>In terms of health and safety management, IoT datasets are considered valuable for smart monitoring of activities related to health and safety aspects. On the other hand, BIM models include a rich repository of information related to building components, which provide the right context for the datasets sourced from IoT devices. Two major applications of integrating BIM and IoT datasets for managing health and safety aspects include development of health and safety training systems to track the location of trainers, trainees, materials and equipment, and on-site monitoring of health and safety by providing real-time data query, identifying risks as well as visualizing and notifying them inside the BIM models. </p>

<p>In construction logistics and management domain, the combination of BIM and IoT datasets provide significant improvements in automating prefabrication and lean construction. BIM and IoT devices such as RFID tags are useful for tracking, visualization and automatic assembly in prefabricated manufacturing. In terms of lean construction, BIM coupled with IoT can facilitate the assessment of work progress, constraints and productivity by providing a reliable basis for information flow. Various investigations showed that integration of IoT datasets and BIM models would enable real-time information sharing, fostering communication between humans and machines throughout the entire supply chain and the building lifecycle. Despite the benefits, there are some limitations in the studies that looked at the integration of BIM and IoT for construction logistics and management. These limitations include; 1) Information overload due to a large amount of data 2) Frameworks and solutions are conceptual or prototypical ones that only work in the laboratory environment, and 3) Proposed prototypical solutions are not realizable in real-world projects due to the conservative attitudes in the construction industry.  </p>
</text>
