<text id="autogum_academic_doc716" title="A Robust Fuzzy Optimization Model for Closed-Loop Supply Chain Networks Considering Sustainability" shortTile="robust-fuzzy-optimization" author="Xin Zhang, Gang Zhao, Yingxiu Qi, Botang Li" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5726/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Mathematical Model</head>
<p>
According to the above description and assumption of the problem, the mathematical model for a CLSCN considering sustainability will be presented in detail. These formulations are developed by extending previous works (mainly). </p>

<head> 5.1. Notations</head><head> 5.1.1. Sets and Indices</head>
<list>
<item> Set of candidate plants, .</item>
<item> Set of candidate distribution centers, .</item>
<item> Set of candidate collection center, .</item>
<item> Set of candidate remanufacturing center, .</item>
<item> Set of fixed customers, .</item>
</list>
<head> 5.1.2. Parameters</head>
<list>
<item> Demand of customer <hi rend="italic">m</hi>.</item>
<item> Return rate of used products from customer <hi rend="italic">m</hi>.</item>
<item> Remanufacturing rate of used products at remanufacturing centers.</item>
<item> Carbon cap of supply chain set by the government.</item>
<item> Cost of producing one unit product at plant <hi rend="italic">i</hi>.</item>
<item> Cost of distributing one unit product at distribution center <hi rend="italic">j</hi>.</item>
<item> Cost of collecting one unit product at collection center <hi rend="italic">k</hi>.</item>
<item> Cost of remanufacturing one unit product at remanufacturing center <hi rend="italic">l</hi>.</item>
<item> Cost of transporting one unit of new product per mile by transport vehicle type A.</item>
<item> Cost of transporting one unit of used product per mile by transport vehicle type A.</item>
<item> Cost of transporting one unit of new product per mile by transport vehicle type B.</item>
<item> Cost of transporting one unit of used product per mile by transport vehicle type B.</item>
<item> Distance between plant <hi rend="italic">i</hi> and distribution center <hi rend="italic">j</hi>.</item>
<item> Distance between distribution center <hi rend="italic">j</hi> and customer <hi rend="italic">m</hi>.</item>
<item> Distance between customer <hi rend="italic">m</hi> and collection center <hi rend="italic">k</hi>.</item>
<item> Distance between collection center <hi rend="italic">k</hi> and remanufacturing center <hi rend="italic">l</hi>.</item>
<item> Distance between remanufacturing center <hi rend="italic">l</hi> and distribution center <hi rend="italic">j</hi>.</item>
<item> Fixed cost of establishing plant <hi rend="italic">i</hi>.</item>
<item> Cost of establishing distribution center <hi rend="italic">j</hi>.</item>
<item> Fixed cost of establishing collection center <hi rend="italic">k</hi>.</item>
<item> Fixed cost of establishing remanufacturing center <hi rend="italic">l</hi>.</item>
<item> Minimum capacity for plant <hi rend="italic">i</hi>.</item>
<item> Maximum capacity for plant <hi rend="italic">i</hi>.</item>
<item> Minimum capacity for distribution center <hi rend="italic">j</hi>.</item>
<item> Maximum capacity for distribution center <hi rend="italic">j</hi>.</item>
<item> Minimum capacity for collection center <hi rend="italic">k</hi>.</item>
<item> Maximum capacity for collection center <hi rend="italic">k</hi>.</item>
<item> Minimum capacity for remanufacturing center <hi rend="italic">l</hi>.</item>
<item> Maximum capacity for remanufacturing center <hi rend="italic">l</hi>.</item>
<item> Carbon emission for producing one unit of product at plant <hi rend="italic">i</hi>.</item>
<item> Carbon emission for distributing one unit of product at distribution center <hi rend="italic">j</hi>.</item>
<item> Carbon emission for collecting one unit of product at collection center <hi rend="italic">k</hi>.</item>
<item> Carbon emission for remanufacturing one unit of product at remanufacturing center <hi rend="italic">l</hi>.</item>
<item> Carbon emission for transporting one unit of new product per mile by transport vehicle type A.</item>
<item> Carbon emission for transporting one unit of used product per mile by transport vehicle type A.</item>
<item> Carbon emission for transporting one unit of new product per mile by transport vehicle type B.</item>
<item> Carbon emission for transporting one unit of used product per mile by transport vehicle type B.</item>
<item> Numbers of missed working days due to work’s damages during establishing plant <hi rend="italic">i</hi>.</item>
<item> Maximum averages of missed days due to work’s damages when establishing plant <hi rend="italic">i</hi>.</item>
<item> Numbers of missed working days due to work’s damages when establishing distribution center <hi rend="italic">j</hi>.</item>
<item> Maximum averages of missed days due to work’s damages when establishing distribution center <hi rend="italic">j</hi>.</item>
<item> Numbers of missed working days due to work’s damages when establishing collection center <hi rend="italic">k</hi>.</item>
<item> Maximum averages of missed days due to work’s damages when establishing collection center <hi rend="italic">k</hi>.</item>
<item> Numbers of missed working days due to work’s damages when establishing remanufacturing center <hi rend="italic">l</hi>.</item>
<item> Maximum averages of missed days due to work’s damages when establishing remanufacturing center <hi rend="italic">l</hi>.</item>
</list>
<head> 5.1.3. Decision Variables</head>
<list>
<item> A binary variable, it is 1: if plant <hi rend="italic">i</hi> is established; otherwise, 0.</item>
<item> A binary variable, it is 1: if distribution center <hi rend="italic">j</hi> is established; otherwise, 0.</item>
<item> A binary variable, it is 1: if collection center <hi rend="italic">k</hi> is established; otherwise, 0.</item>
<item> A binary variable, it is 1: if remanufacturing center <hi rend="italic">l</hi> is established; otherwise, 0.</item>
<item> Volume of products shipped from plant <hi rend="italic">i</hi> to distribution center <hi rend="italic">j</hi>.</item>
<item> Volume of products shipped from distribution center <hi rend="italic">j</hi> to customer <hi rend="italic">m</hi>.</item>
<item> Volume of used products shipped from customer <hi rend="italic">m</hi> and collection center <hi rend="italic">k.</hi></item>
<item> Volume of used products shipped from collection center <hi rend="italic">k</hi> and remanufacturing center <hi rend="italic">l</hi>.</item>
<item> Volume of products shipped from remanufacturing center <hi rend="italic">l</hi> and distribution center <hi rend="italic">j</hi>.</item>
<item> Membership degree for the number of missed working days due to work’s damages for each worker during establishing plants.</item>
<item> Membership degree for the number of missed working days due to work’s damages for each worker during establishing distribution centers.</item>
<item> Membership degree for the number of missed working days due to work’s damages for each worker during establishing collection centers.</item>
<item> Membership degree for the number of missed working days due to work’s damages for each worker during establishing remanufacturing centers.</item>
</list>
<head> 5.2. Objective Functions</head>
<p>
  We use the notations described in the previous subsection to develop the objectives step-by-step as follows:
</p>
</text>
