<text id="autogum_academic_doc030" title="Mitofusin 2-Deficiency Suppresses Mycobacterium tuberculosis Survival in Macrophages" shortTile="mitofusin-deficiency" author="Junghwan Lee, Ji-Ae Choi, Soo-Na Cho, Sang-Hun Son, Chang-Hwa Song" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4409/8/11/1355/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
Several bacterial taxa, such as enteropathogenic <hi rend="italic">Escherichia coli</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Helicobacter pylori</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Shigella flexneri</hi>, survive by preventing apoptosis. Disruption of the mitochondrial fusion/fission balance leads to increased mitochondrial fragmentation. In this study, we showed that infection with attenuated Ra Mtb induced greater mitochondrial fragmentation than infection with Rv Mtb. However, the levels of MMP, OCR, and ATP were significantly lower in Ra-infected macrophages than in those infected with Rv. Mitochondrial dysfunction is reportedly increased in Ra- compared to Rv-infected THP-1 cells, decreasing the MMP and ATP synthesis. Ra-induced mitochondrial fragmentation may be due to disruption of the mitochondrial fusion/fission balance in macrophages. Therefore, lower levels of MMP, OCR, and ATP may be associated with mitochondrial fragmentation during Mtb infection. </p>

<p>Production of MFN2 was significantly reduced in Ra- compared with Rv-infected macrophages. In contrast, the levels of the fission proteins DRP1 and MFF were increased in Ra-infected macrophages compared to the control. DRP1 induces cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c</hi> release during apoptosis and MFN1/2 delays Bax activation, cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c</hi> release, and apoptosis. The difference in mitochondrial fragmentation between infection with Rv and Ra is likely dependent on the levels of fusion/fission protein production. Therefore, our data suggest that increased mitochondrial fragmentation may be caused by reduced MFN2 production during Mtb infection. </p>

<p>Parkin (an E3 ligase) reduces MFN2 production by ubiquitination in damaged mitochondria. A recent study showed that Parkin induction limited Mtb survival through autophagy of Mtb-infected macrophages. However, the relationship between Parkin and MFN2 is unclear during Mtb infections. In this study, Mtb-mediated Parkin production decreased MFN2 production via ubiquitination. The production of Parkin is induced by ER stress. Although ER stress plays an important role in mycobacterial infection, Ra-mediated ER stress was stronger than that induced by the virulent strain Rv. Also, Ra induced a higher level of Parkin production than Rv, possibly due to different intensities of ER stress. Compared to Rv, ER stress response is strong in Ra-infected macrophages. It sequentially induced Parkin production and eventually resulted in strong apoptosis. Three ER stress sensor molecules were involved in Parkin production: PERK, IRE1, and ATF6. These contribute to the generation of reactive oxygen species, which triggers mitochondrial recruitment of Parkin. Our data suggest that ER stress-mediated Parkin is a MFN2 regulator during mycobacterial infection in macrophages. </p>

<p>Knockdown of MFN2 induces apoptosis by disrupting the mitochondrial network, suppressing the growth of Mtb. A low level of MFN2 decreases the MMP, leading to mitochondrial dysfunction and apoptosis. Therefore, our data suggest that regulation of MFN2 levels is important for suppressing the survival of Mtb in macrophages. </p>

<p>In summary, we found that Mtb-induced ER stress increases mitochondrial fragmentation and apoptosis. MFN2 plays a key role in disrupting mitochondria, which suppresses the growth of Mtb in macrophages. Therefore, MFN2 may be a target for host-derived therapeutics against mycobacterial infection.
 </p>
</text>
