<text id="autogum_academic_doc502" title="Impact of Fenugreek on Milk Production in Rodent Models of Lactation Challenge" shortTile="impact-fenugreek" author="Thomas Sevrin, Marie-Cécile Alexandre-Gouabau, Blandine Castellano, Audrey Aguesse, Khadija Ouguerram, Patrick Ngyuen, Dominique Darmaun, Clair-Yves Boquien" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6643/11/11/2571/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The World Health Organisation recommends exclusive breastfeeding for infants up to six months of age, based on the clear health benefits of breastfeeding on mother-infant dyad. Indeed, there is a consensus regarding the association of breastfeeding with a reduced risk of respiratory and gastro-intestinal infections during the first year of life. Infants, who were breastfed for longer periods, may also have a lower risk of developing obesity and type II diabetes at adulthood. For mothers, breastfeeding could limit the risk of developing ovarian cancer and type II diabetes. Despite these benefits, breastfeeding prevalence remains relatively low, particularly in several high-income countries in North America and Europe, where only 40% of mothers breastfeed six months after delivery. Exclusive breastfeeding rate is about 60% at four months in Scandinavian countries, 35% in the Netherlands, 16% in the UK, and 10% in France.  </p>

<p>Early cessation of breastfeeding clearly is multifactorial. One of the main factors is the maternal perception of insufficient milk secretion to quell infant’s hunger or support infant growth and leads to early cessation of breastfeeding in 35% of cases. Perception of insufficient milk production is a complex, multifactorial issue that can have biological, social, or psychological determinants, and it often remains unclear whether the low milk secretion is real or only perceived. Indeed, as a result of the lack of an objective marker of insufficient milk production and the importance of maternal psychology in breastfeeding duration, perceived milk insufficiency is probably much more common than true insufficient production. True insufficient milk secretion can result from many causes, ranging from inability to lactate due to breast abnormalities or endocrine disorder (5% of women) to difficulties in breastfeeding management, maternal stress and anxiety, or early food diversification in the infant. Although maternal milk production can be often increased through psychological support or maternal breastfeeding education, many healthy mothers are eager to enhance their milk production through various nutritional supplements. </p>

<p>Several drugs and herbal preparations have traditionally been prescribed as galactologues: i.e., substances that promote initiation or increase of lactation. Drugs like domperidone® or metoclopramide® carry the risk of adverse side effects such as arrhythmia or hypothyroidism in mother-children dyad. That is why herbal galactologues like fennel, anise, barley, milk thistle, or garlic are becoming more and more popular for increasing lactation. Among these herbal compounds, fenugreek probably is the most widely consumed. Fenugreek has been used since antiquity in traditional Persian, Chinese, and Egyptian medicine for its range of therapeutic effects. It is now increasingly consumed in Western countries for its presumed protective effects against diabetes, atherosclerosis, inflammation, and hypertriglyceridemia, as well as its putative role as a galactologue due, in part, to trigonelline, one of its main active ingredients. There is, however, little evidence for its effectiveness on milk yield. Whereas a positive effect of fenugreek on milk production was observed in various mammals, such as rabbit, buffalo, goat, or ewe; the wide range of doses tested (from 180 mg.kg-1.d-1 to 2.1 g.kg-1.d-1) led to large discrepancies in the reported effect on milk production (ranging from a 10% increase to a 110% increase), which makes it difficult to determine the effective dose of fenugreek. Moreover, other studies failed to demonstrate an effect in rabbits and goats. In these studies, milk production was measured either by the weight–suckle–weight method (in rabbit), or by milking (in larger animals). The latter methods do not, however, directly assess milk production in response to physiological suckling by the pups. Moreover, these studies evaluated the effectiveness of fenugreek to increase milk production with the aim of productivity, under otherwise optimal conditions of lactation, as opposed to mothers challenged by their perception of insufficient milk production. Finally, none of these studies evaluated the metabolic status of mother-infant dyad following fenugreek supplementation. Thus, the true efficacy of fenugreek on milk production in an animal model submitted to a breastfeeding challenge remains to be ascertained. </p>
</text>
