<text id="autogum_academic_doc320" title="Suitability of a Non-Dispersive Infrared Methane Sensor Package for Flux Quantification Using an Unmanned Aerial Vehicle" shortTile="suitability-nondispersive" author="Adil Shah, Joseph Pitt, Khristopher Kabbabe, Grant Allen" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1424-8220/19/21/4705/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The global methane budget is poorly constrained, due in part to the lack of accurate quantification of emissions from anthropogenic facility-scale sources, such as landfill sites, oil and gas infrastructure facilities or herds of cattle. With average annualised atmospheric global methane mole fraction ([<hi rend="italic">X</hi>]) on the increase, it is essential that emission fluxes from facility-scale point sources are accurately quantified, using top-down (atmospheric measurement-based) methods, in order to validate bottom-up (component-based) flux estimates. </p>

<p>A range of flux quantification techniques can be used to derive facility-scale top-down flux estimates using either remote sensing or in situ sampling. Remote sensing provides a greater spatial sampling extent at the expense of reduced spatial resolution by either facing towards the emission plume or by sampling downwards from above it. For example, partial column mole fractions can be derived from satellites, but natural phenomena such as cloud cover and scene heterogeneity can cause retrieval issues. Near-infrared satellites can only be used in daytime and over land. Most remote sensing techniques can only provide column-integrated (or partial column) measurements. In situ techniques allow sampling to take place from within the emission plume itself but as a consequence, spatial sampling coverage is limited to the spatial extent of the sampling platform. In situ [<hi rend="italic">X</hi>] measurements on a vertical downwind flux plane, near to source, can be used to derive a flux by employing a variety of techniques such as mass balance box modelling, the tracer dispersion method or a Gaussian plume inversion. The near-field Gaussian plume inversion (NGI) method, described by Shah et al., is an example of a traditional flux quantification technique, adapted for near-field sampling. </p>

<p>An unmanned aerial vehicle (UAV) is an ideal platform from which to acquire near-field in situ [<hi rend="italic">X</hi>] measurements. UAVs can probe the planetary boundary layer down to ground level, are versatile and are far cheaper than large research aircraft. Furthermore, small lightweight UAV (SLUAV) platforms have fewer airspace restrictions in many jurisdictions, compared to UAVs of over 20 kg (in the UK for example). A number of strategies can be employed to acquire in situ [<hi rend="italic">X</hi>] measurements from a SLUAV. Air samples can be captured on board a SLUAV for subsequent analysis. However, this results in a poor sampling frequency. Alternatively, air can be pumped through a long tube from a SLUAV to an in situ sensor on the ground. However, this can result in issues such as enhanced lag time through the tube and mixing within the tube. In situ [<hi rend="italic">X</hi>] measurements may also be obtained from a sensor mounted on-board a SLUAV. However this requires a light enough sensor with a sufficient precision, accuracy and resolution for flux quantification, depending on the nature of the source. </p>

<p>A number of previous studies have featured methane sensors mounted on-board UAVs. For example, Berman et al. mounted a closed path in situ off-axis integrated cavity output spectroscopy sensor (with a 1 Hz precision of ±2 ppb) onto a UAV, but as the sensor had a mass of 19.5 kg, a 200 kg UAV was used to carry the heavy payload. Many in situ wavelength modulation spectroscopy (WMS) sensors (which use tuneable diode lasers) have been mounted onto SLUAV platforms. For example, Liu et al. designed and tested a 3.5 kg closed path WMS sensor on a UAV with a 1 Hz precision of ±79 ppb. Open path WMS sensors have also been used, for example Khan et al. designed and tested a 2 kg open path WMS sensor with a 1 Hz precision of ±2 ppb, which required 2 W of power. Nathan et al. tested a 3.1 kg open path WMS sensor with a 1 Hz precision of 100 ppb, which required 25 W of power. Golston et al. designed and tested a 1.6 kg (including battery) open path WMS sensor with a 1 Hz precision of ±10 ppb, which required 30 W of power. Lightweight sensors are desired for UAV sampling as this maximises flight duration on a given UAV platform. </p>

<p>Non-dispersive infrared (NDIR) spectroscopy uses direct absorption from broad-band infrared radiation, filtered down to a narrow wavelength, to derive mole fraction measurements of a specific gas, depending on wavelength of the filter. Due to its spectroscopic simplicity, NDIR sensors may be small and light enough to mount onto a SLUAV. In this work, the High Performance Platform (HPP) NDIR methane sensor, manufactured by SenseAir AB, was therefore tested to assess its suitability for UAV-derived flux quantification. It was first packaged in an enclosure which was mounted onto a UAV platform. It was then calibrated at a range of water vapour mole fractions, to quantify the variability in the instrumental gain factor. It was then operated on-board a SLUAV, downwind of the controlled release of methane gas, on a vertical flux plane roughly perpendicular to mean wind direction, to test its suitability in flux quantification. </p>
</text>
