<text id="autogum_academic_doc149" title="Valuing Biodiversity in Life Cycle Impact Assessment" shortTile="valuing-biodiversity" author="Jan  Paul Lindner, Horst Fehrenbach, Lisa Winter, Mascha Bischoff, Judith Bloemer, Eva Knuepffer" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5628/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Materials and Methods</head><head> 2.1. Established LCA Principles</head>
<p>
The impact assessment method we propose is intended as a sub-method of the life cycle assessment method. LCA has been an established method to analyse the potential attribution of environmental impacts of value chains to products for over 30 years. Its principles and requirements are specified in ISO 14040 and ISO 14044. The goal of an LCA is to highlight hotspots of potential environmental impacts in production processes, to compare the potential impacts of alternative materials and to improve the environmental performance of products. Potential impacts are assessed via a number of impact categories, e.g., climate change, acidification and land use. The following four steps are determined by the ISO. In the first step, the system under investigation and the objectives of the LCA are defined including the system boundaries and the relevant impact categories. In the second step, the product inventory is analysed, i.e., all material and energy inputs and outputs for all processes in the value chain are compiled. The third step is the impact assessment as such. The system inputs and outputs are quantified for each impact category. For example, for the impact category Global Warming, this means that the data is translated into an amount of CO2 equivalent. The last step of an LCA is the presentation and interpretation of the results. A detailed description of LCA and its features can be found in Hauschild et al.. </p>

<p>The method introduced in this article can be categorized as an impact assessment method for the integration of biodiversity into LCA. In fact, it is an impact assessment method which aims to quantify potential environmental impacts of land use on biodiversity. The development of impact assessment methods quantifying land use impacts started in the early 1990s with Heijungs et al.. They were the first to describe the impact of land use as the product of area and time, but at that point without the consideration of soil qualities. Later on, the UN Environment Life Cycle Initiative (formerly known as UNEP-SETAC Life Cycle Initiative) defined the impacts of land use as a function of quality (Q), area (A) and time (t). In this framework, the quality can be any indicator on which land use of a specific area has an impact over a specific period. For example, soil quality, water storage capacity or, as presented in this article, biodiversity. Two types of land use can be differentiated—land transformation and land occupation. As illustrated in <figure>Figure 1</figure>, land transformation is the change from a reference situation (Qref) to another quality status at one specific time (t0). Occupation means the continuation of the (typically lower) quality status over a time period (from t0 to tfin). The change of the quality (ΔQ) can either be temporary if it is reversible, or permanent if it is (partly or entirely) irreversible. </p>

<p>This approach is the basis for all impact assessment methods quantifying impacts of land use, and thus also for the method presented here. </p>

<head> 2.2. State of the Art in Biodiversity LCIA</head>
<p>
One consensus in LCA research is that beside climate change, pollution, unsustainable use of resources and invasive species, the main threat to biodiversity is the loss of habitat driven by the use of land for anthropogenic purposes. Thus, biodiversity, including genetic, species and ecosystem diversity as defined by the Convention on Biological Diversity, can be one aspect that represents quality (Q) within the framework presented ahead (see <figure>Figure 1</figure>). Several life cycle impact assessment (LCIA) methods consider biodiversity as a so-called end point indicator. Nevertheless, there is no consensus on which indicators to use to represent impacts of land use on biodiversity in LCIA. In current research, two main directions can be distinguished: LCIA methods which link land use to species richness (positing: Q = species richness), and LCIA methods which link ecological conditions to impacts on biodiversity (positing: Q = function of ecological conditions). For the former approach, species richness of e.g., vascular plants is commonly used as an indicator, often amended with species richness of several animal taxa. The latter approach is usually based on a set of quantifiable conditions, e.g., deadwood availability in forest ecosystems. Additionally, new developments also aim to assess the impacts on functional diversity (e.g.,). However, these are only applicable in very limited contexts to date. The LCIA method presented in this article calculates the impact on biodiversity based on the conditions that in all likelihood define the biodiversity on the patch of land under investigation. </p>
</text>
