<text id="autogum_academic_doc450" title="ER-Negative Breast Cancer Is Highly Responsive to Cholesterol Metabolite Signalling" shortTile="ernegative-breast" author="Samantha  A Hutchinson, Priscilia Lianto, Hanne Roberg-Larsen, Sebastiano Battaglia, Thomas  A Hughes, James  L Thorne" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6643/11/11/2618/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Cholesterol is predominantly synthesized de novo in the liver with lesser amounts obtained from the diet. Dietary intake, de novo synthesis, metabolism and excretion, combine to balance circulating cholesterol levels ensuring extra-hepatic tissues are sufficiently equipped to produce a range of metabolites including steroid hormones, bile acids and seco-steroids. Side-chain hydroxycholesterols (scOHCs) are typically formed through hydroxylation of cholesterol by specialized members of the Cytochrome P450 family, which bind and activate the Liver X Receptor-alpha (LXRA; gene name <hi rend="italic">NR1H3</hi>) and beta (LXRB; gene name <hi rend="italic">NR1H2</hi>) transcription factors. LXR target genes are typically involved in cholesterol and fatty acid metabolism. In normal tissue, expression of LXRA is inducible in the liver, intestine, macrophages and adipocytes, whilst expression of LXRB is more ubiquitous. As well as differences in expression of LXRA and LXRB, local concentrations of the scOHCs differ considerably between tissues, and relative to each other, sometimes by as much as 1000-fold and variance can also depend on disease status. Furthermore, the different scOHCs have varying capacities to activate LXR-mediated transcription, imposing an element of selective modulation onto signalling. 26-OHC (commonly referred to as 27-OHC) for example is the most abundant scOHC, but is a relatively weak LXR agonist. Moreover, there is little difference in scOHC concentrations between breast cancer subtypes. </p>

<p>Transcriptional activity of the LXRs, like the other members of the Nuclear Receptor (NR) superfamily, is not just regulated by ligand bioavailability; chromatin environment, cross-talk and competition for response element binding with other NRs, as well as cell- and tissue-type dependent expression of cofactors are also key mediators. For example, the expression of corepressors such as NCOR1 and NCOR2/SMRT determine how several cancers respond to nutritive ligands. LXRA has a 100-fold higher binding affinity than LXRB for the corepressors NCOR1 and NCOR2 and deregulation of these corepressors allows prostate and bladder cancer cells to evade cancer suppressive signals of Vitamin D (through repression of Vitamin D Receptor (VDR)) and omega-3 fatty acids (through repression of peroxisome proliferator-activated receptors (PPARs)) by impairing sensitivity to ligand. Simply measuring scOHC concentrations does not sufficiently determine their contributions to LXR signalling; concentration and activation potential should be assessed in combination. </p>

<p>In cancer, the function of the scOHC-LXR signalling axis appears site specific as both tumour suppressive and promoting roles have been described. For example, scOHC-LXR signalling impairs invasion and angiogenesis in melanoma and is anti-proliferative in lung cancer in vivo, as it is in almost every cancer cell line studied in vitro. In Oestrogen Receptor (ER)-positive Breast Cancer (BCa) however 26-OHC promotes growth in vivo via ER-alpha. In ER-negative BCa 26-OHC drives the epithelial-to-mesenchymal transition and promotes colonization of metastatic sites in through mobilization of γδ-T cells. Furthermore, concentrations of several scOHCs are altered in BCa relative to normal tissue, and 25-OHC is elevated in the circulation of BCa patients who have relapsed compared to those with primary disease. </p>

<p>We recently evaluated LXR ligand bio-availability in a small BCa cohort and found large inter tumoural heterogeneity in oxysterol content, but no difference in ligand concentrations between tumour subtypes. Systematic evaluation of scOHC bioavailability and activation potential, coupled with analysis of NR cofactor expression between BCa subtypes has not been performed previously. Given the prognostic and therapeutic value of stratifying BCa by hormone receptor status, further delineation of the pathways that are altered between these subtypes, such as scOHC-LXR signalling, may help advance understanding about the emerging roles of cholesterol metabolism in cancer and improve outcomes for patients. </p>
</text>
