<text id="autogum_academic_doc398" title="waveformlidar: An R Package for Waveform LiDAR Processing and Analysis" shortTile="waveformlidar-r-package" author="Tan Zhou, Sorin Popescu" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-4292/11/21/2552/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The advent of Full Waveform (FW) LiDAR (Light Detection and Ranging) data including airborne and spaceborne have enabled new opportunities for vegetation structure characterization at a range of scales. Unlike Discrete-return (DR) LiDAR data which only store the crest of analog signal representing discrete echo, FW LiDAR data can store the entire echo scattered from illuminated objects with different temporal resolutions. This advantage provides more information about the objects that the pulse interacts with and gives users more flexibility to interpret information inherent in waveforms.  </p>

<p>Multiple approaches such as the Gaussian decomposition and deconvolution have been developed to interpret information from waveforms. However, complicated processing steps and algorithms hinder the widespread use of Full Waveform (FW) LiDAR data. To tackle these challenges, our package <hi rend="italic">waveformlidar</hi> proposed several commonly used approaches and functions to conduct waveform processing and analysis such as Gaussian decomposition and deconvolution. These approaches have been successfully applied to extract physical attributes of vegetation such as canopy height, stem volume, aboveground biomass and tree species from LiDAR waveforms. With the aid of the package, these approaches can be easily implemented in the R platform and further relieve users’ concerns on complicated FW processing steps.  </p>

<p>Additionally, currently available tools are mainly oriented for processing DR LiDAR data. There is a lack of handy tools that dedicated to FW LiDAR data, which precludes users to explore the new or potential practices of FW LiDAR data. Therefore, we developed functions to derive commonly used waveform metrics such as front slope and waveform distance. These waveform metrics are different from the metrics derived from waveform decomposition in terms of the information they contained. Thus, they can be complementary to metrics obtained from decomposition, which enable users to make the most use of the waveform information contained.  </p>

<p>Lastly, the package also proposed a new method to convert waveforms into point clouds with hyper point density (Hyper Point Cloud, HPC) and composite waveforms after implementing waveform voxelization steps. The HPC is an alternative product of FW LiDAR data, which not only can preserve information embedded in original waveforms, also offer users a convenient way to visualize and decode information with existing LiDAR processing tools such as LAStools and FUSION. However, not every waveform signal is useful for real-world applications. To explore the HPC’s potential usefulness, this package also provides functions to explore the HPC in 2D and 3D spatial dimensions. Additionally, we also explore the methods to convert original waveforms with waveform intensities distributing at an off-nadir angle into composite waveforms with intensities distributing at the vertical direction. Furthermore, we conducted a comparison between original waveforms and composite waveforms on the tree species identification and detailed information can be found in Zhou et al.. Notably, the storage and computation cost using the composite waveforms is more expensive than original waveforms, which requires users to conduct an assessment of the marginal benefits obtained from composite waveforms.  </p>

<p>Overall, the purpose of this article is to provide an overview of the <hi rend="italic">waveformlidar</hi> package and to ensure the free availability and usability of methodologies including code or algorithms from our previous scholarly publications. We first introduce an example of FW LiDAR data and corresponding ancillary data such as outgoing pulse and system impulse data. Next, we begin to briefly explain the main algorithms’ technical principles and the logic behind them. We end by discussing the main functions such as decomposition, deconvolution and the HPC in the practical use in the R platform. Full tutorials and reports to reproduce the results from these examples are available in the supporting information from our website (<ref target="https://github.com/tankwin08/waveformlidar/vignettes">https://github.com/tankwin08/waveformlidar/vignettes</ref>). </p>
</text>
