<text id="autogum_academic_doc466" title="Comparative Analysis of the Serological Reactivity of Individuals with Clinical History of Malaria using Two Different ELISA Tests" shortTile="comparative-analysis" author="Yorleydy Ruiz Moreno, Silvia  Tavares Donato, Fátima Nogueira, Marcelo Sousa Silva" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2075-4418/9/4/168/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Early diagnosis and treatment of human malaria reduces disease, prevents deaths, and contributes to reduced transmission. Detection of antibody response against malaria antigens is often done through Enzyme-Linked Immunosorbent Assay (ELISA); many of these diagnostic assays are designed with a single antigen or with recombinant antigens of different stages of the parasites (tissue infection or blood), where merozoite surface proteins can be detected, and have demonstrated good sensitivity and specificity. However, many individuals cannot be easily diagnosed due to the low levels of antibodies present in their blood. In this context, the use of ELISA as a tool for laboratory diagnosis of malaria has some limitations, namely: (i) low antibody titres presented by individuals in the acute phase of infection; (ii) many <hi rend="italic">Plasmodium</hi> sp. are involved in human malaria; (iii) different evolutionary forms of <hi rend="italic">Plasmodium</hi> spp. during infection and life cycle; and (iv) different resistance and susceptibility profiles during infection, and consequently in the immunity profile against malaria parasites. </p>

<p>Associations among antibodies against parasite antigens and malaria risk areas are not always consistent; some may depend on parasite antigens and other considerations may be due to the endemic areas of malaria. It should be considered that single responses of antibodies against antigens might be inadequate to for use as biomarkers and indicators of malaria transmission intensity. Other authors have shown that new serological biomarkers can more accurately estimate the recent exposure to <hi rend="italic">P. falciparum</hi> not only of a community, but also for several communities. In 2015, approximately 3.2 billion people—nearly half of the world’s population—were at risk of malaria, mainly by <hi rend="italic">P. falciparum</hi>. </p>

<p>After several decades of disease control campaigns, malaria persists as one of the most serious public health problems, not only in endemic countries, but also in non-endemic regions, where the number of cases of imported malaria via tourists and immigrants is on the rise. <hi rend="italic">P. falciparum</hi> is one the most lethal species of the malaria parasites that infect humans, and is responsible for the highest number of serious pathologies associated with the disease. </p>

<p>In this work, we performed a comparative analysis of the serological reactivity of total antimalarial antibodies obtained by a commercial ELISA using recombinant antigens from <hi rend="italic">Plasmodium</hi> sp., compared to an in-house ELISA, using crude extract of <hi rend="italic">P. falciparum</hi> 3D7. Thus, we showed that several other <hi rend="italic">P. falciparum</hi> antigens are equally important for the serological diagnosis of malaria, as well as some recombinant antigens commonly used in commercial ELISA. </p>
</text>
