<text id="autogum_academic_doc351" title="Facile Method for Fabricating Microfluidic Chip Integrated with Microwell Arrays for Cell Trapping" shortTile="facile-method-fabricating" author="Hongyue Wu, Zhixing Ge, Wenguang Yang, Xiaoduo Wang, Xiaodong Wang, Haibo Yu" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-666X/10/11/719/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Owing to the developments in biological fields, personalized diagnoses and treatments at the single cell level have become important, which will introduce new potential breakthroughs for biomedicine. Recently, the early detection of cancer and drug action on cancer have attracted considerable attention in the field of biotechnology. Microfluidic device is a useful tool in cell research with advantages such as high-throughput manipulation, high level of integration, and requirement of less time and fewer reagents. Furthermore, microfluidic devices have broad applications in cancer cell trapping. Microwell arrays in microfluidic device are often used to trap cells and construct cell arrays. </p>

<p>Cells trapped in a microfluidic device can be cultured, used to detect markers, manipulated, and employed for drug screening. Rettig et al. have developed an easy-to-use method using microwell array fabricated through soft lithography for a single cell trap. Anchorage-dependent cell (3T3 fibroblast cells) and anchorage-independent cell (Basophilic leukemia cell) were successfully trapped in microwell arrays. Lin et al. improved the traditional structure of microwells and introduced a double-well design, including a tapping well and a culturing well for single cell array construction. Neural stem cell differentiation and A549 cell proliferation were performed using this device. Assal constructed a 3D microwell array using polyethylene glycol (PEG) solution cured by ultraviolet (UV) light based on a polydimethylsiloxane (PDMS) mold. Human B cells infected by Kaposi’s sarcoma-associated herpesvirus (KSHV) were trapped in these microwells for 3D culture. </p>

<p>Microfluidic device has been applied in various fields for cell separation, cell proliferation, and cell behavior in biology research. In particular, it has received attention for the in situ characterization of cells after trapping them using microfluidic device equipped with microwell arrays. There are traditional methods for fabricating microfluidic devices such as soft lithography, photolithography, and laser direct writing. Although photolithography has the advantages of high resolution, a physical mask is essential during the fabrication process, and this technique requires extreme environmental conditions. Soft lithography has been successfully and widely applied to microfluidic device fabrication. While it is an easy-to-use approach, it requires a pre-designed mold or stamp, making it considerably time-consuming. Laser direct writing can fabricate complicated 3D microstructures without the need of photomasks owing to its high-resolution and flexibility. However, the linear scanning mode is time-consuming. Therefore, tedious procedures and high-cost equipment are the main challenges of the current methods for fabricating microfluidic devices. Thus, it is crucial to develop a facile technique for creating microfluidic devices that can satisfy the requirements of cell separation and cell trapping. </p>

<p>In this paper, we present optofluidic maskless lithography for rapid fabrication of microfluidic devices. Poly(ethylene glycol) diacrylate (PEGDMA) was selected as the material for microstructures fabrication, and the cured microstructures were firmly adhered to the substrate. The structures of microfluidic chips were on-line designed, and the exposure patterns were modulated by digital micromirror device (DMD). Compared with traditional methods, the proposed system is more flexible and cost-efficient. Furthermore, microwell arrays with various shapes and sizes can be constructed on the microfluidic chip. </p>
</text>
