<text id="autogum_academic_doc191" title="A Simple and Practical Single-Camera Stereo-Digital Image Correlation Using a Color Camera and X-Cube Prism" shortTile="simple-practical" author="Bo Dong, Fancang Zeng, Bing Pan" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1424-8220/19/21/4726/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Stereo-digital image correlation (stereo-DIC) is an image-based non-contact optical technique for retrieving full-field 3D shape, displacement and deformation of materials, structures, and biological trusses. In recent years, significant advances have been made to various aspects of stereo-DIC to improve its robustness, applicability, measurement accuracy, and computational efficiency. As a matter of fact, stereo-DIC has been widely accepted as the most powerful tool in the experimental mechanics community, and it offers several prominent advantages over competing interferometric optical techniques (e.g., electronic speckle pattern interferometry and Moiré interferometry), such as being easy-to-use, a robustness against ambient vibrations, and a wide range of applicability. </p>

<p>The conventional stereo-DIC technique uses two synchronized digital cameras to acquire digital images of a test object from different views and then retrieves the 3D information from the stereo pairs using image registration algorithm and triangulation. However, the requirement of two synchronized cameras usually makes the system both expensive and complicated, especially for the high-speed stereo-DIC measurements. To improve the stereo-DIC, various single-camera stereo-DIC techniques using diffraction-based, refraction-based, and reflection-based optical configurations have been developed and advocated. Among these techniques, full-frame single-camera stereo-DIC technique using a color separation device and a color camera has been considered the most practical one, since it can realize full-frame measurements without any loss of spatial resolution of the camera, while maintaining the prominent advantages of other single-camera stereo-DIC techniques such as cost-effectiveness, compactness, and the avoidance of the complicated camera synchronization.  </p>

<p>The full-frame single-camera stereo-DIC technique using a single-color camera was originally proposed by Yu and Pan. Specifically, they designed an innovative color separation device to facilitate a color camera to acquire images of blue and red colors from different optical paths, and then the 3D information could be retrieved from the extracted two-channel sub-images. <figure>Figure 1</figure>a gives the optical setup of the method, where a cube beam splitter (CBS) is used to combine two different views reflected from two plane mirrors (M) and the color filters (Fb and Fr) arranged in front of the CBS is used to remove the color cross-talk between the two views. Benefitting from its full-frame 3D measurement capability, the technique was then successfully employed for high-speed displacement and deformation measurements in rotation, vibration, and explosion tests. Very recently, this technique was further extended to microscopic scales for characterizing mechanical behaviors of small-size specimens with micro features. Inspired by the novel idea proposed in, several alternative full-frame single-camera stereo-DIC systems were also established, which use other forms of light separation devices instead of using a CBS and two-color filters. For instance, a polarization camera and two polarizers were used to achieve the same function (i.e., full-frame stereo-DIC measurement using a single camera). As shown in <figure>Figure 1</figure>b, the optical setup of the method is similar to the color separation device assisted one, but it uses two polarizers with different polarization angles to remove the interference between the two views. Recently, a seemingly simpler dichroic filter (DF) was also used as a color separation device to realize full-frame single-camera stereo-DIC measurement as shown in <figure>Figure 1</figure>c. </p>

<p>Despite the fact that the feasibility and functionality of these existing single-camera stereo-DIC systems have been well demonstrated in previous works, they do have several following shortcomings. Regarding the first optical configuration shown in <figure>Figure 1</figure>a, it involves too many optical elements, which makes the optical system both cumbersome and not easy to use. In respect to the polarization-based color separation device shown in <figure>Figure 1</figure>b, the practicality and applicability of the technique are very limited because of the high cost of, and inaccessibility to, high-speed polarization cameras. As for the dichroic filter-assisted color separation device, this simplification brings serious imaging problems. First, the ghost image reflected from the rear surface of the DF will degrade the imaging quality of the blue channel. Second, the refraction effect presented when the blue light passes through the DF can lead to considerable measurement error.  </p>

<p>To overcome the limitations of the existing single-camera stereo-DIC systems, a simple and practical solution based on the use of X-cube prism is proposed in this work, which greatly improves the compactness and operability of the full-frame single-camera stereo-DIC system. First, it overcomes the imaging problems existed in the DF-assisted system while maintains its extreme simple optical setup. Second, the symmetrical structure of the X-cube prism-based color separation device also makes the system very compact and easy to adjust. Because both the performance and operability of this newly developed single-camera stereo-DIC are very close to that of the conventional binocular one, this technique can be considered as the best single-camera solution for stereo-DIC measurements. </p>

<p>In the remainder of this manuscript, the system configuration and implementation procedure of the technique are first introduced. After that, X-cube prism assisted single-camera stereo-DIC systems are established and the validation experiments are detailed. Finally, the contours of curved surfaces with complex structures and the deformation fields of specimens under different loadings are successfully measured to exhibit the practicability of the method. </p>
</text>
