<text id="autogum_academic_doc203" title="A Study on Physical and Rheological Properties of Rubberized Bitumen Modified by Different Methods" shortTile="study-physical-rheological" author="Ben Zhang, Huaxin Chen, Honggang Zhang, Dongliang Kuang, Jiayu Wu, Xiaoliang Zhang" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1944/12/21/3538/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Rubberized bitumen has been applied widely in bitumen pavements because of its remarkable performance, eco-friendly characteristics, and energy-saving features, etc.. Adding crumb rubber (CR) to bitumen can effectively reduce high temperature permanent deformation, low temperature thermal cracking, load-associated fatigue cracking, and chemical aging or hardening of bitumen pavements. Currently, two technical routes have been adopted as the primary approaches to produce rubberized bitumen which are wet and dry processes, with the wet process being used most widely today. For the dry process, CR is regarded as particles distributed directly in the aggregate of bitumen mixture and there is limited interaction between CR and bitumen, whereas, during the wet process, CR is mixed with bitumen at a high temperature by a thermomechanical process and a complete interaction exists between CR and bitumen. It can significantly improve engineering performance as compared with conventional paving grade bitumen, however, the high temperature storage instability and high viscosity of rubberized bitumen have restricted its application. The different density and polarity between CR particles and bitumen leads to incompatibility and sedimentation in rubberized bitumen. Furthermore, the amount of aromatic oil absorption and CR particle swelling increases the viscosity of rubberized bitumen. In order to solve these problems, researchers have proposed different methods to enhance the compatibility and interaction between CR and bitumen. Generally, these methods can be grouped into the following three categories: reduce the viscosity by adding warm mix additives (WMA) or blend oil additives, pretreat CR particles with microwave irradiation or chemical reagents, and improve CR compatibility with bitumen by adding preswelling agents or reactive additives. </p>

<p>Modifying the chemical bonds between the functional groups of the modifying agents and bitumen compounds and promoting swelling reactions are useful ways to mitigate phase separation between CR and bitumen. Polyphosphoric acid, crosslinking agent, nanosilica, etc., have been incorporated in rubberized bitumen to improve the compatibility of CR particles with bitumen, among which trans-polyoctenamer (TOR) has shown high reactivity. TOR is a type of polymer that consists of linear and cyclic macromolecules that can facilitate the interaction between CR and bitumen via crosslinking reactions with double bonds and the sulfur component in the bitumen and surface of the CR particles. It has been noted that the addition of TOR improved the elasticity, modulus, and temperature susceptibility of rubberized bitumen. Liu indicated that there was a complex chemical reaction between TOR and rubberized bitumen that changed the rheological properties of rubberized bitumen and contributed to the bitumen binder’s storage stability. In addition, TOR added to rubberized bitumen mixture can improve the high temperature resistance to rutting and low temperature crack resistance of bitumen pavements. </p>

<p>High viscosity caused by aromatic oil absorption and the CR particle swelling is another problem that needs to be solved. Many researchers have been evaluating the performance and investigating the mechanism of warm mix rubberized bitumen, which can decrease viscosity significantly and conserve fossil fuel. On the basis of the chemical composition and modification mechanism, the various WMAs can be grouped into three categories: chemical, organic, and foaming additives or technologies. Researchers have analyzed the workability, mechanical, fatigue, and rheological property characterization of bitumen mixtures modified with various WMAs, and found that the viscosity of rubberized bitumen reduced significantly, however, WMAs had adverse effects on the fatigue property and rutting resistance, with the exception of Sasobit additive. Xiao et al. indicated that the binder type played a key role in determining the rheological properties of WMA binders by using Fourier transform infrared (FTIR) analysis. Furthermore, the modification mechanisms of WMAs were explored by researchers using a set of advanced testing equipment. On the basis of a series of chemical analyses, Yu et al. found that no major chemical reactions were detected after the addition of CR and WMA, but a better dissolution of CR was achieved in rubberized bitumen with Sasobit. However, some studies indicated that the stiffness of rubberized bitumen increased at low temperatures when the WMA was added, which led to cracking of the bitumen pavements. </p>

<p>The desulfurization and degradation behavior of CR particles in bitumen has an important influence on the performance of rubberized bitumen. Several studies have indicated that short-term microwave irradiation improved the devulcanization of CR and reduced its degradation. Yu et al. found that microwave irradiation cleft the surface vulcanization network of CR, resulting in higher surface activity, and improved its compatibility with bitumen. According to the microstructures of CR treated by microwave irradiation, the CR surface became fluffy, which resulted in good affinity, permeability, and reactivity at the interface with oil. Liang indicated that microwave irradiation activated CR and increased the risk of fatigue cracking caused by the hardening effect of aging but endowed the aged residue with stronger resistance to thermal cracking. These results are attributed to the effect of degradation and devulcanization of CR, however, CR treated by microwave irradiation had an adverse effect on the stability of rubberized bitumen. </p>
</text>
