<text id="autogum_academic_doc137" title="Does Ethical Behavior of Management Influence Financial Reporting Quality?" shortTile="ethical-behavior" author="Chaechang Im, Giseok Nam" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5765/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Firms strive to improve their value by efficiently utilizing the resources provided by interested parties, such as shareholders, debtors, and regulators. In particular, managers directly operate and manage their business activities with fiduciary responsibilities. They, in turn, provide accounting information to outsiders of the company in order to help them make appropriate financial decisions. Financial statements are very important sources for stakeholders, especially when they try to make decisions. A firm’s annual report, disclosure, MD&amp;A (Management Discussion and Analysis) and non-financial report also provide significant information to outsiders. Therefore, a firm’s financial performance as well as the quality of reporting is likely to reflect the fulfillment of the manager’s fiduciary responsibilities and reporting obligation. Consequently, when a company’s financial performance is determined by the ability of the manager, the reporting quality would reflect the manager’s level of ethics. Such reporting quality is defined in different aspects; they can be interpreted in terms of reliability of accounting information, earning’s quality, appropriate audit activity and accounting transparency. It is the quality of financial reporting that affects the company’s cost of capital as well as the interested parties’ decision-making. </p>

<p>Jianu et al. demonstrates that sustainability positively influences the performance from the perspective of firms’ marketing and reporting, they argue that a company’s market positioning can be strengthened by sustainability and marketing reports. If it is true, firms’ reporting could be a tool for marketing and public relations documents, and its high quality would lead to sustainable management as well as better positioning on capital markets. </p>

<p>Globally, a firm’s level of ethics and its ethical characteristics are being recognized as important factors for survival in the market in recent years. In the past, corporations used to focus on profit maximization; however, they were required to expand their role in order to mediate the conflict among various interested parties. Ethical practice of business has become an important issue in society with emphasis on firms’ social responsibilities. Due to the development of information technology, deregulation, and the strengthening of consumers’ rights, the demand for ethical practice of business as well as improving the level of consciousness have increased. </p>

<p>Under the circumstances, if a manager’s characteristic, morality, and ethicality affect various corporate activities, we can predict that they can also affect the accounting reporting quality. More specifically, if a manager’s level of ethics affects the reporting quality, which is substantial in financial decision-making for interested parties, we need to examine the relationship between the level of a manager’s ethics and the quality of financial reporting. In the same context, some literatures examined this relation. Jones and Loe et al. argue that ethics of a corporation affects general corporate activities and a high level of ethics prevents the manipulation of accounting information. The obvious example to explain this relation can be Enron’s accounting scandal in 2001. Considered as the worst accounting fraud in history, Enron took advantage of the accounting flexibility and withheld relevant information regarding its low profitability and high risk, only to go through a bankruptcy process. </p>

<p>In South Korea, since the late 1990s, managerial ethics has been strongly emphasized in the realm of business because the government regarded the moral hazard and lack of transparency of financial reporting in corporations as the main cause of the financial crisis at that time. Accordingly, various researchers have attempted to examine the relation between the level of corporate ethics and the quality of accounting reports. Moon examines business ethics as to how it affects the transparency of financial reporting by looking at the discretionary accruals. She suggests that firms that established a business ethics code conveyed higher accounting reporting quality than those that did not. In addition, Pae and Choi provide the ECI (Ethical Commitment Index) (The Ethical Commitment Index indicates a firm’s levels of ethics) and examine the relation between business ethics and accounting report quality, such as discretionary accruals, accounting conservatism, and accruals quality. The result also presents that firms with higher ECI have higher reporting quality. Overall, these results prove the reporting activity as one of the manager’s activities as well as reflect on the level of their moralities and ethics. </p>
</text>
