<text id="autogum_academic_doc642" title="Genome and Phylogenetic Analysis of Infectious Hematopoietic Necrosis Virus Strain SNU1 Isolated in Korea" shortTile="genome-phylogenetic" author="Woo  Taek Oh, Jin  Woo Jun, Sib  Sankar Giri, Saekil Yun, Hyoun  Joong Kim, Sang  Guen Kim, Sang  Wha Kim, Se  Jin Han, Jun Kwon, Se  Chang Park" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-0817/8/4/200/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Infectious hematopoietic necrosis virus (IHNV), one of the most devastating fish pathogens, causes considerable economic losses to the aquaculture industry. The virus is a single-stranded, bullet-shaped, ribonucleic acid (RNA) virus that belongs to the genus <hi rend="italic">Norvirhabdovirus</hi> and the family <hi rend="italic">Rhabdoviridae</hi>. The virus was first reported in the 1950s in sockeye salmon (<hi rend="italic">Oncorhynchus nerka</hi>) from Washington and Oregon fish hatcheries in the United States. Diverse fish species are known to be susceptible to IHNV infections including salmonids, which are the most vulnerable. The pathogenicity of the virus is known to depend on environmental conditions and the size and species of the fish. Outbreaks of IHNV infection are usually associated with a mortality rate of 50–60%, but can be up to 95%, and younger fish have been found to be more susceptible to the clinical symptoms and acute infections. The virus was first reported in Asian countries in 1971 when diseased kokanee salmon (freshwater <hi rend="italic">O. nerka</hi>) were imported to Japan from North America. Although the consumption amount of salmonids and the size of the fisheries rearing this species in Korea are relatively smaller than those in other countries in Europe and North America, some previous studies have been conducted on the presence of IHNV in Korea. In 1991, the first outbreak of IHNV was reported in Korea in cultured rainbow trout (<hi rend="italic">Oncorhynchus mykiss</hi>) and masuo salmon (<hi rend="italic">Oncorhynchus masuo</hi>).  </p>

<p>The IHNV genome consists of six genes in the order 3’-N-P-M-G-NV-L-5’, representing the nucleocapsid protein (N), phosphoprotein (P), matrix gene (M), glycoprotein (G), nonvirion protein (NV), and polymerase protein (L). The size of the genome was approximately 11 kb, and studies analyzing the genome, phylogenesis, and diversity of IHNV have usually used the <hi rend="italic">G</hi>, <hi rend="italic">N</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">NV</hi> genes. Further, epidemiologic studies, including phylogenetic analyses of IHNV isolated from different countries worldwide, have identified five genogroups to date. The presence of genogroups U, M, and L was reported in North America based on studies of isolates collected from genographic areas in the Pacific Northwest of North America including Alaska, British Columbia, the Columbia River basin, and Idaho. Moreover, the genogroup L was observed in isolates from California and the southern Oregon coast. The remaining two genogroups are the E and J genogroups. The lineage of the E genogroup is European, and it is divided into two subgroups: E1 and E2. The J genogroup represents isolates from Japan and South Korea and is also divided into two subclades: J Nagano (JN) and J Shizuoka (JS). In addition, a recent study phylogenetically analyzing Chinese isolates based on the <hi rend="italic">G</hi> gene reported that Chinese IHNV isolates form another individual clade belonging to the J genogroup with Asian lineage. </p>

<p>IHNV is one of the most well-known viruses that cause significantly high mortality rates in rainbow trout fisheries, and recent research indicates that reports on IHNV infections are increasing, especially in almost all geographic regions of China. Moreover, compared to before 2000, the number of IHNV isolates has gradually increased in Korea recently. No study has reported the complete genome sequence of the IHNV isolates in Korea, and the quality of data associated with the phylogenetic analysis of the Korean IHNV isolates is poor compared with that of the data of studies conducted in other countries. Therefore, our study aimed to provide sufficient information on the phylogenetics of IHNV isolates from Korea. Further, to the best of our knowledge, this is first study to report the complete genomic sequence of the IHNV strain isolated from Korea. In addition, we also aimed to study the nucleotide substitution and phylogenetic patterns of IHNV isolated from Korea and compared them to those of other isolates from Asia, Europe, and North America. </p>
</text>
