<text id="autogum_academic_doc186" title="Particle Imaging Velocimetry Gyroscope" shortTile="particle-imaging" author="Ahmed  A. Youssef, Naser El-Sheimy" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1424-8220/19/21/4734/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Navigation is a process by which a moving platform determines its state of motion through what is termed as the navigation states. The navigation states for any given platform are the position, velocity, and attitude of such a platform. The navigation states should be able to characterize the motion of any given body in either a two-dimensional (2D) or three-dimensional (3D) space. </p>

<p>Navigation is performed through various methods; such methods are characterized mainly into two clusters: position fixing and dead reckoning. Position fixing is the process by which the navigation states are driven through the knowledge and use of a set of fixated well-defined positions. An example of position fixing navigation is the global navigation satellite system (GNSS). Whereas, dead reckoning is a process by which the navigation states are determined through a recursive process of relative positioning with respect to the initial states. An example of dead reckoning navigation is the inertial navigation system (INS).  </p>

<p>Inertial navigation is performed by processing the data of inertial measurement units (IMUs). IMUs are an assembly of sensors that are mounted in a geometric form that guarantees capturing the motion of any given platform. Such sensors measure what is referred to as inertial measurements and they include accelerometers, which measure specific forces (i.e., linear accelerations), and gyroscopes, which measure angular rates. The inertial measurements undergo a mathematical process, known as INS mechanization, that mainly includes integrations and geometric transformations to determine the navigation states of the moving platform with respect to a pre-defined reference frame. A typical IMU constitutes a triad of accelerometers and a triad of gyroscopes, placed along three mutually orthogonal axes. </p>

<p>Inertial sensors endure systematic errors which can be calibrated in the laboratory and eliminated from the raw inertial measurements. Such systematic errors include biases, scale factor, scale factor non-linearity, and cross-coupling. The bias is a constant error, whereby the inertial sensor reads out a measurement that is at a constant offset from the actual value. The scale factor is an error that is demonstrated by the existence of a gradient for the input–output relation of the inertial sensor which is not unity. However, if such a gradient is non-linear, then it is said that the inertial sensor suffers from scale factor non-linearity. Cross-coupling error indicates that a given inertial sensor (i.e., accelerometer or gyroscope) measures residual inertial measurements from an axis that is orthogonal to its sensitive axes. Typically, cross-coupling occurs due to the non-orthogonality of the sensitive axis of the inertial sensors. </p>

<p>Furthermore, inertial sensors suffer from random errors that appear as noises within the inertial measurements from electrical and mechanical sources. The noises are assumed to be white for frequencies below 1 Hz. The order of magnitude of such noises depends on the technology behind the manufacturing of the inertial sensor. </p>

<p>Nonetheless, the performance of any given IMU is defined by the order of magnitude of the systematic and random errors. Whereby, IMUs are classified according their performance and accuracy into various categories. </p>

<p>Consequently, IMUs are classified into strategic grade, navigation grade, tactical grade, automotive grade, and low-cost consumer grade IMUs. Strategic grade, also referred to as marine grade, is the highest quality IMUs. Strategic grade IMUs can be used in military ships, submarines, some intercontinental ballistic missiles, and some spacecraft. A strategic grade IMU might cost more than $1 million. Navigation grade IMUs are used in military aircrafts and commercial aviation. Navigation grade IMUs cost around $100,000. Tactical grade IMUs can only be used for stand-alone inertial navigation for a few minutes. However, an accurate navigation solution can be obtained by integration of the tactical grade IMU with an aiding positioning system. Typically, tactical grade IMUs are used in guided weapons and unmanned air vehicles (UAVs). Tactical grade IMUs cost around $2000 to $50,000. The automotive and consumer grade IMUs are the lowest grade of inertial sensors. They are typically used in pedometers, antilock braking, active suspension, and airbags. Consumer grade accelerometers costs start around $1, and the gyroscopes costs start around $10. </p>

<p>Nevertheless, IMU grades are analogous to the technologies adopted to manufacture their inertial sensors (i.e., accelerometers and gyroscopes). Typical commercialized gyroscopes are classified into optical gyroscopes or vibratory gyroscopes. Optical gyroscopes utilize the phase of light waves to determine angular rates. The optical gyroscopes are realized by either ring laser gyroscope (RLG) technology or interferometric fiber-optic gyro (IFOG) technology. Vibratory gyroscopes are low-cost, and often depend on Micro-electro-mechanical system (MEMS) technology, in which quartz-based gyros provide better performance than silicon-based gyros. There are other types of gyroscopes, which include nuclear magnetic resonance gyroscope technology, and cold-atom interferometry. Both technologies provide relatively higher performance at a higher cost. </p>
</text>
