<text id="autogum_academic_doc597" title="Validity and Reliability of a New Optoelectronic System for Measuring Active Range of Motion of Upper Limb Joints in Asymptomatic and Symptomatic Subjects" shortTile="validity-reliability" author="Rodrigo Martín-San Agustín, Jose  A. García-Vidal, German Cánovas-Ambit, Aurelio Arenas-Della Vecchia, Manuel López-Nicolás, Francesc Medina-Mirapeix" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2077-0383/8/11/1851/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion and Conclusions</head>
<p>
The present study showed that Veloflex-IDA is a valid and reliable tool for the ROM assessment of upper limb joints’ ROM. In addition, excellent inter-rater reliability values were obtained after basic training in its use. </p>

<p>Veloflex-IDA and goniometer showed a very high correlation between them, with small mean bias and imprecision. In addition, this was observed in all movements performed, showing a high consistency between instruments independently of the test. Our findings are slightly superior to those of other studies that have examined the validity of other instruments with the goniometer as a gold standard. In the same way, compared to shoulder and wrist studies where the goniometer was used as a reference, our LoAs results were lower. This could be due to their use of a mobile phone application to measure the ROM. Accordingly, that system implies to attach the mobile phone in the body segment doing the movement, while the Veloflex-IDA does not need more than the placement of the markers. </p>

<p>The intra-rater reliability obtained in the ROM measurements proved to be excellent, with minimal differences between movements in both the ICCs and in the SEM variations. In relation to the relative reliability statistics, our ICCs are similar or superior to shoulder studies and slightly superior to others performed on the wrist. Furthermore, absolute reliability statistics proved to be superior to those studies that used a mobile phone or electrogoniometer as a measurement tool both in healthy subjects and in subjects with wrist limitations. Only SEMs and MCDs are similar to the use of video processing tools (e.g., Kinovea) for ROM shoulder measurements. To our knowledge, our study was the first to compare the tool’s reliability to assess the ROM of shoulder, elbow, and wrist joints. Reliability comparisons among joints showed ICCs and SEM% slightly higher for shoulder movements than for the wrist. These differences can be explained by the differences between their ROM values, since previous studies found similar results with better reliability for those movements with higher ROMs. </p>

<p>The inter-rater reliability behaved in a similar way to the intra-rater, with higher values in our study for both relative and absolute reliability statistics compared to those studies that used mobile phones or electrogoniometers and similar with video processing tools. Consequently, we believe that those instruments that need to be placed on the body segment to measure the ROM decrease their reliability, because of the possible error in their placement and the need for the instrument to remain stable during the movement. Inter-rater values were slightly worse than intra-rater reliability for all tests. This finding agrees on other shoulder and wrist studies. We believe that this is not due to the difference between the examiners’ experience, since given a basic training to the newly graduated examiner was enough to obtain high reliability values as in previous studies. </p>

<p>This study provides useful information on Veloflex-IDA validity and reliability to measure the ROM of the upper limb joints, despite being subject to limitations. The main limitation was that the participants were predominantly young and healthy, limiting the generalization of the measurements to other populations. Thereby, future studies should study the methodology used to measure populations with disorders. In addition, only the upper limb joints’ ROM was examined. Thus, future studies should evaluate the Veloflex-IDA’s reliability for other joints. </p>

<p>In conclusion, Veloflex-IDA is a valid and reliable alternative to measure the ROM of the upper limb joints and it can be used in clinical practice and research after basic training.
 </p>
</text>
