<text id="autogum_academic_doc057" title="Decellularized Lymph Node Scaffolding as a Carrier for Dendritic Cells to Induce Anti-Tumor Immunity" shortTile="decellularized-lymph" author="Hung-Jun Lin, Weu Wang, Yi-You Huang, Wei-Tsen Liao, Ting-Yu Lin, Shyr-Yi Lin, Der-Zen Liu" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1999-4923/11/11/553/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Cancer is a major cause of human death worldwide. Most cancer patients receive chemotherapy and radiation therapy, they are often only partially effective and lead to a variety of serious side effects. In recent decades, cancer immunotherapy has been validated as stimulating patients’ own immune systems to eliminate cancers. Compared to chemotherapy and radiation therapy, cancer immunotherapy can specifically target tumor cells by modulating immune cells without damage to normal cells. </p>

<p>A variety of cancer immunotherapies, including DC-based cancer vaccines, chimeric antigen receptor-T lymphocyte therapies, immune checkpoint blockade antibody therapies, oncolytic vaccine, and cytokines therapies, have been developed to induce tumor-specific and cytotoxic T lymphocyte immune responses. Dendritic cell based therapies have been widely investigated because dendritic cells (DCs) are thought to be the initiator in modulating immunity. DCs are known as professional antigen-presenting cells, responsible for swallowing tumor-associated antigens, presenting them to T lymphocytes, and inducing antigen-specific immune responses. When DCs mature and become activated, they will swallow the foreign substances and subsequently present the antigenic epitopes on major histocompatibility complex (MHC) molecules. At the same time, DCs up-regulate the maturation receptor, release potent cytokines, and migrate into lymph nodes to induce systemic immune responses. </p>

<p>The standard DC-based vaccine begins with first isolating DCs from the patient. Then, DCs are stimulated with the patient’s tumor-associated antigen in vitro, and the antigen-stimulated DCs are injected directly back into the patient to induce the activation of T lymphocytes. The patient’s immune system will generate the tumor-specific immune response to destroy cancer cells and prevent cancer recurrence. However, several drawbacks restrict the clinical efficacy of DC therapy. First, only a few DCs actually migrate to the lymph nodes and interact with T lymphocytes, with the result of a failure to induce antitumor immune responses. Moreover, the in vitro culture cannot generate sufficiently powerful DCs, with the result of a weak immune response and limited therapeutic benefit. Thus, it is important to establish an in vitro culturing system or an in vivo DC delivery system that can more reliably induce the immune response and more potently deliver antitumor immunity. </p>

<p>The lymph nodes are extremely critical in responses to pathogens or danger signals, and their major functions are to filter out deleterious substances by their unique mesh microstructure, to maintain matured immunocytes, and to initiate the antigen-specific adaptive immune response. The lymph nodes might lose their function because of cancer, obstruction, or infection; in such cases, surgical resection of lymph nodes is usually indicated. However, lymph node resection often causes a wide range of other problems such as increased infection, impaired cancer surveillance, and lymphedema. Consequently, a promising technique for functional lymph node restoration is urgently needed. </p>

<p>Decellularization has emerged as a process for producing a natural extracellular matrix (ECM), which preserves the intrinsic biological cues and architectural structure of the original tissue. It provides a strategy by which to fabricate lymph node scaffolds on which to grow immune cells with immunological function. Previous studies demonstrated that spleen-derived decellularized ECM or lymph node-associated decellularized ECM can deliver immune cells and promote the organization of lymphoid-like scaffolds; however, whether these can induce antigen-specific immunity or the antitumor immune response is still unknown.  </p>

<p>The aim of this study was to establish a natural decellularized lymph node scaffold (dLN), with preserved original microstructure and ECM, and to validate the ability of the dLN to support DC proliferation and maturation in vitro. The study also aimed to verify whether a bone marrow dendritic cell (BMDC)-dLN can activate a specific antitumor immune response in vivo. </p>
</text>
