<text id="autogum_academic_doc127" title="Effects of Straw Returning and Residue Cleaner on the Soil Moisture Content, Soil Temperature, and Maize Emergence Rate in China’s Three Major Maize Producing Areas" shortTile="effects-straw-returning" author="Jiale Zhao, Yun Lu, Hongli Tian, Honglei Jia, Mingzhuo Guo" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5796/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Conclusions</head>
<p>
Choosing a suitable straw returning amount and residue cleaner can effectively improve the soil moisture content, soil temperature, and maize emergence rate during straw returning. Comparative experiments were conducted with three kinds of residue cleaner under four different straw returning amounts in China’s three largest maize producing areas to reveal the influences of the straw returning amount and type of residue cleaner on the soil moisture content, soil temperature, and maize emergence rate. This study was based in China’s three largest maize producing areas. Due to the relationship between climate and site, three farms that represent the overall climate situation of three major maize producing areas were selected as test sites. </p>

<p>The straw returning amount and type of residue cleaner were shown to have significant effects on the SMC, ST, and MER in the three largest maize producing areas in China. An increase in the straw returning amount was shown to significantly increase the SMC when the straw returning amount was less than 70% in China’s three largest maize producing areas. An increase in the straw returning amount significantly increased the ST in the Inner Mongolia maize producing area and Heilongjiang maize producing area test sites, while it decreased the ST at the Jilin maize producing area test site. An increase in the straw returning amount will also increase the RCT, resulting in a decline in the residue-cleaner working quality, which decreases the MER. Therefore, there should be an extreme point in the straw returning amount so that the MER reaches a maximum value. </p>

<p>After springtime sowing, residue cleaner can decrease the RCT and SC so that the heat-absorption speed of soil is accelerated. In this study, the residue cleaner affected the ST by changing the RCT and SC. The influence of the residue cleaner on the clearing performance was significantly different with different straw returning amounts. Therefore, the best combination of test factors should be used in the three largest maize producing areas in China. </p>

<p>Therefore, in order to obtain a better maize emergence rate, a reasonable straw returning amount and a suitable residue cleaner should be selected. The most optimal combinations of test factors were determined by establishing a regression model of the straw returning amount and the MER with different residue cleaners. In the Jilin maize producing area, when the straw returning amount was 52% and PRC was used as the residue cleaner, the MER was estimated to be 91.7%. In the Heilongjiang maize producing area, when the straw returning amount was 67% and CD was used as the residue cleaner, the MER was estimated to be 94.7%. In the Inner Mongolia maize producing area, when the straw returning amount was 68% and CD was used as the residue cleaner, the MER was estimated to be 91.4%. At present, the straw returning amount is commonly accepted as 100% in China’s three major maize producing areas. The highest MER will occur when RB is used as the residue cleaner, based on the conditions above. </p>

<p>This work will accelerate the popularization of straw returning into China’s three major maize producing areas and promote sustainable agriculture development there.
 </p>
</text>
