<text id="autogum_academic_doc252" title="Characterization and Correction of the Geometric Errors Using a Confocal Microscope for Extended Topography Measurement, Part II: Experimental Study and Uncertainty Evaluation" shortTile="characterization" author="Chen Wang, Emilio Gómez, Yingjie Yu" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2079-9292/8/11/1217/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The increasing demands for manufacturing accuracies and quality control due to the rapid development of nanotechnology, ultraprecision machining, micro-, and nanofabrications, etc. and the requirements for precision in surface finishing in different technologies such as additive manufacturing, mechanical parts with structured surfaces, etc., require the use of increasingly sophisticated measurement systems and measurement traceability from a metrological point of view. </p>

<p>Calibration provides a wide range of information about microscope performances. The ever-increasing demand for improved surface quality and tighter geometric tolerances has led to augmentations in the investigations of manufacturing technologies. Measurements using optical microscopes are often affected by common path noise, disturbance in light source and ambient lighting, etc., which cause measurement defects and outliers, as well as attract investigations on noisy data processing. The need for standardization is becoming ever greater as the range of capturing three-dimensional (3D) information of microscope techniques continues to increase. For optical confocal microscopes, the Z-calibrations at nm levels are typically good, while the X- and Y-accuracies are often left, without further notice than resolution limits of the optics. Among the investigations of lateral calibrations, many studies focus on the optical system. For example, H. Ni et al. proposed a new method to achieve structured detection using a spatial light modulator, which modulates the Airy disk amplitude distribution according to the detection function in the collection arm and B. Wang et al. presented confocal microscopy with structured detection in a coherent imaging process to achieve a higher resolution with a comparably large pinhole, however, the systematic geometric errors which adversely affect the relative position and orientation between measuring probes and measurands are usually neglected. B. Daemi et al. designed a comprehensive verification test by using a high precision metrology method based on subpixel resolution image analysis. The calibration of confocal microscopes usually relies on traceable standard artefacts, which are commonly made up of regular patterns. </p>

<p>This paper describes the experimental studies based on the kinematic modeling and algorithms for the correction of the geometric errors developed in Part I. Section 2 and Section 3 introduce the methodologies for experiments and uncertainty evaluation individually. Section 4 presents the experiment on a dot grid target for correction coefficients determination and their corresponding uncertainty evaluation. Section 5 implements an experiment and corrects the measured data with determined coefficients, comparing the residuals with respect to certified values before and after corrections. Section 6 presents the conclusions. Following Section 6, acknowledgements and references are included. </p>
</text>
