<text id="autogum_academic_doc273" title="An Effective Multiclass Twin Hypersphere Support Vector Machine and Its Practical Engineering Applications" shortTile="effective-multiclass" author="Qing Ai, Anna Wang, Aihua Zhang, Wenhui Wang, Yang Wang" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2079-9292/8/10/1195/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Related Works</head>
<p>
In this paper, we consider a multi-class classification problem with a training dataset , where <hi rend="italic">K</hi> is the number of classes and  is the number of the samples of the <hi rend="italic">k</hi>-th class. The size of training dataset is . Denote, for convenience, by  the sets of samples of the <hi rend="italic">k</hi>-th class, i.e., . </p>

<head> 2.1. Review of K-SVCR Multi-Classifier</head>
<p>
The K-SVCR multi-classifier is based on decomposition-reconstruction strategy.  binary SVM sub-classifiers are constructed, each of which evaluates each sample into 1-vs-1-vs-rest structure. The classification result of K-SVCR is shown in <figure>Figure 1</figure>a intuitively. </p>

<p>The sub-classifier  for two focused classes <hi rend="italic">i</hi> and <hi rend="italic">j</hi> in K-SVCR seeks an optimal hyperplane

(1)

here  is the normal vector and  is the bias term. The optimal hyperplane can be obtained by resolving the following QPP:

(2)

where , , ,  and ,  are slack variables, the parameter  is restricted to . </p>

<p>For a testing sample <hi rend="italic">x</hi>, the sub-classifier  determines its class by

(3)

</p>

<p>For the testing sample <hi rend="italic">x</hi>, the final label can be determined by vote rule. </p>

<head> 2.2. Review of Twin-KSVC Multi-Classifier</head>
<p>
Twin-KSVC is an improvement of K-SVCR. The Twin-KSVC constructs  pairs of binary TSVM sub-classifiers, which evaluates each sample into 1-vs-1-vs-rest structure. The classification result is intuitively presented in <figure>Figure 1</figure>b. </p>

<p>The sub-classifiers  and  for two focused classes <hi rend="italic">i</hi> and <hi rend="italic">j</hi> in Twin-KSVC seek a pair of hyperplane

(4)

where  and  are the normal vector and the bias term of the corresponding hyperplane, respectively. The two hyperplanes can be obtained by resolving the QPPs as follows:

(5)

(6)

where  and  are slack variables. </p>

<p>For a testing sample <hi rend="italic">x</hi>, the sub-classifiers  and  assign its class by

(7)

</p>

<p>For the testing sample <hi rend="italic">x</hi>, the final label can be also determined by vote rule. </p>

<head> 2.3. Review of THKSVM Multi-Classifier</head>
<p>
THKSVM (Twin Hypersphere Multiclass Support Vector Machine) integrates THSVM and 1-vs-rest structure. THKSVM constructs <hi rend="italic">K</hi> hyperspheres in the training stage, whose classification result is intuitively shown in <figure>Figure 1</figure>c. </p>

<p>The sub-classifier for the focused classes <hi rend="italic">i</hi> in THKSVM seeks a hypersphere

(8)

where  and  are the center and the radius of the corresponding hypersphere, respectively. The hypersphere can be constructed by resolving the following QPP:

(9)

where ,  and  are slack variables. </p>

<p>The class of a testing sample <hi rend="italic">x</hi> can be determined by

(10)

 </p>
</text>
