<text id="autogum_academic_doc674" title="Spatial Assessment of Damage Vulnerability to Storms Based on the Analysis of Historical Damage Cost Data in the Korean Peninsula" shortTile="spatial-assessment" author="Hyun  Il Choi" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/6051/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
As there have been many assessments of vulnerability to hydro-meteorological disasters based on the IPCC’s three components, such as exposure, sensitivity, and adaptive capacity, the potential flood damage index was developed by the product of the potential indicator (sensitivity) and the risk indicator (exposure minus adaptive capacity), similar to the livelihood vulnerability index adopting the IPCC’s vulnerability concept. Based on the framework for the potential flood damage index, this study has developed the damage vulnerability index to assess vulnerability to rainstorms and typhoons that pose major and serious damage costs in the Korean Peninsula. As for the aggregation framework for combining the two major components into a composite indicator, a new aggregation function incorporated with a quadratic mean formula was proposed to produce higher vulnerability outcomes when the two components (potential and risk indicators) are both higher, and have some degree of compensability even when either of the two components is zero, as a complement to the existing multiplicative aggregation function. The proxy variables were selected in terms of the damage to people and property for the two major components. The potential indicator comprises the population density for the human factor and the major facilities area ratio for the physical factor. The risk indicator is measured by an expected value for integrating both frequency and severity of the human and economic damage costs, which can provide a better interpretation of the risk indicator outcomes and reduce the nature of uncertainty in the proxy variables being used. The proxy variables for the adaptive capacity component tend to have more uncertainty than other proxy variables. Moreover, the human and economic damage risks are primarily caused by localized heavy rains and storms exceeding designed capacity inducing insufficient capacity of river conveyance and inland drainage systems, in general. Hence, instead of the use of the difference between exposure and adaptive capacity components for the risk indicator, a comprehensive analysis result on both frequency and severity of the historical damage cost records can be interpreted explicitly as a measure of actual experiences and behaviors arising from the lack of adaptive capacity to exposed hazard risks. For more feasible and realistic evaluation in this study, the risk indicator was constructed based on the human and economic damage cost data officially collected during the last two decades from 1997 to 2017. The risk analysis results indicate that the human and economic damage risk were higher mostly in small and medium cities exposed to storm hazards, which tend to have a relatively higher population and infrastructure densities than rural districts but have relatively less ability to prevent or recover from storm damage than metropolises, in general. </p>

<p>The proposed methodology for the damage vulnerability index was implemented for the spatial assessment of vulnerability to rainstorms, typhoons, and both, respectively, over the nationwide 231 administrative districts in the Republic of Korea. There were spatially different vulnerable patterns in the three damage vulnerability index outcomes for storm disasters triggered by different causes. The damage vulnerability to rainstorms was higher in most northern districts, including the Seoul metropolitan areas (northwestern part) and some southeastern districts in Busan metropolis (southeastern part). The damage vulnerability to typhoons was higher in some districts of the Seoul Special City and most districts along southern and eastern coastlines, including Busan metropolis. The damage vulnerability to both rainstorms and typhoons was higher in the Seoul metropolitan areas and some southern districts, including Busan metropolis. Some districts in Seoul and Busan metropolises were assessed to be most vulnerable to all the three cases of storm-induced disasters. The proposed damage vulnerability index needs to be continuously updated by including the most recent storm damage records and successively evaluated with damage data series over several time periods to provide feasible and effective information on sustainable mitigation plans for changes in storm damage patterns. Furthermore, to assess the future vulnerability to storms by the proposed assessment methodology based on the analysis of the past damage cost records, the human and economic damage costs need to be predicted by the regression analysis of the meteorological data in the event of a disaster for the use of future damage cost estimations according to climate change scenarios. For practical use of the proposed damage vulnerability to storms, each administrative district needs to establish region-specific disaster countermeasures relevant to major causes of hazards, and also can quantitatively evaluate their effects on disaster risk reduction and mitigation consequences. </p>
</text>
