<text id="autogum_reddit_doc007" title="Anyone else finding the SJW videos from H3H3 tiring?" shortTile="anyone-finding-sjw" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-05-30" dateModified="2018-05-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8n63qo" speakerList="#Megareddit64, #Theodreo" speakerCount="2">
<head>Anyone else finding the SJW videos from H3H3 tiring?</head>
<sp who="#Theodreo">
<p>I've felt this way for about a month or two now, however Ethan's comments today just brought them up again. I used to love watching videos making fun of Social Justice Warriors; in fact that is a big reason as to why I was originally drawn to H3H3. However, now they're incredibly stale. Everyone knows these people are crazy. No one agrees with them but those that are already within the "cult of outrage". No one's mind is being changed, no awareness is being spread, and nothing new is ever said. If you've seen one you've seen them all. There is just about nothing to gain from these videos. While one may argue that they are entertaining, they get quite old quite fast, as I previously stated. Of course, that last bit is subjective, however I cannot imagine that I'm the only one that feels that way. More damning is that I feel these videos actually do more harm than good. They make people fear that these social justice warriors are everywhere, that people this irrational and easily offended are around every corner, when I have yet to find someone come even close to what is portrayed in the videos, and I live in an extremely liberal town. Of course, these videos are entertainment, so they are going to pick the most ridiculous people of the bunch, yet looking at the comments I see people say they're scared of making jokes because of these people. IMO the right way to combat the overly-offended is to ignore them, they really have no power if their message is not spread. The purpose of this post really isn't about political correctness or social justice warriors, so I won't get too much into that, but you see my point. I know I could "just not watch" (gottem) those of his videos, and trust me I don't, but since that has become a good 60&#37; of the h3h3 channel by now, I just don't want to see these videos consume any more of his channel than it already has.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#Megareddit64">
<p>Very few people ever took the SJWs that became the subject of those videos seriously. What, you think fucking manspreading was ever something people took seriously? It was some lame video made by boring BuzzFeed writers, who were probably the only ones to give a shit about it. </p>
<p>That's what the SJW outrage videos were: Just some angry people who had a meltdown in public and got famous on the internet. It's over, it's done, now that kind of content is boring, the people who still get views out of it are involved in fringe right-wing politics. </p>
</sp>
</text>
