<text id="autogum_bio_doc000" title="Arnon Shani" shortTile="arnon-shani" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2019-11-02" dateModified="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arnon_Shani" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Arnon Shani</head><p><hi rend="bold">Arnon Shani</hi> is an Israeli emeritus professor of chemistry from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ben-Gurion_University_of_the_Negev">Ben-Gurion University of the Negev</ref> who was awarded an honorary membership from the Israel Chemical Society for his major contributions to the community and to chemistry education in the State of Israel.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Early life and education</head>
<p>Born in Israel, Shani served in military service from 1953 to 1956. From 1958 to 1961, he attended <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hebrew_University_of_Jerusalem">Hebrew University of Jerusalem</ref> where he studied for M.Sc. in chemistry under mentorship of E.D. Bergmann. After graduating from it with distinction and M.Sc. degree, Shani did his Ph.D. at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Weizmann_Institute_of_Science">Weizmann Institute of Science</ref> where his mentor was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franz_Sondheimer">Franz Sondheimer</ref>, graduating in 1965.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-bgu-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Career</head>
<p>Prior to graduating, Shani already was working as a researcher specializing in fluorine and phosphorus-containing insecticides at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Israel_Institute_for_Biological_Research">Israel Institute for Biological Research</ref>. He then was promoted to research associate specializing in organic photochemistry at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Chicago">University of Chicago</ref>, working under N.C. Yang. From 1967 to 1969, Shani was a research fellow at the Hebrew University where he was supervised by R. Mechoulam and studied components and photochemicals of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hashish">hashish</ref>. He then was promoted to a senior lecturer at the same university, becoming researcher on organic
photochemistry and natural products from plants that he collected in Negev and Sinai. While serving as such, Shani was an acting chairman of the Department of Chemistry and coordinator of its subdepartment on Organics, and was promoted to chairman position at the Department of Chemistry at the same university.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-bgu-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>From 1973 to 1982, Shani was an associate professor of chemistry at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ben-Gurion_University_of_the_Negev">Ben-Gurion University of the Negev</ref> and during those years also did sabbatical in applied chemistry at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Case_Western_Reserve_University">Case Western Reserve University</ref> and was a chairman of Chemistry Department at University of Negev. After becoming a professor in 1982, he continued his sabbatical at the Division of Entomology of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CSIRO">CSIRO</ref> in 1983 where he taught chemistry and entomology of pheromones, specifically, chemistry of jojoba wax. From 1984 to 1986 he served as deputy rector at Ben-Gurion University of the Negev, and in 1988 he did another sabbatical, this time at the Department of Chemistry, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/State_University_of_New_York">State University of New York</ref> where he continued his lectures on chemistry and entomology of pheromones.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-bgu-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Shani served as director of the Institute for Applied Research at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ben-Gurion_University_of_the_Negev">Ben-Gurion University of the Negev</ref> from 1989 to 1993 and from 1993 to 1994 held sabbatical at Casali Institute for Applied Chemistry, Hebrew University of Jerusalem. The sabbatical was followed by another one a year later at Horticulture and Food Research Institute of New Zealand and another one from 2000 to 2003 at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simon_Fraser_University">Simon Fraser University</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-bgu-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Despite many sabbaticals, Shani was a hardworking man. He served as scientific consultant to such magazines as <hi rend="italic">Chemada</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Pazchem</hi> from 1971 to 1984 and from 1981 to 2000 served on the Committee for Chemistry Curriculum in Israeli high schools, a position which was bestowed on him by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ministry_of_Education_(Israel)">Israeli Ministry of Education</ref>. In 1982, Shani was a member of the Applied Research Grants Committee, a branch of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Israel_Academy_of_Sciences_and_Humanities">Israel Academy of Sciences and Humanities</ref>. From 1983 to 1986, he was a national representative on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Union_of_Pure_and_Applied_Chemistry">International Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry</ref> Committee on Teaching of Chemistry, between which, for a year each, he served as a member of the Chemistry Sub-Committee for Basic Equipment Grants, a branch of the Planning and Granting Committee, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Council_for_Higher_Education_in_Israel">Council for Higher Education</ref> and was a member of the Applied Research Grants Committee at Israel Academy of Sciences and Humanities. Shani was also a member of the Council of the Israel Chemical Society from 1984 to 1986 and in 1986 became a member of the Organizing Committee of the UNESCO.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-bgu-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>From 1986 to 1987, Shani served on board of directors of the Pre-Academic Schools in Israeli Universities and from 1987 to 1990 worked as councilor for the International Society of Chemical Ecology. In 1987, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Government_of_Israel">President of Israel</ref> had appointed him as member of the Council for Higher Education, which position he kept until 1990, while still serving as a member of Organizing Committee of medicinal chemistry. During those years and until 1992, Shani was a member of both the Committee for Environment Quality and the Committee for Industry at the Chamber of Commerce and Industry of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Be'er_Sheva">Be'er Sheva</ref>. From 1990 to 1993, Shani was serving on board of directors of Initiative Center of the Negev (ICN), Center for Future Technologies (MATA) and was a member of the Higher Council for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ministry_of_Agriculture_and_Rural_Development_(Israel)">Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Development in Israel</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-bgu-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Shani was also a member of the advisory council of HEMDA at the Center for Science Education in Tel-Aviv-Yafo from 1991 to 1994 and until 1993 was a member of the advisory council for inventors competition at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manufacturers_Association_of_Israel">Manufacturers Association of Israel</ref>. From 1993 to 1995, he was a scientific consultant for <hi rend="italic">Jojoba Israel</hi> and from 1994 to 1997 served on Steering Committee for Science and Technology Education in Israel.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-bgu-2">[2]</ref> From 1997 to 2003, Shani held a post of president of Israel Chemical Society<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> and served as council member for the Council for Higher Education for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Judea_and_Samaria_Area">Judea and Samaria</ref>. From 1998 to 2000 Shani was a chairman of the Committee for Chemistry Curriculum in Israeli high schools, was a member of Organizing Committee for one year in 2000, and from 2003 to 2008 was a PheroCap employee.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-bgu-2">[2]</ref></p>
</text>
