<text id="autogum_reddit_doc006" title="2 Mile Stones Pt. 2 - High Sex" shortTile="-mile-stones-pt-" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-05-31" dateModified="2018-05-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8nn0p6" speakerList="#forgetyesternight" speakerCount="1">
<head>2 Mile Stones Pt. 2 - High Sex</head>
<sp who="#forgetyesternight">
<p>Part 1 - Anal - <ref target="https://www.reddit.com/r/sexover30/comments/8nmxiy/2_mile_stones_pt_1_anal/">https://www.reddit.com/r/sexover30/comments/8nmxiy/2_mile_stones_pt_1_anal/</ref> I originally posted asking about sex while high here - <ref target="https://www.reddit.com/r/sexover30/comments/883an3/sex_while_high/">https://www.reddit.com/r/sexover30/comments/883an3/sex_while_high/</ref>Quick shout out and thank you to all who commented and those who helped me be more aware of what to expect/experience and provided great suggestions for a first timer. This will be an even longer post... I have a pretty good memory but a lot of my recollection of this night is hazy as I got deeper in. It was all dreamlike and in that sense it's like trying to remember a dream that you know actually happened. Thankfully I've been keeping a journal and actually detail sex whenever we have it. I wanted to remember this so I wrote in my journal after rounds. It is most of what was going on and what we did vs the sensation. Though I still remember the sensations which I will write about.Marked  <hi rend="bold">READ HERE</hi>  on when sex actually begins.  <hi rend="bold">High Sex</hi>   <hi rend="bold">Background:</hi>  Neither my wife(26F) or I(31M) have ever been high nor really messed with any drugs. So my apologies if I use lame terms or the wrong words to describe things. My wife has always been interested but we've just never pursued it. She's gotten into the CBD oil and other related products like a cream that we massage on our necks for tension headaches that works great. So she's been into the medicinal side of it and I was willing to try. Of course there's no THC so there's no real mental effects. During a recent trip to Cali she got introduced to it by her brother and his wife as he uses it medicinally and to get great sleep when he gets behind. I'm sure other things but those were his reasons. She did let me know before she left for the trip that she was thinking of getting some stuff for us as I got more open to it after my initial post above. I was fine with that but I was slightly bummed when I found out she already tried it with her brother and his wife. I kind of wanted to experience it for the first time together but it was nice to hear her experience and what it was like for her. It helped alleviate some apprehension on my side. I have no idea what any of the stuff was called as I was uninterested and in my head at the moment when she was showing me what she got us. It was a black "pen" that had what looked like a USB connector on one end and she got some oil in a vial that connected to the pen. The oil was an indica strain as she wanted to use it for her really bad migraines and to reduce anxiety. The great thing about this was that it didn't give off a smell unless you were just about to take a hit and after. Very discreet. Funny thing... She didn't know how to use the pen as it was completely different than the one her brother had. She kept saying the end looked like a USB but didn't know why. She tried to take a hit from the USB end and... Nothing. We later laughed as she read the box and learned that it was in fact a USB connector used for charging. You took a hit on the vial end which actually had a hole and mouth piece at closer inspection. A light lit up when you took a hit. I was starting to get a headache so she asked if I wanted to try and I said not while the baby was still awake. So we put it away. She asked me if I was scared and I said a little as I don't know how it would affect me. I know this is completely different but I have a bad reaction to alcohol so I was a bit concerned as to what this could do to me. Look up "Asian Flush" and that's what I have. Anybody can have it but apparently it's dominant in Asians?? Basically I'm missing an enzyme in my liver that breaks down the alcohol.  <hi rend="bold">Story and Observations:</hi>  Later that night after my wife put our daughter to bed my wife took out the pen and took a hit while we were in bed. She wanted a good night's rest. She waited a few minutes then took another. She said she could feel it shortly after the second hit. I was skeptical of it working that fast but apparently it can? After she got done coughing (lol) she was noticeably more relaxed. Still skeptical that it could work that fast and thought she was just inexperienced and thought she was high but not actually there yet. I decided to take a hit despite my worries and the idea of having to be taken to the hospital during a nasty/awesome summer storm going on. My wife told me how to do it beforehand and I suprisingly did something naturally that helped me not cough as much. Though I was still hit kind of bad with the coughing fit. Wife was looking up how to do it without coughing and one advice was to breathe in some air with the hit before you exhale. Which I did. I put my mouth on the piece, inhaled and continued to inhale after taking the piece out, then exhaled. To my surprise I could see vapor. I honestly don't know how all of it works and since we only had a lamp on I didn't see any vapors when my wife exhaled. So I got annoyed as I thought it would put the smell in our room (it didn't). But started observing how I was feeling. I started to panic a little as I felt like something was expanding inside my chest and wondered if this was natural or me having a bad reaction. It was maybe 10-15 seconds of panic and feeling that expansion. The expanding then started to make me cough. The expanding feeling continued. After the coughing fit I was fine and I started to wonder if I was feeling it. I didn't think I did but felt this tingly sensation in the back of my head and sort of behind my eyes. Hindsight I think I might have been actually feeling it but very low as I was skeptical about things my wife was saying. Waited a few mins to see if anything else happened and I took another hit. Same way but this time inhaled more of the pen and air. I felt the expansion in my chest again though not as long nor scary like the first and this time I didn't cough at all. She mocked me being an expert. I sat up in bed waiting and observing and wondering if I was feeling it while still feeling the tingly sensation. I started to notice things around the room more and making skeptical faces at whatever my wife was saying. Still unsure if I was actually feeling it. Then after thinking of what I was doing/feeling vs how I normally would... I knew I was feeling something. Main thing that tipped me off was me zoning in on objects in the room and just wondering about how much I noticed certain aspects of said object. Here's where memory gets a bit hazy. I know I turned off the lamp as we sunk into bed. My wife snuggled up against me into the crook of my arm and her head on my chest/shoulder. Talking about whatever. Meanwhile I just noticed and observed the darkness of the room and the faint light coming through the curtains from the window. The occasional brightness with the lightning. My wife said something about not judging her for probably going and eating cereal in a bit. I responded with, "You're hungry?". I don't remember what she said but I then replied with, "I'm just surprised you're still hungry.". She then gets off of me and moves to her side of the bed. I know she's upset but my brain is going from I don't care to why is she upset to guess I need to reassure her. She's been iffy about her weight as she's going through a lot of emotions and stress. She's the biggest she's ever been but she doesn't look big to me as her weight is pretty evenly distributed with her height and settles mostly in her ass and hips then to her boobs. She thicc which I enjoy. She asked recently if I cared and I was honest. So my brain went back and forth between not caring as she should remember what I said before about it to... "You need to reassure her, bro.". This was a long time in my head. It most likely was not as time slows down when you're high. I then touched her, asked if she was mad, told her I didn't mean anything by it and that I'm feeling really weird. She laughed and we started talking some more. I remember saying something like, "I was super confused as to why you got upset cuz I didn't mean anything at all by it. I was just talking." Then for some reason found it funny and we both started laughing. Yeah... Definitely feeling it. I had my arm around her and then said I wished she wasn't on her period. She responded that she's been officially period free since that afternoon. She's been gone on her trip and I just picked her up that morning so I was more than ready to jump her bones.  <hi rend="bold">READ HERE:</hi>  I was planning to put in what I wrote in my journal here but it's more explicit than what I've seen in this sub. I don't completely know the rules about that here so I'll leave it out. I can put it in later if a mod says it's OK. So instead I'll just describe the sensations and thought processes with some details. First off, this was where it really felt like I was dreaming. Like I was completely zoned in on what I was doing and how she felt and made me feel. Definitely understand the cotton mouth and cotton vagina now. Made out with her which was interesting with the dry mouth. Not as dry as it sounds but definitely not as wet as normal making out. Interesting to make out in that state for sure. She grabbed her dildo nearby and we shared control of it on her. Continued making out and her giving me oral in the process. Dry mouth didn't affect this sensation at all. It actually felt amazing especially when she tended to my balls. Normally I feel a bit of pain. Like an extremely minor kick in the balls when she sucks them but I felt none of that. Just pure pleasure. I also noticed my voice changed. Like it was softer more soothing. Guessing cuz I was a lot more relaxed. She then got in doggy and I discovered the cotton vagina. This was an interesting observation as my wife normally gets really wet but also because we used the dildo beforehand. She felt wet on my fingers when I controlled the dildo and she was completely aroused and into it so I was surprised I couldn't go in as easy. I kept asking her to get the lube but she was just zoned in. So I finally gave up and started thrusting hoping she'd get wet as I started. Thankfully she very quickly did. I felt like I was in a completely different place. Just the complete dark around me and feeling my wife's body and having sex. I'm really big on visual and seeing things so the fact I was so immersed without seeing things was awesome. Whenever I sort of zoned back out so I could see her it was like waking up from a dream in the middle of the night and wondering if you were still dreaming. Commenced more dirty talk as I didn't have any inhibitions and have been wanting her to talk more dirty. She asked to be gripped harder and deeper. So I obliged for a good while. Then I went to say something else and she came right as I started to speak and this surprised me. It's difficult to make her cum in PIV and she hasn't done it in months. I don't think she's ever came in doggy either so it was cool to feel her buck and quiver in that position while I was still in her. I would say awesome but my brain was in surprised mode throughout most of the orgasm before it went into sly, confident mode to be more aware of the sensation and capitalize to help it continue. She said it felt so good while I kept thrusting. Skipping some details I eventually also came through doggy through lots of dirty talk from her as she rallied from her own orgasm for me. Again, I was completely zoned in throughout most of it. Only zoning out to just see what I was doing and what was going on only to slip back into the awesome dream. We then took a break where she had her cereal and watched Friends on her phone while I journaled. I could feel myself coming back down from the high as I was more aware of the room rather than being in my weird dream/hazy state. I was somewhere in between that stage and my initial stage of noticing the details in the room. I knew I was still affected as my writing was broken into 1 and 2 sentence paragraphs and looked really choppy. Like I was trying to scramble and remember everything as it came to me before the memories disappeared. I fixed this the next day. I asked her how she felt and she said everything felt amazing and that she was so in the moment. She didn't have normal anxiety of me wearing her out or just anxiety about it in general. We also drank a glass of water each and acknowledged the dry mouth with each other. After she finished her cereal she came back with more water and took 2 hits and another which surprised me. She shrugged when I questioned 3. I took one hit. Same expanding in chest feeling and coughed a little this time. Then we started another round. She started with giving me oral and she thought I was bigger to which she then measured by seeing how much of me fit in her mouth. Normally she can get close to the base but this time she wasn't close. Probably a good inch further than where she normally can go. Always a nice gesture to get cock size acknowledged and then proceed to be measured by mouth :). Tbh... I'm average but if this was the case this would of put me at 7". I will admit I'm judging based on hazy memory and I also don't know how much effort my wife put in regarding measuring. But I do recall me hitting the back of her throat and her closing her lips around me. I had a good idea of where I felt her lips. I also did feel bigger and harder with little mental effort on my part. My wife then said she was ready and we started making out while I fingered her. She wasn't as wet so I asked for the lube again. She was zoned in again but I was persistent and she finally admitted that she didn't know. She then gave me a suggestion on where to look... Looked. Not there. She then found it right next to her on her dresser the whole time. I asked her why she couldn't have got it before and she came back asking why I didn't see it myself. I replied with "I dunno. I was just doing my thing." She gave me a look stating she was doing the same. We also got her vibrator and she came that way. More dirty talk and sharing fantasies uninhibited. She put herself in pretzel pose and I was able to go deeper and harder. Hit one of her fornixes a few times. Came a lot more and harder than the first round. We drank more water and talked a bit more and I attempted a third round. It actually went a long while with her "pillow princessing" it which was fine as I was purely focused on just wanting to do a quickie. She would just caress my back, sides, and arms. Occasionally push herself against me. I took a long while and she was fine the whole time as I would check in but despite the sensation I couldn't cum. We kissed and said our goodnights happy and fulfilled. I checked my clock and the whole thing was maybe 1.5-2 hrs. I was shocked as I thought it would've been 2 in the morning or 4/5 hrs judging how long everything felt. I didn't care that it felt like a long time due to how awesome everything felt plus I just didn't care or think about anything else other than the sex we were having. I was actually really happy it was only 12:20 and we both slept hard and so well. I did wake up around 2:30 to get our daughter as she was crying and I felt like I was still feeling the effects. It might've just been feeling the effects of waking up from a really deep sleep though. I noticed the next day that I still kind of felt different. Genuinely wondered if I was still feeling the effects somehow as I noticed I was just a bit more aware than normal and when I did focus in on something. I was pretty zoned in. This feeling lasted until the evening started and I genuinely felt completely normal. My wife never indicated or said that she felt different that day other than the amazing sleep she had. As parents who still co-sleep (put the baby to sleep in her bed, take her or she walks to our bed in the middle of the night)... I think the extra/great sleep we both experienced just gave us minor super powers for the day.  <hi rend="bold">Tips:</hi>   <hi rend="bold"> Be aware and prepared for the dry mouth and vagina. It's real. Hopefully someone can comment below on how to combat it. </hi>  Indica is a more relaxing strain. Sativa is a more heightened awareness. Do your research on both. My wife did and I trusted her. A hybrid is apparently the way to go for sex though. * Experience it first in an environment where you feel safe. You just really don't know how it will affect you personally.  <hi rend="bold">Questions:</hi>   <hi rend="bold"> How do we prevent the dry mouth or solve it? </hi>  Any suggestions on making this better somehow? * What was your first experience like with high sex?  <hi rend="bold">Final Thoughts:</hi>  This was absolutely amazing for both my wife and I. With her cumming while in doggy I'm wondering what other opportunities this opens up for PIV orgasms. I love watching and giving her orgasms but it was usually clitoral. So her having one while I was still inside her WITH normal effort is awesome. The times I've made her come through PIV it was through a lot of physical effort or really, really getting her going mentally. Even then... Circumstance was at play. I almost only ever want to have high sex now and I wish we did this way before we had a kid. This is coming from someone who really likes to keep their senses and wits about them especially for sex so I can be more present, aware, and just really enjoy the moment. High sex heightened all of that. I was purely focused on her pleasure and mine. She had no anxiety or worries about anything she'd normally have during sex. Said that she wanted to do it again soon as it was just way better. We were both just completely immersed with each other and what we were doing. I was a lot more vocal and so was she. Both in communicating what we wanted and the gasps and moans of amazing sex. I also had more stamina and felt and was bigger due to the heightened arousal. Her brother is supposed to send us a hybrid indica/sativa. Supposedly even better for sex as the sativa will heighten sensation and awareness but the indica will balance it with it's mellow effect. Feel free to ask any questions or provide better tips. Could definitely use more tips to make the next experience better or more prepared. I thought I'd share my first experience and give my insight and observations as a first timer to help others. Would definitely like to hear others first experience of high sex. We plan on going to a hotel soon. Wife will get her wax, possibly do the day with no panties and a dress and going out in public the day of the hotel, then her dressing up in bed. Most likely exploring more of both sexual mile stones. Gonna be a fun and very sexual day/night.  <hi rend="bold">UPDATE:</hi>  Had sex last night with me sober and my wife high. It was interesting as I was wondering what that would be like earlier that day. She wanted to relax before sleep but I guess got horny in the middle of it as she didn't have any underwear and just wrapped her leg around me and started humping while smiling at me. We kissed a couple times but then she just got in doggy and we went at it like that for awhile. She was more wet initially than the first time but still not as wet as she usually gets. She quickly got wetter as we started going and stayed that way throughout. Never really changed position. Just speed, depth, stance etc. Honestly it wasn't that much different from normal sex other than I could tell she was in it a lot more. Just in that zone but because I was a bit inhibited due to my MIL staying that night I didn't really dive into what I wanted. Just focused on trying to get her off. Unfortunately it didn't happen. I actually kind of came a little during a really heated moment but not fully and kept going for a decent while until another really heated moment and then finally, fully came when I couldn't hold back. Mild though as I was still thrusting and trying to get her off but then "faked" the orgasm very shortly after when I knew she wasn't. I ended up staying inside her as she just rocked back and forth into me which felt really good. Very awesome visual and enjoyable to experience. After a good long while of that she finally stopped and laid down. She said that she could've gone forever. Like a rocking chair. Lol. Offered to get her vibrator and she said no in her relaxed state. She just laid there touching and caressing herself and I did the same to her. </p>
</sp>
</text>
