<text id="autogum_interview_doc000" title="part0_Wikinews interviews 2020 US Libertarian Party presidential candidate Adam Kokesh" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2019-09-01" dateModified="2019-09-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_2020_US_Libertarian_Party_presidential_candidate_Adam_Kokesh" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews 2020 US Libertarian Party presidential candidate Adam Kokesh</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 7, 2019</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adam%20Kokesh">Adam Kokesh</ref>, an <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iraq_War">Iraq War</ref> veteran, activist, radio show host, and currently a candidate for the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Libertarian_Party_(United_States)">US Libertarian Party</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2020_United_States_presidential_election">2020 presidential</ref> nomination, spoke with <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> to discuss his background, political positions, and campaign for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/President_of_the_United_States">President of the United States</ref>.</p>
<figure><caption>Adam Kokesh Image: The Adam Kokesh American Referendum Project.</caption></figure>
<p>Kokesh, who hails from Arizona, has been active in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anti-War%20movement">anti-war</ref> movement since returning home from combat in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iraq">Iraq</ref>.  After an initial honorary discharge from active duty with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/US%20Marine%20Corp">US Marine Corp</ref> in 2006, Kokesh was given a general discharge from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marine%20Forces%20Reserve">Marine Forces Reserve</ref> in 2007 after images of him wearing his uniform while participating in a protest with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraq%20Veterans%20Against%20the%20War">Iraq Veterans Against the War</ref> were published in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Washington_Post">The Washington Post</ref></hi>.  Kokesh has also been involved in demonstrations in support of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Free_speech">free speech</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Right_to_keep_and_bear_arms">gun rights</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decriminalization%20of%20non-medical%20cannabis%20in%20the%20United%20States">marijuana decriminalization</ref>.  Some of these activities have resulted in his arrest.  Kokesh previously hosted a show on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RT%20(TV%20network)">RT</ref> and currently hosts a show on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/internet%20radio">internet radio</ref>.</p>
<p>Politically, Kokesh supported the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ron%20Paul%202008%20presidential%20campaign">2008</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ron%20Paul%202012%20presidential%20campaign">2012 presidential campaigns</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ron_Paul">Ron Paul</ref>.  He was a featured speaker at Paul's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Campaign%20for%20Liberty#Rally_for_the_Republic">Rally for the Republic</ref> in 2008.  Kokesh ran for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_Congress">US Congress</ref> as a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(United_States)">Republican</ref> in 2010 in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_Mexico">New Mexico</ref> and for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_Senate">US Senate</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2018%20United%20States%20Senate%20election%20in%20Arizona">Arizona in 2018</ref>.  He announced his 2020 candidacy in 2013 during a jailhouse interview.  He has based his campaign on the pledge to begin "dissolving the federal government in a peaceful, orderly manner" and to resign as president and take the title of "Custodian of the Federal Government."  </p>
<p>Other contenders for the Libertarian Party's 2020 presidential nomination include former Libertarian Party Vice Chairman <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arvin%20Vohra">Arvin Vohra</ref>, businessman <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20McAfee">John McAfee</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_Hampshire">New Hampshire</ref> state representative <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Max%20Abramson">Max Abramson</ref>.  Congressman <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Justin%20Amash">Justin Amash</ref> and former <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Rhode_Island">Rhode Island</ref> governor and US Senator <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lincoln%20Chafee">Lincoln Chafee</ref> are both reportedly considering runs.  Former <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York_State">New York</ref> gubernatorial candidate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Larry%20Sharpe%20(politician)">Larry Sharpe</ref> and former <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Massachusetts">Massachusetts</ref> governor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William%20Weld">William Weld</ref> were both previously considered potential candidates but Sharpe suggested he would not run and Weld has decided to run in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2020%20Republican%20Party%20presidential%20primaries">2020 Republican Party presidential primaries</ref>, challenging President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Donald_Trump">Donald Trump</ref>.</p>
<p>With accredited <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> reporter William S. Saturn, Kokesh details his background and activism, his thoughts on the Libertarian Party, the Presidency of Donald Trump, and the goals for his campaign and presidency. </p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<head id="Background_&amp;_activism">Background &amp; activism</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Which presidential candidates have you supported and/or voted for in previous election cycles during your lifetime?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Kokesh</hi>: I turned 18 in the year 2000, but I was in training with the Marine Corps at the time of the election and did not pay much attention or vote. (I think politicians are smart to not encourage Marines to be active in politics. We generally have a low tolerance for bullshit.) In <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2004%20United%20States%20presidential%20election">2004</ref>, I voted for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael%20Badnarik">Michael Badnarik</ref> and supported him with my college Libertarian Party affiliate and representing him in a mock debate. In <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2008_United_States_presidential_election">2008</ref> I was very active with Iraq Veterans Against the War and actively supported Ron Paul. When he didn't win the nomination, I voted for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cynthia%20McKinney">Cynthia McKinney</ref> because Ron Paul endorsed her and I lived in Washington, DC where I wanted my vote to count towards ballot access for the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Green_Party_of_the_United_States">Green Party</ref>. In <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2012_United_States_presidential_election">2012</ref> I supported and voted for Ron Paul in the Republican primary and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gary_Johnson">Gary Johnson</ref> in the general. In <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2016_United_States_presidential_election">2016</ref> I supported Gary Johnson.</p>
</text>
