<text id="autogum_voyage_doc3" title="Iranian Azerbaijan" shortTile="iranian-azerbaijan" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=15715" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Iranian Azerbaijan</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Iranian Azerbaijan</hi> (<ref target="Persian%20phrasebook">Persian</ref> and <ref target="Azerbaijani%20phrasebook">Azerbaijani</ref>: آذربایجان) is in the extreme northwest of <ref target="Iran">Iran</ref>, by the border with the country and former Soviet Republic of <ref target="Azerbaijan">Azerbaijan</ref>.</p>
<head>Provincial capitals</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> - capital of Ardabil province.</item>
<item> — the biggest economic hub of Northwestern Iran, the most populated city in Iranian Azerbaijan, and the capital of East Azerbaijan province.</item>
<item> — capital of West Azerbaijan province.</item>
<item> - capital of Zanjan province.</item>
</list>


<head>Other major cities</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> </item>
<item> Jolfa - Border town with Nakhchivan exclave of Azerbaijan, but also a good base to visit the Armenian churches and the Aras Valley</item>
<item> - A good base for seeing the spectacular Babak Castle, and the Aras River Valley</item>
<item> — small village with houses carved in the rocks like in <ref target="Cappadocia">Cappadocia</ref>, <ref target="Turkey">Turkey</ref></item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> — Takht-e Soleyman, a Zoroastrian fire temple and a <ref target="UNESCO%20World%20Heritage%20List">UNESCO World Heritage site</ref>, is located nearby</item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> - A scenic valley on the northern border with stepped villages, mountain scenery, and ancient tombs</item>
</list>


<head>Understand</head>

<p>Iranian Azerbaijan is traditionally inhabited by Azeri people , an Iranian ethnic group that speaks a Turkic language , and Kurds, another group of Iranian peoples . The region's formation in its current borders dates back to Turkmanchay Treaty of 1828. By the treaty, Iran (Persia) ceded to Russia control of several Iranian Azerbaijani areas in the South Caucasus, which is now an independent country known as Azerbaijan Republic. The boundary between Russian Empire and Iran (Persia) was set at the Aras river. </p>

<p>This region, especially eastern parts of it, is probably one of the most beautiful places in Iran. The region is known for its friendly people, and also known for the great food.</p>

<p>Iranian Azerbaijan is comprised of four provinces: Ardabil, Zanjan, East Azerbaijan and West Azerbaijan.</p>

<head>Talk</head>
<p>Azeri people of Iran are mostly bilingual. They are fluent in their native language, Azeri, and also the official language of Iran, Persian. Kurds of this region, like most of Kurdish people in and out of Iran, can speak both Persian and Kurdish.</p>

<head>International airport</head>

<p>Tabriz International Airport is the only international airport in Iranian Azerbaijan. It has flights to some Iranian cities and to neighboring countries.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tabriz International Airport</hi> ( TBZ ) (10 km ftom the city center of <ref target="Tabriz">Tabriz</ref></item>
</list>

<p>). A regional hub with domestic flights to Tehran, Mashad, and some other major cities of Iran, and flights to some neighboring countries. </p>

<head>Domestic Airports</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Urmia Airport</hi> ( OMH ) (Northeast of <ref target="Urmia">Urmia</ref>.</item>
</list>

<p>). </p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ardabil Airport</hi> ( ADU ) (Northeast of <ref target="Ardabil">Ardabil</ref></item>
</list>

<p>). </p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Zanjan Airport</hi> ( JWN ) (Northwest of <ref target="Zanjan">Zanjan</ref></item>
</list>

<p>). </p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sahand Airport</hi> ( ACP ) (near <ref target="Maragheh">Maragheh</ref></item>
</list>

<p>). </p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>By the bridge over the Urmia lake Tabriz is reachable from <ref target="Urmia">Urmia</ref> in 1.5 hours.</p>

<head>By train</head>

<p>Some of the Iranian Azerbaijan cities have access to the railway includingː Tabriz, Maraghe, Salmas, and Jolfa.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tabriz Railway Station</hi>, Rah-Aahn Sq., Tabriz ( 5 km W of the city center of <ref target="Tabriz">Tabriz</ref></item>
</list>

<p>). Domestic trains: There are comfortable night trains from <ref target="Tabriz">Tabriz</ref> to <ref target="Tehran">Tehran</ref> (12 hr travel, 152,500 rials for 1-way ) passing <ref target="Maraghe">Maraghe</ref> (2 hr), <ref target="Zanjan">Zanjan</ref> (9 hr) and <ref target="Qazvin">Qazvin</ref>. There is a 2nd class sleeping train (6 people in one room) that leaves Tabriz at 20:30 and arrives to Tehran at 09:30. Price is 40,000 rials. The more comfortable choice is to take 1st class train for 170,000 rials. This train leaves at 17:30 and arrives to <ref target="Tehran">Tehran</ref> at 06:00. There are 4-bed rooms with TV and dinner is included in that price. To get the ticket you need to use some of travel agencies in the city or in the train station (this option only for recent day registration). There is a weekly train goes from Tehran to <ref target="Istanbul">Istanbul</ref> which has a stop in <ref target="Tabriz">Tabriz</ref>. For more info visit <ref target="http://www.Raja.ir">Iranian Passenger Railway</ref> or <ref target="http://www.Seat61.com">Seat61</ref>. International trains: Weekly train to/from Istanbul, twice a week to <ref target="Van">Van</ref>, see <ref target="http://www.tcdd.gov.tr/tcdding/ortadogu_ing.htm">Turkish Railway's site</ref> .</p>


<head>By bus</head>
<p>There are bus lines from Provincial Capitals: <ref target="Tabriz">Tabriz</ref>, <ref target="Ardabil">Ardabil</ref>, <ref target="Urmia">Urmia</ref>, and <ref target="Zanjan">Zanjan</ref> to major Iranian cities. There are minibus lines for connecting the smaller cities to the provincial capitals of Iranian Azerbaijan.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tabriz Main Bus Terminal</hi>, Niyayesh Blvd., Tabriz (S 3 km of city center), ☏ +98-41 34796091 .</item>
</list>


<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> The <ref target="UNESCO%20World%20Heritage%20site">UNESCO World Heritage site</ref> <hi rend="bold">Armenian Monastic Ensembles of Iran</hi>. It consists of three 7th century Armenian Christian buildings in the region — the monasteries of St. Thaddeus, St. Stepanos and the Chapel of Dzordzor.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Bonanb Kabab, a big skewer kabab with ingredient of local spices, onion and beef. It is named after city Bonab in south of Tabriz.</item>
<item> Chelo-Kabab, a dish of rice with ground beef kabab.</item>
<item> Kofte-e-Tabrizi, a big meatball with ingredient of ground beef, rice, and herbd.</item>
<item> Lighvan cheese, a domestic feta cheese from Liqvan village in south east of Tabriz.</item>
</list>
</text>
