<text id="autogum_interview_doc010" title="part1_Simple animals could live in Martian brines: Wikinews interviews planetary scientist Vlada Stamenković" shortTile="partsimple-animals" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2018-10-23" dateModified="2019-01-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Simple_animals_could_live_in_Martian_brines%3A_Wikinews_interviews_planetary_scientist_Vlada_Stamenkovi%C4%87" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Stamenković et al found oxygen levels throughout Mars would be high enough for the least demanding <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aerobic%20organism">aerobic</ref> (oxygen-using) microbes, for all the brines they considered, and all the methods of calculation. They published a detailed map<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Main_Page#Figure_3">[3]</ref> of the distributions of solubility for calcium perchlorates for their more optimistic calculations, which they reckoned were closer to the true case, with and without <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Supercooling">supercooling</ref>. The lowest concentrations were shown in the tropical southern uplands. Brine in regions poleward of about 67.5° to the north and about 72.5° to the south could have oxygen concentrations high enough for simple sponges. Closer to the poles, concentrations could go higher, approaching levels typical of sea water on Earth, 0.2 moles per cubic meter (6.4 mg per liter), for calcium perchlorates. On Earth, worms and clams that live in the muddy sea beds require 1 mg per liter, bottom feeders such as crabs and oysters 3 mg per liter, and spawning migratory fish 6 mg per liter, all within 0.2 moles per cubic meter, 6.4 mg per liter.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>   Does your paper's value of up to 0.2 moles of oxygen per cubic meter, the same as Earth's sea water, mean that there could potentially be life on Mars as active as our sea worms or even fish?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Stamenković</hi>: Mars is such a different place than the Earth and we still need to do so much more work before we can even start to speculate.</p>
<p>Stamenković et al studied magnesium and calcium perchlorates, common on Mars. They found the highest oxygen concentrations occur when the water is colder, which happens most in polar regions.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>   The temperatures for the highest levels of oxygen are really low, -133°C, so, is the idea that this oxygen would be retained when the brines warm up to more habitable temperatures during the day or seasonally? Or would the oxygen be lost as it warms up? Or — is the idea that it has to be some exotic biochemistry that works only at ultra low temperatures like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dirk%20Schulze-Makuch">Dirk Schulze-Makuch</ref>'s life based on hydrogen peroxide and perchlorates internal to the cells as antifreeze?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Stamenković</hi>: The options are both: first, cool oxygen-rich environments do not need to be habitats. They could be reservoirs packed with a necessary nutrient that can be accessed from a deeper and warmer region. Second, the major reason for limiting life at low temperature is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ice%20nucleation">ice nucleation</ref>, which would not occur in the type of brines that we study.</p>
<figure><caption>Varying tilt of Mars's axis over hundreds of thousands to millions of years. The current situation is a 25-degree tilt (top left). Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NASA">NASA</ref>/<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/JPL">JPL</ref>-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caltech">Caltech</ref>.</caption></figure><p>Stamenković et al's paper is theoretical and is based on a simplified general circulation model of the Mars atmosphere — it ignores distinctions of seasons and the day / night cycle. Stamenković's team combined it with a chemical model of how oxygen would dissolve in the brines and used this to predict oxygen levels in such brines at various locations on Mars. </p>
</text>
