<text id="autogum_bio_doc002" title="Christopher C. Horner" shortTile="christopher-c-horner" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-12-25" dateModified="2019-10-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_C._Horner" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Christopher C. Horner</head><p><hi rend="bold">Christopher C. Horner</hi> is an attorney in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Washington,_D.C.">Washington, D.C.</ref> and a Senior Fellow at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Competitive_Enterprise_Institute">Competitive Enterprise Institute</ref> who opposes the mainstream view of climate change and has been prominent in promoting <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Climate_change_denial">climate change denial</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Dunlap_Jaques-1">[1]</ref> He is the author of three books disputing the scientific evidence for man-made <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Global_warming">global warming</ref>. Horner had a financial relationship with coal companies who provided him with funds.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-fang-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-abrams-3">[3]</ref> Horner has been criticized for hounding climate scientists with frivolous requests for documentation and emails.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-fang-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-abrams-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Horner has represented CEI as well as  Members of the U.S. House and Senate on matters of environmental policy in the federal courts, including the Supreme Court. He has written on numerous topics in publications such as law reviews, legal and industrial trade journals, and opinion pages.  He is the author of four books.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">The Liberal War on Transparency</hi> (2012)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Power Grab: How Obama's Green Policies Will Steal Your Freedom and Bankrupt America</hi> (2010)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Red Hot Lies: How Global Warming Alarmists Use Threats, Fraud, and Deception to Keep You Misinformed</hi> (2008)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">The Politically Incorrect Guide to Global Warming (and Environmentalism)</hi> (2007)</item></list>
<p><hi rend="italic">The Politically Incorrect Guide</hi> was on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_York_Times_Bestseller_list">New York Times Bestseller list</ref> (paperback nonfiction) from March to October 2007.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>Horner has testified before the U.S. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Senate_Committee_on_Foreign_Relations">Senate Committee on Foreign Relations</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Senate_Committee_on_Environment_and_Public_Works">Senate Committee on Environment and Public Works</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> and works on a legal and policy level with numerous think tanks and policy organizations throughout the world. He has given numerous addresses to audiences in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/European_Parliament">European Parliament</ref> in Strasbourg and Brussels, and before policymakers in European capitals including London, Rome, Prague, Copenhagen, Madrid, and Warsaw; topics range from rail deregulation and unfunded pension liability to energy and environment issues. He has provided legal, policy, and political commentary several hundred times each on both television and radio, in the United States, Europe, Canada, and Australia, including on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fox_News_Channel">Fox News Channel</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Court_TV">Court TV</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MSNBC">MSNBC</ref> (with repeat visits on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_News_Hour_with_Jim_Lehrer">The News Hour with Jim Lehrer</ref>), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BBC">BBC</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CNN">CNN</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CNN_International">CNN International</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ITN">ITN</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canadian_Broadcasting_Corporation">CBC</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bloomberg_Television">Bloomberg</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reuters_Television">Reuters Television</ref>.</p>
<p>Horner "has been instrumental in orchestrating the attacks on climate scientists over the past decade in the form of vexatious and frivolous <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freedom_of_Information_Act_(United_States)">FOIA</ref> demands, efforts to force scientists to turn over all of their personal email," said <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_E._Mann">Michael Mann</ref>, a climate scientist targeted by Horner.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-abrams-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Horner received his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juris_Doctorate">Juris Doctorate</ref> from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Washington_University_in_St._Louis">Washington University in St. Louis</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<head>Coal company support</head>
<p>In 2015, bankruptcy court documents for the coal company <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alpha_Natural_Resources">Alpha Natural Resources</ref> revealed Horner was privately funded by grants sent to his home address.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-fang-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-abrams-3">[3]</ref> In early June 2015, the Coal &amp; Investment Leadership Forum, a trade show, sent a message to its email list confirming coal industry support of Horner:</p>
<p>As the ‘<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War_on_coal">war on coal</ref>’ continues, I trust that the commitment we have made to support Chris Horner’s work will eventually create great awareness of the illegal tactics being employed to pass laws that are intended to destroy our industry.</p>
<p>The email was signed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alliance_Resource_Partners">Alliance Resource Partners</ref> Joe Craft III, Alpha Natural Resources Kevin Crutchfield, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drummond_Company">Drummond Company</ref>'s Gary Drummond, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arch_Coal">Arch Coal</ref>'s John Eaves and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_Coal_Co.">United Coal Co.</ref>'s Jim McGlothlin.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-fang-2">[2]</ref></p>
</text>
