<text id="autogum_interview_doc003" title="part3_Wikinews interviews 2020 US Libertarian Party presidential candidate Adam Kokesh" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2019-09-01" dateModified="2019-09-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_2020_US_Libertarian_Party_presidential_candidate_Adam_Kokesh" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="On_the_presidency_of_Donald_Trump">On the presidency of Donald Trump</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What qualities of President Donald Trump and his presidency do you admire?  What qualities do you despise?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Kokesh</hi>: I admire Trump's ability to tap into a very powerful part of the <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/zeitgeist">zeitgeist</ref> that lived in a lot of Americans who felt under-represented for a long time. I despise the attitude of meanness and divisiveness, although I recognize how that was connected to the sentiment that got him elected and he has to keep stoking that negativity until he can get people on more positive message. This brings with it an attitude of combativeness that is uncapitalistic. Even in the competition of capitalism, the ground rules include fundamental standards of cooperation. You compete to produce the most value, usually through cooperation, not steal or swindle so you can have the most stuff. I guess I should make this a compliment sandwich and end by saying that I also admire the very natural skin tone of his eyelids.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What actions of President Trump do you support?  What actions do you disapprove?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Kokesh</hi>: Of course if I look at all the little things, I could probably find lots of things that I support that Trump is doing, but there aren't any major policy initiatives of his I could get behind. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tax%20Cuts%20and%20Jobs%20Act%20of%202017">tax "cuts"</ref> sounded good, but without cuts in government spending, it's almost entirely just a reshuffling of who is paying for what exactly and most times government changes the tax code it's for the benefit of its sponsors at the expense of working-class taxpayers. The only legitimate borders for enforcement of anything are private property borders so I can't support a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trump%20wall">wall</ref> or any immigration policy that limits individual freedom of movement, limited only by not violating others' property where you're not welcome. I don't support <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trump%20tariffs">tariffs</ref> because they're just another form of taxation and taxation is theft. The main things I support about Trump are the things he's not doing. He hasn't invaded any new countries, (that we know of) he hasn't been pushing for the right to torture people, he hasn't tried to make cannabis less legal. I wonder how many of those types of things are worth giving him credit for, or are things he would do if he could get away with it in the age of the (now somewhat matured) internet.</p>
<head id="Goals">Goals</head>
<figure><caption>Kokesh speaking at a campaign event in 2018.Image: The Adam Kokesh American Referendum Project.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">As President Trump learned early in his presidency, federal courts can effectively nullify controversial executive orders.  If you are elected president, what will you do in the event a federal court rules your executive order creating a process to dissolve the federal government as unconstitutional?</hi></p>
</text>
