<text id="autogum_bio_doc007" title="Domenico Prattichizzo" shortTile="domenico-prattichizzo" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-04-10" dateModified="2019-08-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domenico_Prattichizzo" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Domenico Prattichizzo</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Domenico Prattichizzo</hi> is an Italian scientist with a strong and international recognized expertise in the fields of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haptic_technology">Haptics</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robotics">Robotics</ref> and, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wearable_technology">Wearable technology</ref>. His researches find their main applications in virtual and augmented reality scenarios and in the rehabilitation of people with upper and lower limbs, visual and cognitive impairments.</p>
<p>He is Full Professor of Robotics and Automation at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Siena">University of Siena</ref>, Senior Scientist at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Istituto_Italiano_di_Tecnologia">Istituto Italiano di Tecnologia</ref> in Genoa and Co-founder of WEART,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> a startup on Wearable Haptics and Tactile Communication.</p>
<p>He has been elevated Fellow of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Institute_of_Electrical_and_Electronics_Engineers">the Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers</ref> (IEEE) in 2016<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> <hi rend="italic">for contributions to haptics and multi-fingered robotic hands</hi>.</p>
<head>Education</head>
<p>In 1991 he obtained the Master of Science in Electronic Engineering at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Pisa">University of Pisa</ref>. In 1994–1995 he has been Visiting Scientist at the Artificial Intelligence Lab of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Massachusetts_Institute_of_Technology">Massachusetts Institute of Technology</ref> in Cambridge, MA, USA and in 1995 he got the PhD in Robotics and Automation at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Pisa">University of Pisa</ref>.</p>
<head>Research</head>
<p>Prattichizzo has contributed and is particularly active in the fields of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haptic_technology">Haptics</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robotics">Robotics</ref> with a special focus on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wearable_technology">Wearable technology</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Human-robot_interaction">Human-robot interaction</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rehabilitation_robotics">Rehabilitation robotics</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virtual_reality">Virtual reality</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Augmented_Reality">Augmented Reality</ref>.</p>
<p>From 2013 to 2017 he has been the Coordinator of the EU FP7 Collaborative Project "WEARHAP: WEARable HAPtics for Humans and Robots", involving 11 European research centers.</p>
<p>In addition he led the research unit in several H2020 and FP7 EU projects ("SoftPro: Synergy-based Open-source Foundations and Technologies for Prosthetics and RehabilitatiOn", "SoMa: Soft-bodied intelligence for Manipulation", "ACANTO: A CyberphysicAl social NeTwOrk using robot friends", "DALi: Devices for Assisted Living", "THE: The Hand Embodied", "ECHORD-European Clearing House for Open Robotics Development", "ROBOCAST: ROBot and SENSors INtegration as Guidance FOR Enhanced Computer Assisted Surgery and Therapy") and international projects (2015 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intuitive_Surgical">Intuitive Surgical</ref> Technology Research Grant  "Comparison of cutaneous feedback methods for pinching palpation in robotic surgery", 2014 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mathworks">Mathworks</ref> Education Award for developing the MOOC "The Art of Grasping and Manipulation in Robotics", 2007 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IEEE">IEEE</ref> RAS New Initiative Grants "Establishing IEEE/RAS Points of Presence and Initiatives in Second Life".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>He coordinated “Remotouch”,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> selected as one of the projects to represent Innovation Italy at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Expo_2010_Shanghai_China">Expo 2010 Shanghai China</ref> within the program “Italia degli Innovatori”.</p>
<p>He is author of more than 350 peer-reviewed papers in the areas of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robotics">Robotics</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haptic_technology">Haptics</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Human-robot_interaction">Human-robot interaction</ref>.</p>
<p>The outcomes of his research generated several patents.</p>
<head>Scientific Leadership</head>
<p>He is President of the Eurohaptics Society <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> and Member of the Technical Board of ARTES 4.0, Advanced Robotics and enabling digital Technologies &amp; Systems,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> one of the highest level tech hub in Italy to accelerate innovation. He has been Chair of the IEEE RAS Italian Chapter <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> from 2006 to 2010, awarded with the RAS Chapter of the Year Award <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> in 2009.</p>
<p>He has been appointed as Area Chair of the conference Robotics Science and Systems (RSS) in 2014 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> and 2015 and as Chair and Plenary/Keynote speaker in many international conferences.</p>
<p>From 2007 to 2013 he has been Co-Editor in Chief of the journal IEEE Transactions on Haptics <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> and he is currently Associate Editor of the journal Frontiers in Robotics and AI, section Biomedical Robotics.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref></p>
</text>
