<text id="autogum_reddit_doc008" title="How realistic?" shortTile="how-realistic" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-05-31" dateModified="2018-05-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8nn9q1" speakerList="#ChazzyJoe, #thrillhouse429" speakerCount="2">
<head>How realistic?</head>
<sp who="#thrillhouse429">
<p>As someone who went to school in the UK, (I'm 22 now so being 17/18 was a while ago for me), just a general question to those who go to school in the US or who have been at school in the US being around 17. How realistic is school life portrayed on the show? In my school, school sports was never a big thing so we never had the groups of sports people and groups of "nerds and jocks" and stuff- sometimes the way they have the cliques of popular girls and not popular groups of people just doesn't seem realistic to me and just seems like something they exaggerate for tv. Similarly, groups of people like Cyrus and his friends, the 'dyed black hair, eyeliner, super rebellious' type also seems like a huge cliche to me, I mean we definitely had 'alternative' people in our school but never on the level that Cyrus was. I understand the tough guy sports dynamic though, I'm in uni at the moment and even though sports again isn't a huge thing, we have the typical 'football/rugby guy' stereotype, tough guy, not always the nicest to girls, but sometimes the way the guys are shown on the show and even some of the things they say just sound a bit cringey to me. Again, not trying to mock anyone or any type of person, just asking how realistic it is coming from a school in the UK.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#ChazzyJoe">
<p>As always, and this may sound like a cop out, it depends. </p>
<p> </p>
<p>Speaking from my own experience I could relate to some of the  <hi rend="bold">individuals</hi>  that people in the show dealt with, but I did not feel that high school in 13RW was representative of my own experience. </p>
<p> </p>
<p>High school (and education at large) in the United States can vary  <hi rend="bold">a lot</hi>  depending not only where you grew up, but the size of the school as well. For example, I went to a relatively small high school in New England where the social groups tended to overlap a lot and thus those stereotypes cliques you pointed out didn't really exist. On the other hand, sometimes larger high schools can have these more segregated groups to some extent. </p>
<p> </p>
<p>In short I would say at best 13RW is a snapshot of one high school experience. It is far from universal or the standard across the US.</p>
</sp>
</text>
