<text id="autogum_interview_doc002" title="part2_Wikinews interviews 2020 US Libertarian Party presidential candidate Adam Kokesh" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2019-09-01" dateModified="2019-09-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_2020_US_Libertarian_Party_presidential_candidate_Adam_Kokesh" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="On_the_Libertarian_Party">On the Libertarian Party</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why did you join the Libertarian Party?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Kokesh</hi>: I joined the Libertarian Party first in my mind in high school because at some point I was given the choice between being a Republican or <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Democratic_Party_(United_States)">Democrat</ref> and thought, "Wait a second! This is America! I'm supposed to have a choice, right? I don't have to be lame, do I?" Fortunately, I found the LP, but at first, mainly because I thought pretty much every politician I'd ever seen on TV was a crooked asshole. (I had never seen a Libertarian on TV at that point. It's still rare!) It wasn't until reading Rothbard about ten years later that I came to understand what the party and the philosophy were really all about.</p>
<figure><caption>Kokesh in 2013. Image: Gage Skidmore.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">In 2016, the Libertarian Party's presidential nominee Gary Johnson received 3.28 percent of the popular vote, the most of any previous Libertarian presidential nominee.  What can you do as the party's nominee to increase the vote share? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Kokesh</hi>: For the last three election cycles, the LP has pursued the losing strategy of hiding behind someone who we like and we think others will like, but doesn't represent what we believe. It's time for the LP to elect a libertarian again. If we can do this — it doesn't matter if it's me or any of the other great potential nominees — we're going to win a lot more votes! As for me personally, I think my advantages are that I'm good at making the message easy to understand and relate to, I have a broad base of existing support and name ID, and being a combat veteran gives me a unique advantage in challenging militarism, which is something our movement has struggled with. More importantly, I think there's something very inauthentic in saying, "You should be free! But this guy should be your President!" My platform of the peaceful, orderly, and responsible dissolution of the federal government in which I resign on day one is the only one right now that addresses this problem and is in line with libertarian principles. This strategy of uniting under the principles of localization rather than fighting for ideology is how we (in the long term if only starting in 2020) build a winning coalition of independents, non-voters, and reluctant old party voters, to WIN not just get more votes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What are your thoughts on your fellow candidates and potential candidates for the Libertarian Party's 2020 presidential nomination, specifically, former Vice Chairman Arvin Vohra, former New York gubernatorial candidate Larry Sharpe, and former Massachusetts Governor William Weld?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Kokesh</hi>: I haven't yet met a potential nominee for the LP that I didn't like! Having been to a handful of state conventions now with other candidates, I can say it's really beautiful how we've come to think of ourselves as a team seeking to do what's best for the cause and the party. I'd like to see more qualified candidates run who can bring more people into the party. I'll just mention one by name, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Vermin_Supreme">Vermin Supreme</ref>, who I'm happy to see has been embraced by the LP as a kind of jester candidate. I want people on stage beside me who represent the message well and make it easy for people who need that personal connection to have someone they can relate to. Everyone who would stand with the LP can relate to being a jester and wanting to laugh while giving the man the finger!</p>
</text>
