<text id="autogum_reddit_doc000" title="Does anyone else's depression manifest in extreme fatigue and complete lack of motivation?" shortTile="anyone-s-depression" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-05-31" dateModified="2018-05-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8nj21e" speakerList="#Idiotecka, #OFGhost" speakerCount="2">
<head>Does anyone else's depression manifest in extreme fatigue and complete lack of motivation?</head>
<sp who="#OFGhost">
<p>I've struggled with depression and anxiety for years. I've gone to two different therapists now (currently on my second therapist), and a psychiatrist who has diagnosed me with major depression and generalized anxiety. Sometimes I feel like I would be better off dead. I'm sad a lot of the time, weepy sometimes, and struggle with anxiety and panic episodes off and on. I also deal with obsessive thoughts and emotions. I feel like my depression is a bit different from others on this sub, though, and was wondering if anyone else can relate and offer me advice. I am exhausted  <hi rend="bold">constantly.</hi>  Even when I sleep 8-10 hours, I'm still falling asleep at work the next day and feel like I need a long nap. When I sleep for more than 10 hours or less than 8, I'm even more exhausted. I feel like I just want to sleep every day away. I'm also completely lacking in motivation. I will sit around all day at home when I'm not working just mindlessly browsing the internet, feeling no motivation or desire to get out of the house, hang out with friends, play games, clean the house, or anything. I have to force myself to do anything, and I'm so mind-numbingly bored all the time, yet I do nothing about it. I feel like my life is going nowhere, and I'm destined to be miserable forever. I'm also extremely irritable and hate all people. I feel like an asshole for admitting this, but it's how I honestly feel. When I want to be left alone and people talk to me, I will become very irritable, snap, or feel incredibly anxious. Some of my obsessive thoughts revolve around my disdain for people. I find myself repeating negative thoughts about other people or myself over and over in my head, especially when I'm stuck in a conversation that I don't want to be in. I "talk to myself" in my head pretty much, and I can't control it. I feel like I'm going a bit crazy, haha. A few years ago I was put on lexapro for depression/anxiety, and it made me even more tired. I was recently put on Prozac, and that also made me exhausted, so now I've been switched to Pristiq. I don't seem  <hi rend="bold">as</hi>  exhausted on Pristiq, but I also haven't noticed any mood lift or a change in thought patterns or anything. I'm unsure where to go from here. Nothing seems to work, and I hate therapy. I feel so uncomfortable going. I have had feelings of superiority and grandeur in the past and have had problems with impulse control, substance abuse, and feeling "high on life," which makes me wonder if I could be bipolar, but I don't think I've ever experienced what they call mania or hypomania. Can anyone relate to this or offer up some advice?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#Idiotecka">
<p>raising my hand here. exercise, therapy, meds, even weed.. it all helps but i can't seem to fucking get to a level where things are steady. and i have been working on myself a lot in the last few years.. i've done great progress. i guess it's a matter of keeping my head down and soldiering on, but man.. it's fucking exhausting. </p>
<p>also i'm pretty sure my sleep is pretty bad. i've been wanting to go to a sleep clinic for quite a while but never really mustered the courage to actually go.</p>
</sp>
</text>
