<text id="autogum_reddit_doc003" title="Vanessa vs Paul" shortTile="vanessa-vs-paul" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-05-31" dateModified="2018-05-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8nlbf1" speakerList="#Zamoqaq, #thorfist7373" speakerCount="2">
<head>Vanessa vs Paul</head>
<sp who="#Zamoqaq">
<p>I understand most people on this sub feel Vanessa is a better player and/or just have a strong disliking for Paul, but in my opinion I believe Paul is the better player. Of course, he did lose twice in back to back seasons, but it's important to remember he got there in two seasons. (however although one of them was with vets, the other featured a weaker cast.) His weak point is unarguably his jury management. However even in this department, he wasn't that bad proven by the fact that he got 4 jury votes in both seasons. Good players can get to the end, which Vanessa wasn't able to do whilst Paul got to the end by winning final HOH and making sure Josh took him. Additionally, even if Vanessa was to get to the end with Steve, there is no guarantee she would have won. Steve already had 4 votes locked up (Austwins due to bitterness plus JMac.) It just took one more vote for Steve to win. However, even though BB19 had a weaker cast, the way Paul absolutely dominated the game and dictated everything from start to finish was masterful, and the fact that he did it in two seasons(although not to the same degree) just solidifies himself as a better player in my opinion. He also played to different games in both seasons, (one from the bottom and one from the top) which increases my opinion of him as a player. Feel free to disagree:) My viewpoint might be slightly extreme in believing he is a top 5 player but I also believe that Paul is extremely underrated on this sub due to the overwhelming dislike towards him. I understand the dislike (although I dont share it) but I dont think it should affect our judgement of him as a player. </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#thorfist7373">
<p>I think you make valid points, however I do disagree. </p>
<p>1. the jury management was blatantly bad. He was shit talking Natalie for no reason after she promised him her vote, then he played a 2nd time and he did absolutely no better, constantly shit talking everyone. Yes he got 4 9 votes each time, but the mistakes were so glaringly obvious and, especially after losing BB18 he should've corrected them. </p>
<p>2. Vanessa was one comp away from winning bb17, a season which she dominated far more on her rookie season than Paul dominated bb18 during his rookie season. </p>
<p>3. Paul played the most dominant game ever on BB19, but it was against the worst cast ever. Against that cast, I think there are a ton of players including Vanessa who could've crushed it and won, which Paul was unable to do. </p>
</sp>
</text>
