<text id="autogum_interview_doc009" title="part0_Simple animals could live in Martian brines: Wikinews interviews planetary scientist Vlada Stamenković" shortTile="partsimple-animals" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2018-10-23" dateModified="2019-01-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Simple_animals_could_live_in_Martian_brines%3A_Wikinews_interviews_planetary_scientist_Vlada_Stamenkovi%C4%87" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Simple animals could live in Martian brines: Wikinews interviews planetary scientist Vlada Stamenković</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 9, 2019</hi></p>
<p>Planetary scientist Vlada Stamenković of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NASA">NASA</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jet_Propulsion_Laboratory">Jet Propulsion Laboratory</ref> and colleagues have developed a new chemical model of how oxygen dissolves in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mars">Martian</ref> conditions, which raises the possibility of oxygen-rich brines; enough, the work suggests, to support simple animals such as sponges. The model was published in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nature%20(journal)">Nature</ref></hi> on October 22. <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> caught up with him in an email interview to find out more about his team's research and their plans for the future.</p>
<figure><caption>Dr. Vlada StamenkovićImage: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jet_Propulsion_Laboratory">JPL</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atmosphere%20of%20Mars">atmosphere of Mars</ref>  is far too thin for humans to breathe or for lungs like ours to extract any oxygen at all. It has on average only around 0.6% of the pressure of Earth's atmosphere, and this is mainly carbon dioxide; only 0.145% of the thin Martian atmosphere is oxygen. The new model indicated these minute traces of oxygen should be able to enter salty seeps of water on or near the planet's surface at levels high enough to support life forms comparable to Earth's microbes, possibly even simple <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/sponge%20(organism)">sponges</ref>.  Some life forms can survive without oxygen, but oxygen permits more energy-intensive metabolism. Almost all complex multicellular life on Earth depends on oxygen.</p>
<p>"We were absolutely flabbergasted [...] I went back to recalculate everything like five different times to make sure it's a real thing," Stamenković told <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National%20Geographic">National Geographic</ref></hi>.</p>
<p>"Our work is calling for a complete revision for how we think about the potential for life on Mars, and the work oxygen can do," he told <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scientific%20American">Scientific American</ref></hi>, "implying that if life ever existed on Mars it might have been breathing oxygen".</p>
<figure><caption>File photo of Halichondria panicea, or the breadcrumb sponge, a simple sponge with low oxygen requirements. Image: <ref target="https://www.flickr.com/people/minette_layne/">Minette Layne</ref> (flickr).</caption></figure><p> Stamenković et al cite research from 2014 showing some simple sponges can survive with only 0.002 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mole%20(unit)">moles</ref> of oxygen per cubic meter (0.064 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/milligram">mg</ref> per <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/litre">liter</ref>). Some microbes that need oxygen can survive with as little as a millionth of a mole per cubic meter (0.000032 mg per liter). In their model, they found there can be enough oxygen for microbes throughout Mars, and enough for simple sponges in oases near the poles.</p>
<p>In 2014, also suggesting multicellular life could exist on Mars, de Vera et al, using the facilities at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/German%20Aerospace%20Center">German Aerospace Center</ref> (DLR), studied some <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/lichen">lichens</ref>, including <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pleopsidium%20chlorophanum">Pleopsidium chlorophanum</ref></hi>, which can grow high up in Antarctic mountain ranges. They showed those lichens can also survive and even grow in Mars simulation chambers. The lichens can do this because their algal component is able to produce the oxygen needed by the fungal component. Stamenković et al's research provides a way for oxygen to get into the Martian brines without algae or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/photosynthesis">photosynthesis</ref>.</p>
</text>
