<text id="autogum_wikinews_doc280" title="UEFA Champions League 2015-2016: Lewandowski scores twice in group stage match against Dinamo Zagreb">
<head>UEFA Champions League 2015-2016: Lewandowski scores twice in group stage match against Dinamo Zagreb</head>
  

<p>On Wednesday, <ref target="Germany">German</ref> football club <ref target="Bayern%20Munich">Bayern Munich</ref> defeated <ref target="Croatia">Croatian</ref> football club <ref target="w:GNK%20Dinamo%20Zagreb">Dinamo Zagreb</ref> in a <ref target="w:UEFA%20Champions%20League">UEFA Champions League</ref> group stage match played <ref target="w:Stadion%20Maksimir">Stadion Maksimir</ref> , <ref target="w:Zagreb">Zagreb</ref> . </p>

<p>Bayern had a greater ball possession. The match saw three <ref target="w:yellow%20card%20%28association%20football%29">yellow cards</ref> , all for the home side. A total of 16 fouls were committed in the match. Zagreb defender <ref target="w:Gon%C3%A7alo%20Santos">Gonçalo Santos</ref> was the first man to be booked for committing a foul on Lewandowski in the 31 minute and Munich won a free kick. <ref target="w:Xabi%20Alonso">Xabi Alonso</ref> took the kick but it was just wide. First half ended in 0&ndash;0.</p>
<p>In the second half, <ref target="w:Thomas%20M%C3%BCller">Thomas Müller</ref> was substituted in for <ref target="w:Franck%20Rib%C3%A9ry">Franck Ribéry</ref> in the 47 minute. Later, in the 61 minute, Thomas Müller assisted <ref target="w:Robert%20Lewandowski">Robert Lewandowski</ref> and he scored a header, making it 1&ndash;0 lead for the visitors. Lewandowski doubled the lead in the 64 minute, assisted by <ref target="w:Sebastian%20Rode">Sebastian Rode</ref> .</p>

<ref target="w:Josip%20Pivari%C4%87">Josip Pivarić</ref> was yellow carded in the 73 minute. In the 87 minute, <ref target="w:Eduardo%20Carvalho">Eduardo Carvalho</ref> was yellow carded for bringing down Arturo Vidal in the penalty area. Bayern won a penalty kick, but Müller hit the woodwork. The match ended 0&ndash;2 
<p>while Bayern had already qualified for the next stage.</p>

<p>Bayern Munich and <ref target="Arsenal%20F.C.">Arsenal</ref> advanced to the Last 16 knockout stage of <ref target="w:2015%E2%80%9316%20UEFA%20Champions%20League">2015–16 UEFA Champions League</ref> . </p>

<p>Zagreb ended fourth in the table and their European journey for this season ended. <ref target="Greece">Greek</ref> <ref target="w:Olympiacos%20F.C.">Olympiacos</ref> , being third in the table after 3&ndash;0 defeat at home by Arsenal moved to <ref target="w:UEFA%20Europa%20League">UEFA Europa League</ref> . </p>



 
<head>Sources</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> "<ref target="http://www.goal.com/en-india/match/dinamo-zagreb-vs-bayern-m%25C3%25BCnchen/2146839/live-commentary%3FICID%3DMP_MS_3">Dinamo Zagreb 0 - 2 Bayern Münichen LIVE Commentary</ref>" — <ref target="w:Goal.com">Goal.com</ref> , December 10, 2015</item>
<item> <ref target="w:Reuters">Reuters</ref>. "<ref target="http://www.theguardian.com/football/2015/dec/09/dinamo-zagreb-bayern-munich-champions-league-match-report">Robert Lewandowski helps Bayern Munich ease past Dinamo Zagreb</ref>" — <ref target="w:The%20Guardian">The Guardian</ref> , December 9, 2015</item>
</list>
</text>
