<text id="autogum_wikinews_doc312" title="Barça defeats Gary Neville's Valencia 7-0 in Copa del Rey semis first leg">
<head>Barça defeats Gary Neville's Valencia 7-0 in Copa del Rey semis first leg</head>
  

<p>On Wednesday, <ref target="FC%20Barcelona">FC Barcelona</ref> defeated <ref target="w:Valencia%20CF">Valencia CF</ref> 7&ndash;0 in the first leg of the <ref target="w:Copa%20del%20Rey">Copa del Rey</ref> semi-final at <ref target="w:Camp%20Nou">Camp Nou</ref> . <ref target="Lionel%20Messi">Lionel Messi</ref> netted three goals and <ref target="Uruguay">Uruguyan</ref> striker <ref target="w:Luis%20Su%C3%A1rez">Luis Suárez</ref> netted four. </p>

<p>The <ref target="Catalonia">Catalans</ref>, Barcelona, have now scored more than 100 goals this season, and have not been defeated in the league since October, winning their last 27 games overall. <ref target="w:Gary%20Neville">Gary Neville</ref> , who became Valencia's manager in December, has yet to win a league game, and the team have not won any of their last eleven <ref target="La%20Liga">La Liga</ref> matches.</p>

<p>Barcelona had greater ball possession in the match. Five <ref target="w:yellow%20card%20%28association%20football%29">yellow cards</ref> and one <ref target="w:red%20card%20%28association%20football%29">red card</ref> were shown.</p>

<ref target="w:Neymar">Neymar</ref> assisted Suárez for the opening goal of the match in the 7 minute. Five minutes later, <ref target="w:Aleix%20Vidal">Aleix Vidal</ref> assisted Suárez, who netted the second goal, Barcelona's 100th goal this season. Valencia were trailing 2&ndash;0 with less than a quarter of an hour played. Just before the half-hour mark, Neymar flicked on for Messi to score the team's third. Valencia's captain <ref target="w:Shkodran%20Mustafi">Shkodran Mustafi</ref> was sent off late in the first half for a foul on Messi in the penalty box, but <ref target="w:Neymar">Neymar</ref> missed the resulting penalty, hitting the post.

<p>Messi scored from an assist by Suárez in the 58 and completed his <ref target="wikt:hat-trick">hat-trick</ref> in the 74 minute, to put the visitors 5&ndash;0 down. Suárez scored from a header in the 83 minute, assisted by <ref target="w:Adriano%20%28footballer%2C%20born%201984%29">Adriano</ref> and then in the 88 minute, he converted <ref target="w:Arda%20Turan">Arda Turan</ref> 's assist, giving Barcelona a comfortable win.</p>



 
<head>Sources</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Alex Young. "<ref target="http://www.goal.com/en-india/match/barcelona-vs-valencia/2196367%3FICID%3DRE">Barcelona 7 - 0 Valencia Match Report</ref>" — <ref target="w:Goal.com">Goal.com</ref> , February 4, 2016</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.goal.com/en-india/match/barcelona-vs-valencia/2196367/live-commentary%3FICID%3DMP_MS_3">Barcelona 7 - 0 Valencia LIVE Commentary</ref>" — <ref target="w:Goal.com">Goal.com</ref> , February 4, 2016</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.bbc.com/sport/football/35463999">Barcelona 7 - 0 Valencia</ref>" — <ref target="w:BBC%20Sport">BBC Sport</ref> , February 3, 2016</item>
</list>
</text>
