<text id="autogum_wikinews_doc317" title="Blanc extends contract with Paris Saint-Germain by two years">
<head>Blanc extends contract with Paris Saint-Germain by two years</head>
  

<ref target="w:Paris%20Saint-Germain">Paris Saint-Germain</ref> (PSG) <ref target="soccer">football</ref> manager <ref target="w:Laurent%20Blanc">Laurent Blanc</ref> has signed a two-year contract extension with the <ref target="France">French</ref> <ref target="w:Ligue%201">Ligue 1</ref> winners.

<p>Blanc joined the <ref target="Paris">Paris</ref> side in 2013, and helped them win consecutive titles in Ligue 1 and one domestic treble last season. Blanc took control of the club when <ref target="Italy">Italian</ref> <ref target="w:Carlo%20Ancelotti">Carlo Ancelotti</ref> joined <ref target="Real%20Madrid">Real Madrid</ref> and won the <ref target="UEFA%20Champions%20League">UEFA Champions League</ref> title with them.</p>
<p>The contract extension means 50-year-old Blanc would be at the capital club till June 2018. "Of course, it's a strong show of faith," PSG's website quoted his remarks, "and I'm very happy, also for my staff. A coach is nothing without his staff." </p>

<p>Blanc was in the French squad of 1998, when they won the <ref target="w:FIFA%20World%20Cup">World Cup</ref> . Under him, PSG reached the Champions League quarter-finals twice, and the French national team reached the <ref target="w:Euro%202012">Euro 2012</ref> quarter-finals as well.</p>

<p>Currently, PSG are 24 points ahead of <ref target="w:AS%20Monaco">AS Monaco</ref> as league toppers, without a single defeat and is to face <ref target="Chelsea%20F.C.">Chelsea F.C.</ref> in the <ref target="UEFA%20Champions%20League">UEFA Champions League</ref> round of <hi rend="italic">Last 16</hi>. </p>

<p>Blanc previously managed <ref target="w:FC%20Girondins%20de%20Bordeaux">Bordeaux</ref> and won the league with them.</p>



 
<head>Sources</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="w:Press%20Association">Press Association</ref>. "<ref target="http://www.theguardian.com/football/2016/feb/11/laurent-blanc-two-year-contract-extension-paris-saint-germain">Laurent Blanc signs two-year contract extension at PSG</ref>" — <ref target="w:The%20Guardian">The Guardian</ref> , February 11, 2016</item>
<item> Liam Prenderville. "<ref target="http://www.mirror.co.uk/sport/football/news/psg-boss-laurent-blanc-signs-7349833">PSG boss Laurent Blanc signs two-year contract extension with Ligue 1 champions</ref>" — <ref target="w:Mirror.co.uk">Mirror.co.uk</ref> , February 11, 2016</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.bbc.com/sport/football/35547918">Laurent Blanc: Paris St-Germain boss extends his contract</ref>" — <ref target="w:BBC%20Sport">BBC Sport</ref> , February 11, 2016</item>
</list>
</text>
