<text id="autogum_wikinews_doc47" title="Ian Holloway sacked as manager of Millwall F.C.">
<head>Ian Holloway sacked as manager of Millwall F.C.</head>
  
<ref target="w:Ian%20Holloway">Ian Holloway</ref> has been sacked as manager of <ref target="w:Millwall%20F.C.">Millwall football club</ref> . His sacking, announced on Tuesday, has come after a 1&ndash;4 defeat to <ref target="w:Norwich%20City%20F.C">Norwich City F.C</ref> . on March 7. He had managed Millwall since January 2014. Former player <ref target="w:Neil%20Harris%20%28footballer%2C%20born%201977%29">Neil Harris</ref> has been placed in charge until season's end.

<p>An official statement was released by club chairman <ref target="w:John%20Berylson">John Berylson</ref> . He said "This was a hard decision to take because we very much hoped that Ollie would prove to be the man to take us forward and on to the next level. I would like to thank him for his efforts, and in particular for keeping us in the Championship last May." He added "Ian Holloway remains a fine manager and it was his impressive track record which led us to appoint him some 14 months ago. However, our view is that the decision to part company at this stage is in the best interests of the football club going forward."</p>

<p>At the time of Holloway's departure Millwall sat in 23rd position of the <ref target="w:Football%20League%20Championship">Football League Championship</ref> , the second tier of English football. They were eight points away from <ref target="w:Promotion%20and%20relegation">safety</ref> . Holloway, 51, was in charge of Millwall for 62 games; during his tenure they won only 14 times, losing 29 and drawing the remaining 19.</p>

<p>Former Millwall player <ref target="w:Matthew%20Lawrence%20%28footballer%29">Matt Lawrence</ref> spoke to <ref target="w:BBC%20London%2094.9">BBC London 94.9</ref> about Holloway's sacking and offered his opinion. He said "I think everybody knew this was coming. Most people are surprised it has taken this long[...] The fans completely turned and the minute you lose the fans your time is up and it is time to move on."</p>



 
<head>Sources</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> "<ref target="http://www.bbc.co.uk/sport/0/football/31833672">Millwall: Ian Holloway sacking 'no surprise', says Matt Lawrence</ref>" — <ref target="w:BBC%20Sport">BBC Sport</ref> , March 11, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www1.skysports.com/football/news/30964/9752487/millwall-have-sacked-manager-ian-holloway">Millwall sack manager Ian Holloway</ref>" — <ref target="w:Sky%20Sports">Sky Sports</ref> , March 10, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.theguardian.com/football/2015/mar/10/millwall-ian-holloway-neil-harris">Millwall sack Ian Holloway and install Neil Harris until end of season</ref>" — <ref target="w:The%20Guardian">The Guardian</ref> , March 10, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.millwallfc.co.uk/news/article/millwall-ian-holloway-neil-harris-2325508.aspx">Club statement - Lions part company with Ian Holloway</ref>" — <ref target="w:Millwall%20Football%20Club">Millwall Football Club</ref> , March 10, 2015</item>
</list>
</text>
