<text id="autogum_wikinews_doc288" title="Chennaiyin FC score late goal, beat Goa 3-2 to win Indian Super League 2015">
<head>Chennaiyin FC score late goal, beat Goa 3-2 to win Indian Super League 2015</head>
  

<p>Today, <ref target="w:Chennai">Chennai</ref> -based football club <ref target="w:Chennaiyin%20FC">Chennaiyin FC</ref> defeated <ref target="w:FC%20Goa">FC Goa</ref> 3&ndash;2 at <ref target="w:Fatorda%20Stadium">Fatorda Stadium</ref> in <ref target="w:Margao">Margao</ref> in the <ref target="w:Indian%20Super%20League">Indian Super League</ref> final.</p>

<p>The match saw five <ref target="w:yellow%20card%20%28association%20football%29">yellow cards</ref> , two for the home side. Chennai's <ref target="w:Mehrajuddin%20Wadoo">Mehrajuddin Wadoo</ref> was the first one to be booked in the 18 minute. In the 33 minute, Goa's <ref target="w:Leonardo%20da%20Silva%20Moura">Moura</ref> 's shot was deflected by Wadoo. With a single booking, the first half ended 0&ndash;0.</p>

<p>In the second half, in the 53 minute, <ref target="w:Pronay%20Halder">Pronay Halder</ref> committed a foul on Chennai's <ref target="w:Stiven%20Mendoza">Stiven Mendoza</ref> in the penalty area, and the visitors were awarded a penalty kick. Stepping forward for the kick, <ref target="w:Bruno%20Pelissari">Bruno Pelissari</ref> 's kick was saved by <ref target="w:Laxmikant%20Kattimani">Laxmikant Kattimani</ref> but the ball bounced back, and Pelissari made no mistake, scoring. Chennai got a 1&ndash;0 lead.</p>

<ref target="w:Thoi%20Singh">Thoi Singh</ref> was booked in the 57 minute. Halder, in the 58 minute, assisted <ref target="w:Thongkhosiem%20Haokip">Thongkhosiem Haokip</ref> and the Indian footballer scored an equaliser for the home side. <ref target="w:Gr%C3%A9gory%20Arnolin">Grégory Arnolin</ref> received a yellow card in the 60 minute for protesting the referee's decision. Chennai was awarded another penalty kick. <ref target="w:Stiven%20Mendoza">Stiven Mendoza</ref> stood up for the penalty, but missed.

<p>Table-turning events took place in the dying moments of the game. <ref target="w:Jofre">Jofre</ref> scored a goal in the 87 minute. A minute later, he was yellow-carded; but, Goa had a 2&ndash;1 lead. Goa's goalie Laxmikant Kattimani scored an <ref target="wikt:own%20goal">own goal</ref> for a 2&ndash;2 equaliser and in the additional time, Mendoza netted a goal assisted by <ref target="w:Jayesh%20Rane">Jayesh Rane</ref> . Next minute, Mendoza was yellow-carded, but the final whistle blew a few moments later, and Chennaiyin FC won the second edition of the Indian Super League in the 3&ndash;2 goal tally.</p>


 
<head>Sources</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> "<ref target="http://www.indiansuperleague.com/news/3495-chennai-beat-goa-in-a-3-2-thriller-to-become-hero-isl-2015-champions">Chennai beat Goa in a 3-2 thriller to become Hero ISL 2015 champions</ref>" — <ref target="w:Indian%20Super%20League">Indian Super League</ref> , December 20, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.goal.com/en-india/match/goa-vs-chennaiyin-fc/2177113/live-commentary%3FICID%3DMP_MS_3">Goa 2 - 3 Chennaiyin FC</ref>" — <ref target="w:Goal.com">Goal.com</ref> , December 20, 2015</item>
<item> Rahul Bali. "<ref target="http://www.goal.com/en-india/match/goa-vs-chennaiyin-fc/2177113/report%3FICID%3DMP_MS_5">Goa 2 - 3 Chennaiyin FC</ref>" — <ref target="w:Goal.com">Goal.com</ref> , December 20, 2015</item>
</list>
</text>
