<text id="autogum_wikinews_doc283" title="UEFA Euro 16 draw takes place in Paris">
<head>UEFA Euro 16 draw takes place in Paris</head>
  

<p>On Saturday evening, the <ref target="w:UEFA%20Euro%202016">UEFA Euro 2016</ref> draw took place at the <ref target="w:Palais%20des%20congr%C3%A8s%20de%20Paris">Palais des Congrès</ref> in <ref target="w:Paris">Paris</ref> ; UEFA Euro 2016 is scheduled to be hosted in <ref target="France">France</ref>. 24 nations were drawn in six groups, with the host nation placed in Group A. The quadrennial football tournament of <ref target="Europe">Europe</ref> is scheduled to start in June 2016, the matches to be played in ten French cities.</p>

<ref target="England">England</ref> had the first draw, and went to Group B. Interestingly, <ref target="Wales">Wales</ref> were also drawn in Group B. World Cup winners <ref target="Germany">Germany</ref> were placed in Group C. <ref target="Poland">Polish</ref> national captain <ref target="w:Robert%20Lewandowski">Robert Lewandowski</ref> , who recently scored a brace against <ref target="Croatia">Croatian</ref> <ref target="w:Dinamo%20Zagreb">Dinamo Zagreb</ref> for <ref target="Bayern%20Munich">Bayern Munich</ref>, potentially faces his Bayern Munich teammate <ref target="w:Thomas%20M%C3%BCller">Thomas Müller</ref> in a Group C match.

<p>Two-time defending champions <ref target="Spain">Spain</ref> are in Group D. <ref target="Netherlands">Netherlands</ref> did not qualify for the first time since 1984 after a shock exit in the qualifying stage.</p>

<p>In full, the groups are as follows: </p>

<p>The opening match of the tournament is scheduled to be France versus Romania.</p>



 

<head>Sister link</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> </item>
</list>



<head>Related news</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> "" — <ref target="Main_Page">Wikinews</ref>, December 12, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="Netherlands%20out%20of%20Euro%2016%20as%20van%20Persie%20scores%20own%20goal%20against%20Czech%20Republic">Netherlands out of Euro 16 as van Persie scores own goal against Czech Republic</ref>" — <ref target="Main_Page">Wikinews</ref>, October 14, 2015</item>
</list>


<head>Sources</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Rob Smith. "<ref target="http://www.theguardian.com/football/live/2015/dec/12/euro-2016-draw-live%3FCMP%3Dshare_btn_fb">Euro 2016 draw – as it happened</ref>" — <ref target="w:The%20Guardian">The Guardian</ref> , December 12, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.uefa.com/uefaeuro/draws/index.html">Draws</ref>" — <ref target="w:UEFA">UEFA</ref> , December 12, 2015</item>
</list>
</text>
