<text id="autogum_wikinews_doc195" title="Biologist Nick Bos tells Wikinews about 'self-medicating' ants">
<head>Biologist Nick Bos tells Wikinews about 'self-medicating' ants</head>
  

<p>Nick Bos, of the <ref target="w:University%20of%20Helsinki">University of Helsinki</ref> , studies "the amazing adaptations social insects have evolved in order to fight the extreme parasite pressure they experience". In a recently-accepted <hi rend="italic"><ref target="w:Evolution%20%28journal%29">Evolution</ref> </hi> paper Bos and colleagues describe ants appearing to self-medicate.</p>
<p>The team used <hi rend="italic"><ref target="w:Formica%20fusca">Formica fusca</ref> </hi>, an <ref target="ant">ant</ref> species that can form thousand-strong colonies. This common black ant eats other insects, and also <ref target="w:honeydew%20%28secretion%29">aphid honeydew</ref> . It often nests in tree stumps or under rocks and foraging workers can sometimes be spotted climbing trees.</p>

<p>Some ants were infected with <hi rend="italic"><ref target="w:Beauveria%20bassiana">Beauveria bassiana</ref> </hi>, a <ref target="w:fungus">fungus</ref> . Infected ants chose food laced with toxic <ref target="w:hydrogen%20peroxide">hydrogen peroxide</ref> , whereas healthy ants avoided it. Hydrogen peroxide reduced infected ant fatalities by 15%, and the ants varied their intake depending upon how high the peroxide concentration was.</p>

<p>In the wild, <hi rend="italic">Formica fusca</hi> can encounter similar chemicals in aphids and dead ants. <hi rend="italic"><ref target="w:The%20Independent">The Independent</ref> </hi> reported self-medicating ants a first among insects. </p>

<p>Bos obtained his doctorate from the <ref target="w:University%20of%20Copenhagen">University of Copenhagen</ref> . He began postdoctoral research at Helsinki in 2012. He also runs the AntyScience blog. The blog aims to help address "a gap between scientists and 'the general public'." The name is a pun referencing ants, its primary topic, science, and "non-scientific" jargon-free communication. He now discusses his work with <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi>.</p>

<p>((Wikinews)) What first attracted you to researching ants?</p>

<p>((Wikinews)) What methods and equipment were used for this investigation?</p>

<p>((Wikinews)) How <ref target="w:Reliability%20%28psychometrics%29">reliable</ref> do you consider your results to be?</p>
<p>((Wikinews)) Where did the ants and fungus you used come from? How common are they in the wild?</p>

<p>((Wikinews)) Are there any ethical considerations around exposing ants to toxins and parasites?</p>

<p>((Wikinews)) This is the first evidence for self-medicating insects. How widespread do you think this phenomenon could be in reality?</p>

<p>((Wikinews)) How might ants locate healing substances in the wild?</p>

<p>((Wikinews)) For your PhD you researched ants' scent-based communications. Could healthy ants perhaps tell other ants are infected and encourage this behaviour?</p>

<p>((Wikinews)) Ants generally avoided the peroxide if they were healthy, but in some circumstances might they try to build resistance against infection in advance?</p>

<p>((Wikinews)) Are there plans to follow this research up? Might you research other species? Other substances? </p>

<p>((Wikinews)) What other research are you working on right now?</p>



 
<head>Sister links</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> * </item>
</list>
<head>Sources</head>

 

<list type="unordered">
<item> "<ref target="http://www.bwars.com/index.php%3Fq%3Dant/formicidae/formicinae/formica-fusca">Formica fusca Linnaeus, 1758</ref>" — <ref target="w:Bees%2C%20Wasps%20and%20Ants%20Recording%20Society">Bees, Wasps and Ants Recording Society</ref> , Accessed September 1, 2015</item>
<item> Jessica Staufenberg. "<ref target="http://www.independent.co.uk/news/science/ants-are-able-to-selfmedicate-by-changing-diet-when-they-are-unwell-in-first-for-insectkind-10467040.html">Ants are able to 'self-medicate' by changing diet when they are unwell in first for insect-kind</ref>" — <ref target="w:The%20Independent">The Independent</ref> , August 22, 2015</item>
</list>


<head>External links</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="https://antyscience.wordpress.com/">AntyScience blog</ref></item>
<item> Nick Bos, Liselotte Sundström, Siiri Fuchs, Dalial Freitak. "<ref target="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/evo.12752/abstract%3Bjsessionid%3D9681B97E6C714FA4EE18B3766F8C44CC.f01t01">Ants medicate to fight disease</ref>" — <ref target="w:Evolution%20%28journal%29">Evolution</ref> , 2015</item>
<item> Stephen Messenger. "<ref target="http://www.treehugger.com/cars/trillions-of-insects-killed-by-cars-every-year-says-study.html">Trillions of Insects Killed by Cars Every Year, Says Study</ref>" — <ref target="w:Treehugger.com">Treehugger.com</ref> , July 10, 2011 , link provided by Nick Bos for further reading</item>
</list>
</text>
