<text id="autogum_wikinews_doc165" title="FC Barcelona defeats Sevilla FC 5-4 to win UEFA Super Cup 2015">
<head>FC Barcelona defeats Sevilla FC 5-4 to win UEFA Super Cup 2015</head>
  

<p>On Wednesday, <ref target="Catalonia">Catalonia</ref>-based football club <ref target="FC%20Barcelona">FC Barcelona</ref> defeated <ref target="w:Seville">Seville</ref> -based football club <ref target="w:Sevilla%20FC">Sevilla</ref> 5&ndash;4 to win the <ref target="w:2015%20UEFA%20Super%20Cup">2015</ref> <ref target="w:UEFA%20Super%20Cup">UEFA Super Cup</ref> . The match was held in <ref target="w:Boris%20Paichadze%20Dinamo%20Arena">Boris Paichadze Dinamo Arena</ref> in the city of <ref target="w:Tbilisi">Tbilisi</ref> , <ref target="Georgia%20%28country%29">Georgia</ref>. <ref target="w:Pedro%20%28footballer%2C%20born%20July%201987%29">Pedro</ref> , who may leave for <ref target="Manchester%20United">Manchester United</ref>, scored the winning goal of the match in the 115 minute. This was the fifth UEFA Super cup won by Barcelona.</p>

<p>Barcelona had stronger possession of the ball in front of Sevilla. The match saw nine <ref target="w:yellow%20card%20%28association%20football%29">yellow cards</ref> , four for Barcelona players and five for Sevilla players. A total of 41 fouls were committed in the match. A total of nine goals were scored in the match, with the first goal scored in the opening minutes of the game.</p>

<p>Barcelona defender <ref target="w:Javier%20Mascherano">Mascherano</ref> committed a foul in the 2 minute and thus Sevilla got a free kick. <ref target="w:%C3%89ver%20Banega">Banega</ref> converted the free kick into goal in the 3 minute of the game. Minutes later, Sevilla's <ref target="w:Grzegorz%20Krychowiak">Krychowiak</ref> committed a foul and this early lead was soon equalised as Barcelona forward <ref target="Lionel%20Messi">Lionel Messi</ref> scored a similar style free kick.</p>

<p>Krychowiak received a yellow card in the 14 minute and Barca were awarded another free kick for Banega's foul on <ref target="Ivan%20Rakiti%C4%87">Rakitić</ref>. Leo Messi converted this free kick into a goal, giving the lead to Barcelona after 16 minutes of game play. This was Messi's 36 goal in 37 games in 2015.</p>

<p>Minutes before half time, <ref target="w:Luis%20Su%C3%A1rez">Luis Suárez</ref> assisted <ref target="w:Rafinha%20%28footballer%2C%20born%201993%29">Rafinha</ref> and the <ref target="Brazil">Brazilian</ref> tripled the lead for the Catalans. First half ended with scoreline 3&ndash;1 with only one booking.</p>

<p>Within ten minutes of the second half, Suárez scored the fourth goal in the 52 making it a one-sided match. Five minutes later, <ref target="w:Jos%C3%A9%20Antonio%20Reyes">Reyes</ref> scored a close ranged shot making the score 4&ndash;2. In the 63 minute, <ref target="w:Andr%C3%A9s%20Iniesta">Andrés Iniesta</ref> was substituted off for <ref target="w:Sergi%20Roberto">Sergi Roberto</ref> . Iniesta made his 550 appearance for Barcelona. After this substitution, the goal difference kept on dropping. In the 71 minute, <ref target="w:J%C3%A9r%C3%A9my%20Mathieu">Mathieu</ref> was booked for a foul on <ref target="w:Vitolo%20%28footballer%2C%20born%201989%29">Vitolo</ref> . Referee awarded a penalty kick for Sevilla. <ref target="w:K%C3%A9vin%20Gameiro">Gameiro</ref> perfectly converted it into a goal making it 4&ndash;3.</p>

<p>Within the next ten minutes, Sevilla equalised with Barcelona. <ref target="w:Yevhen%20Konoplyanka">Konoplyanka</ref> scored an easy tap-in to bring Sevilla from 4&ndash;1 to 4&ndash;4. Within half an hour, the one-sided match changed into a tensed match.</p>

<ref target="w:Coke%20%28footballer%29">Coke</ref> in the 87 minute and Banega in the 90+2 minute were booked for committing foul on Suárez. The game ended in 4&ndash;4. And thus it was extended to additional time. 

<p>Additional time saw five more yellow cards. Pedro was substituted in for Mascherano in the 93 minute and in the next minute, he received a yellow card for foul on Vitolo. Barcelona won a free kick in the dying minutes of the game. Messi's kick became an indirect assist to Pedro who netted it in the top corner. It was the winning goal of the game.</p>

<p>This was Pedro's 99 goal in the Catalonia jersey. By this victory, Barcelona joined <ref target="w:A.C.%20Milan">A.C. Milan</ref> as the most successful club. Both the teams have earned the title five times. This trophy was Messi's and Iniesta's 25 trophy with Barcelona. Messi was awarded Man of the match.</p>
<p>After the match, he said, "We are delighted to start the season with this win, but it was tough [...] The most important thing was to win the Super Cup to start well. Now we think of the Spanish Super Cup against Athletic Club".</p>

<p>On Tuesday, Pedro was asked if he was leaving Barcelona. He replied "The answer is no. But it is a difficult, complicated situation. When you know you may leave it is difficult." Pedro said it wan't about money but the playing time. Pedro said "The truth is that I had a good chance to play. The coach has decided not to count on me. I don't know, I don't know if I will continue here [...] Manchester? Yes, there are nice challenges on all sides. Today I'm here, and I'm happy [...] And if I go, I will go with my head held high having always given everything."</p>



 



<head>Sources</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Michael Toll. "<ref target="http://www.fcbarcelona.com/football/first-team/detail/article/fc-barcelona-v-sevilla-fc-fourth-title-of-2015-54">FC Barcelona v Sevilla FC: Fourth title of 2015 (5–4)</ref>" — <ref target="w:FC%20Barcelona">FC Barcelona</ref> , August 12, 2015</item>
<item> Roger Bogunyà. "<ref target="http://www.fcbarcelona.com/football/first-team/detail/article/lionel-messi-man-of-the-match-in-2015-uefa-super-cup">Lionel Messi man of the match in 2015 UEFA Super Cup</ref>" — <ref target="w:FC%20Barcelona">FC Barcelona</ref> , August 12, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.uefa.com/uefasupercup/season%3D2015/matches/live/day%3D1/session%3D1/match%3D2015790/index.html">UEFA Super Cup - Matches – UEFA.com</ref>" — <ref target="w:UEFA">UEFA</ref> , August 11, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.uefa.com/uefasupercup/">UEFA Super Cup – UEFA.com</ref>" — <ref target="w:UEFA">UEFA</ref> , August 11, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.uefa.com/uefasupercup/season%3D2015/matches/live/index.html%3Fday%3D1%26amp%3Bsession%3D1%26amp%3Bmatch%3D2015790">The official website for European football – UEFA.com</ref>" — <ref target="w:UEFA">UEFA</ref> , August 11, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.uefa.com/uefasupercup/season%3D2015/matches/round%3D2000639/match%3D2015790/index.html">Pedro is Barcelona's UEFA Super Cup hero again</ref>" — <ref target="w:UEFA">UEFA</ref> , August 11, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.bbc.com/sport/0/football/33873813">Pedro: Barcelona forward 'wants to leave the club'</ref>" — <ref target="w:BBC%20Sport">BBC Sport</ref> , August 11, 2015</item>
<item> Sam Robinson. "<ref target="http://www.theguardian.com/football/2015/aug/11/pedro-barcelona-sevilla-uefa-super-cup-match-report">Pedro clinches Uefa Super Cup for Barcelona in thriller against Sevilla</ref>" — <ref target="w:The%20Guardian">The Guardian</ref> , August 11, 2015</item>
<item> Hamish Mackay. "<ref target="http://www.mirror.co.uk/sport/football/transfer-news/pedros-body-language-after-barcelonas-6236687">Pedro's body language after Barcelona's Super Cup win shows he's ready to join Manchester United</ref>" — <ref target="w:Daily%20Mirror">Daily Mirror</ref> , August 11, 2015</item>
</list>
</text>
