<text id="autogum_wikinews_doc326" title="Messi scores twice against Čech, Bayern draw against Juventus in Champions League Last 16">
<head>Messi scores twice against Čech, Bayern draw against Juventus in Champions League Last 16</head>
  

<p>Yesterday, in the Last 16 round of the <ref target="UEFA%20Champions%20League">UEFA Champions League</ref> 2015&ndash;2016, <ref target="Spain">Spanish</ref> <ref target="soccer">football</ref> club <ref target="FC%20Barcelona">FC Barcelona</ref> defeated <ref target="London">London</ref>-based club <ref target="Arsenal%20F.C.">Arsenal F.C.</ref> 2&ndash;0 &mdash; <ref target="Lionel%20Messi">Lionel Messi</ref> scoring both of those at the <ref target="w:Emirates%20Stadium">Emirates Stadium</ref> . <ref target="Munich">Munich</ref>-based club <ref target="Bayern%20Munich">Bayern Munich</ref> were held to a 2&ndash;2 draw against <ref target="Italy">Italian</ref> club <ref target="Juventus%20FC">Juventus FC</ref> in the <ref target="w:Juventus%20Stadium">Juventus Stadium</ref> .</p>
<p>At London, Barcelona had a greater ball possession against <hi rend="italic">The Gunners</hi>. The match saw two <ref target="w:Yellow%20card%20%28association%20football%29">yellow cards</ref> . Unbeaten in their last 32 games, Barça were not able to net goals for more than an hour. <ref target="Ars%C3%A8ne%20Wenger">Arsène Wenger</ref>'s team Arsenal held the defending champions, and it took 49 minutes for the <ref target="Catalonia">Catalonia</ref>ns to have one shot on target. In the 71 minute, Barcelona won the ball and began counter-attacking, where Messi&ndash;<ref target="w:Luis%20Su%C3%A1rez">Suárez</ref> &ndash;<ref target="w:Neymar">Neymar</ref> , the MSN trio, broke the deadlock as the <ref target="Argentina">Argentine</ref> Messi scored his first goal against <ref target="Czech%20Republic">Czech</ref> goalkeeper <ref target="w:Petr%20%C4%8Cech">Petr Čech</ref> .</p>

<p>In the 83 minute, <ref target="w:Mathieu%20Flamini">Mathieu Flamini</ref> who was just subbed in brought the Argentine down in the penalty area and the visitors won a penalty. Messi scored his second of the night leaving the English side facing an uphill battle. Arsenal have been eliminated in the Last 16 round five consecutive times. After the match, Wenger told <ref target="w:BT%20Sport">BT Sport</ref> "Barcelona is a great team[...] We put a lot of energy in the game and technically we were very average."</p>

<p>Barcelona in their last 33 unbeaten games have netted 100 goals. Arsenal are to play the second leg at <ref target="w:Camp%20Nou">Camp Nou</ref> on March 16.</p>

<p>In the other fixture of the night, between Bayern Munich and Juventus, the Germans had better ball possession. <ref target="w:Thomas%20M%C3%BCller">Thomas Müller</ref> and <ref target="w:Arjen%20Robben">Arjen Robben</ref> put the visitors 2&ndash;0 up, netting in the 43 and the 55 minute respectively. But after the hour mark, <ref target="w:Paulo%20Dybala">Paulo Dybala</ref> and <ref target="w:Stefano%20Sturaro">Stefano Sturaro</ref> brought Juventus level by scoring in the 63and the 76 minutes, and the first leg finished in a 2&ndash;2 draw. The match saw four bookings, three for the visitors.</p>

<p>Juventus continued their unbeaten streak of now seventeen home matches in <ref target="Europe">Europe</ref>an competition since defeat in 2013 against Bayern Munich.</p>



 
<head>Sources</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> James Masters. "<ref target="http://edition.cnn.com/2016/02/23/sport/champions-league-arsenal-barcelona/index.html%3Fsr%3DfbCNN022316champions-league-arsenal-barcelona">Champions League: Lionel Messi strikes as Barcelona beats Arsenal</ref>" — <ref target="w:CNN">CNN</ref> , February 23, 2016</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.uefa.com/uefachampionsleague/season%3D2016/matches/round%3D2000635/match%3D2015766/postmatch/report/index.html%23magical%2Bmessi%2Bcasts%2Bspell%2Bover%2Barsenal%2Bbarca">Magical Messi casts spell over Arsenal in Barça win</ref>" — <ref target="w:UEFA">UEFA</ref> , February 23, 2016</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.uefa.com/uefachampionsleague/season%3D2016/matches/round%3D2000635/match%3D2015767/index.html">Juventus fightback frustrates Bayern</ref>" — <ref target="w:UEFA">UEFA</ref> , February 23, 2016</item>
</list>
</text>
