<text id="autogum_wikinews_doc285" title="Suárez scores a hat-trick, Barcelona advances to FIFA Club World Cup 2015 Final">
<head>Suárez scores a hat-trick, Barcelona advances to FIFA Club World Cup 2015 Final</head>
  

<p>Yesterday, <ref target="Catalonia">Catalonia</ref>-based football club <ref target="FC%20Barcelona">FC Barcelona</ref> defeated <ref target="China">Chinese</ref> <ref target="w:Guangzhou%20Evergrande%20FC">Guangzhou Evergrande FC</ref> 3&ndash;0 at <ref target="w:International%20Stadium%20Yokohama">Nissan Stadium</ref> in <ref target="w:Yokohama">Yokohama</ref> in a <ref target="w:FIFA%20Club%20World%20Cup">FIFA Club World Cup</ref> semifinal match hosted in <ref target="Japan">Japan</ref>.</p>

<p>FIFA Club World Cup is a tournament in which football clubs winning in the respective continental confederation championships participate. Barcelona won the <ref target="w:UEFA%20Champions%20League">UEFA Champions League</ref> , and Guangzhou won the <ref target="w:AFC%20Champions%20League">AFC Champions League</ref> . Barcelona's <ref target="w:Neymar">Neymar</ref> , suffering from groin injury, was not included in the squad.</p>
<p>Barça had greater ball possession. The match saw one <ref target="w:yellow%20card%20%28association%20football%29">yellow card</ref> , when <ref target="w:Feng%20Xiaoting">Feng Xiaoting</ref> was yellow carded in the 16 minute, and at least two dozen fouls were committed in the match. The <ref target="w:2015%20AFC%20Champions%20League">2015</ref> AFC Champions League winners Guangzhou prevented the European winners from scoring a goal for more than half an hour. In the 39 minute, <ref target="w:Ivan%20Rakiti%C4%87">Ivan Rakitić</ref> 's shot on the target was saved by the Chinese goalkeeper, but <ref target="w:Luis%20Su%C3%A1rez">Luis Suárez</ref> netted the goal providing Barcelona a 1&ndash;0 lead before half-time. The first half ended in 1&ndash;0. </p>

<p>In the second half, Suárez scored again in the 50 minute, assisted by <ref target="w:Andr%C3%A9s%20Iniesta">Andrés Iniesta</ref> . A quarter of an hour later, Guangzhou player <ref target="w:Huang%20Bowen">Huang Bowen</ref> fouled <ref target="w:Munir%20El%20Haddadi">Munir El Haddadi</ref> in the penalty area, and Barcelona was awarded a penalty kick. Suárez, in the absence of <ref target="Lionel%20Messi">Lionel Messi</ref>, took the penalty and completed a <ref target="wikt:hat-trick">hat-trick</ref> .</p>

<p>After the match, Guangzhou coach <ref target="w:Luiz%20Felipe%20Scolari">Luiz Felipe Scolari</ref> praised the club's performance. "We lost 3&ndash;0, but it's not much different to what has happened to other big clubs. At least we didn't let in four like Real Madrid."</p>

<p>Barcelona, is now scheduled to play the final on December 20.</p>
<head>Related news</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> "<ref target="F.C.%20Barcelona%20wins%20UEFA%20Champions%20League%202014/15">F.C. Barcelona wins UEFA Champions League 2014/15</ref>" — <ref target="Main_Page">Wikinews</ref>, June 8, 2015</item>
</list>
<head>Sources</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> "<ref target="http://www.fifa.com/clubworldcup/matches/round%3D275782/match%3D300338752/index.html%23statistics%23nosticky">FIFA Club World Cup Japan 2015 - Matches - FC Barcelona-Guangzhou Evergrande FC</ref>" — <ref target="w:FIFA">FIFA</ref> , December 17, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.goal.com/en-india/match/barcelona-vs-guangzhou-evergrande/2171847%3FICID%3DHP_HN_1">Barcelona 3-0 Guangzhou Evergrande Match report</ref>" — <ref target="w:Goal.com">Goal.com</ref> , December 17, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.bbc.com/sport/0/football/35095550">Barcelona 3-0 Guangzhou Evergrande</ref>" — <ref target="w:BBC%20Sport">BBC Sport</ref> , December 17, 2015</item>
<item> Stefan Coerts. "<ref target="http://www.goal.com/en/news/7651/club-world-cup/2015/12/17/18463472/at-least-we-didnt-let-in-four-like-real-madrid-scolari-proud">'At least we didn't let in four like Real Madrid' - Scolari proud despite Barcelona defeat</ref>" — <ref target="w:Goal.com">Goal.com</ref> , December 17, 2015</item>
</list>
</text>
