<text id="autogum_wikinews_doc175" title="Wikinews interviews Mark Everson, U.S. Republican Party presidential candidate">
<head>Wikinews interviews Mark Everson, U.S. Republican Party presidential candidate</head>
  
<p>Former <ref target="U.S.">U.S.</ref> <ref target="w:Commissioner%20of%20Internal%20Revenue">Commissioner of Internal Revenue</ref> <ref target="w:Mark%20Everson">Mark Everson</ref> took some time to talk with <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> about his campaign for the <ref target="Republican%20Party%20%28United%20States%29">U.S. Republican Party</ref>'s <ref target="United%20States%20presidential%20election%2C%202016">2016 presidential nomination</ref>.</p>

<p>Everson served as Commissioner of Internal Revenue, the administrative head of the <ref target="w:Internal%20Revenue%20Service">Internal Revenue Service</ref> (IRS) from 2003 to 2007, during the <ref target="w:George%20W.%20Bush">George W. Bush</ref> administration. After his departure, he briefly served as CEO of the <ref target="w:American%20Red%20Cross">American Red Cross</ref> , worked in the cabinet of <ref target="Indiana">Indiana</ref> <ref target="w:Governor%20of%20Indiana">governor</ref> <ref target="w:Mitch%20Daniels">Mitch Daniels</ref> , and worked for the tax consulting firm <ref target="w:alliantgroup">alliantgroup</ref> . He announced his candidacy this past March with a sixteen-page open letter in which he outlined the six pillars of his campaign: amnesty for <ref target="w:Illegal%20immigration%20in%20the%20United%20States">illegal immigrants</ref> , reinstatement of the <ref target="w:military%20draft">military draft</ref> , a promise to serve only a single presidential term, and calls for tax reform, deficit reduction, and corporate responsibility.</p>

<p>He was excluded from the August 6 <ref target="w:Fox%20News">Fox News</ref> <ref target="w:Republican%20Party%20presidential%20debates%2C%202016">Republican presidential debate</ref> and has been excluded from most <ref target="w:Nationwide%20opinion%20polling%20for%20the%20Republican%20Party%202016%20presidential%20primaries">presidential polls</ref> . However, he is listed on the Republican Party's website as one of 18 candidates and filed a <ref target="w:Federal%20Election%20Commission">Federal Election Commission</ref> (FEC) complaint against Fox News for his exclusion from the August 6 debate. </p>
<p>With <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> reporter ‎, Everson discusses his 2016 campaign, the media blackout of his campaign, and his views on the presidency and the possible Everson administration.</p>
<head>Interview</head>
<head>2016 campaign and qualifications</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> ((William S. Saturn)) <hi rend="bold">Why run for president? Why not run for a lower office that you might be more likely to win and effect change?</hi></item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> ((WSS)) <hi rend="bold">What qualifications do you have that will assist you in executing the duties of president?</hi></item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> ((WSS)) <hi rend="bold">How much campaigning have you done so far?</hi></item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> ((WSS)) <hi rend="bold">What are your thoughts on your fellow Republican presidential candidates?</hi></item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> ((WSS)) <hi rend="bold">Would you ever consider running as a third party or independent candidate?</hi></item>
</list>


<head>Media blackout</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> ((WSS)) ♡❤♡<hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> covered the complaint you filed with the FEC against Fox News in your attempt to be included in the August 6 Debate. In our report, Election Law expert <ref target="w:Richard%20Winger">Richard Winger</ref> suggested you file a lawsuit rather than an FEC complaint. Do you have an update on your FEC complaint and might you consider filing a lawsuit if you are excluded from future debates?<hi rend="bold"></item>
<item> ((WSS)) </hi>Your exclusion from National presidential polls appears to be the biggest detriment to your campaign and effort to appear in debates. Is there anything your campaign can do to include your name in polls to qualify for future debates?<hi rend="bold"></item>
<item> ((WSS)) </hi>Are you surprised by your exclusion from presidential polls and events or did you expect this when you announced?<hi rend="bold"></item>
</list>


<head>The presidency and administration</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> ((WSS)) </hi> What are your thoughts on the job <ref target="Barack%20Obama">Barack Obama</ref> has done as president? Specifically, what would you have done differently?<hi rend="bold"></item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> ((WSS)) </hi>If elected, what would constitute a successful presidency for you?<hi rend="bold"></item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> ((WSS)) </hi> Which individuals would you like to see in an Everson administration?♡❤♡</item>
</list>




 

<head>Related news</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> "<ref target="U.S.%20presidential%20candidate%20Mark%20Everson%20challenges%20debate%20exclusion">U.S. presidential candidate Mark Everson challenges debate exclusion</ref>" — <ref target="Main_Page">Wikinews</ref>, August 5, 2015</item>
</list>


<head>Sources</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> "<ref target="https://www.gop.com/presidential-straw-poll/">2016 Presidential Straw Poll</ref>" — <ref target="w:U.S.%20Republican%20Party">U.S. Republican Party</ref> , August 20, 2015 (accessed)</item>
<item> Aditya Agrawal. "<ref target="http://time.com/3986183/republican-debate-mark-everson/">Meet the Republican Candidate Who Won’t Be at the Debates</ref>" — <ref target="w:Time%20%28magazine%29">Time (magazine)</ref> , August 5, 2015</item>
</list>
</text>
