<text id="autogum_wikinews_doc227" title="Bernie Sanders embraces Black Lives Matter movement">
<head>Bernie Sanders embraces Black Lives Matter movement</head>
  
<ref target="United%20States">United States</ref> <ref target="United%20States%20presidential%20election%2C%202016">Presidential candidate</ref> <ref target="Bernie%20Sanders">Bernie Sanders</ref> discussed his understanding of the <ref target="w:Black%20Lives%20Matter">Black Lives Matter movement</ref> on Monday.

<p>"Many white people are not sensitive", Sanders noted, speaking with magazine <hi rend="italic"><ref target="w:Ebony%20%28magazine%29">Ebony</ref> </hi>, "to the kind of abuse that <ref target="wikt:African-American">African-Americans</ref> , especially younger African-Americans, receive at the hands of police officers and police departments".</p>

<p>The Black Lives Matter activist movement protests police brutality against African Americans, and gained traction after the death of <ref target="w:Shooting%20of%20Michael%20Brown">Michael Brown</ref> last year in <ref target="w:Ferguson%2C%20Missouri">Ferguson</ref> , <ref target="Missouri">Missouri</ref>.</p>

<p>Sanders also recently admitted, speaking to magazine <hi rend="italic"><ref target="w:The%20New%20Yorker">The New Yorker</ref> </hi>, that when the Black Lives Matter movement first came to light, he mishandled his dealings with them: "I plead guilty — I should have been more sensitive at the beginning of this campaign to talk about this issue [...] The issues these young people raised are enormously important".</p>

<p>Senator Sanders has had several incidents involving the group, including when they interrupted one of his rallies in <ref target="w:Seattle">Seattle</ref> in August. He said talking with members of the movement has helped him understand what the movement is about.</p>

<p>Sanders has been strongly criticized for his previous treatment of the group, particularly when his campaign began to respond to interruption from the group by shouting "we stand together" repeatedly at them.</p>

<p>The <ref target="w:US%20Senate">Senator</ref> for <ref target="w:Vermont">Vermont</ref> in his <hi rend="italic">Ebony</hi> interview called the US criminal justice system "broken", saying, "One of the ongoing crises in America is institutional racism".</p>



 
<head>Sources</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Sophia Tesfaye. "<ref target="http://www.salon.com/2015/10/05/bernie_sanders_admits_he_initially_mishandled_black_lives_matter_i_plead_guilty_i_should_have_been_more_sensitive/">Bernie Sanders admits he initially mishandled Black Lives Matter: “I plead guilty — I should have been more sensitive”</ref>" — <ref target="w:Salon%20%28website%29">Salon (website)</ref> , October 5, 2015</item>
<item> Abigail Abrams. "<ref target="http://www.ibtimes.com/bernie-sanders-black-lives-matter-white-americans-not-sensitive-african-american-2127789">Bernie Sanders Black Lives Matter: White Americans 'Not Sensitive' To African-American Struggles, Presidential Candidate Says</ref>" — <ref target="w:International%20Business%20Times">International Business Times</ref> , October 5, 2015</item>
<item> Darlena Cunha. "<ref target="http://time.com/3996001/bernie-sanders-black-lives-matter/">Bernie Sanders Is Wrong To Ignore ‘Black Lives Matter'</ref>" — <ref target="w:Time%20%28magazine%29">Time (magazine)</ref> , August 13, 2015</item>
</list>
</text>
