<text id="autogum_wikinews_doc238" title="Ronaldo surpasses Raúl's record, becomes Real Madrid's top scorer">
<head>Ronaldo surpasses Raúl's record, becomes Real Madrid's top scorer</head>
  

<ref target="Portugal">Portuguese</ref> footballer <ref target="Cristiano%20Ronaldo">Cristiano Ronaldo</ref> surpassed <ref target="w:Ra%C3%BAl%20%28footballer%29">Raúl</ref> 's goal scoring record for <ref target="Spain">Spanish</ref> club <ref target="Real%20Madrid">Real Madrid</ref> in a <ref target="La%20Liga">La Liga</ref> match against <ref target="w:Levante%20UD">Levante UD</ref> on Saturday. Ronaldo netted his 324 goal in his 310 match for <hi rend="italic">Los Blancos</hi> on Saturday, breaking the previous record set by Spanish footballer Raúl of 323 goals in 741 games. 

<p>He earlier equaled Raúl's goal scoring record for Madrid in a <ref target="UEFA%20Champions%20League">UEFA Champions League</ref> match against <ref target="Sweden">Swedish</ref> football club <ref target="w:Malm%C3%B6%20FF">Malmö FF</ref> when he scored a <ref target="wikt:brace">brace</ref>, crossing the landmark of 500 career goals and scored the record-breaking goal in the 30 minute from outside the <ref target="w:penalty%20area">penalty area</ref> in this match.</p>
<p>In Saturday's match, Real Madrid had 58% ball possession against Levante. The match saw five <ref target="w:yellow%20card%20%28association%20football%29">yellow cards</ref> &mdash; four for the visitors and one for Real Madrid player <ref target="w:Mateo%20Kova%C4%8Di%C4%87">Kovačić</ref> . A total of eighteen fouls were committed in the game. Ronaldo <ref target="w:Assist%20%28football%29">assisted</ref> <ref target="Brazil">Brazilian</ref> <ref target="Marcelo%20Vieira">Marcelo</ref> in the 27 minute and Marcelo netted the goal in the left corner. Minutes later, <ref target="Toni%20Kroos">Toni Kroos</ref> assisted Ronaldo, and he scored the record-breaking goal in the bottom right corner. The first half ended 2&ndash;0.</p>

<p>At the beginning of the second half, <ref target="w:Lucas%20V%C3%A1zquez">Vázquez</ref> was substituted for <ref target="Gareth%20Bale">Gareth Bale</ref>. He assisted <ref target="w:Jes%C3%A9">Jesé</ref> in the 81 minute and Jesé scored in the top corner providing a 3&ndash;0 win for Real Madrid.</p>

<p>Real is now top of the La Liga table. </p>


 

<head>Match stats</head>
<head>Sources</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Reuters. "<ref target="http://www.dnaindia.com/sport/report-cristiano-ronaldo-overtakes-raul-as-real-madrid-s-record-goalscorer-his-career-so-far-2135913">Cristiano Ronaldo overtakes Raul as Real Madrid's record goalscorer -- his career so far</ref>" — <ref target="w:Daily%20News%20and%20Analysis">Daily News and Analysis</ref> , October 17, 2015</item>
<item> . "<ref target="http://www.espnfc.com/real-madrid/story/2619892/cristiano-ronaldo-breaks-rauls-real-madrid-scoring-record">Cristiano Ronaldo breaks Raul's Real Madrid scoring record</ref>" — <ref target="w:ESPN">ESPN</ref> , October 17, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.bbc.com/sport/0/football/34549203">Cristiano Ronaldo officially became Real Madrid's all-time top scorer with a goal as they beat Levante in La Liga.</ref>" — <ref target="w:BBC%20Sport">BBC Sport</ref> , October 17, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.espnfc.com/gamecast/statistics/id/433903/statistics.html">Real Madrid vs Levante UD live football scores</ref>" — <ref target="w:ESPN%20FC">ESPN FC</ref> , October 17, 2015</item>
</list>
</text>
