<text id="autogum_wikinews_doc142" title="Argentina beats Colombia 5-4 over penalties in Copa America quarter final 2015">
<head>Argentina beats Colombia 5-4 over penalties in Copa America quarter final 2015</head>
  

<p>On Friday, <ref target="Argentina">Argentina</ref> defeated <ref target="Colombia">Colombia</ref> in the third quarter- final of the <ref target="w:2015%20Copa%20Am%C3%A9rica">2015</ref> <ref target="Copa%20Am%C3%A9rica">Copa América</ref> which was held in <ref target="w:Estadio%20Sausalito">Estadio Sausalito</ref> stadium in <ref target="w:Vi%C3%B1a%20del%20Mar">Viña del Mar</ref> , <ref target="Chile">Chile</ref>. Argentina defeated Colombia 5&ndash;4 on <ref target="w:Penalty%20shoot-out%20%28association%20football%29">penalty shootout</ref> .</p>

<p>Argentina had more possession in the match. A total of eight <ref target="w:yellow%20card%20%28association%20football%29">yellow cards</ref> were shown for 35 fouls, of which six came in the first half. Colombian goalkeeper <ref target="w:David%20Ospina">David Ospina</ref> denied <ref target="Lionel%20Messi">Messi</ref> and Agüero's on target shots in the first half. Only one substitution was made in the first half. The second half saw just two yellow cards.</p>

<p>At the end of 90 minutes, 4 minutes were added. But, no side could find the net. Since no <ref target="w:Overtime%20%28sports%29">extra time</ref> is added in quarter-finals of Copa America, penalty shoot-out was called. Colombia began the penalty shoot-out. A total of 5 penalties were missed and Tevez's penalty kick converted into goal sealed the victory for Argentina.</p>

<p>Argentina is now to face the winner of Brazil v Paraguay quarter-final on June 30. </p>



 

<p>Squad</p>

<head>Sources</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Jonny Singer. "<ref target="http://www.dailymail.co.uk/sport/football/article-3140997/Argentina-vs-Colombia-Copa-America-2015-LIVE-score-Lionel-Messi-looking-lead-victory.html">Argentina 0-0 Colombia Copa America 2015 REPORT: Carlos Tevez scores winning penalty after ill-tempered draw</ref>" — <ref target="w:Mail%20Online">Mail Online</ref> , June 28, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.bbc.com/sport/0/football/33085867">Argentina 0-0 Columbia (5-4 pens)</ref>" — <ref target="w:BBC%20Sport">BBC Sport</ref> , June 27, 2015</item>
<item> Keeghann Sinanan. "<ref target="http://www.ca2015.com/en/news/mastercard-man-of-the-match/ncjqbunwcbwc1n9c667ycllh8">Messi handed MasterCard Man of the Match award for Argentina</ref>" — <ref target="w:Copa%20Am%C3%A9rica%20Chile%202015">Copa América Chile 2015</ref> , June 26, 2015</item>
</list>
</text>
