<text id="autogum_wikinews_doc299" title="Messi scores hat-trick as Barça become table toppers">
<head>Messi scores hat-trick as Barça become table toppers</head>
  

<p>Yesterday, <ref target="FC%20Barcelona">FC Barcelona</ref> collected three points defeating <ref target="w:Granada">Granada</ref> -based football club <ref target="w:Granada%20CF">Granada CF</ref> 4&ndash;0 at <ref target="w:Camp%20Nou">Camp Nou</ref> in <ref target="Barcelona">Barcelona</ref> in a <ref target="La%20Liga">La Liga</ref> match and became league leaders again.</p>
<p>Barcelona had greater ball possession. The match saw five <ref target="w:yellow%20card%20%28association%20football%29">yellow cards</ref> . Four away players and <ref target="Aleix%20Vidal">Aleix Vidal</ref> of Barcelona were yellow carded. More than thirty fouls were committed in the match. <ref target="Lionel%20Messi">Lionel Messi</ref> scored the first goal of the match in the 8 minute, assisted by debutant <ref target="w:Arda%20Turan">Arda Turan</ref> . Minutes later, <ref target="Uruguay">Uruguayan</ref> <ref target="Luis%20Su%C3%A1rez">Luis Suárez</ref> assisted Messi and he netted the second goal in the 14 minute. <ref target="w:Rub%C3%A9n%20Rochina">Rubén Rochina</ref> was the first player to be booked in the 29 minute. First half ended in 2&ndash;0 with one yellow card shown.</p>
<p>In the second half <ref target="w:Edgar%20M%C3%A9ndez">Edgar Méndez</ref> and <ref target="w:David%20Lomb%C3%A1n">David Lombán</ref> of Granada were booked in 56 and 57 minute. In the next minute, <ref target="Sergi%20Roberto">Sergi Roberto</ref> assisted <ref target="Brazil">Brazilian</ref> <ref target="Neymar">Neymar</ref> whose try to net a goal was saved, but the ball deflected and Messi scored the third goal of the match, completing his hat-trick.</p>

<ref target="w:D%C3%B3ria">Dória</ref> was yellow carded at the 60 minute. Three minuted later, <ref target="Aleix%20Vidal">Aleix Vidal</ref> was yellow carded for a bad foul. Neymar, in the 83 minute, scored the fourth goal of the match assisted by Suárez.

<p>After the match, Barcelona manager <ref target="Luis%20Enrique%20%28footballer%29">Luis Enrique</ref> said "I'm very satisfied with how the team played. Everybody was focused from the beginning and the players knew how important it was to win these three points."</p>

<p>Also yesterday <ref target="Zinedine%20Zidane">Zinedine Zidane</ref>, recently appointed <ref target="Real%20Madrid">Real Madrid</ref>'s new manager, secured a 5&ndash;0 win against <ref target="w:Deportivo%20de%20La%20Coru%C3%B1a">Deportivo</ref> with <ref target="Wales">Welsh</ref> winger <ref target="Gareth%20Bale">Gareth Bale</ref> scoring a hat-trick as well.</p>

<head>Sources</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> "<ref target="http://www.bbc.com/sport/0/football/35264655">Real Madrid 5-0 Deportivo La Coruna</ref>" — <ref target="w:BBC%20Sport">BBC Sport</ref> , January 9, 2016</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.bbc.com/sport/0/football/35264648">Barcelona 4-0 Granada CF</ref>" — <ref target="w:BBC%20Sport">BBC Sport</ref> , January 9, 2016</item>
<item> <ref target="Associated%20Press">Associated Press</ref>. "<ref target="http://www.theguardian.com/football/2016/jan/09/barcelona-granada-la-liga-match-report">Barcelona back on top of La Liga as Lionel Messi hat-trick sees off Granada</ref>" — <ref target="w:The%20Guardian">The Guardian</ref> , January 9, 2016</item>
</list>
</text>
