<text id="autogum_wikinews_doc307" title="Víctor Valdés to play in Belgian Pro League; Manchester United loans Valdés to Standard Liège till season end">
<head>Víctor Valdés to play in Belgian Pro League; Manchester United loans Valdés to Standard Liège till season end</head>
  

<p>On Sunday, <ref target="Manchester%20United">Manchester United</ref> announced the <ref target="w:Loan%20%28sports%29">loan</ref> of their <ref target="Spain">Spanish</ref> goalkeeper <ref target="w:V%C3%ADctor%20Vald%C3%A9s">Víctor Valdés</ref> to <ref target="Belgium">Belgian</ref> club <ref target="w:Standard%20Li%C3%A8ge">Standard Liège</ref> for the rest of the season.</p>

<p>Last year, Valdés signed an 18-month contract with the English club, but the three-time <ref target="w:UEFA%20Champions%20League">UEFA Champions League</ref> winner was given very little opportunity at <ref target="w:Old%20Trafford">Old Trafford</ref> . He made only two appearances for <hi rend="italic">The Reds</hi> last season, after <ref target="w:David%20de%20Gea">David de Gea</ref> was injured. Relations between Manchester United manager <ref target="w:Louis%20van%20Gaal">Louis van Gaal</ref> and Valdés were not good. Van Gaal did not pick him for the pre-season tour to the <ref target="United%20States">United States</ref>, saying Valdés was unwilling to play a game with the under-21 team.</p>

<p>This season, Valdés was not allowed in the locker room, and van Gaal prevented him from training with the main squad and the under-21 team. The official team photograph omitted him.</p>

<p>Valdés was a member of Spain's squad for the World Cup in 2010 and for Euro 2012, collecting a winner's medal both times. Per Manchester United's statement, "Manchester United and Standard Liege have reached agreement for the temporary transfer of goalkeeper Victor Valdes, effective until the end of the current season. The deal is subject to formalities being completed."</p>

<p>On Instagram, he posted a photo that read "Thank you all for your support during these months of hard work for me, i will never forget! See you soon!"</p>


 
<head>Sources</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Saikat. "<ref target="http://soccerlens.com/victor-valdes-joins-standard-liege-on-loan/186502/">Victor Valdes joins Standard Liege on loan</ref>" — <ref target="w:Soccerlens.com">Soccerlens.com</ref> , January 25, 2016</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.bbc.com/sport/0/football/35395568">Victor Valdes: Man Utd keeper joins Standard Liege on loan</ref>" — <ref target="w:BBC%20Sport">BBC Sport</ref> , January 24, 2016</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.manutd.com/en/News-And-Features/Football-News/2016/Jan/victor-valdes-loan-move-agreed-between-standard-liege-and-manchester-united.aspx">Loan move agreed for Victor Valdes</ref>" — <ref target="w:Manchester%20United">Manchester United</ref> , January 24, 2016</item>
<item> Daniel Taylor. "<ref target="http://www.theguardian.com/football/2015/oct/08/victor-valdes-locker-manchester-united-louis-van-gaal">Víctor Valdés not allowed dressing-room locker by Manchester United</ref>" — <ref target="w:The%20Guardian">The Guardian</ref> , October 8, 2015</item>
</list>
</text>
