<text id="autogum_wikinews_doc146" title="Argentina defeats Paraguay 6-1 in Copa America 2015 semi-finals">
<head>Argentina defeats Paraguay 6-1 in Copa America 2015 semi-finals</head>
  

<p>On Tuesday, <ref target="Argentina">Argentina</ref> defeated <ref target="Paraguay">Paraguay</ref> 6&ndash;1 in the second semi-final of the <ref target="w:2015%20Copa%20Am%C3%A9rica">2015</ref> <ref target="Copa%20Am%C3%A9rica">Copa América</ref> which was held in <ref target="w:Concepci%C3%B3n%2C%20Chile">Concepción</ref> city of <ref target="Chile">Chile</ref> to reach the finals.</p>

<p>Argentina had about 60% possession of the ball in front of Paraguay. Two Argentine players and three Paraguayan players were <ref target="w:yellow%20card%20%28association%20football%29">yellow carded</ref> in this match with 31 fouls committed. <ref target="w:Marcos%20Rojo">Marcos Rojo</ref> netted the first goal of the match in the 15 minute, assisted by captain <ref target="Lionel%20Messi">Lionel Messi</ref>. <ref target="w:Javier%20Pastore">Javier Pastore</ref> scored the second goal for Argentina in the 27 minute, also assisted by Messi. Just two minutes before half-time, <ref target="w:Lucas%20Barrios">Lucas Barrios</ref> scored the goal for Paraguay to make the score 2&ndash;1 at half time.</p>

<p>In the second half, <ref target="w:%C3%81ngel%20Di%20Mar%C3%ADa">Ángel Di María</ref> scored two goals in the 47 and 53 minutes, in which the former goal was assisted by Pastore. <ref target="w:Sergio%20Ag%C3%BCero">Sergio Agüero</ref> scored the fifth goal for Argentina in the 80 minute assisted by Di Maria. Three minutes later, <ref target="w:Gonzalo%20Higua%C3%ADn">Higuaín</ref> scored the last goal of the match assisted by Messi. Thus Messi completed a hat-trick of assists in the match.</p>

<p>Argentina now faces Chile in the Copa America final on July 4 at <ref target="Santiago">Santiago</ref>.</p>



 

<head>Sources</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Michael Emons. "<ref target="http://www.bbc.com/sport/0/football/33085956">Argentina 6-1 Paraguay</ref>" — <ref target="w:BBC%20Sport">BBC Sport</ref> , July 1, 2015</item>
<item> <ref target="w:Reuters">Reuters</ref>. "<ref target="http://www.theguardian.com/football/2015/jun/30/argentina-paraguay-six-copa-america">Argentina hit Paraguay for six to reach Copa America final</ref>" — <ref target="w:The%20Guardian">The Guardian</ref> , June 30, 2015</item>
</list>
</text>
