<text id="autogum_wikinews_doc311" title="Guardiola to replace Pellegrini as Manchester City manager">
<head>Guardiola to replace Pellegrini as Manchester City manager</head>
  

<ref target="Manchester">Manchester</ref>-based <ref target="association%20football">football</ref> club <ref target="w:Manchester%20City">Manchester City</ref> today announced their current manager <ref target="w:Manuel%20Pellegrini">Manuel Pellegrini</ref> will remain only to this season's end. Former <ref target="FC%20Barcelona">FC Barcelona</ref> and current <ref target="Bayern%20Munich">Bayern Munich</ref> manager <ref target="Pep%20Guardiola">Pep Guardiola</ref> is to replace the <ref target="Chile">Chilean</ref> next season.
<p>Pellegrini joined City in 2013 and under him they have won the <ref target="w:Premier%20League">Premier League</ref> and the <ref target="w:League%20Cup">League Cup</ref> . Guardiola, winner of two <ref target="Bundesliga">Bundesliga</ref> titles and one <ref target="w:DFB-Pokal">German Cup</ref> with the <ref target="Germany">German</ref> giants Munich, and a two-time <ref target="UEFA%20Champions%20League">Champions League</ref> winner with Barcelona, has signed a three-year contract with Manchester City. Guardiola also won four <ref target="La%20Liga">La Liga</ref> titles with Barcelona, winning fourteen trophies with them in total in four years and making him their most successful manager. He has suffered just nineteen managerial defeats in 239 league matches. </p>

<p>Pellegrini has managed 64 victories out of 99 games in the Premier League &mdash; only <ref target="Jos%C3%A9%20Mourinho">José Mourinho</ref> has a better record from his first 99 Premier League matches. Manchester City are currently second in the league table and in the fifth round of the <ref target="w:FA%20Cup">FA Cup</ref> . Pellegrini was, the announcement noted, in full support of announcing the change.</p>

<p>Former Manchester City player <ref target="w:Trevor%20Sinclair">Trevor Sinclair</ref> , in remarks to <ref target="BBC%20Radio">BBC Radio</ref>, said "He's the hottest manager out there. Every club would want him." <ref target="Liverpool%20F.C.">Liverpool F.C.</ref> manager <ref target="w:J%C3%BCrgen%20Klopp">Jürgen Klopp</ref> , who previously coached <ref target="Munich">Munich</ref> rivals <ref target="Borussia%20Dortmund">Borussia Dortmund</ref>, praised Guardiola saying "He is one of the best managers in the world, no doubt about this. [...] Pep won everything in Spain, nearly everything in Germany, so I think he wants to win everything in England, that is clear."</p>

<p>On December 20, Bayern Munich announced Guardiola would be replaced by former <ref target="Real%20Madrid">Real Madrid</ref> and <ref target="Chelsea%20F.C.">Chelsea F.C.</ref> manager <ref target="w:Carlo%20Ancelotti">Carlo Ancelotti</ref> . The <ref target="Italy">Italian</ref> has won three Champions League titles in his coaching career.</p>


 
<head>Related news</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> "<ref target="Ancelotti%20to%20replace%20Guardiola%20as%20Bayern%20Munich%20manager">Ancelotti to replace Guardiola as Bayern Munich manager</ref>" — <ref target="Main_Page">Wikinews</ref>, December 21, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="J%C3%BCrgen%20Klopp%20signs%203%20year%20contract%20with%20Liverpool">Jürgen Klopp signs 3 year contract with Liverpool</ref>" — <ref target="Main_Page">Wikinews</ref>, October 10, 2015</item>
</list>


<head>Sources</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> "<ref target="http://www.bbc.com/sport/football/35461090">Pep Guardiola to succeed Manuel Pellegrini as Manchester City boss</ref>" — <ref target="w:BBC%20Sport">BBC Sport</ref> , February 1, 2016</item>
<item> <ref target="International%20Federation%20of%20Association%20Football">FIFA</ref>. "<ref target="https://www.instagram.com/p/BBPvZoknwK1/">FIFAWORLDCUP on Instagram</ref>" — <ref target="w:Instagram">Instagram</ref> , February 1, 2016</item>
</list>


<head>External Links</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> "<ref target="https://www.mcfc.co.uk/News/Team-news/2016/February/Club-statement-1-February/1454330178">Club Statement</ref>" — <ref target="w:Manchester%20City">Manchester City</ref> , February 1, 2016</item>
</list>
</text>
