<text id="autogum_wikinews_doc262" title="Barça thrashes Real Madrid 4-0 in first El Clásico 2015/2016">
<head>Barça thrashes Real Madrid 4-0 in first El Clásico 2015/2016</head>
  

<p>On Saturday, <ref target="w:Catalonia">Catalonia</ref> based <ref target="w:association%20football">football</ref> club <ref target="w:FC%20Barcelona">FC Barcelona</ref> defeated their arch rivals <ref target="w:Real%20Madrid">Real Madrid</ref> 4&ndash;0 at <ref target="w:Santiago%20Bernab%C3%A9u%20Stadium">Santiago Bernabéu Stadium</ref> in <ref target="w:Madrid">Madrid</ref> in a <ref target="Spain">Spanish</ref> <ref target="w:La%20Liga">La Liga</ref> match. </p>

<p>Barça had greater ball possession. The match saw five <ref target="w:yellow%20card%20%28association%20football%29">yellow cards</ref> and one <ref target="w:red%20card%20%28association%20football%29">red card</ref> . Three Madrid players were yellow carded with a total of 23 fouls committed in the match. </p>

<ref target="Uruguay">Uruguayan</ref> striker <ref target="w:Luis%20Su%C3%A1rez">Luis Suárez</ref> scored the first goal of the match in the 11 minute by an assist from <ref target="w:Sergi%20Roberto">Sergi Roberto</ref> . The first booking came in the 23 minute. <ref target="w:James%20Rodr%C3%ADguez">James Rodríguez</ref> went down in the booking list. The first substitution of the match came in the 27 minute when <ref target="Argentina">Argentine</ref> <ref target="w:Mascherano">Mascherano</ref> got injured and <ref target="France">Frenchman</ref> <ref target="w:J%C3%A9r%C3%A9my%20Mathieu">Jérémy Mathieu</ref> was substituted in for him.

<p>Right back <ref target="w:Dani%20Alves">Dani Alves</ref> was booked in the 31 minute for his foul on <ref target="w:Cristiano%20Ronaldo">Cristiano Ronaldo</ref> . During that foul, Alves got injured and the match was interrupted for a while. In the 39 minute, Neymar assisted by <ref target="w:Andr%C3%A9s%20Iniesta">Andrés Iniesta</ref> doubled the lead for the Catalonians. The first half ended 2&ndash;0 with Barcelona leading in the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="w:El%20Cl%C3%A1sico">El Clásico</ref> </hi>.</p>
<p>Real Madrid's <ref target="w:Sergio%20Ramos">Sergio Ramos</ref> was shown the yellow card in the 51 minute. Two minutes later, Neymar assisted Iniesta who scored in the top right corner making the score 3&ndash;0 for the visitors.</p>

<ref target="w:Isco">Isco</ref> was substituted in for James Rodríguez for <hi rend="italic">Los Blancos</hi> in the 55 minute. Two minutes later, <ref target="w:Lionel%20Messi">Lionel Messi</ref> was sustituted in for <ref target="Croatia">Croatian</ref> <ref target="w:Ivan%20Rakiti%C4%87">Ivan Rakitić</ref> after two months of knee injury. <ref target="w:Daniel%20Carvajal">Daniel Carvajal</ref> replaced Brazilian <ref target="w:Marcelo%20Vieira">Marcelo</ref> in the 59 minute. This was Messi's first appearence since September 26.

<ref target="w:Jordi%20Alba">Jordi Alba</ref> assisted Suárez in the 74 minute and he scored in the left corner. Iniesta was substituted off at the 77 minute for <ref target="w:Munir%20El%20Haddadi">Munir El Haddadi</ref> and got a standing ovation from the Bernabéu croud.

<p>Further in the match, Carvajal was yellow carded in the 83 minute and Isco was red carded in the next minute. Two extra minutes were added in which <ref target="w:Sergio%20Busquets">Sergio Busquets</ref> was booked for a foul.</p>

<p>Barcelona had 87% passing accuracy as compared to 83% of <hi rend="italic">Los Blancos</hi>. Andrés Iniesta was awarded as man of the match. Neymar remains the top scorer of <ref target="w:2015%E2%80%9316%20La%20Liga">2015–16 La Liga</ref> with twelve goals.</p>

<p>Barcelona got 6 points clear of Real Madrid and is at the top of the La Liga table.</p>


 

<head>Sources</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Gary Rose. "<ref target="http://www.bbc.com/sport/0/football/34849342">Real Madrid 0-4 Barcelona</ref>" — <ref target="w:BBC%20Sport">BBC Sport</ref> , November 21, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.goal.com/en-india/match/real-madrid-vs-barcelona/2086376/stats%3FICID%3DMP_MS_4">Real Madrid 0 - Barcelona 4 Match Stats</ref>" — <ref target="w:Goal.com">Goal.com</ref> , November 21, 2015</item>
</list>
</text>
