<text id="autogum_wikinews_doc246" title="FIFA World Cup: Germany defeats Argentina in U-17">
<head>FIFA World Cup: Germany defeats Argentina in U-17</head>
  
<p>On Wednesday, the <ref target="w:Germany%20national%20youth%20football%20team">Germany national youth football team</ref> defeated the <ref target="w:Argentina%20national%20under-17%20football%20team">Argentina national under-17 football team</ref> 4&ndash;0 in a <ref target="w:2015%20FIFA%20U-17%20World%20Cup">2015 FIFA U-17 World Cup</ref> group stage match. The match was held in <ref target="w:Estadio%20Municipal%20Nelson%20Oyarz%C3%BAn%20Arenas">Estadio Municipal Nelson Oyarzún Arenas</ref> stadium in the city of <ref target="w:Chill%C3%A1n">Chillán</ref> , <ref target="Chile">Chile</ref>.</p>
<p>Germany had greater ball possession than the Argentines. </p>

<p>A total of five players were <ref target="w:Yellow%20card%20%28association%20football%29">yellow carded</ref> &ndash;three cards for Argentina and two for Germany. 32 fouls were committed in the match. </p>

<p>Janelt scored the first goal in the opening minutes of the game which was <ref target="w:assist%20%28football%29">assisted</ref> by Köhlert. </p>

<p>In the 32 minute, Eggestein scored a goal assisted by Passlack. </p>

<p>Germany was awarded a <ref target="w:penalty%20kick">penalty kick</ref> in the 45 minute because of a foul committed by Ferreyra. He was booked for the foul, and Passlack scored the penalty. The first half ended 3&ndash;0 with three yellow cards issued.</p>

<p>At the beginning of the second half, two substitutions for Argentina and one for Germany took place. </p>

<p>In the 67 minute, Janelt assisted Schmidt and the score-board was 4&ndash;0. </p>

<p>Germany, in Group C, is at the top of its group table and has advanced to the knockout stage.</p>



 

<head>Match statistics</head>
<head>Sister link</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="w:2015%20FIFA%20U-17%20World%20Cup%23Group%20C">2015 FIFA U-17 World Cup</ref></item>
</list>


<head>Sources</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> "<ref target="http://theworldgame.sbs.com.au/match/2037224/argentina-u17-vs-germany-u17/live">Argentina U17 vs Germany U17</ref>" — <ref target="w:The%20World%20Game">The World Game</ref> , October 22, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.fifa.com/u17worldcup/matches/round%3D271783/match%3D300298401/report.html%23nosticky">Match Report</ref>" — <ref target="w:FIFA">FIFA</ref> , October 21, 2015</item>
</list>
</text>
