<text id="autogum_wikinews_doc31" title="Explorers find shipwreck thought to be massive WWII battleship Musashi">
<head>Explorers find shipwreck thought to be massive WWII battleship Musashi</head>
  

<p>Billionaire <ref target="Microsoft">Microsoft</ref> co-founder <ref target="w:Paul%20Allen">Paul Allen</ref> yesterday announced his ocean exploration team has found a wreck thought to be the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="w:Japanese%20battleship%20Musashi">Musashi</ref> </hi>, one of the largest warships ever built. The <hi rend="italic">Musashi</hi> was a <ref target="Japan">Japan</ref>ese battleship sunk by <ref target="US">US</ref> forces during <ref target="World%20War%20Two">World War Two</ref>.</p>

<p>The wreck was discovered yesterday local time under a <ref target="w:kilometre">kilometre</ref> of water in the <ref target="w:Sibuyan%20Sea">Sibuyan Sea</ref> , off the <ref target="Philippines">Filipino</ref> coast. Together with <ref target="w:Yamato-class%20battleship">sister ship</ref> <ref target="w:Japanese%20battleship%20Yamato"><hi rend="italic">Yamato</hi></ref> the <hi rend="italic">Musashi</hi> fought in the <ref target="w:Battle%20of%20Leyte%20Gulf">Battle of Leyte Gulf</ref> , one of the war's biggest sea fights.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Musashi</hi> sank on October 24, 1944, during the battle and two years after commissioning. Over 1,000 crew died. Well-armed with 18-inch guns, the 263<ref target="w:metre">m</ref> (862<ref target="w:foot%20%28unit%29">ft</ref> ) ship struggled to defend itself against waves of aircraft launched from US carriers. <hi rend="italic">Musashi</hi> fired into the water, creating large geysers to knock incoming bombers out of the sky. Eighteen planes were downed.</p>

<p>The battle was won by the US and <ref target="Australia">Australia</ref>, defeating Japan. <hi rend="italic">Yamato</hi> escaped with damage but was sunk the following year, also by US forces. The two battleships were the <ref target="w:Japanese%20Imperial%20Navy">Japanese Imperial Navy</ref> 's centrepieces. <hi rend="italic">Musashi</hi> boasted a 22-<ref target="w:mile">mile</ref> reach with its nine main guns, and seven aircraft.</p>

<p>If confirmed, the find completes Allen's eight-year search for the <hi rend="italic">Musashi</hi>. Following seabed mapping the wreck was found using an <ref target="remotely%20operated%20underwater%20vehicles">ROV</ref>. One of the world's richest people, Allen has reportedly invested much of his wealth in marine exploration and began his quest to find the <hi rend="italic">Musashi</hi> out of a lifelong interest in the war.</p>



 
<head>Sources</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> "<ref target="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-31724995">Japan's WW2 'Musashi battleship wreck found'</ref>" — <ref target="w:BBC%20News%20Online">BBC News Online</ref> , March 4, 2015</item>
<item> Manabu Sasaki. "<ref target="http://ajw.asahi.com/article/behind_news/social_affairs/AJ201503040050">Wreck of battleship Musashi said found off Philippines</ref>" — <ref target="w:Asahi%20Shimbun">Asahi Shimbun</ref> , March 4, 2015</item>
</list>
</text>
