<text id="autogum_wikinews_doc105" title="Jim Murphy announces resignation as Scottish Labour Party leader">
<head>Jim Murphy announces resignation as Scottish Labour Party leader</head>
  
<ref target="Jim%20Murphy">Jim Murphy</ref> yesterday announced he intends to stand down as <ref target="Scottish%20Labour%20Party">Scottish Labour Party</ref> leader next month, after narrowly surviving a <ref target="w:Motion%20of%20no%20confidence">no confidence</ref> vote. Murphy said he will present a list of suggested reforms to be made to the party, including changing the system for electing party leader to <ref target="w:One%20member%2C%20one%20vote">one member, one vote</ref> , upon offering his resignation at the next meeting of its national executive in June. Murphy also said he will not stand for the <ref target="Scottish%20Parliament">Scottish Parliament</ref> <ref target="w:Scottish%20Parliament%20general%20election%2C%202016">election in May 2016</ref> and will "do something else". 

<p>At a meeting in the <ref target="Scotland">Scottish</ref> city <ref target="Glasgow">Glasgow</ref> yesterday, the party's national executive held a vote of no confidence in Murphy; he won by 17 votes to 14. "Today I received more support in the executive vote than I did from members of the executive when I stood for election five months ago", Murphy said. Murphy became Scottish Labour leader in December 2014, following <ref target="w:Johann%20Lamont">Johann Lamont</ref> 's resignation from the role. Until Scottish Labour holds a fresh leadership election &mdash; its sixth in a span of eight years &mdash; <ref target="w:Kezia%20Dugdale">Kezia Dugdale</ref> , currently the party's deputy leader, is to assume the role of acting leader for the time being. Murphy cited concerns about Scottish Labour being divided as a contributory factor to his decision. "Scotland needs a strong Labour party; Scotland needs a united Labour party", he said yesterday. "We have been the greatest force for change in our nation’s remarkable history. The Scottish Labour party will rise again. It will be under someone else’s leadership and I am confident about my party’s future."</p>

<p>The announcement came nine days after the party lost all but one of its 41 <ref target="Scotland">Scottish</ref> seats, including Murphy's <ref target="w:East%20Renfrewshire%20%28UK%20Parliament%20constituency%29">East Renfrewshire constituency</ref> , to the <ref target="Scottish%20National%20Party">Scottish National Party</ref> (SNP) in a <ref target="United%20Kingdom">UK</ref> <ref target="Conservatives%20win%20majority%20in%202015%20UK%20general%20election">general election</ref>, and eight days after <ref target="Ed%20Miliband">Ed Miliband</ref> said he would stand down as leader of the <ref target="UK%20Labour%20Party">UK Labour Party</ref>.</p>

<p>There was controversy regarding whether Murphy should retain his role following this performance. Labour Party supporters were reportedly asked to sign a letter supporting Murphy's leadership, to be presented at the executive meeting yesterday. Calls for Murphy to resign came from multiple quarters, including <ref target="trade%20union">trade union</ref>s <ref target="w:Unite%20the%20Union">Unite</ref> and <ref target="w:Associated%20Society%20of%20Locomotive%20Engineers%20and%20Firemen">ASLEF</ref> , as well as Labour <ref target="Member%20of%20the%20Scottish%20Parliament">MSP</ref>s <ref target="w:Alex%20Rowley">Alex Rowley</ref> and <ref target="w:Elaine%20Smith%20%28Scottish%20politician%29">Elaine Smith</ref> . Earlier in the week, Unite general secretary <ref target="w:Len%20McCluskey">Len McCluskey</ref> said "the anti-Scottish card that was played by <ref target="w:Lynton%20Crosby">Lynton Crosby</ref> and the <ref target="Conservative%20Party%20%28UK%29">Conservatives</ref>" had caused them to win a majority in the general election, before going on to say: "I lay the blame for that very squarely at the feet of Scottish Labour. Not only have they lost Scotland but I think they've been responsible for making certain that the Conservatives were back in power in <ref target="w:Government%20of%20the%20United%20Kingdom">Westminster</ref> ." However, trade unions <ref target="w:Union%20of%20Shop%2C%20Distributive%20and%20Allied%20Workers">USDAW</ref> and <ref target="w:Community%20%28trade%20union%29">Community</ref> were amongst those supporting Murphy's continued leadership. </p>

<p>In a speech, Murphy suggested he did he did not want the party to be divided as a result of his leadership. "It is clear that the small minority who didn’t accept my election as party leader by the majority five months ago also won’t accept the vote of the Executive today and will continue to divide the party if I remain", he said. Murphy singled out McCluskey for criticism, claiming to have "been at the centre of a campaign by the London leadership of the Unite union in blaming myself and the Scottish Labour party for the defeat of the UK Labour party in the general election. That is a grotesque insult to the Scottish Labour party." He went on to criticise what he called McCluskey's "destructive behaviour", commenting that: "Whether in Scotland, or in the contest to come across the UK, we cannot have our leaders selected or deselected by the grudges and grievances of one prominent man. The leader of the Scottish Labour Party doesn’t serve at the grace of Len McCluskey and the next leader of the UK Labour Party should not be picked by Len McCluskey."</p>

<p>Reacting to the news, SNP leader and Scottish <ref target="w:First%20Minister%20of%20Scotland">First Minister</ref> <ref target="Nicola%20Sturgeon">Nicola Sturgeon</ref> <ref target="twitter">tweeted</ref>: "I wish Jim Murphy all the very best for the future. Leadership is not easy and he deserves credit for standing up for what he believes in." <ref target="Scottish%20Liberal%20Democrat%20Party">Scottish Liberal Democrats</ref> leader <ref target="w:Willie%20Rennie">Willie Rennie</ref> said: "Credit to [Murphy]. He stepped up and energetically campaigned for his beliefs. I wish him the best for the future." <ref target="w:Harriet%20Harman">Harriet Harman</ref> , the acting leader of the UK Labour Party, said Murphy had been a "hugely important figure" for them, adding: "Jim has given so much to the Labour Party over the last twenty years. He, I know reluctantly, took the responsibility for leading Scottish Labour at the most difficult election they have ever faced. He did so with incredible energy, purpose and dignity [...] He leaves with the best wishes and thanks of our movement."</p>

<ref target="Scottish%20Green%20Party">Scottish Green Party</ref> <ref target="wikt:convenor">co-convenor</ref> <ref target="w:Patrick%20Harvie">Patrick Harvie</ref> was more critical in his response, arguing the Greens should be the opposition of the Scottish Parliament instead. Harvie said Murphy's resignation was "almost inevitable, but even as he announced it he promised to further weaken Labour’s relationship with the wider labour movement. People haven’t left Labour because of the trade unions, but because the party itself long ago strayed from its principles. Without a clear sense of purpose, it has seemed to care only about holding office instead of creating new ideas for a better society. It’s clear that the Scottish Parliament needs an opposition that’s creative and challenging, but which can act constructively too."

<ref target="Scottish%20Conservative%20Party">Scottish Conservative Party</ref> leader <ref target="w:Ruth%20Davidson">Ruth Davidson</ref> tweeted: "Jim Murphy announces a managed exit in order to help the party, which is to his credit. But leaves a tough gig for whoever comes next."

<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> asked Unite the Union to comment on the story and has yet to receive a response. However, Pat Rafferty, Unite's Scotland leader, earlier stated: "Jim has done the decent thing. Scottish Labour needs to recover, re-engage and reform. It can now begin that process."</p>

<head>Related articles</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> "<ref target="UK%20Independence%20Party%20reject%20leader%27s%20resignation">UK Independence Party reject leader's resignation</ref>" — <ref target="Main_Page">Wikinews</ref>, May 11, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="Conservatives%20win%20majority%20in%202015%20UK%20general%20election">Conservatives win majority in 2015 UK general election</ref>" — <ref target="Main_Page">Wikinews</ref>, May 9, 2015</item>
</list>


<head>Sources</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> "<ref target="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-scotland-scotland-politics-32760196">Scottish Labour leader Jim Murphy to resign</ref>" — <ref target="w:BBC%20News%20Online">BBC News Online</ref> , May 16, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="https://archive.is/RLWxF">Scotland needs a strong Labour party</ref>" — <ref target="w:Scottish%20Labour%20Party">Scottish Labour Party</ref> , May 16, 2015 (access date)</item>
<item> Debi Edward. "<ref target="http://www.itv.com/news/2015-05-16/whoever-replaces-jim-murphy-faces-an-even-bigger-task/">Whoever replaces Jim Murphy faces an even bigger task</ref>" — <ref target="w:ITV%20News">ITV News</ref> , May 16, 2015</item>
<item> <ref target="w:Nicola%20Sturgeon">Nicola Sturgeon</ref>. "<ref target="https://twitter.com/NicolaSturgeon/status/599566155246903296">I wish Jim Murphy all the very best for the future</ref>" — <ref target="w:Twitter">Twitter</ref> , May 16, 2015</item>
<item> <ref target="w:Ruth%20Davidson">Ruth Davidson</ref>. "<ref target="https://twitter.com/RuthDavidsonMSP/status/599567822218522624">Jim Murphy announces a managed exit in order to help the party, which is to his credit</ref>" — <ref target="w:Twitter">Twitter</ref> , May 16, 2015</item>
<item> <ref target="w:Willie%20Rennie">Willie Rennie</ref>. "<ref target="https://twitter.com/willie_rennie/status/599570564269871105">Credit to @jimforscotland</ref>" — <ref target="w:Twitter">Twitter</ref> , May 16, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.itv.com/news/update/2015-05-16/murphy-led-scottish-labour-with-energy-and-dignity/">Murphy led Scottish Labour with 'energy and dignity'</ref>" — <ref target="w:ITV%20News">ITV News</ref> , May 16, 2015</item>
<item> Patrick Harvie. "<ref target="http://www.scottishgreens.org.uk/news/harvie-responds-to-murphy-resignation/">Harvie responds to Murphy resignation</ref>" — <ref target="w:Scottish%20Green%20Party">Scottish Green Party</ref> , May 16, 2015</item>
<item> <ref target="w:Unite%20the%20Union">Unite the Union</ref>. "<ref target="https://twitter.com/unitetheunion/status/599607983396519936">Pat Rafferty, leader of Unite in Scotland on the resignation of Jim Murphy (1/2)</ref>" — <ref target="w:Twitter">Twitter</ref> , May 16, 2015</item>
<item> <ref target="w:Unite%20the%20Union">Unite the Union</ref>. "<ref target="https://twitter.com/unitetheunion/status/599608189022314496">"Scottish Labour needs to recover (2/2)</ref>" — <ref target="w:Twitter">Twitter</ref> , May 16, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-scotland-scotland-politics-32742516">Unite boss McCluskey blames Tory win on Scottish Labour</ref>" — <ref target="w:BBC%20News%20Online">BBC News Online</ref> , May 14, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-scotland-scotland-politics-32729492">Jim Murphy supporters asked to sign letter backing his leadership</ref>" — <ref target="w:BBC%20News%20Online">BBC News Online</ref> , May 13, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/election-2015-scotland-32703365">Alex Rowley and Elaine Smith call for Jim Murphy to resign</ref>" — <ref target="w:BBC%20News%20Online">BBC News Online</ref> , May 12, 2015</item>
</list>
</text>
