<text id="autogum_wikinews_doc254" title="Romanian Prime Minister resigns after nightclub fire">
<head>Romanian Prime Minister resigns after nightclub fire</head>
  

<p>In the aftermath of a deadly nightclub fire in <ref target="Romania">Romania</ref> last week, yesterday Prime Minister of Romania <ref target="Victor%20Ponta">Victor Ponta</ref> announced his resignation, stating "I'm handing in my mandate, I'm resigning, and implicitly my government too".</p>

<p>The announcement came after around 20,000 protesters marched through <ref target="Bucharest">Bucharest</ref> on Tuesday night, blaming the government for lax regulation and corruption. During his televised resignation speech, Ponta said he hoped "the government's resignation will satisfy the people who came out in the streets". However, yesterday night as many as 30,000 protesters demonstrated, demanding further political reform.</p>

<p>The recent protests express deep-seated concern about political corruption in Romania. Ponta is currently on trial for a series of corruption charges, which he denies.</p>

<p>Ponta's resignation came alongside the resignation of <ref target="w:Gabriel%20Oprea">Gabriel Oprea</ref> , who was serving as Interior Minister.</p>

<p>Victor Ponta says he will remain Prime Minister until a temporary replacement is chosen by the President of Romania. Forming a new government might take some time, and could result in elections if the President is unable to find a Prime Minister who can form a government.</p>



 

<head>Related news</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> "<ref target="Romanian%20nightclub%20fire%20kills%20over%20two%20dozen">Romanian nightclub fire kills over two dozen</ref>" — <ref target="Main_Page">Wikinews</ref>, October 31, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="Romanian%20PM%20Victor%20Ponta%20indicted%20in%20fraud%20case">Romanian PM Victor Ponta indicted in fraud case</ref>" — <ref target="Main_Page">Wikinews</ref>, September 17, 2015</item>
</list>
<head>Sister links</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
</list>


<head>Sources</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="w:Agence%20France-Presse">AFP</ref> , <ref target="w:Reuters">Reuters</ref>. "<ref target="http://www.aljazeera.com/news/2015/11/romanians-hold-mass-protests-pm-resignation-151105012032886.html">Romanians hold mass protests despite PM's resignation</ref>" — <ref target="w:Al%20Jazeera">Al Jazeera</ref> , November 5, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-34726826">Romania: Protests despite Victor Ponta's resignation</ref>" — <ref target="w:BBC%20News%20Online">BBC News Online</ref> , November 5, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-34720183">Romania PM Ponta resigns over Bucharest nightclub fire</ref>" — <ref target="w:BBC%20News%20Online">BBC News Online</ref> , November 4, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.aljazeera.com/news/2015/11/romania-pm-ponta-resigns-nightclub-fire-151104090455498.html">Romania PM Ponta resigns over nightclub fire</ref>" — <ref target="w:Al%20Jazeera">Al Jazeera</ref> , November 4, 2015</item>
</list>
</text>
