<text id="autogum_wikinews_doc252" title="Mourinho has nothing to say as Klopp gets first Premier League victory">
<head>Mourinho has nothing to say as Klopp gets first Premier League victory</head>
  

<p>Yesterday, <ref target="w:Liverpool%20F.C.">Liverpool F.C.</ref> defeated <ref target="w:Chelsea%20F.C.">Chelsea F.C.</ref> 3&ndash;1 in the English <ref target="w:Premier%20League">Premier League</ref> <ref target="w:association%20football">football</ref> match held at <ref target="w:Stamford%20Bridge%20%28stadium%29">Stamford Bridge stadium</ref> . This was the sixth defeat of the season for Chelsea manager <ref target="Jos%C3%A9%20Mourinho">José Mourinho</ref> and the first victory for recently-appointed Liverpool manager <ref target="w:J%C3%BCrgen%20Klopp">Jürgen Klopp</ref> in a Premier League match. Throughout the match Liverpool, nicknamed <hi rend="italic">The Reds</hi> had much more possession of the ball than Chelsea. 30 fouls were committed, including 21 by Liverpool, and five <ref target="w:yellow%20card%20%28association%20football%29">yellow cards</ref> were handed out with four going to Liverpool.</p>

<ref target="Brazil">Brazilian</ref> <ref target="w:Ramires">Ramires</ref> scored in the opening minutes of the game with a header from <ref target="w:C%C3%A9sar%20Azpilicueta">César Azpilicueta</ref> 's corner kick. <ref target="w:Philippe%20Coutinho">Coutinho</ref> committed a foul on <ref target="w:Willian%20Borges%20da%20Silva">Willian</ref> and was shown a yellow card. Later, in the injury time of the first half of the game, Coutinho scored a goal, providing the equaliser for Klopp's side. The first half ended with both teams level at 1&ndash;1.

<p>In the 65 minute, Chelsea striker <ref target="w:Diego%20Costa">Diego Costa</ref> avoided a red card for a brutal foul on <ref target="w:Martin%20%C5%A0krtel">Martin Škrtel</ref> . Coutinho scored a second goal in the 74minute, assisted by <ref target="w:Christian%20Benteke">Christian Benteke</ref> , providing Liverpool with a 2&ndash;1 lead. Benteke further widened the gap in the 83 minute, with help from <ref target="w:Jordon%20Ibe">Jordon Ibe</ref> .</p>

<p>Coutinho was awarded the <hi rend="italic">Man of the Match</hi> award. This was the 400 Premier League cap of Liverpool winger <ref target="w:James%20Milner">James Milner</ref> . </p>

<p>After the match, Klopp expressed admiration for Mourinho saying "he's one of the best in the world." Mourinho repeatedly refused to say anything in a post-match interview. He is under pressure because Chelsea, the defending champions, are fighting <ref target="wikt:relegation">relegation</ref> and earlier this week, they lost to <ref target="w:Stoke%20City">Stoke City</ref> 5&ndash;4 in a penalty shoot-out in the <ref target="w:2015%E2%80%9316%20Football%20League%20Cup">2015-16</ref> <ref target="w:Football%20League%20Cup">Football League Cup</ref> .</p>

<p>Chelsea are scheduled to face <ref target="Ukraine">Ukrainian</ref> club <ref target="w:FC%20Dynamo%20Kyiv">Dynamo Kiev</ref> in a <ref target="w:UEFA%20Champions%20League">UEFA Champions League</ref> fixture on Wednesday, November 4. Meanwhile Liverpool will be travelling to Russia on Thursday, November 5, to play against <ref target="w:Rubin%20Kazan">Rubin Kazan</ref> in the <ref target="w:Europa%20League">Europa League</ref> .</p>



 

<head>Match stats</head>
<head>Related news</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> "<ref target="J%C3%BCrgen%20Klopp%20signs%203%20year%20contract%20with%20Liverpool">Jürgen Klopp signs 3 year contract with Liverpool</ref>" — <ref target="Main_Page">Wikinews</ref>, October 10, 2015</item>
</list>


<head>Sources</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Phil McNulty. "<ref target="http://www.bbc.com/sport/0/football/34623902">Liverpool piled the pressure on Chelsea manager Jose Mourinho as Jurgen Klopp secured a hugely impressive first Premier League win since taking charge at Anfield</ref>" — <ref target="w:BBC%20Sport">BBC Sport</ref> , October 31, 2015</item>
<item> Barry Glendenning. "<ref target="http://www.theguardian.com/football/live/2015/oct/31/chelsea-v-liverpool-premier-league-live">Liverpool came from behind to inflict an emphatic defeat on Chelsea courtesy of a Philippe Coutinho brace and one from Christian Benteke</ref>" — <ref target="w:The%20Guardian">The Guardian</ref> , October 31, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.bbc.co.uk/sport/0/football/34577998">Stoke City 1-1 Chelsea (5-4 on pens)</ref>" — <ref target="w:BBC%20Sport">BBC Sport</ref> , October 27, 2015</item>
</list>
</text>
