<text id="autogum_wikinews_doc26" title="Peterborough United F.C. manager Darren Ferguson leaves club">
<head>Peterborough United F.C. manager Darren Ferguson leaves club</head>
  

<ref target="w:Darren%20Ferguson">Darren Ferguson</ref> resigned yesterday as the manager of <ref target="w:Peterborough%20United%20F.C.">Peterborough United</ref> <ref target="Football%20%28soccer%29">Football Club</ref>. His departure comes after a 3&ndash;0 defeat yesterday to <ref target="w:MK%20Dons%20F.C.">MK Dons</ref> . Peterborough United are currently in fifteenth position of <ref target="w:Football%20League%20One">League One</ref> , the third <ref target="w:English%20football%20league%20system">tier</ref> of <ref target="England">English</ref> football. 

<p>Peterborough United's chairman, <ref target="w:Darragh%20MacAnthony">Darragh MacAnthony</ref> , released a statement on the club's website regarding the resignation. He said "It saddens me to say that the club has this evening parted ways with one of the finest managers in our clubs history. After Speaking with Darren, he feels that a new challenge is needed for both himself and the football club."</p>

<p>MacAnthony also spoke about the club's current performance. He said "I’m personally very disappointed in our current league position, the performances from our playing squad and the fact that we have dropped way below our own standards that we set out at as a football club."</p>

<p>Ferguson has managed Peterborough United twice. He had previously led the team from 2007 to 2009. Over his two tenures he has twice led the team to the <ref target="w:Football%20League%20Championship">Championship</ref> , the second tier of English football.</p>

<p>With Ferguson's resignation five other coaches and officials have left the club. Dave Robertson, the academy manger, has been put in caretaker charge and is to lead the club until a replacement manager has been found.</p>

<p>Darren Ferguson is the son of former <ref target="w:Manchester%20United%20F.C">Manchester United</ref> manager <ref target="w:Alex%20Ferguson">Sir Alex Ferguson</ref> .</p>



 
<head>Sources</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> "<ref target="http://www.bbc.co.uk/sport/0/football/31571698">Darren Ferguson: Peterborough boss leaves after MK Dons defeat</ref>" — <ref target="w:BBC%20Sport">BBC Sport</ref> , February 21, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www1.skysports.com/football/news/12040/9726645/darren-ferguson-has-parted-company-with-league-one-side-peterborough">Darren Ferguson has parted company with League One side Peterborough</ref>" — <ref target="w:Sky%20Sports">Sky Sports</ref> , February 21, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.theposh.com/news/article/statement-2287144.aspx">Official Statement From Darragh MacAnthony</ref>" — <ref target="w:Peterborough%20United%20F.C.">Peterborough United F.C.</ref> , February 21, 2015</item>
<item> "<ref target="http://www.bbc.co.uk/sport/0/football/31466272">MK Dons 3-0 Peterborough United</ref>" — <ref target="w:BBC%20Sport">BBC Sport</ref> , February 21, 2015</item>
</list>
</text>
