<text id="autogum_academic_doc121" title="You Can’t See the Woods for the Trees: Invasive Acer negundo L. in Urban Riparian Forests Harms Biodiversity and Limits Recreation Activity" shortTile="t-see-woods-trees" author="Daria Sikorska, Piotr Sikorski, Piotr Archiciński, Jarosław Chormański, Richard  J. Hopkins" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5838/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The increasing urban population of cities worldwide combined with anxiety over the life quality of residents has resulted in an increasing interest in the benefits to be derived from city green areas. Many cities were established on the banks of rivers, and frequently the remnants of former riparian forests constitute an important part of the green systems of the city. Despite remaining under strong anthropogenic pressure, including land-use change, pollution, lack of cyclic flooding, human trampling, or the introduction of non-indigenous organisms, riparian ecosystems generate multiple important services for the city residents. Natural riparian forests are recognized for their positive contribution to nutrient removal, carbon capture, air purification, pollination, noise buffering, and water cleaning. The few examples of riparian forests which were preserved in cities play an additional important role by contributing recreation opportunities to citizens and allowing them to interact with nature. The role of recreation in city green spaces in improving citizen health and well-being has been widely recognized and is regarded as one of the most important ecosystem services urban green spaces offer. More and more studies also reveal an increasing demand from city residents for “less ordered” green areas providing the possibility to experience nature more directly than the traditional urban green spaces, such as parks, can offer. </p>

<p>Physical disturbances to nature in cities, such as pollution, drought, or drainage, lead to irreversible changes in the existing ecosystems. Preserving high biodiversity in urban environments faces major difficulties, and river valleys are additionally highly susceptible to other negative changes, including a high risk of biological invasions. Invasive plant species (IAS) not only severely alter the biodiversity of the areas they colonize, but can also alter the ecosystem services provisioning by those areas. The negative effects of various IAS on ecosystem services provisioning were recognized for multiple services. The impact of different IAS on the provision of ecosystem services is considered negative, listing these more important effects—they hinder land use, thus limiting food production, replace natural ecosystems as barriers for many human pathogens to their easier dissemination, attract native pollinator species, thus decreasing their activity on native plant species, colonize water banks, and are ineffective in coastal stabilization, and reduce recreational and tourist benefits. IAS species also provide certain benefits, but the economic balance seems to be unfavorable for these species. </p>

<p>Yet little is known about the impact of IAS on recreational ecosystem services (RES), as one of the cultural ecosystem services, understood as “the contributions to recreation opportunities”. Even less is known about ecosystem services in riparian forests due to their scarcity and the difficulties in recreational potential assessment, and the socio-cultural context of the human perception of invasive species is also very poorly understood. Nature preservation in cities is strongly driven by social approval, and a participatory approach to spatial urban planning has become good practice. Consequently, it is crucial to recognize if IAS in urban areas, riparian forests in particular, affect the perception of urban green areas and result in a decline of ecosystem service provisioning. Invasive tree species are common in urban forests, and are likely to remain so due to low effectiveness of removal actions, yet little is known concerning their perception as a component of natural vegetation remnants or regenerating forms. Invasive tree species can affect ecosystem services provisioning, but also change their visual appearance, which can affect how people use the space. Invasive plant species may likely be perceived negatively by the public and be associated with their environmental impact, but still a significant share of society might have no negative attitude towards the presence of invasive species. Many plants, now declared as invasive species, were deliberately introduced to urban recreational areas due to their aesthetic values, and despite any ecosystem services lost services, such as use in medicine or biofuels, may occur. Effectively, the public may perceive IAS similarly to native trees, and IAS management consequently receives low priority. </p>
</text>
