<text id="autogum_whow_doc342" title="Choose a Dental Implant Surgeon" shortTile="choose-dental-implant" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-04-07" dateModified="2018-09-30" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Choose-a-Dental-Implant-Surgeon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Choose a Dental Implant Surgeon</head><p>Getting dental implants requires precision reconstructive surgery. You don’t just want anyone operating on your mouth; you want an expert. So, how do you find the right dentist for the job? The best surgeons will have the perfect combination of credentials, facilities and reputation.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Check for AAID Certification. The simplest way to narrow your list of dentists is to use AAID (American Academy of Implant Dentistry) certification as your first requirement. There are several types of dentists who might have this certification, including general dentists, periodon'tists, prosthodon'tists and oral surgeons. Any dentist who performs surgical and/or restorative procedures could potentially acquire certification. And, if they hold that certificate, you know that they are competent in all phases of implant dentistry, have at least five years of experience, are actively involved in leadership roles and have completed at least 400 hours of continuing education. It’s a great place to start!</item>
<item>Inquire About In-Office Technology. Advancements in dental technology have given implant dentists incredible tools to work with; but, not all offices are state-of-the-art. The Cone Beam CT, for example, is a 3D imaging device that can provide views of soft tissue, bone, muscle, and blood vessels, without sacrificing clarity. This allows dentists to plan treatment properly, and safely place implants with incredible precision. Choosing a dentist with in-office access to this technology and others minimizes your risk, while maximizing your convenience.</item>
<item>Find Out If They Have an In-House Surgical Suite. Some dental procedures require multiple visits to the office. The actual surgery may even take place off-site at a hospital or other surgical facility. These are things to consider carefully. Ask your candidate dentists not only what the “turn-around time” is, but how many visits to expect and where you might have to go. Some will have a surgical suite in-house, which tends to make the process quicker and more convenient overall. If your surgery will be performed with IV sedation, you will want to find out if your doctor is certified to perform IV sedation, or if other doctors will be involved.</item>
<item>Research Their Reputation. Just because you “know” your current dentist, doesn’t mean he or she is right for your reconstructive surgery.  There is no harm in asking about their credentials or experience in dental implants, after all, you didn’t need to know until now. Ask about their success rate. Ask to see before and after photos. If they don’t do implants, ask for a referral. Implant dentistry is a very competitive specialty, and most dentists expect these types of inquiries. Use the Internet to dig up some reviews from other dental implant patients. Just be careful to look at the big picture, as a single review (good or bad) may not paint the most accurate picture. And, of course, ask around. More people in your circle of acquaintances may have dental implant experience than you think!</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>At the end of the day, choosing any doctor will go beyond a checklist of “must haves” and “nice to haves”. Talk to the staff and meet the surgeon. Being comfortable with the dentist is important, too.</item></list>
</text>
