<text id="autogum_voyage_doc45" title="Plovdiv" shortTile="plovdiv" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=27872" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Plovdiv</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://www.plovdiv.bg/en/%D1%82%D1%83%D1%80%D0%B8%D1%81%D1%82%D0%B8-2/">Plovdiv</ref></hi> (Bulgarian: Пловдив) is the second-largest city in <ref target="Bulgaria">Bulgaria</ref>, and second oldest (if not the oldest) city in <ref target="Europe">Europe</ref>. It is located in the large plain between the Rhodope Mountains on the south and the Balkan Range (Stara Planina - "Old Mountain") that runs through the center of Bulgaria to the north. Both ranges are visible on clear days. The Maritsa River flows through the city on its way southeast before forming the <ref target="Greece">Greek</ref>/<ref target="Turkey">Turkey</ref> border to the Aegean Sea.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>Plovdiv is debatably the oldest continually inhabited city in Europe, with a history traced back to 6000 BC. Originally it had seven tall hills, some of which were used for quarries. It was originally a Thracian settlement by the name of Eumolpias. The city has changed its name many times with new settlers and rulers: from Philippoupolis and Pulpudeva ("the city of Philip", the father of Alexander the Great), through Trimontium ("the three hills"), to Pəldin, Pləpdiv (Плъпдив) and Plovdiv. They also left their marks behind: there are several Roman ruins that can be seen in or near the city center area. During the long occupation by the Ottoman Empire, a large mosque, still present, was built in the center of the city. During Communist times, a statue of the unnamed Russian soldier was erected on one of the three main hills which overlook the city.</p>

<p>Today, Plovdiv is a famous tourist destination itself and also serves as a gateway to many other points of interest. Plovdiv is well known for hosting the Plovdiv International Fair twice a year and for its ancient, medieval and enlightenment sites.</p>

<p>When you are in Plovdiv, you can get help and more information about the city from one of the two tourist information centers in the city. The first one is located in the middle of the city, right next to the post office; when arriving in the city via train or bus through the "Yug" or "Rhodope" stations, this is one of the first buildings you'll come across in the city center. The second one is located in the Old City, on its main street (Saborna St), close to the Ethnographic museum and the beautiful church of Saint Konstantin and Elena.</p>

<p>Tourist information centers can help you with all kinds of information including city maps, information about concerts, bus and train schedules, and finding a place to sleep.</p>

<p>Plovdiv is a "<ref target="https://plovdiv2019.eu/en">European Capital of Culture</ref>" for 2019, an honour it shares with <ref target="Matera">Matera</ref>.</p>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Plovdiv International Airport</hi> (originally called Krumovo, PDV ). There are flights from/to London-Stansted and Frankfurt-Hahn via Ryanair, and Moscow-Domodedovo via <ref target="w:Plovdiv%20Airport%23Airlines%20and%20destinations">S7 Airlines</ref>.</item>
</list>

 

<head>By train</head>
<p>The is just north of the city center, a 10-15 min walk.</p>

<p>There are around 15 daily <ref target="http://www.bdz.bg/en/bdz.bg">trains</ref> to and from <ref target="Sofia">Sofia</ref>, taking 2 to 4 hours - the slower trains may require a change. </p>

<p>There is a sleeper train every night between Sofia, Plovdiv and <ref target="Istanbul">Istanbul</ref> which takes about 7 hr. </p>

<p>In June 2019, another train ran daytime between Plovdiv and Edirne in western Turkey. It was meant to be a permanent service, but lasted for just one weekend then they cancelled! It's not known if it will ever resume - it created a useful extra route between Bulgaria and Turkey, avoiding arrival / departure in the small hours.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>The A1 expressway/motorway connects Plovdiv westward to Sofia, and eastward all the way to Burgas on the Black Sea. Other destinations require two-lane roads, such as the most direct route to <ref target="Pleven">Pleven</ref>, which is the somewhat adventurous Troyan pass road.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>Plovdiv has 3 bus stations: , , and . There are many buses for cities all around Bulgaria and to some that are outside the country. Buses to destinations near Plovdiv run from Rhodope station. Both the Yug and Rhodope stations are within five minutes walking distance from the main train station.</p>

<p>Yug station has an ATM located just outside so you can easily get local currency there if you're arriving by bus from abroad. Buses for Sofia leave from this station.</p>

<p>Buses run hourly from Sofia and are slightly faster than the trains (approx. 14 leva).</p>

<p>Metro Turizm is a Turkish bus company that runs daily bus services to and from Istanbul in Turkey. Buses going from Plovdiv to Istanbul depart from Yug Station daily at 11:00, 14:00, 19:00, 22:30, and 01:00. The trip costs 105 TL (as of the summer of 2018) and takes roughly 7 hr, depending upon the vagaries of traffic and the border crossing. Metro buses also depart daily for Bursa, Turkey at 19:00. A second bus line (Alpar) also has a daily bus from Yug Station to Istanbul that departs at 22:30.</p>

<p>Eurolines runs a bus to <ref target="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</ref> via Sofia that leaves at 08:00 from the Yug station, tickets can be bought on board. Metro Turizm runs a similar service at 08:30, tickets can be bought from the office at the station.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
 
<p>Taxis and buses are prevalent. Downtown has a large pedestrian zone. Taxis are (Summer 2010) as cheap if not cheaper than bus rides when split between 3-4 people in general. A 5-7 km of traveled distance was charged at around 5 leva (charge for km is 0.75 leva daily and 0.95 leva nightly); an average ride within the city costs around 3 leva. The taxi arrives in about 3-5 min. Remember to order the Taxi from the companies that offer the best deals and wait for it. Generally taking the taxi that is already waiting will cost you more (sometimes up to 5 times more) avoid them or ask for a flat price that fits you! Learn who offers best prices from the locals who often use taxis. Most of the taxi cars have 4-digit numbers on them, remember some and use it if you need a car, for example: 6155, 6142, 9199 and so on.</p>

<p>As of summer 2011, if your taxi ride costs more than 5 leva, you are entitled to a 20% discount off the fare.</p>

<p>Public bus tickets cost 1 lev.</p>
</text>
