<text id="autogum_bio_doc043" title="Gregory J. Slavonic" shortTile="gregory-j-slavonic" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2018-09-07" dateModified="2019-09-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gregory_J._Slavonic" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Gregory J. Slavonic</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Gregory Joseph Slavonic</hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> is the 18th United States <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Assistant_Secretary_of_the_Navy_for_Manpower_and_Reserve_Affairs">Assistant Secretary of the Navy for Manpower and Reserve Affairs</ref> (ASN M&amp;RA). Secretary Slavonic retired as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rear_admiral_(United_States)">Rear admiral</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Naval_Reserve">United States Naval Reserve</ref>, after a 34-year career serving in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/US_Navy">US Navy</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-NavBio-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Military career</head>
<figure><caption>Slavonic as rear admiral.</caption></figure>
<p>Slavonic was born May 6, 1949 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Bend,_Kansas">Great Bend, Kansas</ref> and raised in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oklahoma_City">Oklahoma City</ref>. Following high school, he attended the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oklahoma_State_University">Oklahoma State University</ref> and later graduated with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bachelor_of_Science">Bachelor of Science</ref> degree in Journalism &amp; Broadcasting. Slavonic enlisted the United States Navy in 1971 during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vietnam_War">Vietnam War</ref>, and following his recruit training at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Recruit_Training_Command,_Great_Lakes,_Illinois">Navy Training Center at Great Lakes</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Illinois">Illinois</ref>, he was ordered to the Navy <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Signalman">Signalman</ref> "A" school at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newport,_Rhode_Island">Newport, Rhode Island</ref>. He was then attached to the crew of aircraft carrier <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/USS_Constellation_(CVA-64)">USS <hi rend="italic">Constellation</hi></ref> and participated in the two western Pacific deployments in support of combat operations in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vietnam">Vietnam</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-NewsOK-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FlagO-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Upon his return from sea duties, Slavonic was discharged from active service and entered the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Navy_Reserve">United States Navy Reserve</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oklahoma_City">Oklahoma City</ref>. He attended the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Central_Oklahoma">University of Central Oklahoma</ref> and graduated in summer 1976 with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Master's_degree">Master's degree</ref> in Education. He rose through the ranks of the Navy Reserve and was recalled to active service in November 1990 for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gulf_War">Gulf War</ref>. Slavonic was assigned to the staff of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S._Central_Command">U.S. Central Command</ref> under General <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norman_Schwarzkopf_Jr.">Norman Schwarzkopf Jr.</ref> and assumed duty with the Navy public affairs section, Joint Information Bureau in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dhahran">Dhahran</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saudi_Arabia">Saudi Arabia</ref>.</p>
<p>He then served as a Chief of Navy News desk and combat media escort officer, which included escorting media Combat Correspondent Pools (CCP) pools on board the guided-missile frigate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/USS_Curts_(FFG-38)">USS <hi rend="italic">Curts</hi></ref> to document processing and interrogation of more than 40 Iraqi prisoners of war and floating mines which posed danger to U.S. and international shipping. He was serving as media escort officer with a media pool on the 18,000-ton amphibious assault ship <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/USS_Tripoli_(LPH-10)">USS <hi rend="italic">Tripoli</hi></ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Persian_Gulf">Persian Gulf</ref> when it struck an Iraqi underwater tethered mine.</p>
<p>Slavonic later reached the rank of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rear_Admiral_(United_States)">Rear Admiral</ref> and was recalled to active duty in June 2004 in order to take part in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operation_Noble_Eagle">Operation Noble Eagle</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operation_Enduring_Freedom">Operation Enduring Freedom</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baghdad">Baghdad</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraq">Iraq</ref>. He was the first U.S. Navy flag officer assigned to the Multinational Force Iraq (MNF-I) staff and also served as the director of strategic communications and public affairs officer for Army Commanding General of Multinational Force-Iraq (MNF-I)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-NavyBio2-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>While in Iraq, Slavonic also served as the Director, Combined Press Information Center. He retired from the Navy/Navy Reserve in June 2005.</p>
<head>Private sector</head>
<p>Slavonic joined the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer_Sciences_Corporation">Computer Sciences Corporation</ref>, supporting the U.S. Navy's outreach program.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Okie-6">[6]</ref> Slavonic also served as President, FlagBridge Strategic Communications for more than six years. </p>
<head>Public sector</head>
<p>Slavonic served as the first Chief of staff to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Senate">United States Senator</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Lankford">James Lankford</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oklahoma">Oklahoma</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-NewsOK-2">[2]</ref> In this role, Slavonic was responsible for creating, building and organizing a senate staff including hiring and standing up and transition to a new office in Washington DC, including two state offices. </p>
<head>Awards and decorations</head>
</text>
