<text id="autogum_news_doc335" title="Multiple controversies arise on eve of Hong Kong legislative election" shortTile="multiple-controversies" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-09-03" dateModified="2018-02-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Multiple_controversies_arise_on_eve_of_Hong_Kong_legislative_election" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Multiple controversies arise on eve of Hong Kong legislative election</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 6, 2016</hi></p>
<p>On Saturday, as the citizens of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hong_Kong">Hong Kong</ref> prepared to vote in Sunday's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hong%20Kong%20legislative%20election,%202016">legislative election</ref>, multiple controversies broke out concerning different candidates and the fairness of the election overall. Following suspensions on Friday, another candidate, Kwan Wing-yip of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neo%20Democrats">Neo Democrats</ref>, suspended his campaign; the head of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electoral%20Affairs%20Commission">Electoral Affairs Commission</ref> responded to questions about the logistics of the ballots; a report surfaced concerning Chinese-funded companies calling their Hong Kong employees to vote for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pro-Beijing%20camp">pro-Beijing or pro-establishment</ref> candidates; and allegations were made that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Localism%20in%20Hong%20Kong">localist</ref> party <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Youngspiration">Youngspiration</ref> has ties with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Beijing">Beijing</ref>.</p>
<p>After six <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/pan-democracy%20camp">pan-democratic</ref> candidates suspended their campaigns on Friday, another candidate from the camp, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neo%20Democrats">Neo Democrats'</ref> Kwan Wing-yip of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/District%20Council%20(Second)">District Council (Second)</ref> functional constituency, announced the suspension of his campaign. He stated that after other pan-democrats suspended their campaigns aiming to boost other pan-democratic candidates, members of his party experienced great pressure regarding the suspension of his candidacy. He also said it was a "difficult decision," and the "darkest day" in his political life. </p>
<p>The head of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electoral%20Affairs%20Commission">Electoral Affairs Commission</ref>, Barnabus Fung Wah, responded to reports about the logistics of the ballot papers, saying that allowing the director of each polling station to take the ballot papers home and bring them to the polling stations on election day is more sound than trusting couriers. He also addressed concerns by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pro-Beijing%20camp">pro-Beijing or pro-establishment camp</ref>, such as pro-Beijing news outlet <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wen%20Wei%20Po">Wen Wei Po</ref> and pro-Beijing party <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hong%20Kong%20Federation%20of%20Trade%20Unions">Federation of Trade Unions</ref>, accusing the pan-democratic candidates' campaign suspensions of undermining democracy and proposing to report the incidents to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Independent%20Commission%20Against%20Corruption%20(Hong%20Kong)">Independent Commission Against Corruption</ref>. Fung Wah addressed them by saying that because the candidates can't drop out from the ballot paper after the nomination period by law, the candidates suspending their campaigns would not affect the election's fairness. </p>
<p>Early Saturday morning <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hong%20Kong%20Time">Hong Kong Time</ref>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Reuters">Reuters</ref></hi> reported the Hong Kong employees of Chinese-funded companies were being asked to vote for pro-Beijing candidates in the election. The companies include <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bank%20of%20China%20(Hong%20Kong)">Bank of China</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/China%20Resources%20Land">China Resources Land</ref>, who according to the report showed a list of pro-Beijing candidates to vote for, and for Bank of China the employees were asked to call their managers after they have cast their votes. When asked by <hi rend="italic">Reuters</hi> about the matter, Bank of China responded that it "supports and respects" the right of its employees to vote, while no response was immediately forthcoming from China Resources Land. </p>
<figure><caption>pro-Beijing figure Lau Nai-keung</caption></figure>
<p>Meanwhile, after claiming Hong Kong's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chief%20executive%20of%20Hong%20Kong">chief executive</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CY%20Leung">CY Leung</ref> and the Chinese central government's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liaison%20Office%20of%20the%20Central%20People's%20Government%20in%20the%20Hong%20Kong%20Special%20Administrative%20Region">Hong Kong liaison office</ref> encouraged Hong Kong independence for the past few days, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sing%20Pao">Sing Pao</ref></hi> reported the new <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Localism%20in%20Hong%20Kong">localist</ref> party <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Youngspiration">Youngspiration</ref> has ties with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pro-Beijing%20camp">pro-Beijing</ref> figure <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lau%20Nai-keung">Lau Nai-keung</ref>. Youngspiration responded by stating its members do not know Lau Nai-keung personally or the pro-Beijing organisation "Hong Kong Community Network" mentioned in <hi rend="italic">Sing Pao</hi>'s article, and challenged the newspaper to "present its evidence" regarding the group's alleged ties to Beijing, saying accusing them without evidence "violates media ethics."
<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Special:FilePath/Leticia_Lee_See-yin.jpg">File:Leticia Lee See-yin.jpg</ref></p><figure><caption>Justice Alliance Party candidate Leticia Lee<hi rend="italic">(Image <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Template:Missing_image/message">missing</ref> from commons: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/File:Leticia_Lee_See-yin.jpg">image</ref>; <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Special:Log?page=File%3ALeticia+Lee+See-yin.jpg">log</ref>)</hi></caption></figure>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pan-democracy%20camp">Pan-democratic</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Democratic%20Party%20(Hong%20Kong)">Democratic Party</ref> candidate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lam%20Cheuk-ting">Lam Cheuk-ting</ref> said he received confirmation from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Independent%20Commission%20Against%20Corruption%20(Hong%20Kong)">Independent Commission Against Corruption</ref> (ICAC) that they were investigating pro-establishment Justice Alliance Party candidate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leticia%20Lee">Leticia Lee</ref> for bribery. The pro-establishment group "Alliance in Support of Our Police Force" held a dinner on August 31, and it was reported Leticia Lee took part on stage during the lucky draw, and encouraged its members to vote for herself.</p>
<p>Before Saturday, the election was already controversial, with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electoral%20Affairs%20Commission">Electoral Affairs Commission</ref> barring <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hong%20Kong%20independence">pro-independence</ref> candidates from running, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liberal%20Party%20(Hong%20Kong)">Liberal Party</ref> candidate Ken Chow Wing-kan of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20Territories%20West%20(constituency)">New Territories West</ref> constituency unexpectedly suspending his campaign due to unspecified "threats." The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hong%20Kong%20legislative%20election,%202016">2016 Hong Kong legislative election</ref>, the sixth since the former British colony's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transfer%20of%20sovereignty%20over%20Hong%20Kong">transfer of sovereignty</ref> to China, was held on Sunday, electing 70 legislators to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Legislative%20Council%20(Hong%20Kong)">Legislative Council</ref>. </p>
</text>
