<text id="autogum_interview_doc591" title="part4_Wikinews interviews Australian Paralympic skiers Jessica Gallagher and Eric Bickerton" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-12-10" dateModified="2017-10-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_Paralympic_skiers_Jessica_Gallagher_and_Eric_Bickerton" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Most of us have played sport all our lives, but there's a difference between playing sport and playing sport at a high level, and the higher level you go, the more specialized you tend to become. And here [we're] looking at two exceptions to that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Eric Bickerton:</hi> I suppose that I can round that out by saying to you that I don't think that I would ever reach the pinnacle. I'm not prepared to spend ten years dedicated to that one thing. And to get that last ten per cent or five percent of performance at that level. That's what you've got to do. So I'll play everything to a reasonable level, but to get to that really, really highest peak level you have to give up everything else.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  When you go to the <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/pub">pub</ref>, do your mates make fun of you for having a medal in women's blind skiing?</p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Eric Bickerton:</hi> No, not really.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Gallagher:</hi> Usually they say "I love it!" and "This is pretty cool!"</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Eric Bickerton:</hi> We started at the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Olympics">Olympics</ref>. We went out into the crowd to meet Jess' mum, and we had our medals. There were two of us and we were waiting for her mum to come back and in that two hour period there was at least a hundred and fifty people from all over the world who wore our medals and took photographs. My medal's been all over Australia.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Going to a completely different issue, blind sports have three classifications, that are medical, unlike everybody else, who've got functional ability [classifications]. You've got the only medical ones. Do you think the blind classifications are fair in terms of how they operate? Or should there be changes? And how that works in terms of the IPC?</p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Gallagher:</hi> Yeah. I think the system they've got in place is good, in terms of having the three classes. You've got completely blind which are <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/B1%20(classification)">B1s</ref>, less than 5 percent, which are <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/B2%20(classification)">B2</ref>, and less than 10 percent is a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/B3%20(classification)">B3</ref>. I think those systems work really well. I guess one of the difficult things with vision impairment is that there are so many diseases and conditions that everyone's sight is completely different, and they have that problem with the other classes as well. But in terms of the class system itself I think having the three works really well. What do you think?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Eric Bickerton:</hi> I think the classification system itself's fine. It's the one or two grey areas, people: are they there or are they there?</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  That affected you in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2008_Summer_Paralympics">Beijing</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Gallagher:</hi> Yeah. That was obviously really disappointing, but, ironic as well in that one of my eyes is point zero one of a percent too sighted, so one's eligible, the other's just outside their criteria, which left me unable to compete. Because my condition is degenerative. They knew that my sight would get worse. I guess I was in a fortunate position where once my sight deteriorated I was going to become eligible. There are some of the classes, if you don't have a degenerate condition, that's not possible. No one ever wants to lose their best sight, but that was one positive.</p>
</text>
