<text id="autogum_whow_doc244" title="Effectively Deploy a Distinctive Podcast Marketing Solution" shortTile="effectively-deploy" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2005-12-03" dateModified="2018-10-13" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Effectively-Deploy-a-Distinctive-Podcast-Marketing-Solution" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Effectively Deploy a Distinctive Podcast Marketing Solution</head><p>Each day starts and usually ends with the same BIG question. Our clients and prospects ask us, "How can I grow my business and capture my fair market share?" Our answer is quite simply, "Build yourself a base of prospects and work that pipeline relentlessly and efficiently." Here now is a list of things to do to prepare yourself for your first podcast presentation.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Research the podcast element. Learn precisely what podcasting is all about and how it works. Search for "Podcast Radio" on your favorite search engine. <figure rend="Effectively Deploy a Distinctive Podcast Marketing Solution Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Physically search out only the true professionals. Create a list of those podcasters that undeniably know exactly what they are doing. Align yourself with only the best. From this list, call them on the phone and pick their brain(s). If you cannot locate an actual telephonic point of contact, wipe them from your list. You want to do business with those that believe in "touching" their market with more intimacy and one-to-one personalization rather than just an email. Remember, you are looking for a friend. A mentor. Not necessarily someone to take your money and be off. A solid partnership (friendship) is your objective here. <figure rend="Effectively Deploy a Distinctive Podcast Marketing Solution Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Discover Your Passion. What passion do you share with others? What true value will your audience glean from you? Who is your target audience? Understand your "WHY"! <figure rend="Effectively Deploy a Distinctive Podcast Marketing Solution Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Develop Your Plan &amp; Work Your Process. What do you need to learn? What do you need to do? What specific date will you be ready? Who will provide you with the support you will need to fulfill your plan. What equipment is required? <figure rend="Effectively Deploy a Distinctive Podcast Marketing Solution Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make Your Podcast Happen! As you roll out your "new-to-you" adventure, don't expect total perfection on day one. Be kind to yourself and know that you will evolve. We all started from square one. Enough practice and desire can make you near perfect, but do be fair with you and give yourself time to grow. <figure rend="Effectively Deploy a Distinctive Podcast Marketing Solution Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Listen to other professional podcasters. Listen to your local radio stations. Read books and articles like this one on a daily basis. <figure rend="Effectively Deploy a Distinctive Podcast Marketing Solution Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>No excuses! If you <hi rend="italic">really</hi> want to crank up the heat on your marketing efforts, than podcasting will give you the significant marketing advantage. <figure rend="Effectively Deploy a Distinctive Podcast Marketing Solution Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Podcasting is a term that manifested as a fresh way to describe the technology used to push (share) audio content from web sites down to consumers (clients) of that content, who usually listen to it on an iPod (hence the term "pod") or any other type of .mp3 player (iRiver) at their command, convenience and control.</item>
<item>Podcasting is somewhat similar to the concept of time-shifted video software and devices like TiVo, which let you watch what you want exactly when you want it by simply recording and storing video, except that Podcasting is primarily used for audio to date. (Universal video deployment is most likely just around the corner.) This easy to use emerging technology can be used to push (deploy) any kind of file such as photos (images), software updates, videos and/or text.</item>
<item>Podcasting uses an XML-based technology called RSS (Real Simple Syndication). Content publishers (podcasters) describe new content in an XML RSS file which includes dates, titles, descriptions, and specifics links to the .mp3 files. This "automatically" generated file is referred to as an RSS feed. Dave Winer is considered by many to be the creator of RSS and a pioneer in the environment of applied XML. The component to making podcasting work with RSS is "enclosures" (remember that term), an element supported by RSS 2.0.</item>
<item>As a consumer or end-user, you simply run an "aggregator" (remember this term, too) program like MTV's Adam Curry's iPodder software on your local computer, which lets you easily subscribe to RSS feeds. Programs like Adam's will either by schedule or by random design, download the RSS files, and check to see if any fresh content is available. If new content exists, the audio files are automatically downloaded and put into a folder (of your choice) on your hard disk or directly routed to your mp3 player.</item>
<item>Anyone who properly learns (from a real professional) and activates their own podcast process can reap the significant harvest of BIGGER numbers by creating and nurturing their own emerging community. As an online business owner, this is HUGE and required! This marketing solution can not only make you financially solvent, it can even make you a "STAR"!</item>
<item>Accept no feeble excuses and get working on your very first podcast right away! (At the very least, be sure to move podcasting up near the top of your "TO-DO" list!</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be sure to identify and experiment with all angles of marketing when it comes to producing an on-going, money-generating podcast production for all the world to hear and take notice!</item>
<item>Happy podcast Marketing!</item></list>
</text>
