<text id="autogum_academic_doc348" title="Impact of the October 2018 Storm Vaia on Coastal Boulders in the Northern Adriatic Sea" shortTile="impact-october--storm" author="Sara Biolchi, Cléa Denamiel, Stefano Devoto, Tvrtko Korbar, Vanja Macovaz, Giovanni Scicchitano, Ivica Vilibić, Stefano Furlani" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4441/11/11/2229/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
The comparison of orthomosaics obtained from UAV images, repeated annually, can be a very useful tool for monitoring the variation of the boulder positions. This methodology has been successfully applied in both North Atlantic and Mediterranean boulder sites. UAV-derived orthophotographs and digital surface models (DSMs) can provide excellent data and information on coastal boulder patterns. Orthophotographs allow for the mapping of a axes and b axes, including their orientation, whereas precise values for c axes and boulder volume can be taken from the DSM. In recent years, after an initial decade when the analyses were mostly dedicated to explaining boulder detachment and transport mechanisms and distinguishing between those of tsunamigenic and those of storm origin, boulder studies are now more oriented towards the observation of boulder movements and reassemblage after exceptional storm events. In addition, Hastewell et al. have proposed an innovative technique for boulder movement reconstruction, using radio frequency Identification (RFID) tagging and DGNNS technology. A single RFID tag is inserted inside a boulder and can be activated with an electromagnetic signal emitted by a pole antenna moved by an operator also equipped with a backpack reader and a handheld computer. </p>

<p>On the Premantura Promontory, where the origin of the boulders has been ascribed to storm events, totally excluding those of tsunami origin, and where boulders analysis began only recently (end of 2016), a proper monitoring network including orthophotograph comparison, both aerial and submarine, geomorphological observation, instrumental monitoring techniques, and numerical modeling, is most definitely needed as severe storms are forecast to increase in the near future. </p>

<p>Following the long-term monitoring experience of coastal landslides affecting the northwestern part of Malta, a network of GNSS benchmarks has also been installed in Premantura. At the same time, the submarine 3D model, presented here, could be the starting point for monitoring the effects of future storms in the underwater environment, that represents the source area for the quarrying and detachment of future boulders. Finally, every day since early 2019, the AdriSC operational component has been providing a 48 h forecast of high-resolution wave parameters, which can be used to detect in advance whether or not a potential storm can move boulders. </p>

<p>By comparing UAV-derived orthophotographs, we detected the movement of 13 boulders and the emplacement of a new one after a severe storm. The western part of the boulder field suffered the intensity of the last storm most, whereas the central and eastern part did not show any evidence of boulder movements. This lack of movement is related to the structural setting of the promontory, where, in the central and eastern sectors the boulders (probably older) are located at higher elevations. Thus, active erosion occurs in the western part of the Jugo Promontory (Cape Kamenjak). </p>

<p>By observing boulder movements (<figure>Figure 4</figure>), the maximum inundation flow of the storm waves capable of transporting boulders was estimated to about 50 m of distance from the coast (that has been measured considering wave directions and orientation of the limestone ramps). The displacement followed the azimuth of the limestone beds strikes that, in turn, have conditioned the detachment of rocky material forming scarps throughout the past. These scarps, together with flat, gently inclined limestone bedding planes (pavements), have acted as ramps for boulder transport. Isolated boulders, such as boulder #1 (K8 in), are those that have been subject to the largest movements, while the boulders gathered in clusters were only rotated or toppled, but remained in position, trapped by other boulders or the abovementioned scarps, fractures, and faults. The latter, in particular, have been enlarged over time by coastal karst and marine weathering, as well as by the removal of small portions of rocky material. Some boulders exhibited signs of fragmentation, due to collisions with other boulders or against the rocky scarps. </p>

<p>The submerged scenario, accurately obtained using digital photogrammetric reconstructions, is a high energy environment, with fresh detachment scarps and rounded or sub-rounded potholes, where decimetric cobbles and boulders lie and move, causing the abrasion of the rocky seafloor. The topographical setting of the seafloor reflects the coastal geomorphology and topography, where limestone beds alternate with scarps and faults. With respect to the previous underwater geomorphological surveying, any recent detachment scar has been noted, while a clear detachment niche has been reconstructed in detail. The 3D submarine model obtained, reconstructed using digital photogrammetric analysis of underwater pictures, will be the starting point for future monitoring of the submerged environment, both before and after exceptional storms, that may affect the Adriatic Sea even more given the future climate predictions. </p>
</text>
