<text id="autogum_bio_doc583" title="Philip of Aragon" shortTile="philip-aragon" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-01-17" dateModified="2018-07-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip_of_Aragon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Philip of Aragon</head><p><hi rend="bold">Philip of Aragon</hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[lower-alpha 1]</ref> (born between 1449 and 1456, died 1488) was the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishop_of_Palermo">Archbishop of Palermo</ref> from 31 January 1477, when he received confirmation of his election from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Sixtus_IV">Sixtus IV</ref> until he renounced his see in 1485.</p>
<head>Birth and early childhood</head>
<p>Philip was the eldest son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles,_Prince_of_Viana">Charles, Prince of Viana</ref>, by his third known mistress, Brianda de Vega.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[lower-alpha 2]</ref> His father was the heir of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Navarre">kingdom of Navarre</ref> as the son of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_II_of_Aragon_and_Navarre">John II</ref> and Queen <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blanche_I_of_Navarre">Blanche I</ref>. Philip and his mother are both mentioned for the first time in a document of 13 January 1456, when they were living in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pamplona">Pamplona</ref>, in a house owned by the prior of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Larraga">Larraga</ref>. Already by that time, Philip had been granted the title <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Count_of_Beaufort">Count of Beaufort</ref>. By February, Charles had provided his son with a room in the royal palace.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Miranda-3">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Philip was born in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diocese_of_Pamplona">diocese of Pamplona</ref>, but the date of his birth is unclear. According to some sources, he was  twenty-seven years old when he was elected archbishop, which places his birth in 1449 or 1450.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DBI-4">[2]</ref> According to others, his birth most likely took place shortly before he and his mother were first recognised in an official document of the prince's in January 1456.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Miranda-3">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Philip spent most of his childhood in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barcelona">Barcelona</ref>. He and his mother were first summoned there by Charles in 1461, arriving by June. According to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jerónimo_Zurita">Jerónimo Zurita</ref>, writing a century later, they lived in the house of Charles's sister, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blanche_II_of_Navarre">Blanche</ref>. Zurita also claims that Charles placed Philip in the charge of a knight named Bernat Sapila and separated him from his mother, although there is little evidence of this in the primary sources. In September, Charles died. On 5 October, in his first known public appearance, Philip took part in the funeral cortege through the streets of Barcelona.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Miranda-3">[1]</ref></p>
<p>During the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War_against_John_II">war against John II</ref> (1462–72), Philip continued to live in Barcelona and receive a daily pension of six <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sueldo">sueldos</ref></hi> from the anti-kings elected in opposition to John, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter,_Constable_of_Portugal">Peter(V)</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/René_of_Anjou">René</ref>. From Peter he received gifts: a mansion near the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santa_Anna_de_Barcelona">monastery of Santa Anna</ref> that had previously belonged to Bernat Terré y Dusay and all the goods confiscated from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicolau_Carròs_d'Arborea_i_de_Mur">Nicolau Carròs d'Arborea i de Mur</ref>, a support of John II. René placed the young Philip under the protection of his son, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_II,_Duke_of_Lorraine">John II, Duke of Lorraine</ref>. Towards the end of the civil war, however, Philip switched his support to John II. René confiscated the house by Santa Anna, but in October 1472 Barcelona was occupied by John II.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Miranda-3">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Archiepiscopate</head>
<p>As was common in that time, Philip did not live in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palermo">Palermo</ref>, but delegated his administrative duties to two <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vicar">vicars</ref>. The vicars were prevented from taking up their office by the senate of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Sicily">Kingdom of Sicily</ref> because they were not Sicilians. Only after lengthy negotiations did Philip nominate a Sicilian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canon_regular">canon</ref> to the vicariate. The senate still refused to recognise Philip's appointment as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chancellor">Grand Chancellor of the Realm</ref>, because he was not a Sicilian citizen. Likewise, the senate even challenged his archiepiscopal election because of an irregularity in the papal rescript of confirmation. Finally, on 9 January 1479, the viceroy, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juan_Ramón_Folch_de_Cardona">Juan Ramón Folch de Cardona</ref>, invested him with the temporalities of his diocese.</p>
<p>In 1481, Philip acquired the abbey of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Giovanni_degli_Eremiti">San Giovanni degli Eremiti</ref> and the priory of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santissima_Trinità_di_Delia">Santissima Trinità di Delia</ref> for the diocese. He also acquired the fiefs of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geracello">Geracello</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sattabene">Sattabene</ref> along with other lands in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Val_di_Mazara">Val di Mazara</ref> for the church. After all the trouble of getting himself installed in his see, he renounced it in 1485 in order to become the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grandmaster_(order)">Grand Master</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Order_of_Montesa">Order of Montesa</ref>. He returned to Spain, where he died taking part in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War_of_Granada">War of Granada</ref> in 1488.</p>
</text>
