<text id="autogum_news_doc122" title="Negotiations for hijacked Saudi oil tanker begin" shortTile="negotiations-hijacked" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-11-19" dateModified="2019-01-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Negotiations_for_hijacked_Saudi_oil_tanker_begin" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Negotiations for hijacked Saudi oil tanker begin</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 20, 2008</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vela%20International%20Marine">Vela International Marine</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Saudi_Arabia">Saudi Arabian</ref> company that owns the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MV%20Sirius%20Star">MV <hi rend="italic">Sirius Star</hi></ref> oil tanker which was captured by pirates on November 15, has begun negotiations with the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Somalia">Somali</ref> pirates.</p>
<p>The Saudi Foreign Minister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saud%20bin%20Faisal%20bin%20Abdul%20Aziz">Saud al Faisal</ref> said that talks had begun, but he did not say whether a ransom would be paid. Vela International Marine, which is owned by state-owned <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saudi%20Aramco">Saudi Aramco</ref>, would only say it is "working toward [the crew's] safe and speedy return."</p>
<p>"We do not like to negotiate with pirates, terrorists or hijackers," said Saud al Faisal in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rome">Rome</ref>, after speaking with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franco%20Frattini">Franco Frattini</ref>, the Foreign Minister of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Italy">Italy</ref>.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dubai">Dubai</ref>-based television network <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al%20Jazeera">Al Jazeera</ref> broadcast an audiotape of a man who said he was with the pirates. He identified himself as Farah Abd Jameh.</p>
<p>"Negotiators are located on board the ship and on land. Once they have agreed on the ransom, it will be taken in cash to the oil tanker. We assure the safety of the ship that carries the ransom. We will mechanically count the money and we have machines that can detect fake money," the man said. He did not mention any specific amounts for the ransom.</p>
<hi rend="bold">We do not like to negotiate with pirates, terrorists or hijackers.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Saud al Faisal, Foreign Minister of Saudi Arabia</p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Kingdom">British</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foreign%20and%20Commonwealth%20Office">Foreign Office</ref> released a statement Wednesday which identified two of the crew as chief engineer Peter French and second officer James Grady. The rest of the 25-man crew are from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Croatia">Croatia</ref> (1), <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Poland">Poland</ref> (2), <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Philippines">Philippines</ref> (19) and Saudi Arabia (1). They are all reported to be safe.</p>
<p>Foreign Secretary <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/David_Miliband">David Miliband</ref> said that the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal%20Navy">Royal Navy</ref> was coordinating a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Europe">European</ref> response.</p>
<p>Dominique Montecer, the director of operations at GEOS Group, a corporate risk management firm, cast doubt on a military response.</p>
<p>"Everything is possible but it would take extraordinary means and organization, and the risk of an ecological disaster is very high. They are sitting on a bomb," Montecer said.</p>
<p>"It's certainly a very complex environment to work in — a Liberian-flagged vessel, owned by a Saudi company, in Somali waters, with so many different nationalities on board," said Lt. Nate Christensen of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Navy">United States Navy</ref> when asked about the possibility of taking back the <hi rend="italic">Sirius Star</hi> by force.</p>
<p>"Shipping companies are already making decisions not to go through the Gulf of Aden, and making the decision to take the much longer route around the south of Africa," said Peter Hinchcliffe, marine director of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International%20Chamber%20of%20Shipping">International Chamber of Shipping</ref>. "And with the increase in intensity of attacks, that is something that is going to be much more frequent. It's adding let's say an average of two weeks to the passage time."</p>
<p>Since the capture of the <hi rend="italic">Sirius Star</hi>, pirates in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gulf%20of%20Aden">Gulf of Aden</ref> have taken at least three other ships. These include a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China">Chinese</ref> ship carrying wheat, a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Greece">Greek</ref> bulk carrier, and a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Thailand">Thai</ref> fishing vessel.</p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International%20Maritime%20Bureau">International Maritime Bureau</ref> reports that Somali pirates currently hold 14 ships along with an estimated 250 crew members. Since January, there have been over 30 hijackings in the area, while another 60 ships have been attacked.</p>
<p>Among the ships still held is the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ukraine">Ukrainian</ref> cargo ship <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MV%20Faina">MV <hi rend="italic">Faina</hi></ref>, which has a cargo of 33 <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Russia">Russian</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/T-72">T-72</ref> battle tanks, as well as other weapons. The <hi rend="italic">Faina</hi> was hijacked on September 25.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indian%20Navy">Indian Navy</ref> has reported that it encountered and destroyed what it called a pirate "mother ship" on Tuesday. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/India">India</ref> dispatched frigate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/INS%20Tabar%20(F44)">INS <hi rend="italic">Tabar</hi></ref> last month to protect its merchant shipping in the Gulf of Aden. The pirate vessel reportedly threatened the Indian frigate after it was hailed.</p>
<p>Several <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NATO">NATO</ref> members, as well as Russia, India and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Malaysia">Malaysia</ref> have all sent warships to the region to protect merchant shipping in the area. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Combined%20Task%20Force%20150">Combined Task Force 150</ref>, formed as a multinational coalition in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War%20on%20Terrorism">War on Terrorism</ref>, was restructured in 2006 to aid in anti-piracy efforts.</p>
</text>
