<text id="autogum_academic_doc198" title="Modelling Neurotropic Flavivirus Infection in Human Induced Pluripotent Stem Cell-Derived Systems" shortTile="modelling-neurotropic" author="Giovanna Desole, Alessandro Sinigaglia, Silvia Riccetti, Giulia Masi, Monia Pacenti, Marta Trevisan, Luisa Barzon" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1422-0067/20/21/5404/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The <hi rend="italic">Flavivirus</hi> genus of the family <hi rend="italic">Flaviviridae</hi> includes several arthropod-borne human pathogens that may cause a spectrum of clinical syndromes ranging from a mild febrile illness to severe hemorrhagic fever or neuroinvasive disease. Neurotropic flaviviruses, such as West Nile virus (WNV), Japanese encephalitis virus (JEV), and tick-borne encephalitis virus (TBEV), are maintained in nature in transmission cycles involving mosquito (mainly <hi rend="italic">Culex</hi> spp.) or tick (mainly <hi rend="italic">Ixodes</hi> spp.) vectors and mammalian or bird amplification hosts, with humans serving as dead-end incidental hosts. Most human infections are asymptomatic or characterized by flu-like illness, while a severe and potentially fatal neuroinvasive disease occurs in a minority of cases, mostly immunocompromised and elderly individuals. </p>

<p>Zika virus (ZIKV) has recently drawn attention due to the large outbreaks that occurred in Pacific Ocean countries and the Americas. Like other flaviviruses, ZIKV generally causes asymptomatic infections or a mild febrile illness. Infection during pregnancy, especially during the first trimester, causes fetal microcephaly and other developmental anomalies, defined as congenital Zika virus syndrome. Guillain–Barré syndrome and meningoencephalitis are rare complications of ZIKV infection in adult individuals. ZIKV is transmitted between humans through the bite of infected <hi rend="italic">Ae. aegypti</hi> and other <hi rend="italic">Aedes</hi> species mosquitoes, with humans serving as amplifying hosts. Unique among flaviviruses, ZIKV can persist in immune-privileged sites like the testis and be sexually transmitted. </p>

<p>In addition to these well-known neurotropic flaviviruses, there has been an increasing number of reported cases of neurological complications caused by viruses, such as dengue virus (DENV) and yellow fever virus (YFV), which usually are associated with hemorrhagic disease. </p>

<p>One of the central questions in the search for therapeutic targets for the treatment of flaviviral neurological syndromes is whether these diseases are induced by virus-mediated cytolysis, immune-pathological responses to infection, or a combination of both. Animal models have permitted temporal analysis of the progressive dissemination of virus infection within the CNS and identification of cells targeted by viral infection, have revealed important details regarding host factors that restrict viral replication and the innate and adaptive immune responses to viral infections, and have been fundamental for vaccine development. Breakthroughs on cell reprogramming and generation of human induced pluripotent stem cells (hiPSCs) have revolutionized approaches to the study of human diseases. iPSCs are generated directly from adult differentiated cells that are reprogrammed back into an embryonic-like pluripotent state by introducing genes important for maintaining the essential properties of embryonic stem cells. Generation of hiPSCs and their differentiation into a variety of cells and organoids have allow to set up versatile, non-invasive, ethically sustainable, cruelty-free, and patient-specific models for the investigation of the mechanisms of human diseases, including viral infections and host–pathogen interactions, for the discovery of new drugs, and for the development of personalized therapies. Human iPSC-derived neural cells and brain organoids have been extensively used to investigate the mechanisms of ZIKV and other flavivirus infection and pathogenesis and have been used as platforms to discover therapeutic targets and to test antiviral compounds. Initial studies with hiPSCs studies were crucial to provide evidence of the tropism of ZIKV for human cortical neural progenitor cells and to demonstrate that ZIKV infection impairs cell differentiation and induces apoptosis, supporting the causative role of ZIKV in fetal microcephaly. Human iPSC-derived brain organoids, which are 3D structures mimicking endogenous human brain development and organization, showed that ZIKV preferentially infects radial glia cells as compared to intermediate progenitors or immature neurons, leading to cell death. Activation of TLR3-mediated innate immune response was one of the mechanisms involved ZIKV deleterious effects on neurogenesis. In addition, the ability of viruses to infect and replicate was found to be dependent on cell differentiation status, since stem cells appear to be refractory to viral infection probably due to constitutive high-level expression of interferon-stimulated genes (ISGs), while cell susceptibility to viral infection increases in differentiated cells. Comparisons with other flaviviruses—e.g., DENV—showed that the tropism for neural stem cells was a distinguishing feature of ZIKV, but no extensive comparative analyses have been performed with typically neurotropic flaviviruses like WNV. </p>

<p>In this study, we investigated the infectivity, tropism, and replication kinetics of ZIKV, in comparison with WNV and DENV in hiPSCs, hiPSCs-derived neural stem cells (NSCs) and undifferentiated neurons, and the effect of viral infection on host innate antiviral responses. In addition, we exploited hiPSCs to model ZIKV infection in the embryo and during stem cell differentiation towards the neuronal lineage. The results of this study confirmed the tropism of ZIKV for NSCs, but showed that WNV replicated in these cells with much higher efficiency, inducing massive cell death. Although with lower efficiency, all flaviviruses could also infect pluripotent stem cells and neurons, inducing similar patterns of antiviral innate immune response gene expression. While showing the usefulness of hiPSC-based infection models, these findings suggest that additional virus-specific mechanisms, beyond neural tropism, are responsible for the peculiarities of disease phenotype in humans. </p>
</text>
