<text id="autogum_bio_doc223" title="Governor Blacksnake" shortTile="governor-blacksnake" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-02-03" dateModified="2019-09-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Governor_Blacksnake" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Governor Blacksnake</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tah-won-ne-ahs</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Thaonawyuthe</hi> (born between 1737 and 1760, died 1859), known in English as either <hi rend="bold">Governor Blacksnake</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Chainbreaker</hi>, was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seneca_nation">Seneca</ref> war chief and leader. Along with other <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iroquois">Iroquois</ref> war chiefs (most notably <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mohawk_people">Mohawk</ref> leader <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joseph_Brant">Joseph Brant</ref>), he led warriors to fight on the side of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Great_Britain">British</ref> during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Revolutionary_War">American Revolutionary War</ref> from 1777 to 1783. He was prominent for his role at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Oriskany">Battle of Oriskany</ref>, in which the Loyalist and allied forces ambushed a force of rebels (now called Patriots).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-SenecaNation-1">[1]</ref> After the war he supported his maternal uncle <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Handsome_Lake">Handsome Lake</ref>, as a prominent religious leader. Governor Blacksnake allied with the United States in the War of 1812 and later encouraged some accommodation to European-American settlers, allowing missionaries and teachers on the Seneca reservation.</p>
<p>Importantly, he also led a successful postwar struggle in New York in the 1850s after white men illegally bought reservation land. He helped gain a New York State Appeals Court ruling in 1861 that restored the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oil_Springs_Reservation">Oil Springs Reservation</ref> to the Seneca.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHauptman2008-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>Governor Blacksnake was born near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seneca_Lake_(New_York)">Seneca Lake</ref> in western <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_York_(state)">New York</ref> in the Seneca/Cayuga village of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kendaia">Kendaia</ref></hi> (Apple Town).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> His mother was a Seneca woman of the Wolf clan and his father was known as <hi rend="italic">De-ne-oh-ah-te</hi> or "The Light".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-chainbreaker-4">[4]</ref> In the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matrilineal">matrilineal</ref> kinship system of the Iroquois nations, a child is born into his or her mother's clan and gains social status from her family. The maternal uncles were very influential in the child's life, especially the oldest brother of the mother.</p>
<p>He was raised in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canawaugus,_New_York">Canawaugus</ref>, a Seneca village known as <hi rend="italic">Ga:non'wagês</hi> (in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seneca_language">Seneca language</ref>), on the east side of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genesee_River">Genesee River</ref>. (The site has been absorbed into the village of Avon, Livingston County, New York).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-chainbreaker-4">[4]</ref> The war chief <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cornplanter">Cornplanter</ref> and sachem <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Handsome_Lake">Handsome Lake</ref> were his maternal uncles and also lived at <hi rend="italic">Ga:non'wagês</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-chainbreaker-4">[4]</ref> The Wolf <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clan">Clan</ref>'s traditional function for males of the Seneca was to serve as war chiefs.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHauptman200816-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>His birth date has been given variously from circa 1760 to as early as 1737 (as is claimed on his gravestone, which was erected in 1930. It erroneously states that he supported the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Continental_Army">Continental Army</ref> during the Revolution). A 1737 birthdate would have made him 121 or 122 years old at the time of death; historians do not believe this is likely. Chainbreaker was known to live an exceptionally long life, perhaps reaching the age of 100. He likely became recognized as a war chief for actions as a young adult. According to Draper, Blacksnake said he was two years old at the time of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sir_William_Johnson,_1st_Baronet">William Johnson</ref>'s defeat of the French on Lake George in 1755, and 22 at the time of the 1775 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Bunker_Hill">Battle of Bunker Hill</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-chainbreaker-4">[4]</ref> His death on December 26, 1859 was well documented.</p>
<p>In his youth, Chainbreaker accompanied his uncle <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cornplanter">Cornplanter</ref> "on special missions to see General <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Washington">George Washington</ref> as well as to members of the Continental Congress".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHauptman200816-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>After the Revolutionary War, in 1788 Chainbreaker moved to the large area of land in Pennsylvania granted to his uncle Cornplanter for his service by the state legislature, after his home village (Canawaugus) was sold to the United States in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phelps_and_Gorham_Purchase">Phelps and Gorham Purchase</ref> of Seneca lands. Converted to his uncle <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Handsome_Lake">Handsome Lake's</ref> religion, Chainbreaker became an active promoter of traditional ways. In 1803 he moved with Handsome Lake to nearby Coldspring, after a dispute with Cornplanter.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHauptman200818-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>While Blacksnake continued to advocate "temperance, morality, and adherence to the overall principles of Handsome Lake," he rejected his uncle's "proscription against Indian participation in the 'white man's wars".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHauptman200818-6">[6]</ref> By the 1840s Blacksnake had formulated his own version of his uncle's traditional ways. He generally urged finding a path of compromise. He permitted missionaries and Western schooling on the Reservation and encouraged his followers to work toward social harmony and to take advantage of schooling.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHauptman200818-6">[6]</ref></p>
<head>Involvement in regional warfare</head>
<p>In 1777 Blacksnake took part in the siege of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fort_Stanwix">Fort Stanwix</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Oriskany">Battle of Oriskany</ref> in British General <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barry_St._Leger">St. Leger's</ref> part of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saratoga_campaign">Saratoga campaign</ref>. In 1778 he participated in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Wyoming">Battle of Wyoming</ref> under the command of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Butler_(pioneer)">Colonel John Butler</ref>. In 1779 he attempted to defend Seneca settlements against the raid of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniel_Brodhead_IV">Colonel Daniel Brodhead</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Chainbreaker-7">[7]</ref>
Blacksnake carried messages for the British on a trail that passed through today's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Napoli,_New_York">Napoli, New York</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>After his work on behalf of the British in the Revolutionary War, Chainbreaker became reconciled to the United States establishing independence and forcing the Seneca and other Iroquois from most of their lands. He volunteered to fight on the American side in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War_of_1812">War of 1812</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHauptman2008-2">[2]</ref> and participated in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Fort_George">Battle of Fort George</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-SenecaNation-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Struggle for Oil Spring Reservation</head>
<figure><caption>Photograph of Governor Blacksnake, (Tha-o-na-wyuthe) or ("Tha--o-wa-nyuths,") "The Nephew" (Seneca).</caption></figure>
<p>Governor Blacksnake "helped save the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oil_Springs_Reservation">Oil Spring Reserve</ref>" for the Seneca. His victory in this New York State court case established a precedent for the land claim settled in June 2005 over <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cuba_Lake">Cuba Lake</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p>After the war, European Americans <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stanley_Clark">Stanley Clark</ref>, Benjamin Chamberlain, and William Gallagher bought lands adjacent to the Seneca Oil Spring Reservation. On behalf of these three men, Clark surveyed Reservation lands and claimed the area, granting one-quarter of the reservation to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Horatio_Seymour">Horatio Seymour</ref>, later elected as governor of New York. In the 1850s, Clark conveyed another quarter to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philonius_Pattison">Philonius Pattison</ref>.</p>
<p>In response to these actions, the Seneca filed a legal challenge that reached the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_York_Court_of_Appeals">New York Court of Appeals</ref>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seneca_Nation_of_Indians_v._Philonus_Pattison">Seneca Nation of Indians v. Philonus Pattison</ref></hi>. They protested against the Seymour, Gallagher, Chamberlain, and Clark claims to the northeast quarter of Oil Spring.</p>
<p>Governor Blacksnake, who had attended the negotiations of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treaty_of_Big_Tree">Treaty of Big Tree</ref> that established the reservation, testified that he and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joseph_Ellicott_(surveyor)">Joseph Ellicott</ref> had surveyed the Oil Spring lands and that the omission of a full legal description of the lands from the treaty was a mistake. He produced a map copied by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holland_Land_Company">Holland Land Company</ref>, in which the Oil Spring Reservation was marked similarly to other Seneca lands.</p>
<p>In 1861, the Court found for the Seneca Nation. Pattison, Chamberlain, Clark, Gallagher, and Seymour were forced to leave the reservation. While later incursions by the New York State Board of Canal Commissioners and tourist activities have taken additional land from the Reservation, Governor Blacksnake's actions helped preserve some of Oil Spring as Seneca land.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHauptman200829-10">[10]</ref></p>
<head>Later life</head>
<p>In later life, Chainbreaker's political influence waned, as younger Seneca men assumed control.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref> But he continued to participate in the Iroquois Condolence Council into his nineties. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHauptman200819-12">[12]</ref></p>
<p>Blacksnake died on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allegany_Reservation">Allegany Reservation</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cattaraugus_County,_New_York">Cattaraugus County, New York</ref> in late December 1859. He is remembered by the Seneca Nation as "a man of rare intellectual and moral power."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-SenecaNation-1">[1]</ref></p>
</text>
