<text id="autogum_interview_doc414" title="part4_Canada&amp;apos;s Scarborough East (Ward 44) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-scarborough" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-19" dateModified="2013-09-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Scarborough_East_%28Ward_44%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>I feel quite strongly about this issue because this type of media coverage unfairly stigmatizes the residents of Scarborough and Ward 44 and adversely affects property values and the quality of life of her residents, and makes it easier for downtown politicians to deny services for Scarborough residents.</p>
<p>Please see my website at www.Ward44.ca for a more complete essay on this subject.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What does Toronto mean to you? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> When I think about Toronto I think about home. I think about my ancestors who came to this great city via Ireland and the British Army in the 1850s and who had the intelligence to settle here. Toronto is where I was born and it is where I will live, fate willing, for the rest of my life. Toronto literally means "Meeting Place" deriving its meaning from the First Nations People who traded here. Toronto is still the "Meeting Place" for people from all walks of life and ethnic and religious backgrounds and is rich in history and natural beauty.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Q:'</hi> Which council decision (since the 2003 election) do you feel the city/your ward should be most proud of, and which was least desirable?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> There were no decisions that the City of Toronto implemented since the 2003 election that I am proud of. Our Ward 44 incumbent, Gay Cowbourne, won the 2003 election as a protest vote against the former councillor, Ron Moeser, who was known more for his chronic absenteeism and dismal voting record than in representing the people of Ward 44. Unfortunately, Ms. Cowbourne was not cut out for public life and delegated most of her duties to her paid assistants (who failed miserably in the process) and voted at City Hall according to the interests of the NDP bloc at City Hall and not for the residents of Ward 44. Ms. Cowbourne, not surprisingly, is retiring from politics and will not be seeking re-election.</p>
<p>I am disappointed with Council for concentrating almost exclusively on the Toronto Island Airport issue while the City of Toronto is on the brink of financial ruin with no long term plan to invest in the infrastructure of the city. The City of Toronto does not have the authority to stop the Toronto Airport Authority (which falls under the authority of the federal government) from expanding their operations thus wasting precious time and resources in the process.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> If you were elected as a "rookie" councillor, What would you bring to the table beyond the incumbent? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> First and foremost I would bring a dedication to the council position that Ward 44 has never had.  I will be a strong voice for the people of Ward 44 at City Hall and will not be influenced by special interest groups or the agendas of political parties who rarely represent the local interests and concerns of a particular ward.  Unlike Ron Moeser, who had his chance and failed miserably (Moeser was evicted from office by Ward 44 voters in 2003 due to his chronic absenteeism and his miserable voting record), I will be an extremely hard working councillor who will promote transparency and accountability at City Hall.  I will bring both corporate and academic expertise to the table which I have obtained from my years at the University of Toronto and my extensive business background.  I will bring a level of energy to City Hall that will be an inspiration for others to follow.</p>
</text>
