<text id="autogum_whow_doc500" title="Prepare Yourself for the Week Ahead" shortTile="prepare-yourself" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-11-03" dateModified="2018-10-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Prepare-Yourself-for-the-Week-Ahead" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Prepare Yourself for the Week Ahead</head><p>Do you find that your weekday evenings are absolutely absorbed by going to the gym, ferrying around the kids, catching up on chores, and more? Make things easier for yourself by taking time at the weekend to alleviate the midweek pressure.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Do your food shopping online. Most leading supermarkets offer a deliver-to-your-door service that cuts out the hassle of roaming around a massive food outlet, crammed with hungry shoppers (unless, of course, you live in the middle of nowhere). Before buying anything, plan out your every meal for the week. From this list of recipes, collate all the ingredients you will need. By ordering online, you can save time and money (no impulsive, in-store purchases of chocolate ice cream at 9pm). <figure rend="Prepare Yourself for the Week Ahead Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make meals ahead of time. You can make every single meal you need for the week on Sunday, but this can be a messy and tiring operation. A more time-effective tactic is to make the most of your appliances, such as your blender and your slow cooker. For these meals, you will only need to cut up your fruit and vegetables in advance, freeze, and then throw them together for a breakfast smoothie or main meal. Pinterest has some fantastic inspiration, so it’s worth doing some research. <figure rend="Prepare Yourself for the Week Ahead Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do the big cleaning jobs. Definitely don’t spend your entire, precious weekend scrubbing every nook and cranny of your kitchen, but get the big jobs out of the way, like cleaning out your microwave or treating your sink. You can always perform small maintenance jobs throughout the week, but you don’t want these tasks piling up on you when your time is short. Who can face tackling the oven after a long day at work and a difficult session in the gym? <figure rend="Prepare Yourself for the Week Ahead Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make room for treats and personal projects. Whatever you’ve got in store for your week, make time to do the things you enjoy the most. That could be watching your favourite programme with a tall glass of wine or picking up on an on-going, creative project. When outlining your weekly routine, be sure to allow for an hour of relaxation time for yourself. <figure rend="Prepare Yourself for the Week Ahead Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Create your schedule. This can be a tedious process, but it’s possible to make it fun, too! It may help to make your schedule as public as possible – that means investing in a white board or painting yourself a chalkboard wall! Unlike a diary, you can’t ignore this beacon of reminders. <figure rend="Prepare Yourself for the Week Ahead Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Manage your weekly closet. Hopefully you’re up-to-date with your laundry. If you are, that means you can create your weekly closet! Assemble your daily outfits on hangers marked with the days of the week, and iron what needs ironing. Pre-bag your gym kits (if you need them) and lay out your nightwear. This will allow you an extra ten minutes or so in bed! <figure rend="Prepare Yourself for the Week Ahead Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
