<text id="autogum_interview_doc741" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Christoph Bals of the NGO Germanwatch after conclusion of climate conference" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-12-24" dateModified="2009-03-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Christoph_Bals_of_the_NGO_Germanwatch_after_conclusion_of_climate_conference" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Christoph Bals of the NGO Germanwatch after conclusion of climate conference</head>Correction — February 25, 2008
Translation problems from German to English, see <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Talk:Wikinews_interviews_Christoph_Bals_of_the_NGO_Germanwatch_after_conclusion_of_climate_conference">Talk page</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 27, 2007</hi></p>
<hi rend="bold">A year ago I would have found the current outcome almost revolutionary. ... A lot has been achieved, but the biggest hurdles are still in front of us.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Christoph Bals, Senior Political Executive of Germanwatch</p>
<p>With the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2007%20United%20Nations%20Climate%20Change%20Conference">Climate Conference</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bali">Bali</ref> having come to a successful conclusion, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> journalist <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Sean_Heron">Sean Heron</ref> interviewed Christoph Bals from the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">German</ref> NGO <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Germanwatch">Germanwatch</ref> on his opinion of the outcome, and an outlook on the future negotiations. Christoph is the Senior Political Executive of Germanwatch, Co-Author of the Climate protection-Index and did lobby work on Bali.</p>
<head id="The_interview">The interview</head>
<head id="Introduction_to_Germanwatch">Introduction to Germanwatch</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wikinews: Could you explain what defines the organization Germanwatch and what your targets are?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Christoph Bals:</hi> Germanwatch is a non governmental organization (NGO) that has the environment and north south justice/fairness as its main topics. We don't actually execute any projects in the south, but lend issues that are of relevance to the south - the so called developing nations - a voice towards politics, the economy and on the financial market.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: Could you go into more specifics on what it is you do on climate change?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CB</hi>: Climate Change is one of our main topics. Both the reduction of greenhouse gas emissions and adaptation to climate change is important. For these two issues we engage ourselves both with regard to Germany and the least developed countries (LDCs). We are intensively involved in national and international political processes, building up pressure on politicians and economic players and/or working constructively with them, depending on how greater achievements are to be made.</p>
<head id="The_Negotiations_in_Bali">The Negotiations in Bali</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: The next question, which is very much at hand, is of course how Germanwatch views the outcome of the negotiations? Have your expectations been fulfilled?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CB</hi>: We haven't been able to write in the reduction targets that we would have needed. But these targets can still be achieved in the negotiating framework that the Roadmap has put down. The biggest obstacle here were the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref>. It won't be possible to agree to targets with this administration, but hopefully, in two years and with the next administration, we'll be able to agree to the necessary global targets.</p>
<hi rend="bold">It is to be hoped for ... that a coalition of progressive industrial nations, least developed countries ... and newly industrialized countries - for example China, Mexico, South Africa, India - support this. There were first signs for such a development in Bali.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Christoph Bals</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: Would you have expected this outcome yesterday? Or a year ago?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CB</hi>: A year ago I would have found the current outcome almost revolutionary. Compared with my expectations before the negotiation it's different though; I then still had the hope that there would be more extensive progress at the end of this climate year. If you look at the packages that have been agreed on: technology transfer and development, adaptation to climate change, financial mechanisms, forest protection; then you can see that quite a substantial process has been started. So a lot has been achieved, but the biggest hurdles are still in front of us.</p>
</text>
