<text id="autogum_academic_doc246" title="Multilayer Perceptron-Based Phenological and Radiometric Normalization for High-Resolution Satellite Imagery" shortTile="multilayer-perceptronbased" author="Dae  Kyo Seo, Yang  Dam Eo" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/9/21/4543/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Results and Discussion</head><head> 3.1. Comparisons of Normalization Results</head>
<p>
This section presents the normalization results of the proposed algorithm and then compares them with the results of a conventional algorithm. First, our proposed normalization process is performed step-by-step for the experimental images, in which the radiometric resolution is compressed to 8-bits, and the spectral indices of the blue, green, red, and NIR bands are selected as ExG, COM, ExGR, and ExG, respectively. Subsequently, the results of our proposed method are compared with the conventional methods (MS, NC, histogram matching, and random forest (RF)) to evaluate them visually and quantitatively, and <figure>Figure 6</figure>, <figure>Figure 7</figure> and <figure>Figure 8</figure> show the results for each experimental image. </p>

<p>From the overall visual inspection, the normalization of the proposed method is shown to be better than that of the conventional methods. MS and NC, which are regression-based methods, assume that the relationship between the subject and reference images is linear. However, as shown in the results, neither the phenological properties nor the radiometric properties are normalized. In other words, it can be confirmed that it is not appropriate to assume a linear relationship in the case of high-resolution images, in which vegetation changes exist. In the case of histogram matching, it is a representative nonlinear normalization method, which is based on global statistical information. Overall, the radiometric properties are normalized, while the normalization for the phenological properties is not performed at all. That is, when only statistical information is used, it is possible to normalize the radiometric properties, but there is a limit to phenological normalization. RF is a nonlinear method that is performed through RF regression, which uses neighbor information-based features, such as the mean, variance, and gray-level co-occurrence matrix as the training input values. The results of this method show that the radiometric and phenological normalizations are performed, but spectral distortion is present. Furthermore, blurriness occurs in the results due to the neighbor information-based features, which results in some loss of detail, especially on linear objects. On the other hand, our proposed method shows that the radiometric and phenological normalizations are properly performed, and there is no spectral distortion or blurriness in the results.  </p>

<p>To verify the radiometric and phenological normalization results in detail, some regions are selected and enlarged, with red rectangles representing the built-up areas and green rectangles representing the vegetation areas. <figure>Figure 9</figure> shows built-up areas, which represent the radiometric properties, consist of roads and the roofs of buildings, and the enlarged areas for each normalization result. For roads, the proposed method normalizes the radiometric properties in such a way that the image is the closest in consistency with the reference image, while, in the case of roofs, the results vary for the site. For site 2, showing a relatively large roof, the radiometric properties normalized through the proposed method show the most similarity with those of the reference image, whereas for site 3, showing several small roofs, the proposed method displays some turbidity when compared to other methods. In other words, roofs are affected by their objective size, which is judged according to its geometric distortion. Large-sized objects can be trained properly, even in the presence of geometric distortion, while small-sized objects acquire the characteristic of other surrounding objects, which adversely affects training. For vegetation areas, phenological properties, such as forests, grass, and crops, are included, and <figure>Figure 10</figure> shows the corresponding enlarged areas. In the case of forests, it is confirmed that the areas without vegetation due to the phenological properties in the subject image are normalized to the same phenological properties as the reference image at all sites. For grass and crops, the performance of normalization is somewhat less than that for forests due to the heterogenous characteristics, but it contains the characteristics of the reference image as a whole.  </p>

<p>Although visual inspection is a straightforward and direct manner of comparison, it is highly subjective; thus, quantitative evaluations of each method are further performed based on NRMSE. The NRMSE is defined as in Equations (12) and (13):

(12)

(13)

where  is RCSSs in the normalized image of band ;  is the RCSSs in the reference image of band ;  is the total number of RCSSs; and,  is the mean of RCSSs in the reference image of band <hi rend="italic">i</hi>. Table 3 shows the NRMSE for the results of the proposed method and the conventional methods. </p>
</text>
