<text id="autogum_interview_doc730" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Brian Moore, Socialist Party USA presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-30" dateModified="2016-07-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Brian_Moore%2C_Socialist_Party_USA_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Moore:</hi> The immigration problem stems from greed and exploitive policies of the American government against many third and fourth world nations, that have undermined their economy and caused great poverty and suffering worldwide.  I am in favor of full amnesty for all legal and illegal immigrants, the provision of full social services to all residents in our country, and the implementation of socialism which will guarantee free and full health benefits, education and housing to all its residents.  Plus we will institute worker ownership and a guaranteed annual income for all adults, even for those incapacitated by handicaps, homelessness, etc.  We will eliminate all for-profit corporations, closed down all foreign military bases, reduce our defense budget in half, and then more in the years to come.  We will also end arms sales, and stop the use and sale of all nuclear power both militarily and commercially.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Campaigning for the American presidency is one of the most expensive exercises in the world. How do you deal with the cost and fundraising? </hi></item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">Moore:</hi> Not very well. Presently, the only candidates who succeed in our system are millionaires, or sellouts to corporate America and special interests.  Public funding of future campaigns, universal laws for all fifty states to allow equal and fair ballot access to multiple and minor party candidates will be necessary to open up the system.  Plus, we will take back the airways, and require if not award equal television and radio time for all candidates.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Do you believe that it is really possible for you to win the 2008 election, being a third party candidate and all? </hi></item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">Moore:</hi> Hell no!  We will be fortunate to get on the ballot in 20 states.  There is a possible, but not highly probable, reason that it could happen due to catastrophic events in our country such as war, economic collapse, assassinations, etc. or due to the throwing of support from several other minor parties to a candidate (i.e. a socialist party candidate being endorsed by the Green Party and a strong Independent candidate like Ralph Nader, or visa versa, thereby enabling one single candidate to be on the ballot on 45 to 50 states).</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Can any third party or independent candidate ever win?</hi></item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">Moore:</hi> Yes, per the rationale mentioned in answer #11; or from an attractive third party candidate and an even split from the other two major party candidates.  Remember, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bill_Clinton">Bill Clinton</ref> won the 1992 presidency with 39% of the vote, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/George_H.W._Bush">George Bush</ref> with 37%, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ross%20Perot">Ross Perot</ref> with 20% (he was up to 40% in the early part of the campaign and won up to 28% in some states).  Plus, the country is getting tired of holding its nose and voting for the lesser of two evils, plus the number of Independent and minor party candidates is growing and about to surpass one or both of the two major parties in percentage registered.</p>
</text>
