<text id="autogum_reddit_doc159" title="Another 'be your own advocate' post" shortTile="another--advocate" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2017-01-30" dateModified="2017-01-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/5r5gh7" speakerList="#-particularpenguin-" speakerCount="1">
<head>Another 'be your own advocate' post</head>
<sp who="#-particularpenguin-">
<p>So as I'm sure most of you know, this cycle has been all over the place. Original 7.5mg dose of letrozle did nothing, so we redosed on cd19 which became 'new' cd2. New cd 9 I started bleeding bright red (more than spotting), which lasted til cd12, but cd11 scan showed a big follicle and I was having a ton of eggwhite, so I thought we were set. Cd16 come around and no surge. Asked for a trigger, got it and did that on CD 17. Well, ewcm kept coming on in droves, and I wasn't getting any of my post O symptoms. So I emailed my nurse asking for a blood test - she was insistent that the trigger works, but ordered it anyway. Well, results come back today and my other nurse calls me. The convo goes something like this: Her: so, [nurse] told me to call you with your progesterone results, but I wasnt sure why you had it done. It did come back at .4 though, so you didn't ovulate. Me: yea, I asked for it because I thought the trigger didn't work. Guess I was right. Her: so, yea, but the trigger always works and you had a follicle.. so, maybe you ovulated before. Me: but then wouldn't my progesterone show that? Her: yea, you're right. So, do you want to just end the cycle or see what happens? Me: um, what does the Dr recommend? Her: well, you could have a phone consultation tomorrow - I'll have to charge you $100 though. Me: uh, no, I'll just email her then? Her: OK, well, you should take a pregnancy test in a week, just in case. You know, in case the trigger did work. I couldn't even respond to that - it was almost comical. So emailed the Dr with what happened and she emailed me back in like 10 min with an acknowledgement that the follicle we saw could have been a cyst and an offer to come in tomorrow to get an ultrasound and come up with a plan for no charge (I'll believe that when I see it, hah). Yay for knowing my body and pushing for answers! Will update with the plan tomorrow :) </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#-particularpenguin-">
<p>Update: well, that was all unexpected. Ultrasound showed no follicles growing (hooray, no cyst!). She was very confused about what that follicle was we saw last time or where it came from hah </p>
<p>My lining was still thin-ish so we're redosing letrozle 10mg starting tonight! Woo for no provera! (I asked if my lining would be all old and crusty, and she said no and that there's some evidence that this way has higher success than doing a provera withdrawal bleed - yay for learning something new!) </p>
<p>We're also adding a trigger which should really reduce the stress on both me and Mr Penguin on timing. </p>
<p>If this is a bust we'll add injectables next cycle, but she's pretty nervous that I'll over respond (she only wants to see one follicle). </p>
<p>So overall pretty happy with next steps! </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#-particularpenguin-">
<p>Update: well, that was all unexpected. Ultrasound showed no follicles growing (hooray, no cyst!). She was very confused about what that follicle was we saw last time or where it came from hah </p>
<p>My lining was still thin-ish so we're redosing letrozle 10mg starting tonight! Woo for no provera! (I asked if my lining would be all old and crusty, and she said no and that there's some evidence that this way has higher success than doing a provera withdrawal bleed - yay for learning something new!) </p>
<p>We're also adding a trigger which should really reduce the stress on both me and Mr Penguin on timing. </p>
<p>If this is a bust we'll add injectables next cycle, but she's pretty nervous that I'll over respond (she only wants to see one follicle). </p>
<p>So overall pretty happy with next steps! </p>
</sp>
</text>
