<text id="autogum_voyage_doc371" title="Belgrave" shortTile="belgrave" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=3278" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Belgrave</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.visitvictoria.com/Regions/Yarra-Valley-and-Dandenong-Ranges/Destinations/Belgrave.aspx">Belgrave</ref></hi> is a city in <ref target="Yarra%20Valley">Yarra Valley</ref>, east of Melbourne.</p>

<p>Belgrave is a suburb in <ref target="Melbourne">Melbourne</ref>, 35 km east from central business district. Its Local Government Area is the Shire of Yarra Ranges. At the 2006 Census, Belgrave had a population of 4094. Belgrave was first settled in 1851, it is only 16 years younger than Melbourne.</p>

<p>Belgrave was named after an 1840s chapel in <ref target="Leeds">Leeds</ref>, Yorkshire, England; the name carried by Mr and Mrs R.G. Benson when they came to Melbourne in 1856.</p>

<head>By car</head>

<p>From Melbourne head east along Burwood Hwy.</p>

<p>From Gippsland and Mornington Peninsula head north along Belgrave-Hallam Rd.</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>Belgrave is the final station on the Belgrave line. Travel from Melbourne takes approximately 1 hour.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<p>Hiking and cycling are popular activities in the area and a visitor can appreciate much by choosing one of these methods of transportation.</p>

<p>Adjacent to the Belgrave train station is the major bus terminus for the area with multiple routes servicing the local areas.</p>
<p>There is plenty of parking and much of the hinterland is accessible by car.</p>

<head>See</head>
<p>Every year, usually on the Saturday closest to the Winter solstice (late June) a <hi rend="bold">Winter Lantern Festival</hi> is held along the main street of Belgrave. People are encouraged to make a lantern and bring it along where a procession is then held to light up the night sky.</p>

<head>Do</head>
<p>Puffing Billy historic steam train commences its journey from Belgrave. The train station follows on from the suburban train line.</p>

<p>There are various National Parks in the area, all accessible by car or foot.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sherbrooke Forest</hi> (1km out of Belgrave on the Monbulk Road). A unique and ecologically valuable example of sub-tropical rain forest. The flora and fauna are broad and varied; the forest of great white Victorian mountain ash (the world's tallest tree species) and giant tree ferns. If you walk quietly, especially around dawn you may hear and even be privileged to glimpse the Male Lyrebird's dance. Be sure to include Sherbrooke falls on your walk through this tranquil forest.</item>
</list>


<p>Belgrave Adventure Tree Park is situated approximately 500 metres from the town centre.</p>

<p>The Cameo Cinemas are the local cinemas and are set in an attractive art deco era building. During summer there are also outdoor cinema sessions held.</p>

<head>Buy</head>
<p>Belgrave has an eclectic mix of small shops as well as a supermarket, post office, bakery and organic shop.</p>

<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Earthly Pleasures Cafe.</item>
<item> The Green Bean (cafe).</item>
<item> India Gate restaurant.</item>
<item> Micawbers Tavern (app 1km east of town centre on Monbulk Rd).</item>
<item> Puffing Billy Cafe.</item>
<item> Reel (adjacent to the cinema).</item>
<item> Sushi Train.</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Bells Tavern.</item>
<item> Oscar's Ale House.</item>
<item> Rubys.</item>
<item> Scarab Bar.</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Glen Harrow Heights B&amp;B.</item>
</list>
</text>
