<text id="autogum_interview_doc378" title="part5_Wikinews interviews Australian Statistician Brian Pink" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-19" dateModified="2008-04-30" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_Statistician_Brian_Pink" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Were there any similar initiatives in New Zealand when you were there?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BP</hi>: Yeah, there were. I mean, the Indigenous people in Australia are 2.2 to 2.3 per cent of our population. In New Zealand, Maori people are 15% of the population, and so for an even longer period than here in Australia  an important part of the statistical activities of the national statistical office there have been to provide and improve statistics for Maori people and about Maori people.</p>
<head id='Mathematical_education_and_the_"brain_drain"'>Mathematical education and the "brain drain"</head>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Just on a last note, there are reports every few years talking about the decline in certain skills in graduates, in particular mathematics and science seem to be one of the more heavily affected. As an employer of obviously a lot of statistical graduates, has the Bureau had problems in finding candidates?</p>
<hi rend="bold">I am concerned [...] we're not producing enough people with the skills to take full advantage of this rich range of resources that we produce these days.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—On mathematics graduates from Australian universities</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BP</hi>: We haven't had problems in finding candidates, in fact I think we continue to be very, I won't say "lucky", but we've been very successful in being able to attract the numbers of young mathematical science graduates that we need for our business. But if you asked me in a much more general context, both the previous Statistician and myself, and when I was in New Zealand I pursued this as well, there is definitely a decline in the number of kids basically going through high school and coming out of high school with higher mathematics, doing the tougher mathematics subjects as they go through. That feeds through into the universities - we've seen here in Australia over the last decade or more a significant shrinking of the maths and stats departments in a lot of the universities around Australia, and I think that we do, and I am concerned, at a time when as a society we rely more and more on information and the skills and the abilities to design, collect, analyse, interpret, model information for decision, public and private and personal, at a time when we're putting so much more emphasis on the importance of information in decision processes, we're not producing enough people with the skills to take full advantage of this rich range of resources that we produce these days. So yes, I am concerned.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : And is there another concern with the loss of skilled professionals overseas - the "brain drain"?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BP</hi>: Well I think that's gone on for a long time in Australia, and then if you were in New Zealand they complain about the brain drain to Australia. We live in a global world now, and the skilled people are very portable, and so we have to - and that's another reason why we should be thinking about the sorts of skills that the nation needs as you look forward in the next couple of decades of the 21st century - we need to be encouraging the kids through the school system and then into the post-school education systems to take the sorts of courses that are going to be the sorts of skills that the nation needs to continue to develop and prosper, and I think that's a challenge that's there, and we have to accept that a part of the people that we train and develop will go offshore. That's reality, and we will attract people from overseas to come here. So I don't think we should be - that's not what worries me, to be honest. It's getting enough people coming through to ensure that we do have the skills in our society that allow us to continue to develop those skills, those quantitative skills of being able to work with information and analyse and interpret, model it as I said, and be able to make good decisions based on good evidence in whatever context - in biotechnology, in technology, in social sciences, in environmental sciences - they all need people with skills of being able to understand and work with data, and we're not producing enough really well-skilled people in that space.</p>
</text>
