<text id="autogum_reddit_doc134" title="solo Kryla carry for Scorch of the White Dragon Trial (3/4 missions completed)" shortTile="solo-kryla-carry" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-04-28" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8fmjy7" speakerList="#GymTurtle, #m177a" speakerCount="2">
<head>solo Kryla carry for Scorch of the White Dragon Trial (3/4 missions completed)</head>
<sp who="#m177a">
<p># Kryla carry for Scorn of the White DragonTrial  <hi rend="bold"> A week hasn't even passed and yet my Kryla was able to solo this boss without any issues. The main thing to take into consideration is that you will probably have to run this trial again to get the 5</hi>  trust moogle but with all of the other restrictions out of the way, it should be a lot easier to achieve.  <hi rend="bold"> Why does this work? The Hex mechanic is a consistent DOT damage that feeds off of negative effects on a unit. This boss only has 1.2 million hp and the damage from Hex is not effected by the buffs of the target. # What to bring: </hi>  Bring one unit with the Hide skill. This unit will remain hidden for the entire fight. Kryla cannot generate enough esper orbs for you to do a summon. # Boss Fight  <hi rend="bold"> Turn 1: use Nullifying Chant </hi>  Turn 2 and on: cycle through debuffs and Hex. *  <hi rend="bold">ALERT: DEFEND when the boss' HP drops below 80%, 60%, and 40%. If you don't, you risk dying from his elemental attacks.</hi>  Note: using Kryla's LB is optional but keep in mind that it will add one extra turn into the rotation. Just remember to use Wicked Eye instead of Hex. You have 2 turns to use it before it disappears. # Link to video  <hi rend="bold"> https://youtu.be/_m7XprgSURg # Equipment and Esper </hi>  Kryla 6★  <hi rend="bold"> Right hand: Wing Edges ATK+45 </hi>  Left hand: Zodiac Escutcheon DEF+60, SPR+70  <hi rend="bold"> Head: Cat-ear Hood MAG+25, SPR+25 </hi>  Body: Rainbow Robe DEF+45, MAG+45, SPR+45  <hi rend="bold"> Accessory 1: Ring of the Lucii ATK+30%, MAG+3, MAG+30%, SPR+3 </hi>  Accessory 2: Ring of the Lucii ATK+30%, MAG+3, MAG+30%, SPR+3  <hi rend="bold"> Materia 1: Magic Sanctuary SPR+15% </hi>  Materia 2: Pure White Blessing  <hi rend="bold"> Materia 3: True Spirit of Freedom ATK+20% </hi>  Materia 4: Equip H Shield  <hi rend="bold"> Esper: Titan HP+60, MP+20, ATK+53, DEF+40, MAG+18, SPR+32 </hi>  Total: HP:5275, MP:346, ATK:371, DEF:301, MAG:350, SPR:407 # Other Carries Anyone willing to carry should make a top level comment below. If you want to carry and would like the help please comment directly to the post with your ID and equipment. # Notes and Updates Please post your ID and user name. When you are done with beating it, kindly remove yourself to make room for others.  <hi rend="bold">Updates: 5/1/18 - 7:59 am PST - looks like the majority of players are done with this trial. I will end the carry tonight after reset.</hi>  # Friends List and Friends Request List (what's the difference?) * Make room on your  <hi rend="bold">FRIENDS LIST</hi>  (this is NOT the same as your friend request list)!! * If your friends list is full, I will get this <ref target="https://imgur.com/a/XKKeg">message</ref>. Please make space on your <ref target="https://imgur.com/a/UTUGx">Friends List</ref>! * Make room on your  <hi rend="bold">FRIENDS REQUEST LIST</hi>  (this is NOT the same as your friend list)!! * If your friends request list is full, I will get this <ref target="https://imgur.com/a/KwqZ6">message</ref>. Please make space on your <ref target="https://imgur.com/a/T43TV">Friends Request List</ref>!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#GymTurtle">
<p>ID : 987,079,675 </p>
<p>IGN: DSPhil </p>
<p>Just recently got back into the game and the damage meta has changed so much. Thank you, appreciate you helping people.</p>
</sp>
</text>
