<text id="autogum_interview_doc497" title="part0_Eric Bogosian on writing and the creative urge" shortTile="parteric-bogosian" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-16" dateModified="2014-05-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eric_Bogosian_on_writing_and_the_creative_urge" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Eric Bogosian on writing and the creative urge</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 17, 2008</hi></p>
<figure rend="Eric Bogosian by David Shankbone.jpg"></figure>Eric Bogosian is one of America's great multi-dimensional talents.  "There's sort of three different careers, and any one of them could exist by itself, on its own two feet.  There was that solo stuff, and then I started writing plays in the late seventies."  Although his work has spanned genres, most readers will recognize Bogosian for his acting, which has included a memorable performance in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Woody%20Allen">Woody Allen</ref>'s <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deconstructing%20Harry">Deconstructing Harry</ref></hi> to co-writing and starring in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oliver%20Stone">Oliver Stone</ref> movie <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk%20Radio%20(film)">Talk Radio</ref></hi> (based upon his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pulitzer%20Prize">Pulitzer Prize</ref>-nominated <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk%20Radio%20(play)">play</ref>) to playing the bad guy in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Under%20Siege%202">Under Siege 2</ref></hi> to his current role in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Law%20&amp;%20Order:%20Criminal%20Intent">Law &amp; Order: Criminal Intent</ref></hi> as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Danny%20Ross">Captain Danny Ross</ref>.  They may not know, however, that he had collaborated with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frank%20Zappa">Frank Zappa</ref> on a album, worked with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sonic%20Youth">Sonic Youth</ref>, and was a voice on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mike%20Judge">Mike Judge</ref>'s <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beavis%20&amp;%20Butthead%20Do%20America">Beavis &amp; Butthead Do America</ref></hi>.  He started one of New York City's largest dance companies, The Kitchen, which is still in existence.  He starred alongside <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Val%20Kilmer">Val Kilmer</ref> in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wonderland%20(film)">Wonderland</ref></hi> and his play <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk%20Radio%20(play)">Talk Radio</ref></hi> was recently revived on Broadway with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liev%20Schreiber">Liev Schreiber</ref> in the role Bogosian wrote and made famous. 
<p>Currently at work on his third novel, tentatively titled <hi rend="italic">The Artist</hi>, Bogosian spoke with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref> about the craft of writing and his life as a creative.</p>
<head id="Bogosian's_view_of_his_work">Bogosian's view of his work</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">David Shankbone:  Which role are you most proud of?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Eric Bogosian:</hi>  The <hi rend="italic">Talk Radio</hi> role was pretty significant, I mean, that film is still out there.  And it continues to draw attention to itself.  I pretty much starred in three movies; <hi rend="italic">Talk Radio</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Under Siege 2</hi>, and a film called <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wonderland%20(film)">Wonderland</ref></hi> with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Val%20Kilmer">Val Kilmer</ref> that I did a few years ago, in which I played a--anyway, you can look it up on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IMDB">IMDB</ref>.  But it's, um--that was a pretty insane role.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What kind of roles do you typically go for?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  Well, I'll play anything if I like the role, if I like the writing; if I think that the character has a real agenda, is an interesting character.  I avoid what I think of as "furniture roles,"--I don't care how large or small the role is.  For instance, my part in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Woody%20Allen">Woody Allen</ref> movie <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deconstructing%20Harry">Deconstructing Harry</ref></hi> on the page is a small role.  It's only a few pages long.  But it's a great character, and it's a memorable character.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And it's Woody Allen.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  And it's Woody Allen, yeah.  I'm three of the voices on Beavis &amp; Butthead Do America.  I have had this really exciting time of being working with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taylor%20Hackford">Taylor Hackford</ref> and Woody Allen and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert%20Altman">Robert Altman</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul%20Shrader">Paul Schrader</ref>.  But also, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mike%20Judge">Mike Judge</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frank%20Zappa">Frank Zappa</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sonic%20Youth">Sonic Youth</ref>...  These are wide-ranging in the different kinds of things I've worked on.  Those are some of the more prominent things.  That play in 1994 was a big deal; the film that came out of it is a big deal.  Around 2000 I started doing the books, and now I'm on my third novel.  That's sort of the overview of the whole thing, at least from my perspective.</p>
</text>
