<text id="autogum_reddit_doc093" title="So expo is over and feedback is coming in. So far it sounds.... bad. Did fan expo/Informa ruin our CCEE?" shortTile="expo-over-feedback" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-04-30" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8g1tqz" speakerList="#MrGraveRisen, #zoziw" speakerCount="2">
<head>So expo is over and feedback is coming in. So far it sounds.... bad. Did fan expo/Informa ruin our CCEE?</head>
<sp who="#MrGraveRisen">
<p>So some cliffnotes on what I've seen/heard complaints about both internally and externally: * Accessibility assistance is all but removed. <ref target="http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/calgary/calgary-expo-accessibility-1.4635825">with valid complaints</ref>  <hi rend="bold"> "cosplay is not consent" signs were.... completely removed. </hi>  Vendor booth prices rose drastically after Informa took over, and policies were required of existing booths suck as fire-resistant tablecloths, that forced many to drop out due to costs. And costs are expected to rise even more next year  <hi rend="bold"> BMO hall rows were lined up the opposite direction of what they were in previous years, resulting in booths that had support poles in the middle of them. No discount for a space with a pole intruding in it. </hi>  On setup there were no clear numbers marking booths, just chalk outlines. Many vendors had no idea where they were supposed to be because of the chalk being worn off and having no clear signage at all as to where the numbers were.  <hi rend="bold"> During load in/out no cars were allowed near the loading docks. Carts were available to move gear in and out of the expo hall, but they were limited and some vendors were sitting for hours trying to load in/out waiting for a big enough cart to be free. </hi>  Space in artists alley sold out to tesla and mazda, because a new car is just what every broke nerd needs  <hi rend="bold"> Refundable passes were actively difficult to get refunded and cost far more than they should have. And there was a lot of regret for non-refundable tickets after all the cancellations </hi>  the cancellations! We were left with really.... one "big ticket" celebrity that people were dying to meet. Even aquaman decided that he would only show up for a day and a bit.  <hi rend="bold"> Autograph and photo prices were significantly higher than even last year and forced many people out of being able to justify purchasing. </hi>  Saturday afternoon, busiest day of the expo, and there was NO LINEUP at the big4 food court in the lower level. None. Nobody was in line at any of the food stalls. I have NEVER seen that happen at expo.  <hi rend="bold"> Passes available to vendors for help/volunteers was extremely limited. vendors did not get lanyards this year (just black string) and had to pay for actual lanyards. </hi>  The rain on Sunday caused roof leaks which damaged products on a few vendors tables, and there was absolutely no response or compensation from expo. The leaks were just left to... leak. All this is coming directly from vendors that I know, or friends of friends who are also vendors. there are a LOT of very frustrated and upset people who tried to make something of expo this year. </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#zoziw">
<p>I went with my kid on Saturday from about 11 am to 3:30 pm. Everywhere was busy, especially the Big4 food court when we were there at 2:30. Massive lines, no place to sit. It took us 15 minutes to get a drink at the Coke Freestyle booth. </p>
<p>We weren't able to find as much merchandise as last year, vendors either didn't have what we were looking for or not in our size. Every second booth seemed to be selling bobbleheads though...I must be missing the trend or something. </p>
<p>I went for my son to see Tom Cavanagh from The Flash and we enjoyed both his panel and getting to meet him quickly during the photo op. He has a short film he showed before the panel and was very entertaining while answering fan questions...maybe a bit overboard on the habs though. The 20 - 30 seconds we saw him for the photo op seemed like 5 minutes to my son, class act all the way. </p>
<p>Our attending next year will be based on who is coming and what panels are on. I won't make a trip just to browse the vendors.</p>
</sp>
</text>
