<text id="autogum_interview_doc661" title="part4_Gay Talese on the state of journalism, Iraq and his life" shortTile="partgay-talese-state" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-27" dateModified="2019-01-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gay_Talese_on_the_state_of_journalism%2C_Iraq_and_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="On_the_media_and_Iraq">On the media and Iraq</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do you think is the reason there is this collective idea to give Americans a certain view of a place or a people that is not necessarily accurate? I think Iran is another good example, where we are consistently fed images and notions about a people and a culture that aren't really accurate.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  Or fair minded.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Or fair minded. But the reality is far more interesting than the same stories we are consistently fed.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  Well it involves more work. I think most journalists are pretty lazy, number one. A little lazy and also they're spoon-fed information, such as the weapons of mass destruction back in 2003. It's easy. There are all these lobbyist groups, these special interest groups. Each of them has a position with regard to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taiwan">Taiwan</ref>, for example. The anti-China lobby is very strong. Whether it's the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National%20Rifle%20Association">gun lobby</ref> or the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Israeli%20lobby">Israeli lobby</ref> or the Taiwan lobby, whatever the hell it is, you have these people who create a package of news, develop it as a story line, a scenario, and they find, as Mailer once said about the press, that they're like a donkey. You have to feed the donkey. The donkey every day has to eat. So these people throw information at this damn animal that eats everything. Tin cans, garbage.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And Americans are the donkeys as well?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  Well the media ....</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But people are still consuming what they're throwing out there though.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  Yeah, they are, because they're getting stories. In Iraq the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Embedded%20journalist">whole press is embedded</ref>. Those correspondents who drive around in tanks and armored personnel carriers, who are spoon-fed what the military gives them and they become mascots for the military, these journalists.  I wouldn't have journalists embedded if I had any power! You said what would you do? Well there are stories to be done. There are a lot of stories to be done. You don't have to have military protection.  There are stories you can do that aren't done. I've said that many times. What story would you do? Well even if you're stuck in the Green Zone you can do stories.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It's dangerous to actually go out there and hit the pavement. </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  Supposed you don't have to go out there? There are stories to be done in the Green Zone, within whatever the walls of protection are. You could do stories about Iraqis who work within the Green Zone. You could do stories about what kind of sexual activity goes on. Back to sex now. Here's what's important: In times of occupation of every historical event involving the United States, whether it's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World%20War%20II">World War II</ref>, whether it's the war in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vietnam%20War">Vietnam</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Korean%20War">Korea</ref>, occupation of Japan after World War II, World War I, there's always been a private relationship with the people of the country that's been invaded. Always.</p>
</text>
