<text id="autogum_interview_doc246" title="part4_Dr. Joseph Merlino on sexuality, insanity, Freud, fetishes and apathy" shortTile="partdr-joseph-merlino" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-04" dateModified="2013-09-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dr._Joseph_Merlino_on_sexuality%2C_insanity%2C_Freud%2C_fetishes_and_apathy" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How would psychoanalysis handle something like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Obsessive-compulsive%20disorder">Obsessive-compulsive disorder</ref>?  It seems like the treatments that have been most successful are <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/behavioral-cognitive">behavioral-cognitive</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SSRI">SSRI</ref> therapy.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  I think we have to cede ground on that.  As a psychiatrist who is analytically trained, I like to think of myself as a dynamic psychiatrist.  Meaning that I use some of the theories that we have talked about to help inform my approach to a patient, but I importantly also consider my medical and psychiatric knowledge.  In the case of OCD, the preferred treatments are often medication and cognitive behavioral therapy.  I recently worked with an OCD individual, at the insistence of his behavior therapist who wanted me to help the individual figure out why he was having a hard time accepting medication.  In the end, frankly, I referred him back to the behavioral therapist because our treatment wasn't going anywhere.</p>
<head id="Gender_identity_and_Heteronormativity">Gender identity and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heteronormativity">Heteronormativity</ref></head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How do you explain the exaggerated <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Effeminacy">femininity</ref> of some gay men?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  It's a complex question and I do not have an easy answer.  I think some of it is political, some of it is provocative, and some of it is genuine.  I think that there <hi rend="italic">are</hi> people who are naturally feminine.  We all come in different flavors and colors, and it's the same in terms of our personality tributes, whether male or female.  There are some heterosexual women who are more masculine, and some heterosexual men who are more feminine.  The same with gay men.  In addition to that, some of it is a provocative stance, certainly earlier on back when it was more of a 'fuck you' attitude than it might need to be today.  For example, drag queens or the front of the gay pride parade, which is more of a very in-your-face, we are here, we are comfortable with who we are, and we can be as provocative as we can be because we are who we are, and we are entitled to be this way.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chris%20Crocker%20(Internet%20celebrity)">Chris Crocker</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/YouTube">YouTube</ref> celebrity known for his in-your-face femininity, perhaps falls in that category.  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  Look at the other side of it, some of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hip%20hop%20culture">rappers</ref> who epitomize raw masculinity in an in-your-face kind of way, and I would see that as the other end of the spectrum, but doing a similar thing.  A 'fuck you' kind of attitude, 'I have the right to be who I am' kind of thing.  There's a whole spectrum, and most of us fall in the middle.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What is the process by which a person develops a gender?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi> It's complex.  Part of it is genetic endowment.  Nature versus nurture.  Part of it is what we come from, who we come from, and that, together with the environment in which we grow.  For example, we can have a genetic endowment that predisposes us towards femininity, but we are nurtured in a family that is extremely orthodox, 'you're a boy, so you're going to be a man.'  That kid may grow up to be a rather straight, but conflicted, kind of individual.  A macho kind of guy, or a macho gay guy, may have some conflict around the environment he grew up in.  I think it's an amalgam of genetics, our environment we grow up in, and whatever experiences we come across along the way.  That's what fine tunes that individual into what he or she will become.</p>
</text>
