<text id="autogum_interview_doc248" title="part6_Dr. Joseph Merlino on sexuality, insanity, Freud, fetishes and apathy" shortTile="partdr-joseph-merlino" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-04" dateModified="2013-09-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dr._Joseph_Merlino_on_sexuality%2C_insanity%2C_Freud%2C_fetishes_and_apathy" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Can a person be a paraphiliac and not have it be a problem?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  No, because the term itself is a diagnosis and if you look at the current listing of diagnoses, the one thing you will find as a qualifier on every one of them for it to be considered a disorder is that it must interfere with functioning, personal interrelationships, career, etc.  Absent that, we can't give it a diagnosis.  So <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rudolph%20Giuliani">Giuliani</ref> gets dressed up, we don't say he has a disorder.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When would <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/cross-dressing">cross-dressing</ref> become a disorder?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi> When it creates a problem for that individual.  For instance, I'm a cross-dresser and I don't want to keep it confined to my circle of friends, or my party circle, and I want to take that to my wife and I don't understand why she doesn't accept it, or I take it to my office and I don't understand why they don't accept it, then it's become a problem because it's interfering with my relationships and environment.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So pathology is almost always defined in relation to your interaction with the outside world?  If I lived on an island I could just do anything I wanted and nothing would be a pathology because I am a person unto myself and it doesn't affect anyone else?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  I don't think that's exactly right.  Take an example of a schizophrenic individual, or a self-cutter, who is tormented by voices who are telling him to hurt himself.  If he hurts others we say it's a problem.  If he is just hurting himself, is it a problem?  In our society we would take the position that it is, because we can't understand why someone would—we aren't talking about just sex play, where you might inflict a little pain to enjoy an erotic experience, or things of that sort—but if somebody is actually attempting to take his life or severely injure himself, or multiple self-cutting, we would fall back on a somewhat paternalistic position and say, 'Wait a minute, this is crossing the line, and this is a disorder because we are judging it is hurtful to yourself.'  We would judge that a disorder.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Autoerotic%20asphyxiation">autoerotic asphyxiation</ref> where a person engages in that activity that can be highly dangerous—fatal—yet they don't believe it?  Is it a 'smoker's denial'?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  I think so.  Somebody going into that who doesn't consider it a serious threat to himself is somebody who is not informed.  It could have a very lethal outcome.  It's a pathology, strictly engaging in that, like someone who wants to play <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russian%20Roulette">Russian Roulette</ref> to have the excitement of hearing a click, but the bullet is not coming out.  That's a disorder because it has the potential for lethality or serious injury.</p>
</text>
