<text id="autogum_interview_doc749" title="part1_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Libertarian candidate Larry Stevens, Kitchener-Conestoga" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-04" dateModified="2008-11-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Libertarian_candidate_Larry_Stevens%2C_Kitchener-Conestoga" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why? What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?</hi></p>
<p>Most of the other candidates are promoting more government, more inefficiencies and consequently higher taxes. I consider none of them competitors as their goal is diametrically opposed to my own. Only the candidate for the Freedom Party has similar goals to my own and I consider him a colleague working toward the same end as myself, namely much less government and much lower taxes.</p>
<p>I'm the most desirable candidate in the riding, because of my goals of much less government and much lower taxes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p><list type="ordered"><item>Too Much Government: The main issue in Kitchener-Conestoga is over regulation by government. This is the cause of the problems in education and health care; its even the major cause of poverty and youth crime. All regulations are enforced by coercion and the rich and powerful always arrange to direct the coercion at the poor or the powerless. To solve problems, we need to use cooperation not compulsion. We need to adopt the approaches used by other jurisdictions that have dealt with problems successfully without resorting to government regulations.</item>
<item>Farmers and Manufacturers: Our people are knowledgeable and hard-working. If government gets out of their way, they'll do just fine.</item>
<item>The Environment: In Earth in the Balance, Al Gore admitted: "The most serious examples of environmental degradation in the world today are tragedies that were created or actively encouraged by governments". Asking the government to protect the environment is like putting a fox in charge of the security of a hen house.</item></list></p>
<p>Ontario environmental specialist Elizabeth Brubaker has shown that private property rights protected our environment very effectively before the Ontario government passed laws to allow pollution and promote the unsustainable use of resources. We need to repeal the laws that allow pollution and we need to allow individuals to again protect our environment from businesses and municipalities that would destroy it.</p>
<p>As far as global warming goes, new evidence indicates there is no threat. It's just another ploy by environmentalists and politicians to gain more power.</p>
<p>The bottom line is that politicians continually distort the facts in their efforts to gain support and get elected. Much of what we've been told in the past has been and still is false. Minimum wages do not and never have helped the poor; seat belts do not and never have saved lives. Research going back decades have these fallacies over and over, but our government still tells us they are true.</p>
</text>
