<text id="autogum_interview_doc017" title="part5_Wikinews attends 2018 Bangalore ComicCon" shortTile="partwikinews-attends" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2018-11-21" dateModified="2019-07-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_attends_2018_Bangalore_ComicCon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  So, you are a freelancer, right?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DW</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Do you plan on fixing to one job or do you wish to continue freelancing?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DW</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Yeah, I think, I think most comics creators tend to work freelancing, and it's a really nice was of doing it. It's a really nice to have a balance between making your own stuff from scratch, and working on other things where you don't have to worry about the sort of world-building and creating everything, explaining everything. To sort of jump in to someone else's sandpit is really freeing sometimes as well. So I wanna keep doing both, as much as possible. And I want to work in other mediums: I want to write plays, I want to write novels. I want to write everything.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How does a normal day of work look like?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DW</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  [Chuckles] I kind of try and like trick myself into thinking that there's no such thing as a "normal day", but there really is. Because I am a freelancer, I could just sit home the whole day, but the idea of that is horrific. So I try [to] get up and get out as early as I can in the morning, which doesn't necessarily mean super early. [Laughs] But I get up and go out. I spend way too much money in coffee shops, because I go work in a coffee shop: just sit there for like hours with my laptop, like a proper writer's cliché.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Other than writing what else do you prefer to do?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DW</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I mean, writing is kind of a black hole, in that everything sort of ends up getting pulled into it. So, I mean I love to read, I always have. If I am left alone for an hour, what I want to do is read. The other thing that I've got quite into this year is rock climbing but I'm not very good at it. But it's a really nice thing that turns off, it's the only thing I know that turns off that side of my brain, that turns of the right side, there's so much problem-solving that you can't think of other stuff while you are doing it. So I really enjoy that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How has the significance of comics changed over the years?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DW</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Oh, now, how long have you got? It's a difficult question, because, the industry, I have heard people talking: you get a lot of angry people on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Twitter">Twitter</ref> talking about the dying industry and everything, but it's just, I think, working out, what it needs to be; what the medium needs to be. The superhero films and stuff is all fantastic and it's great, but I don't think it massively impacts the actual comics fan bases in any big way. And I think in the last few years we have seen a real build-up and influx of shorter, create-your-own books, which is something I really like, because it means that's just like ideas after idea after idea after idea sort of getting out there. So I am excited to see where comics goes in the next few years.</p>
</text>
