<text id="autogum_reddit_doc005" title="Daycare workers of reddit! What is the most shocking family secret you have been told by a three-year-old?" shortTile="daycare-workers-reddit" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-05-31" dateModified="2018-05-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8nk12m" speakerList="#SecretGaygent128, #hekkamekka, #nfmadprops04, #rehmanmemezaib" speakerCount="4">
<head>Daycare workers of reddit! What is the most shocking family secret you have been told by a three-year-old?</head>
<sp who="#SecretGaygent128">
<p>When my husband was little and his mom was pregnant with his sister, they told him there was going to be a baby. They then asked him if he wanted a little brother or a little sister. </p>
<p> I want a robot. </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#hekkamekka">
<p>Finally, something I can answer! First off, kids say a LOT more than parents would probably like to know. I had a girl who was going to court against her biodad who had raped her (got the full story from a coworker) , and she would not stop telling people Don't let (biodads first name) come near you because he's mean and bad and will touch your privates! it really shocked me because this girl is the sweetest and funniest little girl ever, shes only 4. </p>
<p>Ive had kids who were playing barbies and one of the mom barbies started yelling at the child barbies shit like I wish you were never born! I hate you! I wish i had never carried you etc. Kids who talk about their parents fights, what they said, where they went and how many doors they slammed. Nothing is off limits at (a good) daycare, because children can't go through these things alone, and often the parents don't want to talk about it or they're the ones causing the problem. It's heartbreaking really. </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#rehmanmemezaib">
<p>Not a daycare worker but mom works for the YMCA and she once had a girl that said to her My daddy hits me sometimes and when the dad showed up, he completely denied it.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#nfmadprops04">
<p>I had a student in my class, age 3, who was constantly dropped off by his barefoot mom without any underwear. Granted, he was completely potty-trained so it wasn't a huge deal and I just figured out they were hippies. So one day, we're coloring and talking about superheroes and punching comes up. My mommy punches me, to which I responded, you mean like this? and I gave him a light friendly nudge like hey you! and he shook his head. No like this. and he SLAMMED his fist down on the table. So I told him that it was a good thing he told me, asked for a subsitute to take a potty time (which was our code for I need help from a senior employee - if you actually needed to pee, you used the term potty break. ) My manager met me in the front office and we filed a complain with the CPS. Unfortunately, I gave birth about a week later and never returned, so I don't know what became of him :(</p>
</sp>
</text>
