<text id="autogum_bio_doc559" title="Hugh Inge" shortTile="hugh-inge" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-05-06" dateModified="2019-04-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hugh_Inge" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Hugh Inge</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">Hugh Inge</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Ynge</hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref>(c. 1460 – 3 August 1528) was an English-born judge and prelate in sixteenth century Ireland who held the offices of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Meath">Bishop of Meath</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishop_of_Dublin_(Roman_Catholic)">Archbishop of Dublin</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Chancellor_of_Ireland">Lord Chancellor of Ireland</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Inge was born at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shepton_Mallet">Shepton Mallet</ref> in Somerset. Not much seems to be known about his parents, except that they  destined him for a career in the Church from an early age.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> He was educated at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Winchester_College">Winchester College</ref> and became a fellow of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_College,_Oxford">New College, Oxford</ref> in 1484 and a Doctor of Divinity in 1511. He held a number of minor benefices in England including the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church_of_St_Mary_the_Virgin,_Westonzoyland">Church of St Mary the Virgin, Westonzoyland</ref> from 1508.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> After travelling for a time around Europe, he became attached to the household of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adriano_Castellesi">Adriano Castellesi</ref>, the Italian-born <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Bath_and_Wells">Bishop of Bath and Wells</ref>, and went with him to Rome in 1504. In about 1511 he came to the notice of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Wolsey">Cardinal Wolsey</ref>, who recognised his gifts and advanced his career: he later admitted that he owed everything he achieved to Wolsey,  and  that "without him I had no comfort in this world".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>Inge in Ireland</head>
<p>In 1512, through Wolsey's influence, he was made Bishop of Meath. There  seems to have been a  later quarrel between the two men,  leading to a brief estrangement, since in 1514 Inge wrote to Wolsey imploring him not to "cast him away".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> The quarrel was short-lived, and Inge followed the same career path as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Rokeby">William Rokeby</ref>, whom he succeeded both as Archbishop of Dublin and Lord Chancellor of Ireland in 1521. He was a popular and respected figure in Ireland, and enjoyed the friendship of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gerald_FitzGerald,_9th_Earl_of_Kildare">Gerald FitzGerald, 9th Earl of Kildare</ref>, the dominant figure in Irish politics for many years.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>Inge carried out extensive repairs to the episcopal palace of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manor_of_St._Sepulchre">St. Sepulchre</ref>; his name is commemorated in <hi rend="bold">Hugh Inge's door</hi>, which was restored in the eighteenth century;<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> a few fragments of the door were discovered during excavations some years ago, at present-day Kevin Street.  The door was described as having an unusual three-centred head.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p>The Archbishop was vigilant in protecting the rights and privileges of the See of Dublin, and in 1524 he complained to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Privy_Council_of_Ireland">Privy Council of Ireland</ref> that the city fathers of Dublin, headed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_Queytrot">Nicholas Queytrot</ref> (or Coitrotte), who had lately held office as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Mayor_of_Dublin">Lord Mayor of Dublin</ref>, had unlawfully occupied the Manor of St. Sepluchre (St. Sepulchre actually consisted of several adjoining manors, which covered most of present day Dublin city south of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/River_Liffey">River Liffey</ref>).  According to Inge, the manor was a "liberty" under the jurisdiction of the Archbishop (Queytrot was a prominent Dublin merchant and builder, who later served as the city <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Auditor">auditor</ref>). The Council referred the matter to the three Chief Justices of the Courts of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Common_Law">Common Law</ref>, who ruled that the disputed lands were indeed within the liberty of the Archbishop,  and that he and his successors were entitled to hold  them in perpetuity  without  let or hindrance by the Mayor of Dublin.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> At the same time he was engaged in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lawsuit">lawsuit</ref> with the Dean and Chapter of the Diocese of Kildare as to his rights of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canonical_visitation">Visitation</ref> in the Diocese if the office of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Kildare">Bishop of Kildare</ref> happened to be vacant: the outcome of this lawsuit is unknown<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref></p>
<head>Death and reputation</head>
<p>In 1528 the fourth and most severe epidemic of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sweating_sickness">sweating sickness</ref> swept through England and Ireland, and then ravaged much of the continent of Europe. Inge was among its victims: he died on 3 August and was buried in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Patrick's_Cathedral,_Dublin">St. Patrick's Cathedral, Dublin</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref></p>
<p>O'Flanagan<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref> praises him as a judge who was noted for his honesty, good sense and desire to do impartial justice; though his recorded judgements are few, they are said to have carried great weight. In his own time <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polydore_Vergil">Polydore Vergil</ref> praised him as an honest man who brought a measure of order and good government to a notoriously troubled kingdom. D'Alton calls him a man noted for "great justice and probity".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref></p>
</text>
