<text id="autogum_voyage_doc244" title="Morgantown" shortTile="morgantown" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=23016" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Morgantown</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.morgantown.com/">Morgantown</ref></hi> is in Monongalia County, <ref target="West%20Virginia">West Virginia</ref> and is the county seat. It is home to the West Virginia University Mountaineers. It has been described as the #1 small city in America. Its main claim to fame is the Morgantown PRT, a "Personal Rapid Transit" system that was supposed to be the future of public transportation in the 1970s but found no takers elsewhere after cost overruns and delays.</p>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Morgantown Municipal Airport</hi> ( MGW ). Has nonstop service from Baltimore, Maryland, and Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. </item>
<item> <ref target="http://www.flypittsburgh.com"><hi rend="bold">Pittsburgh International Airport</hi></ref> ( PIT ) is north of Morgantown, and has scheduled commercial service from many airports in the U.S. and other countries.</item>
</list>


<head>By car</head>
<p>Major routes in and out of Morgantown include:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">I-79</hi>, which runs in a north-south fashion through the eastern side of Morgantown</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">I-68</hi>, which runs in an east-west fashion through the southern side of Morgantown</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">WV 43</hi>, a section of the Mon-Fayette Expressway connecting the Morgantown area to Fayette County, Pennsylvania</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">US 119</hi>, which runs in a north-south fashion through downtown</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">US 19</hi>, which runs through downtown</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">WV 7</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">WV 705</hi></item>
</list>


<p>Morgantown is:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> 77 miles (120 km) south of Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania;</item>
<item> 385 miles (615 km) north of Charlotte, North Carolina;</item>
<item> 528 miles (845 km) east of Chicago, Illinois;</item>
<item> 218 miles (350 km) west of Washington, D.C.</item>
</list>


<head>By bus</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="http://us.megabus.com"><hi rend="bold">Megabus</hi></ref>. Service from Pittsburgh and Washington, D.C. Buses stop at Mountaineer Station, 1112 Van Voorhis Road.</item>
</list>


<head>Get around</head>

<p>The <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://transportation.wvu.edu/prt">PRT</ref></hi> (Personal Rapid Transit) is a unique urban rail system that provides the primary mode of transportation for students, faculty, and staff of the university, and for residents of the Morgantown area. There are five station stops: Walnut, Beechurst, Engineering, Towers, and Medical. The PRTs transport between Downtown Morgantown, the WVU Downtown Campus, the Evansdale Campus and the Medical Center Complex. $0.50/ride; free with WVU ID.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Regular hours (during school year): M-F 6:30AM-10:15PM, Sa 9:30-5PM. No Sunday service, unless the day before classes begin is a Sunday, in which case PRT runs on Saturday hours. No service on days when class is not in session. Extended hours for special events, most notably football and basketball games.</item>
<item> Summer hours: M-F 6:30AM-6:15PM, Sa 9:30AM-5PM.</item>
</list>


<p>The <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.busride.org/">Mountain Line</ref></hi> is a public transit bus system providing service in and around the city of Morgantown. The service is free to students, with nominal fares for the public. The city of Morgantown subsidizes the bus system, making the fares very affordable.</p>

<p>Since a lot of recreational activities are available close to one another they are easily accessible by <hi rend="bold">car</hi> and <hi rend="bold">foot</hi>. There is no need to worry about parking. There are four parking garages with a total of 1,600 parking spots in Morgantown. They are at University Ave and Chestnut Street, Pleasant Street, Spruce Street and Wharf Street.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Core Arboretum</hi>, ☏ +1 304 293-5201 . Monongahela Boulevard. Daily, dawn to dusk. 91 acres of forest with 3.5 miles of trails and 3 acres of lawns planted with specimen trees. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Dorsey's Knob</hi>. An excellent view of the Rolling Hills of West Virginia at no cost. </item>
</list>


<head>Museums</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Royce J. and Caroline B. Watts Museum</hi>, 401 Evansdale Drive, ☏ +1 304-293-4609 , ✉ wattsmuseum@mail.wvu.edu . MWF Sa: 1-4PM. Mineral Resources Building Room 125. Dedicated to preserving the social, cultural, and technological history of the coal, oil and natural gas industries of the state of West Virginia. free. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cook-Hayman Pharmacy Museum</hi>, 1132 Health Sciences North, ☏ +1 304 293-5212 . Tours by appointment booked through website. Built to resemble a 19th-century drugstore, the museum includes texts, medicines, furnishings, apothecary jars, mills, bottles, scales and other devices used by pharmacists over the past 100 years. Free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Morgantown Glass Museum</hi>, 1628 Mileground Road, ☏ +1 304-685-5760 , ✉ mgt_glass@hotmail.com . By appointment only. Please call.. Displays thousands of glass pieces from the late 19th century to around 1980, made in factories of the Morgantown Glass Company, the Seneca Glass company and the Gentile Glass Company in the Morgantown area.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Old Morgantown Glass Collector's Guild Glass Museum</hi>, 709 Beechurst, ✉ oldmorgantown@aol.com . W-Sa 10AM-3PM, Su 1-5PM.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Scott's Run Museum</hi> (exit 155 from I-79, Osage), ☏ +304-599-1931 . Sa 1PM-4PM, or by appointment. Celebrating and preserving the history of coal and the coal boom area in Morgantown. Free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Morgantown History Museum</hi>, 175 Kirk St, ☏ +1 304-319-1800 , ✉ info@morgantownhistorymuseum.org . MWFSa 10AM-4PM. Tu,Th 11AM-4PM. local and regional history</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">West Virginia University's Creative Arts Center</hi>, ☏ +1 304-293-4841 . Gallery hours F noon-9PM; Sa 1PM-9PM.. 4 theatres and 1 performance hall. All exhibitions, lectures, and receptions are free and open to the public.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Monongalia Arts Center</hi>, 107 High Street (between the historic Hotel Morgan and the old Morgantown Post Office on South High Street), ☏ +1 304 292-3325 , ✉ info@monartscenter.com . M-F 11AM - 7PM, Sa 11AM - 4PM. A non-profit arts and culture center serving Monongalia County and surrounding areas. MAC offers classes in the visual and performing arts, and houses the Benedum Gallery, Davis Gallery, Tanner Theatre, and a gift shop featuring artwork by various local artists. </item>
</list>


<head>Spectator sports</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">West Virginia Mountaineers</hi>, WVU Coliseum, 3450 Jerry West Blvd. (between Blue and Gold Gate entrances), toll-free: +1 800 WVU-GAME . M-F 9AM–5PM. WVU sports teams are undoubtedly Morgantown's highest-profile attraction. The Mountaineers field teams in seven men's sports, 10 women's sports, and one coeducational sport (rifle shooting), mostly as members of the Big 12 Conference. As at most other big schools, the football and men's basketball teams are the biggest draws. Notably, when WVU fills Milan Puskar Stadium for football games, the stadium becomes the largest "city" in the state by a healthy margin. While a small number of WVU fans aren't exactly friendly to opposing fans, violence is largely nonexistent, and neutral visitors should have no trouble. Like the WVU campus, the school's main athletic venues are disjointed—the football stadium is at the Health Sciences campus; the WVU Coliseum (several indoor sports, most notably basketball) and some other venues are at the Evansdale campus; and the baseball stadium is at University Town Centre in Granville. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">West Virginia Black Bears</hi>, Monongalia County Ballpark (University Town Centre, Granville), ☏ +1 304 293-7910 , ✉ wvblackbears@gmail.com . The Black Bears, which moved from Jamestown, New York, after the 2014 season, play in the New York–Penn League, a short-season Class A league, and share WVU's ballpark. The season runs from mid-June to early September. </item>
</list>
</text>
