<text id="autogum_academic_doc514" title="The Pivotal Role of TRP Channels in Homeostasis and Diseases throughout the Gastrointestinal Tract" shortTile="pivotal-role-trp" author="Alessandro Alaimo, Josep Rubert" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1422-0067/20/21/5277/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. TRP Channels in Colorectal Cancers</head>
<p>
Colorectal cancer (CRC), the most prevalent cancer of the GI tract, represents the third most commonly diagnosed malignancy worldwide in men and women and the second largest cause of death in Europe related to cancer. Growth factors, oncogenes and receptors play a critical role in the tumorigenesis, and the propagation of CRC. However, other environmental and genetic factors play significant roles in the development of CRC. Over the last two decades, accumulating evidence has demonstrated that several members of the TRP family channels show altered expression and activity in cancer cells. Levels of expression of TRPC, TRPM, and TRPV proteins depend on the cancer stage. Those differences have been recognized mainly in melanoma, glioma and prostate, breast, kidney, and bladder cancers, suggesting an oncogenic role for some TRPs while others may function as tumor suppressors. TRPs activity implicates many aspects of cancer development or “hallmarks of cancer”, such as tumor migration and invasion, exaggerated cell proliferation, cell survival, angiogenesis, and enhanced resistance to cell death. </p>

<p>To date, TRPV1 and TRPV6 have been exclusively recognized as relevant in CRC carcinogenesis. As mentioned above, the TRPV1 channel is also involved in IBD, a chronic disorder strongly correlated with risk of CRC. Animal models have demonstrated a protective role for TRPV1 in the tumorigenesis of colon cancer, indeed TRPV1- Knockout mice exhibited lower expression of anti-inflammatory neuropeptides and greater occurrence and number of CRC compared with controls. In accordance with these data, Sung and colleagues demonstrated that agonist-mediated activation of TRPV1 induced apoptosis of CRC cells. On the other hand, an overexpression of TRPV6 in SW480 colorectal cancer cell lines and colon carcinomas have been associated with an enhanced proliferation of malignant cells. In a recent report, Pérez-Riesgo et al. have assessed differential gene expression of all human TRP channels by Next Generation Sequencing (NGS) to investigate differences in expression of several genes involved in intracellular Ca2+ transport in CRC. The results obtained, comparing human normal colonic cells versus human colon cancer lines, revealed that only a dozen of the TRPs are expressed in colonic cells, either normal or tumor. The data also indicated that TRPV6 was the unique TRP gene significantly overexpressed in CRC cells, resembling the previously reported enhanced levels of TRPV6 in prostate cancer. Notwithstanding, the functional consequences of changes in expression of TRPV1 and TRPV6 channels in CRC remain to be established. </p>
</text>
