<text id="autogum_whow_doc348" title="Prepare for Top Surgery" shortTile="prepare-top-surgery" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2012-05-14" dateModified="2019-06-09" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Prepare-for-Top-Surgery" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Prepare for Top Surgery</head><p>Top surgery is a major step of physical transitioning for some transgender men, and as such it is important to prepare. Here are some suggestions for how to prepare for top surgery, both physically and emotionally.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Know if this is right for you. If you feel unsure of having top surgery, try to understand why you feel unsure of this. It's a good idea to talk to a gender therapist or a trusted friend to discuss about this issue. You <hi rend="italic">must</hi> listen to yourself. You have to listen what your gut instinct is telling you about getting the top surgery. There are plenty of trans men who are comfortable with having breasts. Do not let people tell you what's best for you. Only you can tell yourself what's right for you.  <figure rend="Prepare for the Top Surgery Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Look into the two different types of top surgery, double incision vs. keyhole. Keyhole is generally only an option for people with smaller breasts.</item></list></item>
<item>Understand. Be cautious when considering surgery. It can take several months for your scars to heal, although they will be considerably less noticeable with the keyhole procedure. Your chest may not end up looking exactly the way you were expecting. Some trans/gender non-conforming people feel unhappy with their chests even after this surgery. You must let go of higher expectations you have about your chest. Getting top surgery will not always end all the intense dysphoria you have, though it does for some people. Everyone feels differently about their own body. Decide what is right for you and look at pictures of other people who have had top surgery. Consider examples you consider "good" and "bad"  and decide how you would deal with it if your result was not what you had hoped for.  <figure rend="Prepare for the Top Surgery Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Bring things you may need when your recovering from surgery. After the procedure, you will have to limit your arm movements to reduce the risk of pulling a stitch out or injuring yourself. Rearrange furniture and other items in your house beforehand to make it easier for you to reach things in case you don't have somebody to assist you while you recover. Clothes that are easy to put on and remove can be especially helpful for you. Sweatpants and button-up/zip-up shirts and hoodies are good choices. <figure rend="Prepare for the Top Surgery Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure you are healthy. This is an important part of any pre-op care for any surgery. For one thing, it is important to make sure you are as physically fit as possible. If you do not exercise regularly, try starting an exercise routine. Nutrition is also very important - try to ensure that you're eating a healthy, balanced diet with lots of whole grains, fresh fruit and vegetables. If you smoke, it is a good idea for you to try to quit. Try your best not to put yourself under a lot of stress before <hi rend="italic">and</hi> after you have the top surgery. Being stressed can make it harder for you to heal after you have the surgery. <figure rend="Prepare for the Top Surgery Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Contact a surgeon and discuss the operation. Try to select a reputable surgeon. If you are not sure which surgeon to pick, you can ask men who have already had top surgery who they would recommend, or go online and research. Transbucket is a very helpful guide. It's important to ask questions to your surgeon about getting surgery. You might be given suggestions about what kind of top surgery you should have; depending on your size, you may be eligible for certain types.  <figure rend="Prepare for the Top Surgery Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be wary of any surgeon that doesn't require a letter from a therapist, as the WPATH standards of care call for a letter. Surgery may cost about $USD 6,000 to 10,000 and isn't typically covered by insurance.</item></list></item>
<item>Prepare for the big day. If you're anxious, talking to a therapist can help. This is a big change in your life and it's important to be prepared. It's important to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Relax">relax</ref> on the day you're having the operation. Try to think positive. The risks are very low, particularly for young, healthy people.  <figure rend="Prepare for the Top Surgery Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Follow all post-operation instructions from your healthcare providers to make sure you heal properly. <figure rend="Prepare for the Top Surgery Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
</text>
