<text id="autogum_academic_doc618" title="Development of a Minimum Data Set Registry for Chronic Venous Insufficiency of the Lower Limbs" shortTile="development-minimum" author="Erica Homs-Romero, Angel Romero-Collado" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2077-0383/8/11/1779/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
The MDS-CVI is primarily a data-collection tool. However, when completing the registry, healthcare professionals are reminded of important actions that can be carried out in people with risk factors such as older age, female sex, and obesity, which increase their likelihood of having CVD. Activities to promote health, prevent CVD, and diagnose it at earlier stages will help halt or delay disease progress. Healthcare professionals, and those working in primary health in particular, should aim to educate at-risk patients to lead a healthy lifestyle and use compression stockings. </p>

<p>Due to increased awareness of CVD, the tendency is generally for earlier diagnosis and treatment. However, in some countries, the disease is not detected until more advanced stages. There are gaps in healthcare professionals’ knowledge of venous leg ulcer physiology and its healing process, partly due to a lack of training at a degree level. By applying and incorporating this MDS-CVI in patients’ health records, healthcare professionals will find it easier to monitor the disease course at every stage. Above all, they should follow the recommendations to ensure correct diagnosis and treatment. </p>

<p>The CEAP classification system is a very easy method to classify venous disease and reach a reliable diagnosis of CVD/CVI in the population. The clinical part of the system can be obtained simply by observing a patient’s legs in the primary care setting. It is estimated that 80% of the population have the mildest level of symptoms (C1–C2, spider and varicose veins), while 5% have the most advanced stages (C3–C6). Implementation of this evidence-based MDS-CVI would result in more reliable data collection and facilitate monitoring of a specific population to observe disease progression, the treatments used, and their effectiveness. With the existing level of evidence of the importance of therapeutic compression of the lower limbs, it is unacceptable that 90% of patients with CVI in Turkey and 54% of patients with venous ulcers in Spain are not given compression stockings. The MDS-CVI will also permit health managers to plan interventions according to the venous state of the population and identify which quality indicators should be applied. </p>

<p>People with CVI have a poor quality of life. It is therefore important to determine how the venous disease affects each individual. Specific instruments are available to measure quality of life in these patients, such as the Aberdeen Varicose Vein Questionnaire (AVVQ) or the Chronic Venous Insufficiency Quality of Life Questionnaire (CIVIC) for patients with CVI, and the Charing Cross Venous Ulcer Questionnaire for patients with venous ulcers. The instruments are valid for only certain languages and cultures and they therefore need to be adapted to be effective. </p>

<p>Non-pharmacological measures are essential in the prevention and adjuvant therapy of CVD and healthcare professionals should therefore be aware of their existence and use them in their clinical practice. Recommendations such as weight loss or taking regular exercise will help venous return and delay symptom progression. </p>

<p>The MDS for CVI establishes minimum quality care criteria and can help to guide in the purchase of necessary services. </p>
</text>
