<text id="autogum_bio_doc152" title="Katy Carr" shortTile="katy-carr" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-16" dateModified="2019-09-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Katy_Carr" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Katy Carr</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Katy Carr</hi> is a British singer-songwriter and musician known for her songs about Polish history. A fan of the 1930s and 1940s, she plays vintage instruments and wears clothing and hairstyles from the period. Although she was born in England, she lived in Poland for the first five years of her life. Her album <hi rend="italic">Paszport</hi>, a tribute to those who fought in World War II, won Best <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Concept_album">Concept Album</ref> from the <hi rend="italic">Independent Music Awards</hi> in 2014. In 2016 she was given Poland's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pro_Patria_Medal_(Poland)">Pro Patria Medal</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-About_Katy-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Aitken-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Carr was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nottingham">Nottingham</ref>, England to a Polish mother and a Scottish-English father, but until she was five lived in Poland where her parents met and her father worked. Her English grandmother's stories about the 1930s and 40s stirred an interest in the era, as did photographs of the clothing and hairstyles.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Chatting-3">[3]</ref> She admired <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Édith_Piaf">Édith Piaf</ref> and female pilots <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amy_Johnson">Amy Johnson</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amelia_Earhart">Amelia Earhart</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Spencer-4">[4]</ref> An undisciplined girl, she joined the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Air_Training_Corps">Air Cadets</ref>, a youth group affiliated with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_Air_Force">Royal Air Force</ref>, and learned to fly.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Chatting-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Career</head>
<head>2009: <hi rend="italic">Kommander's Car</hi></head>
<p>The single "Kommander's Car" was inspired by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kazimierz_Piechowski">Kazimierz Piechowski</ref>'s escape from an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Auschwitz_concentration_camp">Auschwitz concentration camp</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> Piechowski was sent to Auschwitz in 1940. Two years later a fellow prisoner who repaired the cars of SS officers suggested they steal a car. Carr's song is about their escape.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Silverman-6">[6]</ref></p>
<head><hi rend="italic">Kazik and the Kommander's Car</hi> documentary</head>
<p><hi rend="italic">Kazik and the Kommander's Car</hi> is a documentary produced by Carr and directed by British film maker Hannah Lovell.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> It documents Carr's first visit to meet and present her tribute song, "Kommander's Car", to Polish World War II veteran Kazimierz Piechowski. Piechowski was present for the debut of the documentary, which included a concert on 27 January 2010 in Warsaw, Poland to mark the 65th anniversary of liberation of Auschwitz. Two years later a DVD of the film was released.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> The film was shown in museums and festivals in England and Poland.</p>
<head>Touring and humanitarian work</head>
<p>In March 2011, Katy Carr and the Aviators embarked on The Escapologist Tour. Kazimierz Piechowski was present for the first two London performances.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> The aim of the Escapologist Tour was, in Carr's words, "to help unite both British and Polish communities throughout the UK through film, music and the sharing of stories." Events included concerts and screenings of <hi rend="italic">Kazik and the Kommander's Car</hi>, as well as outreach with Polish retirement and care homes. Carr sang Polish folk songs to World War II veterans. In 2012, the tour was nominated for the National Lottery Good Causes Awards.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-lotterygoodcauses1-10">[10]</ref> She embarked on a US Polish diaspora tour and performed in Chicago, and New York City. Short films about Polish history from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polish_Institute_and_Sikorski_Museum">Polish Institute and Sikorski Museum</ref> archives were shown by Hannah Lovell, director of <hi rend="italic">Kazik and the Kommander's Car</hi>. Carr studied Polish at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jagiellonian_University">Jagiellonian University</ref> so she could communicate better with the Polish media during her tour and also to "help to share the joys of learning the Polish language".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref></p>
<head>2012: <hi rend="italic">Paszport</hi></head>
<p>Carr's fourth album, <hi rend="italic">Paszport</hi>, contains lyrics in English and Polish. She worked with British producer Nigel of Bermondsey and with musicians from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Klezmer">Klezmer</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gypsy_jazz">Gypsy jazz</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Folk_music">Folk music</ref> to create a sound that would be both traditional and contemporary.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Spencer_Review-12">[12]</ref> The album was released in Poland on 17 September 2012 to mark the anniversary of the Soviet invasion, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Independence_Day">National Independence Day</ref> in Poland and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Remembrance_Day">Remembrance Day</ref> (also known as <hi rend="italic">Poppy Day</hi> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Armistice_Day">Armistice Day</ref>). <hi rend="italic">Paszport</hi> was released in the UK on 11 November 2012 to positive reviews, some considering it one of the best albums of the year.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Spencer_Review-12">[12]</ref></p>
<p>Aside from the single about Piechowski, the album's subjects include the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soviet_invasion_of_Poland">Soviet invasion of Poland</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polish_resistance_movement_in_World_War_II">Polish resistance</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soviet_repressions_of_Polish_citizens_(1939–46)">the repression of Polish people by the Soviets</ref>. Regarding the title of the album, Carr cited a poem by Jerzy Harasymowicz: "it's not a very well known poem, but I think it says everything about my album, 'Masz paszport, więc jesteś' – "You have a passport, therefore you exist".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Chatting-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>In 2013, Carr was given the Polish Daily Award for Culture.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Kendall-14">[14]</ref></p>
<head>Discography</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>2001: <hi rend="italic">Screwing Lies</hi></item>
<item>2003: <hi rend="italic">Passion Play</hi></item>
<item>2008: <hi rend="italic">The Crow Club</hi> (compilation album)</item>
<item>2009: "Kommander's Car" (single)</item>
<item>2009: <hi rend="italic">Coquette</hi></item>
<item>2012: "Kommander's Car" (remastered single)</item>
<item>2012: <hi rend="italic">Kazik and the Kommander's Car</hi> (DVD)</item>
<item>2012: <hi rend="italic">Paszport</hi></item>
<item>2015: <hi rend="italic">Polonia</hi></item></list>
<head>Awards</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>2011: Nominated for London Music Award</item>
<item>2012: Nominated for National Lottery Good Causes Award<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-lotterygoodcauses1-10">[10]</ref></item>
<item>2013: Polish Daily Award for Culture</item>
<item>2013: Nominated for Best Artist, Songlines Music Awards</item>
<item>2014: Best Concept Album, <hi rend="italic">Paszport</hi>, Independent Music Awards<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref></item>
<item>2014: Honorary membership, Polish 1st Armoured Division</item>
<item>2016: Pro Patria Medal (Poland)</item>
<item>2016: Nominated Best Concept Album, <hi rend="italic">Polonia</hi>, Independent Music Awards<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[16]</ref></item></list>
</text>
