<text id="autogum_academic_doc419" title="Pre-Service Teachers’ Reflections on Cooperative Learning: Instructional Approaches and Identity Construction" shortTile="preservice-teachers" author="Dolors Cañabate, Teresa Serra, Remigijus Bubnys, Jordi Colomer" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5970/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head><head> 1.1. Students’ Cooperative Learning and Sustainable Development</head>
<p>
Providing future generations of professionals with the skills for sustainable development relies mainly on integrating approaches and strategies into Higher Education Institutions and their systems. Education for sustainable development, when developed in Higher Education, should enhance students to understand how their professional activity interacts with society and the environment in order to identify possible challenges, risks, and impacts. Therefore, Higher Education Institutions should transfer sustainability competences to the teaching profession by developing curricula competences in education for sustainability, linking sustainability to both student learning and in-practice teaching. It entails promoting student interaction and fostering relationships in socialization and learning. Education for Sustainable Development is directed towards promoting the development of critical thinking, strategic action, and interpersonal relationships as well as collaboration, personal involvement, and tolerance for ambiguity, in which students accept uncertainty and acknowledge dilemmas. It empowers students to change their way of thinking and to work towards a sustainable future. How students understand what they know and how they are progressing as they develop their knowledge through reconsidering what they learn in practice is a fundamental element of sustainable education. </p>

<p>Education for Sustainable Development concerns sustainable actions at all educational levels, favoring the development of competences that allow people to think about their actions. Competences integrate knowledge, skills, values, and attitudes, and a competence-based education is a type of education that focuses on the implementation, development, and assessment of competences. Both cooperative and reflective learning are instructional practices that can activate and promote sustainable-oriented competences. For example, reflecting on beliefs, actions, and goals are the foundations of critical thinking and analysis. Sustainable-oriented competences also promote developing ideas and applying strategies, planning and executing projects, reflecting on risks, taking responsibility for motivating others; all of which form the basic principles of strategic action. </p>

<p>Cooperative learning is an educational methodology based on small (usually heterogeneous) groups of students working together. In cooperative learning, students join forces and share ideas and resources to learn something themselves and encourage other team members to learn as well. Cooperative learning activates peer-to-peer learning, which is defined as building both sustainable knowledge and skills through interaction. The five variables that mediate the effectiveness of cooperative learning are positive interdependence, individual accountability, promotive interaction, the appropriate use of social skills, and group processing. Cooperative learning relies mainly on the interdependence of the students among each other, with the roles of the team members being clearly mapped out, although they can be negotiated. The students submit the complete group task at the end of the lesson and during the final group processing. In contrast, in collaborative learning, if this method is properly directed by the teacher, the students themselves can learn to manage the task with no further instruction. Most important, in collaborative learning, each student is responsible for their own individual work, separately. In general, authors see collaborative learning as a broader, more general concept covering multiple approaches on peer collaboration, among which, for example, is cooperative learning. </p>

<p>Cooperative physical challenges are cooperative learning activities that have a clearly defined objective and are posed as a collective (team) challenge in which the group, in the first stage, must resolve a specific problem by using multiple solutions and, in the second stage, reflect on the whole process. To do so, each team needs not only to agree on their actions as a group but, more importantly, to consider and value the individual characteristics of each and every one of its members to resolve the problem posed. While a specific response to completing the challenge may be valid for one team, it may not be for another. Cooperative physical challenges maximize the acquisition of competences through individual cooperation in teamwork, the intrapersonal construction of professional identity, and the definition of strategic decision actions. </p>

<p>Cooperation is the reciprocal relationship between people or groups, which are characterized by being heterogeneous, aimed at achieving a goal through a common effort. Cooperation is also a principle that can guarantee a more creative and sound teaching process, provided the teacher and the student are involved in the construction of knowledge. Cooperative learning is an educational strategy in which students work together in groups to achieve a common goal that is characterized by a structure that promotes positive interdependence between the group members. Students gain both academically and socially when they have opportunities to interact with others to accomplish shared goals. In the process, students learn to communicate effectively by explaining the experiences in which they have been involved, and the language they learn to use to explain the experiences, in turn, helps them to construct new ways of thinking. In addition, if students are encouraged to participate in group discussions, they demonstrate a more sophisticated level of discourse and intellectually valuable contributions. </p>
</text>
