<text id="autogum_academic_doc311" title="An Empirical Assessment of Angular Dependency for RedEdge-M in Sloped Terrain Viticulture" shortTile="empirical-assessment" author="Chizhang Gong, Henning Buddenbaum, Rebecca Retzlaff, Thomas Udelhoven" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-4292/11/21/2561/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The concept of precision viticulture has rapidly developed and extended to a variety of unmanned aerial vehicle (UAV) applications in recent years. These include digital 3D vineyard structure reconstruction from UAV imagery for precise row monitoring and crop status quantification, such as evaluating growth conditions with hyperspectral sensors, RGB, multispectral, thermal sensors combined together, and utilizing machine-learning techniques for multispectral sensors to schedule the irrigation. All of the mentioned quantification works have used optical sensors, which heavily rely upon the accurate derivation of canopy reflectance. </p>

<p>In viticulture, this demand faces two unique geometric problems. First, the canopy converges to a narrower shape after pruning, limiting the retrievable information from nadir orthophotos. Second, although the former problem can be improved by tilting the camera’s view angle to observe the side of the canopies, the enlarged sun-target-sensor angle in the sloped areas will further interfere with the target reflectance anisotropy. The resulting consequences have been demonstrated in other scenarios. One study on wheat showed that SCOPE-modeled directional reflectance was largely different from the UAV hyperspectral spectrometer measurement in low-tilt angles. Another hyperspectral study highlighted the influence of viewing geometry on the Normalized Differential Vegetation Index (NDVI) values, demanding the necessary compensation.  </p>

<p>The angular reflectance dependency has been intensively studied within the framework of the bidirectional reflectance distribution function (BRDF). For vegetation canopies, the anisotropic reflectance can be dependent on the canopy structure (surface curvature, leaf layers, shadow proportion, leaf orientations, etc.) and visible background at different view geometries. This has resulted in a series of modeling tools. One of the commonly used models was described by Walthall et al.. It was then improved in a detailed layout in Nilson and Kuusk’s work, which was illustrated by Beisl et al.. Another commonly used model was proposed by Rahman et al.. These models have been used to semi-empirically establish the relation between canopy directional reflectance and geometry. Further modeling with BRDF simulation tools, such as PROSAIL, can also be found in application reviews.  </p>

<p>Early works have used ground goniometers to study the angular reflectance dependency. But by paralleling the goniometer measured ground truth and UAV measurements, studies have already shown that the UAV-mounted cameras can obtain bidirectional reflectance factors without ground measurements. For example, a correspondence was found between goniometer and UAV commercial camera on a smooth snow surface. A low standard deviation between goniometer and UAV directional reflectance on reference panels was found in another study. By involving a sun sensor, UAV directional reflectance can also be derived without a reference panel. Such a method was tested and evaluated in a very recent work, where high correlation coefficients were found between UAV measurement and literature goniometer values on a spectralon white reference panel.  </p>

<p>A range of dedicated UAV reflectance anisotropy studies have been conducted on different types of vegetation. Aside from the wheat study mentioned before, another hyperspectral study on wheat and barley found that the scattering parameter in the Rahman–Pinty–Verstraete model differed by the crop heading stage. It also found a strong backscattering reduction in potato after the full coverage of canopies, indicating the potential of crop-growth stage monitoring by angular observation. Taking the bidirectional effect into consideration, the radiometric correction via geometric block adjustment method was developed to significantly improve the uniformity of spectral mosaics. Another assessment study of BRDF in UAV near-infrared (NIR) imagery has illustrated the compensation method for angular radiometric disturbances.  </p>

<p>As part of a UAV-monitoring project on a sloped vineyard, this paper focuses on delivering a feasible approach to sample, model, and correct the angular dependency for the vine canopy reflectance from UAV imagery without field measurements. In the study, the UAV carried a tilted RedEdge-M sensor to take the images from a sloped vineyard. The reflectance anisotropy was studied on these images by combining the RedEdge Python package and the 3D-reconstruction software Agisoft© Metashape applications. Then, both the corrected and uncorrected reflectance images of the red and NIR bands were used to compute their side-view orthomosaics and corresponding NDVI maps from different directions.  </p>

<p>The goal of this study is to deliver a 3D NDVI surface that is independent of the angular effects. The hypothesis is that the corrected NDVI values from different views should be significantly lower than the uncorrected ones.  </p>
</text>
