<text id="autogum_interview_doc548" title="part0_Ingrid Newkirk, co-founder of PETA, on animal rights and the film about her life" shortTile="partingrid-newkirk" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-20" dateModified="2018-02-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ingrid_Newkirk%2C_co-founder_of_PETA%2C_on_animal_rights_and_the_film_about_her_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ingrid Newkirk, co-founder of PETA, on animal rights and the film about her life</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 20, 2007</hi></p>
<figure rend="Ingrid Newkirk by David Shankbone.jpg"></figure>Last night <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Home%20Box%20Office">HBO</ref> premiered <hi rend="italic">I Am An Animal: The Story of Ingrid Newkirk and PETA</hi>.  Since its inception, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/People%20for%20the%20Ethical%20Treatment%20of%20Animals">People for the Ethical Treatment of Animals</ref> (PETA) has made headlines and raised eyebrows.  They are almost single-handedly responsible for the movement against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Animal%20testing">animal testing</ref> and their efforts have raised the suffering animals experience in a broad spectrum of consumer goods production and food processing into a <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cause%20célèbre">cause célèbre</ref></hi>.  
<p>PETA first made headlines in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Silver%20Spring%20monkeys">Silver Spring monkeys case</ref>, when <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alex%20Pacheco">Alex Pacheco</ref>, then a student at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George%20Washington%20University">George Washington University</ref>, volunteered at a lab run by Edward Taub, who was testing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neuroplasticity">neuroplasticity</ref> on live monkeys.  Taub had cut sensory <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ganglia">ganglia</ref> that supplied nerves to the monkeys' fingers, hands, arms, legs; with some of the monkeys, he had severed the entire spinal column.  He then tried to force the monkeys to use their limbs by exposing them to persistent electric shock, prolonged physical restraint of an intact arm or leg, and by withholding food.  With footage obtained by Pacheco, Taub was convicted of six counts of animal cruelty—largely as a result of the monkeys' reported living conditions—making them "the most famous lab animals in history," according to psychiatrist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Brain%20That%20Changes%20Itself">Norman Doidge</ref>.  Taub's conviction was later overturned on appeal and the monkeys were eventually <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euthanasia">euthanized</ref>.</p>
<p>PETA was born.</p>
<p>In the subsequent decades they ran the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stop%20Huntingdon%20Animal%20Cruelty">Stop Huntingdon Animal Cruelty</ref> against Europe's largest animal-testing facility (footage showed staff punching <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beagle">beagle</ref> puppies in the face, shouting at them, and simulating sex 
acts while taking blood samples); against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Covance">Covance</ref>, the United State's largest importer of primates for laboratory research (evidence was found that they were dissecting monkeys at its <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vienna,%20Virginia">Vienna, Virginia</ref> laboratory while the animals were still alive); against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/General%20Motors">General Motors</ref> for using live animals in crash tests; against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/L'Oreal">L'Oreal</ref> for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Testing%20cosmetics%20on%20animals">testing cosmetics on animals</ref>; against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fur_clothing#Anti-fur_campaigns">the use of fur for fashion</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fur%20farming">fur farms</ref>; against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smithfield%20Foods">Smithfield Foods</ref> for torturing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Butterball">Butterball turkeys</ref>; and against fast food chains, most recently against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/KFC">KFC</ref> through the launch of their website <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/KentuckyFriedCruelty.com">kentuckyfriedcruelty.com</ref>.</p>
<p>They have launched campaigns and engaged in stunts that are designed for media attention.  In 1996, PETA activists famously threw a dead raccoon onto the table of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anna%20Wintour">Anna Wintour</ref>, the fur supporting editor-in-chief of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vogue%20(magazine)">Vogue</ref></hi>, while she was dining at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Four%20Seasons">Four Seasons</ref> in New York, and left bloody paw prints and the words "Fur Hag" on the steps of her home.  They ran a campaign entitled <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Animal%20rights%20and%20the%20Holocaust">Holocaust on your Plate</ref> that consisted of eight 60-square-foot panels, each juxtaposing images of the Holocaust with images of factory farming. Photographs of concentration camp inmates in wooden bunks were shown next to photographs of caged chickens, and piled bodies of Holocaust victims next to a pile of pig carcasses.  In 2003 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jerusalem">Jerusalem</ref>, after <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exploding%20donkey">a donkey was loaded with explosives and blown up</ref> in a terrorist attack, Newkirk sent a letter to then-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palestine%20Liberation%20Organization">PLO</ref> leader <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yasser%20Arafat">Yasser Arafat</ref> to keep animals out of the conflict.  As the film shows, they also took over <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean-Paul%20Gaultier">Jean-Paul Gaultier</ref>'s Paris boutique and smeared blood on the windows to protest his use of fur in his clothing.</p>
</text>
