<text id="autogum_interview_doc223" title="part4_Wikinews interviews former New Mexico governor Gary Johnson, presidential nominee of the Libertarian Party" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-11-05" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_former_New_Mexico_governor_Gary_Johnson%2C_presidential_nominee_of_the_Libertarian_Party" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Johnson</hi>: Well, I think libertarians are libertarians. I mean, the largest political affiliation in the country right now is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Independent%20(politics)">Independent</ref> and I think if you took the pulse of Independents, I think you'd find that majority of Independents are libertarians. I think libertarian-leaning, if you go to that category, if you include Democrats, Independents, and Republicans, I think the majority of Americans in some way, shape, or form describe themselves as libertarian-leaning.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Well let's say someone is a libertarian-leaning Republican like Rand Paul in the Senate. Should such libertarian Republicans support you and guaranteeing their vote will go to you rather than voting Republican...Let me rephrase this question... Let's say that a Rand Paul Republican was considering who to vote for and they could choose between guaranteeing their vote would not go to the Republican, which they see as the small-government alternative in the duopoly, rather than voting Republican and ensuring their vote will go to someone who they believe is the small government alternative, should they still support you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Johnson</hi>: Well yeah, because really Republicans aren't small government. I mean, if you go back to the [Vice presidential] debate the other night between [Republican vice presidential nominee <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Paul_Ryan">Paul] Ryan</ref> and [Vice president <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Joe_Biden">Joe] Biden</ref>, Ryan says toward the end of the debate, he goes, hey, look we're going to increase spending by three percent, they're going to increase spending by four and a half percent, what's the big deal? I would echo that. What's the big deal? There's not a big deal between either one of them and if libertarian-leaning Republicans want to send a message to elected Republican leaders then vote for me that's how you're going to send a message. You're not going to send a message by voting in the status quo. The status quo being much to do about nothing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">This is my final question here. The <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OC%20Weekly">OC Weekly</ref></hi> website reported last week that your running mate, Judge Jim Gray remarked during an appearance at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tulane%20University">Tulane University</ref> that you two plan to run again in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_presidential_election,_2016">2016</ref>. Can you confirm whether that is correct?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Johnson</hi>: Well, we've created statewide organizations. There's a tremendous amount of interest. What is that going equates when it comes to votes? You know what, I don't know what that's going to equate to votes on Election Day, but I'll just say from my standpoint, William, there's just a whole lot of enthusiasm and I do think that this is the future of politics so I'm staying around here, I think the last thing anyone wants to hear is that I'm going to run again when, you know, this is an election that hasn't even taken place, and I mean the one on Tuesday. [There's] lots of time to be looking at those kind of options.</p>
</text>
