<text id="autogum_bio_doc192" title="Tahir Pasha (governor)" shortTile="tahir-pasha-governor" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-05-30" dateModified="2019-07-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tahir_Pasha_%28governor%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Tahir Pasha (governor)</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tahir Pasha</hi>, (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albanian_language">Albanian</ref>: <hi lang="sq" rend="italic">Tahir Pashë Krajani</hi>, died 1913<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Vahide-1">[1]</ref>) was an Ottoman Brigadier General (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mirliva">mirliva</ref>) who originated from the region of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Krajë">Krajë</ref>, now in modern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Montenegro">Montenegro</ref> and he was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albanians">Albanian</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Gawrych83-2">[2]</ref> He served as governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mosul">Mosul</ref> and Bitlis toward the latter years of his life.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Warfield-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Vahide-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Background</head>
<p>Tahir Pasha entered the service of the Ottoman crown prince prior to 1876 and became his confidant.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Gawrych83-2">[2]</ref> After the prince became sultan <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abdul_Hamid_II">Abdul Hamid II</ref> he remained with him until the end of his reign.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Gawrych83-2">[2]</ref> While Abdul Hamid II was in power, Tahir Pasha headed the palace guard and attained the rank of marshall, due to the growth of his protection force and responsibilities.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Gawrych83-2">[2]</ref> Tahir Pasha served as a <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vali_(governor)">vali</ref></hi> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_rulers_of_Mosul">governor of Mosul</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman Empire</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Warfield-3">[3]</ref> from 1910 to 1912. Prior to that he was the <hi rend="italic">vali</hi> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Van,_Turkey">Van</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bitlis">Bitlis</ref>, Turkey.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Vahide-1">[1]</ref>:27, 37</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Djevdet_Bey">Cevdet Bey</ref>, his first son, was a leader of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Committee_of_Union_and_Progress">Committee of Union and Progress</ref> (CUP) and was also <hi rend="italic">vali</hi> of Van.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Vahide-1">[1]</ref>:30, 112 Cevdet's brother-in-law was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enver_Pasha">Enver Pasha</ref>, who established a department whose mission was to "free all the Islamic lands from foreign influence". Governors of "frontier provinces", like Van and Mosul, were specially picked for their positions and worked in conjunction with this department established as part of the Ministry of War. The goals was to create "free and independent Muslim states".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Vahide-1">[1]</ref>:112</p>
<p>Prior to 1918, Enver Pasha was the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Young_Turks">Young Turks</ref> political movement leader.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Becker-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Pasha kept a library of journals, newspapers and books about Islam, Ottoman culture, current affairs, astronomy, mathematics, geology, geography, history, chemistry, physics, and philosophy. He was a mentor or teacher, organizing contests on subjects like mathematics.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Vahide-1">[1]</ref>:28 One of his students, Molla Said, dressed haphazardly and refused Pasha's offer that, if Said would dress as a religious scholar, Pasha would allow him to wed his daughter and give him a house and 1000 gold liras.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Vahide-1">[1]</ref>:30</p>
<p>Pasha was quite upset by a newspaper article that mentioned his concern about Europe's intentions towards Muslims and a quote that in order to dominate people of the Muslim faith, they must either change their religion convictions or take them away from them.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Vahide-1">[1]</ref>:30,1</p>
<head>Career</head>
<p>Tahir Pasha transferred from Van to Bitlis about the time of the Turkish Tax Revolts of 1906–1907.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Kansu-5">[5]</ref> The previous <hi rend="italic">vali</hi>, Salim Pasha, was considered "able and energetic" and Tahir had made financial decisions that were not previously under the governor's domain. For instance, he was ignoring "depredations" against the Kurdish people.  His time was sent on diverting funding from Armenian schools elsewhere. There was also an increase in murders during his rule. Repeated calls to fire Tahir were made to the Committee of Union and Progress (CUP) by the Kurdish and Armenian communities, particularly the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Armenian_Revolutionary_Federation">Armenian Revolutionary Federation</ref> (ARF), and governmental personnel. Having originally believed that Pasha was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second_Constitutional_Era">constitutionalist</ref> (wanting restoration of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_constitution_of_1876">Ottoman constitution of 1876</ref>), by March 1910 CUP was in agreement that a change in leadership was necessary.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Kaligian-6">[6]</ref>:66 In July it was announced that Tahir's replacement would be Ismael Hakki, who was <hi rend="italic">vali</hi> of Isgeti.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Kaligian-6">[6]</ref>:67</p>
</text>
