<text id="autogum_interview_doc109" title="part0_Wikinews interviews specialists on South Korea military parade" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-10-02" dateModified="2015-01-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_specialists_on_South_Korea_military_parade" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews specialists on South Korea military parade</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, October 6, 2013</hi></p>
<figure><caption>File photo of South Korean military troops. Image: US Military.</caption></figure>
<p>On Tuesday, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/South_Korea">South Korea</ref> staged a huge military parade to mark its armed forces' 65th anniversary in a display of long-range missiles considered a direct threat to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/North_Korea">North Korea</ref>. 11,000 troops and 190 different weapons systems were on display in the parade.  <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> interviewed several specialists about the parade's possible significance.</p>
<head id="Interviewees">Interviewees</head>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> interviewed:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Robert Kelly</hi></hi>, Associate Professor of International Relations <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pusan%20National%20University">Pusan National University</ref> (PNU) in South Korea</item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Margaret Kosal</hi></hi>, Assistant Professor at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sam%20Nunn%20School%20of%20International%20Affairs">Sam Nunn School of International Affairs</ref> at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Georgia%20Institute%20of%20Technology">Georgia Institute of Technology</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atlanta">Atlanta</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Georgia_(US_state)">Georgia</ref></item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gari%20Ledyard">Gari Ledyard</ref></hi></hi>, Professor Emeritus of Korean Studies at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Columbia%20University">Columbia University</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York">New York</ref></item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Sue Mi Terry</hi></hi>, Senior Research Scholar at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Weatherhead%20East%20Asian%20Institute">Weatherhead East Asian Institute</ref>, Columbia University in New York</item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Young-hae Chi</hi></hi>, Instructor in Korean at the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/University_of_Oxford">University of Oxford</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/England">England</ref></item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Seungkwon You</hi></hi>, Associate Teaching Professor of Korean Studies at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University%20of%20Missouri">University of Missouri</ref></item></list>
<head id="Wikinews_Q&amp;A"><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> Q&amp;A</head>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Special:FilePath/Robert_Kelly_File_Photo.JPG">File:Robert Kelly File Photo.JPG</ref></p><figure><caption>File photo of interviewee Robert Kelly. Image: Robert Kelly.<hi rend="italic">(Image <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Template:Missing_image/message">missing</ref> from commons: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/File:Robert_Kelly_File_Photo.JPG">image</ref>; <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Special:Log?page=File%3ARobert+Kelly+File+Photo.JPG">log</ref>)</hi></caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What is your job role?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Kelly</hi>: I am a Professor of International Relations at PNU.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Kosal</hi>: I am an Assistant Professor in the Sam Nunn School of International Affairs at the Georgia Institute of Technology, more commonly known as "Georgia Tech." I also direct the Emerging Technology and Security Program and the Biological and Chemical Nonproliferation and Counterterrorism Program.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ledyard</hi>: I retired from my professorship at Columbia thirteen years ago; since then I've had no role. When I was active there since 1964, I taught Korean history and culture, emphasizing the traditional periods of Korea's earlier history. In those years I wrote a few articles on contemporary political issues but my research has been almost all in Korea's past.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Terry</hi>: I am a Senior Research Scholar at Columbia University's Weatherhead East Asian Institute.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chi</hi>: I have been teaching Korean studies at Oxford University. I am specialized in international relations of the Far East and particularly North Korean human rights and refugee issues. I worked as an analyst of security issues at the Korea Institute for Defence Analyses in Seoul between 1983 and 1988 authoring a number of policy papers for the South Korean Government.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">You</hi>: Associate Teaching Professor of Korean Studies teaching Korean Unification, Korean film, Korean society [at the University of Missouri].</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Is the display of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/cruise%20missile">cruise missiles</ref> and other weapons in a military parade by South Korea in direct response to repeated similar North Korean parades?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Kelly</hi>:  Yes. I don't actually think these sorts of demonstrations are proper in a democracy. Liberal states should not really be flashing their hardware in a strutting, provocative way like this. This is the sort of thing Putin would do. But SK's [South Korea's] case is rather exceptional. NK [North Korea] tries pretty regularly to bully SK, and as its nuclear and missile programs advance, SK deterrence become ever more important. So parades like this are a way of SK saying 'don't mess with us even though you have nukes.'</p>
</text>
