<text id="autogum_interview_doc185" title="part0_Wikinews interviews U.S. Green Party presidential candidate Cynthia McKinney" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-07" dateModified="2017-09-30" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_U.S._Green_Party_presidential_candidate_Cynthia_McKinney" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews U.S. Green Party presidential candidate Cynthia McKinney</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, March 7, 2008</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> held an exclusive interview with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cynthia%20McKinney">Cynthia McKinney</ref>, one of the candidates for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Green%20Party">Green Party</ref> nomination for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2008%20U.S.%20presidential%20election">2008 U.S. presidential election</ref>.</p>
<p>McKinney is a former <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Democratic%20Party%20(United%20States)">Democratic</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Congresswoman">Congresswoman</ref> from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Georgia">Georgia</ref>. She was first elected to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House%20of%20Representatives">House of Representatives</ref> in 1992 and held her seat for ten years until being defeated by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Denise%20Majette">Denise Majette</ref> in 2002. She was the first ever <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/African%20American">African American</ref> woman from her state to be elected to Congress.</p>
<p>We asked her why she made the recent switch to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Green%20Party">Green Party</ref>. She replied, "Due to the importance of environmental issues, Green issues are the issues of today.  The Ten Key Values of
the Green Party stress us getting along with each other in harmony with the planet that gives us life."</p>
<p>When asked about how she would handle Iraq she replied, "I would instruct the Joint Chiefs to draw up a plan for the orderly withdrawal of all U.S. troops from the country. I would dismantle our military bases in the area, and I would also demand that U.S. and
other international corporations relinquish any claims to Iraqi oil or
other resources and withdraw as well."</p>
<p>McKinney is running for president because, basically, she thinks that "it's time that the people win".</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why are you running for president?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Congresswoman McKinney:</hi> It is clear that the country needs an additional political party that is not beholden to special interests or corporate lobbyists. Just 5% of the electorate, voting for a third party candidate gets the nation just that. Therefore, for those who are tired of the ability of special interests and corporate interests to subvert the will of the people, their values, or change their policy makers,winning the 5% is the best way to infuse structural change into our political system.</p>
<p>A victory for the Green Party in this election is possible and necessary. The alternative we present will appeal to the large numbers of disfranchised voters who do not see the major party candidates addressing their issues. In order for a democratic government to work in the public interest, it has to be both transparent and accountable. If 5% vote Green, it will put a third chair at the table of American politics, and it will open the door to the people to see what is going on inside the two-party system that has become controlled by corporations and the expanding power of a military, industrial, and intelligence complex that President Eisenhower warned of in 1960. The Green Party will represent the voices of the majority of diverse and disfranchized voters and citizens and will directly and effectively address their issues.</p>
<p>I spent my birthday last year protesting in front of the Pentagon. At that rally, I stated that upon winning a majority of the seats in the Congress, the Democratic representatives should have repealed the Bush tax cuts, repealed the Patriot Act, the Secret Evidence Act, and the Military Tribunals Act. And that the majority in Congress should have voted a livable wage for America's workers. And that someone should be trying to locate the $2.3 trillion lost by the Pentagon to pay instead for jobs, health care, and education. I was saddened by the Democratic majority's failure to stop funding the war, and declared my own independence from a national leadership that gave us war crimes, torture, and crimes against humanity. Unfortunately, there is not a major party candidate in the race that has not voted to fund this war. And that vote to fund what is clearly an immoral and illegal war is a vote of complicity in the torture and war crimes that are being committed as part of this war.</p>
</text>
