<text id="autogum_voyage_doc209" title="Amstelveen" shortTile="amstelveen" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=127177" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Amstelveen</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Amstelveen</hi> is a town in <ref target="Amstelland">Amstelland</ref>. It is a suburb of <ref target="Amsterdam">Amsterdam</ref> in an area that used to be known as Nieuwer-Amstel until 1964.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>Amstelveen, known as Nieuwer-Amstel until 1964, is a city in the <ref target="Amstelland">Amstelland</ref>. The city grew from a town founded for the harvesting of bog, which was a popular fuel at the time. During the seventeenth and eighteenth century, wealthy Amsterdammers moved to the town in search of some peace and quiet. Originally, <ref target="Amsterdam/Zuid">Southern Amsterdam</ref> was a part of the municipality. After annexation of Amsterdam Zuid, the former town hall of Nieuwer-Amstel housed the Amsterdam city archives from 1914 to 2007.</p>

<p>Not late after the first annexation, in 1921, another annexation followed taking away the northern and most densely populated part of Amstelveen. This left the municipality to conclude of the town of Amstelveen as well as several small towns. Amstelveen, however, kept its appeal to the wealthier citizens of Amsterdam, which shows from the suburbs built around 1930 in the northwest of the municipality.</p>

<p>After the <ref target="Second%20World%20War">Second World War</ref>, Nieuwer-Amstel became an overflow for Amsterdam, housing more and more people that could not find or did not want a home in Amsterdam, as well as people that worked at the growing <ref target="Schiphol%20Airport">Schiphol Airport</ref>. During the 1960s Amstelveen was even the largest growing city of the Netherlands. In 1964 the municipality was renamed after the city that by now was considered an extension of Amsterdam.</p>

<p>Since the last half of the 1990s, Amstelveen's expansion has become more and more gradual. At this time, no further expansion is planned. The most recent expansion is Westwijk to the southwest of town. To suit the needs of the already existing population, the <hi rend="italic">Stadshart</hi> has been created to replace the former town centre. Here you will find a central library, large mall, as well as cultural and gastronomical services and offices. In 2003 Amstelveen was named <hi rend="italic">Most attractive city of the Netherlands</hi> for its proximity to the nation's capital <ref target="Amsterdam">Amsterdam</ref>, its safety, accessibility and richness of culture.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>The A9 crosses straight through the municipality and functions as a ring-road for traffic that does not need to go to Amsterdam per se. Amstelveen can be reached from <ref target="The%20Hague">The Hague</ref>, <ref target="Rotterdam">Rotterdam</ref> and <ref target="Leiden">Leiden</ref> using the A4 followed by the A9 once having passed by <ref target="Schiphol">Schiphol</ref>. <ref target="Utrecht">Utrecht</ref>, <ref target="Den%20Bosch">Den Bosch</ref> and <ref target="Eindhoven">Eindhoven</ref> can use the A2, followed by the A9 after passing by Abcoude. <ref target="Apeldoorn">Apeldoorn</ref> and everything north there of is best off using the A1, followd by a kilometre of A2 heading away from Amsterdam, quickly followed by the A9.</p>

<head>By public transit</head>
<p>Amstelveen has a direct connection to the central station of <ref target="Amsterdam">Amsterdam</ref> via line 51 of the Amsterdam Metro. The metro has many stops in Amstelveen. The most notable of which is . Tram line 5 terminates at Binnenhof, which is several metres away from Amstelveen Centrum. Busses also run from the central busstation to <ref target="Aalsmeer">Aalsmeer</ref> (line 171 and 357), <ref target="Uithoorn">Uithoorn</ref> (line 174 and 374), <ref target="Haarlem">Haarlem</ref> (line 300 and 356), <ref target="Amsterdam/Zuidoost">Amsterdam Bijlmer ArenA</ref> (line 356) and <ref target="Amsterdam/Binnenstad">Amsterdam Centraal</ref> (line 347 and 357).</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<p>Amstelveen's city centre is navigable on foot, with metro line connecting to most of the city that cannot be reached easily by foot. Buslines 165, 166 and 167 serve as city busses, connecting all of the city with the central bus hub near the Amstelveen Centrum  metro station.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Molen de Dikkert</hi>, Amsterdamseweg 104a (Corner of Molenweg and Amsterdamseweg), ☏ +31 20 643 3333 . Windmill, which serves as a restaurant now. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Amsterdamse Bos</hi>. A larger forest/park that straddles the border between Amstelveen and Amsterdam. Access from Amstelveenseweg. Horse rental, canoe rental and an open air theater are some of the attractions. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cobra Museum of Modern Art</hi>. The collection of the museum consists of key works by artists of the movements Vrij Beelden (1945), Cobra (1948–1951), and Creatie (1950–1955). </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Museum Jan van der Togt</hi>. A modern visual art museum, which was established in 1991 by Jan van der Togt, an industrialist and founder of the company Tomado who was a collector of contemporary art. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Poppodium P60</hi>, Stadsplein 100a, ☏ +31 203 453 445 , ✉ info@p60.nl . P60 offers an audience to up and coming pop artists, as well as already established artists, whether they are Dutch or not. </item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">EDDY'S</hi>, Stadsplein 18, ☏ +31 204 415 244 , ✉ eddys@eddysrestaurant.nl .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kokusai</hi>, Stadstuinen 2, ☏ +31 206 407 200 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Rembrandt</hi>, Laan van de Helende Meesters 14, ☏ +31 208 223 947 , ✉ info@restaurantrembrandt.nl .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fierro</hi>, Noorddammerlaan 80, ☏ +31 206 454 881 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Aan de Poel</hi>, Handweg 1, ☏ +31 203 451 763 , ✉ info@aandepoel.nl .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Buenos Aires</hi>, Dorpsstraat 23, ☏ +31 206 418 931 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Haddock Grill Club</hi>, Stationsstraat 9, ☏ +31 203 044 969 , ✉ info@haddockgrillclub.nl .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">'t Oude Dorp</hi>, Dorpsstraat 104, ☏ +31 203 453 366 , ✉ info@grandcafeoudedorp.nl .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">De Jonge Dikkert</hi>, Amsterdamseweg 104a, ☏ +31 206 433 333 , ✉ info@jongedikkert.nl .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kaya</hi>, Karel Doormanweg 4, ☏ +31 203 452 555 .</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Het Wapen van Amstelveen</hi>, Dorpsstraat 76, ☏ +31 208 223 556 , ✉ info@hetwapenvanamstelveen.nl .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Café Thijs</hi>, Dorpsstraat 64b, ☏ +31 206 408 972 , ✉ info@cafethijs.nl . Mo-Th: 15:00 - 01:00, Fr, Sa: 15:00 - 02:00, Su: 15:00-01:00, opens an hour before any match by AFC Ajax..</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">De Manen / De Eetkamer</hi>, Noorddammerlaan 9, ☏ +31 206 413 586 . Ma-Th: 10:00 - 02:00, Fr, Sa: 10:00 - 03:00, Su: 11:00 - 02:00.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Le Pain Quotidien</hi>, Nieuw Loopveld 2, ☏ +31 203 542 180 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">BLVD Café</hi>, Stadsplein 10, ☏ +31 203 472 880 , ✉ contact@blvdcafe.nl .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Délifrance</hi>, Stadsplein 12, ☏ +31 203 375 631 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Naeckte Brouwers Annakerk B.V.</hi> (ANNA Amstelveen), Amsterdamseweg 22, 1182 HD Amstelveen, ☏ +31 20 789 5689 . Th-Sa 11:00-23:00 Su 11:00-20:00.</item>
</list>
</text>
