<text id="autogum_news_doc551" title="Malaysia Airlines Flight 17 shot down over eastern Ukraine, killing 298" shortTile="malaysia-airlines" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-07-18" dateModified="2015-08-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Malaysia_Airlines_Flight_17_shot_down_over_eastern_Ukraine%2C_killing_298" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Malaysia Airlines Flight 17 shot down over eastern Ukraine, killing 298</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, July 19, 2014</hi></p>
<figure><caption>File photo from 2010 of Malaysia Airlines Boeing 777 9M-MRD, the aircraft that was shot down. Image: Alan Wilson.</caption></figure>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Malaysia_Airlines">Malaysia Airlines</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malaysia%20Airlines%20Flight%2017">Flight 17</ref>, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boeing%20777">Boeing 777</ref>, was shot down by a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/surface-to-air%20missile">surface-to-air missile</ref> on Thursday according to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US">US</ref> officials, over disputed eastern <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ukraine">Ukraine</ref> by an unidentified party.</p>
<p>The flight, which departed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amsterdam%20Airport%20Schiphol">Amsterdam Airport Schiphol</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Netherlands">The Netherlands</ref> at 10:15 UTC en route to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kuala_Lumpur_International_Airport">Kuala Lumpur International Airport</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Malaysia">Malaysia</ref>, disappeared from radar at 13:15 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UTC">UTC</ref> near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hrabove%20(Donetsk%20Oblast)">Hrabove</ref>, a village in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Donetsk_Oblast">Donetsk Oblast</ref> of Ukraine. 283 passengers and 15 crew were aboard the aircraft, all 298 in total perished. The area the plane was flying over is a conflict zone currently between Ukrainian forces and pro-<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Russia">Russian</ref> separatist forces.  </p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> officials confirmed the aircraft has been shot down, according to data from a surveillance satellite which showed the last trajectory and impact of the missile. The missile is believed to be a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buk%20missile%20system">Buk</ref> M1 surface-to-air missile which are believed to be in the hands of rebels according to reports from the area. </p>
<figure><caption>Flight path of Malaysia Airlines Flight 17. Image: Geordie Bosanko and cmglee.</caption></figure>
<p>So far no party has claimed responsibility for the attack. Ukrainian officials denied the missile which shot down the airliner belonged to Ukraine. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pavlo%20Klimkin">Pavlo Klimkin</ref>, Ukraine's foreign minister, said to <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Guardian">The Guardian</ref></hi>, "We are absolutely sure and we checked yesterday that no missiles have been taken from the Ukrainian army". The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Security%20Service%20of%20Ukraine">Security Service of Ukraine</ref> (SBU) published on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/YouTube">YouTube</ref> an alleged wiretap of separatist commanders and Russian intelligence officers discussing the shoot-down and acknowledging the aircraft shot down was civilian.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, Russia's defense ministry has denied involvement, posting a statement on their website which read, "In view of various types of speculation concerning operations of the Russian armed forces in the areas bordering Ukraine, we affirm that the anti-aircraft means of the Russian armed forces did not operate in that region July 17".</p>
<p>Ukrainian president <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Petro_Poroshenko">Petro Poroshenko</ref> said, "This was not an 'incident', this was not a 'catastrophe', this was a terrorist act". Malyasian prime minister <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Najib_Razak">Najib Razak</ref>, said, "If it transpires that the flight was shot down, we insist that the perpetrators must swiftly be brought to justice."</p>
<p>All civilian aircraft have been barred from flying over eastern Ukraine.  The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US">US</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal%20Aviation%20Adminstration">Federal Aviation Adminstration</ref> issued a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Notice%20to%20Airmen">Notice to Airmen</ref> (NOTAM) prohibiting flight operations by United States carriers over eastern Ukraine. However, questions remain as to why the aircraft was flying over the contested area. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eurocontrol">Eurocontrol</ref> noted airspace was closed up to 32,000 feet. Flight 17 was flying at 33,000 feet just above the restricted airspace. Malaysia Airlines issued a statement saying "The usual flight route was earlier declared safe by the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/International_Civil_Aviation_Organisation">International Civil Aviation Organisation</ref> (ICAO). [The] <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International%20Air%20Transportation%20Association">International Air Transportation Association</ref> (IATA) has stated that the airspace the aircraft was traversing was not subject to restrictions."</p>
</text>
