<text id="autogum_interview_doc458" title="part2_Former &amp;apos;Top Model&amp;apos; contestant Whitney Cunningham defends plus size models, celebrates the &amp;quot;regular woman&amp;quot;" shortTile="partformer-top-model" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-12-03" dateModified="2012-06-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Former_%27Top_Model%27_contestant_Whitney_Cunningham_defends_plus_size_models%2C_celebrates_the_%22regular_woman%22" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Did Tyra encourage a certain standard among the girls (weight or otherwise) that was unhealthy?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WC:</hi> Not at all. I think that viewers think that we have a whole lot more interaction with Tyra than we actually do. We only really saw her during panel and during our "interventions." [laughs]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Do you think Tyra still believes her show is about finding "the next top model" even though none of the show's winners have had that success?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WC:</hi> [laughs] That is a phenomenal question. I don't think that the show gives its winners enough time to reign. The show puts out two cycles a year. While one cycle is airing, they are taping another and apparently the show is scheduled to continue until 2010! I think it was about finding a "Top Model" during the show's beginnings, but I think that über-success of the show has turned it into a profit-driven production. I just wish that the show would put more time and cultivation into their winners even <hi rend="italic">after</hi> their cycle's conclusions. And I truly think that the show would see a return on cultivating their winners, because the show's credibility would increase.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> A fan wrote in to ask, "What struggles did you face on the show as a plus sized model?"</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WC:</hi> I think that my biggest struggle was realizing that plus sized models and straight sized models are apples and oranges...I couldn't study magazines and try to develop my poses, because a woman who weighs 110 pounds and is 5'10" looks completely different when she shapes and curves her body than a woman who is 5'10" and weighs 175 pounds. I, therefore, had to figure things out as I went along. The other girls had a reference/vantage point to learn from. I'm still figuring things out.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Do you think it was unfair for Tyra to ask that [studying magazines and developing your poses] of you and Diana, considering that even though she's fuller-figured now, she has a lot more experience under her belt than you two did?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WC:</hi> Well, you know, I would say that it would have been fair if there were magazines for us to study! But there were none. That's why I think that it's so important that publications like Plus Model Magazine continue to blossom and flourish. I've learned more reading that magazine and getting to know the folks who write for that magazine than I ever learned about being a plus-sized model on ANTM. P.S. I'll be gracing the cover of that magazine in January of '08. Look out for me.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> It sounds like you're doing just fine for yourself. Which one fan also asked, "Have you faced adversity about your weight since being on the show?"</p>
</text>
