<text id="autogum_voyage_doc17" title="Seychelles" shortTile="seychelles" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=32277" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Seychelles</head>

<p>The <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.seychelles.travel/en">Seychelles</ref></hi> are a group of 115 islands in the Indian Ocean that lie off the coast of <ref target="East%20Africa">East Africa</ref>, northeast of <ref target="Madagascar">Madagascar</ref>. Only a few are inhabited.</p>
<head>Regions</head>
<h3><ref target="Outer%20Seychelles">Outer Seychelles</ref></h3>
<p>The Outer Seychelles are corralline and mostly uninhabited. Visitors are rare, and will find themselves traveling either by private yacht or between remote airstrips on small local planes.</p>

<head>Inner Seychelles</head>
<p>The vast majority of the Seychelles' population lives on these granite islands, home to the bulk of the country's resorts.</p>

<head>Cities</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> - The Capital City</item>
<item> </item>
<item> - district in Seychelles</item>
</list>


<head>Understand</head>
<p>The Seychelles is the smallest African country by size and population.</p>

<head>History</head>

<p>Maldivian and Arab traders were the first to visit the uninhabited Seychelles. The first European to arrive at the islands was Portuguese Admiral Vasco da Gama who passed through the Amirantes in 1502 and named them after himself (Islands of the Admiral). They became a waypoint on the <ref target="Cape%20Route">Cape Route</ref>.</p>

<p>The Seychelles were disputed between France and Great Britain during the age of colonialism, with Britain ending up in control in 1814 after the <ref target="Napoleonic%20Wars">Napoleonic Wars</ref>. The islands achieved independence in 1976; however, free elections did not occur until 1993.</p>

<p>The politics of this island group remain in something of a state of flux, although this should not bother the tourist seeking a relaxing beach vacation.</p>

<head>Climate</head>
<p>Seychelles is hot and humid, with an average yearly temperature of 84°F (29°C), and average sea temperature rarely dropping below 81°F (27°C). However, the heat is usually mitigated by refreshing sea breezes, especially by the beaches. The cooler season in Seychelles is during the southeast monsoon season (May to September) and the warmer season is during the northwest monsoon (November to March). April and October are "changeover months" between the two monsoons, when the wind is variable. The northwest monsoon season tends to be warmer with more rain, while the southeast monsoon season is usually drier and cooler.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>No visa is required for any nationality, though all foreigners must have a passport that is valid for at least 6 months, and must have proof of accommodation bookings before arrival. An initial entry permit is granted for 1 month but can be extended for a maximum of 3 months at a time up to a maximum of 1 year in total. See the official travel web-site <ref target="http://www.seychelles.travel/en/plan_your_visit/entry_formalities.php"></ref> .</p>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.seychellesairports.sc/">Seychelles International Airport</ref></hi> (SEZ<ref target="IATA"></ref>). The only international gateway to the Seychelles near the national capital, <ref target="Victoria%20%28Seychelles%29">Victoria</ref>. <ref target="http://www.airseychelles.com/"><hi rend="bold">Air Seychelles</hi></ref> is the country's flag carrier and flies to Cape Town, Abu Dhabi, Mumbai, Hong Kong, Paris, as well as Dar Es Salaam, Johannesburg, Mauritius and Antananarivo in Madagascar. International service is also available from Addis Ababa (<ref target="http://www.ethiopianairlines.com/">Ethiopian Airlines</ref>), Nairobi (<ref target="http://www.kenya-airways.com/">Kenya Airways</ref>), Dubai (<ref target="http://www.emirates.com/">Emirates</ref>), Abu Dhabi (<ref target="http://www.etihadairways.com/">Etihad</ref>), Istanbul (<ref target="http://www.turkishairlines.com/">Turkish Airlines</ref>), Doha (<ref target="http://www.qatarairways.com/">Qatar Airways</ref>), and regular charter services from Frankfurt (<ref target="http://www.condor.com/">Condor</ref>) and Amsterdam (<ref target="http://www.martinair.com/">Martinair</ref>).</item>
</list>


<head>By boat</head>
<p>The strict controls imposed on cruising yachts in the early 1990s have been gradually lifted and rules and regulations are no longer so complicated. However, some restrictions remain in force, mostly for the sake of environmental protection as most of the islands are surrounded by coral reefs near the surface.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<ref target="http://www.airseychelles.com/">Air Seychelles</ref> operates multiple daily flights between Mahe and Praslin. Over two dozen flights vary in frequency from 15-minute to 2-hour intervals, depending on time of day.

<p>Air Seychelles also operates once daily or several times per week between Mahe and the islands of Bird, Denis, Fregate, Desroches and Alphonse. Assumption Island and Coetivy can be reached by air charter.</p>

<head>By helicopter</head>
<p>Zil Air provides charter helicopter flights to/from most of the inner and outer Seychelles Islands. It is the only scenic flight operator in the Seychelles. Scenic flights can be booked to cover the main islands of Mahé, Praslin, La Digue and the surrounding smaller islands of (among others) Cousine, Félicité, Grande Seour, Curieuse and Bird Island.</p>

<head>By boat</head>
<p>Cat Cocos operates catamaran ferries that provide several daily crossings between <ref target="Mahe">Mahe</ref> and <ref target="Praslin">Praslin</ref> and a daily crossing extension to La Digue. The sailing normally takes one hour. Non-residents should budget between €90 and €100 per person (price at July 2013, based on a single adult fare of 835 rupees one way) for a same day return ticket from Mahe to Praslin. Tickets can be purchased from the Cat Cocos office, opposite the pier, on the same day before travel subject to availability.</p>

<p>Similarly, Inter Island Ferry operate a route between <ref target="Praslin">Praslin</ref> and <ref target="La%20Digue">La Digue</ref> with 8 daily departures taking 15 min to cross. Tickets cost around €15 for an adult single (July 2013). The schedule usually allows for onward connections to Mahe with Cat Cocos at Praslin harbour.</p>

<p>Belle Serafina, a small schooner ferry makes the passage between Mahe and Praslin or La Digue in 3-4 hours, usually departing weekdays shortly around 12 from Mahe and heading back at 5AM from Praslin to Mahe. In October 2010 the price for the passage was 125 rupees. Schedules and routing need to be confirmed by phone.</p>

<p>It is also possible to take small boats from Mahe direct to La Digue, although departures can be unreliable, there is limited wet weather cover and the journey takes about 3 hours (but that's cheaper than an Indian Ocean Island cruise!)</p>

<p>As of June 2013, online bookings with live seat availability and e-ticketing are possible for Cat Cocos and Inter Island Ferry by Seychellesbookings.com <ref target="http://seychellesbookings.com"></ref>.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>Driving in Seychelles is on the <hi rend="bold">left</hi> side of the road. The roads on Mahe are low-traffic, mountainous, narrow roads, so caution is generally advised.</p>

<p>Having a car is really a good idea and makes life much more simple. For as little as 100 rupees worth of gas you can see the entire island of Mahe in a couple of hours, including stops at beaches and whatever else catches your eye. There is free parking in 'downtown' Victoria on Mahe, and if you go with a B&amp;B or self-catering option for accommodations its by far the easiest way to pick up groceries. A car will also allow you access to the stores where locals do their regular shopping, and the prices are more reasonable as compared to the small convenience stores along the beaches. There is no substitute for running your vacation on your own schedule</p>

<p>You can only rent on Mahé and Praslin. You can find a small car (e.g., Hyundai Atos) for €35-45 per day, but keep in mind that renters must be at least 21 years old, have a valid driver's license, and have at least three years of driving experience. There are several car hire counters outside the arrivals hall at Mahe international airport, which provide a convenient way to compare prices from different hire companies. Prices can be negotiated, with the better rate available for rental periods of 3 consecutive days or more. The 'excess' payable by the customer in the event of a claim, ranges from €300 to €1000 depending on the company, so choose carefully and ask the right questions.</p>

<p>Taxis are also a popular means of transportation for both short trips and day rental and can be obtained almost anywhere. Taxi prices for non-residents (approx. 20 rupees per km in Sept 2010) on a relatively long trip, can easily exceed the cost of hiring a small car for a day.</p>
</text>
