<text id="autogum_interview_doc613" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Joe Schriner, Independent U.S. presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-04-16" dateModified="2019-08-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Joe_Schriner%2C_Independent_U.S._presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">When you announced your candidacy following the 2008 election, you remarked that this would be your final run. Why did you make that decision, and why did you announce your candidacy so early in the electoral process?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Given the strategy about using running for president as a way of getting a message out to help change America now, I always announce early and start hitting the road often just as early.  For instance, I was just on the front page of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LaGrange,%20Georgia">LaGrange (GA)</ref> News talking about a project we'd researched (the Alterna Project) to provide long-term, affordable housing for new Hispanic immigrants in a community setting.  Now if I had walked in the doors of that newspaper, approached an editor and said:  “Hi.  I'm Joe from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cleveland,%20Ohio">Cleveland</ref> and I have some great ideas I'd like to share with you.”  He/she would have looked at me, not like I was from Cleveland, but rather like I was from, oh, Mars...  Also being on the road early, gives me that much more time to continue my cross country research for our position papers, and such.    And it gives me more time to, well, campaign in general.  When you're short on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lear%20Jet">Lear Jets</ref> and have to travel in a 1984 family camper, it just takes you a bit more time to get around.  “America is a lot bigger than it looks on the map,” I often joke.  And as far as this being our final run... we're planning on winning this time.   Although it just occurred to me that when I win this time, I'll have to run again for a second term. They don't call me “average Joe” for nothing. (My wife Liz says I’m sometimes a bit short on forward planning.)  For more about Liz . </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Back in 2000, Steve Chawkins with <hi rend="italic">Ventura County News</hi>, wrote to you "<ref target="http://articles.latimes.com/2000/jan/19/local/me-55503">You won't win, you won't be president.</ref>" Why do you believe you lost that particular election as well as the 2004 and 2008 elections? What have you done differently during this run?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Why I didn't win in 2000, 2004 and 2008?  I didn't get enough votes. (Sorry.) Actually, each election I have been somewhat quietly, and under-the-radar, going about meeting with people on the ground, giving talks, doing local media, putting up fliers...We do all the things the other campaigns do, only with a much smaller budget.  I recently told the Sun News in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lakewood,%20New%20York">Lakewood</ref>, that this, indeed, is “...a serious attempt by an average citizen to run for president.”  Yet as for the current state of election dynamics in America, we're up against this huge <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goliath">Goliath</ref>(s), and our 'sling shot and stone' – if one allows that metaphor – will be sparking a grassroots revolution.  But for this to happen, and for this to become a national story with staying power (and not a 15-minutes-of-fame national media blip), people would have to know that there has been tremendous depth and breadth to the research and campaigning. (As just another example, I have traveled more than 80,000  miles campaigning in the past 11 years.  And I might well be the most well traveled presidential candidate (domestic road miles) -- in the history of U.S. politics.)    So as to what we'll do different in this election?  Not much.  I intend to stick to our “back road to the White House” strategy  , continuing to go from town to town – waiting for that long caravan – both literally and metaphorically – to start lining up behind us.   </p>
</text>
