<text id="autogum_bio_doc280" title="John Malcolm (Loyalist)" shortTile="john-malcolm-loyalist" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-11-26" dateModified="2019-07-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Malcolm_%28Loyalist%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>John Malcolm (Loyalist)</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">John Malcolm</hi> (died 1833) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Captain_(nautical)">sea captain</ref>, army officer, and British <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Customs">customs</ref> official who was the victim of the most publicized <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tarring_and_feathering">tarring and feathering</ref> incident during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Revolution">American Revolution</ref>.</p>
<p>A <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boston">Bostonian</ref>, Captain Malcolm was a staunch supporter of royal authority. During the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War_of_the_Regulation">War of the Regulation</ref>, he traveled to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Province_of_North_Carolina">province of North Carolina</ref> to help put down the uprising. While working for the customs service, he pursued his duties with a zeal that made him very unpopular. The fact that he was a loyalist during the Tea Act, the three-pence tea tax detested by the patriots did not help his reputation. In November 1773, sailors in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portsmouth,_New_Hampshire">Portsmouth, New Hampshire</ref>, tarred and feathered him. Malcolm got off relatively easy in this attack, since the tar and feathers were applied while he was still fully clothed.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Young47-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>As a hard-line <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loyalist_(American_Revolution)">Loyalist</ref>, Malcolm often faced abuse and provocation from Boston's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patriot_(American_Revolution)">Patriots</ref>, the critics of British authority. People often "hooted" at him in the streets, but Governor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Hutchinson_(governor)">Thomas Hutchinson</ref> urged him not to respond.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Young47-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>A confrontation with Patriot shoemaker <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Robert_Twelves_Hewes">George Hewes</ref> thrust Malcolm into the spotlight. On January 25, 1774, according to the account in the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Massachusetts_Gazette">Massachusetts Gazette</ref></hi>, Hewes saw Malcolm threatening to strike a boy with his cane. When Hewes intervened to stop Malcolm, the two men began arguing, with Malcolm insisting that Hewes should not interfere in the business of a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gentleman">gentleman</ref>. When Hewes replied that at least he (Hewes) had never been tarred and feathered, Malcolm struck Hewes hard on the forehead with the cane, knocking him unconscious.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>That night, a crowd seized Malcolm in his house and dragged him into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King_Street_(Boston)">King Street</ref> in order to punish him for the attack on Hewes and the boy. Some Patriot leaders, believing that mob violence hurt their cause, tried to dissuade the crowd, arguing that Malcolm should be turned over to the justice system. Hewes, who had recovered, also protested against the attack on Malcolm. The crowd refused to relent, however, citing (among other arguments) the fact that Ebenezer Richardson, a customs official who had killed an 11 year old Bostonian named <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Seider">Christopher Seider</ref>, had escaped punishment by receiving a royal pardon.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> Malcolm was stripped to the waist and covered with tar and feathers. The crowd then took him to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liberty_Tree">Liberty Tree</ref> and told him to apologize for his behavior and renounce his customs commission. When Malcolm refused, the crowd put a rope around his neck and threatened to hang him. This did not break him, but when they threatened to cut off his ears, Malcolm relented and was sent home. The event was reported in newspapers on both sides of the Atlantic.</p>
<p>After these events, Malcolm moved to England, where he unsuccessfully ran for Parliament against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Wilkes">John Wilkes</ref>, the controversial champion of colonial rights.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
</text>
