<text id="autogum_interview_doc700" title="Exclusive report on New Zealand&amp;apos;s digital TV service" shortTile="exclusive-report" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-08-17" dateModified="2007-08-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Exclusive_report_on_New_Zealand%27s_digital_TV_service" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Exclusive report on New Zealand's digital TV service</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, August 17, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> has compiled the views from various politicians on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_Zealand">New Zealand's</ref> latest digital television service, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freeview%20(New%20Zealand)">Freeview</ref>. Those interviewed were <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sue%20Kedgley">Sue Kedgley</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jonathan%20Coleman%20(politician)">Jonathan Coleman</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve%20Maharey">Steve Maharey</ref>, the broadcasting spokespeople for their respective parties; the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Green%20Party%20of%20Aotearoa%20New%20Zealand">Green Party of Aotearoa New Zealand</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20Zealand%20National%20Party">New Zealand National Party</ref>, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20Zealand%20Labour%20Party">New Zealand Labour Party</ref>.</p>
<p>Freeview, modelled after the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20Kingdom">United Kingdom</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freeview">Freeview</ref>, is competing directly with New Zealand's only other digital pay TV provider, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sky%20Network%20Television">Sky Network Television</ref>. Sky reaches around 44.5% of New Zealand households. However, unlike Sky, Freeview has no on-going subscription fees, and only has a one-off fee for a set-top box and, if needed, a satellite dish.</p>
<p>The Labour-led <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20Zealand%20Government">Government</ref> has provided Freeview with around <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NZ$">NZ$</ref>25 million over a five-year period to help New Zealand change from the old analogue technology and align itself "as the rest of the world moves to digital television broadcasting," Mr Maharey said. The funding use is monitored by the Ministry for Culture and Heritage. Dr Coleman also described the same reasons why Freeview was necessary for New Zealand and is supported by the National Party.</p>
<p>However, Ms Kedgley takes a different approach and describes the Freeview service as "a belated and inadequate response to the digital challenge", but does state that digital TV is the "growth area." She also said that the Government is now trying to catch up after they scrapped TVNZ's (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Television%20New%20Zealand">Television New Zealand</ref>) digital plan, which she describes as far more ambitious.</p>
<p>National, despite being supportive of Freeview, think that the Government has not done a good job with Freeview, describing it as a "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/white%20elephant">white elephant</ref>". Firstly because Dr Coleman says there isn't enough good programming currently available to get people interested in switching, and, secondly, there hasn't been a definite date when analogue transmission will be cut off.</p>
<p>Mr Maharey said that the Government is engaging various broadcasters and interested parties to get a definite analogue switch off date, and talk about other various regulatory factors. He expects the date to be within the next six to ten years.</p>
<p>While the Greens do welcome the new government-funded TVNZ channels, a news and current affairs channel and a family-related channel (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TVNZ%207">TVNZ 7</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TVNZ%206">TVNZ 6</ref> respectively), "The whole exercise however, smacks of too little, too late." They also say that the amount of funding allocated to new programming cannot pose a threat to Sky. But do support "packaging and marketing [...] existing TVNZ content on the emerging digital platforms." <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MediaWorks%20NZ">MediaWorks</ref>, which runs <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TV3%20(New%20Zealand)">TV3</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C4%20(TV%20channel)">C4</ref>, will announce their two new channels in around 18-months. And <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Triangle%20TV">Triangle TV</ref> will add their own channel, Stratos TV, in October, 2007.</p>
<p>National are questioning Mr Maharey why he hadn't released the viewer number figures. Dr Coleman said that Mr Maharey was trying to distance himself away from the "reality" of what was going on. So <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> requested, under the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Official%20Information%20Act%201982">Official Information Act</ref>, the amount of set-top boxes sold. The request was denied as Freeview was to release the information themselves in a months time. On August 13 the figures were released, with a total over 21,000. General Manager Steve Browning said that “we're tracking well ahead of forecast”. Mr Maharey concurred with what Mr Browning said, saying it exceeds their first year expectations.</p>
<p>Ms Kedgley, Dr Coleman, and Mr Maharey all say that they don't have Freeview, nor know anyone who has the service. Though, Mr Maharey will consider getting it when more channels and the 2008 terrestrial service is launched in eight major New Zealand cities.</p>
</text>
