<text id="autogum_bio_doc342" title="Isaq Schrijver" shortTile="isaq-schrijver" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-01-23" dateModified="2019-08-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isaq_Schrijver" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Isaq Schrijver</head><p><hi rend="bold">Isaq Schrijver</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Floruit">fl.</ref> 1689 – 1705/06) was a Dutch ensign and South African explorer. Although born and raised in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leiden">Leiden</ref>, both his parents were born near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aachen">Aachen</ref>, Germany. Little else is known of his origins, but by 1667 he was a marine.</p>
<p>In February 1684, Schrijver, then a sergeant in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dutch_East_India_Company">Dutch East India Company</ref> and stationed at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cape_of_Good_Hope">Cape</ref>, headed a reconnaissance expedition into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Namaqualand">Namaqualand</ref>. They went as far north as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garies">Garies</ref> and brought back samples of copper ore to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cape_Town">Cape Town</ref>.</p>
<p>Schrijver was involved in salvage operations of the <hi rend="italic">Nossa Senhora dos Milagros</hi> which had run aground on the night of 16 April 1686 at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Struisbaai">Struisbaai</ref> near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cape_Agulhas">Cape Agulhas</ref>. This was a Portuguese vessel with 150 crew, commanded by Don Emmanual Da Silva, en route from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goa">Goa</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portugal">Portugal</ref> and bearing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diplomatic_gift">diplomatic gifts</ref> from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Narai">Narai</ref>, King of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siam">Siam</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_II_of_Portugal">Pedro</ref>, King of Portugal, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_XIV">Louis XIV</ref> of France and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_II_of_England">Charles II of England</ref>. Also aboard were three Siamese ambassadors who were left to fend for themselves by the crew. Two were found in a desperate state a month after the wreck, the third having succumbed.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simon_van_der_Stel">Simon van der Stel</ref> sent a party consisting of lieutenant Olof Bergh, Isaq Schrijver and others to salvage what they could. Very little of any value was returned to the governor, but rumours of theft of the treasure soon started circulating, substantiated by the attempted sale of items to Cape Town residents and the unearthing in Olof Bergh's garden of a box holding objects from the wreck. Bergh later confessed to the theft and alleged that van der Stel himself was involved. Bergh was sentenced to three and a half years on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robben_Island">Robben Island</ref> while Schrijver was cleared of any wrongdoing.</p>
<p>On 4 January 1689, two years after being promoted to the rank of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ensign_(rank)">ensign</ref>, Schrijver embarked on his most enterprising expedition. His orders were to barter cattle with the Inqua <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Khoikhoi">Hottentots</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eastern_Cape">Eastern Cape</ref>. He set off with a party of about 20 well-armed soldiers and 2 wagons on a trip which would cover about 1600km. Also in the party was <ref target="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heinrich%20Bernhard%20Oldenland">Heinrich Bernhard Oldenland</ref> (1663–99), an able botanist and expert on herbs, who had studied medicine for 3 years at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leiden_University">Leiden University</ref>, and who would in 1693 be appointed as master gardener in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dutch_East_India_Company">Company's</ref> garden in Cape Town, and oddly as land surveyor for the Government followed by the post of superintendent of roads, bridges and buildings. The mission lasted more than three months and reached as far east as the present-day town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aberdeen,_Eastern_Cape">Aberdeen</ref>, returning on 10 April 1689 with about a thousand head of cattle from trading with a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Xhosa_people">Xhosa</ref>-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Khoi">Khoi</ref> tribe and quite amazingly having suffered no loss of life.</p>
<p>Early travelers were obliged to cross the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Outeniqua_Mountains">Outeniqua Mountains</ref> near present-day <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mossel_Bay">Mossel Bay</ref> so as to avoid the near-impenetrable ravines and forests to the east. At that time the only way across the mountains was through <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Attaquas_Kloof">Attaquas Kloof</ref>, named after a chief of the Hessequa <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Khoikhoi">Khoikhoi</ref>. This route was pioneered by Schrijver who, following an elephant track, traversed the kloof to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Olifants_River_(Southern_Cape)">Olifants River</ref> in January 1689. The Duivenhoks River at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heidelberg,_Western_Cape">Heidelberg</ref> was named by Schrijver, and "Schrijvershoek" near Langebaan lagoon was named after him.</p>
<p>He retired in 1699 to his farm <hi rend="italic">Schoongezicht</hi> near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stellenbosch">Stellenbosch</ref> - the farm was substantially enlarged by the addition of surrounding property that had formed part of the deceased estates of freed slaves. <hi rend="italic">Schoongezicht'</hi>s history goes back to 1692 when <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simon_van_der_Stel">Simon van der Stel</ref>, Governor of the Cape, granted 17 hectares of land to freed slaves Manuel and Antonia of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Angola">Angola</ref>, Louis of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bengal">Bengal</ref> and Isaac Schryver.</p>
<p>Schrijver married Marie Elizabeth van Coningshoven. Soon after, Schryver travelled north once again to search for copper. He returned after a few years and finally died on the farm, survived by Marie Elizabeth, who later married Jacob Groenewald. The farm remained in the family ownership for some 100 years. <hi rend="italic">Schoongezicht</hi> passed through numerous hands in the three centuries of its existence. Coenraad Fick built the gabled <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cape_Dutch">Cape Dutch</ref> home about 1830. In the 1920s a Mrs. English bought the estate, restored the buildings, and improved the vineyards, renaming it <hi rend="italic">Lanzerac</hi> after a wine-growing region in France. In 1958 the entrepreneur David Rawdon converted the estate into a successful hotel. In 1990 business tycoon Christo Wiese purchased the property, converting it into a winery and hotel.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Contemporary copies of Schrijver's journals of the expeditions have survived and are now kept in the Cape Archives.</p>
<head>References</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Standard Encyclopaedia of Southern Africa (vol.9) - NASOU, (Cape Town 1973)</item>
<item>Mossop, E.E. <hi rend="italic">Journals of the expeditions of the Honourable Ensigns Olof Bergh (1682 and 1683) and Isaq Schrijver (1689)</hi>. Van Riebeeck Society, Cape Town, 1931.</item></list>
</text>
