<text id="autogum_voyage_doc200" title="Goulburn" shortTile="goulburn" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=13079" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Goulburn</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.visitnsw.com/destinations/country-nsw/goulburn-area/goulburn">Goulburn</ref></hi> is a small regional city 200km (120 miles) south-west of <ref target="Sydney">Sydney</ref>, <ref target="Australia">Australia</ref>. With a population of 24,000, Goulburn is one of the largest cities in the region and a rural hub for surrounding agriculture. Goulburn lays claim to be Australia's first inland city to be settled.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Situated at the confluence of the Wollondilly and Mulwaree Rivers, the fertile lands which surround the area of Goulburn were for centuries the home a number of the local Aboriginal populations. White settlers discovered the area in the late 1700s, and the first land grant was made in 1825. The city grew as a result of its location, being located on the road south from Sydney (now the Hume Highway) and in the 19th century it became the administrative centre for the "Argyle County" district. Goulburn gained a great deal of its prosperity during the Gold Rush (when many of its main buildings were constructed) and the coming of the Main South Railway Line between Sydney and <ref target="Melbourne">Melbourne</ref> in 1869 (which is still in operation). In particular, the area became known for its merino wool which was sent from Goulburn around Australia and overseas. The city had the unique distinction of being granted city status twice - once in 1853 by Queen Victoria (which established the city as a "cathedral city" and allowed its cathedral, St Saviour's, to be constructed), then officially again in 1885.</p>

<p>In the twentieth century, the city's importance declined as a result of the growth of coastal cities in Australia, as well as Goulburn's proximity to the new national capital <ref target="Canberra">Canberra</ref>. These factors led to many government bodies and institutions that had established branches in Goulburn departing the city for Canberra or Sydney, and leaving Goulburn to rely on its wool trade and its place as a service centre on the highway. The city was finally bypassed by the Hume Highway in the 1990s and the wool trade has declined, but Goulburn is still considered the major "city" between Sydney and Canberra and visitors still take the turn off the highway to visit. Importantly, the city has retained its heritage and remains an important part of Australia's early history.</p>

<p>Though it might be considered quiet compared to the bustling Sydney two hours up the road, the Goulburn area still has a surprisingly large number of things to do and see, and it remains a good stop-off point in between Sydney, Canberra, the <ref target="Southern%20Highlands%20%28New%20South%20Wales%29">Southern Highlands</ref> and the <ref target="South%20Coast%20%28New%20South%20Wales%29">South Coast</ref>.</p>

<head>Climate</head>
<p>Goulburn has a climate unlike most of its neighbouring towns due to its location at the bottom of a valley: summers tend to be relatively hot and dry and winters cold. The summer temperature range is 10-40°C (50-104°F) and winter's is -5-18°C (23-64°F). Be sure to bring layers in winter as it can get quite windy and very cold. Despite the varied temperature, Goulburn can be visited at any time of year as long as you bring the right clothing.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Goulburn Visitor Information Centre</hi>, 201 Sloane St (opposite Belmore Park in the centre of town), ☏ +61 2 48234492 , fax: +61 2 48222692 . 9AM-5PM weekdays, 10AM-4PM weekends and public holidays.</item>
</list>


<head>Get in</head>
<p>Goulburn's position as a service centre between two major cities gives a visitor plenty of options to choose from when visiting.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>Goulburn is located just off the <hi rend="bold">Hume Highway</hi>, approximately 90km from <ref target="Canberra">Canberra</ref> and 195km from <ref target="Sydney">Sydney</ref>. From Canberra, take the Federal Highway (Northbourne Ave) and then the Hume Highway North. From Sydney, take the M5 Motorway and then the Hume Highway. There are two exits to Goulburn from the freeway.</p>

<p>An alternative, and more scenic route from Canberra is to take the Kings Highway east to Bungendore, then follow <hi rend="bold">Tarago and Braidwood Roads</hi> north into the city. This route is slightly longer than the freeway and takes just under 2 hours.</p>

<p>If coming from the <ref target="Blue%20Mountains">Blue Mountains</ref>, <ref target="Bathurst%20%28New%20South%20Wales%29">Bathurst</ref> or the <ref target="Central%20West%20%28New%20South%20Wales%29">Central West</ref>, a quicker way to get to Goulburn than to drive through Sydney is to drive to <ref target="Oberon">Oberon</ref> and take the <hi rend="bold">Taralga Road</hi> which comes into Goulburn from the north.</p>

<head>By train</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://nswtrainlink.info/">NSW Trainlink Regional</ref></hi> runs 4-5 train services per day from Central Station in <ref target="Sydney">Sydney</ref> to Goulburn on the way to <ref target="Melbourne">Melbourne</ref> and <ref target="Canberra">Canberra</ref> (from $28 one-way). A train from Sydney will take just over two and a half hours to reach Goulburn. Goulburn's historic railway station is in the centre of town on Sloane Street in the centre of town. NSW Trainlink Regional trains need to be booked in advance.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.transportnsw.info">NSW Trainlink Intercity</ref></hi> also run local trains integrated with the Sydney Trains network to and from Goulburn on the <hi rend="bold">Southern Highlands Line</hi>. Services are geared more around getting travellers from Goulburn to and from Sydney, meaning that unless you plan on travelling when the commuters do, you will need to catch a bus and be prepared to spend up to 4.5 hours with two trains and a bus to get there (change at Campbelltown, for train to Moss Vale, Moss Vale for bus to Goulburn). The upside is that tickets are cheap ($8.20 adult/$4.20 child one way), accept Opal, and have the Opal caps and rewards.</item>
</list>


<head>By bus</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Greyhound</hi>, ☏ 1300 473 946 (local rate call) , fax: +61 746382178 . include Goulburn as a request stop on its GF230 service between Sydney and Melbourne. The Sydney-Melbourne service leaves Sydney's Central Station at 9:00 and arrives Goulburn at 12:30PM, going on to Canberra (1:30PM) and arriving Melbourne at 11PM the same day. The reverse Melbourne-Sydney service leaves Melbourne's Southern Cross Station at 7:15AM, arrives Canberra 4:30PM, Goulburn 6:30PM and Sydney Central at 9:25PM. Fares from $32.40 from Sydney. <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.fireflyexpress.com.au/">Firefly</ref></hi> also advertise this route but it is codeshared with Greyhound.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Murray's</hi>, ☏ +61132251 , ✉ reservations@murrays.com.au . run a daily service between Canberra and <ref target="Wollongong">Wollongong</ref> which stops at Goulburn (from $20.30). The Canberra-Wollongong service leaves Goulburn at 6PM and arrives 7:10PM each day. The reverse service leaves Goulburn at 12:30PM (2:30PM on Sundays), arriving Canberra at 1:40PM (3:40PM on Sundays). Note that the express Sydney-Canberra Murray's buses do not stop in Goulburn.</item>
</list>
</text>
