<text id="autogum_bio_doc271" title="Boki (Hawaiian chief)" shortTile="boki-hawaiian-chief" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-20" dateModified="2019-09-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boki_%28Hawaiian_chief%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Boki (Hawaiian chief)</head>For other people or places named "Boki", see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boki_(disambiguation)">Boki (disambiguation)</ref>.
<hi rend="bold">Warning:</hi> Page using <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Infobox_officeholder">Template:Infobox officeholder</ref> with unknown parameter "signature_size" (this message is shown only in preview).<hi rend="bold">Warning:</hi> Page using <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Infobox_officeholder">Template:Infobox officeholder</ref> with unknown parameter "religion" (this message is shown only in preview).
<p><hi rend="bold">Boki</hi> (sometimes <hi rend="bold">Poki</hi>, born <hi rend="bold">Kamāʻuleʻule</hi>) (before 1785–after December 1829) was a High Chief in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ancient_Hawaii">ancient Hawaiian</ref> tradition and served the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Hawaii">Kingdom of Hawaii</ref> as royal governor of the island of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oahu">Oahu</ref>.  Boki ran a mercantile and shipping business and encouraged the Hawaiians to gather sandalwood for trade.</p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>Boki was the son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kekuamanoha">Kekuamanoha</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kamakahukilani">Kamakahukilani</ref>. His father was a chief of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maui">Maui</ref> and grandson of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kekaulike">Kekaulike</ref>, King of Maui. He was a younger brother of William Pitt <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kalanimoku">Kalanimoku</ref>, but it was rumored that he was a son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kahekili_II">Kahekili II</ref>. His original name was <hi rend="bold">Kamāʻuleʻule</hi> ("The one who faints") and his nickname came from a variation of "Boss", the name of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kamehameha_I">Kamehameha I</ref>'s favorite dog which was a very common name for dogs in Hawaii at the time.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Historical_Collections_of_The_Hawaiian_Islands-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-hawaiianencyclopedia-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Royal governor</head>
<p>Boki was appointed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_Governor_of_Oahu">Royal Governor of Oahu</ref> and chief of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waianae,_Hawaii">Waiʻanae</ref> District by Kamehameha I, and continued in his post under Kamehameha I's son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kamehameha_II">Kamehameha II</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Boki and his wife <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kuini_Liliha">Kuini Liliha</ref> (1802—1839) were leading members of a delegation to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/England">England</ref> led by King Kamehameha II and Queen <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kamamalu">Kamamalu</ref> in 1824. After the monarchs died from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Measles">measles</ref> during the stay, Boki and his wife returned to Hawaii with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Byron,_7th_Baron_Byron">Admiral Lord Byron</ref> aboard the British frigate, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HMS_Blonde_(1819)">HMS<hi rend="italic">Blonde</hi></ref>, which bore the bodies of the late king and queen.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-blonde-4">[4]</ref> En route, the ship stopped at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brazil">Brazil</ref> and obtained several <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coffea_arabica">Arabica</ref> coffee trees, which Boki gave to ex-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/West_Indies">West Indies</ref> settler and agriculturalist John Wilkinson, to plant on the Chief's land in Oahu's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manoa">Mānoa Valley</ref>.  Wilkinson was never able to cultivate the strain for commercial production.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Kona_Coffee_History_A_Compelling_Hawaiian_Chronology-5">[5]</ref> He also transplanted South American native turkeys to Hawai'i and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rotuma">Rotuma</ref>, along with the Hawaiian transliteration of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portuguese_language">Portuguese</ref> name for turkey, <hi rend="italic">peru</hi> (<hi rend="italic">pelehu</hi> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hawaiian_language">Hawaiian</ref>, <hi rend="italic">perehu</hi> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rotuman_language">Rotuman</ref>).</p>
<p>Emboldened by the voyage, Boki sought to trade on the fame it gave him.  He moved a wood frame house inland and opened a store and inn called the Blonde Hotel. He became unpopular with local missionaries because he sold liquor there. He stocked his bar with cheap but bad wine, saying it was good enough for visiting sailors. Like his other business ventures, it was not profitable to himself, but perhaps was to his employees. One of them claimed the building in the 1830s, calling it the "Boki House".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<head>Catholicism</head>
<p>Boki agreed to the breaking of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kapu">kapu</ref> (the ancient system of strict rules) in 1819 and accepted the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protestant">Protestant</ref> missionaries arriving in 1820. He had been <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baptism">baptized</ref> as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catholic">Catholic</ref>, along with his brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kalanimoku">Kalanimoku</ref>, the previous year aboard the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_France#France_in_modern_times_I">French</ref> vessel of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_de_Freycinet">Louis de Freycinet</ref>. Although he was one of the first chiefs to be baptized, when he married Liliha, he refused to marry her in church and, despite his conversion, was known to enjoy partaking of "sinful" and "immoral" treats, such as drinking <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Okolehao">okolehao</ref> (liquor made from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cordyline_fruticosa">ti</ref> root).</p>
<p>Queen regent Kaʻahumanu had become influenced by the Protestant missionaries in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Honolulu">Honolulu</ref> and was baptized into the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Congregational_church">Congregational church</ref>.  Heeding the advice of her Congregationalist ministers, Kaʻahumanu influenced King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kamehameha_III">Kamehameha III</ref> to ban the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_Catholic_Church">Roman Catholic Church</ref> from the islands. Boki and Liliha were a constant threat to Kaʻahumanu and her hold on the boy-king and when she learned that they were among the first chiefs to convert to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_Catholic_Diocese_of_Honolulu">Hawaii Catholic Church</ref> it angered her, since she wanted all the chiefs to accept Protestantism, an example she hoped all Hawaiians would follow. Torn in conflicting directions, the young king under the influence of Boki turned to alcohol in what was portrayed as a clear rejection of the either Christian standards of morality.</p>
<head>Sandalwood</head>
<p>After restrictions on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sandalwood">sandalwood</ref> trading placed by Kamehameha I lapsed, Boki immersed himself in the business. He grew rich, like many other chiefs, but the chiefs' lack of understanding of financial concepts caused him to become deeply indebted by 1829. When word reached him that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Hebrides">New Hebrides</ref>, a faraway group of South Pacific islands, was heavily forested in sandalwood, he pulled together a fleet of two ships and set sail. It is known that he reached Rotuma in 1827 and also called at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Erromango">Erromango</ref>.  However, when he failed to return to Hawaii it was assumed that he had perished at sea.</p>
<p>Despite the Hawaiian belief that he died during his sandalwood expedition, there is evidence that Boki was alive and well in Samoa in the year 1830. According to Marques' 1893 report, Boki's ship was wrecked in 1830 near Iva on the Samoan island of Savaiʻi where he rallied under the banner of the ambitious Samoan chief, Malietoa Vaiinupo. The Hawaiian embassy delegation sent to Samoa by King Kalakaua in 1886 learned that the two Prussian cannons from Boki's ships were indeed still to be found in Iva village along with "many of his descendants".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>Before departing, Boki entrusted administration of Oahu to his wife and, subsequently, widow, Liliha who was made chiefess of Waiʻanae and governor of Oʻahu, until she tried to overthrow Kaʻahumanu. Her father <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hoapili">Hoapili</ref> talked her out of it at the last minute, but she was, nevertheless, relieved of her duties. After Kaʻahumanu died in 1832, Liliha was described as no longer observant of the missionary rules.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-makaha-8">[8]</ref></p>
</text>
