<text id="autogum_news_doc341" title="Four killed, dozens injured in southern Thailand bombings" shortTile="four-killed-dozens" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-05-28" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Four_killed%2C_dozens_injured_in_southern_Thailand_bombings" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Four killed, dozens injured in southern Thailand bombings</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, May 28, 2007</hi></p>
<p>Four people were killed and about two dozen injured in a bombing at a crowded market in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amphoe%20Saba%20Yoi">Saba Yoi</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Songkhla%20Province">Songkhla Province</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Thailand">Thailand</ref>.</p>
<p>The day before, a series of bombings in Songkhla's main city <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hat%20Yai">Hat Yai</ref> injured 13 people. Police are investigating those attacks, which occurred at around 9 p.m. (1400 GMT) on Sunday, when seven coordinated explosions went off at stores, hotels and restaurants in a city that is popular with tourists.</p>
<p>In Monday's bombing, the dead were two women and two girls, ages 4 and 8. The bomb, which exploded shortly after 4 p.m. local time (0900 GMT), was hidden in a motorcycle parked in front of the market next to a railway station.</p>
<p>Authorities have not concluded if the blasts are linked to the ongoing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South%20Thailand%20insurgency">insurgency</ref> by Muslim separatists in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Southern%20Thailand">southern Thailand</ref>. The past year has seen an escalation of violence, with almost daily fatal shootings of civilians and frequent ambush attacks on soldiers. Since early 2004, more than 2,200 people have been killed, mainly in the southernmost provinces of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yala%20Province">Yala</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pattani%20Province">Pattani</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Narathiwat">Narathiwat</ref>. Thailand is predominantly a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buddhist">Buddhist</ref> country, but in those three provinces, the majority of residents are <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Islam">Islamic</ref>.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Council%20for%20National%20Security">Council for National Security</ref> chairman General <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sonthi%20Boonayaratkalin">Sonthi Boonayaratkalin</ref> said he believed Sunday night's bombings were only meant to cause a disturbance. Other officials compared the Hat Yai blasts to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2006%20Bangkok%20bombings">Bangkok New Year's Eve bombings</ref>, which they say were caused to create political tensions, though in those blasts, three people were killed.</p>
<p>Business analysts believe Sunday night's bombings will hurt Hat Yai's tourist trade, which has been struggling since a spate of bombings in 2005, including one that killed two people at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hat%20Yai%20International%20Airport">Hat Yai International Airport</ref>, as well as blasts in a department store and hotel, with about 70 people wounded. In September 2006, four people were killed in a series of bombings in Hat Yai.</p>
<p>The latest bombings come at a tense time for Thailand. In the nation's capital, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bangkok">Bangkok</ref>, security forces are on alert ahead of a court ruling expected on Wednesday that could lead to the dissolution of the former ruling <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thai%20Rak%20Thai">Thai Rak Thai</ref> party and the main opposition <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Democrat%20Party%20(Thailand)">Democrat Party</ref>. Since a military-led <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2006%20Thai%20coup%20d'état">coup d'état</ref> last year, in which prime minister and Thai Rak Thai leader <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thaksin%20Shinawatra">Thaksin Shinawatra</ref> was ousted, all political activity has been banned by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Council%20for%20National%20Security">junta</ref>.</p>
<p>Last week, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chakri%20Dynasty">King</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bhumibol%20Adulyadej">Bhumibol Adulyadej</ref> made a rare televised address as he granted an audience to the administrative court judges. He urged them to use care in their verdict. "You have the responsibility to prevent the country from collapsing," he told them.</p>
<p>Authorities believe supporters of the political parties may cause trouble if they are displeased with the verdict.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, the nation's constitution is being rewritten, and Buddhists are demanding that <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Demonstrators_demand_Buddhism_be_made_Thai_national_religion">Buddhism be made the national religion</ref>, a move that experts believe will lead to an even bigger increase in violence in Muslim-dominated southern Thailand.</p>
This story has updates
See <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bomb_tossed_at_southern_Thailand_hotel;_victim_of_Sunday_blast_dies">Bomb tossed at southern Thailand hotel; victim of Sunday blast dies</ref>
</text>
