<text id="autogum_voyage_doc199" title="East Coulee" shortTile="east-coulee" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=10343" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>East Coulee</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">East Coulee</hi> is a small community in the <ref target="Alberta%20Badlands">Alberta Badlands</ref> region of <ref target="Alberta">Alberta</ref>, <ref target="Canada">Canada</ref>, near the community of Cambria. It is part of the Town of <ref target="Drumheller">Drumheller</ref>, which is a hub for dinosaur tourism.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>East Coulee is known for its <hi rend="bold">Atlas Coal Mine</hi>. East Coulee lies in the Red Deer River valley at an elevation of 675 m (2,215 ft). It was one of the filming locations of the television series <hi rend="italic">MythQuest</hi>.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>East Coulee is on Highway 10, approximately 20 km (12 mi) southeast of Drumheller's main townsite and 112 km (70 mi) northeast of Calgary.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Atlas Coal Mine National Historic Site</hi>, 110 Century Drive (20 minutes SE of Drumheller along Highway 10), ☏ +1 403-822-2220 . May 1–Jun 22: 9:30AM-5PM; Jun 23–Aug 26: 9:45AM-7:30PM; Aug 27–Oct 8: 9:30AM-5PM. Climb the last wooden tipple in Canada. Learn how coal was sorted, stored, and shipped in this unique processing plant. Walk the gantry – a gradual ascent - 125 feet up to the top of the Tipple to learn about the reality young boys faced: that the dangers of the surface were a training ground for the formidable "belly of the beast. Follow in the historic footsteps of the miners. Put on a cap lamp and hike up the inclined conveyer tunnel to the mine entry, set high in the Badlands. Explore the dark side of coal mining – learn about accidents, brawls, the women, and the unmentionable side of Drumheller Valley history. $10 per person, $30 family.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">East Coulee School Museum</hi>, 359 2nd Ave (from Hwy 10, go past the old garage and the East Coulee Motor Inn; turn right at the second intersection, at the Community Hall; museum is dead ahead), ☏ +1 403-822-3970 , fax: +1 403 822-2111 , ✉ info@ecsmuseum.com . May-Sept: daily 10AM-5PM; Oct-Apr: private bookings only. Displays of life during the coal-mining era. $7.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Willow Creek Hoodoo Interpretive Trail</hi> (take Highway 10 southeast 16km from Drumheller, look for sign marking turnoff, drive 1 km NE to parking area). Hoodoos are a characteristic rock formation of the badlands. Looking like 2m tall mushrooms, they were formed when a cap of more resistant rock protected the softer rock underneath from erosion. Hoodoos can be found in other parts of the region, but this trail makes a few of them easy to visit. A picture there shows that, sadly, there are fewer hoodoos now than even a few decades ago, as erosion and tourist curiosity take their toll. The trail is under 1 km and an easy scramble across rocks. Parking area includes covered picnic tables and chemical toilets. There is also a <hi rend="bold">Hoodoo Trail</hi> drive through the area, along Route 10.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>
<p>The <ref target="East%20Coulee%23See">School Museum</ref> has a cafe/lunch room, but otherwise, either go to Drumheller to get a meal or bring your own food beforehand.</p>

<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">East Coulee Guest House</hi>, 110 2 Avenue, ☏ +1 403-823-0737 . Continental breakfast. Featuring barbecue facilities, a garden, a terrace and a shared lounge. Free WiFi and private parking. All rooms have a shared bathroom. Doubles $69.</item>
</list>


<head>Go next</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Drumheller">Drumheller</ref></item>
</list>
</text>
