<text id="autogum_bio_doc078" title="Martyrs of Nowogródek" shortTile="martyrs-nowogrodek" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-27" dateModified="2019-08-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martyrs_of_Nowogr%C3%B3dek" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Martyrs of Nowogródek</head>
<p>The <hi rend="bold">Martyrs of Nowogródek</hi>, also known as the <hi rend="bold">Blessed Martyrs of Nowogródek</hi> and the Eleven Nuns of Nowogródek or Blessed Mary Stella and her Ten Companions were a group of members of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sisters_of_the_Holy_Family_of_Nazareth">Sisters of the Holy Family of Nazareth</ref>, a Polish <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_Catholic_Church">Roman Catholic</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Religious_congregation">religious congregation</ref>, executed by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gestapo">Gestapo</ref> in August 1943 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Occupied_Poland">occupied Poland</ref> (present-day <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Navahrudak">Navahrudak</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Belarus">Belarus</ref>). They have been declared <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beatification">Blessed</ref> by virtue of martyrdom by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_John_Paul_II">Pope John Paul II</ref> on 5 March 2000.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-stella-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Background</head>
<p>The Sisters of the Holy Family of Nazareth had arrived in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nowogródek">Nowogródek</ref>, then part of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second_Polish_Republic">Second Polish Republic</ref>, in 1929 at the request of Zygmunt Łoziński, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_(Catholic_Church)">Bishop</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_Catholic_Diocese_of_Pinsk">Roman Catholic Diocese of Pinsk</ref>. The Sisters became an integral part of the life of the town. In 1939, Nowogrodek, located in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/West_Belarus">West Belarus</ref> (then Poland), was annexed by the Soviet Union and incorporated into the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Belarusian_Soviet_Socialist_Republic">Belarusian Soviet Socialist Republic</ref>. In 1941, the town was occupied by the German army as part of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operation_Barbarossa">Operation Barbarossa</ref>.</p>
<p>During the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_Poland_(1939–45)">Nazi and Soviet occupations of Nowogrodek</ref>, the Sisters invested great effort in preparing the residents of the town for religious services – as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liturgy">liturgical</ref> prayer became a beacon of hope amid the hopelessness of the occupation.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-stella-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>The Nazi terror in Nowogródek began in 1942 with the extermination of the town's Jewish population as part of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operation_Reinhard">Operation Reinhard</ref>. Of the 20,000 inhabitants of the town before the war, approximately half were Jews. The Germans murdered about 9,500 of the Jews in a series of "actions" and sent the remaining 550 Jews to slave labor camps. This was followed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nazi_crimes_against_ethnic_Poles">a surge in Polish arrests</ref>, then the slaughter of 60 people, including two <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catholic_priest">Catholic priests</ref>. This situation was repeated on 18 July 1943, when more than 120 people were arrested and slated for execution.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-stella-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>The women of the town turned to the Sisters to pray for the prisoners’ release. After discussing the matter, the Sisters unanimously expressed their desire to offer their lives in sacrifice for the prisoners. The Superior of the community, Sister Maria Stella, C.S.F.N., shared the Sisters' decision with their local <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pastor">pastor</ref>, Father Zienkiewicz, telling him: "My God, if sacrifice of life is needed, accept it from us and spare those who have families. We are even praying for this intention." Almost immediately, the plans for the prisoners were changed to deportation to work camps in Germany, with some of them even being released. When the life of Zienkiewicz was threatened, the Sisters renewed their offer, saying, "There is a greater need for a priest on this earth than for us. We pray that God will take us in his place, if sacrifice of life is needed."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-stella-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Execution</head>
<p>Without warning or provocation, on 31 July 1943, the community was summoned by the local Gestapo commander to report to the local police station, where they were held overnight. The next morning, 1 August 1943, they were loaded into a van and driven beyond the town limits.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11nuns-3">[3]</ref> At a secluded spot in the woods about 3 miles from the town, the eleven women were machine gunned to death and buried in a common grave. Before reporting to the police station, Sister Stella had asked one member of the community, Sister M. Malgorzata Banas, C.S.F.N., who worked as a nurse in the local public hospital, to stay behind at the convent, whatever happened, to take care of the church and their pastor. She was the best candidate for that among the community as she wore civilian clothing due to her job. It was days before she and the townspeople knew that the Sisters had been killed. Eventually, Banas located their grave, quietly tending to it and the parish church during the war years and during the post-war Soviet occupation, until her death in 1966.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-stella-2">[2]</ref>  The Church of the Transfiguration, known as <hi rend="italic">Biała Fara</hi> (or White Church), now contains the remains of the eleven Sisters.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-stella-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Martyrs</head>
<p>The eleven murdered Sisters are listed below, along with their birth names, dates of birth, and ages at the time of their deaths.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-stella-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11nuns-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Veneration</head>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beatification">beatification</ref> process for the eleven Religious Sisters was officially opened on 18 September 1991, and, on 28 June 1999, it was announced by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Congregation_for_the_Causes_of_Saints">Congregation for the Causes of Saints</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holy_See">Holy See</ref> that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_John_Paul_II">Pope John Paul II</ref> had confirmed that they were <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martyr">martyrs</ref>, having died for others in the name of the Catholic faith. Pope John Paul formally <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beatification">beatified</ref> them, along with a group of thirty-three others, on 5 March 2000.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11nuns-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
</text>
