<text id="autogum_interview_doc593" title="part6_Wikinews interviews Australian Paralympic skiers Jessica Gallagher and Eric Bickerton" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-12-10" dateModified="2017-10-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_Paralympic_skiers_Jessica_Gallagher_and_Eric_Bickerton" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  But if you're not getting paid to be a sponsor for all that is awesome in Australia, what do you do outside of skiing, and the long jump, and the javelin?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Gallagher:</hi> I'm an osteopath. So I finished my masters' degree in 2009. I was completing a bachelor's and a masters. I was working for the Victorian Institute of Sport guiding program but with the commitment to London having so much travel I actually just put everything on hold in terms of my osteo career. There's not really enough time. And then the ambassador role, I had a few commitments with that, and I did motivational speaking.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  That's very cool. Eric, I've read that you work as a guide in back country skiing, and all sorts of crazy stuff like that. What do you do when you're not leading Jessica Gallagher down a ski slope?</p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Eric Bickerton:</hi> I'm the Chief Executive of Disabled Winter Sports Australia. So we look after all the disability winter sports, except for the Paralympics.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Gallagher:</hi> Social, recreational...</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  You like that? You find it fulfilling?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Eric Bickerton:</hi> The skiing aspect's good. I dunno about the corporate stuff. I could give that a miss. But I think it is quite fulfilling. Yeah, they're a very good group of people there who enjoy themselves, both in disabilities and able bodied. We really need guides and support staff.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Has it changed over the last few years?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Eric Bickerton:</hi> For us?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Being a guide in general? How things have changed or improved, have you been given more recognition?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Eric Bickerton:</hi> No. I don't see myself as an athlete. Legally we are <hi rend="italic">the</hi> athlete. If I fail, she fails. We ski the exact same course. But there's some idiosyncrasies associated with it. Because I'm a male guiding, I have to ski on male skis, which are different to female skis, which means my turn shape I have to control differently so it's the same as her turn shape. It's a little bit silly. Whereas if I was a female guiding, I'd be on exactly the same skis, and we'd be able to ski exactly the same all the way through. In that context I think the fact that Jess won the medal opened the eyes to the APC about visual impairment as a definite medal contending aspect. The biggest impediment to the whole process is how the Hell do you get a guide who's (a) capable, (b) available and (c) able to fund himself. So we're fortunate that the APC pushed for the recognition of myself as an athlete, and because we have the medal from the previous Olympics, we're now tier one, so we get the government funding all way through. Without that two years before the last games, that cost me fifteen, sixteen months of my time, and $40,000 of cash to be the guide. So while I enjoyed it, and well I did, it is very very hard to say that a guide could make a career out of being a guide. There needs to be a little bit more consideration of that, a bit like the IPC saying no you're not a medal winner. It's quite a silly situation where it's written into the rules that you are both the athlete and yet at the same time you're not a medal winner. I think there's evolution. It's growing. It's changing. It's very, very difficult.</p>
</text>
