<text id="autogum_interview_doc061" title="part1_Biologist Nick Bos tells Wikinews about &amp;apos;self-medicating&amp;apos; ants" shortTile="partbiologist-nick" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-09-01" dateModified="2015-10-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Biologist_Nick_Bos_tells_Wikinews_about_%27self-medicating%27_ants" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>We infected the ants by preparing a solution of the fungus <hi rend="italic">Beauveria bassiana</hi>. Afterwards, each ant was dipped in the solution for a couple  of seconds, dried on a cloth and put in the nest. After exposing the  ants to the fungus, we took pictures of each foraging arena three times per day, and counted how many ants were present on each food-source.</p>
<figure><caption>Example of aerated concrete, which provided a home for the subjects.Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Marco%20Bernardini">Marco Bernardini</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>This gave us the data that ants choose more medicine after they have  been infected.</p>
<p>The result that healthy ants die sooner when ingesting ROS [<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reactive%20oxygen%20species">Reactive Oxygen Species</ref>, the group of chemicals that includes hydrogen peroxide] but infected ants die less was obtained in another way (as you have to 'force feed' the ROS, as healthy ants, when given the choice, ignore  that food-source.)</p>
<p>For this we basically put colonies on a diet of either food with medicine or without for a while. And afterwards either infected them  or not. Then for about two weeks we count every day how many ants  died. This gives us the data to do a so-called survival analysis.</p>
<p>We measured the ROS-concentration in the bodies of ants after they ingested the food with the medicine using a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/spectrophotometry%20">spectrophotometer</ref>. By  adding certain chemicals, the ROS can be measured using the emission of light of a certain wave-length.</p>
<p>The detrimental effect of ROS on spores was easy to measure. We mixed  different concentrations of ROS with the spores, plated them out on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/petri%20dishes">petridishes</ref> with an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/agar%20plate">agar-solution</ref> where fungus can grow on. A day after, we counted how many spores were still alive.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reliability%20(psychometrics)">reliable</ref> do you consider your results to be?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NB</hi> The results we got are very reliable. We had a lot of colonies containing a lot of ants, and wherever possible we conducted the experiment blind. This means the experimenter doesn't know which ants belong to which treatment, so it's impossible to influence the results  with '<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Observer-expectancy%20effect">observer bias</ref>'. However, of course this is proof in just one  species. It is hard to extrapolate to other ants, as different species  lead very different lives.</p>
<hi rend="bold">At the moment it seems that sick ants mostly take care of the problem themselves</hi>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Where did the ants and fungus you used come from? How common are they in the wild?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NB</hi> For ants, see above about the collection.</p>
<p>This species of fungus does appear in Finland, but we chose to use a  different strain from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Denmark">Denmark</ref> (with thanks to Prof. J. Eilenberg and  the laboratory technician Louise Lee Munch Larsen from the University  of Copenhagen). Animals can adapt to local strains ('local  adaptation'), and just to make sure we thought it would be good to use  a strain of fungus that the ants definitely did not evolve specific resistances against. This means that the reaction of the ants (to self-medicate) is very likely to be a general response, and not just  against their local fungal enemies.</p>
</text>
