<text id="autogum_bio_doc527" title="Rodrigo de Bastidas" shortTile="rodrigo-de-bastidas" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-02-07" dateModified="2019-07-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rodrigo_de_Bastidas" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Rodrigo de Bastidas</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Rodrigo de Bastidas</hi> (Spanish pronunciation:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Help:IPA/Spanish">[roˈðɾiɣo ðe βasˈtiðas]</ref>; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Triana,_Seville">Triana, Seville</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andalusia">Andalusia</ref>, c. 1465<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> – <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santiago_de_Cuba">Santiago de Cuba</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cuba">Cuba</ref>, 28 July 1527) was a Spanish <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conquistador">conquistador</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_explorers">explorer</ref> who mapped the northern coast of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South_America">South America</ref>, discovered <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Panama">Panama</ref>, and founded the city of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santa_Marta">Santa Marta</ref>.</p>
<head>Personal life</head>
<p>Rodrigo de Bastidas was a well-to-do notary from the town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Triana,_Seville">Triana, Seville</ref>, a suburb of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seville">Seville</ref>. He was born around 1465 and his father was named Rodrigo de la Bastidas y Ruiz. Rodrigo de Bastidas married Isabel Rodríguez de Romera Tamaris and the couple had eight children; Juan, Gonzalo, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rodrigo_de_Bastidas_y_Rodriguez_de_Romera">Rodrigo de Bastidas y Rodriguez de Romera</ref>, Teresa de Bastidas, Cristobal de Sanabria, Gaspar de Villadiego, Sebastian, and Isabel de Bastidas.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-GeniBastidas-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Exploration</head>
<p>After sailing with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Columbus">Christopher Columbus</ref> during his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Voyages_of_Columbus">second voyage</ref> to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_World">New World</ref> in 1493, De Bastidas petitioned the Spanish Crown to start his own quest to be financed totally with his own money. In exchange for granting De Bastidas the right to explore various territories in the New World, the Crown required him to give them one fourth of the net profits he would acquire. The King and Queen issued a charter that is still preserved in the National Archives in Spain. He sailed to the New World from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cádiz,_Spain">Cádiz</ref> in October? 1500 with two ships; the <hi rend="italic">San Antón</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Santa Maria de Gracia</hi>. He was accompanied on this voyage by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juan_de_la_Cosa">Juan de la Cosa</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vasco_Núñez_de_Balboa">Vasco Núñez de Balboa</ref>.</p>
<p>At the South American coast he sailed westward from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cabo_de_la_Vela">Cabo de la Vela</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colombia">Colombia</ref>, in an attempt to explore the coastline of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caribbean_sea">Caribbean basin</ref>. He discovered the mouth of a river he named the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magdalena_River">Magdalena River</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gulf_of_Urabá">Gulf of Urabá</ref> on the Colombian coast. He reached <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/La_Punta_de_Manzanillo">La Punta de Manzanillo</ref> on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Panama">Panama</ref>'s upper Caribbean coast before having to abandon his effort. He is acknowledged to be the first European to have claimed that part of the isthmus, and therefore is credited with the discovery of Panama which includes the San Blas region of the indigenous <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kuna_people">Kuna</ref>. However, the poor condition of his ships, caused by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shipworm">shipworm</ref> that ate the wooden hull, forced him to turn back and head to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santo_Domingo">Santo Domingo</ref> to effect repairs. Despite repeated repairs, the ships eventually sank in port at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacaragua">Jacaragua</ref>, leaving most of the indigenous slaves to drown, while some gold and pearls were saved. De Bastidas was forced to return overland to Santo Domingo, trading trinkets for food and supplies with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taino_people">Taino</ref> natives along the way. On arrival in Santo Domingo he was placed under arrest by Governor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francisco_de_Bobadilla">Francisco de Bobadilla</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-BancoBastidas-3">[3]</ref> and sent back to Spain for allegedly trading with the indigenous people without permission. He was acquitted of these charges by the Spanish Crown, and rewarded with a pension. He returned to Santo Domingo with his family, and became "rich in cattle, at one time possessing 8000 head".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Anderson-4">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Floyd-5">[5]</ref> In 1504 he undertook another expedition to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Province_of_Tierra_Firme">Tierra Firme</ref>, raiding 600 slaves for sale in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hispaniola">Hispaniola</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Anderson-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Foundation of Santa Marta</head>
<p>In 1520 the governorship of Trinidad was granted to De Bastidas, but this was opposed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diego_Columbus">Diego Columbus</ref>, and De Bastidas waived the grant. He received instead permission to exploit a region from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cabo_de_la_Vela">Cabo de la Vela</ref> westward to the Magdalena River; however this expedition was delayed for several years.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Anderson-4">[4]</ref> In 1524 he returned to the New World and accompanied by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juan_de_Céspedes_Ruiz">Juan de Céspedes</ref> founded the city of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santa_Marta">Santa Marta</ref> on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caribbean_sea">Caribbean</ref> coast of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colombia">Colombia</ref>. He named the city Santa Marta because it was on Saint Martha's feast day (July 29th) that the city was founded.</p>
<p>De Bastidas has been called Spain's <hi rend="italic">Noblest Conquistador</hi> because he had a policy of respect, humanity and friendship towards the native people; he maintained pacifistic relations with his neighbors, the native <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taganga_people">Taganga</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dorsino_people">Dorsino</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gaira_people">Gaira</ref>, although it is said he had slaves too. The following quote related to the founding of Santa Marta does not support this appellation:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>I assure you that with the help of God I will enter powerfully against you, and I will make war on you in every place and in every way that I can, and I will subject you to the yoke and obedience of the church and their highnesses, and I will take your persons and your women and your children, and I will make them slaves, and as such I will sell them, and dispose of them as their highnesses command: I will take your goods, and I will do you all the evils and harms which I can, just as to vassals who do not obey and do not want to receive their lord, resist him and contradict him. And I declare that the deaths and harms which arise from this will be your fault, and not that of their highnesses, nor mine, nor of the gentlemen who have come with me here.</p>
<p>On a trip to the interior and the territories of Bonda and Bondigua in present-day Colombia, he traded a substantial amount of gold. De Bastidas had a policy prohibiting his troops from brutally using the indigenous people or robbing them of their goods. His troops, many of whom had gone adventuring in the hopes of obtaining gold, asked De Bastidas for a share. He refused to share it with his men, saying that he needed it to help defray the costs of the colony.</p>
<head>Death</head>
<figure><caption>Monument to Rodrigo de BastidasCathedral of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santa_Marta">Santa Marta</ref></caption></figure>
<p>De Bastidas' refusal to share the gold that he had acquired greatly angered some of his men, among them his lieutenant Villafuerte,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Andagoya-7">[7]</ref> who led a conspiracy of some fifty men to murder De Bastidas. One night, while Bastidas was asleep, he was attacked and stabbed five times. He was able to cry out, and his men rushed to his aid. Although seriously wounded, he did not die immediately.</p>
<p>Owing to a lack of adequate medical facilities in Santa Marta, Bastidas attempted to sail to Santo Domingo, but bad weather forced him to land in Cuba, where he died from his injuries. Later, his only son, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishop">Archbishop</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rodrigo_de_Bastidas_y_Rodriguez_de_Romera">Rodrigo de Bastidas y Rodriguez de Romera</ref>, moved his remains to Santo Domingo where he is interred along with his wife and son at The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cathedral_of_Santa_María_la_Menor">Cathedral of Santa María la Menor</ref> in the Colonial Zone of Santo Domingo, the oldest cathedral in the Americas.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Anderson-4">[4]</ref></p>
</text>
