<text id="autogum_whow_doc566" title="Hold a Dog and Tickle Its Toes" shortTile="hold-dog-tickle-toes" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-06-23" dateModified="2018-06-23" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Hold-a-Dog-and-Tickle-Its-Toes" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Hold a Dog and Tickle Its Toes</head><p>When owning a pupper and having the urge to tickle it, you want to do it properly so that your doggo doesn't give you strange looks or misunderstand your intentions. If your doge isn't ready for this kind of intimacy you might consider talking about it with them or waiting until your relationship is ready for it.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Lappy tappy</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>To do the Lappy Tappy, you must first get the doggo into your lap. If your dog is smaller this step is easier to do because you can usually just pick it up. However, If your dog is bigger you might have to lure your dog. Here are some ways to get the dog into position:
<list type="unordered"><item>Treats! Find treats that your dog enjoys and tempt them by teasing or leaving a trail to your lap.</item>
<item>Words of endearment. Your dog probably loves you, but if they don't you might try just using a tone of voice that is non-threatening and saying something like, "Here puppy." Or "Come here precious."</item>
<item>If all else fails you might just have to grab the doggo and carry it to the designated spot. Be careful when doing this because some doggies do not like to be picked up or manhandled.</item></list></item></list>
<list type="ordered"><item>Getting into position.Getting the pupper into position is the harder part. You need the doge to be on it's back if possible to give you access to the little foot fingers that you wish to tickle.
<list type="unordered"><item>Try belly rubs. Belly rubs are a good way to get the dog to roll over in your lap. If your dog is too big for that you might want to try tickling its toes while it's in sitting position.</item>
<item>Pats. Patting your dog starting at the chest might encourage your doggo to relax or lay down. If your dog lays down, it might be the perfect time to tickle.</item>
<item>Head pets. Head pets may relax the pupper and again make it easier to get the dog more comfortable with the idea of tickles on the feets.</item></list></item></list>
<list type="ordered"><item>Tickles! Once your dog is in position, you can begin the procedure. Make sure your dogger is relaxed and isn't trying to escape you. You don't want the pupper in question to misunderstand or feel concerned when you tickle its toes.</item></list>
<head>Hyped strike</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>If your pupper is a hyper one, you might try the Hyped strike method. To begin you must get your doggo excited.
<list type="unordered"><item>Grab a toy and tease your doge. Some pups only require toys to get them excited. Make sure you playfully tease them and wink a lot.</item>
<item>Ask if your dog would like an adventure. Teasing your doggo with an adventure such as going outside can quickly make any lethargic doge into a hyped one.</item>
<item>Try running around. If your house is large enough you might try running around and chasing your pupper until he/she is excited enough for the tickles.</item></list></item></list>
<list type="ordered"><item>Talk to them! Once your dog is excited and running around you should start calling their name and then running away just to be sure your dog is ready to come for tickles.</item></list>
<list type="ordered"><item>Tickles! Now you have to catch your excited dog. Chase them around until you manage to catch them. Once you have the dog in your possession you can grab the foots and tickle the toes.</item></list>
<head>Romantic rubs</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Every pupper loves to be pet or scratched in certain places. For a more relaxed toe tickle, you might just try messaging the paws. This may also get your doggo accustomed to the feeling of their paws being touched before you proceed to tickle.</item>
<item>Tickle 'zem. Now that your puppo has gotten a desirable message you can proceed to tickle the toes.</item></list>
<head>Tickling the foot fingers</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>If you are unsure of how to properly tickle a doggos toeses, then you need to learn. You don't want your dog to think of you as a weirdo or some kind of creep.</item></list>
<list type="ordered"><item><list type="unordered"><item>Take the paws in hand. Make sure you have the paw in position by holding it in the palm of your hand.</item></list></item>
<item>Begin to rub in a vertical fashion. Move the designated tickle finger up and down on your pup's paw.</item></list>
<list type="ordered"><item>Rotate. Now you may begin moving your finger(s) around the entire bottom of the paw. You can go between the toes and even poke at the dog's toenails. Make sure your dog is comfortable with the situation. If your pup is giving you strange looks you might want to stop.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Build trust with the dog by asking it personal questions and getting to know it's preferences.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure your doggo, pupper, or doge is comfortable in the situation.</item></list>
</text>
