<text id="autogum_reddit_doc009" title="As best you can, explain the dynamic between your school/team and the rest of the schools in your conference" shortTile="best--explain-dynamic" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-05-31" dateModified="2018-05-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8nj69z" speakerList="#goblue10, #wordsonascreen" speakerCount="2">
<head>As best you can, explain the dynamic between your school/team and the rest of the schools in your conference</head>
<sp who="#goblue10">
<p>#How does each school feel about you? How do you feel about them? Any history that a casual fan wouldn't know? For instance, here's Michigan:  <hi rend="bold">Ohio State</hi> : Pure straight hatred, with a sort of cold war dehumanization vibe. This is due to the fact that most UM/OSU fans don't know very many fans on the other side of the rivalry (unless you're from Toledo). It goes beyond the schools; the states of Michigan and Ohio just don't like each other (stemming from a border dispute over Toledo, of all places).  <hi rend="bold">Michigan State</hi> : It's really a sibling rivalry. Michigan considers MSU "the little brother" with an inferiority complex, while they consider us snobbish, self-righteous pricks. There's... some truth to both sides. The series has been historically dominated by Michigan, but the past decade has been MSU heavy. Also, while The Game is king in football, MSU is our primary rival in most other sports.  <hi rend="bold">Edit: As some have pointed out, while we hate Ohio State more, there's somehow more mutual respect there. There's no mutual respect between Michigan and Michigan State. None.</hi>   <hi rend="bold">Penn State</hi> : They joined the B1G in the early 90s, and Lloyd Carr  <hi rend="bold">dominated</hi>  JoePa. Since then, it's been a lot more even, with the teams trading blowout victories over the past two years. While Michigan fans used to respect PSU/JoePa a ton, a lot of that went away with, well... you know. Now there's a lot of Michigan fans who lump all PSU fans in with the Joe Believers.  <hi rend="bold">Wisconsin</hi> : Most Michigan fans... like Wisconsin? I think? Historically, Michigan has dominated the series (50-15-1 all time), but the games have been very competitive recently. After like 5 years off the schedule, we play every year from 2016 until like 2022.  <hi rend="bold">Northwestern</hi> : Respect for Pat Fitzgerald, and my God there have been some bullshit wins for Michigan recently (2012, 2013, and 2014). Ryan Field is fun to go to, and it's >60% Michigan fans there every time I've been.  <hi rend="bold">Maryland</hi> : I feel nothing about Maryland. DJ Durkin used to be a coach here? So that's cool?  <hi rend="bold">Rutgers</hi> : Most Michigan fans have an open disdain for Rutgers being in the B1G (they have no conference titles or conference tournament titles in  <hi rend="bold">any</hi>  sport in their 4 years here). Most Rutgers fans hate Michigan because we beat them 78-0 one year and steal all their NJ recruits.  <hi rend="bold">Indiana</hi> : Under Kevin Wilson they were C H A O S T E A M. Under Tom Allen they'll probably be more boring. IU hasn't beaten Michigan since the 1980's, so other than desire to keep that streak alive we don't really have any animosity towards them.  <hi rend="bold">Purdue</hi> : Michigan fans generally like Purdue, especially since they occasionally rise up out of nowhere and beat Ohio State (something we're still working on).  <hi rend="bold">Iowa</hi> : We love to make fun of Kirk Ferentz's contract. We don't love losing at Kinnick. Iowa is one of the few B1G teams with a winning record against Michigan since 2000.  <hi rend="bold">Illinois</hi> : Illinois straight hates us, because Bo ran up the score on them a couple of times for various reasons. We feel nothing towards them.  <hi rend="bold">Minnesota</hi> : We battle for The Little Brown Jug, the oldest traveling trophy in college football. Other than that, the relationship is pretty amicable on our end, although that may be because Michigan usually wins.  <hi rend="bold">Nebraska</hi> : Our relationship with Nebraska is predicated entirely upon arguing about the 1997 split title. That will only increase with Frost there (he was the QB on that 1997  <hi rend="bold">Coaches Poll Champion</hi>  Nebraska team). Some Michigan fans are annoyed with Frost already, since he talked about how his UCF team "outhit" Michigan after a 51-14 loss. Also, his mom wrote a snarky letter to the Michigan Daily back in the day? Or something? I don't know. **Feel free to do some schools in your conference, or all of them! Or none of them I guess. It's your life.**</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#wordsonascreen">
<p>For ASU: </p>
<list type="unordered">
<item></item>
<item>ARIZONA</item>
<item> - lots of hate between these schools. Big brother dynamic at play, with a superiority complex based on an out of date belief that their academics are somehow superior. It’s a geographical rilvalry as well. </item>
<item></item>
<item>EVERYONE ELSE</item>
<item> - can’t even remotely tell the difference between ASU and Arizona. Location, mascot, coaches, doesn’t matter, they’ll fuck it up.</item>
</list>
</sp>
</text>
