<text id="autogum_bio_doc417" title="Edward Phelips (speaker)" shortTile="edward-phelips-speaker" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-07-01" dateModified="2019-11-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Phelips_%28speaker%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Edward Phelips (speaker)</head>
<figure><caption>Sir Edward Phelips, by unknown artist</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>Arms of Phelips: <hi rend="italic">Argent, a chevron gules between three roses of the second seeded or barbed vert</hi></caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sir Edward Phelips</hi> (ca. 1555/1560–1614) was an English lawyer and politician, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Speaker_of_the_British_House_of_Commons">Speaker of the English House of Commons</ref> from 1604 until 1611, and subsequently <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Master_of_the_Rolls">Master of the Rolls</ref> from 1611 until his death in 1614. He was an elected <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Member_of_Parliament">MP</ref> from 1584, and in 1588, following a successful career as a lawyer, he commissioned <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Montacute_House">Montacute House</ref> to be built as a Summer house for himself and his family. He was knighted in 1603<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> and one of his major roles was as the opening prosecutor during the trial of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gunpowder_Plot">Gunpowder Plotters</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>He married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Margaret_Newdigate">Margaret Newdigate</ref>, and his son, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Phelips">Sir Robert Phelips</ref>, inherited his land and property.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>He was fourth and youngest son of Thomas Phelips (1500–1588) of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Montacute">Montacute</ref>, Somerset, by his wife Elizabeth (d. 1598), daughter of John Smythe of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Long_Ashton">Long Ashton</ref> in the same county. His father stood godfather to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Coryate">Thomas Coryate</ref>. Edward was born about 1560: according to Coryate, who refers to him as a patron, he was about 53 in 1613.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DNB-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>He joined the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Middle_Temple">Middle Temple</ref>, where he was autumn reader in 1596. In 1584 he entered parliament as MP for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bere_Alston_(UK_Parliament_constituency)">Bere Alston</ref>, followed by terms as MP for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Weymouth_and_Melcombe_Regis_(UK_Parliament_constituency)">Weymouth and Melcombe Regis</ref> in 1586, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penryn_(UK_Parliament_constituency)">Penryn</ref> in 1593 and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andover_(UK_Parliament_constituency)">Andover</ref> in 1597. In 1601 he was elected <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knight_of_the_shire">knight of the shire</ref> for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Somerset_(UK_Parliament_constituency)">Somerset</ref>. On 11 February 1603 he was named <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serjeant-at-law">serjeant-at-law</ref>, but Queen Elizabeth died, and he did not proceed to his degree until the following reign. On 17 May he was made king's serjeant and knighted. In November he took part in the trial of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sir_Walter_Raleigh">Sir Walter Raleigh</ref>. He was re-elected to parliament for Somerset on 11 February 1604, and on 19 March was elected speaker. According to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sir_Julius_Cæsar">Sir Julius Cæsar</ref>, he was the best speaker for some decades, and although long-winded, did expedite some business for the king.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DNB-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>On 17 July 1604 he was granted the office of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Justice_of_common_pleas">justice of common pleas</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/County_palatine_of_Lancaster">county palatine of Lancaster</ref>. In this capacity he was very active against Catholics; he is said to have declared that, as the law stood, all who were present when mass was celebrated were guilty of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Felony">felony</ref>. He was one of those appointed to examine the Gunpowder Plot conspirators, and in January 1606 opened the indictment against Guy Fawkes. He was also chancellor to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Frederick,_Prince_of_Wales">Henry Frederick, Prince of Wales</ref>. On 2 December 1608 he was granted the reversion of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mastership_of_the_rolls">mastership of the rolls</ref>, but did not succeed to the office until January 1611. On 14 July 1613 he was appointed ranger of all <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_forest">royal forests</ref>, parks, and chases in England.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DNB-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Besides his London house in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chancery_Lane">Chancery Lane</ref>, and another at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wanstead">Wanstead</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Essex">Essex</ref>, where he entertained the king, Phelips built a large mansion in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Somerset">Somerset</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Montacute_House">Montacute House</ref>, which is still standing, and in the possession of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Trust_for_Places_of_Historic_Interest_or_Natural_Beauty">the National Trust</ref>. He died on 11 September 1614, having married, firstly, Margaret (d. 28 April 1590), daughter of Robert Newdegate of Newdegate, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Surrey">Surrey</ref>, by whom he had two sons, Sir Robert and Francis; secondly, Elizabeth (d. 26 March 1638), daughter of Thomas Pigott of Doddershall House, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buckinghamshire">Buckinghamshire</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DNB-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Parliamentary convention</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>the 2d of April, 1604, rule. That a question being once made, and carried in the affirmative or negative, cannot be questioned again, but must stand as judgment of the House.</item><item>...</item><item>...</item><item>On the 1st of June, 1610, agreed for a rule. That no Bill of the same substance can be brought in the same session.</item></list>—<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Hatsell">John Hatsell</ref>, Rules of Proceeding, in <hi rend="italic">Precedents of proceedings in the House of Commons: with observations</hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref>
<p>It was under Phelips that the "1604 rule" was established: a parliamentary convention that "no motion can be put by the Government to the Commons twice in the same parliamentary session if the wording is exactly or substantially the same." The rule was invoked 12 times between 1604-1920; and was also invoked in 2019 in relation to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brexit_withdrawal_agreement">Brexit withdrawal agreement</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
</text>
