<text id="autogum_voyage_doc131" title="Dera Ghazi Khan" shortTile="dera-ghazi-khan" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=9343" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Dera Ghazi Khan</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Dera Ghazi Khan</hi> <hi rend="italic">abbreviated as D. G. Khan</hi>, is a city located in <ref target="Pakistan">Pakistan</ref>'s <ref target="Punjab%20%28Pakistan%29">Punjab province</ref>. It is a mid-country city located at the junction of all four provinces of Pakistan. The city also gives its name to the Dera Ghazi Khan Division, which consists of the Dera Ghazi Khan, Rajanpur, Muzaffargarh and Layyah districts. It is also the capital of Dera Ghazi Khan District</p>

<head>By plane</head>

<p>Dera Ghazi Khan International Airport is over 15 kilometres from the city. Pakistan's flag carrier PIA operates here directly from Karachi, Lahore, Islamabad, Quetta, Bahawalpur, Dubai and Jeddah. Shaheen Air and Air Indus also operate here from Karachi.</p>

<head>By train</head>

<p>Khushhal Khan Khattak Express, a daily express train service between Karachi and Peshawar briefly stop at Dera Ghazi Khan Cantt.</p>

<head>By road</head>

<p>The city is well connected with whole country by road. Daewoo, Faisal Movers, Baloch, Ghazi and Adil Shah are the buses which connect Dera Ghazi Khan to other major cities.</p>

<head>By auto-rickshaw</head>
<p>Auto-rickshaws / tuk-tuks are open rickshaws with (narrow) rear-facing seats, or with two seats facing forward and two backward. They are handy for moving around in the Inner City, since it's easier to see where you're going. Try to find a rickshaw with a well-padded seat, otherwise you will come out bruised and aching.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fort Munro</hi>, Quetta Road. A beautiful hill station, located at a height of 6,470 feet above sea level located around 80 kilometres west ward from Dera Ghazi Khan city, is a cool resort in summers for the people living in Southern part of Punjab. This hill station is part of the Sulaiman Mountain range, attracts many visitors for short stays during the season of summer to enjoy mild and pleasant weather for a day or two. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tomb of Hazrat Sakhi Sarwar</hi>, Village Muqam (35 kilometres from Dera Ghazi Khan city). Tomb of Hazrat Sakhi Sarwar Syed Ahmed Sultan, built in the 13th century is a unique building of Mughal architecture. Thousands of people from all over the Subcontinent come here on the Annual Celebrations of Birth of Sakhi Sarwar in March every year.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Dera Ghazi Khan Zoo</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tomb of ghazi khan</hi>.</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Rani Bazar</item>
<item> Sadar Bazar</item>
<item> Model Bazar</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> GOLGAPAY</item>
<item> PISHAWARI CHIPS(ALOO WALAY)</item>
<item> HALWA POOORI</item>
<item> MIRZA KAY SAMOOSAY</item>
<item> JALAYBIAN</item>
<item> PAKOORAY</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>
<p>COOL DRINK</p>

<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Shalimar Hotel</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ajwa Hotel</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pakeeza Hotel</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">indus Hotel</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Airport Hotel</hi></item>
</list>


<head>Connect</head>
<p>Many people speak Saraiki and some people speak Urdu</p>
</text>
