<text id="autogum_interview_doc604" title="part9_Wikinews interviews John Wolfe, Democratic Party presidential challenger to Barack Obama" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-05-19" dateModified="2013-09-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_John_Wolfe%2C_Democratic_Party_presidential_challenger_to_Barack_Obama" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">On your campaign website, you propose a reinstatement of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glass–Steagall%20Act">Glass–Steagall Act</ref> and creation of an alternative Federal Reserve.  These require cooperation with Congress. How can a president work with a hostile congress to accomplish these goals?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Wolfe</hi>: Well, we still have money left. The president has a lot of authority. He has an army and things like that. He has the federal reserve and things like he's been giving to European banks, distributed to other countries. We were told. We didn't find out about until I guess six or seven months ago just how broad the money was and the way the Federal Reserve chose to prioritize and things like that. So, why not give some of that to the community? If you're gonna give <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bank%20of%20America">Bank of America</ref> that uses this money to speculate an interest rate of one third of one percent, then why aren't these community banks down here working with people to do real things, why aren't they getting money instead? They should be.</p>
<p>
<p>| <hi rend="bold">I could sit here with a chart, put all this information up in probably 30 or 40 minutes in a national press conference and I guarantee you 70 percent of the people would approve of what I said, and we'd have a whole new discourse in this country</hi></p>
</p>
<p>And that's why I'm talking about there needs to be an alternative, when I say alternative federal reserve, a better way of putting would be the federal reserve needs to reform. That's the alternative that I would push for. Because we have a lot of people here that don't work. These small towns have really been hurt by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NAFTA">NAFTA</ref>. A lot of factories have closed. A lot of people don't have anything to do. A lot of people have turned to drugs. I mean you got a lot of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Methamphetamine">crystal meth</ref> problems in the school. I'm for enforcing the law and everything and the individual responsibility, however, we didn't have those sorts of problems at the scale we have now, when we had people in factories where people could work, and we had employment opportunities for those with just a high school education. Now we don't have so much of that anymore. The economy basically has changed. It's now financial. Forty percent of the profits in this country now are made by the financial sector. It used to be different. Factories used to make more. Service industries used to make more of the national profits. But now it's the finance. The finance doesn't require so many people to do it. That's why the finance is basically based on computer trade, automated means, so human beings are superfluous. Especially because its machines in factories and things that are so efficient. So a lot of things are run by robots.</p></p>
</text>
