<text id="autogum_whow_doc623" title="Experience Heaven on Earth" shortTile="experience-heaven" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-02-19" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Experience-Heaven-on-Earth" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Experience Heaven on Earth</head><p>Heaven can be a place on earth if you choose to see it. Life is heaven by perspective and by the way we choose to see the world. If our mental state of mind chooses a happy peaceful state we can maintain a wealthy mind. This can be done through many different methods. As cliché and corny as it might sound we can also experience heaven through our six different senses. But we must choose to use them wisely. We can also experience a glimpse of actual heaven through out extrasensory perception. Therefore by your choice heaven can be a state of mind in our material world and spiritual world.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Experience mindfulness and meditation classes. Go out and get into nature as much as possible.To embrace positivity we must also experience negativity.Embrace bad times and acknowledge bad days.Have an attitude of gratitude.Love every quirk about yourself!</item>
<item>Explore your six senses. Every sense we have has an impact on all our personal daily experiences. Make sure you hear positive music and films. Speak as many positive words as possible and make sure believe in the good in all situations. Make sure you eat fantastic healthy food that makes you feel energetic and alive. If your limited and can't afford certain food enjoy every bite and enjoy the taste. Remain in the present moment and pay your full attention to the food your eating.Whatever you smell around you could bring pleasant or unpleasant feelings. The best part of being in heaven is being unaffected! Or leaving the area with the bad smell as we normally would anyway. The less reactive we become the more calm and peaceful we feel.What we see is our world around us. Good and bad experiences can occur on a daily basis. We never have only good experiences but if we choose to see the light in every bad experience we feel calmer and naturally more in tune with peace. Leave any bad experience behind and don't think about it.Touch is what creates bonding and even awareness. We greet people with a handshake to make them aware of our presence. We hug a friend or hold a lovers hand. Every touch brings people together and creates more beauty for interaction. Touch can also be harmful. Someone can accidently knock your arm on the tube. People hit each other in a fight. Touch is powerful if you can find the beauty it in. If you can maintain positivity in the worse of any scenario you can find heaven everywhere around you.The sixth sense is the final extra sense where the spiritual realm is opened and connected into our earthly realm. We can connect with spiritual beings from these other realms. The heaven realm includes your guardian angel and all other angels. We can contact our spirit guides through mediumship. Depending on how in tune we are with our sixth sense determines if we will see our spirit guides and a vision of heaven. Through practice we can see a new world. We can connect with lost loved ones and heaven.</item>
<item>Be an indigo. We are all different and we all experience the world differently. If you can accept yourself and your individual identity you will be happy to have experienced heaven inside yourself. Remain true and don't follow other people or trends if it doesnt make you happy! It's as simple as that! Follow your own heart.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Remember to be patient as it might not happen over night!</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>People might be spiteful and try to bring you down as some people don't want to see other people happy!</item></list>
</text>
