<text id="autogum_interview_doc609" title="part1_Wikinews interviews spokesman for Greek far-left party Xekinima" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-05-03" dateModified="2013-05-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_spokesman_for_Greek_far-left_party_Xekinima" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">PT</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> There has always been tension between the governments of Greece and Turkey, some created by attempts to cover mistakes by both sides. It is no coincidence that both are in dire straits financially.</p>
<p>It is an artificial thing created by [the] government[s]. Of course these things can escalate; both Greece and Turkey have a policy of arms buildup. We recently had the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sledgehammer%20(coup%20plan)">sledgehammer controversy</ref> in Turkey where they planned to create incidents within Greece in an effort to seize power.</p>
<p>Also, many high-ranking army officers have been prosecuted in Turkey for trying to seize power in a coup.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">IM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Why do you oppose the current austerity measures? What has the government, in your view, got so wrong?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">PT</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> The government, in its effort to pay back banks and in fact to pay back interest on loans, has already paid in some cases twice the original loan at high interest rates.</p>
<p>They're trying to grab as much money as they can and we know for a fact that’s also on the orders of the Greek capitalist class.</p>
<p>They are reducing the worker’s rights for more money and this actually leads to poverty. Greece will be in guaranteed recession for two years and hopes then to create a 0.1% GDP rise. That will be very hard.</p>
<p>We know from a variety of statistics that the working class will be made to pay around 35% of the current GDP.</p>
<p>Consuming will go to standstill so that in two years time debt will rise from 120% of current GDP to 150% GDP and people will suffer. We know all the loans, just like the previous loans, will be siphoned off by business and will not go into Greek coffers. It will go instead to lining the pockets of big business.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">IM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> I have heard that people in Greece are upset that the euro has weakened Greece’s economic position, as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drachma">Drachma</ref>’s low value actually encouraged spending by foreigners. What steps would a socialist government take to encourage new spending in Greece by both foreign tourists and investors?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">PT</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> A socialist government could actually work if other economies and other people would follow Greece’s steps. Greece would then be a self-sufficient economy and not need these investments. Of course we once had these investments, through the tourism industry, and they didn’t work.</p>
<p>This is whether with the new currency of the euro or the old. The government is seriously thinking of relapse right now which would be a disaster because it would be so devalued. It would possibly even go into a tailspin of devaluation.</p>
<p>The possibilities are grossly underestimated in Greece and not enough investments are made in these possibilities.</p>
</text>
