<text id="autogum_interview_doc608" title="part0_Wikinews interviews spokesman for Greek far-left party Xekinima" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-05-03" dateModified="2013-05-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_spokesman_for_Greek_far-left_party_Xekinima" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews spokesman for Greek far-left party Xekinima</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, May 3, 2010</hi></p>
<p>Wikinews reporter Iain Macdonald today interviewed Petros Tzomakas, a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Greece">Greek</ref> far-left activist and member of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Xekinima">Xekinima</ref>, which is the Greek division of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Committee%20for%20a%20Workers'%20International">Committee for a Workers' International</ref>. The party is a member of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coalition%20of%20the%20Radical%20Left">Coalition of the Radical Left</ref> (SYRIZA).</p>
<p>Tzomakas also sits on his local 5th <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Athens">Athens</ref> Municipal District committee, which is a joint effort by left-wing parties including SYRIZA, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anticapitalist%20Left%20Cooperation%20for%20the%20Overthrow">Anticapitalist Left Cooperation for the Overthrow</ref> and a number of other political parties to oppose austerity measures proposed by the government. All left-wing parties in the country except the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Communist%20Party%20of%20Greece">Communist Party of Greece</ref> (KKE) are involved. Tzomakas explained that the KKE prefers not to co-operate with other radical left-wing groups.</p>
<p>The interview comes amid tensions in cash-strapped Greece, where the government is introducing controversial austerity measures to try to ease the nation's debt-problem. An international rescue package has been prepared by <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/European_Union">European Union</ref> member states and the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/International_Monetary_Fund">International Monetary Fund</ref> – should Greece require a bailout; protests have been held against government attempts to manage the economic situation.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Iain Macdonald</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> How are you doing today?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Petros Tzomakas</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> We are coping; we’re looking at numbers and digits and how they're tearing us apart.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">IM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Has slavish pursuit of free-market capitalism been the cause of Europe, and particularly Greece's, economic woes? How, given the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/collapse%20of%20the%20Soviet%20Union">Soviet collapse</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China">China</ref> being communist in name only, would your vision of a communist system have been better for the majority of citizens?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">PT</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Given current circumstances I think the main goal should be to nationalise means of production and services such as banks but under democratic control by unions and local councils where it effects local economies and re-elect local representatives where needed.</p>
<p>There is a necessity for a planned economy but one controlled not by bureaucracy but by the people participating in it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">IM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> For right or for wrong, we have now reached a situation where Greece is on the brink of an international bailout. If you were given power tomorrow, what steps would you take immediately to get Greece back on track?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">PT</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> We would immediately nationalise the  banks. We would refuse to pay the bonds which were called upon during this time, renationalise privatised industries and invest in such a planned economy.</p>
<p>Basically, we would refuse to pay debts created by the banks on our government.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Petros then gave some statistics on Greek defence expenditure. He stated that Greece is the 5THin the world in such expenditure; but, has only the 28TH-highest <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/gross%20domestic%20product">GDP</ref> combined with the 73RD highest population count.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">IM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Picking up on your comments about defense expenditure: Is that expenditure a result of a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greek–Turkish%20relations">perceived threat</ref> from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Turkey">Turkey</ref>, and if so, is this really an issue or a creation of a problem where there isn’t one?</hi></p>
</text>
