<text id="autogum_academic_doc199" title="Readable High-Speed Racetrack Memory Based on an Antiferromagnetically Coupled Soft/Hard Magnetic Bilayer" shortTile="readable-highspeed" author="Ziyang Yu, Chenhuinan Wei, Fan Yi, Rui Xiong" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2079-4991/9/11/1538/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Model</head>
<p>
The numerical investigation is based on the model shown in <figure>Figure 1</figure>. The dimension of the cell for the simulation is 5 nm × 1 nm × 6 nm. We consider an HM1/FM/NM/FM/HM2 multilayer track system. Here, HM1 and HM2 are two different heavy metal layers, and NM is a nonmagnetic metal layer working as the media for the Ruderman-Kittel-Kasuya-Yosida (RKKY)-typed exchange coupling between the two FM layers with PMA. The interlayer RKKY AFM exchange coupling is characterized by a negative exchange coupling constant (<hi rend="italic">Jex</hi>).  </p>

<p>In an HM/FM system, the magnetic parameters such as the uniaxial-anisotropy constant and the DMI constant can be manipulated experimentally. For example, the uniaxial-anisotropy constant can be too small to maintain the PMA or be as large as 106 J/m3. The DMI constant can be between 0 and 3 mJ/m2, depending on the composition and thickness of the HM or FM layers and the annealing treatment. All the parameters used in our simulation are in an experimentally achievable range. Without loss of generality, we applied a positive DMI constant and a positive spin-Hall angle that ensures the motion of a right-handed DW against the direction of the current (along the direction of electron flow). The change of the sign of DMI or the spin Hall angle only reverses the motion direction of the DW but does not influence the conclusion of this paper. </p>

<p>In the HM1/FM1/NM/FM2/HM2 system, to ensure the inter-layer AFM coupling between the DW moments, the DMI constants of the HM1/FM1 and FM2/HM2 need to share the same signs. When the DMI constants of both layers are positive, the chirality requires the DWs to exhibit an “up-down” configuration that is favorable for an inter-layer AFM coupling between the DWs of the two layers (<figure>Figure 2</figure>). To ensure the motion of the two DWs in the same direction, the spins injecting into FM1 and FM2 should have the same sign in principle. Therefore, the signs of the spin Hall angles of HM1 and HM2 needs to be opposite since the HM1 is below FM1 while the HM2 is above FM2. However, when the interlayer AFM coupling is strong, the rotation of the moment in one layer is pinned by that in the other one. Therefore, it is enough that one HM layer has spin Hall effect. Some compositions of HM/FM satisfy the above requirement, such as Pt/Co and Co/Ir/Pt, and W/Co and Co/Ru/W. </p>

<p>Because of the difference in the uniaxial-anisotropy constants between the two FM layers and a moderate inter-layer exchange coupling, the velocities of the DWs in the two layers can be very different. As a result, there is a region consisting of the staggered domains between the two neighboring DWs in the two layers, and the magnetic moments in this staggered region are parallel aligned. Two orientations (+z and −z) of the moments in the staggered region can be exploited to label the information stored in the neighboring AFM-coupled domains moving in a fixed direction. For example, as shown in <figure>Figure 1</figure>, when the reading head nearby the track detects the magnetization of +2MS in a staggered domain region, the reader provides an output voltage of +V. When the domain walls move left, the AFM-coupled domains following this staggered region has the magnetization of −MS for the upper layer and +MS for the lower one. This sort of AFM coupling can be encoded as 0. On the contrary, the AFM-coupled domains with the magnetization of +MS for the upper layer and −MS for the lower one can be encoded as 1. This reading function can be realized by connecting a Schmitt trigger to the sensor. In the track with the domains moving left, when the reader gives an output of +V, a digital signal 1 is triggered, and it holds for the following AFM-coupled domains till the sensor detects the magnetization of −2MS. Afterwards, the sensor outputs a voltage of −V that changes the digital signal to 0. </p>
</text>
