<text id="autogum_whow_doc313" title="Know Proper Table Manners in China" shortTile="know-proper-table" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-03-23" dateModified="2016-05-13" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Know-Proper-Table-Manners-in-China" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Know Proper Table Manners in China</head><p>Table manners are important in every culture; however, there is no universal rule for table manners. Like many cultures, the Chinese have specific rules of etiquette when sharing a meal.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Know where to sit. The seat of honor faces the door. To show respect, choose a different seat. The person with the lowest status sits with their back to the door, directly opposite the guest of honor. When in doubt, wait for the host to seat you.</item>
<item>Do not begin the meal until everyone arrives. After that, wait for the highest ranking or oldest person to begin eating before you start.</item>
<item>Keep both hands visible. In China, it is alright to put your elbows on the table.</item>
<item>Do not gesture with your chopsticks. Never point them at someone else. This is highly disrespectful. Chopsticks are used in the right hand, even for left-handed people. Avoid banging dishes with your chopsticks. This is considered to be the behavior of a beggar.</item>
<item>Pour tea for other people, but not yourself. Do not fill the cup all the way, as this means you want them to leave. Do not point the teapot's spout at anyone.</item>
<item>Never stick your chopsticks straight up in your rice when eating. This signifies incense for the dead.</item>
<item>Be aware that meals are usually family style. Expect people to use their chopsticks to serve their food. Often, the host will use their own chopsticks to serve you food.</item>
<item>Do your best to try everything. Don't hog a dish just because you like it; this is not polite behavior. There are people that need to eat other than you, so it's important to share. Also, don't refuse a dish because you don't like it. Eat at least a little in order to be polite.</item>
<item>Be aware that many Chinese dishes contain animal bones. These bones can be spat out and placed to the right of your plate or, if available, a trash can on the floor.</item>
<item>Know that, if drinking alcohol, you may be expected to 干杯, which is translated to mean "Cheers", but actually means "drink the entire glass of alcohol". If you are a special guest, every single person will toast to you. When clinking glasses, try to place the rim of your glass below theirs. This indicates that you respect them.</item>
<item>Know that, in general, the host pays for the entire meal. If you are the host, you are expected to offer to pay, though nine times out of ten, they will refuse. If you invited them to the meal, you will pay for everyone.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>For banquets and large dinners, pace yourself. They will be serving a large amount of food.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Never try to secretly pay the bill for your host. This is extremely rude. However, if you are the host, you may have to pay the bill without letting anyone else know. The battle for the check can be intense.</item></list>
</text>
