<text id="autogum_academic_doc375" title="Sustainable Tourism in the Open Innovation Realm: A Bibliometric Analysis" shortTile="sustainable-tourism" author="Valentina Della Corte, Giovanna Del Gaudio, Fabiana Sepe, Fabiana Sciarelli" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/6114/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Literature Review: Sustainable Tourism and Its Interconnections with Experiential and Digital Components in the Era of Open Innovation</head>
<p>
Literature on sustainable tourism has experienced growing expansion in the last decades. Despite this increasing interest in sustainable tourism and its application for the three pillars (environmental, social, and economic), little has been done in terms of systematization of contributions of articles recalling the topic of sustainable tourism and its interconnections with digital and experiential components in the era of open innovation. </p>

<p>Some studies have indeed paid attention to how the topic of sustainability has evolved within the tourism industry. </p>

<p>The study of explores how sustainable restaurant literature within hospitality research has developed from 1991 to 2015. It reveals that scholars concentrate their attention on green aspects of sustainability rather than on economic and social aspects, finally claiming the necessity of a holistic approach. </p>

<p>The research of focuses the attention of ecotourism sustainability conceived from the perspective of marine ecologists. It shows a lack of integration with economic aspects of sustainability. They also highlight the necessity of synergies between ecotourism and productive sectors (fisheries, aquaculture, etc.) that can represent the economic base for the local communities. </p>

<p>As regards the use of bibliometrical analysis for the topic of sustainable tourism, there is an intense production of the literature. </p>

<p>While the study of focuses on the theory, methods, subjects, perspectives/approaches, and geography of scholars used in the articles, the research of mapped the knowledge base on sustainable tourism development from 1990 to 2018. The study presents the core topics of the literature, including “climate change, tourist behaviors and impact, empowerment, policymaking, and the role of cultural heritage in sustainable tourism development”. </p>

<p>The study of reveals that the topic is in constant growth, the United States is the leading country on this topic, and the issue of sustainability is strategic for both companies and destinations. In the same direction, show the results of their research identifying the development status and leading trends in terms of impact, main journals, papers, topics, authors, institutions, and countries. </p>

<p>Although bibliometrical studies on sustainable tourism already exist, the attention and novelty of this research lies in the precise topic of sustainable tourism in the digital era, also with specific reference to open innovation and how the use of digital technology can enhance the tourist’s experience. </p>

<p>Indeed, nowadays, there is a growing interest in what scholars label as digital sustainability.  </p>

<p>According to, “Digital resources are handled sustainably if their utility for society is maximized, so that digital needs of contemporary and future generations are equally met. Digital needs are optimally met if resources are accessible to the largest number and reusable with minimal restrictions”. Hence, sustainability is digital when it deals with digital resources. </p>

<p>Among the numerous characteristics of digital sustainability (i.e., intergenerational justice, regenerative capacity, economic use of resources, risk reduction, absorptive capacity, economic and ecological added value), there are some that fit with the interests of sustainable tourism well.  </p>

<p>Sharing the idea that digital tools are considered a transversal component of innovation in the tourism sector and not the key component, such as the organizational and experiential, they can enhance the core pillars of sustainability, as they are supportive through their characteristics of economic and ecological added value. </p>

<p>Firstly, digital goods have the feature to be freely available and this characteristic helps tourists obtain free information as in the case of downloading and installing applications for the knowledge of the destination or other tourist attractions. From the ecological point of view, with digital information and communication technology, for example, there is a reduction of printed papers, brochures, or maps, and this helps to implement more sustainable practices. </p>

<p>Actually, the vision offered by some scholars is reduced if we consider only the digital technology per se without recalling the definition of a tourist product as global and as a result of an overlapping perspective between the demand and offer side. </p>

<p>The so called “memorable experience” is also given by the ability of the companies and/or the destination to create a storytelling (demand side perspective) of the places and of the local community that constitute the social humus of the real tourist experience. Through digital tools, destination/companies can tell their stories and digital tourists can use the virtual world to communicate their experiences with other people. </p>

<p>The potentiality of storytelling can act on the social pillar of sustainability since it can enhance the visibility of the community in terms of traditions, culture, folklore, and local identity, creating a certain belonging with the community. </p>

<p>In this direction, digital sustainability assumes two specific connotations shaped by the holistic perspective of the supply and demand side together. From the demand side, there are digital tourists, like experiencing the destination, attractions and services according to the vision of using digital technologies during their stay. These technologies offer the possibility of increasing the level of immersion within the tourism experience. </p>
</text>
