<text id="autogum_interview_doc628" title="part0_CanadaVOTES: NDP incumbent Wayne Marston running in Hamilton East—Stoney Creek" shortTile="partcanadavotes-ndp" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-09-25" dateModified="2016-07-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CanadaVOTES%3A_NDP_incumbent_Wayne_Marston_running_in_Hamilton_East%E2%80%94Stoney_Creek" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>CanadaVOTES: NDP incumbent Wayne Marston running in Hamilton East—Stoney Creek</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 25, 2008</hi></p>
<p>On October 14, 2008, Canadians will be heading to the polls for the federal election. <hi rend="bold">New Democratic Party incumbent <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wayne%20Marston">Wayne Marston</ref></hi> is standing for re-election in <hi rend="bold">the riding of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hamilton%20East—Stoney%20Creek">Hamilton East—Stoney Creek</ref></hi>.</p>
<p>Marston ran in the former federal riding Hamilton East three times, in 1993 and 1997 election and 1996 by-election, losing to prominent Liberal Shelia Copps. Prior to his winning election campaign in 2006, Marston was President of the Hamilton and District Labour Council, serving for 11 years. He was also a School Board Trustee (Ward 5) for the Hamilton-Wentworth District School Board from 2000 to 2006.</p>
<p>Wikinews contacted Wayne, to talk about the issues facing Canadians, and what they and their party would do to address them. Wikinews is in the process of contacting every candidate, in every riding across the country, no matter their political stripe. All interviews are conducted over e-mail, and interviews are published unedited, allowing candidates to impart their full message to our readers, uninterrupted.</p>
<p>This riding consists of the part of the Hamilton lying north of the Niagara Escarpment and east of Ottawa Street. It was formed in 2003 from parts of the old ridings Hamilton East and Stoney Creek. Wanting to take Marston's seat from his are Liberal Larry Di Ianni, Green David William Hart Dyke, and Conservative Frank Rukavina. A candidate from the newly formed Progressive Canadian party, Gord Hill, as well as independent Sam Cino are also running.</p>
<p>For more information, visit the campaign's official website, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Main_Page#External_links">listed below</ref>.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why did you choose to run for office, and why do you wish to continue as an MP?</hi></p>
<p>Forty years ago, I moved to Hamilton.  I've lived and worked there ever since. I quickly became involved in the union and held many positions over the years.  In 1995 I retired from Bell Canada and served as the President of the Hamilton and District Labour Council for 11 years.</p>
<p>During this time, we saw growth and then we saw the loss of good paying manufacturing jobs.  This scarred our community.  Hamilton is a city that has so much potential. Unfortunately, we saw the loss of thousands of good paying that could have supported a family; and no one stepped up to help us.</p>
<p>I wanted to give something back to this amazing community which has helped me raise my children and grandchildren, so in 2000, I decided to get involved in politics.  I realized that our families needed more than empty promises from their elected representatives.</p>
<p>This led me to run in 2006 as the NDP's candidate in the federal election.</p>
<p>I have strived to ensure that my office works for its community, cares and brings fairness and honesty to Canadians.</p>
</text>
