<text id="autogum_bio_doc130" title="Hui Liu" shortTile="hui-liu" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-12-10" dateModified="2018-11-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hui_Liu" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Hui Liu</head>
<p>Dr. <hi rend="bold">Hui Liu</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chinese_language">Chinese</ref>:刘辉) is a Chinese American professor and an entrepreneur in the field of wireless and satellite communications. He is a prolific researcher with more than 200 scholarly articles and 2 textbooks, and a creative innovator with 67 awarded patents in areas ranging from wireless systems, signal processing, satellite networks, to machine learning <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-paper-1">[1]</ref>. He has more than 12,000 paper citations and an H-index of 56 as of 2018. Dr. Liu is also one of the principal designers of three industrial standards on cellular networks, terrestrial broadcasting, and satellite communications, respectively.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ee-2">[2]</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-silkwave-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Liu graduated from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fudan_University">Fudan University</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shanghai">Shanghai</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/China">China</ref> with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bachelor_of_Science">B.Sc</ref> degree in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electrical_engineering">electrical engineering</ref> in 1988 and obtained master's degree at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portland_State_University">Portland State University</ref>. By 1995 he completed his Ph.D. in the same field as well from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Texas">University of Texas</ref> at Austin. From September of the same year till July 1998 Liu worked at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Virginia">University of Virginia</ref> as a tenure-track Assistant Professor. After that, he joined the Electrical Engineering department of University of Washington where he became a tenure Full Professor and the Associate Chair of Research. From 2013-2016, he was the ZhiYuan Chair Professor and the Associate Dean at School of Electronic, Information &amp; Electrical Engineering (SEIEE) at Shanghai Jiao Tong University.
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sjtu-4">[4]</ref>. He worked as a chief scientist at Cwill Telecom and was one of the principal designers of the 3G TD-SCDMA technologies. He founded Adaptix in 2000 and pioneered the development of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orthogonal_frequency-division_multiple_access">OFDMA</ref>-based mobile broadband cellular networks (mobile WiMAX and 4G LTE) <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ee-2">[2]</ref>.  He is the President and CTO of Silkwave Holdings Limited <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-silkwave-3">[3]</ref>.</p>
<head>Inventor</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Dr. Liu is the Architect of the terrestrial broadcasting technology in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/China_Multimedia_Mobile_Broadcasting">China Multimedia Mobile Broadcasting</ref> networks</item></list>
<list type="unordered"><item>He is the author of the 6 original patents on TD-SCDMA, one of the ITU standards on mobile cellular networks. He won the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gold_Prize_Patent_Award">Gold Prize Patent Award</ref> for his patent on "Smart Antenna CDMA Wireless Communication Systems," U. S. Patent 6,122,260.</item></list>
<list type="unordered"><item>Currently he is the CTO and Vice Chairman of Silkwave Holdings and CMMB Vision, a listed company in Hong Kong,  developing the world’s first satellite direct-to-mobile (DTM) multimedia network that delivers Cloud-based video, audio entertainment and data services to vehicles and mobile devices that is data-free, abundant, and ubiquitous <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-silkwave-3">[3]</ref>.</item></list>
<head>Awards</head>
<p>In 1997 the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Science_Foundation">National Science Foundation</ref> awarded Liu with the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NSF_Early_Faculty_CAREER_Award">NSF Early Faculty CAREER Award</ref></hi>;  In 2000 he became a recipient of the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Young_Investigator_Award">Young Investigator Award</ref></hi> from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Office_of_Naval_Research">Office of Naval Research</ref>. During the same year, with the help of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Artech_House">Artech House</ref> he published his <hi rend="italic">Signal Processing Applications in CDMA Communications</hi> book and five years later published another one which was called <hi rend="italic">OFDM-Based Broadband Wireless Networks – Design and Optimization</hi>. Before he published his second book through <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wiley_Online_Libarry">Wiley</ref> he was twice nominated for the IEEE <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Best_Paper_Award">Best Paper Award</ref></hi> and became the recipient of the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gold_Prize_Patent_Award">Gold Prize Patent Award</ref></hi> for his patent on 3G TD-SCDMA . Liu has received multiple IEEE <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Best_Conference_Paper_Award">Best Conference Paper Award</ref></hi> and in 2008 he was honored to be an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Institute_of_Electrical_and_Electronics_Engineers">IEEE</ref> Fellow "for contributions to global standards for broadband cellular and mobile broadcasting".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ee-2">[2]</ref></p>
</text>
