<text id="autogum_bio_doc524" title="John of Gloucester" shortTile="john-gloucester" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-02-26" dateModified="2019-09-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_of_Gloucester" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>John of Gloucester</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">John of Gloucester</hi> (or <hi rend="bold">John of Pontefract</hi>) (1468–1499 (based on historical hypothesis)) was a son of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_III_of_England">Richard III of England</ref>. John is so called because his father was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duke_of_Gloucester">Duke of Gloucester</ref> at the time of his birth. His father appointed him <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Captain_of_Calais">Captain of Calais</ref>, a position he lost after his father's death. He seems to have been held in custody at some point during the reign of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VII_of_England">Henry VII</ref> and may have been executed around 1499.</p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>The identity of John's mother is not known, nor is his date of birth. However, since Katherine, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_III">Richard III</ref>'s other illegitimate child, was old enough to be wedded in 1484 and John was old enough to be knighted in September 1483 in York Minster (when his half brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_of_Middleham,_Prince_of_Wales">Edward</ref>, Richard's only legitimate heir, was invested Prince of Wales) and to be made Captain of Calais in March 1485, most historians agree these 2 children were fathered during Richard's teen years.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> There is no trace of infidelity on Richard's part after his marriage in 1472, when he was around 20.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Dr Ashdown-Hill suggests that John was conceived during Richard's first solo expedition to the eastern counties in the summer of 1467 at the invitation of John Howard and that the boy was born in 1468 and named after his friend and supporter. Richard himself noted John was still a minor (not being yet 21) when he issued the royal patent appointing him Captain of Calais on 11 March 1485, possibly on his seventeenth birthday.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>An order referring to his appointment as Captain of Calais calls him "John de Pountfreit Bastard."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> Because of this, it has been suggested that he was born at Pontefract.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> Michael Hicks has suggested that John's mother was Alice Burgh, who was granted an annuity of 20 pounds when Richard was at Pontefract on 1 March 1474; the grant states that it was made for "certain special causes and considerations."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> Another candidate is Katherine Haute, who Rosemary Horrox has suggested was a mistress of Richard and possibly the mother of Richard's illegitimate daughter Katherine, who married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Herbert,_2nd_Earl_of_Pembroke">William Herbert, 2nd Earl of Pembroke</ref>. Horrox notes that Richard granted Katherine Haute an annuity of five pounds in 1477.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> It is unknown, however, whether Katherine and John had the same mother. They were both half-siblings of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_of_Middleham,_Prince_of_Wales">Edward of Middleham, Prince of Wales</ref>.</p>
<head>Career</head>
<p>John was one of two persons <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knight">knighted</ref> on 8 September 1483 in York during the celebrations which invested his half-brother Edward of Middleham as Prince of Wales.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p>John is known to have been in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calais">Calais</ref> by November 1484 and was officially appointed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Captain_of_Calais">Captain of Calais</ref> by his father on 11 March 1485. His letter of appointment has Richard referring to him as "our dear bastard son". The patent appointing John gave him all of the necessary powers of his position, except of appointing officers, which it reserved until he turned twenty-one; it does not indicate how close to turning twenty-one he was. A warrant dated 9 March 1485 to deliver clothing to "the Lord Bastard" probably refers to John.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref></p>
<head>Under Henry VII</head>
<p>After Richard was killed in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Bosworth_Field">Battle of Bosworth Field</ref> (22 August 1485), Henry VII removed John from the position of Captain of Calais, but did not further persecute him and, on 1 March 1486, granted him an annual income of 20 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pound_sterling">pounds sterling</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref></p>
<p>In his confession, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Perkin_Warbeck">Perkin Warbeck</ref> stated that when he began his impersonation of Richard, Duke of York, in 1491, "King Richard's bastard son was in the hands of the king of England."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref> In the seventeenth century, an early defender of Richard III, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Buck">George Buck</ref>, claimed that around the time of the executions of Warbeck and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward,_Earl_of_Warwick">Edward, Earl of Warwick</ref>, in 1499, "there was a base son of King Richard III made away, and secretly, having been kept long before in prison." Buck, who does not identify John by name, claims that he was executed to prevent him from falling into the hands of certain Irishmen who wished to make him their chief or prince.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref> There are no other sources for John's execution.</p>
</text>
