<text id="autogum_whow_doc598" title="Self Reflect" shortTile="self-reflect" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2012-02-29" dateModified="2019-10-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Self-Reflect" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Self Reflect</head><p>In this extremely fast paced world, millions forget how to live for themselves and others. When one does, they live wrongly for themselves and incidentally, and act selfishly towards others. Self reflection is about taking time to think about your life and your purpose, as well as your place in the world. It's about questioning the choices you've made, to check now and then that you're still living true to your own values.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Understanding the Purpose of Self Reflection</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Know why you are self-reflecting. Ask yourself why are you self-reflecting. Did you do something wrong or things are always going wrong for you? What is it? <figure rend="Self Reflect Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Know the subject on your self-reflection moments. What is about? Is it about your life in general or you being hurt by someone. <figure rend="Self Reflect Step 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Finding a Quiet Place</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Spend this time alone somewhere where no one can possibly hear you. Possibly, have a pen and paper to map out your thoughts. <figure rend="Self Reflect Step 3.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Practicing Self Reflection</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Talk to yourself. No one is judging you. It's just that you are thinking aloud. This is very important as you are engaging your senses. <figure rend="Self Reflect Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do a breathing exercise. Inhale and exhale as many times as as you want. For every breathing, say something out, i.e, <hi rend="italic">I've done well</hi> <hi rend="italic">I need to do this..</hi> Thank yourself for even realizing that you need to self-reflect. <figure rend="Self Reflect Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pour out your emotions. Cry if you need to. The point is to reach the goal of solving a problem and understanding your self better. Write them down. <figure rend="Self Reflect Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Read. We all need to read at one point of time to see and feel how much luckier you may be than the millions whose lives are in danger every single day, without a choice. Read widely to find out how people live elsewhere and what they do to survive against the odds. <figure rend="Self Reflect Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Some more suggestions are provided in Tips, below.</item></list></item>
<item>Focus on the past. Try to remember a time in your past. It could be a year ago, ten years, five minutes, however far back you'd like to reflect. <figure rend="Focus-with-ADHD-Step-11.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Focus on events that happened around that time in your past. How did you feel about them? How did you react and why?</item>
<item>Learn to understand all perspectives of the situation. Maybe you were irrational at first; maybe you were completely right in your actions.</item>
<item>Let go of any negative feelings or grudges you still hold. Wallowing in your misery or anger won't help you grow as a person.</item>
<item>Many people believe that everything happens for a reason. If your past had been altered, you wouldn't be who you are today. Everything in life is a lesson if you look at it the right way.</item>
<item>Return to the present. With everything you've learned from your past, you'll hopefully have a wiser perspective of your present and future life.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Putting Self Reflection into Action</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Count your blessings. Are you having a first world problem? Do you know there's also something known as a <hi rend="italic">third world problem?</hi> <figure rend="Self Reflect Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Say these out based on your subject matters: <hi rend="italic">I can do it</hi> <hi rend="italic">I feel sorry now for that person maybe I can help</hi> <hi rend="italic">I will take care of myself from now on</hi> <hi rend="italic">Thank you thank you thank you thank you!</hi> <hi rend="italic">I need to change my ways to be a better person</hi> etc. <figure rend="Self Reflect Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Plan to pay it forward. Donate, help others out and ask yourself, why are you donating. <figure rend="Self Reflect Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>When you read a fiction book, always seek to find what the story is about and ask yourself what can you learn from it, no matter what it is about. This will keep you in check time and time again.</item>
<item>Read a non-fiction book. Memoirs, bio, non-fiction are categorized for a reason. Mostly, you can learn from. For example, read <hi rend="italic">I'm Prohibited</hi> by Hanz Moniefiero Medina. A short novel but you can learn many things from this particular ebook. It'll take you one crazy ride. Search it on Amazon or Kobo and Smashwords. Read books that pull your heartstrings and or you can relate to from reading the description of the book or synopsis.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>The idea of self-reflection is to never get depressed or brood about and hold grudges. You are supposed to be either be thankful of how lucky you are, finding a solution on how to reach out to help yourself or anything. Smile at the end of it all and read what you have mapped out and plan your next move to being a better person. We are all supposed to live, learn, give, receive, thank, have fun. Problems are created by your thoughts and many times it's easy to solve it.</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
