<text id="autogum_interview_doc313" title="part0_John Reed on Orwell, God, self-destruction and the future of writing" shortTile="partjohn-reed-orwell" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-18" dateModified="2015-01-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Reed_on_Orwell%2C_God%2C_self-destruction_and_the_future_of_writing" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>John Reed on Orwell, God, self-destruction and the future of writing</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 18, 2007</hi></p>
<figure><caption>John Reed: "A kid who reads a book and says, 'This isn't for me. It doesn't have anything to do with my time period; I don't know why I'm reading it. Literature is completely removed from my experience.' They're right! There's no reason to have that kid reading books that are removed from their experience." Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref>.</caption></figure><p>It can be difficult to be <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20Reed%20(novelist)">John Reed</ref>.  </p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher%20Hitchens">Christopher Hitchens</ref> called him a "Bin Ladenist" and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cathy%20Young">Cathy Young</ref> editorialized in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Boston%20Globe">The Boston Globe</ref></hi> that he "blames the victims of terrorism" when he puts out a novel like <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Snowball's%20Chance">Snowball's Chance</ref></hi>, a biting send-up of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George%20Orwell">George Orwell</ref>'s <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Animal%20Farm">Animal Farm</ref></hi> which he was inspired to write after the terrorist attacks on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/9/11">September 11</ref>.  "The clear references to 9/11 in the apocalyptic ending can only bring Orwell's name into disrepute in the U.S.," wrote William Hamilton, the British literary executor of the Orwell estate.  That process had already begun:  it was revealed Orwell gave the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/British%20Foreign%20Office">British Foreign Office</ref> a list of people he suspected of being "crypto-Communists and fellow travelers," labeling some of them as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jews">Jews</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homosexuals">homosexuals</ref>.  "I really wanted to explode that book," Reed told <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20New%20York%20Times">The New York Times</ref></hi>.  "I wanted to completely undermine it."</p>
<p>Is this man who wants to blow up the classic <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Western%20canon">literary canon</ref> taught to children in schools a menace, or a messiah?  <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref> went to interview him for <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> and found that, as often is the case, the answer lies somewhere in the middle.</p>
<p>Reed is electrified by the changes that surround him that channel through a lens of inspiration wrought by his children.  "The kids have made me a better writer," Reed said.  In his new untitled work, which he calls a "new play by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William%20Shakespeare">William Shakespeare</ref>," he takes lines from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bard">The Bard</ref>'s classics to form an original tragedy.  He began it in 2003, but only with the birth of his children could he finish it. "I didn't understand the characters who had children. I didn't really understand them. And once I had had kids, I could approach them differently."  </p>
<p>Taking the old to make it new is a theme in his work and in his world view.  Reed foresees new narrative forms being born, Biblical epics that will be played out across print and electronic mediums.  He is pulled forward by revolutions of the past, a search for a spiritual sensibility, and a desire to locate himself in the process. </p>
<p>Below is <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref>'s conversation with novelist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20Reed%20(novelist)">John Reed</ref>.</p>
<head id="On_the_alternative_media_and_independent_publishing">On the alternative media and independent publishing</head>
<p>[<hi rend="italic">Conversation in progress...</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20Reed">John Reed</ref>:</hi>  Yeah, exactly.  Well, working with the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brooklyn%20Rail">Brooklyn Rail</ref></hi> is my community service.</p>
</text>
