<text id="autogum_academic_doc656" title="The Mode of Action of Bacillus Species against Fusarium graminearum, Tools for Investigation, and Future Prospects" shortTile="mode-action-bacillus" author="Khayalethu Ntushelo, Lesiba  Klaas Ledwaba, Molemi  Evelyn Rauwane, Oluwafemi  Ayodeji Adebo, Patrick  Berka Njobeh" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6651/11/10/606/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Tools for the Detection of Surfactin, Fengycin, and Iturin Genes in <hi rend="italic">Bacillus</hi> Strains and Culture with Biological Activity against <hi rend="italic">Fusarium graminearum</hi></head>
<p>
Genomic analysis of <hi rend="italic">Bacillus</hi> has shown that these bacteria possess genes which code for metabolites associated with biological control. Genetic information made available by genomic sequencing has led to a better understanding of <hi rend="italic">Bacillus</hi> biocontrol features. Chen et al. characterized the genome of the <hi rend="italic">Bacillus velezensis</hi> LM2303 strain, known for its strong biocontrol potential against <hi rend="italic">F. graminearum</hi>. This strain presented the largest number of biocontrol genes and gene clusters when compared with strains studied earlier. Thirteen biosynthetic gene clusters associated with biocontrol activity were identified using an integrated approach of genome mining and chemical analysis, including the three antifungal metabolites fengycin B, iturin A, and surfactin A. Another strain, <hi rend="italic">B. velezensis</hi> LM2303, which has antimicrobial activity against <hi rend="italic">F. graminearum</hi> in addition to other plant pathogenic fungi, also presented a plethora of genes encoding antimicrobial compounds. These findings demonstrated the value of genomic analysis in both biocontrol strain characterization and understanding of the basis of biocontrol activity. A plethora of co-culturing studies have utilized PCR to detect genes involved in biological control in culture, to later identify the basis of their biological control activity. However, biological control genes are sometimes detected in pure <hi rend="italic">Bacillus</hi> strains undergoing characterization. The study by Adeniji et al. analyzed seven isolates of <hi rend="italic">Bacillus</hi> with bio-suppressive effects against <hi rend="italic">F. graminearum</hi> and found them to have valuable gene clusters encoding biocontrol agents. The fingerprint of the combination of genes detected by PCR indicates that strain differentiation and selection are important to identify the strain demonstrating the highest antimicrobial activity as a candidate biocontrol agent. Studies to identify surfactin, fengycin, and iturin in culture are routinely carried out and have uncovered a myriad of antimicrobial substances able to act against plant pathogenic fungi, including <hi rend="italic">F. graminearum</hi>. These studies make use of combined chromatography and mass spectrometry to identify the compounds which have antagonistic activity. Using reverse-phase high-performance liquid chromatography and electrospray ionization mass spectrometry (RP-HPLC/ESI–MS) analyses, Gong et al. identified iturin and surfactin in a culture of <hi rend="italic">B. amyloliquefaciens</hi> isolated from wheat infected with <hi rend="italic">F. graminearum</hi>. Further characterization of iturin showed that it causes leakage and/or inactivation of <hi rend="italic">F. graminearum</hi> cellular contents. Using thin-layer chromatography–bioautography, Lee et al. identified iturin A in a butanol extract of a culture of <hi rend="italic">B. amyloliquefaciens</hi> strain DA12, which was found to be active against <hi rend="italic">F. graminearum</hi>. The same study also attributed this activity to volatile heptanones, some of which were detected using gas chromatography–mass spectrometry (GC–MS). A similar study was performed using ultra-high-performance liquid chromatography coupled with mass spectrometry (UHPLC–MS) to confirm the presence of fengycin B, iturin A, and surfactin A in <hi rend="italic">B</hi>. <hi rend="italic">velezensis</hi>. Also, the study of Adeniji et al. used electrospray ionization–quadrupole mass spectrometry (ESI–Q-ToF-MS) to detect surfactin, fengycin, and iturin in the <hi rend="italic">F. graminearum</hi>-supressing <hi rend="italic">B. velezensis</hi> strain NWUMFkBS10.5. The power of these analytical techniques lies on their sensitivity and accuracy of detection, and their application is critical for, amongst other things, the detection of toxins in food to ensure compliance with food safety standards based on critical threshold values. Moreover, their application to detect bioactive components of <hi rend="italic">Bacillus</hi> against <hi rend="italic">F. graminearum</hi> is particularly relevant. </p>
</text>
