<text id="autogum_whow_doc430" title="Celebrate Friday the 13th" shortTile="celebrate-friday" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2009-02-12" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Celebrate-Friday-the-13th" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Celebrate Friday the 13th</head><p>Only around 10 percent of modern-day Americans believe that Friday the 13th is an unlucky day, yet it is still a well recognized superstition. If you want to have some fun on Friday the 13th, there are many things you can do to mark the day. Take advantage of any local events, like events at museums. Have a party where you eat spooky food and watch scary movies. You can also plan fun activities, like ghost hunting, somewhat related to the day.
</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Taking Advantage of Local Events and Attractions</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>See if there are any local events planned. Some towns may have events planned around the community for Friday the 13th. You can search online, typing in something like "local Friday the 13th events," or look for flyers at a local community center. Something like a potluck, cookout, or free movie screening, can be a fun way to spend the day. <figure rend="Celebrate Friday the 13th Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Check out spooky or odd local museums. Look up the various museums in your area and see if you find anything spooky or odd. Maybe there's a museum of medical history in your area. Maybe there's a museum of oddities. Something like Ripley's Believe It Or Not, for example, can be fun to do on Friday the 13th. <figure rend="Celebrate Friday the 13th Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Museums may also host local events on the date. For example, maybe a local history museum is having a special exhibit or talk about the history of Friday the 13th.</item></list></item>
<item>Take a tour of local hauntings and legends. Look into your own town's quirky history. Figure out some superstitions, or allegedly haunted sites, and give them a visit on the day. See if there are any guided tours in your area that feature local oddities. <figure rend="Celebrate Friday the 13th Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Look into local superstitions. For example, maybe there's an old playground where people believe you can make wishes. This would be a great place to visit on Friday the 13th.</item></list></item>
<item>Find local deals and specials. Some businesses may have deals or specials to mark the day. A local bar, for example, may have special Friday the 13th themed drinks. A local restaurant may have half-off appetizers or special food for the day. See if you can go out to a local business and save some money while enjoying food and drink specials for the day. <figure rend="Celebrate Friday the 13th Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you're interested in getting a tattoo, check out tattoo parlors. Many tattoo parlors offer discounts on Friday the 13th-themed tattoos.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Having a Party</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Decorate with spooky or dark-themed items. As Friday the 13th is believed to be a day marked by bad luck, opt for spooky decorations. Pick a variety of decorations in colors like black, gray, and red to give off a spooky, ominous feel. <figure rend="Celebrate Friday the 13th Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, find wreathes made out of black and gray flowers to give off a deadly, creepy look.</item>
<item>Cut pieces of red felt into the shapes of droplets. Glue them onto a long piece of string to make a blood drop garland.</item>
<item>Make use of your own bookshelf for decorations. Pull out copies of horror stories, like the works of Poe, to display at your party.</item></list></item>
<item>Watch Friday the 13th-themed movies. You can try watching films from the <hi rend="italic">Friday the 13th</hi> franchise at your party. You can also just watch horror movies in general to give off the spooky feel of the day. For example, watch horror classics like <hi rend="italic">The Exorcist</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Rosemary's Baby.</hi> <figure rend="Celebrate Friday the 13th Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Play games with a dark or superstitious twist. Put a spooky twist on classic games. For example, look for trivia games online that have questions centered around horror and superstition. Play a game like Truth or Dare that pushes people out of their comfort zone. Try doing a game of Pictionary where you have to draw spooky pictures. <figure rend="Celebrate Friday the 13th Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make a Friday the 13th playlist. Many bands, such as Everlast and Deer Tick, have songs called "Friday the 13th" that would be appropriate to add to a playlist for your party. You can also add songs about the day Friday, such as humorous choices like Rebecca Black's "Friday." Generally spooky sounding songs (e.g., hauntings, true crime, and real life disasters) can also fit on a Friday the 13th mix. Add something like, "The Wreck of the Edmund Fitzgerald." <figure rend="Celebrate Friday the 13th Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Websites like Spotify, Pandora, and YouTube may have ready made Friday the 13th playlists.</item></list></item>
<item>Make dark and spooky refreshments. Make dark refreshments, such as cupcakes, cakes, and cookies with black frosting. You can also use cookie cutters to cut out cookies into shapes of bad omens like black cats and full moons. <figure rend="Celebrate Friday the 13th Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try to make 13 of each refreshment for an extra fun twist at the party. However, make sure you have enough snacks to go around.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Planning Fun Activities</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Go ghost hunting. Get a group of friends together to explore haunted ares in your home. You can go on your own ghost hunting trip where you explore places like old theaters, parks, and other allegedly haunted areas in your hometown in search of paranormal activity. <figure rend="Celebrate Friday the 13th Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure you only go in areas open to the public. You don't want to hamper your day by getting in trouble for trespassing.</item></list></item>
<item>Buy a lottery ticket. While Friday the 13th is thought of as an unlucky day, many people find it funny and ironic to buy a lottery ticket. This is a way of showing you won't let superstition get to you. Splurge on something like a scratch off ticket at a local gas station and see if you win any money. <figure rend="Celebrate Friday the 13th Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do some feng shui. Feng shui is the art of designing furniture in a room to bring in good vibes and expel any bad energy. As Friday the 13th is thought to be unlucky, this can be a fun activity to do with a friend on the day. Stop by your local library and buy a book on feng shui or look up the basics online. Spend the afternoon doing some redecorating. <figure rend="Celebrate Friday the 13th Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make 13 cookies or other baked good. If you love baking, spend the afternoon of Friday the 13th making cookies or another baked goods. Make 13 of your baked good to celebrate the day and then share your food with friends and family members. <figure rend="Celebrate Friday the 13th Step 13.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you don't like baking, you can buy 13 of a particular baked good. Stop by a bakery, for example, and get a baker's dozen of donuts.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Avoid scaring people who are clearly worried about the day.</item></list>
</text>
