<text id="autogum_interview_doc249" title="part7_Dr. Joseph Merlino on sexuality, insanity, Freud, fetishes and apathy" shortTile="partdr-joseph-merlino" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-04" dateModified="2013-09-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dr._Joseph_Merlino_on_sexuality%2C_insanity%2C_Freud%2C_fetishes_and_apathy" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  With obsessions such as paraphilias, a person presents things to themselves in a series of questions.  What if I'm really gay?  What if I really want to seduce my patient?  What if I really was aroused by a picture of that child?  If someone comes to you and says, 'I just can't get out of my head the thought that I want to kill my baby', how do you handle such a challenging problem?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  It is very challenging.  Obviously, the risk of potential outcome judges how intense the intervention has to be.  For example, someone who is thinking a lot about wanting to kill his or her child, that is a very serious thing.  An evaluation would have to look very carefully at what is the likelihood of such a thing happening, is it really a symbolic way of expressing something?  For example, 'Susie pissed me off so much I could kill her.'  As opposed to having a vision of slashing her throat, burning her body and tossing her into the ocean.  That would be considered a very serious concern.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  The difference is between having a thought occur, and actually acting it out in one's head?  It's "I thought about wanting to kill my baby," versus, "I'm picturing drowning my baby in the bathtub almost every night I wash her."</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  Yes, that is the very important differential.  Many of us have all kinds of thoughts, like the seduction of a student by a teacher, or those kinds of things.  We have them, it's part of our humanity.  The taboo nature makes it alluring.  But it's when the person <hi rend="italic">fears</hi> losing control, and the ability to control the thinking.  There's a very big difference between a thought and an action.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I have a personal example that makes me laugh.  There is a 60-year-old woman at work named Barbara who I have never met, but to whom I have spoken on the phone.  I don't know many Barbaras, but I remember the opening scene of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Night%20of%20the%20Living%20Dead">Night of the Living Dead</ref></hi> where the brother and sister are in the cemetery and to give the sister, Barbara, a scare, the brother starts going, "Baahbarah, Baaahbarah, they are coming to get you, Barbara."  It makes me laugh to imagine a scenario of calling this 60-year-old Barbara at work and saying that into the phone.  I have acted this out many, many times with my office mates, and it makes us laugh.  It's making me laugh now, the thought of doing something that bizarre—  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>] —And behind this is what?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Behind it is the idea...I would never...</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi> Barbara's the boss?</p>
</text>
