<text id="autogum_voyage_doc161" title="Delhi/South East Delhi" shortTile="delhisouth-east-delhi" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=154068" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Delhi/South East Delhi</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">South East Delhi</hi> is a district of <ref target="Delhi">Delhi</ref> which, like <ref target="Delhi/South%20Delhi">South Delhi</ref>, is high-income and with easy motorway access to the airport. The current district borders of South East Delhi include a number of important sites near the city center, such as <hi rend="bold">Humayun's Tomb</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Purana Qila</hi>, and the southeast part of planned city of <hi rend="bold">New Delhi</hi>.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>The violet and magenta metro lines crisscross South East Delhi.</p>

<p>The 405 bus service from Mori Gate Bus Terminal goes south across South East Delhi.</p>

<head>See</head>
 

<p>The region of South East Delhi can be further broken down into several sub regions like <hi rend="bold">Naizamuddin</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Humayun's Tomb area</hi>, <hi rend="bold">East Kailash</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Kalkaji</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Tughlakabad</hi>.</p>

<head>Humayun's Tomb Complex</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Humayun's Tomb</hi> (Urdu: ہمایوں کا مقبرہ Humayun ka Maqbara) (in south Delhi, near Hazrat Nizamuddin station). daily from sunrise to sunset. is one of Delhi's three <ref target="UNESCO%20World%20Heritage%20Site">UNESCO World Heritage Site</ref>s. - The tomb is in large, immaculately maintained gardens in the Persian <hi rend="italic">Char Bagh</hi> (four corners) style that were thoroughly renovated in 2003 with the Aga Khan's help and are consequently probably the best in Delhi. As you pass through the first gate, you will glimpse the dome of the tomb and enter a floral path leading to the second (West) gate, which now acts as the entrance to the giant central garden. - The centrepiece is the eponymous <hi rend="bold">tomb of Humayun</hi>, the second Mughal emperor. Built starting in 1562, it was the first major Mughal structure in the city and has been described as a predecessor or prototype of <ref target="Agra">Agra</ref>'s Taj Mahal. The structures are, indeed, stylistically similar, although Humayun's Tomb is built from red sandstone, not white marble, and was built by a wife grieving for her husband, not the other way around. You can climb up to the second level (the stairs on the west side are very steep, those on the south side less so), and on the south side you will find the entrance into the main crypt where Humayun is buried. Before you leave, be sure to visit the South Gate, the original royal entrance, from where you can get picture-postcard views without too many tourists in the way. The Humayun's Tomb Complex alsohouses several other tombs and structures, including <hi rend="bold">Isa Khan's Tomb and Mosque</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Barber's Tomb</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Arab Sarai</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Afsarwala Mosque and Tomb</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Ba Halim's Garden and Tomb</hi></item>
</list>

 ₹ 10/250, Indians/foreigners. 


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Isa Khan's Tomb</hi>, Within Humayun's Tomb Complex. As you enter the Humayun's Tomb Complex, the first major structure on your right is the bulbous, octagonal tomb of Iza Khan, a court noble who built it in his own lifetime, some 20 years before Humayun's Tomb</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Barber's Tomb</hi>, Within Humayun's Tomb Complex. In the southeast corner is the Barber's Tomb, also built in the same style. Historians do not know who is buried in this picturesque tomb made of red and grey sandstone.</item>
</list>



<head>Around Humayun's Tomb</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Khan-I-Khana's Tomb</hi>, Nizamuddin East (10 minutes from Jangpura metro station. Right north of Barapulllah Elevated Rd. Take bus #40, 101, 181, 274, 402, 403, 405, 405A, 408, 409, 410, 411, 429, 436, 438 stop Hazrat Nizamuddin). This is a tomb built by Khan-I-Khana in 1598 after his wife's death. He was later buried here in 1627. Khan-I-Khana was a great composer during Akbar's time and also belonged to his Navaratna or his nine jems. The motif is similar to that of the Humayun's tomb.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kos Minar</hi>, Inside National Zoological Park. "Kos Minar," or distance markers are pillars built by Sher Shah Suri in order to measure distance. The distance between two Kos Minar is roughly 8 km. They are massive pillars, 9 m high, built on a high platform.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Nila Gumbad</hi>, Located on the south - eastern corner of Humayun Tomb Complex (Approched from outside the Humayun Tomb past the Sundar Bagh Nursery and Gurudwara Dam Dama Sahib). The octagonal tomb is crowned with a huge dome, covered with dark blue tiles.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sundarwala Mahal</hi> (Sundar Mahal) (North of Humayun's Tomb Complex. Located inside Sundar Bagh Nursery). A rectangular rubble built tomb, with five arches on each side. The chamber below houses a grave but nothing is known about its occupant</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sunderwala Burj</hi> (Sunder Nurserym) (North of Humayun's Tomb Complex. Located inside Sundar Bagh Nursery). Located within the Sundar Bagh Nursery the tomb stands on a square base and has sloped walls. It is crowned with a dome. It is believed to be an pre Mughal tomb but nothing is known about its occupant. Free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bara Batasha</hi> (Bara Batashewala Mahal), Bharat Scouts and Guides Marg, Nizamuddin (Located in the road leading to Nizamuddin station. - North 200 m from Humayun's Tomb). This structure houses the tomb of Mirza Muzaffar who was the son of Babur and Gulrukh Begum. The speciality of this structure is that it has 5 arches on each side.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sabz Gumbad</hi>, Nizamuddin, Sabz Burj? (Located near Humayun's Tomb. - JNL Stadium metro station about one km). Now entry is prohibited inside.. Though it literally means "green dome", its dome is nowhere green in colour. The dome is blue coloured and the tower is believed to be built between 1530 and 1535. The tower is an influence of Central Asian architecture. There are blue and yellow tiles on the drum. Moreover it was used as a police station during British rule.</item>
</list>


<head>Purana Qila</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Purana Qila</hi> (Old Fort, मथुरा रोड), Purana Qila, Mathura Road (Near Delhi Zoo), ☏ +91 11 2435 5387 . 09:00 - 17:00. Purana Qila is the walled citadel of Mughal Emperor Humayun. It later turned into an urban village before becoming a monument. Ruins of the 16th century city of Shergarh, this complex sits on top of what is believed to be the site of Indraprastha, the capital of the Pandavas in the Mahabharata epic. ₹5 for Indians, ₹100 for foreigners. </item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Qila-i-Kuhna Masjid</hi>, Purana Qila. 09:00-17:00. A mosque in the Purana Qila built by Sher Shah Suri</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sher Mandal</hi>, Purana Qila. 09:00 - 17:00. The two storeyed library inside Purana Qila. It is in this library that Humayun fell from stairs and died</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Humayun Darwaza</hi>, Purana Qila. A gate built by Humayun located in Purana Qila. It is the southeast gate of the fort.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Talaqi Darwaza</hi>, Purana Qila. The northern gate of Purana Qila. It has a marble carving of warring lions with a man in front.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Purana Qila Baoli</hi> (Stepwell), Located within the Purna Qila Complex. A small elongagted step well (baoli) located near the Qila-i-Kuhna Masjid and Sher Mandal</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hammam</hi> (Bath House) (Located within the Purna Qila Complex). Located next to the Sher Mandal the ruined hammam (bath house) have remains of terracotta pipes and ribber water chutes.</item>
</list>
</text>
