<text id="autogum_academic_doc430" title="Enhanced Current Reference Calculation to Avoid Harmonic Active Power Oscillations" shortTile="enhanced-current" author="Javier Serrano, Javier Moriano, Mario Rizo, Francisco Javier Dongil" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/21/4075/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Nowadays, distributed energy resources (DER) are leading the change in power generation as a result of the interest in renewable energy systems (RES). These DER could be connected to the utility grid or microgrids through three-phase voltage source converters (VSCs), consequently, the technical requirements, which must be accomplished by the power converter and its control algorithm, are growing. </p>

<p>The trend in multifrequency control using vectorial complex theory has increased the possible features. Among those possibilities, there is an useful one in power oscillations mitigation. Nevertheless, the techniques and objectives fulfilled can vary in each application when dealing with unbalanced grids. </p>

<p>Basically, if the active power oscillations are reduced in the VSC AC side, the low-frequency ripples in the DC-bus will decrease. Firstly, when low-frequency DC ripple currents flow through the DC-bus capacitor, the temperature of the passive component increases, which causes a decreasing lifetime of this component. The batteries also suffer this problematic effect and DC microgrids converters also look for reduced voltage oscillations due to power oscillations. Secondly, the DC bus ripple voltage can have a harmful effect on the induction machine performance characteristics as torque pulsations. Besides, on doubly fed induction generators (DFIGs) for wind turbines, active power oscillations are related to electromagnetic torque ripples that increase the mechanical stress on the turbine system. </p>

<p>The harmonic power oscillations in three-phase three-wire AC electrical systems come from the presence of distorted or unbalanced grids. Therefore, the control strategy aims to regulate the instantaneous active power at a constant value by injecting the suitable currents into the grid. The current reference could be calculated by means of the active and reactive power theory, first introduced in Reference. From that theory, many works have dealt with the regulation of active power oscillations when grid imbalances or grid faults are faced by the power converter. However, these methodologies only remove the second harmonic power ripple due to the appearance of fundamental negative sequence (FNS) voltage and its interaction with the fundamental positive sequence (FPS) current. In distorted grids, there are higher even harmonic power ripples due to other harmonic sequence voltages (−5, +7, −11, +13). Hence, an effective multifrequency current reference calculator is required by the algorithm to accomplish the power ripple removal. </p>

<p>The presented control objective has an unavoidable characteristic in three-phase three-wire systems—the elimination of active power oscillations implies more reactive power fluctuations. Previous publications such as References claimed the elimination of both active and reactive power oscillations, simultaneously. However, this approach in three-wire systems leads to the injection of zero-sequence currents. Hence, the harmonic distortion in the injected current increases dramatically. Even so, there are some works where this injection is regulated. In Reference, two control coefficients are added to control the injection of 3rd order current harmonics, that is, zero-sequence. Nevertheless, most case studies only consider positive and negative sequences because zero-sequence voltages of unbalanced voltage dips do not exist in three-wire systems, nor can they propagate to the secondary side of star-ungrounded or delta-connected transformers in four-wire systems. Even for unbalanced systems with zero-sequence voltage, four-leg inverter topologies can eliminate zero-sequence current with appropriate control. </p>

<p>The multifrequency current reference calculator purpose, just taking into account positive and negative sequences, has been partly fulfilled for DER applications as well as DFIG ones. Both proposals are defined in synchronous reference frames (SRF), hence, coordinate transformations are required. This implies online computation of trigonometric functions, which is usually performed through tables, increasing the memory requirements of the algorithm to get considerable accuracy. However, they are unnecessary because the current reference calculation can be directly implemented in the stationary reference frame (StRF), as Reference has shown for unbalanced grids. However, the StRF approach has been unemployed for the multifrequency control of instantaneous power, which avoids redundant transformations for each one of the dealt harmonics. Besides, grid frequency variations are under the scope in recent years and grid frequency offset around its nominal values decreases the quality of injected currents. Therefore, frequency-adaptive techniques must be applied in order to accomplish the control objective of constant active power, as is shown in this paper. </p>

<p>From the grid code operation point of view, the injected harmonic sequence currents are limited by the total harmonic distortion (THD) standards. In order to achieve standards limitations, any of the harmonic sequence currents could be set to zero or current HD minimization could be performed. Both approaches must sacrifice the cancellation of one power ripple component, and the smallest power ripple is chosen for the optimum performance. Therefore, the optimum current harmonics shaping is also applied in this proposal. </p>
</text>
