<text id="autogum_academic_doc195" title="Harmonic Loads Classification by Means of Currents’ Physical Components" shortTile="harmonic-loads-classification" author="Yuval Beck, Ram Machlev" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/21/4137/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Theoretical Background</head><head> 2.1. Currents’ Physical Component Theory Overview</head>
<p>
The Currents’ Physical Component based power theory deals with the calculations of various powers in a single and three phase systems. The concept is applied usually for the calculation and definition of non-active powers in the presence of non-sinusoidal currents and voltages. The spectra of each waveform are used to define the waveform origin by means of CPC theory. CPC theory was developed by L. S. Czarnecki. Since it was first publicized, there have been developments and adaptations of this power theory. In this section, a short overview of the method is presented with emphasis on the components and the powers which are used in this study as features for uniquely identifying an electric load. </p>

<p>Fourier series is the most general way to present time domain non-sinusoidal harmonic voltage

(1)

where  is the DC component (which is ignored in the rest of the paper since it usually does not exist) and  is the complex RMS value of the voltage at the <hi rend="italic">n</hi>th harmonic, where , and <hi rend="italic">N</hi> is an integer. The harmonic  admittance for the <hi rend="italic">n</hi>th harmonic can be expressed by the complex expression,

(2)

</p>

<p>Multiplying the voltage and admittance yields the resulting current harmonic Fourier series  as follows

(3)

</p>

<p>The active power of such a system is derived from the scalar product of Equations (1) and (3) and therefore only the harmonic components which have the same index in both the voltage and the current will contribute to this power ,

(4)

where  and  are the voltage and current amplitudes at the <hi rend="italic">n</hi>th harmonic, and  is the angle between the voltage and the current at the same harmonic. After the active power is calculated, the equivalent active conductance of the system can be defined as

(5)

where  is the RMS value of the voltage, which can be expressed as

(6)

</p>

<p>The active current  can now be calculated as

(7)

</p>

<p>Subtracting this <hi rend="italic">active</hi> current from the general current yields

(8)

</p>

<p>The imaginary part of Equation (8) can be considered as , the <hi rend="italic">reactive</hi> current, which is  shifted relative to the same voltage harmonic,

(9)

</p>

<p>The remaining part of Equation (8) is called the <hi rend="italic">scattered</hi> current . This current appears if  and it is a measure at voltage  of the source current increase due to a scattering of conductance  around the equivalent conductance  as shown next

(10)

</p>

<p>Nonlinear loads can be considered as harmonic generating loads. In the presence of such loads the direction of energy flow between the source and the load can be decided by investigating the angle between the current and the voltage  of the <hi rend="italic">n</hi>th harmonic. If  then there is an average energy flow from the source to the load and, if , then the energy flow is from the load towards the source. In this case, the harmonics can be sorted into two groups: (1)  is the set of harmonics which are originated at the source; and (2)  is the set of harmonics which are originated at the load. Therefore, the system can be divided into two subnetworks at the measuring point. The first is the source network, denoted by <hi rend="italic">D</hi> and include the  set of harmonics. The second is the load subnetwork, <hi rend="italic">C</hi>, which includes the  set of harmonics. Each subnetwork can be considered to have its own current and voltage, as noted below. </p>

<p>The current which is associated with the  group is called the <hi rend="italic">load generated</hi> current, . The total current can now be written as

(11)

</p>

<p>This current can be rewritten with respect to the  and  disaggregation as follows:

(12)

where <hi rend="italic">N</hi> is the set of all harmonic content in the decomposed total current. This set is divided into the source and load sets  and , accordingly:

(13)

</p>

<p>Note that the load generated current can be also disaggregated to the , , and  components; however, in this work, we limit the amount of features and take into consideration the aggregated . </p>

<p>It can be shown that all components in CPC theory are orthogonal and therefore

(14)

</p>

<p>The same procedure can be implemented to the voltage. Thus, the expression for the voltage, taking into account the direction of the energy flow, is:

(15)

</p>
</text>
