<text id="autogum_interview_doc462" title="Wikinews interviews You-peng Wang of Taipei Electrical Commercial Association" shortTile="wikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-10" dateModified="2008-07-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_You-peng_Wang_of_Taipei_Electrical_Commercial_Association" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews You-peng Wang of Taipei Electrical Commercial Association</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, November 11, 2007</hi></p>
<p>Besides becoming a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Candidates_make_campaign_stop_at_trade_fairs_ahead_of_2008_Taiwan_Presidential_Election">political stomping ground</ref> for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pan-Green%20Coalition">Pan-Green</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pan-Blue%20Coalition">Pan-Blue</ref> coalitions, there are other changes from past years of Taipei Audio Video Fair (TAVF). With those changes in mind, <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:BrockF5">Rico Shen</ref> interviewed You-peng Wang, chairman of the Taipei Electrical Commercial Association (TECA), the main organizer of TAVF, about the 60th year anniversary of TECA and the changes to the show.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<head id="Part_1:_Yuanshan_Hall_in_The_Grand_Hotel">Part 1: Yuanshan Hall in The Grand Hotel</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Rico Shen</hi>: This show features exhibition at the twin halls, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Grand%20Hotel">The Grand Hotel</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taipei%20World%20Trade%20Center">Taipei World Trade Center</ref>, why did TECA decide to exhibit at these two halls?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wang</hi>: In past years of TAVF, many participants promoted subwoofers, loudspeakers, and AV-media devices for sale, but some world-class Taiwanese companies may need good environment for the Hi-End experiences. As of this year, you can see some exhibitors imported a truck container house or rented a guest room for soundproof and high quality experiences and to serve senior AV-media consumers.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Rico Shen</hi>: Particularly the Hi-End quality is the best arrangement for TECA. Also, I sincerely congratulate TECA for the 60th year anniversary. By the way, what are the changes in Taiwan's AV-media industry?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wang</hi>: In the past, some Taiwanese companies served as agencies and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Semiconductor%20fabrication%20plant">foundries</ref> for international manufacturers. They used <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Original%20design%20manufacturer">original design manufacturers</ref> (ODM), manufacturing for other brands. Now, local brands and products (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Original%20equipment%20manufacturer">OEM</ref>) with good quality are increasingly marketed to the world, receiving praise by world-class professional media outside of Taiwan. We at TECA are proud of this success.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Rico Shen</hi>: In recent press conferences, some gaming and video companies cooperated with AV-media companies for high-definition and quality promotion. It caused some companies to become notable. What does TECA think about this trend and fashion? Does TECA support this way of promotion or cooperating?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wang</hi>: We are extremely encouraged by our member companies who cooperate with different companies from the other industries like gaming, video, and information technology. I believe they've seen good factors at high-definition AV-media infrastructure in Taiwan.</p>
<head id="Part_2:_TWTC_Hall_(Taipei_World_Trade_Center)">Part 2: TWTC Hall (Taipei World Trade Center)</head>
<p>Before returning to TWTC, Wang mentioned on the effectiveness of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/soundproofing">soundproofing</ref>, after a visit to a container house, some exhibitors thought soundproofing to be a key factor when experiencing loss-less Hi-End sound and said: "We must provide the best experience and conditions to show the greatest performances of loudspeakers". The interview below mentions the "quality conception".</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Rico Shen</hi>: At the 60th year anniversary of the TECA this year, besides of the twin halls exhibition, what's the reason for the feature of the "Global Audio &amp; Video History Corridor" Pavilion at TWTC Hall?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wang</hi>: If you're involved with the AV-media industry for the first time, you may not understand the evolution of its industry especially "old antiques". We made several old consumer AV-media players available to trace back on the history of the AV-media industry world-wide. And newbies (new consumers who just got involved with this industry) can learn the evolution of this industry by viewing the display of notable AV-media products from the past to the present.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Rico Shen</hi>: I just forgot to say something at Yuanshan, because TAITRA and Taipei Computer Association (TCA) ever held "Exhibitors' Coordination of 2008 Computex Taipei" last month, and I interviewed <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Taipei_Computer_Association_-_a_key_player_at_IT_industry_and_exhibition_in_Taiwan">Enoch Du, the Secretary General of TCA</ref>. Both of those mentioned the recent issue of traffic problems. With the twin halls' exhibition, how the TECA solve the traffic issue during the show?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wang</hi>: We [TECA] submitted the traffic solutions to the Department of Transportation of Taipei City Government and applied the shuttle bus service to Metropolitan Transport Corporation (MTC) for the visitors' convenience to go TWTC or Yuanshan and back. During the weekend hours, MTC will supply more shuttle buses to decrease the waiting period. For the MRT stations, we decided to improve the MRT shuttle bus service at MRT Yuanshan Station rather than Taipei City Hall Station because Capital Bus Co., Ltd has served the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taipei%20101">Taipei 101</ref> shuttle bus for a long period.</p>
<head id="Summary">Summary</head>
<p>Taipei Audio Video Fair in this year is different than the past years. It is not just a "local domestic show" but conjoined education with enjoyment so that the 2007 TAVF takes advantage of the show's contents. The quality of a show is more valuable than the results to keep its good image with the media and the public.</p>
</text>
