<text id="autogum_academic_doc696" title="Homicide Rates and the Multiple Dimensions of Urbanization: A Longitudinal, Cross-National Analysis" shortTile="homicide-rates-multiple" author="Matthew  Thomas Clement, Nathan  W. Pino, Jarrett Blaustein" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5855/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Data and Analysis</head>
<p>
Data used for this study came mostly from the World Bank’s online World Development Indicators, covering the years 2000–2015 for 217 countries (see Appendix A for list of countries). We also drew from the Standardized World Income Inequality Database to access a measure of inequality (see below).  </p>

<p>The World Development Indicators are regularly used by quantitative scholars studying the many dimensions of development. Nevertheless, in the World Bank data, there are many countries that do not have complete longitudinal coverage for the variables being incorporated into the analysis. Therefore, given the panel estimation techniques commonly used in these studies (e.g., Prais–Winsten), if the longitudinal coverage is incomplete for a particular country (i.e., if a country has a single missing value for one variable in one time period), the wave with incomplete data for that country is entirely dropped from the model. As a result, with these particular panel techniques, some countries have more time periods of data than other countries, resulting in what are called unbalanced panels. In this sense, the default for handling missing data in these commonly used longitudinal models is listwise deletion, which can result in a reduction in the overall sample size and the amount of information used for estimation. In our study, we report results from Prais–Winsten models using the default of listwise deletion. </p>

<p>Some quantitative scholars ran longitudinal models after having selected a stratified sample of countries using different criteria (e.g., countries with populations greater than 500,000 or one million; high income countries; least developed countries; Organization for Economic Co-Operation and Development (OECD) Countries; former Soviet republics, etc.). Nevertheless, as seen in Appendix B, many countries meeting these selection criteria, including OECD countries and countries with more than one million people, still have missing values, and with listwise deletion, get dropped from the panel models.  </p>

<p>While some social scientists have utilized advanced imputation procedures (e.g., multiple imputation) to handle missing values, these approaches require the researcher to make numerous decisions affected by uncertainty. As such, statisticians have cautioned against their use, now preferring instead readily available, user-friendly techniques using maximum likelihood for handling missing values in longitudinal data analysis. For instance, we considered the recent statistical work on linear, dynamic panel-data estimation using maximum likelihood and structural equation modeling.  </p>

<p>For linear, dynamic panel-data estimation using maximum likelihood and SEM, Allison et al. provide commands for use in a variety of statistical software packages. For our analysis, we utilized the command xtdpdml in Stata, the syntax of which is in Appendix C, which also provides the syntax for Prais-Winsten regression models with panel corrected standard errors and an AR (1) serial correlation, using the Stata command xtpcse. </p>

<p>Using structural equation modeling (SEM) for longitudinal data analysis allows the option to handle missing values with full information maximum likelihood (FIML). Here we provide a conceptual summary of this technique. With listwise deletion, if a case has a missing value in one time period for one variable but not another variable, that wave of information is still dropped from the longitudinal model. Moreover, with FIML, missing values are not imputed, as they are in mean imputation, linear imputation, or multiple imputation; instead, with FIML, the missing values are mathematically integrated out of the likelihood function; for a detailed review of the mathematics of this technique, see. Thus, for the time period with partially complete coverage, the available information for that case is used to estimate the slope of the variable in the model. FIML has long been a common technique used to handle missing values in SEM, and criminologists have begun using this statistical tool to study the longitudinal variation in homicide rates across cities in the United States. Compared to multiple imputation, the FIML option greatly simplifies the process of handling missing values in longitudinal models.  </p>

<p>While we emphasize the benefits of full information maximum likelihood, we also acknowledge some of its limitations, particularly with respect to problems of computational speed and convergence. Common data issues, such as high collinearity over time and severely unbalanced panel data, can slow down processing speed and prevent convergence. Indeed, linear dynamic panel-data estimation using maximum likelihood and structural equation modeling is a computationally intensive command and is sensitive to model specification and variable selection. Nevertheless, it has many options, and there are a number of other techniques available in various software packages to address these issues. </p>
</text>
