<text id="autogum_academic_doc448" title="Elevation of Trimethylamine-N-Oxide in Chronic Kidney Disease: Contribution of Decreased Glomerular Filtration Rate" shortTile="elevation-trimethylaminenoxide" author="Caroline  C. Pelletier, Mikael Croyal, Lavinia Ene, Audrey Aguesse, Stephanie Billon-Crossouard, Michel Krempf, Sandrine Lemoine, Fitsum Guebre-Egziabher, Laurent Juillard, Christophe  O. Soulage" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6651/11/11/635/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Discussion</head>
<p>
Identified mechanisms for target molecule elevation in CKD patients are either a decrease in renal excretion, an increase in endogenous production or both. Thus, TMAO levels could result from variations in production levels (including dietary precursor intake, TMA endogenous production from gut microbiota, TMA and TMAO intestinal absorption, and FMO3 enzymatic activity) or from its renal excretion. This study was therefore designed to assess the exact changes in TMAO values according to CKD stages as determined by gold standard measurements of GFR and its potential modifications during renal metabolism. </p>

<p>In the present study, we confirmed that TMAO is increased in CKD based on an inverse, although weak, correlation (<hi rend="italic">r2</hi> = 0.388) between plasma TMAO and mGFR. Surprisingly, in all stages of CKD, we did not find any correlation between TMAO levels and its precursors, except a weak correlation with carnitine. Measured clearances of TMAO showed a complete renal excretion of TMAO by glomerular filtration with a steady FE of 105% during CKD, regardless of the stage. Unlike previous studies, we reported no evidence for effective contribution of tubular excretion or reabsorption during renal clearance of TMAO. In hemodialysis patients, we confirmed a greater increase in TMAO even though FR was similar to that of urea. </p>

<p>This study investigated for the first time TMAO levels in all stages of CKD using gold standard measures of GFR. Results of TMAO plasma concentrations in CKD were in good accordance with previous studies. Median TMAO plasma levels found herein were similar to those published by Stubbs et al. in 2015, even though their data was based on estimated GFR. Another study reported a negative correlation between TMAO and mGFR but both data sets were restricted to CKD stages 3 or more severe. To the best of our knowledge, no study has performed urinary clearance measures of TMAO in CKD. Previously, Hai et al. published TMAO clearances in control subjects, reporting a higher clearance of TMAO compared to creatinine, suggesting an active secretion of TMAO. Due to its low molecular weight (75 Da) and soluble non ionizable nature, with minimal protein-bound fraction, we consider TMAO to be entirely filtered through the glomerular basement membrane, which is the main known elimination route for TMAO. Our results showed a likely complete TMAO glomerular filtration with a steady FE of TMAO, regardless of CKD stages. TMAO clearance was similar to that of mGFR, higher than that of urea, and lower than that of creatinine, suggesting that TMAO is neither secreted as creatinine nor reabsorbed as urea by renal tubules. We however cannot exclude that the secretion rate exactly matched the reabsorption of TMAO. Furthermore, high fractional reabsorption of sodium indicates that study participants had no tubular impairment, which reinforces the validity of these data. However, the IQR of TMAO FE showed that some patients exhibited higher or lower clearances of TMAO compared to mGFR; especially in the control group where the median FE of TMAO was 103% [IQR 55–144]. This dispersion could be explained by several factors. First, urinary clearance of TMAO was not assessed at the exact same time points than mGFR, measured by inulin or iohexol clearance. Second, the variability of TMAO excretion could also be related to the amount of ingested TMA precursors. We unfortunately did not administer standardized meals to avoid this bias. Yet, we did not find a significant correlation between plasma levels of TMAO and total protein intake. Moreover, several studies in animal or cellular models have shown involvement of tubular transporters such as organic cation transporter 2 (OCT2) in TMAO cellular uptake and efflux. This, however, has not been confirmed in humans unlike what has been previously described for creatinine. We observed that elevation of TMAO is mostly due to a decrease in mGFR rather than tubular dysfunction. These results are in line with another recent study reporting that urinary TMAO/creatinine ratios (used as a surrogate of TMAO excretion rate) were not significantly different between control and CKD subjects. </p>
</text>
