<text id="autogum_whow_doc156" title="Deliver a Speech Using Visual Aids and Props" shortTile="deliver-speech-using" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2009-12-19" dateModified="2019-09-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Deliver-a-Speech-Using-Visual-Aids-and-Props" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Deliver a Speech Using Visual Aids and Props</head><figure rend="Joseph Estrada delivering a speech at the University of the Philippines.jpg"></figure>You've been tasked with giving a speech or presentation.  The last thing you want to do is bore your audience and you know that the audience would especially want a speaker who is interesting, very informative, and can provide entertainment.  So how do you make your presentation a powerful one?  Through the use of visual aids!
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Engage your audience to capture their attention, and hold it throughout, adding power to your message.</item>
<item>Make the opening of your presentation a powerful one, if you want to gain control of your audience's attention.  Since the first thirty seconds of your speech are probably the most important, you will need some passion for your subject matter here.  In that period of time you must grab the attention of the audience and engage their interest in what you have to say in your speech.</item>
<item>Use an icebreaker like a joke or an introduction.  However, your opening will carry much more impact if it is not only a bit off-the-wall, but also relevant to your message.</item>
<item>Consider opening your speech by launching a small rocket to seize attention.   Just a small rocket pumped up with an air charge or a gyro would be enough to get your point across.  It's simple, it's effective, and it's straight to the point.  In the first thirty seconds, you've grabbed their full attention.</item>
<item>Once your audience is interested and intrigued, move forward and advance to the core part of your speech.  The more of the five senses (sight, hearing, taste, touch, and smell) you can involve in that part of the speech, the better you can hold your audience's interest.</item>
<item>Make use of clear illustrations or examples. As an example, in a company presentation where the speaker was saying that the way forward was a matter, simply, of following a recipe and making sure that all of the ingredients were there.  Just prior to saying this the room was filled with the smell of hot, fresh-baked chocolate chip cookies as the caterers brought in warm plates of gooey cookies.  Her illustration was well received and her presentation continued to compare “the way forward” to her “cookie recipe”.  The message was offbeat and had a strong impact.</item>
<item>When using a PowerPoint presentation as visuals, be careful not to read the slides or the bullet points word-for-word as this might imply that your audience cannot read for themselves.  Rather, use the slides or bullet points as a guide to drive home the strongest parts of the message you are delivering.</item>
<item>Don't read your slides to your audience. Instead create a bond with them as a speaker, by giving your full attention and eye contact to them.  You do not have to keep looking at your slides for long periods of time through the course of your speech.</item>
<item>Do not underestimate the value of a good story.</item>
<item>Try not to speak monotonously and indifferently, which creates a sense of detachment not appreciated by the audience.  It implies a lack of passion for your subject matter and, after all, if you don't care about the subject, why should they?  The stage is not the time to become dispassionate.  Instead, tell your audience a really juicy and riveting story.</item>
<item>Use emotion to sway your listeners.</item>
<item>Watch and copy good speakers. You can learn from the most prominent orators and their secrets of success by telling our audience a good story that illustrates your point.</item>
<item>Learn to make us of a pregnant pause.  Somerset Maugham said that “if you take a pause, make it a long one.”  Scientists determined that being silent (not shouting) serves as an attention grabber, as long as it is on purpose.  Let your silence be thoughtful and deliberate.  You will impress everyone, if after a reflecting pause, you continue your speech with more energy.  Contrasts are a great way to capture attention. Your pauses will have the added benefit of giving you listener the ability to think about your words and really absorb your message.</item>
<item>Involve as many of your audience members' five senses as possible.  Use visual aids and props, tell moving stories, vary your speech patterns, use a pregnant pause, and offer them something to taste, feel, or smell.  Get them up out of their chairs and moving.  Do whatever you can think of to get them involved!</item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><list type="ordered"><item>To give a presentation about the current plight of Ethiopia, as an example, your slide might state that, according to the United Nations, 126,000 children are in urgent need of food and medical assistance there.  However, instead of stating this fact, since your audience is able to read the slide for themselves, you carry on to speak about the drought and skyrocketing global food prices that are causing this problem.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
