<text id="autogum_interview_doc898" title="part4_Eurovision &amp;apos;04 winner Ruslana discusses her paths as singer, spokesmodel, stateswoman and source of inspiration" shortTile="parteurovision--winner" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-03-30" dateModified="2015-05-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eurovision_%2704_winner_Ruslana_discusses_her_paths_as_singer%2C_spokesmodel%2C_stateswoman_and_source_of_inspiration" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>I think this is a very important issue and I will do everything I can to draw attention to it!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You were one of the public faces of the Orange Revolution, and ended up becoming a member of Parliament for a while. What caused you to throw your support behind Viktor Yushchenko so publicly, considering it could have been dangerous not only to your career, but your life? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ruslana</hi>: It seems that staying in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Verkhovna%20Rada">Verkhovna Rada</ref> [<hi rend="italic">Editor's note: The Parliament of the Ukraine</hi>] may [be able to solve] certain problems. Unfortunately, not always. I realized that in our country, if you want to do something for your Motherland – you should do it by yourself; not hoping that one day somebody will hear or help you...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> When you left Parliament, you said, "I still hope for real changes and for a new political generation to come with the mentality to work and not being corrupt." What did you mean by that? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ruslana</hi>: All that I can say is that I'm not in policy any more. And I'm very happy because of that! It seemed to me that [passing policies] could help me make more for my country, but on the contrary, [policy] just tied my hands. I came into politics [with] "[rose-colored] glasses" and [left] there very disappointed...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> When I was asking for research help among the Ukrainian and Russian-speaking Wikipedians, one of the Russians made an off-hand comment to me that stuck. "<hi rend="italic">Ukraine is just a part of Russia anyway.</hi>" When I asked a Ukrainian Wikipedian what that meant to him, he said it upset him. How do you feel when you encounter such attitudes, considering you also release your music to the Russian market?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ruslana</hi>: Ukraine is [an] absolutely independent country, with her own culture, language, [and] history. </p>
<p>After winning on the Eurovision I [received] a lot of invitations [to] Russia. Many friends of mine live there. My grandparents live in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yekaterinburg">Yekaterinburg</ref>. I had a lot of propositions to make a big tour in Russia. I like to give concerts there. We will definitely show Russia my new <hi rend="italic">Wild Energy</hi> show.</p>
<head id="Counterpoint_on_the_East_in_Eurovision">Counterpoint on the East in Eurovision</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> One final political question, and this one relates to Eurovision: I interviewed past winners <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eurovision_'82_winner_Nicole_talks_about_'Ein_bißchen_Frieden',_her_success_and_the_Contest_today">Nicole</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eurovision_'73_winner_Anne_Marie_David_discusses_her_four-decade_career_and_the_Contest,_past_and_present">Anne Marie David</ref>, and both seemed to indicate that "bloc voting" could exist amongst nations; in Nicole's case, she believed it is currently occurring, especially between the countries of Eastern Europe. Your song received votes from nearly every country in Europe, but other winners weren't so fortunate, like the song from Russia last year. Do you believe "bloc voting" exists between the countries of Eastern Europe, and do you feel it is unfair to Western European performers who enter the Contest?</hi></p>
</text>
