<text id="autogum_academic_doc628" title="Spatial Distribution Characteristics and Pollution Evaluation of Soil Iron in the Middle Hanjiang River" shortTile="spatial-distribution" author="Yuting Cheng, Peng Li, Guoce Xu, Kexin Lu, Feichao Wang, Tiegang Zhang, Zhaohong Feng" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4075/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Fe is a necessary trace element for plant growth; it is an important component of various redox enzymes in plants and an essential element for synthesizing chlorophyll. When the Fe content in soil is too low, plant growth and development will be affected, leading to yellow-leaf disease in plants. However, high Fe content can change the physiological state of plants and indirectly affect human health. Soil is the main source of the requisite iron for plants, and under certain conditions, the iron content responds to the level of iron supply in the soil. Although it is a small proportion of the trace elements in soil, it plays a very important role in soil fertility and environmental protection; it also has a high degree of spatial variability, like other soil properties. The soil total iron was generally not less than 1%, but this varies greatly depending on available iron in the soil; low content was 1–5 mg/kg and high content can be up to 1000 mg/kg. Plants grown on calcareous soils are prone to iron deficiency chlorosis, which results in decreased crop yield and growth. According to statistics, the area of soil with potential iron deficiency accounts for 25% to 30% of the world’s land area. The effectiveness of iron mainly depends on the soil’s PH and redox potential. Large areas of calcareous soil are distributed in northwestern China. Due to the high PH and high bicarbonate concentration, the iron deficiency and chlorosis of plants are widespread. At present, research on trace elements in soil has focused on overall elemental content and studies of the available form are relatively few, especially for iron. </p>

<p>Despite the need for more research, the findings of this study suggest that the spatial variability of soil iron is mainly caused by random and systematic variation, indicating that this variability is related not only to natural factors, but also to human activities. Soil iron content in farmland and irrigated fields is higher than in forested land, and soil pH, organic matter, and clay content have a great influence on the soil iron distribution. Hence, the study of soil iron has mainly focused on different land uses, different functions and intensity, and different soil properties, but very few studies have analyzed its spatial distribution characteristics in combination with topographic factors in small watersheds, including pollution evaluation. </p>

<p>Soil iron is affected by plowing, the erosion–deposition–transportation process, soil properties, and soil element properties. These factors cause a non-uniform spatial distribution of Fe, resulting in a deficiency or excess of iron in a particular area, with resulting impacts on plant growth. Information on the spatial distribution of soil total phosphorus and its relationship with land use and topographic factors at watershed scale is therefore of great significance to sustainable regional land use and the estimation of potential environmental pollution, as well as for protecting human health. </p>
</text>
