<text id="autogum_interview_doc026" title="part4_Wikinews attends ComicCon in Bangalore, India" shortTile="partwikinews-attends" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-12-03" dateModified="2019-08-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_attends_ComicCon_in_Bangalore%2C_India" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  If you had something to tell something to your younger self, what would you tell?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JL</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  To my younger self? Just keep going. Because there's a lot of years where, you know, you are not making money and you are working real hard and you don't think you are ever gonna get there, but just keep at it, and you will get there.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  All these years, since the technology has taken over, how has the comic book industry changed in your opinion?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JL</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Well, when I first started; it has got much easier, and it has gotten more global. Like I could work with someone in India and it wouldn't matter because with Wi-Fi and with e-mail and instant message, you know, the old days, you had to FedEx pages, and you had to scan them, and it would take literally twenty minutes to save a giant file on Photoshop and then you would have to upload film and then you would have to drive the film to FedEx. Now, everyone's got their own scanner. Everyone can do things by email. You can upload files by FTP. Like I work with people all around the world now, and before, you almost had to kind of work with the Americans and now its really easy to be global.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Who was your inspiration?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JL</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Um, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kurt%20Vonnegut">Kurt Vonnegut</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fredric%20Brown">Fredric Brown</ref>. They're both science fiction writers.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Are you self-taught?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JL</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Oh, yeah, yeah. Well, as an editor, I read scripts. Again and again and again and you read bad scripts and you read good scripts and you learn from everything. Like even a bad script can teach you what not to do. So I studied all the scripts I read and learned from that. And you learn from mistakes. You, sometimes you write a bad script and then you figure out what you did wrong, you do better next time.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Which is your favourite superhero? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JL</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Plastic Man. And Batman. And Spider-Man.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  If you had a chance to become a superhero, which one would you choose?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JL</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Um, probably someone who could fly. Maybe someone who could be invisible. I don't wanna be Batman. Batman's got too many issues.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What would you recommend to the new people  getting into comic writing and drawing?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JL</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Oh! Well that's two different questions. Like do you want to write? My advice is figure out what you want to do and then focus on that because some people try to do everything and they don't do it well because they are trying to do everything. So figure out really what you want to do and just fine-tune that.</p>
</text>
