<text id="autogum_whow_doc600" title="Choose Personal Core Values" shortTile="choose-personal-core" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-06-11" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Choose-Personal-Core-Values" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Choose Personal Core Values</head><p>Google defines core values as <hi rend="italic">the guiding principles that dictate behavior and action</hi>. Knowing your personal core values can help you make decisions, reduce stress, and live in alignment with your life choices. Identifying these values can be difficult. Learn how to choose personal core values that truly represent the qualities you value most in life; ones that help to guide you in making decisions.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Brainstorm a list of potential values. Think about the roles and ideas that are important to you. <figure rend="Choose Personal Core Values Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Think about the people with whom you interact; your mom, dad, friend, mentor or others that may have a special relationship with you.</item>
<item>Look at how you spend your time. You may hang out with friends regularly, or you may spend a lot of energy fighting for a specific cause.</item>
<item>Examine how you spend your money to discover certain values in yourself. Money is another indicator of what you value. For example, if you tend to buy a lot of books, you may value knowledge or education. If you save money, you may be thrifty.</item>
<item>Reflect on some of your favorite experiences. Identify what you were doing, who you were with, and why it is so memorable.</item></list></item>
<item>Look at a list of values. It can be hard to identify your values on your own, as many can seem abstract, like love or kindness. After brainstorming the values you identify with, look at a list that provides you with options that you may not have considered. <figure rend="Choose Personal Core Values Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Search for different lists online or in books on personal vision or development.</item>
<item>Choose other values you identify with and relate to. Some websites try to put limits on how many core values a person can have. Others state that it does not matter how many core values you have, as long as you live your life accordingly.</item></list></item>
<item>Choose between five and seven core values that stand out above the rest. This will be the hardest part. These will be the values you hold closest and use to guide the decisions you make in your every day life. <figure rend="Choose Personal Core Values Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Take your time. Rushing this process may make you choose values that do not represent the things closest to your heart.</item>
<item>Ask others. If you are not sure what to choose, ask others that know you well to share with you their opinion on what you value.</item></list></item>
<item>Define each core value. First, define each value in your own words. For example, identify what "kindness" means to you or describe what having the value of "family" means. This will be the definition of what the value means to <hi rend="italic">you</hi>. Now look each up in the dictionary. It will be interesting to see the differences in the definitions. <figure rend="Choose Personal Core Values Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Prioritize your core values. Some values will stand out to you over others. Knowing which you hold in higher regard will help you decide where to spend your time and energy. It may also help you work through specific conflicts. For example, you may value both achievement and family. Holding family in a position of higher importance, you are more likely to spend unscheduled time at home instead of the office. <figure rend="Choose Personal Core Values Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Revisit your core values from time to time. Values tend to remain pretty constant throughout one's life. There are circumstances or events in life that may cause you to modify your values or how you define them.</item></list>
</text>
