<text id="autogum_voyage_doc272" title="Tehran" shortTile="tehran" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=35507" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Tehran</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Tehran</hi> (also spelled Teheran) (<ref target="Persian%20phrasebook">Persian</ref>: تهران), is the capital city of <ref target="Iran">Iran</ref>. A bustling metropolis of 14 million people, it sits at the foot of the towering Alborz mountain range.</p>
<head>Understand</head>
<p>Tehran is a cosmopolitan city, with great museums, parks, restaurants, and warm friendly people. It deserves at least a few days of your Iranian itinerary.</p>

<p>The city can be roughly divided into two parts - north and south. The northern districts of Tehran are more prosperous, modern, cosmopolitan and expensive while southern parts are less attractive but cheaper.</p>

<p>At the time of the Zand dynasty, it was a little town that was significant from a strategic point of view. The first of the Qajar kings, Agha Mohammed Khan, named Tehran as the country's capital in 1778, and most of its growth started during the reign of a subsequent Qajar monarch, Fath-Ali Shah. The castle which Agha Mohammed Khan had built was to contain the new majestic buildings.</p>

<p>At the same time, the city's population doubled. Due to the increasing significance of the city, gates, squares and mosques were built and it was at the time of Nassereddin Shah that the city's master sketch was prepared and modern streets were constructed. Later, huge central squares like Toopkhaneh square (now Imam Khomeini) and quite a few military buildings were built. Even though the Qajar dynasty was in a period of decline, Tehran soon took the shape of a modern city. The structure of large government buildings, new streets, recreation centres, urban service organizations, and academic and methodical centres were started, even as most of the old gates and buildings were destroyed and the city's old architectural fabric replaced by a contemporary one.</p>

<p>Tehran has also earned itself an unenviable reputation as a smog-filled, traffic-clogged and featureless sprawl of concrete bursting at the seams with 14 million residents. But you can also find an endless number of nice and cosy places in and around the city - if you know where to look. Tehran is a city of more than 800 parks, all well-kept. The city is nearly a mile high above sea level and as a result is cooler than other cities in the Middle East. Summer temperatures are around 32°C or 90-95°F. The air tends to be very dry.</p>

<p>A combination of factors make Tehran a pleasant place to visit: the dry climate which is cool in the evenings, the proximity of the mountains, the parks and gardens where flowers blossom all through the year, the alleys of trees in the avenues or even smaller streets, and even the water that runs down from the upper city along deep and wide gutters which look like small rivers during spring. The Alborz range on the north of Tehran, which hosts the highest peak in Iran, provides fantastic conditions for ski lovers in the winter. In winter, the mountain hotels and ski clubs at Shemshak, and Dizine are full several days a week. Some specialist skiers consider the snow value in northern Tehran to be one of the most excellent in the world.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>For information on Iranian visas please refer the <ref target="Iran%23visas">Iran#visas</ref> page.</p>
<head>By plane</head>
 <hi rend="bold">Imam Khomeini International Airport</hi> ( IKA ) (55 km southwest of the city center, Robat Karim railway station (ایستگاه راه آهن رباط کریم) around 3 km northwest near Line 1 'Kahrizak' ~ 20 km NE). The only airport in Tehran to which international passenger flights operate. 

<p><hi rend="italic">Ground transportation</hi>:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="italic">Metro</hi> easiest way to reach city center is by metro line. Line number 8 connects Airport Terminal A with metro line 1 (red line) (75000 rials, that can be used for the full network, Mar 2019). Runs irregularly: 06:50, 08:10, 09:30, 10:50, 12:10, 13:30, 14:50, 16:10, 17:30, 18:50, 20:10.</item>
<item> <hi rend="italic">Buses</hi> between the airport and the city (e.g. Haram Metro station) run every 30-60 min 07:00-23:00. They leave right in front of the main exit and cost 20,000-30,000 rial. There are unconfirmed reports of a shuttle bus operating between IKIA and Mehrabad Airport every 4–5 hours.</item>
<item> <hi rend="italic">Taxis</hi> cost a fixed rate of 800,000 rials (or US$25 or €20 as of Oct 2017), ask at the taxi counter. The drive to/from the city center takes 45 minutes without traffic, but can take upwards of 90 minutes with traffic. There is a booth organizing taxis right outside the arrivals hall. You can also bargain with taxis dropping off passengers at the arrivals hall because otherwise they would have to go back to Tehran empty. Taxis to the nearest metro station (Haram-e-Motahhar) cost 500,000 rials.</item>
<item> <hi rend="italic">Shuttle taxis and green minibuses</hi> operate between the airport and Shahed Station on the red line of the metro. This can be a convenient option going to the airport from town, but finding the shuttle taxis at the airport will be difficult as many don't stop there. At 7000 rials for a metro ticket and 40,000 rials for a shuttle taxi (they will try to rip you off or charge for bringing in luggage even if there is space, so make sure to only occupy one seat if you don't want to pay extra), it is probably the cheapest option from town that doesn't require waiting a long time for the bus (shuttle taxis leave when full). At Shahed station, get out to the parking area (there is only one exit and you can't miss it) and on the very left you will see green minibuses. It takes about 30-40 min from there to the airport. Last one departs around 21:30.</item>
<item> <hi rend="italic">Metro Line 1 (Red) </hi>During daytime there is a metro from IKA to Tehran. The trains run hourly so check schedule (Sep 2017).</item>
</list>


 <hi rend="bold">Tehran's Mehrabad airport</hi> ( THR ). Mehrabad is only used for domestic and cargo flights. It is connected to Tehran Metro Line 4. 

<p>Despite the warnings in some travel guides, there is no exit fee for foreign travellers, neither in Mehrabad nor in Imam Khomeini Airport. The <hi rend="italic">exit fee</hi> applies to foreign travellers only when leaving Iran on land or by sea.</p>
</text>
