<text id="autogum_voyage_doc366" title="Viñales" shortTile="viales" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=37937" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Viñales</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Viñales</hi> is a beautiful and lush valley in <ref target="Pinar_del_Rio_%2528province%2529">Pinar del Río</ref> province of <ref target="Cuba">Cuba</ref>, with a population of around 10,000. It's about 26 km north of the city of Pinar del Río, and was declared a <ref target="UNESCO%20World%20Heritage%20Site">UNESCO World Heritage Site</ref>. This article also covers the town by the same name.</p>

<p>The mountains are beautiful, the farmers grow the best tobacco, and tourists come every day by the busload.</p>

<head>Landscape</head>

<p>Cuba was once covered by limestone ("karst"). Much of this limestone has eroded away, leaving mountains with steep sides and rounded, jungly tops. The mountains are called <hi rend="italic">mogotes</hi>, which means "haystacks." Many <hi rend="italic">mogotes</hi> have caves. Several caves are developed for tourists to visit.</p>

<p>The red farmland and unique microclimate produce the best cigars in the world. Some tobacco farms are set up for tourist tours.</p>

<head>People</head>

<p>Start at a tourist office or your hotel or <hi rend="italic">casa particular</hi>. Point out something in the guidebook you'd like to see or do, and offer to pay someone to take you there. Or offer to pay for a Spanish lesson or a salsa lesson. Hire a local guide for a few hours and you'll make a friend, and he or she will introduce you to his or her family, and they'll invite you to do more stuff, and you won't be bored the rest of your visit.</p>

<p>But be aware of what's illegal to pay for. You can't pay someone to drive you somewhere, unless it's a licensed taxi. You can't pay for lodging, unless it's a licensed <hi rend="italic">casa particulares</hi> (bed&amp;breakfast).</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.viazul.com/">Viazul</ref></hi> runs buses twice a day between <ref target="Havana">Havana</ref> (12 <ref target="Cuba%23Money">CUC</ref>) via <ref target="Pinar%20del%20Rio">Pinar del Rio</ref>.</p>
<p>There’s an early morning bus to <ref target="Cienfuegos">Cienfuegos</ref> and <ref target="Trinidad">Trinidad</ref>. Buses arrive and leave opposite of the ticket office near the central town square.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Viazul ticket office</hi>, Salvador Cisneros, 63 A (on main street opposite town square). Open daily. They will book your bus to Havana, and can organize transfers in smaller coaches to <ref target="Soroa">Soroa</ref>, <ref target="Las%20Terrazas">Las Terrazas</ref> and other locations.</item>
</list>



<head>By shared taxi</head>
<p>You will likely be offered a <hi rend="italic">collectivo</hi> already at the Havana bus station. They run to Viñales for 20 CUC per person.</p>
<p>Transport back can also be found by taxi touts near the Viazul ticket office. One typically inquires at least a day before the intended departure to make a taxi reservation. The driver will then pick you up at your <hi rend="italic">casa</hi>. It is easiest to find a transport for morning departures.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Collectivos</hi> also run to other destinations such as <ref target="Cienfuegos">Cienfuegos</ref> (40 CUC) <ref target="Trinidad">Trinidad</ref> (40 CUC or more) if there is sufficient demand. Beware that taxi drivers will sometimes claim to have transport to Trinidad or Cienfuegos, but in fact require a change of vehicle in Havana, which may involve re-negotiating the price for the remaining trip.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Shared taxis for <ref target="Pinar%20del%20Rio">Pinar del Rio</ref> </hi> (at the south junction of the main street). These run relatively frequently and depart on demand once the car is full. 1 CUC.</item>
</list>


<head>Fees and permits</head>
<p>Entrance to the valley is free. Some attractions like the <hi rend="italic">Cueva de la piscina</hi> will charge a fee though.</p>

<head>Viñales</head>
<p>The town is easily walkable on foot. Most amenities such as banks and restaurants cluster on the main street (<hi rend="italic">Salvador Cisneros</hi>) and accommodation is found everywhere off this street, esp <hi rend="italic">Calle Rafael Trejo</hi> which runs on south parallel to the main street essentially only consists of <hi rend="italic">casas particulares</hi>.</p>

<head>The valley</head>

<p>There is a green minibus that takes tourists around the valley. For 5 CUC you can ride all day, with stops at the tourist hotels, in the village, at the caves and other sights.</p>

<p>Many sights are in the proximity of the city and not more than 4km away. As such it’s possible to walk, also riding on a bike or a horse may be less strenous esp. considering the often very hot weather. Other sights such as the <hi rend="italic">Santo Tomás</hi> cave are further away and out of walking distance.</p>

<p>To get there hire a cab, rent a bike or join an organized tour.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Calle Salvador Cisneros</hi>. The main street was named after Salvador Cisneros Betancourt, who was a leader in the war of independence (1868-1878) and later was President of Cuba from 1895 to 1897. Today it’s more and more covered with all sorts of restaurants that cater to tourists.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Casa de la Cultura</hi>. In the central plaza, the Casa de la Cultura puts on events every day (or night), including music, fashion shows, and children's events. cover charge typically ~1 CUC.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Central plaza</hi>. Also on the central plaza is an art gallery and the church. On Saturday mornings there's a farmer's market at the plaza.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Museo Municipal</hi> (further down the main street). The small museo municipal, former home of independence heroine Adela Azcuy.</item>
</list>


<head>Around Viñales</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Parque Nacional Vinales visitor centre</hi>. The park covers 150 km² and the visitor centre located close to the hotel Los Jazmines offers information, hiking and guides. (2 km from Vinales). The visitor centre does not have a lot to see, some wall charts with walking routes and a small model of the valley. It is the view that is stunning and from here you can organise your excursions into the valley.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mural de la Prehistoria</hi>. Perhaps the worst tourist attraction in Cuba. In 1961 Fidel Castro visited the beautiful <hi rend="italic">valley of the two sisters</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Valley de Dos Hermanas</hi>) 3 km west of Viñales. He commissioned a cliff to be painted with snails, dinosaurs, and a family of cavepersons, in garish colors! There's a restaurant, bar, and gift shop. To be fair, reputedly, the food in the restaurant is excellent and the live music is good. Also there's horseback riding. So consider visiting the mural and doing something other than looking at the mural. You don’t need to pay the entrance fee to see the painted mountain cliff, its visible from the road already.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">El Palenque de los Cimarrones</hi>. Tiny museum as you walk through a smaller cave (Cueva de San Miguel) showing how slaves hid out in centuries past. Restaurant at back with slave show, mostly for bus tours. Cave is best known for its disco at the weekends where all the locals go to hang out. Food also served. (4km from Vinales)</item>
</list>
</text>
