<text id="autogum_news_doc522" title="Scottish Labour elect Kezia Dugdale new leader" shortTile="scottish-labour-elect" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-08-15" dateModified="2016-06-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scottish_Labour_elect_Kezia_Dugdale_new_leader" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Scottish Labour elect Kezia Dugdale new leader</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 15, 2015</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Kezia Dugdale MSP, new leader of Scottish Labour. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scottish_Labour">Scottish Labour</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kezia%20Dugdale">Kezia Dugdale</ref> MSP (Member of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scottish_Parliament">Scottish Parliament</ref>) has been elected as the new leader for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scottish_Labour">Scottish Labour</ref>, it was announced today in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stirling,%20Scotland">Stirling</ref>. Dugdale replaces former MP <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jim_Murphy">Jim Murphy</ref> who resigned in June following Labour losing 40 of its 41 Scottish seats in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Kingdom_general_election,_2015">UK general elections</ref>. Dugdale received 72.1% of the vote, beating out <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ken%20Macintosh">Ken Macintosh</ref> who got 27.9% of the vote. Alex Rowley MSP was elected deputy leader.</p>
<p>Dugdale — the youngest Scottish Labour leader at age 33, and the third woman to take the role — said she will now work "night and day" to try and restore Labour's position in Scottish politics. In a statement to voters, she tried to appeal to Labour's lost supporters: "Take another look at the Scottish Labour party. I am not so presumptuous to ask instantly for your vote. But at the recent election 700,000 of you stuck with us but many chose someone else. All I ask is that you take a fresh look at the Scottish Labour party under my leadership."</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harriet%20Harman">Harriet Harman</ref>, who is acting leader while the leadership elections for the national party are underway, welcomed Dugdale's election: "I would like to congratulate Kezia Dugdale on being elected as the Leader of the Scottish Labour Party, and Alex Rowley on being elected as Deputy Leader. They will be leading the historic task of rebuilding our Party in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scotland">Scotland</ref>, reconnecting Labour with the people of Scotland and re-energising the links between our party in Scotland, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wales">Wales</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/England">England</ref>, and I know they will lead the party in Scotland forward with energy and commitment to Labour values and principles and will have the full support of the whole of the Labour Party."</p>
<p>Derek Mackay from the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scottish_National_Party">Scottish National Party</ref> said a change of leadership won't fix "the deep, deep problems which the Labour Party in Scotland now faces".</p>
<p>During the election campaign, Dugdale criticised the length of time it was taking to select a new national party leader, both for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Labour_Party_(UK)">UK Labour</ref> and for the Scottish party, and expressed concern UK candidate <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jeremy_Corbyn">Jeremy Corbyn</ref> would not be electable as Prime Minister, telling <hi rend="italic">The Guardian</hi>: "I want there to be a Labour government; otherwise I'm wasting my time. I don't want to spend my whole life just carping from the sidelines. [...] Here's a guy that's broken the whip 500 times. So how can the leader of the party enforce discipline with that record?"</p>
<p>This week, she said on BBC Good Morning Scotland: "That is hardly the most critical thing that anybody has said about his campaign. I am excited about his campaign and many people across the country are."</p>
<p>Deputy leader of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scottish_Conservatives">Scottish Conservatives</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jackson%20Carlaw">Jackson Carlaw</ref> described her change of tune on Corbyn's leadership bid as a "spectacular flip-flop": "Only last week she was attacking Mr Corbyn by warning that a Labour party led by him would be 'carping from the sidelines'. Now she says that they 'share the same views'. What appears to have changed her mind is the dawning realisation that Mr Corbyn is heading for a landslide victory and she needs to get on board if she's going to win her own election campaign."</p>
</text>
