<text id="autogum_interview_doc432" title="part1_French workers use threats in compensation demand" shortTile="partfrench-workers" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-07-17" dateModified="2019-09-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/French_workers_use_threats_in_compensation_demand" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What is your take on the present situation and the rising tensions, is it morally justified?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JLG worker</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> The experience of these lay-offs is of punishment, while those who have made mistakes at higher levels are always protected. Executives with high salaries unfortunately seem to be more concerned with their own careers, to satisfy instructions from abroad, then with efficiency and pragmatism. The perception of supine obedience to directives from the U.S. is difficult to accept.</p>
<p>Things must change in the future, in order for the course to be corrected to ensure the good health of the JLG company, we are well aware of it. The changes involved, the massive dismissals, give the semblance of a brutal and symbolic pruning of the wage bill of the company, without touching and reducing costs or increasing the efficiency of the better-paid.</p>
<p>The best paid ten at JLG France obtained a 17% increase [in salary] for the year of 2008. The case of an expensive car park facility, that it is not planned to be reduced, is another strange case given the current crisis. Bizarrely, on the part of the technicians and employees on site, we are not offered similar increases: we are offered redundancies with a € 3,000 payoff.</p>
<p>While this is legal, it is not morally acceptable. A company is an organism, it is not just legal contracts and wages that ensure the loyalty of employees, but also the moral contract, of good governance, equity, efficiency. These moral conditions do not seem to have been offered to us. The proposal for a € 3000 payoff was ridiculous. There is a willingness on the part of employees to work, and behind these to-be dismissed employees, families who want to continue to progress, to educate their children, to continue living in their homes, to live with dignity. </p>
<p>The tension created is deplorable. We would all have preferred an amicable agreement from the beginning of the dispute. The tensions are the result of two forces, both equally responsible: </p>
<list type="unordered"><item>The knowledge, by we the employees, of the wealth created by our labour in recent years, and our pride;</item>
<item>Refusal of the French management in the context of the dislocation of the company to ensure an [equitable] distribution of this wealth.</item></list>
<p>We are pleased that the situation defused that night with dignified exits and fairness to all.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Had you considered other forms of pressure, are others in the movement you are in contact with as "hardball" as you are?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JLG worker</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Yes, for sure! But we are trapped in a situation of general apathy, low unionisation, and the psychology of a media who are interested only in the spectacular! We first tried 3 months of negotiations in which we achieved almost nothing. In a second step, we embarked on 3 weeks of strikes and a blockade of the premises with calm and without overspill, however we did not achieve much more, all this has driven up tensions</p>
</text>
