<text id="autogum_interview_doc323" title="part10_John Reed on Orwell, God, self-destruction and the future of writing" shortTile="partjohn-reed-orwell" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-18" dateModified="2015-01-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Reed_on_Orwell%2C_God%2C_self-destruction_and_the_future_of_writing" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How do you raise your children?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  I tortured myself about this before I had kids, and now that I have them, there a couple of things that make it very difficult for me to choose any one particular religion.  I can't forgive <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman%20Catholic%20sex%20abuse%20cases%20by%20country">Catholicism for the kind of pederasty that it allowed</ref>.  It's hard for me--Jewish--I can't--I don't even know, I'm afraid to publish that, but--I can't, you know, abide a religion that would distinguish a child from its parents, to say this child isn't part of this religion because its mother isn't.  To me, that's exactly the kind of distinction that makes religion sinister and destructive.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How do you circumvent that in the rearing of children, then?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  I'm thinking of something like a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unitarian">Unitarian</ref>.  I would do a Gnostic church if they really existed.  And I know they sort of exist, but they seem a little small.  I think Unitarian is probably as close as I'm going to come.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why would you be afraid to have it published that you're part Jewish?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  First of all, I'm tired of being Jewish.  I'm tired of the fact that I'm counted among Jewish people; when I'm at a funeral, and there have been a lot of funerals on that side of the family, they're perfectly happy to have me carry a casket.  But you know, I'm not part of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Promised%20Land">Promised Land</ref>, and I'm tired of the selective tally.  Also, people say that Judaism is a philosophy, and then it comes up:  "Are your kids Jewish?  Is their mother Jewish?"  I say, "No"; to me, that makes it a religion, you know?  I'm getting <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baptism">baptized</ref> in the next few months, because the Gnostic principle--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  [chuckles] As a big "Fuck you" to Judaism, or--?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Partly, but I appreciate Gnostic principle of--the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gospel%20of%20Thomas">Gospel of Thomas</ref> is meaningful to me.  I like it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So you're going to be baptized into the Gnostic church?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Well, this is the other thing.  I've got to decide exactly how to do it.  Baptism is looked at in different ways contingent on what Christian group we're talking about.  Some think it's okay to baptize children.  Others think it's part of a later conversion in life.  For me, the ones that think it's okay to baptize children, that's precisely what I don't want, because the idea that a child wouldn't be accepted, blessed by God regardless, whether or not they've been baptized--to say that God would have anything against any child is just disgusting to me.  I can't forgive it.</p>
</text>
