<text id="autogum_news_doc196" title="AFC Asian Cup: Lights fail as Korea draw with Saudi Arabia, Iran defeat Uzbekistan" shortTile="afc-asian-cup-lights" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-07-12" dateModified="2012-05-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/AFC_Asian_Cup%3A_Lights_fail_as_Korea_draw_with_Saudi_Arabia%2C_Iran_defeat_Uzbekistan" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>AFC Asian Cup: Lights fail as Korea draw with Saudi Arabia, Iran defeat Uzbekistan</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 12, 2007</hi></p>
<p>A lighting failure five minutes from the end interrupted the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2007%20AFC%20Asian%20Cup">2007 AFC Asian Cup</ref> Group D match between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Korea%20Republic%20national%20football%20team">Korea Republic</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saudi%20Arabia%20national%20football%20team">Saudi Arabia</ref>.</p>
<p>The match, played at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bung%20Karno%20Stadium">Bung Karno Stadium</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jakarta">Jakarta</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Indonesia">Indonesia</ref>, was stopped for 27 minutes after the lighting on one half of the stadium suddenly turned off.</p>
<p>At the time of the disruption - 84 minutes 35 seconds played - the match was delicately poised at one goal apiece.</p>
<p>An spokesperson for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asian%20Football%20Confederation">Asian Football Confederation</ref> has said that the lighting failure was 'due to problems with power around Jakarta city'.</p>
<p>Referee <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark%20Shield">Mark Shield</ref>, from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia">Australia</ref>, immediately stopped the match after the lights turned out. Under tournament rules, officials had one hour to get the lights and play restarted before the match would have to be abandoned. An emergency generator was used to restore some of the knocked-out lights to a sufficient level for playing, allowing Shield to restart play after the lengthy delay.</p>
<p>The match was an eventful one generally, especially after half time. Both teams played a cautious first half which was devoid of any real scoring opportunities.</p>
<p>However, after the break, Korea went 1-0 ahead through striker <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Choi%20Sung-Kuk">Choi Sung-Kuk</ref> after sixty-six minutes. A curling cross from the left-hand wing found the head of Sung-Kuk, who moved in front of the Saudi defender and headed the ball into the bottom right-hand corner of the net.</p>
<p>Eleven minutes later, referee Shield awarded Saudi Arabia a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/penalty%20kick">penalty kick</ref> after <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malek%20Mouath">Malek Mouath</ref> was adjudged to have been fouled inside the penalty box by a Korean defender. Captain <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yasser%20Al-Qahtani">Yasser Al-Qahtani</ref> stepped up and converted to level the scores 1-1 after seventy-seven minutes.</p>
<p>After play was restarted due to the power failure, Saudi Arabia had an excellent chance to win the match with the final kick of the game. Striker <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saad%20Al%20Harthi">Saad Al Harthi</ref> missed a one-on-one opportunity with the Korean goalkeeper, pushing his shot wide.</p>
<p>The draw leaves hosts <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indonesia%20national%20football%20team">Indonesia</ref> on top of the Group D table after defeating Bahrain 2-1 in the opening match of the group.</p>
<p>In Group C, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iran%20national%20football%20team">Iran</ref> has come back from a goal down to defeat <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uzbekistan%20national%20football%20team">Uzbekistan</ref> 2-1 at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National%20Stadium,%20Bukit%20Jalil">Bukit Jalil Stadium</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kuala%20Lumpur">Kuala Lumpur</ref>.</p>
<p>Iran conceded the lead to Uzbekistan on sixteen minutes when Iranian defender <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rahman%20Rezaei">Rahman Rezaei</ref> scored an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/own%20goal">own goal</ref>. Trying to head the ball back to his goalkeeper <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hassan%20Roudbarian">Hassan Roudbarian</ref>, Rezaei only managed to head the ball over Roudbarianand into the back of his own net.</p>
<p>The score remained 1-0 until the fifty-fifth minute, when Iran equalised through <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seyed%20Jalal%20Hosseini">Seyed Jalal Hosseini</ref>. Hosseini headed a fast-moving <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corner%20kick">corner kick</ref> from the right hand side by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mehdi%20Mahdavikia">Mehdi Mahdavikia</ref> past Uzbekistan's defence to equalize.</p>
<p>Iran then went ahead after seventy-eight minutes after midfielder <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andranik%20Teymourian">Andranik Teymourian</ref> provided a through-pass which found <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Javad%20Kazemian">Javad Kazemian</ref> on the edge of the penalty box. Kazemian struck his shot sweetly to beat the goalkeeper and made the scoreline 2-1.</p>
<p>No further goals came, however Iranian coach <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amir%20Ghalenoei">Amir Ghalenoei</ref> was sent from the sidelines by the referee due to an indiscretion. </p>
<p>The result puts Iran on three points and at the top of Group C, however they trail <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/China%20national%20football%20team">China</ref>, who defeated <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malaysia%20national%20football%20team">Malaysia</ref> 5-1 a day prior, on goal difference.</p>
</text>
