<text id="autogum_interview_doc855" title="part0_Q and A with New Zealand Prime Minister hopeful" shortTile="partq-new-zealand" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-05-17" dateModified="2019-09-19" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Q_and_A_with_New_Zealand_Prime_Minister_hopeful" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Q and A with New Zealand Prime Minister hopeful</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, May 18, 2008</hi></p>
This article is part of the series
<figure><caption>New Zealand General Election</caption></figure>
<hi rend="bold">New Zealand General Election</hi>
<hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Other election coverage</hi></hi>
<list type="unordered">
<item><ref target="/wiki/Q_and_A_with_New_Zealand_Prime_Minister_hopeful">Q and A with New Zealand Prime Minister hopeful</ref></item></list>
Background
<p>Wikipedia, Wikinews' sibling project, has in-depth background articles on:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Political%20parties%20in%20New%20Zealand">Political parties in New Zealand</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20Zealand%20Parliament">New Zealand House of Representatives</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Politics%20of%20New%20Zealand">Politics of New Zealand</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Additional%20Member%20System">Mixed Member Proportional voting system</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20Zealand%20elections">Previous New Zealand General Elections</ref></item></list>
<p>John Key is the leader of the New Zealand National Party and with the New Zealand General Election this year, Wikinews' Gabriel Pollard spoke to John Key via email. </p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Are you taking much notice over the polls that currently show National leading by a big margin?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">John Key</hi>: No. National remains focussed on putting together a series of policies that will lift living standards, raise after-tax incomes and deliver better social services alongside First World infrastructure. The polling in election year is always likely to bounce around a bit, and we take nothing fore granted.  Helen Clark is desperate for a fourth term, so I fully expect they will be spending taxpayer money with little regard for the longer term consequences.  National will remain focussed on delivering on the real issues affecting New Zealanders, like after-tax incomes which are drifting further and further behind Australia, a health system which has delivered thousands of bureaucrats, and fewer operations on a per capita basis, and an education system that doesn’t fail thousands of our children.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Do you take any signs of possible outcomes in New Zealand based on the election result in Australia last year?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.K.</hi>: No. I don’t think you can take the Australian result and superimpose that on New Zealand.  For starters, we are working in an MMP environment, and we are working under a very different set of Government-designed election laws that were set up to sow confusion, deny free-speech, and curb Labour’s critics in election year. Nevertheless, as I travel around the country I do get the sense that people are tired of the Labour-led Government, and hungry for some new ideas and fresh thinking. National is under no illusion as to the challenges that lie ahead, not just in terms of the election but more importantly, for the future direction of this country.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">If elected, what is the first major reform you would like to undertake?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.K.</hi>: My top priority is to start restoring the faith of New Zealanders in New Zealand.  This is a great country with huge potential and a bright future.  I want more Kiwis to believe that their future, and their children’s future, lies here in New Zealand, not Australia or elsewhere. In terms of policy – I want to share more of the gains from economic growth with hardworking New Zealanders through a programme of ongoing tax cuts.  In National’s view, the Government should spend taxpayer money with the same discipline that households do, and return the taxes that it does not need to the people who paid them.</p>
</text>
