<text id="autogum_interview_doc171" title="part4_Canada&amp;apos;s Don Valley West (Ward 25) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-don-valley" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-16" dateModified="2007-06-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Don_Valley_West_%28Ward_25%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process?  </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> As President of a community association for 12 years, I saw the threats and challenges faced by one stable residential community.  They ranged from inappropriate and intrusive development to a property assessment system which resulted in unstable annual reassessments.  Through my colleagues, presidents of other community associations, I learned that the problems were not isolated in my community.  They were systemic across the ward, the City – and indeed, across the province.</p>
<p>I saw cases of unfair impact on homeowners who had previously believed that the Official Plan and the zoning by-law would protect their quiet enjoyment of their homes, apartments and their investment in the community.  In every case, I felt there were ways for governments – particularly Toronto City Council – to protect our stable residential communities.  In conversation and discussion with people in Ward 25, I found it resonated.  Many people were and are impacted by inappropriate development.  People want a planning process which serves them.</p>
<p>I developed an election platform in 2003 around protection of our stable residential communities.  Once elected, I set out to implement it, against entrenched interests – with considerable success in many aspects, for example:  Official Plan amendments, changes in the Committee of Adjustment, and new freedom for people to access previously withheld building permits.</p>
<p>There is more to do.  The new harmonized zoning by-law coming before Council will require provisions to close existing loopholes.  The planning process reform must be completed – to ensure that people are engaged earlier and meaningfully consulted on development applications in their community.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent this particular ward on council? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> My wife Liz and I have lived in Ward 25 for 21 years, raising our three sons, Neil, Scott and David here.  Ward 25 is a vibrant, wonderful place to live, work and enjoy life.  Ward 25 residents are proud and protective of their neighbourhoods.  Our employment areas on Leslie and Scarsdale and our commercial areas are thriving - but some are at risk from purchase and conversion to residential uses.  Our parks and natural areas are magnificent.  The ravines of the Don Valley are life-giving ribbons of green that benefit the entire City.  Ward 25 is a jewel in Toronto.  I want the best for it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> To be a conscientious Councillor is to be deeply involved in the community.  It requires very frequent attendance at local events and meetings.  It is critical for a Councillor to hear what people have to say about matters affecting their communities, about their hopes and desires for their communities.  I attend many evening meetings with ratepayer groups, with tenant groups, with school organizations and with other community groups.  Doing that is more than a full time job.  Consequently, I've temporarily deferred most voluntary activity – particularly my long-time involvement in my own ratepayer association where I was President for twelve years.  I've also been a junior boys' baseball coach and junior boys' curling team advisor.  My wife Liz, however, maintains her volunteer work.  For many years she was active in Home and School associations as our kids worked their way through school – serving as President from time to time.  As well, she was a volunteer for many years at Tennis Canada – rising to the position of Volunteer Co-ordinator for the annual men's/women's Canadian Open Tennis Championship.  And now, she is a volunteer at Sunnybrook Hospital.</p>
</text>
