<text id="autogum_whow_doc340" title="Maintain Psychological Health" shortTile="maintain-psychological" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-10-27" dateModified="2019-04-25" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Maintain-Psychological-Health" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Maintain Psychological Health</head><p>The World Health Organization describes psychological, or mental, health as "a state of well-being in which the individual realizes his or her own abilities, can cope with the normal stresses of life, can work productively and fruitfully, and is able to make a contribution to his or her community." Just like physical health, mental health needs to be maintained during times of low emotional stress, in order to make you resilient to future troubles. Doctors believe that psychological and physical health are perpetually linked, and both should be actively maintained. There are a number of ways you can promote mental health, through physical activity, lifestyle changes, community contact and more. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Physical Maintenance</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Eat a balanced diet. Good nutrition can give you all the nutrients your body needs to be physically and mentally well. Overeating and eating junk food are negative influences that can affect your mood, weight and self-confidence. <figure rend="Parboil Broccoli Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Exercise regularly. Cardiovascular exercise releases endorphins, which lift your mood and positively affect your quality of life. Exercise also builds self confidence in managing your life. <figure rend="Get Rid of Period Cramps when Medicine Does Not Work Step 1Bullet1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Sleep well. Resting your mind for at least 8 hours per day through sleep helps to manage stress and improve your physical and emotional well-being. High stress and lack of sleep can compromise your immune system and create opportunity for sickness. <figure rend="Get Curly Hair Naturally Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get a dose of sunlight to help your mood. Sunlight produces serotonin in your brain, a mood-enhancing chemical. Doctors suggest you go outside and sit in the sun for 15 minutes a day, or 30 minutes if you need a big mood boost. <figure rend="Make a Room Smell Clean Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Some people suffer from Seasonal Affective Disorder (SAD), a depression caused by lack of sunlight. It is common in northern climates where people don't see direct sunlight for months. If you feel you might have this condition, consult your doctor. You can buy indoor full spectrum lights that have been shown to improve this condition. <figure rend="Stop Being Emotional Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Limit your intake of alcohol. Although alcoholic substances can make you feel happy on a short-term basis, they are a depressant. High intake of alcohol can lead to depression, physical consequences and possibly alcoholism, all which take their toll on mental health. <figure rend="Clean Your Hair With Beer Step 1.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Emotional Maintenance</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Build self-confidence. Identify your strengths and your weaknesses. Play to your strengths, accept compliments and don't indulge in negative thoughts. <figure rend="Develop Poise Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Build a support system. Relationships with family and friends must be maintained, and many are strengthened through sharing life's high and low points. Share your emotions with the people you trust and encourage them to confide in you. <figure rend="Not to Be Shy at a New School Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep track of your moods with a journal or conversation. Self-reflection can help you identify times when you are prone to mood shifts. This can help you to recognize the warning signs of stress, anxiety and depression and possibly prevent them. <figure rend="Deal With Bitter Memories Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Manage stress through relaxation methods. Although exercise, support systems and sleep can help you manage stress, you should also find a way to limit the effects on your body and mind. Massage, meditation, yoga, baths, writing and walking can help you to manage stress before it develops into anxiety. <figure rend="Feel Refreshed Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Positive Lifestyle Changes</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find a creative pursuit. Studies show that making or being creative outside of your job can help give you a feeling of accomplishment and improve quality of life. Try gardening, writing, playing an instrument, drawing, painting or crafting as a hobby. <figure rend="Span Large Intervals on a Piano Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Manage your finances. Money issues are 1 of the largest causes of stress and anxiety. Take the time to create a reasonable budget. <figure rend="Look Presentable for School (Girls) Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Plan leisure time every day. Many people become overwhelmed with work or family responsibility. Care for yourself like you care for others, by planning "playtime." <figure rend="Stimulate Children's Self Confidence Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Good adult "playtime" activities include reading a book, talking to a friend, going for a walk, listening to music or walking. Add laughter and positive feedback by going out with friends or joining a book club or knitting bee. <figure rend="Train Your Ear Step 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try volunteering to improve mood. Giving unselfishly to others can improve your quality of life. You can feel even more satisfied with volunteer work than with paid work.</item>
<item>Consider getting a pet. If you have the means to take care of an animal, you can benefit from the unconditional love and support a pet can give. Studies have shown that making eye contact with your dog can release oxytocin, a mood-lifting brain chemical.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Consult a doctor or mental health professional immediately if you feel overwhelmed with anxiety or depression.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Sunlight</item>
<item>Sleep</item>
<item>Exercise</item>
<item>Healthy food</item>
<item>Family and friends</item>
<item>Journal</item>
<item>Creative hobby</item>
<item>Leisure activities</item>
<item>Pet (optional)</item>
<item>Volunteer work</item></list>
</text>
