<text id="autogum_interview_doc112" title="part3_Wikinews interviews specialists on South Korea military parade" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-10-02" dateModified="2015-01-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_specialists_on_South_Korea_military_parade" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Kosal</hi>: Secretary of Defense Hagel's presence, along with Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff General <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin%20Dempsey">Martin Dempsey</ref>, shows the commitment of the United States to support its ally. The United States remains committed to the transfer of operational control (OPCON) to the South Koreans for general defense of South Korea. The US is also strongly committed to limiting proliferation of nuclear, chemical, and biological weapons. Their presence reinforces that to the North Koreans as well as to the international community.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ledyard</hi>: It is simple routine in the USA–<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Republic_of_Korea">ROK</ref> alliance. South Koreans depend on it and the US takes care to show support.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Terry</hi>: Yes, it further showcases the depth of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Washington_DC">Washington</ref>'s support for South Korea against any provocation from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Pyongyang">Pyongyang</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chi</hi>: Certainly he is there to add symbolic strength to the alliance which tended to be weakened until recently. Behind his presence is the recent agreement to reconsider the planed transfer of the war-time operation control from the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UN">UN</ref>/US to the Korean army.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">You</hi>: US–South Korea alliance is strong but it is a bit more complicated since [the] US is supporting <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Japan">Japan</ref> in arming in naval forces to check <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China">China</ref>, which is a great concern for South Korea and [the] South Korean people. This might cause some issues in US–South Korea alliance.</p>
<figure><caption> File photo of interviewee Gari Ledyard. Image: Gari Ledyard.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  North Korea's rhetoric vows the repeated bolstering of its nuclear arsenal to what it calls US military threats. Do you think a military parade of this type backed by the US is likely to influence further hostility?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Kelly</hi>: No, because NK must be permanently hostile toward the US and SK anyway. NK has no reason to exist as a separate, poorer Korean state, just as the GDR [<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/East%20Germany">East Germany</ref>] had no post-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cold%20War">cold war</ref> reason to exist, unless SK and the US can be regularly described as the enemy. So NK doesn't want a war, but they certainly don't want a warm peace, as then NK then loses its <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/raison%20d'être#English">raison d'etre</ref></hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Kosal</hi>: No, North Korea and its leadership are responsible for its choices, which are the primary source of instability on the Korean peninsula with potential regional effects.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ledyard</hi>: The "military threats" are more a reflection of North Korea's fears than any concrete threats. They are more for internal DPRK [North Korea] efforts to keep its own population in tune with government policies.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Terry</hi>: No.  I think it's important to remember Pyongyang's periodic provocations and its pursuit of nuclear arsenal are not reactions or self-defense measures against a threatening Seoul or Washington.  Incapable of competing with economically flourishing South Korea, the North relies on bolstering its nuclear arsenal and on military and political brinkmanship to make up ground.</p>
</text>
