<text id="autogum_interview_doc461" title="part5_Former &amp;apos;Top Model&amp;apos; contestant Whitney Cunningham defends plus size models, celebrates the &amp;quot;regular woman&amp;quot;" shortTile="partformer-top-model" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-12-03" dateModified="2012-06-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Former_%27Top_Model%27_contestant_Whitney_Cunningham_defends_plus_size_models%2C_celebrates_the_%22regular_woman%22" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> There were a lot of negative reactions from fans when Jaslene won. Do you think she was the best choice? If so, why? If not, who would have been the better choice and why?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WC:</hi> Oh, my God, negative reactions? Are you kidding? Jaslene was, without a doubt, the best model at the time on the show. The only possible negative reaction I could think of is that she's so thin. And what people don't know is that Jaslene could give me a run for my money in eating. [laughs] She's just naturally built the way she is.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Some negative fan reactions were "How could Jaslene sell a product when she can't speak English well?" and "Model? She's not even pretty! She looks like a man!" Which, I wish I was making it up, but it's a rather loud fan voice on those points. What do you say to them about that? And following on that, do you think fans can be excessively cruel toward the contestants?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WC:</hi> Those "fans" can kiss my ___. She is from Puerto Rico and represents all that America is—a large nation made up of a multitude of people from different backgrounds and places. And Jaslene is beautiful as are we all. And yes, I do believe that the fans can be excessively cruel. I don't even consider those folks fans though. They're people who have nothing else better to do with themselves than sit around and bash reality TV contestants on anonymous blog sites.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> You and Diana were some of the only models in this cycle who were working toward a college degree. Did you feel that you were smarter than the other girls? Did people at your college watch Top Model to see you and root for you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WC:</hi> Smarter? [laughs] I don't like that term because I'm an honest believer in the fact that people are all relatively smart, just in different things. I would say that I was well versed in certain areas that others were not, but that doesn't mean I'm smarter per se. And yes, folks at my school definitely watched the show. I got really positive feedback! They said I represented well.</p>
<head id="Where_Whitney_is_today">Where Whitney is today</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> And on that note, a fan wanted to know if you finished your degree at Dartmouth.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WC:</hi> Yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> This past May, right?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WC:</hi> I walked in June.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Do you plan on moving back to Florida, or are you going to continue living in New York City?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WC:</hi> I'm definitely going to continue to live in New York for a while. I need to be where the industry is.</p>
</text>
