<text id="autogum_interview_doc151" title="part5_Wikinews interviews Irene Villa" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-02-25" dateModified="2013-11-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Irene_Villa" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Irene Villa</hi>: No... Besides, that part about me being a political figure... I have nothing to do with politics. I don't know why people always... Why? Because of what happened to me. I was a kid. A 12 year old has nothing to do with politics. We know too that <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/ETA">ETA</ref> has attacked people who had nothing to do with politics as well. My mother was a police director. What may have interfered is the fact that since I was a known figure I've tried that other people.... Let's see, for example I started doing sport so other people would know you could do sport. So it is true that the fact of being known has pushed me to do more things that I would've probably not have done. Because I wanted to show people that you could ski. And I ended up hooked. I only did it for a tv reportage. "Okay okay, a reportage and let's have people know that yes, we can". In fact, my book is titled "Knowing that you can" [<hi rend="italic">Saber que se puede</hi>, in Spanish]. Later I got hooked. But the fact of being known motivates you to show other people a path that could be very beneficial to them, and at the end you get addicted to it. ((es))Spanish language: ‍No... Es que además, lo de política me suena a que... yo no tengo nada que ver con la política. No sé por qué la gente siempre... ¿Por qué? Porque me pasó lo que me pasó. Era una niña. Una persona que tiene 12 años no puede tener nada que ver con la política. ETA ya sabemos que ha atentado contra gente que no tenía que ver con la política. Mi madre era funcionaria de policía. El caso es que lo que quizás ha podido interferir es que el hecho de ser una persona conocida he tratado de intentar que otras personas... A ver, yo empecé por ejemplo a hacer deporte para que otras personas supieran que se podía hacer deporte. Así que sí que es verdad que el hecho de ser conocida me ha impulsado a hacer más cosas de las que hubiese hecho seguramente. Porque yo quería mostrar a la gente que se podía esquiar. Y acabé enganchándome yo. Lo hice simplemente por un reportaje. "Venga venga, un reportaje y que la gente sepa que se puede". De hecho mi libro se llama <hi rend="italic">Saber que se puede</hi>. Luego me enganché. Pero el hecho de ser relevante o conocida te impulsa a mostrar a otras personas un camino que puede ser muy beneficioso para ellos, y al final acabas tú enganchada.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : When all is said and done, what do you kind of want your legacy to be? Do you want to be known as Irene Villa, disability sport advocate figure? Do you want to be known like <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jon_Santacana">Jon Santacana</ref>, or do you want to be known as somebody who has pushed the boundaries in other areas?  ((es))Spanish language: ‍Al final del día, ¿qué clase de herencia desea dejar? ¿Ser conocida como Irene Villa, deportista y defensora del deporte discapacitado? ¿Ser conocida como Jon Santacana, o como alguien que ha forzado los límites en otras áreas?</p>
</text>
