<text id="autogum_news_doc674" title="&apos;Birther King&apos; announces 2016 campaign for U.S. president" shortTile="birther-king-announces" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-08-16" dateModified="2019-10-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/%27Birther_King%27_announces_2016_campaign_for_U.S._president" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>'Birther King' announces 2016 campaign for U.S. president</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, August 16, 2015</hi></p>
<p>Via press release on Friday, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Andy_Martin">Andy Martin</ref>, a perennial candidate for political office and self-proclaimed "Birther King", announced he is seeking the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S.">U.S.</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(United_States)">Republican Party</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_presidential_election,_2016">2016 presidential nomination</ref>, his fourth bid for the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_White_House">White House</ref>.  In his announcement and subsequent release, Martin expresses a desire to participate in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republican%20Party%20presidential%20debates,%202016">Republican presidential debates</ref> and aligns himself with fellow Republican presidential candidate <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Donald_Trump">Donald Trump</ref>.  Additionally, he outlines six reasons for running, including degrading the candidacy of former <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Florida">Florida</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Governor%20of%20Florida">governor</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jeb_Bush">Jeb Bush</ref>, who is also seeking the Republican nomination.</p>
<figure><caption>"Birther King" Andy Martin.Image: Andy Martin.</caption></figure>
<p>"I have been a loyal Republican," says Martin in his announcement, "loyal to the principles of our party but not necessarily loyal to some of its failed leaders."</p>
<p>Martin, best known for spreading multiple conspiracy theories concerning the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barack%20Obama%20citizenship%20conspiracy%20theories">birth</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barack%20Obama%20religion%20conspiracy%20theories">religion</ref> of U.S. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/President_of_the_United_States">President</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref>, previously ran for the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Democratic_Party_(United_States)">Democratic Party</ref> presidential nomination in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20presidential%20election,%201988">1988</ref>, and unsuccessfully sought the backing of the Republican Party in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20presidential%20election,%202000">2000</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_presidential_election,_2012">2012</ref>.  In 2012, he received a total of 19 votes in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20Hampshire%20Primary">New Hampshire Primary</ref>, the only primary ballot on which he appeared. </p>
<p>For 2016, Martin does not harbor high expectations of electoral success, though he hopes to receive an invitation to the debates.  In reference to the seventeen candidates invited to the two August 6 <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Fox_News">Fox News</ref> debates, Martin casts himself as the "eighteenth candidate," willing to participate in the second-tier debate.  Moreover, he declares himself as the "second-most exciting" candidate, reserving first place for Trump, whom Martin praises throughout his announcement.  Although he described Trump's previous foray into politics as a "charade" during a 2011 interview with <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi>, Martin now sees himself as Trump's "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/tag%20team">tag team</ref>" partner in attacking the Bush candidacy.</p>
<p>"Trump has the raw media power to weaken Bush," says Martin, "I have the negative information and hardball media tactics to make Bush a toxic candidate for the Republican base."    </p>
<p>Martin adamantly opposes Bush because of the foreign policy of the candidate's brother, former President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/George_W._Bush">George W. Bush</ref>.  He also criticizes Bush for his alleged economic benefit from the collapse of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lehman%20Brothers">Lehman Brothers</ref>, labeling Bush as a "front man for a handful of corrupt <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plutocracy">plutocrats</ref> that have raped [the nation's] economy."  Martin has previously criticized the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bush%20family">Bush family</ref> during his 2000 campaign, when he ran television ads accusing then-presidential candidate George W. Bush of abusing <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Cocaine">cocaine</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/alcohol">alcohol</ref>.</p>
<p>In addition to preventing Bush from gaining the Republican nomination, Martin intends to focus his campaign on protecting the prestige of the New Hampshire Primary and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iowa%20Caucus">Iowa Caucus</ref>, defending the economic legacy of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Founding%20Fathers%20of%20the%20United%20States">Founding Father</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander%20Hamilton">Alexander Hamilton</ref>, combating <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/political%20correctness">political correctness</ref>, emphasizing U.S. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greece–United%20States%20relations">relations</ref> with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Greece">Greece</ref>, and fighting political corruption.</p>
<p>Martin filed paperwork with the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Federal_Election_Commission">Federal Election Commission</ref> last month to run for president in 2016 officially.  He joins 139 other Republican Party presidential candidates who have done likewise.</p>
</text>
