<text id="autogum_whow_doc543" title="See if You Are Ready for a Pet" shortTile="see-ready-pet" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2008-03-22" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/See-if-You-Are-Ready-for-a-Pet" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>See if You Are Ready for a Pet</head><p>Many kids want pets, but when they get them they see they are not ready for it. See if you are ready for a pet and decide what type of pet you really would like to get.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Decide which pet you want. You might want to get a dog at first, but then find out they're too much trouble. Read books, do your research or ask family members and friends. You can also visit an animal shelter and see the animal you wanna get, and if you like it.  <figure rend="See if You Are Ready for a Pet Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get a toy that is the same as the pet. This sounds silly, but it actually helps. This will help you see the pet physically. Also, you could pretend he/she is the real pet and act like you have to take very good care of him/her. This kind of shows you if you are ready for a pet. <figure rend="See if You Are Ready for a Pet Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Name the toy pet. Come up with something cute. Act like it's the real pet, and that you need an adorable name. You might turn out to like the name a lot, and might name the actual pet that. <figure rend="See if You Are Ready for a Pet Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Treat it  as if it were real. Train it, feed it, and care for it greatly. This will show your parents that you are responsible enough to have your own pet! <figure rend="See if You Are Ready for a Pet Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make a bed for it with paper, a food bowl, and make paper foods. You can also make a paper cage as well. But remember, the real stuff will cost money, so don't expect a beautiful cage and lots of toys and snacks for your pet. <figure rend="See if You Are Ready for a Pet Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wake up early in the morning and care for it. Give it food and take it for a walk or clean up the cage. This will show you the real responsibilities of caring for a pet. There can be consequences if you don't care for your pet properly. So, do care for him/her great, and you will be the World's Best Owner! <figure rend="See if You Are Ready for a Pet Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Play with it in the evening and give it food. You will have to do this with a real animal because they get hungry and bored easily. Again, this sounds silly, but really does teach you about how having a pet is a lot of responsibility! <figure rend="See if You Are Ready for a Pet Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Go to sleep at night by putting into your bed. Get a home or a cage for the pet and place it in there. This also teaches you about having a pet! When you're done with the fake animal, enjoy your new, live pet! <figure rend="See if You Are Ready for a Pet Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Follow this for a week and see if you can do it. If you could, it means you are ready and you can take responsibility. If you couldn't, it means pets aren't for you yet.</item>
<item>Show your parents and go to a pet store.</item>
<item>Pets can be reptiles, birds, fish, dogs, and cats. Be prepared to create cages and food for the pet of your choice.</item></list>
</text>
