<text id="autogum_voyage_doc331" title="West Bali" shortTile="west-bali" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=38848" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>West Bali</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">West Bali</hi> is in <ref target="Bali">Bali</ref>, <ref target="Indonesia">Indonesia</ref>.</p>

<head>Cities</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> — the westernmost town in Bali and the ferry to <ref target="Java">Java</ref></item>
<item> — capital town of Jembrana Regency, bull racing and Pura Rumbut Siwi</item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> — surfing and a touch of old Bali fishing village life</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Menjangan Island</hi> — small island off the north west coast with great diving and part of the <ref target="West%20Bali%20National%20Park">West Bali National Park</ref></item>
<item> — great diving and beaches with a stunning backdrop of the western mountains</item>
<item> — trekking, birdwatching and diverse marine life</item>
</list>


<head>Understand</head>
<p>This is the least populated and least visited region of Bali. It is dominated by the <ref target="West%20Bali%20National%20Park">West Bali National Park</ref> and a huge area of protected reserve, much of which is completely uninhabited. Both the north and south coasts of this region offer quiet beaches but of a very different nature. Those in the north fringe calm seas which are excellent for diving and snorkelling. The southern beaches are wilder and include a number of renowned surfing spots. The town of <ref target="Gilimanuk">Gilimanuk</ref> on the very westernmost tip of Bali is the departure point for ferries to <ref target="Java">Java</ref>.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>Two major roads lead into West Bali, one on the north coast and one on the south coast.</p>

<p>The northern route links <ref target="Lovina">Lovina</ref> and <ref target="Singaraja">Singaraja</ref> in <ref target="North%20Bali">North Bali</ref> to <ref target="Pemuteran">Pemuteran</ref>. This is a relatively quiet road which offers some great scenery and attractions en-route and visitors are advised to take it slowly.</p>

<p>Much busier is the southern route as this carries the bulk of the commercial traffic to and from <ref target="Java">Java</ref>. This road links <ref target="South%20Bali">South Bali</ref> to <ref target="Tabanan">Tabanan</ref> in <ref target="Central%20Bali">Central Bali</ref> and then to the western region towns of <ref target="Negara">Negara</ref> and <ref target="Gilimanuk">Gilimanuk</ref>. A car journey from <ref target="South%20Bali">South Bali</ref> all the way to <ref target="Gilimanuk">Gilimanuk</ref> will take upwards of 3 hours.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>Scheduled shuttle buses run from many of Bali's main visitor centres to <ref target="Gilimanuk">Gilimanuk</ref> and these are widely advertised in towns such as <ref target="Kuta">Kuta</ref>, <ref target="Lovina">Lovina</ref>, <ref target="Sanur">Sanur</ref> and <ref target="Ubud">Ubud</ref>. Check locally and book one day in advance.</p>

<p>Bemos servicing <ref target="Negara">Negara</ref>, <ref target="Gilimanuk">Gilimanuk</ref> and other parts of the south coast leave from Ubung terminal in <ref target="Denpasar">Denpasar</ref> and Pesiapan terminal in <ref target="Tabanan">Tabanan</ref>.</p>

<head>By boat</head>
<p>Ferries run from Ketapang ferry terminal, <ref target="Banyuwangi">Banyuwangi</ref>, <ref target="East%20Java">East Java</ref> to <ref target="Gilimanuk">Gilimanuk</ref> every 30 minutes, 24 hours a day. The journey itself takes about 45 minutes but loading and unloading may extend that time considerably. Since Bali has been the subject of terrorist interest from <ref target="Java">Java</ref> security has tightened enormously - be prepared for delays.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>This remote region of Bali lends itself to getting around by hire car or motorcycle. Cars for rent are not all common here so best to bring it in with you from one of the main tourist destinations. You will find motorbikes easier to come by, especially in the beach communities of <ref target="Pemuteran">Pemuteran</ref> and <ref target="Medewi%20Beach">Medewi Beach</ref>.</p>

<head>See</head>
<ref target="West%20Bali%20National%20Park">West Bali National Park</ref> covers some 770 square kilometres and is the dominant feature of this region. All visitors should check in and purchase permits (Rp 25,000) at the main park ofice in the village of Cekik south of <ref target="Gilimanuk">Gilimanuk</ref>. Visitors intending to visit only Menjangan Island (part of the national park), please see below. For treks through forest and into the hills of the national park, proceed to the ranger station at Sumber Klampok about 20 minutes west from Cekik. A guide is mandatory and will cost between Rp 200,000 and Rp 500,000 depending on the length and nature of your trek. Discuss all of this and make plans with the staff at the Cekik park office. If you are very lucky you might get to see a <hi rend="bold">Bali Starling</hi>, Bali's only endemic vertebrate species.

<p><hi rend="bold">Vibrant marine life.</hi> Uninhabited Menjangan Island is a renowned diving and snorkelling destination. This is part of <ref target="West%20Bali%20National%20Park">West Bali National Park</ref> and boats with a guide can be chartered at Labuan Lalang just to the west of <ref target="Pemuteran">Pemuteran</ref> on the north coast. Dive operators in <ref target="Pemuteran">Pemuteran</ref> can arrange everything for you as well as other dive trips along this very attractive stretch of coastline. If the water does to appeal so much, then you can walk around in the island in about one hour and there are lots of good photo opportunities.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Remote black sand beaches</hi>. The south coast of this region is fringed by black sand beaches and fishing villages that attract few visitors. The most well known of those is <ref target="Medewi%20Beach">Medewi Beach</ref>. This is a surf destination but also a great place to experience laid back life in a tiny Balinese fishing village. Just relax and do not expect to see too many other visitors. On the north coast at <ref target="Pemuteran">Pemuteran</ref> there is a more developed but still very relaxed beach scene which centres on diving, snorkelling and marine conservation. Lots of accommodation options here to suit all budgets.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Buffalo racing</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Mekepung</hi>) in Delod Berawah about 9 km east of Negara town. Thought to originate in <ref target="Madura">Madura</ref>, <ref target="Java">Java</ref>, the buffalo races were originally held as part of the harvest festivities in Negara. The colorfully decorated carts and buffaloes race on a four km course every 2nd and 4th Sunday morning starting at 7.00 AM.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Rambut Siwi Temple</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Pura Rambut Siwi</hi>). About equidistant between <ref target="Negara">Negara</ref> and <ref target="Medewi%20Beach">Medewi Beach</ref>. Located on a low cliff top overlooking a breathtaking panorama of paddy fields and the mountains of <ref target="West%20Bali%20National%20Park">West Bali National Park</ref> on one side and black sand beaches on the other. The temple itself was built by the 16th century Javanese sage Dang Hyang Nirartha, also the creator of <ref target="Tanah%20Lot">Tanah Lot</ref> temple. According to legend, he made a gift of his hair to the temple. Hence the name Rambut Siwi, which literally means ” Hair Worship”.</p>

<head>Do</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Trekking and birdwatching</hi> in <ref target="West%20Bali%20National%20Park">West Bali National Park</ref> are key activities in this region. You might, just might, even get to see a Bali Starling, one of the rarest birds in the world with just a handful left in the wild.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Surfing</hi> is top class on the south coast beaches with the regional surf scene is being centred at <ref target="Medewi%20Beach">Medewi Beach</ref>.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Diving and snorkeling</hi> around <ref target="Pemuteran">Pemuteran</ref> and <ref target="West%20Bali%20National%20Park">Menjangan Island</ref> rates up there with the very best in Bali. At the same time, get to learn about marine conservation initiatives for which Pemuteran is a key centre in the whole of Indonesia.</p>
</text>
