<text id="autogum_bio_doc402" title="Kara Mustafa Pasha (governor of Egypt)" shortTile="kara-mustafa-pasha" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-10-16" dateModified="2017-09-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kara_Mustafa_Pasha_%28governor_of_Egypt%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Kara Mustafa Pasha (governor of Egypt)</head>This article is about the Ottoman governor of Egypt (1623, 1624–1626). For the Ottoman grand vizier (1676–1683), see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kara_Mustafa_Pasha">Kara Mustafa Pasha</ref>. For the Ottoman grand vizier (1638–1644), see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kemankeş_Kara_Mustafa_Pasha">Kemankeş Kara Mustafa Pasha</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Kara Mustafa Pasha</hi> (died 1628)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-France1796-51-1">[1]</ref> was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman</ref> statesman who served twice as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Ottoman_governors_of_Egypt">Ottoman governor of</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Egypt_Eyalet">Egypt</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sicilli-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Öztuna1994-3">[3]</ref> firstly from 20 July to 9 October 1623 and secondly from 12 February 1624 to 16 May 1626.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Öztuna1994-3">[3]</ref> He also served earlier as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agha_(Ottoman_Empire)">agha</ref> (chief) of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Janissary">Janissary</ref> corps in 1623.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sicilli-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Mustafa Pasha was educated in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enderun_School">Enderun</ref> palace school.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sicilli-2">[2]</ref> He married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fatma_Sultan_(daughter_of_Ahmed_I)">Fatma Sultan</ref>, a daughter of Sultan <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ahmed_I">Ahmed I</ref>, in 1628<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sicilli-2">[2]</ref> but was executed that same year by the reigning Sultan (and his new brother-in-law) <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Murad_IV">Murad IV</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-France1796-51-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>First term</head>
<p>After taking office as governor of Egypt for the first time, he accused his predecessor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Silahdar_Ibrahim_Pasha">Silahdar Ibrahim Pasha</ref> of failing to pay the customary contribution of every governor of Egypt to the treasury.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-France1796-46-4">[4]</ref> He sent his <hi rend="italic">kaymakam</hi> (lieutenant) Salih Bey after Ibrahim Pasha, who told Salih Bey that whatever money he owed, he would give directly to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sultan_of_the_Ottoman_Empire">sultan</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Istanbul">Istanbul</ref>, where he was headed anyway. However, the deposition of the Sultan <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mustafa_I">Mustafa I</ref> and the succession of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Murad_IV">Murad IV</ref> to the throne, as well as the political chaos around the event that occurred before Ibrahim Pasha arrived back in Constantinople, allowed him to keep the money.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-France1796-46-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Controversy over replacement</head>
<p>When the sultan replaced Mustafa Pasha with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Çeşteci_Ali_Pasha">Çeşteci Ali Pasha</ref> after only five months in office, as the custom of the sultans was to change the governors of Egypt in rapid succession, the local Ottoman troops marched to the new <hi rend="italic">kaymakam</hi>'s house and demanded the bonus salaries they usually received when the governor was replaced.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-France1796-47-5">[5]</ref> The new <hi rend="italic">kaymakam</hi> delayed them until the next day and at the same time asked them to bring Mustafa Pasha to him, as the <hi rend="italic">kaymakam</hi>'s initial task was to analyze the affairs of Mustafa Pasha; one of the paintings belonging to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seraglio">seraglio</ref> was lost, and it was suspected that Mustafa Pasha had taken it for himself.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-France1796-47-5">[5]</ref> However, the army refused this request, telling him,</p>
<p>"We cannot seize the person of the vizier, nor make any inquiry after his effects; let them appoint <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sanjak-bey">sanjak-beys</ref> for guards, and let them conduct him to Alexandria. If <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Çeşteci_Ali_Pasha">[Çeşteci] Ali Pasha</ref> is already arrived in that city, they will put him into his hands; if they do not find him there, let them conduct him to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Istanbul">Constantinople</ref>."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-France1796-47-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>The entire army then reportedly swore on the Quran to be resolute in their will. The next day, 11 October 1623, the armies and the sanjak-beys had Mustafa Pasha read the sultan's orders for his replacement and audit. When the army members again demanded compensation from the new <hi rend="italic">kaymakam</hi> and deputy governor, they reproached the soldiers by saying that they constantly demanded the same thing every three months, to which the soldiers replied,</p>
<p>"Why, then, does the sultan, our master, change the beylerbeys (governors) of the province every three months, to the great injury of the inhabitants? If he chooses to nominate every day new beylerbeys, we shall also demand every day new contributions."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-France1796-48-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>When the deputy governor replied that he could not compensate the soldiers until the new governor arrived in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cairo">Cairo</ref>, the soldiers grew enraged and nearly killed him and the <hi rend="italic">kaymakam</hi> before they escaped.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-France1796-48-6">[6]</ref> The soldiers then declared, "We will have no other governor than Mustafa; let Ali return to the place from whence he came."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-France1796-48-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>As the soldiers welcomed Mustafa Pasha back as governor, he privately wrote to the sultan to ask for a confirmation of his re-commencement of the office, with many local figures also writing to the sultan on his behalf.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-France1796-48-6">[6]</ref> When the soldiers were informed that the now-unemployed replacement governor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Çeşteci_Ali_Pasha">Çeşteci Ali Pasha</ref> had landed in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexandria">Alexandria</ref>, they sent messengers to inform him of what had occurred.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-France1796-48-6">[6]</ref> Ali Pasha, angry at the news, proceeded to put one of the messengers in chains, but the troops in the area loyal to Mustafa Pasha released the messenger, destroyed Ali Pasha's camp, and forced him to reembark on his ship.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-France1796-49-7">[7]</ref> When a wind accidentally brought his ship back to the port, Mustafa Pasha had his troops fire cannonballs at the ship. Because of unfavorable wind conditions, Ali Pasha was forced to spend the winter in another port before heading back to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Istanbul">Constantinople</ref>.</p>
<p>No news arrived from the capital confirming or denying whether Mustafa Pasha was the rightful governor, and the populace began to grow uneasy. Finally, on 16 February 1624, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carrier_pigeon">carrier pigeon</ref> arrived with a letter from the sultan in Constantinople confirming the reinstatement, and soon afterwards, the chief footman of the sultan arrived to deliver Mustafa Pasha's governor's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caftan">caftan</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-France1796-49-7">[7]</ref></p>
<head>Second term</head>
<p>In the first year (1624) of Mustafa Pasha's second term as governor of Egypt, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flooding_of_the_Nile">the Nile flooded</ref> to higher-than-expected level, but the waters receded in time for sowing, and a successful harvest followed.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-France1796-49,50-8">[8]</ref> Mustafa Pasha reportedly confiscated the inheritances of a large number of wealthy Egyptians for himself, growing wealthy from the practice; when heirs existed, he would reportedly fake their seal and claim their money.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-France1796-50-9">[9]</ref> Furthermore, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Egypt_Eyalet">province of Egypt</ref> experienced a plague from November 1625 to June 1626, which, although largely restricted to affecting those over 60 years old, nevertheless reportedly killed approximately 300,000 people.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-France1796-50-9">[9]</ref> To mollify and hasten the grieving process (and possibly to avoid further contagion from corpses), Mustafa Pasha banned all funerals, and the bodies were carried through the streets and buried without ceremony.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-France1796-50-9">[9]</ref> Mustafa Pasha was dismissed from the office of governor for the second and final time on 16 May 1626.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Öztuna1994-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Later life</head>
<p>After leaving office, Mustafa Pasha was hounded by his successor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bayram_Pasha">Bayram Pasha</ref>, who demanded of him a large restitution (reported as 20 <hi rend="italic">sandıks</hi>) after auditing the treasury, in a way similar to what Mustafa Pasha himself had done to his own predecessor Silahdar Ibrahim Pasha.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-France1796-50-9">[9]</ref> Mustafa Pasha, acting as though he could not pay the amount (despite the wealth he had apparently amassed while in office), sold his belongings to further his ruse. However, Bayram Pasha did not let up until Mustafa Pasha paid the entire sum.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-France1796-51-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In 1628, Mustafa Pasha married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fatma_Sultan_(daughter_of_Ahmed_I)">Fatma Sultan</ref>, a daughter of the late Sultan <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ahmed_I">Ahmed I</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sicilli-2">[2]</ref> but that same year, he was executed by the reigning 16-year-old <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sultan_of_the_Ottoman_Empire">Sultan</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Murad_IV">Murad IV</ref> (and his newlywed wife's brother) for some action "contrary to the law of God."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-France1796-51-1">[1]</ref></p>
</text>
