<text id="autogum_academic_doc513" title="An Association of Gut Microbiota with Different Phenotypes in Chinese Patients with Rheumatoid Arthritis" shortTile="association-gut-microbiota" author="Hsin-I Chiang, Jian-Rong Li, Chun-Chi Liu, Po-Yu Liu, Hsin-Hua Chen, Yi-Ming Chen, Joung-Liang Lan, Der-Yuan Chen" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2077-0383/8/11/1770/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
In the present study, we performed 16s rRNA deep sequencing and obtained large amounts of data concerning the microbial composition, diversity, and abundance in healthy subjects and RA patients with various clinical phenotypes. The results have demonstrated that a lower abundance and evenness of gut microbiota in RA patients compared with healthy subjects, with α-diversity lower in RF-positive or ACPA-positive RA patients than healthy subjects. Using the permutational multivariate analysis of variance (PERMANOVA), the β-diversity of gut microbiota in healthy subjects was significantly different from that in RA patients with different phenotypes. The phylum Verrucomicrobiae and genus Akkermansia were more abundant in RA patients compared with healthy subjects. Among RA patients, those with higher levels of TNF-α or IL-17A had increased the relative abundance of the phylum Gammaproteobacteria compared to those with lower cytokine levels. In addition, RA patients exhibited a different microbial composition which was related to RF/ACPA seropositivity.  </p>

<p>Our RA patients in either active or inactive status had a lower α-diversity of gut microbial taxa than healthy subjects, consistent with the findings in Korean patients with early RA. Moreover, α-diversity of gut microbiota was lower in ACPA-positive patients compared to HC. Although Chen et al. revealed similar findings, the significant association of α-diversity with ACPA positivity in their RA patients could not be reproduced in the present study. Our statistical data has suggested that there was no significant difference which may be due to the small sample size of RA subgroups with different phenotypes. In addition, the production of ACPA may be multifactorial, such as genetic factor, smoking, and the severity of periodontitis. After the pooling of RF-positive and ACPA-positive patients in a single goup, a significantly lower α-diversity was observed in seropositive patients compared to seronegative patients.  </p>

<p>Regarding the difference in the β-diversity between healthy subjects and RA patients, the PERMANOVA analysis showed a significant difference in phenotypes characterized by different disease activity and RF/ACPA status (Table 2). The weighted UniFrac distance, qualitative measurement of phylogenetic abundance difference, showed a statistical significance between RA patients and healthy subjects. There was a trend of difference finding in the β-diversity between patients with the lowest and the highest levels of TNF-α or IL-17A, indicating an association of gut microbiota composition with the inflammatory parameters in RA patients.  </p>

<p>Using pre-trained Naive Bayes Greengenes classifier to explore the taxonomic composition of gut microbiota, we observed an increased abundance of phylum Verrucomicrobiae, which might be driven by the genus Akkermansia (<hi rend="italic">Akkermansia muciniphila</hi>), in RA patients compared with healthy subjects. Our findings support the results revealing that the implication of <hi rend="italic">Akkermansia muciniphila</hi> in the pathogenesis of murine model of arthritis. Akkermansia has also been associated with the proinflammatory pathways, including upregulation of B- and T-cell receptor signaling. These proinflammatory effects may be related to its ability to degrade mucus and thus increase the exposure of resident immune cells to gut microbial antigens. In contrast to previous studies revealing that the predominance of Prevotella in the gut microbiota was associated with the untreated or new-onset RA and phylum Bacteroidetes was enriched in early RA patients, we did not observe significant increase in the abundance of family <hi rend="italic">Prevotellaceae or</hi> phylum Bacteroidetes. The differences in patients’ characteristics and treatment regimens of our enrolled patients may explain this discrepancy.  </p>

<p>It is interesting that active RA patients have an increased abundance of Collinsella compared with inactive RA patients. The arthrogenic role of Collinsella has been confirmed both in vivo using a humanized murine model of arthritis and in vitro by a human intestinal epithelium cell-based study. Chen et al. further demonstrated that Collinsella could be transferred to germ-free mice with resultant exacerbation of arthritis in a murine model. These observations suggest a potential role of the Collinsella expansion in the pathogenesis of active RA.  </p>
</text>
