<text id="autogum_voyage_doc183" title="Glovertown" shortTile="glovertown" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=12873" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Glovertown</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Glovertown</hi> is a town of 2,000 people (2016) in <ref target="Central%20Newfoundland">Central Newfoundland</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Visitor Information Center</hi>, 25 Main Street South, ☏ +1 709 520-3044 .</item>
</list>


<head>History</head>
<p>Glovertown was founded as "Bloody Bay". That name dated back to the 18th century and supposedly it referred to a massacre of a family of 11 by Beothuk Aboriginals that were living in the area at the time. The town was renamed Alexander Bay in 1894. During 1894, a section of railway was being built in the area. A few years later the town was renamed "Glovertown", after Sir John Hawley Glover who served as the Governor of Newfoundland from 1876 to 1881 and from 1883 to 1885.</p>

<p>The first settlers of Glovertown appeared in the early 19th century. In 1845, 12 people lived there. By 1857 there were only 10 and by 1862 there Glovertown became a thriving center for the fishery, boat building and lumbering industries. </p>

<p>In 1913, one of the sawmills at Rosedale exploded and six people were killed. In 1946 there was a fire that was started by sparks coming from a passing train. The fire destroyed 46 homes. Two schools, several businesses and 390 km² of timber were also destroyed during the fire. The lumber industry has never recovered from this loss.</p>

<p>Eventually people from Greenspond, Flat Island, Bragg's Island, and Gooseberry Island began to resettle to Glovertown and the influx of new people brought new industries to the town, including dairy and construction.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<p>Glovertown can be accessed via <hi rend="bold">Trans-Canada Highway 1</hi> east of <ref target="Gander">Gander</ref> and Gambo and west of <ref target="Terra%20Nova%20National%20Park">Terra Nova National Park</ref>. There are two exits: one that leads directly onto Station Road in Glovertown and another that leads to Eastport and Traytown.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<p>Glovertown is primarily a one street town, with other smaller residential roads along the way. You can arrive through Traytown on Main Street North or through Station Road and from there, you just have to follow Main Street.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Janes House Museum</hi> (Glovertown Museum), 11 Memorial Street, ☏ +1 709 533-6004 . Seasonal. The museum was developed with the theme of resettlement in mind, which is the story of people's movement from the Islands of Bonavista Bay to 'growth centres' such as Glovertown. Other themes at the museum include boat building, the Spring log drive, and general Glovertown history and heritage.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Splash n’ Putt</hi> (on the Trans-Canada Highway five minutes east from the Station Road exit), ☏ +1 709 533-2753 , toll-free: +1-844-533-2753 . A family water park that offers a range of activities and services. Splash n’ Putt offers a gift shop, restaurant, dairy bar and cabins ($136-194 double).</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Timber &amp; Twine</hi>, 79 Main St, ☏ +1 709 533-2557 . Home decor.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Greco Express/Captain Sub</hi>, 56 Main Street South, ☏ +1 709 533-9203 . Pizza, subs, donairs, wings.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Timber &amp; Twine</hi>, 79 Main St, ☏ +1 709 533-2557 . M-F 6AM-8:30PM, Sa Su 7AM-8:30PM. Coffee shop and mobile food truck. Fish and chips available.</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Glovertown Ocean View Suites and Cottages</hi>, 19 Randell’s Ave, ☏ +1 709 533-7414 . Heated outdoor pool, decks on most units, laundry facilities on site, boat launch, fire pit, barbecue is most suites, WiFi and cable TV. Peak season: $115-170.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lilac Inn</hi>, 13 Pinetree Road, ☏ +1 709 533-6038 . $115-133 includes a home cooked breakfast for two.</item>
<item> Splash-n-Putt Cabins - see listing under "Do"</item>
</list>


<head>Go next</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Terra%20Nova%20National%20Park">Terra Nova National Park</ref></hi>: The landscape of the park varies from the rugged cliffs and sheltered inlets of the coastal region to the rolling forested hills, bogs and ponds of the inland. Popular summer activities in the Park include camping, hiking, canoeing, kayaking, biking and boat tours. Winter is also a good time to explore the park by cross-country skiing or snowshoeing the trails and winter camping at Newman Sound.</item>
</list>
</text>
