<text id="autogum_interview_doc843" title="part13_ACLU President Strossen on religion, drugs, guns and impeaching George Bush" shortTile="partaclu-president" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-30" dateModified="2019-02-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/ACLU_President_Strossen_on_religion%2C_drugs%2C_guns_and_impeaching_George_Bush" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Do I think it would be a good idea to impeach him?  I think it would be a <hi rend="italic">terrible</hi> idea to impeach him.  Among other reasons, I think it would have the effect of placing disproportionate responsibility on to him when a lot of the blame for the violations I’m talking about rests in the hands of Congress.  Congress did not have to vote for the Patriot Act, as they did almost unanimously in the Senate.  Congress did not have to expand his domestic wire-tapping power this summer, even beyond what he was initially doing in his secret program.  Congress did not have to roll over and play dead with respect to torture and rendition and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guantanamo">Guantanamo</ref> and all the other human rights disasters.  They really bear a lot of responsibility and we should not be letting them off the hook.  By going after Bush, it deflects responsibility from Congress, it deflects responsibility from the courts, which have been issuing a lot of bad decisions, I think.  It also deflects responsibility from the Democrats.  It makes it too much of a partisan issue.  There is bipartisan responsibility here.  For that reason I strongly oppose it.  I’m not speaking for the ACLU, I know some people in the ACLU <hi rend="italic">would</hi> like to see it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You just don’t think it would be productive.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  I don’t think it would advance civil liberties.</p>
<head id="Gun_rights">Gun rights</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Where do you stand on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second%20Amendment">Second Amendment</ref> and the rights of gun owners?  Are the rights accorded to well-armed militias, or is it accorded to unfettered rights of individuals to own guns?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  I actually don’t think in reality that the difference is that profound, because when you look at the big debate, and you stated it well, does the government protect the individual right to bear arms, does it only protect a collective right through the state militias?  Let’s assume for the sake of argument it does protect an individual right, it is no more absolute than freedom of speech or any other right in the Constitution.  No right is absolute; the government is always allowed to restrict the right if it can satisfy Constitutional strict scrutiny and show the restriction is narrowly tailored to promote a goal of compelling importance.  Ironically, the very first federal appellate court in recent history to hold that there was an individual <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Right%20to%20bear%20arms">right to bear arms</ref> under the Second Amendment, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Court%20of%20Appeals%20for%20the%20Fifth%20Circuit">Fifth Circuit</ref>, then went on to nevertheless uphold the particular restriction that was being challenged!  Mainly, that the guy was under a restraining order for domestic abuse and he wasn’t allowed to possess a gun.  The court said the Second Amendment protects your right, but this regulation doesn’t violate your right.  So I don’t think it makes a big difference.  And conversely, to say it’s not an individual right doesn’t mean that gun owners are without all rights, and the ACLU has often collaborated with gun owners rights organizations to defend their rights to privacy, to defend their rights to due process; in other words, they don’t forfeit all of their Constitutional rights just because they are gun owners, even if the Second Amendment doesn’t protect.   So I think it’s more a philosophical debate than it has any practical difference.</p>
</text>
