<text id="autogum_news_doc485" title="Poland: Thousands of far-right nationalists gather in Warsaw to march for white supremacy, anti-liberalism, and anti-Islam on Polish independence day" shortTile="poland-thousands" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-11-12" dateModified="2019-01-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Poland%3A_Thousands_of_far-right_nationalists_gather_in_Warsaw_to_march_for_white_supremacy%2C_anti-liberalism%2C_and_anti-Islam_on_Polish_independence_day" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Poland: Thousands of far-right nationalists gather in Warsaw to march for white supremacy, anti-liberalism, and anti-Islam on Polish independence day</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 14, 2017</hi></p>
<p>On Saturday afternoon, thousands of far-right <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/nationalist">nationalists</ref> gathered in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Poland">Poland</ref>'s capital <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Warsaw">Warsaw</ref> to participate in "<hi rend="italic">Independence March</hi>" which was organized by far-right groups including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/All-Polish%20Youth">All-Polish Youth</ref>, the National Movement, and the National-Radical Camp. Participants objected to liberalism, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Islam">Islam</ref>, and some banners supported <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/White_supremacy">white supremacy</ref>.</p>
<p>The slogan of this year's <hi rend="italic">Independence March</hi> was "We want god". The march, which coincided with Poland's independence day, began at 3:00 P.M. local time (1400 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UTC">UTC</ref>). Marchers chanted "Great national Poland, religion is the basis of the Polish nation, Great <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Roman_Catholicism">Catholic</ref> Poland and one nation across the borders" under banners reading "We want God" and "White Europe of brotherly nations." There were also anti-leftist, anti-<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> slogans as well as slogans against liberal media broadcasters.</p>
<p>Poland's Interior Minister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mariusz%20Błaszczak">Mariusz Błaszczak</ref> said, "We are proud that so many Poles have decided to take part in a celebration connected to the Independence Day holiday." <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Andrzej_Duda">Andrzej Duda</ref>, Polish president, condemned the march and called this march a display of "sick nationalism". He also added "there is no place [for xenophobia] in Poland". Emmanuel Nahshon, spokesperson of the Israeli Foreign Ministry, called the march "a dangerous march of extreme and racist elements" and told the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Associated_Press">Associated Press</ref></hi>, "We hope that Polish authorities will act against the organisers [...] History teaches us that expressions of racist hate must be dealt with swiftly and decisively."</p>
<p>Rafał Pankowski, a sociologist of the anti-extremist organization <hi rend="italic">Never Again</hi>, said, "I think that most of the organisers are not very religious, either. [...] But use <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Christianity">Christianity</ref> as a kind of identity marker, which is mostly about being anti-Islam now."</p>
<p>Muslims make up under one percent of Poland's population, and Poland has refused to welcome refugees.</p>
<p>The organizers of the march estimate more than 100,000 people attended, but the police put the number at 60,000. Antifa Warsaw (Anti-fascist Warsaw) organized a counter-march in the capital. One of the participants, lidia Domanska said about 5000 people participated in the march. Only one clash between the two groups was reported, of a man kicking women who were holding a flag reading "Stop Fascism."</p>
<p>The event drew people from other European countries, including <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Slovakia">Slovakia</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sweden">Sweden</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hungary">Hungary</ref>. 39-year-old <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard%20B.%20Spencer">Richard Spencer</ref>, a white supremacist from the United States, was invited to Poland by far-right groups, and he was scheduled to attend the event but did not. On October 27, Poland's Foreign Minister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Witold%20Waszczykowski">Witold Waszczykowski</ref> said, "He [Spencer] should not appear publicly, and especially not in Poland." Saying Spencer's opinions "are in conflict with the legal order" of the country, Waszczykowski added, "as a country which was one of the biggest victims of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nazism">Nazism</ref>, we believe that the ideas promoted by Mr Spencer and his followers could pose a threat to all those who hold dear the values of human rights and democracy".</p>
<p>November 11 is the anniversary of the end of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/World_War_I">World War I</ref>, after which Poland regained its status as an independent country in 1918. The <hi rend="italic">Independence March</hi> was first organised in 2009 and the number of participants has grown since.</p>
</text>
