<text id="autogum_whow_doc353" title="Observe the Veil Nebula" shortTile="observe-veil-nebula" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2017-07-31" dateModified="2017-08-02" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Observe-the-Veil-Nebula" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Observe the Veil Nebula</head><p>The Veil nebula is the visible part of the Cygnus Loop, a supernova remnant from a star that exploded between 5000 and 8000 years ago. The nebula is quite large, covering an area over thirty times larger than the full moon. It is also relatively bright; however, since the light is spread out over such a wide area, it makes it difficult to spot.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Gather your equipment. You will need:
<list type="unordered"><item>A telescope or binoculars. The nebula is too dim to be seen with the naked eye, except under the most exceptional of circumstances.</item>
<item>An OIII telescope filter: optional, but recommended. Most of the light from the nebula is emitted by doubly ionised oxygen, or OIII. This filter will isolate that light and make the nebula stand out. You may be able to get filters for binoculars, but if you can't, just get two telescope filters and stick them over the lenses.</item>
<item>A dark site: optional, but highly recommended. Less light pollution will make the nebula easier to find.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Summer triangle.png"></figure> Start by locating the Summer Triangle. This is a relatively prominent asterism, or star pattern, that appears in the sky in summer and autumn. It is formed from the brightest stars in Cygnus, Lyra and Aquila. If you look in the middle of the triangle, you should notice a dimmer star, called Albireo.</item>
<item><figure rend="Cygnus.png"></figure> Focus on Deneb and Albireo. These form the edges of the Cygnus constellation. Use them to locate the rest of the stars in the constellation. If you are having trouble finding Zeta Cygni, try using a small pair of binoculars.
<list type="unordered"><item>Fun factoid: Cygnus X-1, an object generally accepted as being a black hole, is located near Eta Cygni.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="NGC 6960.png"></figure> Trace one line from Albireo to Zeta Cygni, then trace a second from Deneb down through Epsilon Cygni. NGC 6960, part of the Veil Nebula, is at the junction. Focus on this point with your telescope.</item>
<item><figure rend="Veil nebula.png"></figure> Move around to focus on parts of the Nebula. The Veil Nebula is so extensive that all the parts have different names. Try finding the following:
<list type="unordered"><item>The Western Veil Nebula, NGC 6960. This is the part that the instructions lead you to focus on.</item>
<item>Pickering's Triangle. A triangular shaped patch of gas, located north of NGC 6960.</item>
<item>NGC 6979 and NGC 6974: two small knots of gas, east of Pickering's Triangle.</item>
<item>The Eastern Veil Nebula: made of three parts. NGC 6992 is east of NGC 6974. NGC 6995 is south of NGC 6992, and IC 1340 is south again.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Once you've tried it with the OIII filter, try it without. The filter blocks light not emitted by OIII, so it can obscure some details.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not look at the sun. It can leave you permanently blinded.</item>
<item>If you are searching for a dark site, do not trespass on anybody's land.</item></list>
</text>
