<text id="autogum_voyage_doc157" title="Kraainem" shortTile="kraainem" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=151011" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Kraainem</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Kraainem</hi> is a municipality on the outskirts of the <ref target="Brussels">Brussels</ref> Capital Region, administratively belonging to <ref target="Flemish%20Brabant">Flemish Brabant</ref>. It began as a rural village, but the expansion of Brussels has led to a fast-paced urbanization of Kraainem throughout the 20th century, and the municipality has become a popular residence for Eurocrats and expats alike.</p>

<head>Early history</head>
<p>Little is known about the early history of Kraainem, aside from a few lithic artifacts found during agricultural activities. During the urbanization of Stokkel and South Kraainem, a large concentration of artifacts was discovered in 1928 near the border with <ref target="Brussels/Woluwe">St.-Pieters-Woluwe</ref>. These finds are dated to the meso and neolithicum.</p>

<p>Remains of Roman settlements were uncovered at the end of the 18th century, and a Roman villa once stood at the location of the current town hall. It was known as <hi rend="italic">Villa Crainham</hi>, and gave Kraainem its name. None of the classical remains were preserved, unfortunately. It is known that <hi rend="italic">Villa Crainham</hi> remained until the 11th century, from 1003 also a church is recorded in charters: <hi rend="italic">crainham villa cum ecclesia</hi>. The <hi rend="italic">Keulsebaan</hi> crosses through Kraainem, connecting Roman <ref target="Brussels">Brussels</ref> to <ref target="Cologne">Cologne</ref>, parts of which remain today.</p>

<p>Most of Kraainems current territory remained uninhabited throughout the first millenium. The northern urbanized area of Kraainem, <hi rend="italic">High Kraainem</hi>, evolved from a Frankish court centered around what is now known as the Jourdain Castle. It was little more than a fortification surrounded by a few dwellings in the first half of the 9th century. A map from 1771 shows the historic division of Kraainem between a high and low area: to the west a church built upon earlier fortifications, and to the east numerous farm houses and a few smaller dwellings. It is unknown how the fortifications might have looked, but remains of a double octagonal moat can be traced to the west of the church and remained prominent until 1836. The development of High Kraainem remained limited to this core until well into the 19th century, with a survey in 1830 counting only 15 houses.</p>

<p>The noth-west of Kraainem hosts a second urbanization core, <hi rend="italic">Low Kraainem</hi>. It was more densely populated than <hi rend="italic">High Kraainem</hi>, but of less significance because it lacked High Kraainems church and defensive fortifications. Low Kraainem owed its importance to the confluence of the Maalbeek in the <ref target="Brussels/Woluwe">Woluwe</ref>. Water mills were already constructed in 1397 to harness the power of the water for agricultural purposes, and a residential core grew around these mills. Around 1427 the St. Anthony chapel was built, taking advantage of merchants crossing through the area over the <hi rend="italic">Keulsebaan</hi>. Laag Kraainem flourished economically in the 14th and 15th century, but the St. Anthony chapel had disappeared again by 1850. The <hi rend="italic">Jozef Van Hovestraat</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Jef. Thumasstraat</hi> are the oldest remaining streets of Low Kraainem.</p>

<p>Stokkel is Kraainem's third core of habitation, and evolved from a small settlement in the 12th century as part of the Woluwe abbey. The abbey ensured the soil was made fertile, thus allowing agriculture and the development of a settlement there. The area south of Stokkel, now a residential neighborhood, remained forrested until the 19th century and a source of income from hunting.</p>
<head>In the 19th century</head>
<p>At the end of the 19th century, Stokkel gained a tram connection to <ref target="Brussels">Brussels</ref>, which still exists today as tram 92. The improved accessibility started rapid urbanization of Stokkel, whereas northern Kraainem retained its rural characteristics. Until the end of the <ref target="Second%20World%20War">Second World War</ref>, only 2 unpaved roads connected Low and High Kraainem to Stokkel, and they were only usable a few months a year.</p>

<p>Wheras Stokkel urbanized, northern Kraainem developed slowly and became industrialized in the early 19th century. Paper mills had existed in Kraainem since the Middle Ages, and gained importance from the Belgian independence in 1830 to supply the new capital city of <ref target="Brussels">Brussels</ref> with newspapers. By 1892, it had evolved into a large industrial complex with a hundred craftsmen. A grain mill and brewery were also part of the complex. Today, Kraainem still bears the fruits of this history, and is considered one of the richest municipalities of Belgium.</p>

<p>From 1860 onwards, the monumental construction projects in Brussels drove the bourgeoisie out of the capital city, and many found refuge around Stokkel, which gave it a development boost and much of its wealth.</p>

<head>Modern Kraainem</head>
<p>Improvements to the road network after the <ref target="First%20World%20War">First World War</ref> led to a gradual decline of Kraainem's industrial importance, and by 1932 all mills had been closed and demolished. Very little of that industrial heritage remains today, as the industrial sites were reclaimed as residential areas after the <ref target="Second%20World%20War">Second World War</ref> when the connections between north Kraainem and Stokkel were paved, and subsequently also northern Kraainem experienced accelerated urbanization. Kraainem's population increased from 1739 in 1920 to 3330 inhabitants in 1947.</p>

<p>From 1927 onwards, the area south of Stokkel became the focus of further residential development. Still a part of the <ref target="Brussels/Sonian%20Forest">Sonian Forest</ref> until then, roads were constructed in the southern half of Kraainem, and soon afterwards the first villas were built. The Second World War put a temporary stop to the development of South Kraainem, but from the 1950s the deforestation accelerated and had completely urbanized the area by 1967. Only a small fraction of the Sonian Forest was preserved in the southern most point of Kraainem. It permanently shifted the municipality from an agricultural, forestry and trade to a residential focus. Kraainem is almost completely urbanized, although a few meadows remain in the northern half of Kraainem.</p>

<p>In the second half of the 20th century, Kraainem transformed from a <ref target="Flanders">Flemish</ref> town into an international community. Migration of <ref target="Wallonia">Wallonian</ref> citizens settling in Kraainem gave it an increasingly mixed urban population, to which Eurocrats were added after establishment of the European institutions in nearby Brussels.</p>

<head>Orientation</head>
<p>Situated to the east of <ref target="Brussels">Brussels</ref> and to the north of <ref target="Tervuren">Tervuren</ref>, Kraainems territory has the shape of an hourglass, with at its narrowest point a width of only 160 m. It is scarred by numerous highways, cutting into Kraainem from the west and north side. The north of Kraainem is a mostly flat area in the valley of the Maalbeek river, towards the centre and south its topography becomes hilly.</p>
</text>
