<text id="autogum_voyage_doc162" title="Driving in Italy" shortTile="driving-italy" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=154107" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Driving in Italy</head>


<ref target="Italy">Italy</ref> has a well-developed system of motorways (<hi rend="italic">autostrade</hi>) in the North, while in the South it's a bit worse for quality and extent.

<p>When on a timetable, use the <hi rend="italic">autostrade</hi> - marked in green - where available and avoid using the general highways - marked in blue - for long distances (unless they are the divided-carriageway, grade-separated <hi rend="italic">superstrade</hi>). While the toll on the <hi rend="italic">autostrade</hi> can be rather expensive, they significantly decrease your travel time, whereas general roads can be annoyingly slow since they are heavily used by local traffic, can be clogged with trucks, can feature lots of roundabouts or traffic lights and will often run through towns and villages without bypasses. On the other side, general roads often offer breath-taking scenery and should be your first choice if you are not in a rush and want to explore the real nature of the country.</p>

<head>Toll roads</head>

<p>Every motorway is identified by an A followed by a number on a green backdrop. Most motorways are toll roads. Some have toll stations giving you access to a whole section (particularly the <hi rend="italic">tangenziali</hi> of Naples, Rome, and Milan, for example), but generally, most have entrance and exit toll stations; on those motorways, you need to collect a ticket upon entrance and your toll amount will be calculated upon exit depending on the distance covered. Tolls depend on the motorways and stretches; as a rough estimate, you should expect a toll between €0.06 and €0.12 for each kilometre. Don't lose your entrance ticket, for if you do, it will be assumed you have entered the motorway at the farthest station from your exit and be charged the maximum toll possible.</p>

<p>All the <hi rend="bold">blue lanes</hi> (marked <hi rend="bold">"Viacard"</hi>) of toll stations are automatic machines accepting major credit cards as well as pre-paid cards (called <hi rend="italic">Viacard</hi>) that are for sale at service stations along the motorway or for instance at several tobacconists' in cities. If you have problems with the machine (e.g. your credit card can't be read), press the <hi rend="italic">assistenza</hi> button and wait for an operator to help you - be prepared to have to pay your toll in cash if problems persist. <hi rend="bold">Do not reverse</hi> to move into another lane, even if you might see other locals doing it, unless the personnel or the police clearly instruct you to do so; reversing in toll stations is considered equivalent to reversing on the motorway and <hi rend="italic">very heavily</hi> fined if you get caught.</p>

<p>Many Italians use an electronic pay-toll device, and there are reserved lanes marked in <hi rend="bold">Yellow</hi> with the sign <hi rend="bold">"Telepass"</hi> or a simply <hi rend="bold">"T"</hi>. Driving through those lanes (controlled by camera system) without the device will result in a fine and a payment of the toll for the longest distance. Due to agreement with other countries, if you're foreigner, you'll pay also extra cost for locating you in your country.</p>

<head>Traffic speed</head>

<p>Speeding on the <hi rend="italic">autostrade</hi> is nowadays far less common than in the past because of sensibly strengthened control in the last years. There are a number of automatic and almost invisible systems to punish speeding and hazardous driving, also Italian Highway Patrol (<hi rend="italic">Polizia Stradale</hi>) operates several unmarked cars equipped with very advanced speed radars and camera systems. Several sections of the Italian Highways are equipped with an automatic system called <hi rend="italic">Tutor</hi> with automatic license plate recognition, which checks the average speed of all vehicles over a road stretch. The coverage of this system is being extended to more and more motorways. At times, road signs will remind you of the presence of this system.</p>

<p>If virtually all vehicles around you seem to behave, scrupulously driving at the speed limit or even a bit below, this is a good hint that some kind of enforcement system is in operation on that road. As a foreigner, it will be better to stay on the safe side and respect limits and rules at all times, even when locals driving like crazy might lead you to think a certain speed limit or "no passing" sign was a mere suggestion: every now and then, those locals do encounter the police on their way.</p>

<p>Unless different limits are posted, general speed limits are:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> 130 km/h on motorways (<hi rend="italic">autostrade</hi>) (110 km/h in case of rain);</item>
<item> 110 km/h on divided, grade-separated highways marked with blue motorway signs at the entrances, called <hi rend="italic">superstrade</hi>;</item>
<item> 90 km/h general speed limit on highways and roads outside urban areas;</item>
<item> 50 km/h in urban areas - an urban area beginning with a white sign with the town/city name written in black, and ending with a similar sign barred in red.</item>
</list>


<p>Italian laws allow a 5% (minimum 5 km/h) tolerance on speed limits.</p>

<p>Fines are generally very expensive. If you are caught doing more than 40 km/h over the speed limit, you will be fined in excess of €500 and will receive an immediate driving ban from 1 to 3 months, leaving you on foot that very moment (you may reach the destination of your current journey). Non-resident drivers of vehicles with foreign registration are required either to pay their fines on the spot if they accept it, or to pay a deposit on the spot if they intend to appeal afterwards; either way, you must pay something immediately and the police won't hesitate to escort you to the nearest ATM to withdraw the cash you need. While chances of getting caught are admittedly not terribly high, you really don't want all of this to happen to you.</p>

<head>Traffic laws</head>

<p>All vehicles must use headlights at all times outside urban areas, including motorways. Motorbikes must drive with headlights on at all times everywhere.</p>

<p>The issue of drunk driving has received a great deal of attention in the last years after a series of lethal accidents. The tolerated limit is <hi rend="bold">0.50g/L</hi> in blood; being above this limit is a crime punishable by heavy fines, license revocation, jail time and even immediate confiscation of one's own vehicle in the most serious cases. The limit for drivers under 21 years of age or less than 3 years of driving experience or professional drivers is <hi rend="bold">zero</hi>. Unfortunately, enforcement, although stronger than before, is still insufficient and drunk driving is still somewhat an issue.</p>

<p>All passengers are required to wear their seat belts and children under 10 must use the back seats. Children under 12 years of age must use either an approved car seat or a seat booster, depending on the age.</p>

<p>At unmarked intersections, you are supposed to yield to any vehicle coming from your right. Be on the look-out because many Italians seem to ignore this rule and will insist on an non-existent right of way just because they are going straight on or they are travelling on what they think is the main road, even if the intersection is actually completely unmarked. This especially occurs in large cities at night time, when traffic lights at some intersections are switched off. Most times, the minor roads at those intersections will have a "give way" sign, but sometimes they don't, which is both confusing, because you never know if the crossing road has a sign or is unmarked, and dangerous because you might expect the vehicle coming from your left to let you pass while it will assume you have a "give way" sign and will carry on travelling like a bullet.</p>

<p>Many Italians don't take road markings too seriously (a few of them don't even seem to notice there are any road markings...), which can be odd if you come from north of the Alps. On multi-lane roads, you should always be wary of vehicles on other lanes invading your lane in curves. Lane markings in multi-lane roundabouts are systematically ignored and virtually all motorists will "cut off" while negotiating the roundabout and again when exiting, of course without signalling. There is a fair amount of confusion in Italy about the correct behaviour in large roundabouts; you should exercise caution there, expect vehicles entering, turning and exiting at any time without signalling and never travel side by side with other vehicles in a roundabout assuming the other will respect the lane markings.</p>
</text>
