<text id="autogum_whow_doc193" title="Parent Without Punishments" shortTile="parent-without-punishments" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-02-02" dateModified="2019-02-03" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Parent-Without-Punishments" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Parent Without Punishments</head><head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><figure rend="Think Step 5.jpg"></figure>Consider if this is right for your child. this parenting style will work for children that are cooperative and don't cause much trouble. on the other hand a child that tends to be quite stubborn and is defiant won't benefit from it.</item>
<item><figure rend="Be a Good Parent Step 2.jpg"></figure>Focus on positive reinforcement. because you won't be punishing your child you need to focus on praising and encouraging good behaviours as much as possible. even the small things matter like getting up on time or putting away their toys without being asked.
<list type="unordered"><item>There is no such thing as praising your child too much, this won't spoil them</item>
<item>Make sure to use descriptive praise, instead of saying "good boy" say "i really liked how you did your homework without being asked it really helps me out"</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Reward Your Child for Good Behavior Step 13.jpg"></figure>Reward your child for good behaviours. Every so often, give your child a reward such as a small new toy or a trip to the pool for good behaviour. Make sure to explain why they are getting the reward, for example "I thought we could go to the movies tonight because of how nice you were to your brother all week".
<list type="unordered"><item><figure rend="Reward Your Child for Good Behavior Step 12.jpg"></figure>See how to create a reward chart here: <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/Set-up-a-Reward-System-for-Children">https://www.wikihow.com/Set-up-a-Reward-System-for-Children</ref></item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Stay Calm when Your Parents Are Scolding You Badly Step 7.jpg"></figure> Ignore bad behaviours. If your child misbehaves, do not give them the attention they are acting out for until they stop. Afterwards say something short and quick such as "Thank you for stopping", then change the subject to something else so you can get on with the day.
<list type="unordered"><item>You can't ignore behaviours like violence and bullying you have will have to intervene</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Be a Good Parent Step 12.jpg"></figure> Scold worse behaviours. It's important to criticise the behaviour, not the child, so instead of saying "bad girl", say "I don't like your behaviour, please stop".
<list type="unordered"><item>Keep in mind that this isn't exactly punishing them, it is just asking them to stop their bad behaviour. Punishing would be grounding them or taking away their screen time.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Be a Good Parent Step 4.jpg"></figure> Make sure your home is judgement-free and listens to everyone's opinion; this includes your child's opinion. Never judge your child for their behaviour and always listen to their opinion. They deserve a say in how things work. This doesn't mean they get to dictate everything, but they have an influence on the final decision.
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, if a the child wants to go to the park but the mum doesn't want to drive there then they could settle on a park that is closer to their home.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Be a Good Parent Step 19.jpg"></figure> Make sure to support your child and ask what's wrong when they feel down. If you notice a change in their behaviour this could be due to something else that's happening in their life. Ask how school was everyday (to make sure nothing bad happened) and let your child know they can always come and talk to you.
<list type="unordered"><item>Be warned that if you judge your child's actions, even if they were wrong, your child can shut down and stop talking to you.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Sometimes just asking your child politely to do something instead of commanding them to will make them more willing to do it.</item>
<item>Consider hiring a counsellor if your child's behaviour or emotions get too out of hand.</item>
<item>A child that feels loved and listened to will be more likely to cooperate and have good behavior.</item>
<item>Encourage your child to do things to help around the house - but don't force them. If they do help, reward them.</item>
<item>Let children learn from their actions, for example if they don't wash their uniform before school they will have to wear a dirty uniform to school, or if they stay up late they will be tired the next morning.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Never ever hit a child - this is physical abuse and will severely affect your child, especially if you hit them often.</item>
<item>Don't say mean things to your child or make fun of them. It can lower their self esteem and can be considered emotional and verbal abuse.</item></list>
</text>
