<text id="autogum_voyage_doc75" title="Melbourne/Inner east" shortTile="melbourneinner-east" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=21935" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Melbourne/Inner east</head>

<p>The <hi rend="bold">inner east</hi> of <ref target="Melbourne">Melbourne</ref> consists of a number of suburbs and localities within the Yarra municipality. Compared with glitzy <ref target="Melbourne/Stonnington">Stonnington</ref> on the other side of the river, the inner eastern area is known among Melburnians as a working-class district, filled with pubs and old factories.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Richmond</hi> is the home of many low price fashion stores and restaurants; the northern area, centred on Victoria Street, is often called <hi rend="italic">Little Saigon</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Little Vietnam</hi> due to the huge number of Vietnamese food and shopping outlets. South Richmond is well known for its low price fashion - along Bridge Road - and other wholesale outlets, mostly found along Swan Street. <hi rend="bold">Fitzroy</hi> is known as the Bohemian quarter of the city, with numerous trendy boutiques interesting restaurants. Squeezed in the middle is <hi rend="bold">Collingwood</hi>, a suburb that is not held to such a high esteem as the surrounding neighbourhoods, but still has its fair share of character-filled pubs and heritage-listed industrial buildings. <hi rend="bold">Abbotsford</hi> sits on the eastern fringe by the river, with some nice parkland among disused factories and breweries.</p>

<head>Get in</head>


<p>The inner east can be easily accessed by tram, train and road. As far as public transport is concerned, all of the district lies within Zone 1 of Melbourne's two fare zone structure. See <ref target="Melbourne%23Get%20around">Melbourne's Get around</ref> section for an explanation of the zone system and fares.</p>

<head>By tram</head>
<p>There are an abundance of trams in the district, as most routes must pass through in order to reach suburbs that are further out. Major roads are listed along with the respective tram routes that traverse them.</p>

<head>Richmond</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Victoria Street</hi> in North Richmond is served by trams <hi rend="bold">30</hi> and <hi rend="bold">109</hi>. Tram 30 can be caught along La Trobe Street (weekdays only) while tram 109 can be caught along Collins Street in the City Centre.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bridge Road</hi> is served by trams <hi rend="bold">48</hi> and <hi rend="bold">75</hi>. The 48 operates along Collins Street and the 75 can be caught along Flinders Street in the City Centre.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Swan Street</hi> in the southern part of Richmond is served by tram <hi rend="bold">70</hi> which can also be caught along Flinders Street in the City Center.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Church Street</hi> is the main north-south road in Richmond and is served by tram <hi rend="bold">78</hi>. The route begins at the intersection of Victoria Street and Church Street in North Richmond and travel south along Church Street which then becomes Chapel Street. The tram terminates at Prahran in <ref target="Melbourne/Stonnington">Stonnington</ref>. They do not go into the City Centre.</item>
</list>


<head>Fitzroy</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Gertrude Street</hi> is the major east-west thoroughfare in Fitzroy. Tram <hi rend="bold">86</hi> runs its length, before turning into Smith Street. In the <ref target="Melbourne/City%20Centre">City Centre</ref>, it can be caught along Bourke Street. The two end stations for this line are the Telstra Dome in the Docklands, and RMIT Bundoora campus.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Nicholson Street</hi> is a major north-south thoroughfare that borders the <ref target="Melbourne/Inner%20north">inner north</ref> district. Tram <hi rend="bold">96</hi> can be caught along Bourke Street in the City Centre. The tram runs between <ref target="Melbourne/St%20Kilda">St Kilda</ref> and West Brunswick.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Brunswick Street</hi> also runs north-south, closer to the centre of town. It is served by tram <hi rend="bold">11</hi> and can be caught along Collins Street in the City Centre. The tram runs between <ref target="Melbourne/City_Centre">Docklands</ref> and West Preston in the <ref target="Melbourne/North">northern suburbs</ref>.</item>
</list>


<head>By train</head>
<p>Trains may be faster but they do not bring you to the heart of <hi rend="bold">Richmond</hi>, mostly skirting the western edge of the suburb. The exception is in the southern part of Richmond where trains on the Belgrave, Lilydale and Glen Waverly lines run parallel to <hi rend="bold">Swan Street</hi>, which is served by <hi rend="bold">Richmond</hi> (all trains stop here), <hi rend="bold">East Richmond</hi> (which most trains skip) and <hi rend="bold">Burnley stations</hi> (also skipped by many trains). North Richmond is served by <hi rend="bold">North Richmond</hi> station which is accessed from Victoria Street, whereas Bridge Road can be reached from <hi rend="bold">West Richmond</hi> station. While the stations are on both the South Morang and Hurstbridge lines, only the South Morang trains stop at both stations.</p>

<head>By bicycle</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bikes</hi> are the best way to get around a large part of the three inner city hubs of Collingwood, Fitzroy and Richmond. Thanks to the ample bike lanes, biking is the fastest way to get around.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>A number of frequent bus routes service areas not generally covered by tram or train services. They are best used for east-west travel or for getting to the University of Melbourne. Routes 200 and 207 operate every 10 minutes on Johnston St and Lygon Street (weekdays) from Melbourne Central in the CBD. Routes 250 and 251 also operate along Rathdowne Street.</p>

<head>By road</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Fitzroy</hi> can be easily reached from the <ref target="Melbourne/City%20Centre">City Centre</ref> via Nicholson Street, which connects to Spring Street in the eastern edge of the CBD, or Victoria Parade, which forms the southern border of the area. Gertrude Street runs off Nicholson Street while Smith and Brunswick Streets run off Victoria Parade. In the northern part of Fitzroy, both Brunswick Street and Smith Street intersect with Alexander Parade which leads on to the Eastern Freeway and the <ref target="Melbourne/Eastern">Eastern suburbs</ref>.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bridge Road</hi>. Within Richmond, it is most well known for its abundance of clothing factory outlets, which makes it a popular tourist attraction. There are also many stores of up-and-coming local fashion designers.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Brunswick Street</hi> - Long and lively cafe/bar strip in Fitzroy with cheap and decent eats. It's a mixture of eclectic and interesting shops, clothes and food. If street art is your thing, the surrounding alleyways and backstreets are also interesting, with an ever-changing array of graffiti, stencils and stickers on show.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Gertrude Street</hi> - Charming street of Fitzroy with cafes, bars, and unique clothing (and other) shops and art galleries. It runs an after dark light show. Centre of the local Aboriginal community.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Johnston Street</hi> - A street in Fitzroy, the western end is home of the local Hispanic community. Many restaurants, bars and pubs, and the infamous Tote Hotel.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Smith St</hi> - Slightly run down yet charming street in Fitzroy with cafes, bars, and unique clothing (and other) shops.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Victoria Street</hi> - In North Richmond, the street contains a strip of Vietnamese restaurants and shops.</item>
<item> The heritage listed <hi rend="bold">Foy &amp; Gibson factory</hi> buildings in Oxford St.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fitzroy Gardens and Conservatory</hi>. Conservatory is open daily 9AM-5PM (5:30PM daylight savings). Features a cafe and a conservatory amidst a lush garden setting.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Centre for Contemporary Photography</hi>, 404 George St, Fitzroy, ☏ +61 3 9417 1549 , ✉ info@ccp.org.au . W-Sa 11:00-6:0; Su noon-5PM. Daily night projections after dark. One of Australia's premier venues for displaying contemporary photographic works.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Collingwood Children's Farm</hi>, 18 St Heliers St, Abbotsford (Buses 200 or 207: Clarke St stop; cross road and up Clarke St, left at St Heliers and at end of street.), ☏ +61 3 9417 5806 , ✉ reception@farm.org.au . 9:15AM-4:30PM. Perched on the banks of the Yarra River, the attraction's aim is to provide a traditional country farm experience for city-dwellers. A perennial favourite with kids, the farm allows visitors to unwind in the peaceful setting whilst interacting with a variety of farm animals. Cow milking is held daily at 10AM and 4PM, and visitors can also cuddle animals such as guinea pigs, lambs and goats. A café is on-site, and a lively farmer's market is held on the second Saturday morning of each month. $10 adults, $5 children/concessions, $20 families (2A+4C).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Abbotsford Convent</hi>, 1 St Heliers St, Abbotsford (Buses 200 or 207: Clarke St stop; cross road and up Clarke St, left at St Heliers and on the right), ☏ +61 3 9415 3600 , ✉ info@abbotsfordconvent.com.au . 7:30AM-10PM daily. This site is host to a number of historic buildings which were originally home to sisters from a Christian religious order. Traditionally associated with community service, the convent now houses a variety of community organisations, including restaurants, bars and two art galleries. Many visitors simply enjoy the ambience of the grounds and soak up the building's history. Guided social history tours run every Sunday at 2PM for $15/person, but must be booked. There are also occasional markets and rotating exhibitions. Free entry.</item>
</list>
</text>
