<text id="autogum_interview_doc565" title="part1_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Family Coalition Party candidate Suzanne Fortin, Nepean-Carleton" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-26" dateModified="2013-03-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Family_Coalition_Party_candidate_Suzanne_Fortin%2C_Nepean-Carleton" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Aside from the personal qualities mentioned above, I think my commitment to fiscal and social policies makes my candidacy most attractive.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>Nepean-Carleton is a very family-oriented riding, so the important issues revolve around education, taxes and healthcare.</p>
<p>On the education front, the Family Coalition Party recognizes the parents as those  primarily responsible for the education of their children. We therefore propose a voucher system, where parents receive a voucher for each child and use it to fund the school of their choice, whether public or private, religious or not. This system would stimulate competition between schools and allow for greater local initiative, as there would be a greater opportunity for private individuals to start schools and fill needs without having to go through the public system.</p>
<p>With respect to taxes: we propose that the personal and spousal exemption be raised to $14 000 a year. We also think that there should be tax credits for each child in a family. We promote fiscal restraint so that we can keep down the tax burden.</p>
<p>On Healthcare: We propose a greater involvement of the private sector, while implementing a system of medical savings accounts. This system would be paid by the government, but insurance coverage would be provided by a private insurance company. The account would consist of CA$2000 for each resident, paid by the government. Whatever part of this account the individual does not use during the year will be rolled into an RRSP to help fund a retirement pension. If treatments cost more than $2000 a year for an individual, the insurance company covers those payments. The patient would not have to spend any of his own money, but he would have an incentive to not use the system, and the money that is not spent would be invested. The insurance company would have an incentive to keep down costs. Hospitals would finance themselves through services rendered.  If the patient chooses, he can purchase his own private insurance.</p>
<p>I would say that my three top issues are not entirely the same. Personally, I believe that the most urgent issue is the absence of legal protection for unborn children, and the fact that our tax dollars go towards paying for abortions. Most people favour de-funding abortion, because they recognize that scarce healthcare dollars should go towards treating injury and disease, so I don’t think this is very controversial.</p>
<p>This top issue of mine is interrelated with my other two top issues, as well as taxation that I mentioned above. They are democratic reform and eliminating excessive bureaucracy.  Eliminating bureaucracy means less government and fewer taxes. That way, families can rely on themselves and not have the government tell them how to spend their money. In this way they are somewhat interrelated.</p>
</text>
