<text id="autogum_whow_doc016" title="Become an Eclectic or Independent Music Beacon" shortTile="become-eclectic-independent" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2005-11-22" dateModified="2019-03-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Become-an-Eclectic-or-Independent-Music-Beacon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Become an Eclectic or Independent Music Beacon</head><p>It can be a daunting task, building a large, eclectic and interesting play list. This is an entirely subjective guide to how to be happier, more elitist and more impressive, on a tiny budget, without illegal downloading.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Start with a couple favorite bands that you already like. This is usually an option. It's generally best if you already like one of the historically important old indie rock bands listed below, mainly if you are going for the all-encompassing eclectic-indie kind of play list that is so very rewarding. However, if you, right now, fit into the Warnings category, you have to start somewhere on the road to cool-geekdom (it's the best way to superficial popularity there is!).If you don't already, buy at least one full album each by at least three of the bands listed below. Make sure you actually like the bands. <figure rend="Become an Eclectic or Independent Music Beacon Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Read up on the bands you've chosen using the sources listed in Tips. Pay attention to the movement, genre or scene the band is considered a part of, and even more attention to any given similar-artists type information. <figure rend="Become an Eclectic or Independent Music Beacon Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Look up whatever related bands you can find. This is important. Listen to them if possible. Start making a list of albums to buy, or just bands to look for. <figure rend="Become an Eclectic or Independent Music Beacon Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep  reading about the history of the bands! Not the members or the dates of course, but the influences and music and genre. <figure rend="Become an Eclectic or Independent Music Beacon Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Never be intimidated by bands you've never heard of, especially not old ones. If someone is talking to you about a band you don't know, ask them. Go to small venue concerts whenever possible. Who cares if you know the band? <figure rend="Become an Eclectic or Independent Music Beacon Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Develop your own tastes. Find your own bands. Try to focus on a niche genre while also building your overall collection. Jazz. Noise rock. Experimental. Delta blues. Lounge. Soul. Crust punk. There are so many weird bands out there, what are you waiting for? No one will ever think you are cool because you listen to loud music. Remember that metal is the most popular form of music as far as sales go.  "Just because it's loud doesn't mean it's good."If you go to a noise rock concert, seriously, wear earplugs. <figure rend="Become an Eclectic or Independent Music Beacon Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Last.fm and Pandora.com are great ways to find new music you like.  Here's their description of themselves: "Pandora is a music discovery service designed to help you find and enjoy music that you'll love. It's powered by the Music Genome Project, the most comprehensive analysis of music ever undertaken. Just tell us one of your favorite songs or artists and we'll launch a streaming station to explore that part of the music universe."</item>
<item>If you live near one, Half Price Books is a great place to get cheap music. They almost always have CDs for $2 or less.</item>
<item>There are many independent music distribution sites out there now where you can stock up on huge amounts of obscure mp3s for free - try sites like Amie Street, Podcomplex and Broadjam.</item>
<item>iTunes is an excellent way to find new music, except that it doesn't have an entirely complete selection. But the music store's Browse feature is awesome. Look randomly for interesting-looking bands, then double click them and see if there's a biography. Also, the All-Music Guide To Rock is very nice. It's a little hard to build your tastes from this, but LastFM is good for seeing what people like you are listening to - particularly if you live outside the US, now that Pandora has been blocked.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are just listening to the bands just to look cool, people who are really into the bands will see right through your pathetic attempts.</item>
<item>Don't spend too much money, as in: don't go broke for music.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>A computer</item>
<item>An Internet connection</item>
<item>A media library program, such as Media Monkey or iTunes</item>
<item>Songbird, a program based off of the Mozilla open-source platform, aggregates mp3 blogs and samples songs (it's a great way to access new and upcoming artists)</item></list>
</text>
