<text id="autogum_voyage_doc383" title="Diving in Mozambique" shortTile="diving-mozambique" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=9620" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Diving in Mozambique</head>

<p>This article is intended to provide the already qualified Scuba diver with information which will help to plan dives in the waters of <ref target="Mozambique">Mozambique</ref>, whether as a local resident or a visitor. Information is provided without prejudice, and is not guaranteed accurate or complete. Use it at your own risk.</p>

<head>General topography</head>
<p>Mozambique has a long coastline spread out over the tropical east coat of Africa south of the equator, with several islands on the continental shelf. Reef-building corals live where there is suitable substrate and good light – generally where there is no major river mouth nearby. The current generally flows north to south, and can be strong. This carries turbid water away, and makes drift diving necessary in many places.</p>

<head>Climate, weather and sea conditions</head>
<p>Mozambique has a tropical climate with two seasons, a wet season from October to March and a dry season from April to September. Rainfall is heavy along the coast and decreases in the north and south. Cyclones are common during the wet season.</p>

<p>The sea temperature is tropical. Water temperatures range from 29˚C in summer to 22˚C in winter, and will seldom be below 24˚C. Diving is year round. People from cooler climates may find winter more comfortable, and there are fewer mosquitos as this is the dry season.</p>

<p>Visibility can range from 8–40 m, depending on the amount of plankton in the water.</p>

<head>Marine ecology</head>

<p>The marine ecology of Mozambique is classified as Tropical Indo-Pacific, which is the most diverse marine ecology known. Obviously not all species from this bioregion will be found in all parts of it, but this is an indication of the diversity which can be expected here. A wide range of reef building corals, and also other coral types can be found here, along with a diverse invertebrate fauna sharing the shelter and habitat provided by the corals. Fish are also represented by a large diversity of species, many of which are particularly colourful.</p>

<p>Humpback whales can be spotted during their migration from June until November.</p>

<p>Whale sharks are present all year round and in abundance between November and March. These gentle</p>
<p>giants can reach up to 12m in length and weigh up to 20tonnes.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<p>Pick up's can be arranged through lodges, dive centres etc. But there is ample public transport and it is safe and easy to walk to most places in the area.</p>

<head>Southern Mozambique</head>
<p>Southern <ref target="Mozambique">Mozambique</ref> includes the <hi rend="italic">Municipios</hi> of <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Maputo%20%28region%29">Maputo</ref></hi>, <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Gaza%20%28region%29">Gaza</ref></hi>, <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Inhambane%20%28region%29">Inhambane</ref></hi> and <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Sofala%20%28Region%29">Sofala</ref></hi> from the southern border with <ref target="South%20Africa">South Africa</ref> at <ref target="Ponta%20d%27Ouro">Ponta d'Ouro</ref> north to the Zambesi river.</p>

<head>Ponta do Ouro to Ponta Mamoli</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Dive sites include:</hi></p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> G-Spot</item>
<item> Fish Basket</item>
<item> Pinnacles</item>
<item> Bass City</item>
<item> Kev's Ledge</item>
<item> Wayne's World</item>
<item> Aquarium</item>
<item> Three Sisters</item>
<item> Doodles</item>
<item> Mavericks</item>
<item> Texas</item>
<item> Shallow Malongane</item>
<item> Paradise Ledge</item>
<item> Checkers</item>
</list>


<head>Manta Coast</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Dive sites include:</hi></p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Amazon</item>
<item> Arcadia</item>
<item> Area 51</item>
<item> Barra Lagoon/Estuary</item>
<item> <ref target="Diving%20in%20Mozambique/Batfish%20Pinnacle">Batfish Pinnacle</ref></item>
<item> Buddies Reef</item>
<item> Deep Reef South</item>
<item> <ref target="Diving%20in%20Mozambique/Devils%20Peak">Devil's Peak</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Diving%20in%20Mozambique/Disneyland">Disneyland</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Diving%20in%20Mozambique/Greentree%20Reef">Greentree Reef</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Diving%20in%20Mozambique/Hard%20Rock">Hard Rock</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Diving%20in%20Mozambique/Island%20Rock">Island Rock</ref></item>
<item> Kitwe</item>
<item> <ref target="Diving%20in%20Mozambique/Manta%20Reef">Manta Reef</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Diving%20in%20Mozambique/North%20Greentree">North Greentree</ref></item>
<item> The "Klipfontein" wreck</item>
<item> <ref target="Diving%20in%20Mozambique/The%20Office">The Office</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Diving%20in%20Mozambique/Paindane%20Coral%20Garden">Paindane Coral Garden</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Diving%20in%20Mozambique/Paindane%20Express">Paindane Express</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Diving%20in%20Mozambique/Pao%20Reef">Pao Reef</ref></item>
<item> Playstation</item>
<item> Pomene Estuary</item>
<item> Salon</item>
<item> Three Sisters</item>
<item> Trojan Wall</item>
<item> Witch's Hat</item>
<item> <ref target="Diving%20in%20Mozambique/Xstacy%20Reef">Xstacy Reef (XTC)</ref></item>
</list>


<h5><ref target="Tofo%20Beach">Tofo Beach</ref></h5>
<p>Nice coral but known more for its abundance of manta rays, reef sharks, whale sharks and humpback whales.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Liquid Adventures</hi>, ☏ +258 845363636 . They are a PADI dive centre offering all courses from Open Water through to Assistant Instructor and also offer various other watersport activities.</item>
</list>


<h5><ref target="Guinjata%20Bay">Guinjata Bay</ref></h5>
<p>A small bay just south of Inhambane on a long stretch of sandy coastline. The reefs are sedimentary rock with a covering of hard and soft corals and other invertebrates. Marine life is Indo-Pacific.</p>

<head>Ponta Morrungulo</head>

<p>About half way between Inhambane to the south and Vilanculos to the north.</p>
<p>About one and a half hours from Inhambane by road, and six hours from Maputo.</p>
<p>Depth range 6 to 40m.</p>
<p>Water temperatures about 24°C in winter to 29°C in summer.</p>
<p>Humpback whales visit from June tyo October.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Dive sites include:</hi></p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Sylvia shoal</hi> — about 12 km north of Ponta Morrungulo. The shoal is about 14 km long, rising from bottom at about 22m to around 10m on top, with a shallow point at 8m. The reef is home to a large variety of nudibranchs, turtles, mantas, rays, eels and sharks</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Aladdin's Palace</hi> — In the middle of Sylvia shoal. The reef is about 35m wide, on a sand bottom. There is a cleaning station on the seawrd side of the reef which is frequently visited by mantas. The reef includestable corals and large crevices, in which large rock lobster can be seen. Moray eels also lurk in the cracks, and schools of barracuda and kingfish are often seen above the reef. Residents include grouper, potato bass, and turtles. Eagle rays, devil rays and white tip sharks are also to be seen.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tokyo Drift</hi> — Clear water in the Mozambique current. Reef with hard and soft corals and a wide variety of reef fish species. Also eagle rays, devil rays, and mantas may be seen, and possibly a shark or two. Hammerheads,Tiger sharks, Bull sharks and Oceanic black tip sharks have been spotted here.</item>
</list>


<p><hi rend="bold">New Year reef</hi> — A 9 km long reef system south of Sylvia shoal.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sherwoods Bookshelf</hi> — About 1 km east of the New Years reef system. It has a 300m long rocky fault line. There are massive green tree corals large numbers of reef fish. On the outside of the shoals of reef fish there are often large game fish.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">King Deep</hi> — The site is named after the South African underwater photographer, Dennis King, because this is the furthest north that the Tiger Angel Fish, which he identified, has been recorded. On the reef there are forests of Green Tree Coral with large numbers of coral fish sheltering from predators such as Kingfish and Barracuda. You may also see Potato Bass, Mantas, Sharks, Eagle Rays and other game fish.</item>
</list>


<h4>Vilanculos and the <ref target="Bazaruto">Bazaruto</ref> Archipelago</h4>
<p><hi rend="bold">Dive sites include:</hi></p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> The Corner</item>
<item> Ray Alley</item>
<item> Brindle Bass Ridge</item>
<item> Allan's realm</item>
<item> Amphitheatre</item>
<item> Camel Hump</item>
<item> Twelve Mile Reef</item>
<item> Turtle Ridge</item>
<item> Manta Ray Reef</item>
<item> Rainbow Runner</item>
<item> Aquarium</item>
<item> Greek Temple</item>
<item> Ponta Dundo</item>
<item> Five Mile Reef</item>
</list>
</text>
