<text id="autogum_interview_doc821" title="part6_Satanism: An interview with Church of Satan High Priest Peter Gilmore" shortTile="partsatanism-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-04" dateModified="2018-10-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Satanism%3A_An_interview_with_Church_of_Satan_High_Priest_Peter_Gilmore" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  If someone wanted to explore your beliefs, what should they read?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Satanic%20Bible">The Satanic Bible</ref></hi> is the place to start, because that is the foundational literature for the organization.  All of Anton LaVey’s books are worth reading.  <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Satanic%20Witch">The Satanic Witch</ref></hi> is his compendium of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lesser%20Magic">Lesser Magic</ref>, which is our concept for how you manipulate people on a day-to-day basis to get them to do things in your favor.  It’s geared toward women because we think it’s fine for women to use their <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Human%20female%20sexuality">sexuality</ref> to get what they want.  It’s part of nature, so go ahead!  Dress for success!  But it works for guys, too.  Whatever you have to charm people.  Glamor is worthwhile, so <hi rend="italic">The Satanic Witch</hi> is useful for that.  He’s got collections of essays, too, and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Satanic%20Rituals">The Satanic Rituals</ref></hi> is more for a formal setting, where different cultures were examined to see what kind of diabolical imagery was in them.  Rituals can be fun to do in a large group setting; but they’re not anything you have to do.  Here’s a Russian one, here’s a French one; here’s a German one.   Here's a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black%20Mass">Black Mass</ref>—what would that be like?  In Satanism a Black Mass is not something we are running out and eager to do because as far as we’re concerned, Christianity is a dead horse, unless in your life you feel there has been this really negative Christian influence that you need to purge, it’s just kind of pointless.</p>
<p>And my book, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Satanic%20Scriptures">The Satanic Scriptures</ref></hi>, is worth reading, because it ties up where we have been, where we are now, and where we are going.  So if you only picked two, I would say read <hi rend="italic">The Satanic Bible</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Satanic Scriptures</hi>, because then you’ll have the book ends of the over forty year span of the Church of Satan.</p>
<head id="On_current_events_and_politics">On current events and politics</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I’d like to give you some political situations and ask how a Satanist would handle them.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  Okay, but I want to preface that and say we don't really determine people’s political backgrounds.  We feel that each Satanist who is a member of the church must make those decisions based upon their own personal values, so there can be a wide range of answers depending upon the people you talk to, whether it be abortion, governmental decisions of going to war…</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You can just speak for yourself, then.  If you were <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/President_of_the_United_States">President</ref>—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  —[<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  —How would you handle the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Israeli-Palestinian_conflict">Israeli-Palestinian issue</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  I don't have a solution for that.  If I did, I would be out there telling people about it, because I don't really see myself as a politician or arbiter of people’s interactions with each other.  I can see that there are issues on both sides of the fence and that when people are fighting over a territory, generally speaking the folks who have the power win and then they write the histories and the world moves on.  But we have a situation here where there are bigger players behind the smaller nations, and it keeps this conflict enduring.  So they will either have to have compromise and discussion, or one side will have to destroy the other side and "win" and then move on, which is usually the way the world works.</p>
</text>
