<text id="autogum_bio_doc438" title="Francis Gawdy" shortTile="francis-gawdy" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-09-23" dateModified="2019-03-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_Gawdy" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Francis Gawdy</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sir Francis Gawdy</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen's_Serjeant">QS</ref> (died 15 December 1605) was an English judge. He was the third son of Thomas Gawdy, and was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baptism">baptised</ref> Thomas Gawdy, as were his two older half-brothers.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-odb-1">[1]</ref> Francis then had his name changed at his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Confirmation">Confirmation</ref>, establishing legal precedent that a name given at baptism could be changed at confirmation.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> He may have studied at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trinity_Hall,_Cambridge">Trinity Hall, Cambridge</ref>, matriculating in 1545,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> and was called to the bar at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inner_Temple">Inner Temple</ref> in 1549, becoming a bencher in 1558 and treasurer in 1571. He served as a reader at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lyon's_Inn">Lyon's Inn</ref> in 1561 and at Inner Temple in 1566 and 1571. He had an unremarkable parliamentary career, elected to represent <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morpeth_(UK_Parliament_constituency)">Morpeth</ref> for the 1571 election, but focused mainly on his legal career. He was made <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serjeant-at-law">Serjeant-at-law</ref> in 1577 and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen's_Serjeant">Queen's Serjeant</ref> in 1582, and as Queen's Serjeant opened the prosecution against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary,_Queen_of_Scots">Mary, Queen of Scots</ref>. In 1563 he married Elizabeth Coningsby,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-odb-1">[1]</ref> who was described by Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Spelman">Henry Spelman</ref> as </p><p>having this manor, in right of his wife, he induced her to acknowledge a fine thereof upon which she became a distracted woman and continued so to the day of her death and was to him for many years a perpetual affliction</p>
<p>Perhaps because she believed (correctly) he had cheated her out of interest from Eston Hall, her ancestral home.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-odb-1">[1]</ref> He also obtained <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fincham_Hall">Fincham Hall</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-finch-5">[5]</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wallington_Hall_(Norfolk)">Wallington Hall</ref> which had been in the possession of Elizabeth's father, William Coningsby's family.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-spel-6">[6]</ref> Collinsby had been the recorder in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King's_Lynn">King's Lynn</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-house-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>Gawdy succeeded his elder brother, the middle <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Gawdy_(died_1588)">Thomas Gawdy</ref>, as a justice of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King's_Bench">King's Bench</ref> in 1588, and took part in many of the major trials of this period, including that of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_Raleigh">Sir Walter Raleigh</ref> in 1603, and was knighted the same year. Gawdy apparently expected to succeed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sir_William_Peryam">Sir William Peryam</ref> as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Chief_Baron_of_the_Exchequer">Lord Chief Baron of the Exchequer</ref>, but <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_I_of_England">James I</ref> informed him he was being saved for a more senior position when it became available, appointing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Fleming_(judge)">Sir Thomas Fleming</ref> instead. In August 1605 Gawdy was appointed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chief_Justice_of_the_Common_Pleas">Chief Justice of the Common Pleas</ref>, a position he did not get to enjoy, dying of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apoplexy">apoplexy</ref> on 15 December at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serjeant's_Inn">Serjeant's Inn</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-odb-1">[1]</ref> He had one daughter who was also called Elizabeth.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-spel-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>After his death his body was brought from London to Wallington and it is said that they could find no place to bury his body as he was refused space locally.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-house-7">[7]</ref> (Gawdy had depopulated the town around his hall and converted the church to a dog kennel or hay store.) As the smell of the body became offensive he was eventually buried without ceremony at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Runcton">Runcton</ref> church and only paving stones were used to cover the grave. The parish register at Runcton records that he was buried in the chancel by the local parson on 27 February (although the differing calendars would account for much of this apparent delay).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-finch-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>It was noted in 1829 that Wallington church was in ruins although the Hall was well repaired.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-spel-6">[6]</ref> Wallington Hall which has been described as a "Tudor Rose in Bloom". The house still stands today in nearly 600 acres (2.4km2) near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King's_Lynn">King's Lynn</ref> and was valued at five million pounds in 2006.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-house-7">[7]</ref></p>
</text>
