<text id="autogum_academic_doc270" title="On Expansive Mappings" shortTile="expansive-mappings" author="Marat  V. Markin, Edward  S. Sichel" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2227-7390/7/11/1004/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><quote><hi rend="italic">O God, I could be bounded in a nutshell, and count myself a king of infinite space - were it not that I have bad dreams.</hi>William Shakespeare (Hamlet, Act 2, Scene 2)</quote> </p>

<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>We take a close look at the nature of expansive mappings on certain metric spaces (compact, totally bounded, and bounded), provide a finer classification for such mappings, and use them to characterize boundedness. </p>

<p>When finding an original proof to a known result describing all expansive mappings on compact metric spaces as surjective isometries (Problem ), we reveal that relaxing the condition of compactness to total boundedness still preserves the isometry property and nearly that of surjectivity. </p>

<p>We provide a counterexample of a not totally bounded metric space, on which the only expansion is the identity mapping, demonstrating that the converse to the above descriptions do not hold. </p>

<p>Various examples for different types of expansions are furnished, in particular the one of a nonsurjective expansion on a totally bounded “dial set” in the complex plane which allows us to better understand the essence of the latter. </p>

<head> 2. Preliminaries</head>
<p>Here, we outline certain preliminaries essential for the subsequent discourse (for more, see, e.g.,).<hi rend="bold">Definition</hi><hi rend="bold">1</hi></p>

<p>(Sequential Compactness)<hi rend="bold">.</hi> </p>

<p><hi rend="italic">A set A in a metric space  is called sequentially compact, or compact in the Bolzano-Weierstrass sense, if every sequence  of its elements contains a subsequence convergent to an element of A.</hi> </p>

<p><hi rend="italic">A metric space  is said to be sequentially compact if sequentially compact is the set X.</hi><hi rend="bold">Remark</hi><hi rend="bold">1.</hi></p>

<p><hi rend="italic">In a metric space setting, the above definition of compactness is equivalent to compactness in the Heine-Borel sense defined via open covers (see, e.g.,).</hi> </p>

<p>It is convenient for us to use a sequential definition for total boundedness as well (see, e.g.,).<hi rend="bold">Definition</hi><hi rend="bold">2</hi></p>

<p>(Total Boundedness)<hi rend="bold">.</hi> </p>

<p><hi rend="italic">A set A in a metric space  is called totally bounded if every sequence of its elements contains a fundamental (Cauchy) subsequence.</hi> </p>

<p><hi rend="italic">A metric space  is said to be totally bounded if totally bounded is the set X.</hi><hi rend="bold">Definition</hi><hi rend="bold">3</hi></p>

<p>(Boundedness)<hi rend="bold">.</hi> </p>

<p><hi rend="italic">A set A in a metric space  is said to be bounded if</hi>

<hi rend="italic">the number  being called the diameter of A.</hi> </p>

<p><hi rend="italic">A metric space  is said to be bounded if bounded is the set X.</hi><hi rend="bold">Remark</hi><hi rend="bold">2.</hi></p>

<p><hi rend="italic">In a metric space, a (sequentially) compact set is totally bounded and a totally bounded set is bounded but not vice versa (see, e.g.,).</hi> </p>

<head> 3. Expansive Mappings</head>
<p>Now, we introduce and further classify the focal subject of our study, <hi rend="italic">expansive mappings</hi> (or <hi rend="italic">expansions</hi>).<hi rend="bold">Definition</hi><hi rend="bold">4</hi></p>

<p>(Expansive Mapping)<hi rend="bold">.</hi> </p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Let  be a metric space. A mapping  on  such that</hi> <hi rend="italic">is called an expansive mapping (or expansion).</hi> </p>

<p>It is important for our discourse to introduce a finer classification of expansions.<hi rend="bold">Definition</hi><hi rend="bold">5</hi></p>

<p>(Types of Expansions)<hi rend="bold">.</hi> </p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Let  be a metric space.</hi> </p>

<p>
<list>
<item><hi rend="italic">(1)</hi> An expansion  such that <hi rend="italic">is called an isometry, which is the weakest form of expansive mappings.</hi></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">(2)</hi><hi rend="italic">An expansion  such that</hi><hi rend="italic">we call a proper expansion.</hi></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">(3)</hi><hi rend="italic">An expansion  such that</hi><hi rend="italic">we call a strict expansion.</hi></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">(4)</hi><hi rend="italic">Finally, an expansion  such that</hi><hi rend="italic">we call an anticontraction with expansion constant E.</hi></item>
</list>
</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Remark</hi><hi rend="italic">3.</hi></p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Clearly, any anticontraction is necessarily a strict expansion, which in turn is also a proper expansion. However, as the following examples demonstrate, the converse statements are not true.</hi><hi rend="bold">Example</hi><hi rend="bold">1.</hi></p>

<p>
<list>
<item><hi rend="italic">1.</hi><hi rend="italic">On  with the standard metric, the mapping</hi><hi rend="italic">i.e., the counterclockwise rotation by one radian, is an isometry which is not a proper expansion.</hi></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">2.</hi><hi rend="italic">On the space  of all real- or complex-termed bounded sequences with its standard supremum metric</hi><hi rend="italic">the right shift mapping</hi><hi rend="italic">is also an isometry which is not a proper expansion.</hi></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">3.</hi><hi rend="italic">On , the mapping</hi><hi rend="italic">is a proper expansion that is not strict, since, for ,</hi><hi rend="italic">but, for ,</hi></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">4.</hi><hi rend="italic">In the space , consider the set of the equivalence classes  represented by the functions</hi><hi rend="italic">( is the characteristic function of a set), which is a subset of the unit sphere</hi><hi rend="italic">For any  with , we have:</hi><hi rend="italic">The map , , with an arbitrary fixed  is an isometry on  since, for any  with ,</hi><hi rend="italic">On the other hand, the map , , is a strict expansion on  since, for any  with ,</hi><hi rend="italic">which is not an anticontraction since</hi></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">5.</hi><hi rend="italic">On  with the standard metric, the mapping</hi><hi rend="italic">is an anticontraction with expansion constant . However, the same mapping, when considered on  equipped with the metric</hi><hi rend="italic">turning  into a bounded space (see, e.g.,), is merely a strict expansion, which is not an anticontraction since</hi></item>
</list>
</p>

<head> 4. Expansions on Compact Metric Spaces</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Theorem</hi><hi rend="bold">1</hi></p>
<p>(Expansions on Compact Metric Spaces (Problem ))<hi rend="bold">.</hi> </p>

<p><hi rend="italic">An expansive mapping T on a compact metric space  is a surjection, i.e.,</hi><hi rend="italic">and an isometry, i.e.,</hi><hi rend="bold">Proof.</hi></p>

<p>For an arbitrary point , and an increasing sequence  of natural numbers, consider the sequence in . </p>
</text>
