<text id="autogum_interview_doc841" title="part11_ACLU President Strossen on religion, drugs, guns and impeaching George Bush" shortTile="partaclu-president" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-30" dateModified="2019-02-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/ACLU_President_Strossen_on_religion%2C_drugs%2C_guns_and_impeaching_George_Bush" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iranian_President_Ahmadinejad_speaks_at_Columbia_University">Ahmadinejad came to Columbia</ref> and brought that argument up.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  Yeah, right.  So we have squandered our moral legitimacy, we have squandered the legitimacy of the whole international human rights regime post World War II, of democracy, and as I always tell my students, once you lose your credibility or people’s respect for your integrity, it may not be irreparable, but it takes <hi rend="italic">such</hi> a long time to restore that, and ultimately our national security depends on that.  So I’m really fearful.  I’m ultimately optimistic in the long run, but it’s a longer run than it would have been pre-9/11, and not because of the terrorist attacks, but because of our reaction to the terrorist attacks.  And the use of that to get us into Iraq, and the erosion of trust—this is something <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chuck%20Hagel">Hagel</ref> was talking about—the erosion of trust toward government on the part of the American people, and particularly younger generations.  It was really corrosive.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It’s surprising that Hagel gave that criticism since it is his party that has instituted the fear of government into our culture.  Such as Reagan’s famous line that the most terrifying words in the English language are, “I’m from the government and I’m here to help.”</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  These parties are so heterogeneous, believe me, I would not want to be associated with a single one.  Even the ACLU does things I personally disagree with, so I would not want guilt by association.  If the party platform reflected [Hagel’s] views, it would be a different party than it is now.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gay_Talese_on_the_state_of_journalism,_Iraq_and_his_life">When I interviewed Gay Talese</ref>, I asked him how the Iraq War affected him and he said it had not.  He said, “I wish it did!”  He said he doesn’t feel anything and that he doesn’t think anyone else does, either.  He feels you can’t have a war affect people unless you have <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conscription%20in%20the%20United%20States">conscription</ref>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  I totally agree with that, I completely agree with that.  Charlie Rangel, as you probably know, I completely agree with that.  The ACLU has always opposed the draft, going back to our founding, as in our view being inconsistent with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thirteenth%20Amendment%20to%20the%20United%20States%20Constitution">Thirteenth Amendment</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Involuntary%20servitude">involuntary servitude</ref>, but our fall-back position has always been, having lost on that argument, that if you are going to have a draft then it may not be discriminatory; it should apply to women as well as men.  We took that case to the Supreme Court.  You can’t have exemptions for students and others who are privileged, and partly because that’s consistent with Equal Protection guarantees, but that means that the way to enforce fairness:  everybody has to be treated equally.  To have members of Congress and the Executive Branch send <hi rend="italic">other</hi> people’s kids off to war, or other people’s spouses, they are <hi rend="italic">not</hi> making a responsible decision if they do not have to feel the cost.  I could not agree with that more strongly.  The result might be then we would then have no war.  It’s the same thing with all the deprivations of liberty in the war on terror, if I may say so.  All those surveys that say, “Are you willing to give up freedom to enhance national security?”  The reason people say yes is they are willing to give up somebody ELSE’S freedom.  Okay, so take it away from the Muslims…</p>
</text>
