<text id="autogum_news_doc617" title="NASA&apos;s InSight lander and MarCO craft launch in new mission to Mars" shortTile="nasas-insight-lander" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2018-05-05" dateModified="2019-08-23" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NASA%27s_InSight_lander_and_MarCO_craft_launch_in_new_mission_to_Mars" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>NASA's InSight lander and MarCO craft launch in new mission to Mars</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, May 7, 2018</hi></p>
<figure><caption>The foggy launch of the Atlas V rocket carrying <hi rend="italic">InSight</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">MarCO</hi> cubesats. Image: Bill Ingalls, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NASA">NASA</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>On Saturday, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20Launch%20Alliance">United Launch Alliance</ref> launched a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atlas%20V">Atlas V 401</ref> rocket carrying <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NASA">NASA</ref>'s <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/InSight">InSight</ref></hi> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mars">Mars</ref> lander and two <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mars%20Cube%20One">Mars Cube One</ref></hi> (<hi rend="italic">MarCO</hi>) miniature spacecraft known as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CubeSat">cubesats</ref>. The pre-dawn launch from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vandenberg%20Air%20Force%20Base">Vandenberg Air Force Base</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vandenberg%20AFB%20Space%20Launch%20Complex%203">Space Launch Complex 3E</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lompoc,%20California">Lompoc, California</ref> was declared a success. This was the very first deep space launch from the west coast of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref>, and aimed to send a lander to the surface of the planet Mars to study its interior. </p>
<p>Launched alongside <hi rend="italic">InSight</hi> were two <hi rend="italic">MarCO</hi> cubesats, the first to be sent beyond Earth, nicknamed 'WALL-E' and 'Eve' after the protagonists of the 2008 animated science fiction film <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WALL-E">WALL-E</ref></hi>. They were designed as a dual telecommunications relay for <hi rend="italic">InSight</hi> during the spacecraft's descent through the Martian atmosphere.</p>
<p>Traditionally, NASA launched interplanetary spacecraft at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cape%20Canaveral%20Air%20Force%20Station">Cape Canaveral Air Force Station</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Florida">Florida</ref> on the United States' east coast. There, rockets were sent eastward over the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Atlantic_Ocean">Atlantic Ocean</ref>, borrowing the Earth's rotational velocity to shoot their payloads out into the solar system. Due to congestion on the launch calendar at Canaveral, NASA chose to launch the spacecraft from from Vandenberg Air Force Base on the country's west coast instead. A launch eastward from Vandenberg would have been dangerous due to densely populated areas being located downrange. Instead, rockets launched from Vandenberg were sent in a south-southeast trajectory. For <hi rend="italic">Insight</hi> and <hi rend="italic">MarCO</hi>, the spacecraft was placed in a temporary <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/polar%20orbit">polar orbit</ref> after the launch, with the pair being shot towards Mars during a escape burn performed over the North Pole.</p>
<p>Despite a heavy fog settling in at the rocket's launch pad in Lompoc, the United Launch Alliance declared a "100% chance of favorable weather for liftoff". Spectators in Lompoc were treated to a mostly obscured view of the launch, though they were witness nonetheless to the sound and shock waves of the Atlas V's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Common%20Core%20Booster">Common Core first stage</ref> as it lifted the spacecraft off the ground on-schedule at 4:05 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pacific%20Time%20Zone#Daylight_time">PDT</ref> (1105 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UTC">UTC</ref>). People along the coast of southern <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/California">California</ref> and northern <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Baja_California_peninsula">Baja California</ref>, however, were in clear view of the Atlas V's main engine burn and the first burn of the rocket's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Centaur%20(rocket%20stage)">Centaur upper stage</ref>. People in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Orange_County,_California">Orange County, California</ref> were treated to the sight of <hi rend="italic">InSight</hi> and the Centaur almost eclipsing the planet <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jupiter">Jupiter</ref> in the night sky.</p>
<figure><caption>Artist concept of <hi rend="italic">InSight</hi> probing the Mars surface Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NASA">NASA</ref>/<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JPL">JPL</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>The recently-inaugurated Administrator of NASA, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jim%20Bridenstine">Jim Bridenstine</ref>, congratulated the <hi rend="italic">InSight</hi> team in an address televised live on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NASA%20TV">NASA TV</ref> after the launch, along with the United Launch Alliance on what was their 128th successful launch in a row. The <hi rend="italic">InSight</hi> mission part of NASA's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Discovery%20program">Discovery program</ref>, a class of low-cost solar system exploration missions. It was selected to launch in the program after beating the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comet%20Hopper">Comet Hopper</ref></hi> and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Titan%20Mare%20Explorer">Titan Mare Explorer</ref></hi> proposals amongst responses to a 2010 request.</p>
<p>Both <hi rend="italic">InSight</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">MarCO</hi> cubesats are en route to Mars. <hi rend="italic">InSight</hi> carries eight scientific instruments, including a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/seismometer">seismometer</ref> known as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seismic%20Experiment%20for%20Interior%20Structure">Seismic Experiment for Interior Structure</ref> (SEIS). The SEIS instrument will be recording the very first seismic measurements of Mars, which scientists hope will shed light on the structure of Mars beneath its surface. The lander was equipped with two cameras, based on the architecture of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mars%20Exploration%20Rover">Mars Exploration Rover</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Navcam">navigation camera</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hazcam">hazard avoidance camera</ref>, to allow mission scientists to monitor the activity of the instruments. NASA scheduled a November 26 landing for <hi rend="italic">InSight</hi> on a broad plain in the planet's northern hemisphere, known as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elysium%20Planitia">Elysium Planitia</ref>.</p>
</text>
