<text id="autogum_bio_doc242" title="Francis Moore (geographer)" shortTile="francis-moore-geographer" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-03-09" dateModified="2019-10-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_Moore_%28geographer%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Francis Moore (geographer)</head><p><hi rend="bold">Francis Moore</hi> (baptized 1708, died in or after 1756) was a British travel writer of the eighteenth century.</p>
<p>Moore was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Worcester">Worcester, England</ref>, but few details are known about his early life. He came into prominence after publishing <hi rend="italic">Travels into the Inland Parts of Africa</hi> in 1738. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abolitionism">abolitionist</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Clarkson">Thomas Clarkson</ref> attributed his commitment to the anti-slavery cause to reading the few experts on Africa of the time, including Moore.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Account of Africa</head>
<p>Moore was appointed a writer (i.e., clerk) by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_African_Company">Royal African Company</ref> in 1730 and sailed for the company’s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gambia_River">Gambia River</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Entrepôt">entrepôt</ref> on July of that year. He left the region in April 1735 after also serving as a factor (agent) for the company. Moore was one of the first Englishmen to travel into the interior of Africa, serving in and visiting numerous towns and trading posts along the Gambia River from its mouth to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guinea_Highlands">Guinea Highlands</ref>, hundreds of miles inland.</p>
<p>Moore’s observations were published as <hi rend="italic">Travels Into the Interior Parts of Africa</hi>. The short account describes in rich detail the physical and cultural geography of the region before the intensification of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atlantic_slave_trade">Atlantic slave trade</ref> and the resulting depopulation and economic disintegration. Moore’s work and Richard Jobson’s <hi rend="italic">The Golden Trade</hi> were the only detailed accounts of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Gambia">Gambia</ref> before the colonial period.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Excerpts from <hi rend="italic">Travels Into the Interior Parts of Africa</hi> were published in several subsequent volumes on exploration and the slave trade, including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samuel_Johnson">Samuel Johnson</ref> et al., <hi rend="italic">The World Displayed</hi> (1740); <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Astley">Thomas Astley</ref>’s <hi rend="italic">A New General Collection of Voyages and Travels</hi> (1745); and Elizabeth Donnan’s <hi rend="italic">Documents Illustrative of the Slave Trade to America</hi> (1931).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Association with Job ben Solomon</head>
<p>Moore related the saga of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Job_ben_Solomon">Job ben Solomon</ref>, also known as Ayuba Suleiman Diallo, in <hi rend="italic">Travels Into the Interior Parts of Africa</hi>. Job was an African aristocrat taken by slavers in 1730 in an incident recorded by Moore. He was enslaved in Maryland until 1733, when he was sent to England after <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Oglethorpe">James Oglethorpe</ref> received a letter from him and purchased his freedom. After becoming well-known and respected in London society, Job returned to the Gambia, where he became re-acquainted with Moore.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>Account of the Georgia Colony</head>
<p>Moore sailed to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Province_of_Georgia">Province of Georgia</ref> on November, 1735, only four months after returning to England from Gambia, with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Oglethorpe">James Oglethorpe</ref> and over 200 colonists. It was a return trip for Oglethorpe, who had founded the colony in February 1733. Among those also on the voyage were newly ordained brothers <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Wesley">John Wesley</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Wesley">Charles Wesley</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>Moore served as Oglethorpe's secretary, and as storekeeper at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fort_Frederica">Fort Frederica</ref> on the southern frontier of the Georgia colony. He served in the colony until 1743, visiting his homeland once before permanently returning to England the same year as Oglethorpe.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>Moore’s early observations in the colony were published under the title <hi rend="italic">A Voyage to Georgia</hi>. The account contains some of the most detailed information available on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oglethorpe_Plan">Oglethorpe Plan</ref> and its implementation. Moore’s account of Georgia is silent on Oglethorpe’s emerging anti-slavery position; however it seems likely that the two men discussed Africa and the slave trade at length, and this may have informed the latter’s views.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
</text>
