<text id="autogum_reddit_doc042" title="I (18f) don’t feel attached to my baby (3wkm) [Xpost]" shortTile="f-dont-feel-attached" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-05-31" dateModified="2018-05-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8nm86z" speakerList="#buggiegirl, #unknown" speakerCount="2">
<head>I (18f) don’t feel attached to my baby (3wkm) [Xpost]</head>
<sp who="#unknown">
<p>I gave recently gave birth within the last month to a baby boy, we will call G. Ever since bringing him home and for some of our stay at the hospital, I haven’t felt attached to him. When he was born he swallowed some of his first stool (I don’t know the actual term for it) and required observation. He also was required to be kept in a warmer and on oxygen for the majority of our stay so i had little to no interaction with him. I was unable to go into the nursery to check on him, the nurses would simply say he was okay and tell me to return to my room. When I saw him through the nursery windows, it pained me to see him in an incubator and with tubes sticking out of him. After the first few times of being turned away from actually seeing him when he happened to be out of the incubator, I didn’t want to see him. I didn’t want to see him through the windows or at all. It’s gotten better since we got to come home though. I still don’t have that overwhelming love and desire to basically helicopter over him at all hours that seems the norm. When people ask me what I think about him, all that I can think is that he is my son, but he is a baby just like the other babies in the world. I don’t wait on him with baited breath to see if he did a thing, I still go about and clean and indulge in my hobbies when he is sleeping. I’m not saying that I don’t run to him when he cries, but I give G a chance to self-soothe as encouraged by his doctor. I check on him multiple times during the night to make sure he is still breathing and doesn’t require oxygen. I ordered a tank at home at the insistence of his doctor as a precaution in case he begins to have issues again. I try to make sure that he doesn’t sit in a dirty diaper for long, to the extent that I will wake him up when he is sleeping to check. But it’s been brought up multiple times by my family that I will probably be a mom just like mine was. I admit that I’m not attached to him but it doesn’t automatically mean that I’m going to be neglectful or abusive to him. It’s been brought up that since I don’t like holding my son, that I must not want to be around him at all and it’s the first sign that I will be neglectful. I’ve been trying to bond with him. I’ve been babbling to him even though I find it awkward since he can’t say anything back. I don’t let anyone else except his father watch him since my family is heavy smokers and I don’t trust them to not smoke around him. They all smoke in their houses and get petty when they come to visit and I make them smoke outside and wash their hands before they touch him. I just don’t know how to make my family see that I am trying to bond with my son but their remarks are making it harder to do so.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#buggiegirl">
<p>Give it time. Its hard at the start and it takes time to fall in love with someone new. </p>
<p>As for the holding etc, I say fake it til you feel it. I know I did that sometimes when my twins were infants. They were in the NICU for 9 weeks, so we had a delay to the bonding etc too. I held them, kissed them, did all the things I knew they needed from me... even if I wasn't feeling it at the time. </p>
<p>And holy shit did I fall in love with them. For me, this didn't happen until they were 7 months old and I realized I had postpartum depression and got help for it. If you are healthy, it will likely happen way sooner for you :) </p>
<p>Hang in there, it's really hard having a newborn (or two!).</p>
</sp>
</text>
