<text id="autogum_interview_doc262" title="part1_Wikinews interviews US National Archives Wikipedian in Residence" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-06-11" dateModified="2014-04-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_US_National_Archives_Wikipedian_in_Residence" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>The "Wikipedian in Residence" position falls within the Archives' social media staff within the Open Government division of Information Services, since the institution's goal is to distribute as much content to the widest audience possible. The internship is 40 hours per week from mid-May to late August.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<figure><caption>The Archivist of the United States, David Ferriero, has been very supportive of Wikipedia. He is shown here welcoming Wikipedians to the Archives to celebrate the project's tenth birthday. Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Missvain">Sarah Stierch</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Before you started your internship, how close of a relationship did the National Archives have with Wikipedia?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Dominic McDevitt-Parks</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> There was no official relationship, however the National Archives has long been supportive of Wikipedia. Earlier this year, for instance, the National Archives hosted a meetup in the main DC location in honor of Wikipedia's tenth anniversary. The Archivist of the United States, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20Ferriero">David Ferriero</ref>, is incredibly friendly to Wikipedia, as are many of the National Archives' staff. As he wrote after WikiXDC, "As an agency, I look forward to our staff learning more about the fabric and culture of Wikipedia and how to get involved." He also <ref target="https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Wikimedia%20letter%20of%20support.pdf">penned a letter</ref> to the Wikimedia Foundation offering support from the National Archives for the successful Washington D.C. bid for <ref target="https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Wikimania%202012">Wikimania 2012</ref>. In all likelihood, this is not a relationship that will end after this summer, either.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why is it important that institutions like the National Archives foster this sort of relationship with Wikipedia?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DMP</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Archives and other such institutions preserve our cultural heritage not just for the sake of keeping them, but so that we may access and use them. In the 21st century, accessibility is about more than just having exhibitions or a public research room; it is about having a digital presence and proactively delivering content to people with an information need, whether or not they were looking for a particular document from an institution's holding. Wikipedia and its sister projects are perfectly suited for this purpose in a number of ways. The most obvious is <hi rend="italic">visibility</hi>. There is no institutional web site in the world that is more popular among general web users than Wikipedia, which is one of the top 10 ranked web sites according to volume of traffic. Its article on a given topic will nearly always rank higher in search engine results than any institution's page, even one about a document actually held by that institution. In general, Wikipedia is the first and often only place online searchers will go to learn about the issues and items in which an institution might specialize. This means that there is no better way to reach the public than Wikipedia, and there is no better way to make one's holdings accessible and—just as important—discoverable than by making it directly available on Wikipedia. The pervasiveness of Wikipedia also means that work to improve it will have much more impact than many other education and outreach programs.</p>
</text>
