<text id="autogum_voyage_doc394" title="Rochester (Indiana)" shortTile="rochester-indiana" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=132909" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Rochester (Indiana)</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Rochester</hi> is the county seat of <ref target="Fulton%20County%20%28Indiana%29">Fulton County</ref>, <ref target="Indiana">Indiana</ref>, <ref target="USA">USA</ref>, and is the only city there (although there are a number of small towns). Its name comes from the much larger city in <ref target="New%20York%20%28state%29">New York</ref>, USA. Its proximity to <ref target="South%20Bend">South Bend</ref> and <ref target="Fort%20Wayne">Fort Wayne</ref> makes it a handy place to stay and maybe visit if everything closer is taken, without being too far away or too expensive.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>Rochester's located where <hi rend="bold">Indiana 25</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Old US 31</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Indiana 14</hi> join up, and <hi rend="bold"> New US 31</hi> loops around the south and west edges of the city. The <hi rend="bold">Fulton County Airport</hi>, for small private aircraft, is also a way to get in and out.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>Driving yourself is the best way to get around. Downtown is small enough to park at one spot and walk around, but this isn't feasible for the entire city.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fulton County Transpo</hi>, ☏ +1 574 223-4213 , ✉ fccoa@rtcol.com . 6:30AM-5PM Monday-Friday. Fulton County's only public transportation. $1/stop in town, $3/stop elsewhere in the county, private fees for out-of-county needs, free will donation for ages 60+.</item>
</list>


<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fulton County Museum</hi>, 37 E 375 N (Follow US 31 north of Rochester for 4 miles. Turn left on 375 N, then left again onto the driveway.), ☏ +1 574 223-4436 . 9 AM-5 PM Monday-Saturday (closed on holidays). A collection of historical items from Fulton County and the surrounding area, as well as books and local experts to aid in research and other needed purposes. There are sections about, among other things, old important buildings, early settlers, and the county's claim to fame as being the Round Barn Capital of the World. Four historical events are hosted by the museum and Fulton County Historical Society each year: The Living History Faire in March, the Redbud Trail Rendezvous in April, the Historical Power Show in June, and the Trail of Courage in September. Free will donation.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lake Manitou</hi>. The largest lake in Fulton County, Lake Manitou is located in the southeast part of the city and prized for its good fishing waters, natural beauty, and abundance of boat-friendly waters. The spillway dam on the north side of the lake is also and interesting place to visit. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tippecanoe River</hi>. "The River of Lakes" goes through the northern part of Fulton County. It's fairly shallow and perfect for paddling. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fulton County Courthouse</hi>. </item>
</list>


<head>Events</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">4th of July Fireworks</hi>, 545 N State Road 25. The night of the 4th of July sees a big fireworks show at the county airport (don't worry, there's no planes coming or going at the time!).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Chili Cook-off and Red Hot Car Show</hi>, 815 N Main Street. Shiny cars and chili-loving people cover the courthouse lawn on the second Saturday of October. Come out and enjoy samples of chili made on-the-spot by various local groups and see all kinds of rare cars!</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fulton County 4-H Fair</hi>, 1009 W 3rd Street, ☏ +1 574 223-3397 . A week in July of livestock shows, community building projects, and county fair food come together to make a time that's hard to beat.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Haunted Woods Trail</hi>, 37 E 375 N (At the Fulton County Museum, see below). The Historical Society grounds are turned into a scary walk in the woods for the two weekends before Halloween. $6 for ages 12 and up, $3 ages 6-11, free for 5 and under.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Historical Power Show</hi>, 37 E 375 N (At the Fulton County Museum, see below). Owners of historical tractors and other such machinery gather in an open-to-the-public festival every June. $5, free for 11 and under.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Living History Faire</hi>, 37 E 375 N (At the Fulton County Museum, see below). An indoor festival held every March, the Living History Faire showcases experts and vendors from all different historical times and places, ranging from 1700s Russia to Civil War-era America to pre-Columbus Indian lore.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Redbud Trail Rendezvous</hi>, 37 E 375 N (At the Fulton County Museum, see below). A living history festival in April with historical goods, food, experts, and reenactors from the 1800s. $3 ages 12 and up, 11 and under free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Round Barn Festival</hi>. Paying tribute to the county's claim to fame as the Round Barn Capital of the World, downtown is turned into a big festival on a weekend in June with all kinds of activities and local vendors, as well as a twilight parade. Free admission.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Trail of Courage</hi>, 37 E 375 N (At the Fulton County Museum, see below). The largest event put on by the Fulton County Historical Society, the Trail of Courage is an 1800s living history festival held in September based off of the Trail of Death, which spent its first night near Rochester. Historical experts, vendors, reenactors, food made on location, and activities of all sorts can be found. $7 ages 12 and up, $3 ages 6-11, $2 each bus students, 5 and under free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Suds in the City</hi>, 703 Main Street. An annual tasting festival featuring all kinds of Indiana craft beers. What's not to like? $20 in advance, $25 at the door.</item>
</list>
<head>Indoor Activities</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Farmer's Market</hi>, 37 E 375 N (At the Fulton County Museum, see below). Local gardeners and farmers gather to sell their produce and other goodies most Saturdays and Wednesdays.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fulton County Public Library Rochester Branch</hi>, 320 W 7th Street, ☏ +1 574 223-2713 . The largest library in the county has a wide collection of media, a room full of historical and genealogical materials, free computer access and wi-fi, and a small rotating local art gallery.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">WROI Radio Station</hi>, 110 E 8th Street, ☏ +1 574 223-6059 . "The Window on 8th Street", 92.1 WROI's station is open for visits and tours.</item>
</list>


<head>Outdoor Activities</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Elks Lodge No. 2120 Golf Course</hi>, 2506 S Country Club Drive, ☏ +1 574 223-3704 . A 9-hole golf course at the local Elks lodge.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Rochester City Park</hi>. A large park with numerous pavilions, picnic tables, and areas for various sports all surrounding Manitou Mountain, a massive playground.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Rochester Community Swimming Pool</hi>. 12PM-8PM Monday-Saturday, 1PM-8PM Sunday, generally closed when the air's under 70 degrees. The city pool ranges from 3 to 12 feet deep with two waterslides. There's also a small wading pool for younger children and a concession stand. It's right by the driving range and putting green for the Round Barn Golf Club at Mill Creek, making it perfect to hit a bucket, then wind down at the pool. $3 ages 5 and up.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Round Barn Golf Club at Mill Creek</hi>, 1024 Lakeview Drive, ☏ +1 574 223-5717 . A 72-par 18-hole golf course on Mill Creek. Its clubhouse is the restored Gerig Round Barn, giving it one of the most unique features of any golf course. It's commonly referred to by its old name, Mill Creek Golf Course, or simply Mill Creek.</item>
</list>
</text>
