<text id="autogum_interview_doc685" title="part8_Sam Brownback on running for President, gay rights, the Middle East and religion" shortTile="partsam-brownback" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-12" dateModified="2014-12-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sam_Brownback_on_running_for_President%2C_gay_rights%2C_the_Middle_East_and_religion" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="On_gay_rights">On gay rights</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Augusten_Burroughs_on_addiction,_writing,_his_family_and_his_new_book">I interviewed the writer Augusten Burroughs</ref>.  I would like you to answer a question that he posed.  He said that "God does not care that the person I watch TV with also has hairy arms, that the idea that a God would not like homosexuals is patently absurd, that it doesn't even begin to become logical in any way, that the idea that the architect of gravity, the being that created the ability for elemental particles that are absolutely nothing to come together and create living organisms and bricks and buildings and cars and jets, that the architect of absolutely everything would care about the sex of the person that this little human loves seems ridiculous."  Why is that not ridiculous?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  I think He cares about everything.  I don't know that everybody would take this as authoritative, but the Bible talks about a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/sparrow">sparrow</ref> not falling without Him knowing that--He's numbered the hairs on your head, so that He cares about everything, and He's certainly a God of love-- He loves us very much.  That's one of His central attributes, that He's a God of love, so I think He cares about everything and that there's nothing that would escape His view.  We also have absolute <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/free%20will">free will</ref> to do as we see fit; we're not robots by any means.  But I think He cares about everything.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why do you think it would bother God that somebody is gay?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  Well, you're asking a theological question on something I'm just really probably not competent to answer.  It usually gets asked in a context of the institution of marriage, and there, where I think the great need is for our society, is to uphold the institution as it has been, to recognize its great contribution to the raising of the next generation, and to see that more people, more of our next generation, is raised in a setting where you have a mom and a dad bonded together for life.  The reason there is a State interest is that in all the social data--we know from all the social data that the best place to raise a child, is between a mom and a dad bonded together for life, that your highest percentage of children in that setting will get a good education, will generally get a good working environment, life—they’ll perform best.  Now you can raise a good child in a single-parent family; you can raise a terrible child in a two-parent, stable setting.  So things don't always work that way.  But we do know from all the data that the best place for most is in that two-parent setting.  When you redefine marriage--the countries that have done this, they've see their marriage rates go down, and the institution be weakened, and fewer children raised in that setting.  That's why I think it's important to really stand for marriage being the union of a man and a woman.</p>
</text>
