<text id="autogum_academic_doc392" title="The Association between Social Support Sources and Cognitive Function among Community-Dwelling Older Adults: A One-Year Prospective Study" shortTile="association-between" author="Taiji Noguchi, Ippei Nojima, Tomoe Inoue-Hirakawa, Hideshi Sugiura" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4228/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Dementia is a global health problem, as the number of people with dementia worldwide may exceed 82 million by 2030. Dementia and the decline of cognitive function greatly contribute to disability, health problems, and social care needs among older people. Because there is no current cure for dementia, there is increasing interest in the identification of modifiable factors to delay or prevent dementia onset and the decline of cognitive function among older people. </p>

<p>According to the World Health Organization’s (WHO) policy framework on active aging, social relationships are a key factor in achieving active aging and a potentially important modifiable factor that can decrease cognitive decline. Several epidemiological studies have suggested that rich social relationships are protective against cognitive decline and the onset of dementia. Rich social relationships may increase cognitive activity and prevent low mood, which is linked to delays in cognitive decline. Studies of social relationships and health have used various measurement strategies to assess social relationships. One type of strategy uses a quantity-based approach to measure factors such as the number of social ties or the amount of participation in organizations. The other type of strategy uses a quality-based approach to measure characteristics such as the nature of social support. </p>

<p>Social support can be defined as an exchange between persons and is embedded in people’s social networks. Social support is exchanged in the form of daily assistance, care, financial assistance, gift-giving, counseling, or emotional assurance. Previous studies have suggested that social support has protective effects against cognitive decline and dementia onset. The health and psychological impact of social support may vary according to the source of support. For instance, social support from friends may contribute to net subjective well-being, because friends are typically about the same age and often share similar cohort experiences, lifestyles, and residential proximity. Support within the family, particularly from spouses, is often the main source of support in old age and has positive effects, but there may be gender differences in support. Additionally, support from adult children is not necessarily positive, as relationships with children are often stressful and sometimes fraught with unwelcome reciprocal obligations. Although it is important to understand differences in the effects of social support by differentiating between support sources inside (coresiding family) and outside (non-coresiding family and relatives, neighbors, and friends) the family, few studies have examined these social support sources separately. </p>

<p>A few previous studies have shown that different sources of social support have different effects. One cross-sectional study reported that family support was protectively associated with cognitive function among older people, but support from friends was not. Another study found that support from friends had a positive effect on cognitive function. In a longitudinal study, Murata et al. reported that social support from family, but not from relatives and friends, was protective against cognitive decline. In contrast, Chen and Chang found that emotional support from friends or relatives had a protective effect. There is little consensus in these findings owing to the small number of reports. Therefore, we aimed to examine the prospective effect of different sources of social support on cognitive function among community-dwelling older people through a one-year follow-up. </p>
</text>
