<text id="autogum_interview_doc456" title="part0_Former &amp;apos;Top Model&amp;apos; contestant Whitney Cunningham defends plus size models, celebrates the &amp;quot;regular woman&amp;quot;" shortTile="partformer-top-model" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-12-03" dateModified="2012-06-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Former_%27Top_Model%27_contestant_Whitney_Cunningham_defends_plus_size_models%2C_celebrates_the_%22regular_woman%22" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Former 'Top Model' contestant Whitney Cunningham defends plus size models, celebrates the "regular woman"</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 5, 2007</hi></p>
<p>Once you get a chance to talk to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/West%20Palm%20Beach,%20Florida">West Palm Beach, Florida</ref> native Whitney Cunningham, who placed seventh on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/America's%20Next%20Top%20Model,%20Cycle%208">eighth cycle</ref> of the popular reality TV series <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/America's%20Next%20Top%20Model">America's Next Top Model</ref></hi>, you begin to understand what host <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tyra%20Banks">Tyra Banks</ref> meant when she described her as the "full package." </p>
<p>First of all, she is confident and headstrong, which is a must on these kinds of shows, almost as much as it is to take a beautiful modelesque picture. Second, she turns that confidence into drive. She has been receiving steady work as a model since leaving the show, and still believes that her goal of being the first woman to wear a size ten dress on the cover of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vogue%20(magazine)">Vogue</ref></hi> is in reach. Third, and probably most important to television viewers, she obliterates the age-old model stereotype that to be pretty and photograph well, one must also be vapid and without a thought. A graduate of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dartmouth%20College">Dartmouth College</ref>, Cunningham also dreams of becoming a writer, and is working toward dual goals: a model who can express herself like no other model before her.</p>
<p>Cunningham recently sat down with Wikinews reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:TheCustomOfLife">Mike Halterman</ref> in an impassioned interview, taking hours to field questions from the reporter as well as from fans of <hi rend="italic">America's Next Top Model</hi>. Always in high spirits, Cunningham shows that she is a distinct personality who has carved her own niche in the <hi rend="italic">Top Model</hi> history books. At the same time, she exhibits a <hi rend="italic">joie de vivre</hi> that is oddly reminiscent of earlier <hi rend="italic">Top Model</hi> fan favorite <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toccara%20Jones">Toccara Jones</ref>, who showed America just how to be "big, black, beautiful and loving it." However, Cunningham is quick to remind everyone that she isn't big at all; she is simply a regular woman.</p>
<p>This is the first in a series of interviews with <hi rend="italic">America's Next Top Model</hi> contestants. Interviews will be published sporadically.</p>
<head id="Whitney's_beginnings,_and_looking_back">Whitney's beginnings, and looking back</head>
<p><hi rend="italic">Whitney was going to be interviewed with fellow Top Model contestant Keenyah Hill, but the interviews were ultimately done separately. Whitney and Keenyah, both based in New York City, chitchat before the interview about the restaurant where Keenyah works. Keenyah wonders if Whitney has ever eaten there, and to Keenyah's surprise, Whitney has. They make plans to keep in touch after the interview. Whitney's interview followed later.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman:</hi> So, who were the people you looked up to and inspired you to pursue modeling?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Whitney Cunningham:</hi> You know modeling was something that I was always interested in, but I would have to say that modeling was not an interest of mine that took a priority over my other interests. I've always been a basketball player and someone who was serious about academic achievement so I looked up to people who were eminent in those areas—i.e., <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cheryl%20Miller">Cheryl Miller</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maya%20Angelou">Maya Angelou</ref>. I would have to say that Tyra Banks was probably someone I always revered because she has always been such a trailblazer and that is a huge quality and characteristic I strive for in myself.</p>
</text>
