<text id="autogum_interview_doc484" title="part0_ACLU, EFF challenging US &amp;apos;secret&amp;apos; court orders seeking Twitter data" shortTile="partaclu-eff-challenging" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-04-06" dateModified="2019-09-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/ACLU%2C_EFF_challenging_US_%27secret%27_court_orders_seeking_Twitter_data" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>ACLU, EFF challenging US 'secret' court orders seeking Twitter data</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 7, 2011</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Logo of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Electronic_Frontier_Foundation">Electronic Frontier Foundation</ref>.</caption></figure><figure><caption>Logo of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/ACLU">American Civil Liberties Union</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>Late last month, the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/American_Civil_Liberties_Union">American Civil Liberties Union</ref> (ACLU) and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Electronic_Frontier_Foundation">Electronic Frontier Foundation</ref> (EFF) filed objections to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> Government's 'secret' attempts to obtain <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Twitter">Twitter</ref> account information relating to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/WikiLeaks">WikiLeaks</ref>. The ACLU and EFF cite First and Fourth amendment issues as overriding reasons to overturn government attempts to keep their investigation secret; and, that with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Birgitta%20Jonsdottir">Birgitta Jonsdottir</ref> being an <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iceland">Icelandic</ref> Parliamentarian, the issue has serious international implications.</p>
<p>The case, titled "<hi rend="italic">In the Matter of the 2703(d) Order Relating to Twitter Accounts: Wikileaks, Rop_G, IOERROR; and BirgittaJ</hi>", has been in the EFF's sights since late last year when they became aware of the US government's attempts to investigate WikiLeaks-related communications using the popular microblogging service.</p>
<head id="Case_background">Case background</head>
<figure><caption>2009 File photo of Bradley Manning. Image: Daniel Joseph Barnhart Clark.</caption></figure>
<p>The key objective of this US government investigation is to obtain data for the prosecution of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bradley_Manning">Bradley Manning</ref>, alleged to have supplied classified data to WikiLeaks. In addition to Manning's Twitter account, and that of WikiLeaks (@wikileaks), the following three accounts are subject to the order: @ioerror, @birgittaj, and @rop_g. These, respectively, belong to Jacob Apelbaum, Birgitta Jonsdottir, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rop%20Gonggrijp">Rop Gonggrijp</ref>.</p>
<p>Birgitta is not the only non-US citizen with their Twitter account targeted by the US Government; Gonggrijp, a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Netherlands">Dutch</ref> 'ex-hacker'-turned-security-expert, was one of the founders of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XS4ALL">XS4ALL</ref> – the first <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet%20Service%20Provider">Internet Service Provider</ref> in the Netherlands available to the public. He has worked on a mobile phone that can encrypt conversations, and proven that electronic voting systems can readily be hacked.</p>
<p>In early March, a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Virginia">Virginia</ref> magistrate judge ruled that the government could have the sought records, and neither the targeted users, or the public, could see documents submitted to justify data being passed to the government. The data sought is as follows:</p>
<list type="ordered"><item>Personal contact information, including addresses</item>
<item>Financial data, including credit card or bank account numbers</item>
<item>Twitter account activity information, including the "date, time, length, and method of connections" plus the "source and destination Internet Protocol address(es)"</item>
<item>Direct Message (DM) information, including the email addresses and IP addresses of everyone with whom the Parties have exchanged DMs</item></list>
<p>The order demands disclosure of absolutely all such data from November 1, 2009 for the targeted accounts.</p>
<p>The ACLU and EFF are not only challenging this, but demanding that all submissions made by the US government to justify the Twitter disclosure are made public, plus details of any other such cases which have been processed in secret.</p>
<head id="The_Manning_connection">The Manning connection</head>
<figure><caption>Gun camera footage of the airstrike of July 12, 2007 in Baghdad, showing the slaying of Namir Noor-Eldeen and a dozen other civilians by a U.S. helicopter. Image: WikiLeaks.</caption></figure>
</text>
