<text id="autogum_voyage_doc61" title="Hakodate" shortTile="hakodate" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=13894" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Hakodate</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.hakodate.travel/">Hakodate</ref></hi> (函館) is a large city in southern <ref target="Hokkaido">Hokkaidō</ref>, <ref target="Japan">Japan</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>Hakodate is in the north of Japan, and is the largest city in southern Hokkaidō. As one of the first cities in Japan to be opened to trade, like <ref target="Yokohama">Yokohama</ref> and <ref target="Kobe">Kobe</ref>, there are some signs of foreign influence in Hakodate, notably architecture.</p>

<p>Hakodate has been one of the largest settlements of explorers of the Hokkaido island through and after the Meiji era, following the few years of the Republic of Ezo since 1868 (see box). Separated just by a 20-km strait of Tsugaru (津軽海峡) from <ref target="Honshu">Honshu</ref>, Japan's main island, the city has naturally been seen as an entrance to Hokkaido. It was the second largest city in Hokkaido until 1950s and still is the third largest with a 350,000 population, surpassed only by <ref target="Sapporo">Sapporo</ref> and <ref target="Asahikawa">Asahikawa</ref>.</p>

<p>Hakodate, like <ref target="Kanazawa">Kanazawa</ref> and <ref target="Nagasaki">Nagasaki</ref>, is one of the hidden gems of Japanese tourism. Everyone should see <ref target="Kyoto">Kyoto</ref> and <ref target="Tokyo">Tokyo</ref>, because they're amazing cities. But Japanese domestic tourists, having done those cities before, come in droves to some places that international tourists may not have heard of and appreciate the fabulous food, culture and history of some of Japan's lesser known cities. Hakodate should not be missed on a trip to Japan. </p>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hakodate Airport</hi> ( HKD 函館空港 ) (is 20 minutes by bus (¥300) from the train station). JAL and ANA offer nonstop service to Hakodate from <ref target="Tokyo">Tokyo</ref> (Haneda), <ref target="Osaka">Osaka</ref> (Itami) and <ref target="Nagoya">Nagoya</ref> (Chubu); Air Do (ADO) also flies the Tokyo route and offers slightly cheaper fares. There are turboprop flights to several other cities in Hokkaidō, as well as daily Korean Air service to <ref target="Seoul">Seoul</ref>.</item>
</list>

 

<head>By train</head>
<p>JR trains run from Honshu to Hokkaido via the <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.jrhokkaido.co.jp/seikan/index.html">Seikan Tunnel</ref></hi> (青函トンネル). With a total length of 53.85 km (33.49 mi) and a 23.3-km (14.5-mi) section under the waters of the Tsugaru Strait, the Seikan Tunnel is the world's longest undersea tunnel, and the world's second longest railway tunnel (surpassed in 2016 by the Gotthard Tunnel in <ref target="Switzerland">Switzerland</ref>). Shinkansen services began running through the Seikan Tunnel in March 2016, connecting Hakodate to cities including <ref target="Aomori">Aomori</ref>, <ref target="Morioka">Morioka</ref>, <ref target="Sendai">Sendai</ref> and <ref target="Tokyo">Tokyo</ref>.</p>

<p>Hakodate has two major train stations:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hakodate Station</hi> (函館駅) is in the center of the city and is served by conventional trains.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Shin-Hakodate-Hokuto Station</hi> (新函館北斗駅) is 18 km north of Hakodate station and is the northernmost terminal for the shinkansen.</item>
</list>

<p>Both stations are connected in 15-20 minutes by local services, including the <hi rend="italic">Hakodate Liner</hi> (はこだてライナー) shuttle trains which are timed to connect with shinkansen services.</p>

<p>From Tokyo it takes approximately 4½ hours to reach Hakodate using the <hi rend="italic">Hayabusa</hi> shinkansen service and the <hi rend="italic">Hakodate Liner</hi>. A one-way trip costs ¥23,010 in standard class, and is fully covered by the national <hi rend="bold">Japan Rail Pass</hi>.</p>

<p>If you are just traveling between Tokyo and Hokkaido, consider the <hi rend="bold">JR East-South Hokkaido Rail Pass</hi>, which is slightly cheaper than the national pass (¥26,000 for advance purchase). This pass covers travel from Tokyo to Hakodate, and also covers express trains from Hakodate to Sapporo. It can be used on any 6 days within a 14-day period. Unlike the national pass, however, the JR East-South Hokkaido Pass only comes in one version for standard class travel.</p>

<p>Both Hakodate and Shin-Hakodate-Hokuto stations offer service to <ref target="Sapporo">Sapporo</ref> on the <hi rend="italic">Hokuto</hi> (北斗) limited express service (3½ hours, ¥8,830).</p>

<head>Overnight travel</head>
<p>Overnight trains to Hokkaido were discontinued when the shinkansen began operations through the Seikan Tunnel in March 2016.</p>

<p>For journeys from Tokyo to Hakodate, it is now easier to just make the trip during the daytime. If you want to travel overnight over a longer distance (i.e. from <ref target="Osaka">Osaka</ref> and cities beyond), you may wish to split up your journey - stop to visit another city along the way, or simply find a station along the bullet train route where you can find cheap accommodation, <ref target="Morioka">Morioka</ref> and <ref target="Sendai">Sendai</ref> are good options with lots of connections and a number of cheaper hotels. An intermediate stop is a good option for Rail Pass holders, as only the lodging has to be paid for.</p>

<head>Seishun 18 Ticket</head>
<p>Since the <ref target="Seishun%2018%20Ticket">Seishun 18 Ticket</ref> does not allow travel using bullet trains, users who want to go to Hakodate from Honshu must purchase a separate <hi rend="bold">option ticket</hi> for ¥2300. The special ticket allows trips in any available standard class seat on Hokkaido Shinkansen trains between Okutsugaru-Imabetsu (the last bullet train stop in Honshu) and Kikonai (the first such stop on Hokkaido). It also covers travel on the private Isaribi Line between Kikonai and Goryokaku, where the rest of the local JR network can be accessed. You must be in possession of a valid Seishun 18 Ticket to purchase and use the option ticket.</p>

<p>Trains to areas outside of Hakodate leave infrequently (compared to areas like Tokyo where trains come every few minutes) so plan ahead.</p>

<head>By boat</head>
<p>Hakodate's main ferry terminal is 4 km from the center and reachable on buses 1 and 19; a direct shuttle is also available between the ferry terminal and train station.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.seikan-ferry.co.jp">Seikan Ferry</ref></hi> and <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.tsugarukaikyo.co.jp/global/english/">Tsugaru Kaikyo Ferry</ref></hi> operate ferry services from Hakodate's port to <ref target="Aomori">Aomori</ref> with multiple departures daily. Trips take 3 hr 45 min. One way fares are cheapest on the Seikan Ferry, ¥1600 for a carpet space. The Tsugaru Kaikyo's Blue Dolphin ferry offers several classes of service, from standard carpet space (¥2220 one-way) up to a suite with two beds and an in-room shower and toilet (¥4940 one-way) and a luxurious suite that adds a living room (¥12,340 one-way). Note that during peak travel periods, these fares are higher.</p>

<p>Tsugaru Kaikyo also operates to <ref target="%C5%8Cma">Ōma</ref> on the remote <ref target="Shimokita%20Peninsula">Shimokita Peninsula</ref>, with two daily round-trips. Fares start at ¥1810 for second class and ¥2220/2460 for a reserved seat. Travel time is 1 hr 40 min.</p>

<p>Cars and motorcycles can also be carried on the Hakodate-Oma ferry, and on some of the Hakodate-Aomori ferries.</p>

<p>Tsugaru Kaikyo offers online booking of all of their ferry services in English through a third party. Fares are paid in euros and reservations are confirmed within 48 hours of booking. They also offer checked baggage service for an extra fee.</p>
</text>
