<text id="autogum_whow_doc491" title="Dress Up Your Basics" shortTile="dress-up-basics" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2017-01-12" dateModified="2019-05-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Dress-Up-Your-Basics" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Dress Up Your Basics</head><p>If you have a wardrobe full of basics, good for you. You've got the hard part down. Now, you just need to figure out how to dress up those looks when you need to. You probably already have what you need in your wardrobe to create dressier looks, such as suit jackets or cardigans. Accessories also are key to creating more sophisticated looks, which you probably already have on hand. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Creating Dressier Looks</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Consider getting your basics tailored. If you have a limited wardrobe, making sure your clothes fit really well can make them seem dressier. It can be cheaper to take well-made clothes you already have to a local tailor than to buy a higher class, better fitting wardrobe. <figure rend="Dress Up Your Basics Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Add a jacket to dress up a shirt. One simple way to dress up a shirt is to pair it with a suit jacket. This simple step makes a plain button-up shirt or even a nice t-shirt into a dressed-up outfit that you can wear to work or even for a night out on the town. <figure rend="Dress Up Your Basics Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Similarly, adding a skirt or nice pants to a blouse will create a dressier look.</item></list></item>
<item>Put on a cardigan for a more sophisticated look. A cardigan won't solve all your wardrobe problems. However, adding a cardigan over a classic black tank, for instance, can make the look much dressier. Button at least a few of the buttons for a classier look. <figure rend="Dress Up Your Basics Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use a belt. A belt can act solely as an accessory, but it can also help you change up the look of your wardrobe. For instance, you can wear a skinny belt over a tight-fitting suit jacket or add one on top of a dress to create a waistline. Doing so can make your look more polished and put-together. <figure rend="Dress Up Your Basics Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For guys, a belt can help tie a look together, so pick one that is classic and sophisticated, such as a leather belt in black or brown.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Adding Accessories</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Choose statement jewelry. One easy way to dress up basic pieces is to choose jewelry that adds a pop of color to your outfit. You could try a big chunky necklace in a bright color, for instance, to dress up a plain top. Alternatively, you could pick some sparkly earrings to make a statement with a dress. <figure rend="Dress Up Your Basics Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Bangle bracelets or dainty metallic bracelets can also elevate an outfit, depending on the occasion.</item>
<item>For a guy, consider adding a snazzy tie clip or a fancy watch.</item></list></item>
<item>Pick a scarf to add pizzazz. In the winter, a thick blanket scarf can turn a boring outfit into something much more interesting and sophisticated. Try plaid with neutrals or a soft grey to break up a black outfit. In the summer, a lightweight shimmery scarf can add a touch of interest. <figure rend="Dress Up Your Basics Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>In the winter, you can also add fancy gloves for a dressier outdoor outfit.</item>
<item>For guys, a well-made classic wool scarf can add sophistication, while a tie in a subtle pattern can add a bit of flair.</item></list></item>
<item>Add a well-made handbag. A well-made handbag can make any outfit dressier. If you pick something that fits the style of what you're wearing, it can elevate the outfit. The opposite is also true. If you wear the same sloppy handbag with every outfit, it can bring it down. You don't need hundreds of bags, but try having two or three nice bags that go with most of your outfits. <figure rend="Dress Up Your Basics Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You don't have to spend a fortune on a name-brand bag. However, spending a little bit more than you normally would will give you a bag that will last longer. Look for good materials, a nice lining, and well-made seams.</item>
<item>Choose at least one bag that can add some color to your wardrobe, and pick another for its ability to blend in well (think: neutral or black).</item>
<item>For a guy, pick a stylish bag that will go with most of your looks. Leather is a classic choice, and you can get an upscale messenger bag or more classic briefcase.</item></list></item>
<item>Wear a classy shoe. Having a few stylish shoes on hand is a great way to dress up your wardrobe. For instance, a pair of classy heels (such as black stilettos) can take a suit up a level. Similarly, a pair of leather boots can turn an average dress into something dressier and edgier. A pair of wing-tipped shoes can turn an average suit into something much snazzier. <figure rend="Dress Up Your Basics Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Once you find shoes you love (that are of decent quality), consider getting them resoled when they wear out. You'll give them a new life!</item></list></item>
<item>Don't go overboard. While it can be tempting to add a big necklace, big sparkly earrings, a large scarf, and a bright watch, adding too much can push your outfit over the edge. Aim for one large statement piece, and keep your other accessories more subdued. <figure rend="Dress Up Your Basics Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The same goes for guys. If you wear a flashy tie, lighten up on the fancy jewelry and vice versa.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
