<text id="autogum_interview_doc873" title="part13_Wikinews interviews World Wide Web co-inventor Robert Cailliau" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-07-22" dateModified="2014-09-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_World_Wide_Web_co-inventor_Robert_Cailliau" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi>: There were recently reports in the Belgian media about the rise of reported internet crime. Does that illustrate your call for international regulations of internet behaviour? If someone poses problematic behaviour on the internet, how should he or she be dealt with?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Robert Cailliau</hi>: What do we use in common law?  The police searches for the offender and works through a number of procedures.  There are rules for establishing complicity.  On the net it is only different  because time and space break down there.</p>
<p>Problematic behaviour, as you euphemistically call it, can be exhibited from anywhere and it usually goes very fast.  We therefore need a world-wide law.  There are however at least three large legal frameworks in conflict here:  the European, the US and the Chinese systems.  Making those work together is a problem that I do not see solved in time.</p>
<p>What upsets me too is the idea that it is the responsibility of the ISP or service to act.  Recently <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/MySpace">MySpace</ref> removed a number of users that were known as sex offenders.  They must have used some register.  Who decided that?  Who transmitted the register?  The reaction of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scotland%20Yard">Scotland Yard</ref> was right:  it's not because these people had committed an offence that they should be excluded forever, certainly not when they had served their sentences.  Or we should first change the law.  But we see more and more cases in which commercial companies take the law in their own hands.</p>
<hi rend="bold">We see more and more cases in which commercial companies take the law in their own hands. And that makes me worried about what the commercial sector will do in the vacuum that the governments just let be.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Robert Cailliau</p>
<p>And that makes me worried about what the commercial sector will do in the vacuum that the governments just let be.  Much more than about what governments would do.
That in turn is related to my worries over leaving my data in the hands of sites rather than having full control myself.</p>
<p>Let's not forget that the sex offenders maybe did nothing wrong in MySpace.  The terms of MySpace are very simple: they have the right to do what they want and to exclude you when they want without reason.  In addition they transfer all your data to the U.S., although they are honest enough to warn you that the protection of private data in the U.S. "may be different".  No, I prefer to stay away from social sites in these circumstances.</p>
<p>Finally, do these sex offenders have a telephone?  That is allowed?  And they can use the post office?  And the road system with their cars?  Yeah, let's just keep on messing about.</p>
</text>
