<text id="autogum_news_doc065" title="Poverty rises as food prices increase" shortTile="poverty-rises-food" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-04-14" dateModified="2011-04-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Poverty_rises_as_food_prices_increase" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Poverty rises as food prices increase</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, April 17, 2011</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Various <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cereal">grains</ref>.Image: Rainer Zenz.</caption></figure>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/World_Bank">World Bank</ref>, an organization that provides loans to developing countries, warned Thursday that rising food prices are driving millions of people deeper into poverty.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert%20Zoelick">Robert Zoelick</ref>, World Bank president, said that food prices have risen 36% over the last year,  pushing 44 million more people into poverty since last June. About 1.2 billion people are extremely poor.</p>
<p>He warned that a further increase of 10% in the cost of food would move  an additional 10 million persons into extreme poverty, and there was no sign of a near term  reversal  in  the inflation of food prices, which affects the developing world disproportionately. </p>
<p>"We have to put food first and protect the poor and vulnerable, who spend most of their money on food,"  said Zoellick. “The general trend lines are ones where we are in a danger zone… because prices have already gone up and [food] stocks are relatively low,” he said.</p>
<hi rend="bold">The general trend lines are ones where we are in a danger zone.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Robert Zoelick, World Bank president</p>
<p>The cost of the  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Staple%20food">basic foods</ref>, such as  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/wheat">wheat</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/maize">maize</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/soy">soy</ref> are all surging. Only <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/rice">rice</ref> has shown a slight decrease in price. </p>
<p>The steep rise in the cost of food is being driven by a combination of factors, including bad weather in food exporting areas such as <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Russia">Russia</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ukraine">Ukraine</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/North_America">North America</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China">China</ref>,  rising energy costs that increase the cost of producing and transporting food, and the incentives for  farmers in many countries to produce crops for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/biofuel">biofuel</ref>s  instead of for food. </p>
<p>"The linkage between food and fuel is much tighter than it was ten years ago," said Zoellick.</p>
<p>Additionally,  the change in diet of the growing middle class  in developing countries means they  consume more meat and pork products which take increased grain to produce and drives up the price of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fodder">feed stocks</ref>.</p>
<hi rend="bold">The linkage between food and fuel is much tighter than it was ten years ago.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—Robert Zoelick, World Bank president</p>
<p>National food investment and export policies of some wealthier countries are affecting poorer nations. For example, China is acquiring large amounts of land in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Africa">Africa</ref> to grow food for the needs of the Chinese; <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Saudi_Arabia">Saudi Arabia</ref> has given up wheat production to invest overseas for food, and a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/drought">drought</ref> in Russia has led it to implement an export ban on wheat.</p>
<p>Zoellick spoke in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Washington,_D.C.">Washington</ref> at the opening of the  meetings of the World Bank and the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/International_Monetary_Fund">International Monetary Fund</ref> (IMF). He hopes to discuss food policies with officials of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G-20%20major%20economies">G-20</ref> countries to develop a "code of conduct" on export bans and to encourage these countries to do more to  increase food production and aid developing countries in managing  agricultural problems.</p>
<p>On Saturday, the World Bank and the IMF issued "Global Monitoring Report 2011: Improving the Odds of Achieving the MDGs" which said the world was still on track  toward reaching a key goal of reducing the number of the world's people living in extreme poverty and hunger by half, to  883 million, by the target date of 2015.  Most of the world's progress is due to fast growth in India and China, while African countries are behind.  </p>
</text>
