<text id="autogum_interview_doc838" title="part8_ACLU President Strossen on religion, drugs, guns and impeaching George Bush" shortTile="partaclu-president" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-30" dateModified="2019-02-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/ACLU_President_Strossen_on_religion%2C_drugs%2C_guns_and_impeaching_George_Bush" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="Judicial_activism">Judicial activism</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When you hear the phrase “<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Judicial%20activism">judicial activism</ref>” what comes to your mind?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  I think of a judge who is actively enforcing the Constitution and living up to his or her responsibility and oath of office to protect and defend the Constitution, even in unpopular cases.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So you believe in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Living%20Constitution">living Constitution</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  I don’t know I can say what is a living Constitution.  The Constitution itself contains provisions that on their face call for interpretation that has to take into account evolving developments in society.  Why did they talk about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cruel%20and%20unusual%20punishment">cruel and unusual punishments</ref> when they could have simply said—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  “These are cruel and unusual punishments”</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  --Exactly.  So that there was a conscious choice on the part of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Framers%20of%20the%20Constitution">framers</ref> to leave it to future generations to pour specific content into the open-ended values they were endorsing.  So to me that’s being faithful to the text and intent of the framers <hi rend="italic">not</hi> to have hide-bound <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eighteenth%20Century">Eighteenth Century</ref> interpretation.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think there is a right to privacy in the Constitution?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  I think that the Constitution is a document that bestows limited powers upon any government that was intended to have limited powers.  Unless the government is given power to invade certain individual rights, then that power does not exist.  So to me the question is not does the Constitution grant people a right to privacy, it’s does the Constitution grant the government the power to invade an individual’s inherent and pre-existing right to privacy.  Let us not forget that the founding document of the country, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Declaration%20of%20Independence">Declaration of Independence</ref>, as we all know, says we are all born with certain inalienable rights that to secure these rights, governments are instituted among men.  So the purpose of government was not to grant us rights, which we already had by virtue of being human, the purpose of government was to protect those rights.  If you look at the preamble of the Constitution, which is implementing those ideals that are set out in the Declaration, it talks about one of the prime purposes being to secure the blessings of liberty to ourselves and our posterity.  It doesn’t say <hi rend="italic">grant</hi> liberty.</p>
<head id="Capital_punishment_and_criminal_justice">Capital punishment and criminal justice</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What argument for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capital%20punishment%20debate">capital punishment</ref> do you think is <hi rend="italic">most</hi> compelling for it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  If I had to be a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Devil's%20advocate">devil’s advocate</ref>…  Boy.  I-I-you’re really tongue-tying me, which is novel.  I would say just on a Constitutional level there is a pretty strong argument, textually, which is that the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Due%20Process%20Clause">Due Process Clause</ref> of both the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fifth%20Amendment">Fifth</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fourteenth%20Amendment">Fourteenth Amendment</ref>, says that no state or the federal government shall deny any person of life, liberty or property, without Due Process of law, which suggests that the government <hi rend="italic">may</hi> deprive somebody of life, as long as it lies with Due Process of law.  So I think that is a pretty strong textual argument that it was contemplated by the framers.  But, if you are going to make a moral argument or policy argument, I would really come up short on that because every study that has been done shows that it is fraught with all kinds of discrimination, racial discrimination as we know; discrimination based upon wealthy or poverty; geographical discrimination, depending upon what the polices are of the prosecutors in a certain jurisdiction.  There’s no evidence that it deters anybody who commits homicide.  So I can’t see any policy justification.  I don’t believe that it makes us safer, I don’t think it deters crime.  I think it is inherently inconsistent with human dignity or possible rehabilitation, which is I guess the word that they use.</p>
</text>
