<text id="autogum_bio_doc102" title="Animesh Ray" shortTile="animesh-ray" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-04-23" dateModified="2019-07-19" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Animesh_Ray" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Animesh Ray</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Animesh Ray</hi> is a professor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computational_biology">computational</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Molecular_biology">molecular biology</ref> at Keck Graduate Institute.</p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>Animesh Ray was born in a suburb of Calcutta (now Kolkata), which used to be a French colony in India, to parents both of whom had their ancestral homes in East Bengal (now Bangladesh). He studied in a Bengali medium high school, and then in Presidency College (now Presidency University). After his undergraduate studies, he went to Jawaharlal Nehru University in New Delhi, to obtain Masters of Science in the new School of Life Sciences. He obtained his Ph.D. in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microbial_genetics">microbial genetics</ref> from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monash_University">Monash University</ref>. From 1984 to 1988 he was a postdoctoral researcher in the Institute of Molecular Biology at the University of Oregon, Eugene, USA, in the laboratory of Professor Franklin W. Stahl. He was a postdoctoral fellow at Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) in 1989-1991, in the laboratory of Professor Ethan Signer. From 1991 to 1995 he was an assistant professor at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Rochester">University of Rochester</ref> and then was its associate professor from 1996 to 2001. He joined Keck Graduate Institute as a professor in 2001. From 2001 to 2004 he was also an adjunct professor at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_California,_San_Diego">University of California, San Diego</ref> and during the same years was a visiting professor at University of Rochester. In 2009 he became visiting professor at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Institute_for_Systems_Biology">Institute for Systems Biology</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Hyderabad">University of Hyderabad</ref> and currently works as director of Ph.D. programs at Keck Graduate Institute as well as Center for Network Studies. Since 2009, he also has been an adjunct professor at the Center for Computational Sciences, San Diego State University, San Diego, and at the School of Mathematical Sciences at the Claremont Graduate University in Claremont, California.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Career</head>
<p>Since 1985 Animesh Ray has studied mechanisms of DNA recombination. In 1989 Animesh Ray published on mechanisms of homologous recombination induced by a DNA double strand break using <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HIS3">HIS3</ref> gene of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saccharomyces_cerevisiae">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</ref></hi> and suggested that its <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chromosome">chromosomes</ref> produce double chain break during DNA recombination.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>From 1995 to 2002, he conducted research on computing with DNA. In May 1997 he and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mitsunori_Ogihara">Mitsunori Ogihara</ref> discovered <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DNA">DNA</ref> based computers can perform massively parallel computations.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>In June 1997 Animesh Ray suggested that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gametophyte">gametophyte</ref> is responsible for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pollen_tube">pollen tube</ref> guidance but also mentioned that it might be indirectly accomplished.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>In 2002 he studied <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ovule">ovule</ref> of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arabidopsis_thaliana">Arabidopsis thaliana</ref></hi> and discovered a new type of gene regulation, involving post-transcriptional gene silencing, through a gene called <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DCL1">DCL1</ref> which is required for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RNA_silencing">RNA silencing</ref> all multicellular organisms, including plants, in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drosophila">Drosophila</ref></hi> and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caenorhabditis">Caenorhabditis</ref></hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>In 2007 he and his students used <hi rend="italic">Arabidopsis thaliana</hi> to track a footprint of broken DNA and suggested that the genes move from one locus to another.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>In 2011 he suggested that microRNA gene, miR-34b can be of use to diagnose <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Melanoma">melanoma</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<head>Awards</head>
<p>Animesh Ray has had numerous awards from the National Science Foundation since 1993. In 2009 Animesh Ray and Ali Nadim were awarded with $100,000 grant from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Science_Foundation">National Science Foundation</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
</text>
