<text id="autogum_interview_doc308" title="part1_Interview with Sue Gardner of the Wikimedia Foundation" shortTile="partinterview-sue" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-19" dateModified="2012-01-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Sue_Gardner_of_the_Wikimedia_Foundation" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Matt: Have you had much to do with Wikinews during the course of your work for the Wikimedia Foundation?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SG:</hi>  No, very little. I am a big supporter of Wikinews for obvious reasons. Can I talk a little bit about that?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Matt: Sure.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SG:</hi>  I am very interested in Wikinews because of my background. I worked for seven years in online journalism, and spent a lot of time talking with my colleagues at other organizations about the future of online news, citizen journalism, participatory journalism etc. I am still doing some of that—next week, for example, I will be in Washington helping the Corporation for Public Broadcasting decide who to give funding for to cover the US presidential election online. So I am very interested in these issues. And I don't think that any media organization has got this figured out, even a little bit. It seems to me that Wikinews is in a very good position to make real progress on participatory news/citizen journalism, etc., because the WMF projects are extremely good at fostering collaboration. So I am watching Wikinews with a lot of interest. Yeah. I am really hoping that someone applying for funds from the CPB will propose a collaboration with Wikinews</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Dodge: When the Foundation moves to San Fransisco <hi rend="italic">[sic]</hi>, will you be going with it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SG:</hi>  Yes</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Matt: Do you believe that citizen journalism sites like Wikinews should have an editorial review process?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SG:</hi>  That is a good question. I assume you mean prepublication, right?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Matt: Yeah.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SG:</hi>  It's a good question, and there are good arguments on both sides. I know that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nick%20Denton">Nick Denton</ref> of Gawker Media has a kind of 'shoot first ask questions later' stance—they say they value transparency and are fine to admit their mistakes and publish corrections immediately. I think in general that's the direction the media are moving in; that we would publish and correct, rather than hold off publishing. There are lots of reasons for that, and there's an interesting argument to be made that it's the most respectful stance vis-a-vis the readers.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Brian: Gawker sounds like what we do, only a lot less cautious.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SG:</hi>  Yes. I like Nick Denton a lot—he is very honest and modest about the work he does. He sometimes mocks traditional media for being overly pompous</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike: Sue, the community initiative "Conference of the Americas" is getting support from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turner%20Broadcasting%20System">Turner Broadcasting</ref> for the citizen journalism unconference. How do you feel about the community partnering with such a big name in journalism?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SG:</hi>  I don't know anything about that particular proposal for collaboration, but I am generally very much in favour of us collaborating with external entities. I have begun talking a little with a guy at CNN myself, as I think Brian knows.</p>
</text>
