<text id="autogum_bio_doc518" title="Robert Hungerford, 3rd Baron Hungerford" shortTile="robert-hungerford" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-04-06" dateModified="2019-10-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Hungerford%2C_3rd_Baron_Hungerford" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Robert Hungerford, 3rd Baron Hungerford</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Robert Hungerford, 3rd Baron Hungerford</hi> (c.1429–1464) was an English nobleman. He supported the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Lancaster">Lancastrian</ref> cause in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War_of_the_Roses">War of the Roses</ref>. In the late 1440s and early 1450s he was a member of successive parliaments. He was a prisoner of the French for much of the 1450s until his mother arranged a payment of a 7,966<hi rend="italic">l</hi> ransom. In 1460 after successive defeats on the battlefield he fled with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VI_of_England">Henry VI</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scotland">Scotland</ref>. In 1461 he was attainted in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_IV_of_England">Edward IV</ref>'s first parliament, and executed in Newcastle soon after he was captured at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Hexham">Battle of Hexham</ref>.</p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>Hungerford was son and heir of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Hungerford,_2nd_Baron_Hungerford">Robert Hungerford, 2nd Baron Hungerford</ref>, and was grandson of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_Hungerford,_1st_Baron_Hungerford">Walter Hungerford, 1st Baron Hungerford</ref> (died 1449).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTELee1891256-4">[4]</ref> Hungerford was summoned to parliament as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baron_Moleyns">Baron Moleyns</ref> in 1445, and received a like summons until 1453.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTELee1891256-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Dispute with John Paston</head>
<p>In 1448 Hungerford began a fierce quarrel with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Paston_(died_1466)">John Paston</ref> regarding the ownership of the manor of Gresham in Norfolk. Hungerford, acting on the advice of John Heydon, a solicitor of Baconsthorpe, took forcible possession of the estate on 17 February 1448. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Waynflete">William Waynflete</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Winchester">bishop of Winchester</ref>, made a vain attempt at arbitration. Paston obtained repossession, but on 28 January 1450 Hungerford sent a thousand men to dislodge him. After threatening to kill Paston, who was absent, Hungerford's adherents violently assaulted Paston's wife Margaret, but Hungerford finally had to surrender the manor to Paston.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>French wars</head>
<p>In 1452 Hungerford accompanied <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Talbot,_2nd_Earl_of_Shrewsbury">John Talbot, 2nd Earl of Shrewsbury</ref>, to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aquitaine">Aquitaine</ref>, and was taken prisoner while endeavouring to raise the siege of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Castillon">Chastillon</ref>. His ransom was fixed at 7,966<hi rend="italic">l</hi>., and his mother sold her plate and mortgaged her estates to raise the money. His release was effected in 1459, after seven years and four months' imprisonment. In consideration of his misfortunes he was granted, in the year of his return to England, licence to export fifteen hundred sacks of wool to foreign ports without paying duty, and received permission to travel abroad. He thereupon visited Florence.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTELee1891256-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Wars of the Roses</head>
<p>In 1460 Hungerford was home again, and took a leading part on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Lancaster">Lancastrian side</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wars_of_the_Roses">Wars of the Roses</ref>. In June 1460 he retired with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_de_Scales,_7th_Baron_Scales">Lord Scales</ref> and other of his friends to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tower_of_London">Tower of London</ref>, on the entry of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Neville,_16th_Earl_of_Warwick">the Earl of Warwick</ref> and his Kentish followers into the city; but after the defeat of the Lancastrians at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Northampton_(1460)">battle of Northampton</ref> (10 July 1460), Hungerford and his friends surrendered the Tower to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yorkist">Yorkists</ref> on the condition that he and Lord Scales should depart free,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>After taking part in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Towton">Battle of Towton</ref> (29 March 1461)—a further defeat for the Lancastrians—Hungerford fled with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VI_of_England">Henry VI</ref> to York, and thence into Scotland. He visited France in the summer to obtain help for Henry and Margaret, and was arrested by the French authorities in August 1461. Writing to Margaret at the time from  Dieppe, he begged her not to lose heart.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> He was attainted in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_IV_of_England">Edward IV's</ref> first parliament in November 1461. He afterward met with some success in his efforts to rally the Lancastrians in the north of England, but was taken prisoner at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Hexham">Battle of Hexham</ref> on 15 May 1464, and was executed at Newcastle. He was buried in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salisbury_Cathedral">Salisbury Cathedral</ref>. On 5 August 1460 many of his lands were granted to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_III_of_England">Richard, Duke of Gloucester</ref> (afterward Richard III). Other portions of his property were given to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Wenlock,_1st_Baron_Wenlock">Lord Wenlock</ref>, who was directed by Edward IV to make provision for Hungerford's wife and young children.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTELee1891257-8">[8]</ref></p>
<head>Marriage and children</head>
<p>Hungerford married at a very early age (about 1441) Eleanor (born 1426), daughter and heiress of Sir William Moleyns (died 1429).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTELee1891256-4">[4]</ref>  Among their children were:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTELee1891257-8">[8]</ref></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Hungerford_of_Rowden">Thomas Hungerford of Rowden</ref></item>
<item>Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_Hungerford_of_Farleigh">Walter Hungerford of Farleigh</ref></item></list>
<p>Eleanor survived her husband and subsequently married Sir Oliver Manningham. She was buried at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stoke_Poges">Stoke Poges</ref>, Buckinghamshire, in 1476.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTELee1891257-8">[8]</ref></p>
</text>
