<text id="autogum_voyage_doc535" title="West Kootenays" shortTile="west-kootenays" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=39055" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>West Kootenays</head>

<p>The <hi rend="bold">West Kootenays</hi> is south-eastern <ref target="British%20Columbia">British Columbia</ref>, <ref target="Canada">Canada</ref>. The area is approximately defined as being the area south of the Trans Canada Highway (Hwy # 1) from <ref target="Revelstoke">Revelstoke</ref> and including the valleys of Slocan Lake and Kootenay Lake and at least part of the Arrow Lake valley (Columbia River), as far south as the USA border.</p>
<head>Cities, towns and villages</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> is "the Queen City" of the Kootenays, renowned for its tourism, culture and outdoor activities.</item>
<item> is the crossroads of the Kootenays. Whether you decide to stop here or not, you will likely pass through it if you visit the West Kootenays</item>
<item> is an industrial town dominated by one of the largest lead-zinc smelters in the world</item>
<item> is a medium-sized town on the east side of Arrow Lakes (Columbia River).</item>
<item> is a small village on Slocan Lake, about 45 minutes drive east of Kaslo.</item>
<item> is a picturesque mountain town world famous for its skiing at Red Mountain Resort and also noted for great mountain biking.</item>
<item> is a small town near the US border, a convenient food and fuel stop on the Crowsnest Pass Highway.</item>
<item> is an attractive village on the west shore of Kootenay Lake, nestled between the Purcell Mountains and Selkirk Mountains and home to the world's oldest intact sternwheeler, the <hi rend="italic">SS Moyie</hi>.</item>
<item> is a village equidistant from Nelson, Castlegar, and Trail, known as "the Hub of the Kootenays".</item>
<item> is at the south end of Kootenay Lake next to some of the best of the limited agricultural areas around this region.</item>
<item> is the eastern terminal of the <hi rend="bold">Arrow Lake ferry</hi>, connecting Highway 6 with Needles on the western shore.</item>
</list>


<head>Understand</head>

<p>In general, the West Kootenays is a little more remote and a little more difficult to get into and travel around than some of the more populated parts of the province. You will probably find that the residents of this area live here at least partly because that's what they like. Winding roads require somewhat slower travel. If locals have one complaint, especially during tourist season, it's about visitors roaring about, making excessive noise and generally making the highways unsafe and unpleasant. To fully appreciate the place, visitors need to slow down, relax and enjoy what the region has to offer. There's little interest in seeing the frantic bustle of the big city imported here by visitors in too much of a hurry.</p>

<p>The West Kootenays doesn't include the Columbia River and Kootenay River Valley south of Golden to Cranbrook. This is the <ref target="East%20Kootenays">East Kootenays</ref>. It's very nice, but it's not the West Kootenays.</p>

<head>Talk</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> You may hear the phrase <hi rend="bold">Kootenay Time</hi> used occasionally. This may be interpreted as "I'll get there when I get there" or "It will happen when it happens". You may find some shops that aren't always open right on time. Relax. It's not usually a crisis.</item>
<item> The ubiquitous <hi rend="bold">FSR</hi>. This is a Forest Service Road or, more commonly, a logging road, which is what these roads were built to service. They are often identified by brown Forest Service signs, they seem to be everywhere and they are the only real access into the backcountry. Many are rough and steep and require high clearance vehicles. Maybe a vehicle that doesn't have a paint job you're unusually fond of. If there is active logging going on, you may also meet large trucks with loads of logs. You can get lost or stuck. Caution is advised.</item>
</list>


<head>Get in</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> By plane - the only airport served by a major carrier is in <ref target="Castlegar">Castlegar</ref>. Air Canada Express is the only major airline available with flights to Vancouver, the Okanagan and Calgary. There is a smaller airstrip near Trail which has a commercial operation connecting to Vancouver. Private planes could also land at strips in <ref target="Kaslo">Kaslo</ref>, <ref target="Nelson%20%28British%20Columbia%29">Nelson</ref> and <ref target="Creston">Creston</ref>.</item>
<item> By road - by heading south from <ref target="Revelstoke">Revelstoke</ref> towards <ref target="Nakusp">Nakusp</ref> or from Hwy 3 through <ref target="Creston">Creston</ref> or <ref target="Trail">Trail</ref>.</item>
<item> By bus - possible but slow and not very convenient.</item>
</list>


<head>Get around</head>

<p>The easiest way to see the Kootenays is by private vehicle. There is very limited public transit in this region. Some routes are pretty quiet so hitch-hiking could be chancy, especially late in the day and outside the main tourist season. In the summer, it's a popular destination for motorcyclists. Some hardier types will enjoy biking in the area, just be aware that the hills will give you a good workout.</p>

<p>BC Transit operates the <ref target="http://bctransit.com/west-kootenay/home">West Kooteney Transit System</ref> which runs within and between many towns.</p>

<head>See</head>

<p>The area generally has quite stunning scenery. Details are contained in the listings for many of the towns in the region.</p>

<head>Do</head>

<p>There are many reasons to visit (or live in) the West Kootenays. The longer one stays, the more opportunities appear. In addition to the most noticeable such as the various Provincial Parks, towns and local ski hills, there are many backcountry trails which really expose you to some of the wilderness that remains in this part of the province. There is a trails guidebook which is a good start, but repeated visits and contact with the locals can get you into some quite amazing destinations. Accessing many of these areas often requires a high-clearance vehicle, travel on logging roads and good maps, just to sort out where to go.</p>

<head>Eat</head>

<p>If all you want is the usual fast food, the West Kootenays has the usual complement of fast food outlets, but it is possible to do better than that.</p>

<p>All of the communities in the region have at least a few good to excellent establishments serving a pretty wide selection of food. There isn't really a regional cuisine but many of the establishments cater to vegetarians and to omnivores, many take the trouble to source locally-grown produce and some have created some pretty unique menu items.</p>

<head>Drink</head>

<p>There are at least 3 brewing companies in the West Kootenays:</p>

<p>In <ref target="Creston">Creston</ref> there is the <hi rend="bold">Columbia Brewing Company</hi>, in <ref target="Revelstoke">Revelstoke</ref> there is the <hi rend="bold">Mt Begbie Brewing Company</hi> and in <ref target="Nelson%20%28British%20Columbia%29">Nelson</ref> there is the <hi rend="bold">Nelson Brewing Company</hi>, advertising organic ales.</p>

<p>Given this choice, make it a point to sample some of the local brews while travelling in the region.</p>

<p>The region isn't well known for wineries; there just isn't the heat or the soil available here the way there is in the Okanagan. However, despite that, there are at least two wineries in the region: <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.cgwinery.com/">Columbia Gardens Vineyard &amp; Winery</ref></hi> just south of <ref target="Trail">Trail</ref> and <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.skimmerhorn.ca/">Skimmerhorn Winery &amp; Vineyard</ref></hi> in <ref target="Creston">Creston</ref>.</p>
</text>
