<text id="autogum_academic_doc213" title="Impact of Nitrogen Fertilizer Levels on Metabolite Profiling of the Lycium barbarum L. Fruit" shortTile="impact-nitrogen-fertilizer" author="Zhigang Shi, Feng Wei, Ru Wan, Yunxiang Li, Yajun Wang, Wei An, Ken Qin, Guoli Dai, Youlong Cao, Jiayue Feng" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1420-3049/24/21/3879/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Lycium barbarum</hi> L., also known as goji, is a perennial deciduous shrub planted in large areas in the west of China. It prefers to grow in sunny; cold weather; and moist, fertile soil. Goji berry is also an excellent medicinal herb and healthy food. The fruit is rich in vitamins, essential amino acids, and linoleic acid. These nutrients can promote blood flow and prevent arteriosclerosis. Long-term consumption of goji berry can also help to prevent fat accumulation in the liver, improve cell metabolism, and ensure regular body metabolism, thus playing an essential role in slowing down aging of the body. Furthermore, goji berry also has effects on the reduction of inflammation and fever, the elimination of phlegm, liver protection, diabetes prevention, cough relief, moistening of the lungs, and mucus removal. Recently, the beneficial effects of goji berry have been gradually recognized by people, and the fruit is rapidly becoming an indispensable food supplement. Previous studies have shown that total phenolics, total flavonoid, and total polysaccharide contents of goji fruits from 13 different regions in China ranged from 6.899–8.253 mg gallic acid equivalents/g dry weight (DW), 3.177–6.144 mg rutin equivalents/g DW, and 23.62–42.45 mg/g DW, indicating that the goji berry from Guyuan of Ningxia was most similar to Daodi herbs. Liu et al. reported a comparative analysis of carotenoid accumulation in red fruit of <hi rend="italic">Lycium barbarum</hi> L. and black fruit of <hi rend="italic">Lycium ruthenicum</hi> L., finding more extensive contents of carotenoids in red fruit than in black fruit. </p>

<p>Nitrogen fertilizer is an essential nutrient that has an important impact on crop growth, yield, and product quality. The proper application of nitrogen fertilizer can increase the soil’s nitrogen content for better plant growth. Several studies investigated the absorption, assimilation, and effects of nitrogen fertilizer on plant development. Nitrogen is mainly absorbed in the form of nitrates and ammonium salts, but may also be absorbed in organic form (e.g., urea or amino acids). The assimilation of inorganic N and organic N requires a series of strictly regulated enzyme catalysis steps. The growth and development, yield, and quality of goji are all quantitatively limited by nitrogen demand, where either too much or too little nitrogen can inhibit the growth and development of goji. Previous studies showed that about 20% of the nitrogen absorbed during the growth and development of goji comes from fertilizers, with 80% coming from the soil. In two-year-old goji, nitrogen uptake from the fast-growing period to the fruit-harvesting period (from early May to mid-August) continuously increased during the annual growth cycle and in early May to late June. The nitrogen content of the fertilizer absorbed by the plant was higher than that of the total nitrogen, indicating that these two periods were the peak period of nitrogen absorption and the key period for nitrogen fertilizer application. It was also found that the greatest effect of fertilizers on the growth of goji shoots in spring time was observed in response to nitrogen fertilizer, followed by phosphate fertilizer and, lastly, potash fertilizer. Most of the studies on goji berry mainly focused on the effects of goji berry on human health, as well as the antioxidant activity of goji berry through phytochemical analysis. The impact of fertilizer on the metabolites of goji berry has not yet been reported. </p>

<p>Although many reports have identified the pharmacological properties, biological activity, and nutrient benefits of goji berry, the relationship between fertilization and the goji berry metabolome is still under-reported. In this study, we utilized an integrated UPLC-ESI-MS/MS detection system to study the effects of different nitrogen fertilizations on the yield and metabolites of goji berry and provided a theoretical model for the regulation of goji berries’ nutrient compounds by fertilization. </p>
</text>
