<text id="autogum_interview_doc665" title="part8_Gay Talese on the state of journalism, Iraq and his life" shortTile="partgay-talese-state" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-27" dateModified="2019-01-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gay_Talese_on_the_state_of_journalism%2C_Iraq_and_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Or really much about anything.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  Less so because of this technology that's absorbed them, you know with their God damn ears closed and their eyes affixed. and the God damn games they play.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It doesn't get better as you go higher</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  It doesn't?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  No, that was one of the things that stood out to me at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fordham%20Law%20School">Fordham Law</ref>.  It's a top 25 law school in a very vibrant city with a lot of thinkers.  I told this anecdote to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Floyd%20Abrams">Floyd Abrams</ref>: I was in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constitutional%20Law">Constitutional Law</ref> class right after <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samuel%20Alito">Alito</ref> was nominated to be on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Supreme%20Court">Supreme Court</ref>.  The professor asked 120 law students on the first day of class how many of them thought he should be confirmed.  About five students raised their hands.  "New York," I thought.  Then he asked how many of them thought Alito should <hi rend="italic">not</hi> be confirmed.  About ten students raised their hands.  Then he asked how many did not feel they had enough information to know.  about another five students raised their hands.  What is that?  100 students in a Constitutional Law class at a top school can't proffer an opinion on a Supreme Court nominee?  Is that apathy...confusion...fear...?  What is it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  When I was in the military, there was no war.  1954, 1955; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Korean%20War">Korea</ref> was over by then.  I had to camp with people from different parts of the United States.  Farmers, sons, rich people, poor people.  We were all together for at least six weeks of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basic%20training">basic training</ref>, and then later on when you are assigned to a unit you really had a sense of the country if you didn't have the opportunity to travel.  Very few of us did; I never traveled anywhere until I was in the army.  I went to college, from New Jersey to Alabama as a student, so I was at least in a different part of the United States than that where I was born.  Out of college I went into the army, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fort%20Knox,%20Kentucky">Fort Knox, Kentucky</ref>, and I was with people from Texas, North Carolina and people from Boston.  Those who don't have to serve, or choose not to, can say that it's not their war.  But it's an economic war; it's a sad commentary on who has to serve, because it is mercenary.  They are economic mercenaries.  They are economically deprived people, without opportunities, and they seek this opportunity and they never imagine how ill-chosen was their choice when they are missing a leg, or witnessing the horror.  It's been close to five years, and still no protests?  You don't find the students at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Columbia%20University">Columbia</ref> protesting?  They can protest the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/President%20of%20Iran">President of Iran</ref>!  They're good at that, but they are no good at protesting what is going on in to their generation that couldn't afford to get into Columbia, or any place.  It's so unfair, and so un-protested after so many years...it's been close to five years!</p>
</text>
