<text id="autogum_academic_doc412" title="Job Insecurity: A Comparative Analysis between Migrant and Native Workers in Australia" shortTile="job-insecurity-comparative" author="Xiaomin Liu, Steven J. Bowe, Allison Milner, Lin Li, Lay San Too, Anthony D. LaMontagne" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4159/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
Consistent with our broad hypothesis, migrant workers, especially non-ESC-born and recently arrived migrants, experienced higher job insecurity than Australia-born workers. These disparities gradually decreased as years since arrival in Australia increased, becoming similar to Australia-born workers after 11+ years post-arrival, with a notable exception regarding highly educated migrants, for whom disparities persisted. Importantly, the migrant status–job insecurity relationships in our study were not confounded by gender, age, educational attainment, or occupational skill level. However, migrant status–job insecurity relationships were modified by educational attainment, and the disparities in job insecurity between non-ESC-born migrants and Australia-born workers increased with increasing educational attainment, contrary to expectation. </p>

<p>There are a limited number of previous studies directly comparing job insecurity between migrant workers and native workers, with most of them reporting that migrant workers experienced higher job insecurity. For example, Kim-Godwin and Bechtel showed that migrant farmworkers reported high job insecurity in the US, and Font, Moncada, Llorens, and Benavides reported that migrant workers experienced higher job insecurity in Spain. Null results were also reported. An Australian study restricted to skilled migrants found no significant difference in job insecurity compared to Australia-born workers, and Torá et al. also reported that migrant workers showed no significant difference in job insecurity compared to Spanish-born workers. In addition to differences between countries, inconsistencies in the results of our study compared to previous studies may have been due to differences in the samples, job stressor measurements, and analytical methods. For example, some studies looked at job insecurity in specific occupational groups, such as farmworkers, without comparison to reference groups. Some studies compared migrants to native-born workers, but did not study migrant subgroups based on language proficiency or time since arrival in the host country. Finally, job insecurity measures vary between studies. Job insecurity in McGuinness and Wooden was measured by the percent chance of involuntary job loss, re-employment prospects, and intention to quit. Calculation methods for job insecurity may also have differed; some studies used binary job insecurity, while we treated job insecurity as a continuous measure. </p>

<p>With respect to research question one, our finding that the disparities in job insecurity were more significant among non-ESC-born migrants and decreased with increasing years post-arrival in Australia may indicate an acculturation effect. This may be explained by new migrants, especially those with low English proficiency, being more likely to find temporary or lower quality jobs, or having a higher risk of job loss due to their low language skills, unfamiliarity with local policies, or discrimination, which would correlate with lower job security. With respect to research question two, we found that only educational level was a significant effect modifier of migrant status–job insecurity relationships. Language difficulties may be more notable among newly arrived, low-educated migrants, and this may partly explain the result that migrant workers with high school or lower educational attainment had the highest levels of job insecurity in the first five years since arrival. Over time, these people may have improved chances of finding better jobs with better job security. Further, we observed an unexpected finding that the disparities in job insecurity persisted among highly educated non-ESC-born migrants even 11+ years post-arrival, which may be partly explained by language difficulties having persistent adverse effects on work experience among highly educated migrant workers. Highly educated migrants were more likely to be employed in professional jobs, which require a high level of language skills. Non-ESC-born migrants may have more language difficulties in a functional communication context, which may result in a perceived higher risk of future job loss. For example, language difficulty was regarded as the primary weakness of international medical residents in hospitals, which may result in a high risk of obtaining negative feedback and failure to register, thereby leading to increased job insecurity. Therefore, continuing language training or language training for a specific purpose may be beneficial to highly educated migrants. </p>
</text>
