<text id="autogum_voyage_doc335" title="Melukote" shortTile="melukote" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=21961" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Melukote</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Melukote</hi> is a temple and wildlife sanctuary in <ref target="Mandya%20%28district%29">Mandya</ref>, <ref target="Karnataka">Karnataka</ref>, <ref target="Southern%20India">Southern India</ref>.</p>
<head>Understand</head>
<p>Melukote is a 4,000-year-old town near Mysore city. The buildings are simply amazing and the people follow the same 4,000-year-old Brahmin lifestyle even now. Eyesores like electricity, motor bikes and mobile telephones have affected this hillock also.</p>
<head>Talk</head>
<p>Even though the language that is generally spoken is Kannada, Tamil is also understood and spoken by many, English can also be used as people are well educated.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>If you are travelling by public transportation, you have to alight at Jakkanahalli junction and get an autorickshaw for the last seven kilometer trip up the hill. Buses are also available every one hour from Jakkanahalli junction.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>KSRTC operates buses regularly from Mysore, K.R.Pet and K.R.Nagar to Melukote.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>Melukote is 51 km from Mysore and It is 131 km from Bangalore.</p>
<p>From Mysore, You have to go on Mysore-Bangalore Highway and after Srirangapatana, You have to take a diversion on the left and then reach Pandavapura and go straight for another 26 km to reach Melukote.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>Upper Melukote can be covered by foot in one hour. Autorikshaws charge Rs.50 for dropping you in the upper temple and Rs.150 for wait and return arrangement. Lower Melukote is more spacious and filled with many ancient buildings. More natural scenery can be enjoyed by walking down the hill for a distance of seven kilometers up to Jakkanahalli junction.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cheluvanarayana Swamy Temple</hi>, Upper Melukote (1 km). Very beautiful stone structure of unbelievable big area.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Yoga Narasimha Temple</hi>, Old Melukote (1 km uphill). It's atop the hill. You can take a car halfway up and have to climb a few steps to reach it. All temples in Melukote are open till 6 PM.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The old buildings</hi>. The old buildings on the hilltop are so numerous that they cannot be counted in one stretch. Their beauty is beyond description and enjoying a single hut can take half an hour and their style cannot be captured in your modern camera. People here appear to have frozen into a lifestyle that is thousands of years old and their architectural tastes match with their way of life.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>
<p>Melukote is famous for Puliyogare, A south Indian food made with Rice, Tamarind and Ground nuts. You can buy Puliyogare gojju from any Iyengar shop which can be mixed with rice to prepare a quick snack at home.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Subbanna Mess</hi>, Upper Melukote (1 km). Rs.100 for a Rs.50 level lunch. You are not allowed to eat in peace as the owner constantly observes you and intervenes giving directions for proper ancient way of eating.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Annapoorna Mess</hi>, Near Yedhushala Bookstall (1 km). Rs.60 for vegetarian lunch on stiched leaves.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Shree Nidhi Restaurant</hi>, KSRTC bus station (2 km).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">KSRTC Canteen</hi>, KSRTC Bus Station (1 km from the temple). Only snacks, cool drinks and juice items are available.</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bagur Yathri Nivas</hi>, Upper Melukote (1 km). Roof level ventilators give light and keep away cold winds. Simple accommodations. ₹500 for rooms without bath with only bed and no windows.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Yadhugiri Guest House</hi>, Near Upper Temple (1 km), ☏ +91 7676767638, +91 9900873987 . Rs.650.</item>
</list>


<head>Stay safe</head>
<p>Melukote is a safe place with police station and no robbers around.</p>
</text>
