<text id="autogum_bio_doc345" title="Henri de Tonti" shortTile="henri-de-tonti" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2003-09-16" dateModified="2019-06-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henri_de_Tonti" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Henri de Tonti</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Henri de Tonti</hi> (1649/50 – August 1704) was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Italy">Italian</ref> soldier, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Explorer">explorer</ref>, and fur trader in the service of France.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-MR-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>Henri de Tonti, an Italian from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Naples">Kingdom of Naples</ref>, was most likely born near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gaeta,_Italy">Gaeta, Italy</ref>, in either 1649 or 1650. He was the son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lorenzo_de_Tonti">Lorenzo de Tonti</ref>, a financier and former governor of Gaeta. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alphonse_de_Tonti">Alphonse de Tonti</ref>, one of the founders of what is now <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Detroit,_Michigan">Detroit</ref>, was his younger brother. His father, Lorenzo, was involved in a revolt against the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spain">Spanish</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Viceroy">viceroy</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Naples">Naples, Italy</ref>, and was forced to seek <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Refugee">political asylum</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/France">France</ref> around the time of Henri's birth.</p>
<p>In 1668, Henri joined the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/French_Army">French Army</ref> and later served in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/French_Navy">French Navy</ref>. During the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Third_Anglo-Dutch_War">Third Anglo-Dutch War</ref>, Henri was part of the French troops that King Louis XIV sent to Sicily in 1675 under the Command of The Duke of Vivonne to support the rebellion of the important town of Messina (circa 100.000 inhabitants in 1674) against the crown of Spain. Tonti took part in the military operations in the village of Gesso, up the hills near Messina  and he lost his  hand in a grenade explosion.  From that time on, wore a prosthetic hook covered by a glove, thus earning the nickname "Iron Hand". Among the officers fighting beside the French expedition corps, there were the brothers Antonio and Thomas Crisafy, who years later Tonti will have the chance to meet again in Nouvelle France. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-MR-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Exploring with La Salle</head>
<figure><caption>La Salle's expeditions on the Mississippi</caption></figure>
<p>In the summer of 1678, Tonti journeyed with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/René-Robert_Cavelier,_Sieur_de_La_Salle">René-Robert Cavelier, Sieur de La Salle</ref>, who recognized him as an able associate. La Salle left Tonti to hold <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fort_Crèvecoeur">Fort Crèvecoeur</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Illinois">Illinois</ref>, while La Salle returned to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ontario">Ontario</ref>. While on his return trip up the Illinois River, LaSalle concluded that Starved Rock might provide an ideal location for another fortification and sent word downriver to Tonti regarding this idea. Following La Salle’s instructions, Tonti took five men and departed up the river to evaluate the suitability of the Starved Rock site. Shortly after Tonti’s departure, on April 16, 1680, the seven members of the expedition who remained at Fort Crevecoeur ransacked and abandoned the fort and began their own march back to Canada.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>In the spring of 1682, Tonti journeyed with La Salle on his descent of the Mississippi River. Tonti's letters and journals are valuable source materials on these explorations.</p>
<p>When La Salle returned to France in 1683, he left Tonti behind to hold <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fort_Saint_Louis_(Illinois)">Fort Saint Louis</ref> on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Illinois_River">Illinois River</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> He was to relinquish this control for a period to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis-Henri_de_Baugy,_Chevalier_de_Baugy">Louis-Henri de Baugy</ref>, under the orders of Frontenac. Three years later, he learned from remnants of La Salle's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/French_colonization_of_Texas">ill-fated Texas settlement</ref> that La Salle was attempting to ascend the Mississippi River.  De Tonti proceeded south on his own in an attempt to meet La Salle on his ascent. He failed to find La Salle and made it to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gulf_of_Mexico">Gulf of Mexico</ref> before turning back. He left several men near the mouth of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arkansas_River">Arkansas River</ref> to establish a trading post there on land granted to him by La Salle for his service. This location would become the historical <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arkansas_Post">Arkansas Post</ref>, the first permanent European settlement in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lower_Mississippi">lower Mississippi</ref> region.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-EncyclopediaArkansasArkansasPost-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Wars with English settlers</head>
<p>During 1687, Tonti was engaged in wars with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/England">English</ref> and their <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iroquois">Iroquois</ref> allies. In 1688, he returned to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fort_Saint_Louis_(Illinois)">Fort Saint Louis</ref> and found members of La Salle's party who concealed the fact of La Salle's death.
Tonti sent out parties to find survivors and then started out himself in October 1689.</p>
<p>Tonti travelled up the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Red_River_of_the_South">Red River</ref> and reached the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caddo">Caddo</ref> villages in northeastern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Texas">Texas</ref> in the spring of 1690. The Caddo offered him no assistance, and he was forced to withdraw.</p>
<head>Life in lower French Louisiana</head>
<p>Tonti experienced several financial difficulties in the 1690s, and in early 1700, he commenced a journey down the Mississippi to make contact with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pierre_Le_Moyne_d'Iberville">Pierre Le Moyne d'Iberville</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-MR-1">[1]</ref> who had established the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louisiana_(New_France)">Louisiana (New France)</ref> colony. Tonti reached French Louisiana and joined the colony.</p>
<p>In 1702, at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old_Mobile_Site">Old Mobile</ref>, he was chosen by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pierre_Le_Moyne_d'Iberville">Iberville</ref> as an ambassador to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Choctaw">Choctaw</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chickasaw">Chickasaw</ref> tribes and conducted several negotiations.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-MR-1">[1]</ref>
De Tonti, for whom the historic district north of present-day downtown <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mobile,_Alabama">Mobile</ref> is named, returned to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old_Mobile_Site">Old Mobile Site</ref>, with three Chickasaw chiefs and 2 Choctaw chiefs. The chiefs were rivals, but after Iberville had finished addressing them and presenting them gifts of guns and ammunition, they agreed to aid the settlers. The 22-year-old <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bienville">Bienville</ref> (a younger brother of Iberville) translated for Iberville.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>Tonti also led punitive expeditions from 1696 until 1704, with his cousin <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pierre-Charles_de_Liette">De Liette</ref>.</p>
<p>In August 1704 Tonti contracted <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yellow_fever">yellow fever</ref> and died at Old Mobile, north of present-day <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mobile,_Alabama">Mobile, Alabama</ref>.</p>
</text>
