<text id="autogum_academic_doc520" title="Small Animal Veterinarians’ Perceptions, Experiences, and Views of Common Dog Breeds, Dog Aggression, and Breed-Specific Laws in the United States" shortTile="small-animal-veterinarians" author="Lori  R. Kogan, Regina  M. Schoenfeld-Tacher, Peter  W. Hellyer, James  A. Oxley, Mark Rishniw" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4081/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Materials and Methods </head>
<p>
In collaboration with VIN (Veterinary Information Network—an online veterinary community), an anonymous online survey was created to evaluate veterinarians’ views regarding common dog breeds. This survey was administered directly through the VIN data collection portal. The survey was created and tested by researchers at Colorado State University and VIN. As part of this development, a pilot test in which the survey was distributed to a small sample of VIN members (~10) was conducted to screen for question flow, appropriate branching, ambiguous questions, and survey errors. Feedback from the pilot test was analyzed and incorporated into the final version of the survey. A link to the survey was distributed via an email invitation to all VIN members (n ~ 35,000), and access was made available from 18 June 2018–14 August 2018. A follow-up message was sent two weeks after the initial invitation. Only data from respondents who stated they currently practice veterinary medicine as a small animal practitioner in the U.S. were included in the study. This was an anonymous survey; therefore, written informed consent was not required; instead, an introductory statement included an explanation of the study and the fact that potential participants were giving implied consent by completing the survey. The study was categorized as exempt by the Colorado State University’s Institutional Review Board. </p>

<head> Questionnaire Design </head>
<p>
The questionnaire consisted of nine sections, beginning with an introduction that explained the purpose of the study. This was followed by a section gathering respondents’ demographic information (age, gender, and number of children). The second section asked about current dog ownership, breed bans within the respondent’s locality, and their consideration of a pit bull breed dog as a pet.  </p>

<p>Section three presented questions relating to whether the respondent was currently a practicing veterinarian, veterinary practice type (e.g., private, not for profit), main practice type (e.g., small animal, large animal, animal shelter, or feline-only), their number of years in veterinary practice, and their experiences with pit bull dogs inside and outside of the veterinary practice.  </p>

<p>The fourth section included 18 statements and asked participants to indicate their level of agreement (i.e., strongly disagree, disagree, neither agree/disagree, agree, strongly agree), with each statement. These questions pertained to general dog ownership (e.g., “<hi rend="italic">an adult should be able to own any breed of dog</hi>”); veterinarians involvement in the breed ban legislation (e.g., “<hi rend="italic">veterinarians should support breed ban legislation in their local communities</hi>”); banning breeds and authority involvement (e.g., “<hi rend="italic">banning certain breeds of dog by a government entity (city, county, state) is an overreach of governmental authority</hi>”); and perceptions of banned breed ownership and public safety (e.g., “<hi rend="italic">banning specific breeds improves public safety</hi>”).  </p>

<p>The next section included three questions related to a list of twenty-three dog breeds. These breeds, with the exception of pit bull, were selected to reflect the most common dog breeds, according to the American Kennel Association, in the U.S.. Pit bull was included in the list, even though it is not an actual breed, because of the common use of the term. The first question asked respondents to rate each breed in terms of serious bite risk from ‘minimal’, ‘moderate’, ‘high risk’, or ‘don’t know’. A further two questions asked participants if they feel some breeds should be banned and an open-ended question asking them to explain the reason for their answer. The next question asked participants to “Picture you are out for a walk and the following adult dog off-leash runs up to you. Please indicate your immediate emotional response” for a list of 23 common breeds. The possible answers ranged from 0 = petrified to 10 = deliriously happy/excited. The following question asked participants to indicate whether they thought each dog breed was appropriate for families with children under the age of 18. The last section asked about participants’ endorsement to several dog-related laws that might affect public safety (e.g., “<hi rend="italic">Stricter leash laws”, “Mandatory muzzling of specific breeds when in public</hi>”).  </p>

<p>Statistical analysis, including descriptive statistics, Chi-square, and Cochran–Mantel–Haenszel test (CMH), was conducted with a commercially available statistical software program (SPSS, Version 25; IBM Corp, Armonk, NY, USA). The CMH was used to test the association between gender and outcomes to the agreement level statements (agree or disagree) while taking into account the stratification of child status and pit bull ownership. The agreement statements were recoded into binary statements whereby ‘strongly agree’ and ‘agree’ were combined into ‘agree’ and ‘neutral’, ‘disagree’ and ‘strongly disagree’ were recoded into ‘disagree’. CMH is used in observational studies to measure confounding variables when random assignment is not possible. Due to the number of analyses conducted, the significance level (α) was set at a more conservative level of <hi rend="italic">p</hi> = 0.01. Not all survey questions received responses; therefore, the number corresponding to each particular question is indicated in the text and the tables. </p>
</text>
