<text id="autogum_voyage_doc251" title="United States without a car" shortTile="united-states-without" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=144657" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>United States without a car</head>


<p>The <ref target="United%20States%20of%20America">United States of America</ref> is called the home country of the automobile; having a quarter of a billion cars on the roads (which amounts to roughly 25% of <hi rend="italic">all cars in the world</hi>), more than any other nation. It also has the highest number of cars <hi rend="italic">per capita</hi> of any non city-state country. Consequently, car dependent settlement patterns and mass motorization have arguably reached higher, more extreme, levels in the U.S. than anywhere else, and cars have become so pervasive that their ownership is still often assumed as the default. In fact the form of ID most Americans own is usually a driver's license.</p>

<p>Unlike in most European and East Asian countries, where public transport is seen as an essential public utility, public transport in the U.S. is largely regarded as a social welfare program for those too poor to afford a car. As such, frequencies tend to be bad, and public transit authorities struggle to obtain enough funding even for the most basic maintenance, particularly in areas dominated by the Republican party (who are largely opposed to any government spending on welfare). Moreover, heavy political lobbying from car manufacturers and oil companies also means that any taxpayer dollars designated for transportation are often used to build new roads for more cars rather than improving public transportation. If you decide to take the plunge, you'll often find decaying infrastructure that makes use of technology that has not been updated for decades, and you may also find that buses and trains are dirtier compared to the rest of the developed world. The Anglosphere in general - and the U.S. in particular - also tend to have higher construction costs for public infrastructure, meaning that when money does become available, they get less "bang for the buck".</p>

<p>Still, many travelers want to <hi rend="bold">get around without a car</hi>, whether for the lack of a driver's license, <ref target="budget%20travel">to save money</ref>, or <ref target="ecotourism">to minimize environmental footprint</ref>. Another reason is that city driving can be quite stressful and many people want to enjoy a relaxing holiday away from even the thought of their annoying daily commute.</p>

<p>For both local and long-distance public transportation in the U.S., detailed information is almost always available online (on individual transit companies' websites and often on services like Google Maps), making it easy to plan ahead of time.</p>

<head>By train</head>

<p>One popular alternative to car travel are the various forms of urban and intercity rail service. Unfortunately, due to successful political lobbying by car manufacturers and airlines, American rail services suffer from chronic underinvestment and are slower than most counterparts in <ref target="Europe">Europe</ref> and <ref target="East%20Asia">East Asia</ref>, with intercity services that often run no more than once a day. However, <ref target="urban%20rail">urban rail</ref> networks are expanding in many cities and some intercity rail lines have had minor improvements as well. The area best covered by passenger rail services (of all kinds) is generally the Northeast between the cities of <ref target="Boston">Boston</ref> and <ref target="Washington%2C%20DC">Washington, DC</ref> with some urban rail and Amtrak services branching out further with reasonable travel times and frequencies even beyond that area. Another area that is surprisingly well covered both in terms of frequency of trains and number of stops is <ref target="California">California</ref>. Train service between <ref target="Oakland">Oakland</ref> and <ref target="Los%20Angeles">Los Angeles</ref> will remain slow until the completion of the <ref target="high-speed%20rail">high-speed rail</ref> link in a few years; nonetheless, the Bay Area is well covered by BART (Bay Area Rapid Transit) and CalTrain, which goes all the way south to <ref target="Gilroy">Gilroy</ref>, and with the extension of the LA Subway and light rail lines (Metro Rail), the notoriously car-centric <ref target="Los%20Angeles">Los Angeles</ref> area is now at least partially accessible without a car. Current trends indicate that local and regional train coverage will only get better in the future, with several local and statewide rail improvements either scheduled for construction or being built right now. </p>

<p>Another important hub for rail travel is <ref target="Chicago">Chicago</ref>, with many Amtrak lines terminating there or going through the city. If you are traveling by train from coast to coast, chances are you will pass through Chicago. However, few lines have top speeds significantly higher than , even though some upgrades are planned or underway. In addition to that, Chicago has a functioning and well patronized urban rail system. Still, some of the most popular tourist destinations in the U.S. cannot be reached by train alone. Neither <ref target="Las%20Vegas">Las Vegas</ref> nor the <ref target="Yellowstone%20National%20Park">Yellowstone National Park</ref> gets any regular train service. Amtrak serves 46 states, i.e. all with the exception of Hawaii (<ref target="urban%20rail">urban rail</ref> under construction on <ref target="Oahu">Oahu</ref>), Alaska (served by the Alaska Railroad, see below), South Dakota and Wyoming (both states entirely without passenger trains). Even in some of the states it does "serve", the biggest city or metro area is not served by Amtrak. <ref target="Idaho">Idaho</ref> for example only sees one route passing through the panhandle in the extreme north of the state, while missing the major population centers.</p>

<p>If you want to combine bike and rail, Amtrak offers you to carry your bike. See <ref target="http://www.amtrak.com/servlet/ContentServer%3Fc%3DPage%26amp%3Bpagename%3Dam%252FLayout%26amp%3Bcid%3D1251621565020">their regulations on special items</ref> for details. See also <ref target="http://www.amtrak.com/bring-your-bicycle-onboard">here</ref>.</p>

<ref target="Alaska">Alaska</ref> is not served by Amtrak but does have train service through the <ref target="http://www.alaskarailroad.com/">Alaska Railroad</ref>, which mainly serves a corridor between <ref target="Seward">Seward</ref> and <ref target="Fairbanks">Fairbanks</ref> via <ref target="Anchorage">Anchorage</ref>. Outside of that corridor, Alaska is fairly inaccessible by rail. However, this is also true to a degree for cars. For example, the capital, <ref target="Juneau">Juneau</ref>, cannot be reached by other means than sea and air. As a matter of fact, some of the places served by the Alaska railroad are not connected to any road and hence the train is the only practicable way to get there.

<ref target="Heritage%20railways">Heritage railways</ref> exist throughout the U.S. and in some places they do provide some transportation value, with some serving a station Amtrak also serves and coordinating their schedule with Amtrak. In other places <ref target="tourist%20railways">tourist railways</ref> or dinner trains are mostly employed for their novelty value and don't offer transportation beyond short round trips or circular tours.

<p>The largest cities are often served by one or several <ref target="urban%20rail">urban rail</ref> systems. In some cases they are the best way for getting around a city. Some of them, like the cable cars of San Francisco or the L of Chicago, are iconic for the city and double as attractions.</p>
</text>
