<text id="autogum_interview_doc401" title="part2_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Family Coalition Party candidate Vicki Gunn, Glengarry-Prescott-Russell" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-02" dateModified="2010-06-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Family_Coalition_Party_candidate_Vicki_Gunn%2C_Glengarry-Prescott-Russell" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly?</hi></p>
<p>The first order of business should be to recognise the intrinsic value of the family and seek to withdraw all programs which interfere in the health of the family. This would include: eliminate funding for abortion which has contributed to our nationwide crisis due to the loss of 'replacement birthrate'. This problem will still compound for many years but it would be a first step towards resolving the issue; it would also include a voucher system for education to ensure that parents are in control of how their children are educated; The FCP would also seek to remove social assistance to youth under 18 who have parents able to support them.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are the property taxes in your riding at a fair level for the amount of services received in the municipality?</hi></p>
<p>Because of the vast infrastructure which must be maintained using a limited income source, I believe that property taxes are above what they should be. Municipalities are closer to the people thus they should be able to provide the services using some of the tax strategies of federal and provincial governments. Property taxes are paid only by homeowners, there are many people who do not own homes but using the services. We need a system of taxing fairly all users of our infrastructure.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How can the province lead the way in stimulating job creation?</hi></p>
<p>The province can lead the way by encouraging the growth of small business. Enabling people to become self-employed stimulates the economy with new jobs. By taking the pressure off municipalities to offer incentives for large companies to move from municipality to municipality, depending on where they get the best tax break.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What are your views on the mixed member proportional representation (MMP) referendum?</hi></p>
<p>I believe it will better represent the diverse opinions which are part of this province. Under the present FPTP system the majority of opinions are not represented in the Legislature because they have been effectively silenced by false majority governments. We need to allow representation to all members and viewpoints in Ontario.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What role, if any, does "new media" play in your campaign, and the campaign of your party? (websites, blogs, Facebook, YouTube videos, etc) Do you view it as beneficial, or a challenge?</hi></p>
<p>My campaign is largely based in 'new media'. I live 3-4 hours from the riding for which I am the candidate. This means that I must use the opportunities provided by websites, emails etc.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Of the decisions made by Ontario's 38th Legislative Assembly, which was the most beneficial to your this electoral district? To the province as a whole? Which was least beneficial, or even harmful, to your this riding? To the province as a whole?</hi></p>
</text>
