<text id="autogum_interview_doc400" title="part1_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Family Coalition Party candidate Vicki Gunn, Glengarry-Prescott-Russell" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-02" dateModified="2010-06-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Family_Coalition_Party_candidate_Vicki_Gunn%2C_Glengarry-Prescott-Russell" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?</hi></p>
<p>I am not a resident of the riding so my decisions will not be based in local bias or favouritism. I come with a commitment to help empower families with the authority which is rightfully theirs. I seek to serve, not because of a love for power but, because I believe that we need strong families to build a strong society and economy. I would cheerfully address the issues of G-P-R and maintain a residence there to ensure there is access to me as their MPP.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>My first priority is our families. It is for them that we work and seek to maintain a stable home life. I believe the welfare of their families is of prime importance to the people of G-P-R. Whether it's recreational concerns, information provided to them outside of approved sources such as the internet, education or child care. People are concerned primarily about their family. This would be the first area I would seek to address. I would do so by decreasing government involvement in our personal lives. I would like to see parents empowered to make decisions for the well-being of their family. This would include the freedom to choose what form of education the children should have.</p>
<p>Access to health care - There are too many people who do not have access to a family doctor. A cooperative clinic does not provide the same access. Wait times in hospitals can be as long as 10 hours in the emergency room. For all the touting of things getting better, this was about 1 month ago. These are important issues.</p>
<p>Elective surgeries should not be paid for by public health care. They are elective and thus un-essential. The health care savings would ensure that we are able to fully provide necessary and lifesaving medical care.</p>
<p>I would work with the federal government to develop a testing and upgrading system to ensure qualified foreign doctors become active medical practitioners within our system.</p>
<p>Rural areas find the shortage of doctors even more challenging than large cities. We would strengthen the Under-serviced  Areas Training Program, providing tuition, books and living expenses for each year of medical school in exchange for an equal number of years in under-serviced areas.</p>
<p>While small communities generally have less dramatic crimes, where there is crime there are victims. We need to protect the rights of law abiding citizens over those of convicted offenders.</p>
<p>Educationally, we need to promote personal responsibility. Violent offenders should need not receive reduced sentences.</p>
</text>
