<text id="autogum_academic_doc478" title="Fibrin as a Multipurpose Physiological Platform for Bone Tissue Engineering and Targeted Delivery of Bioactive Compounds" shortTile="fibrin-multipurpose" author="Bruno Bujoli, Jean-Claude Scimeca, Elise Verron" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1999-4923/11/11/556/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Fibrin Handling for Bioactive Compounds Delivery</head><head> 5.1. Tuning Fibrin Intrinsic Characteristics</head>
<p>
Bioactive compounds including growth factors, cytokines, drugs, and nucleic acids can be easily entrapped in the fibrin matrix by mixing them with fibrinogen or thrombin. In general, fibrin matrix remains porous regardless the conditions and/or thrombin and fibrinogen ratios. However, increasing fibrinogen and/or thrombin concentrations densifies the structure of a fibrin gel and reduces its degradation rate, thus slowing down the diffusion of loaded molecules (e.g., FGF). </p>

<p>In addition, the release profile of active compounds is affected by their physicochemical properties including partition coefficient, size and functional groups. For example, hydrophilic molecules readily leach out (e.g., erythromycin, mitomycin C, fluorouracil etc.), while hydrophobic molecules, or those which display a strong chemical affinity for the matrix components, are released more gradually (e.g., streptomycin, sulfamethoxazole-trimethoprim, cefazolin, enocitabine etc.). Thus, some compounds need to be modified chemically to become more hydrophobic, resulting in a prolonged retention within the matrix. Conversely, a proteolytic degradation may be required to speed up the diffusion process. </p>

<p>Lastly, fibrin matrix proteolysis through the action of thrombin or plasmin induces the release of entrapped compounds. In order to restrict this breakdown of the matrix, the co-entrapment of proteolysis inhibitors (aprotinin, matrix metalloproteinases inhibitors such as galardin) was investigated. Ahmed et al. identified in their model (i.e., chondroprogenitor clonal cell line) the enzymes responsible for fibrin gel breakdown. It appeared that metalloproteinases (MMP-2, MMP-3, MMP-9) were secreted concomitantly with fibrin hydrogels breakdown. They also noted high plasmin activity in the conditioned media during hydrogel breakdown. Then, they demonstrated that aprotinin and galardin, in combination or separately, prevented fibrin hydrogels degradation. <figure>Figure 4</figure> summarizes the modifications which can be made on fibrin matrix to regulate the release of entrapped agents. </p>

<head> 5.2. Modifying Fibrin and/or Active Agents for Efficient Combination and Delivery</head>
<p>
In some instances, fibrin exhibits innate affinity for therapeutics and growth factors but in other cases, the covalent attachment of these compounds to fibrin is considered. This generally requires chemical modifications with reactive functional groups (thiols, azides) allowing a stable association. Then, reduction/hydrolysis reactions or enzymatic cleavage mediate the release of active molecules. It was shown that this approach prolongs the delivery phase of growth factors for example. </p>

<p>As another illustration, covalently binding of BMP and RGD sequences to fibrin allows interactions with bone marrow stromal cells through integrin surface receptors that triggered downstream signaling pathways. More sophisticated constructions have been tested. Starting from BMP-2, Schmoekel et al. propose a tripartite fusion protein denoted as TG-pl-BMP-2. Under the control of the blood transglutaminase factor XIIIa, the N-terminal transglutaminase substrate domain (TG) provides a covalent attachment to fibrin during coagulation. In addition, upon the action of cell-activated plasmin, the central plasmin substrate domain (pl) gives a cleavage site for the local release of the attached growth factor from the fibrin matrix. Lastly, the C-terminal human BMP-2 domain displays an osteogenic activity. </p>

<p>As an alternative to active molecules derivatization, fibrin functionalization can also be achieved. For example, to facilitate BMP interaction with a fibrin matrix, Yang et al. grafted heparin onto fibrin, this leading to electrostatic interactions between the negative charges of heparin sulfate groups, and the positive charges of BMPs amino acid residues. Interestingly, heparin presence slowed down fibrin degradation, and consequently the release of loaded BMPs. Similar observations were made with FGF. </p>

<p>Despite positive effects reported in literature, there are several drawbacks to fibrin or growth factors/proteins functionalization. First of all, it requires specific skills, and it is time consuming and expensive. Furthermore, proteins functionality can be altered by these modifications. Indeed, covalent binding can mask active sites, thus affecting their bioactivity. As an alternative, non-modified compounds can be internalized into particles, to slow down their release. Wang et al. developed a sophisticated system which could serve to deliver low-molecular weight hydrophilic drugs. They used an antithrombosis drug (i.e., Tirofiban®) as a drug model. Drug-loaded liposomes were first encapsulated in a fibrin gel, and then combined to chitosan. To document/characterize the in vitro drug release profile, different parameters were studied including the surface charge of liposomes, the pore size of chitosan structure, and the crosslinking degree of fibrin gels. All these experimental conditions offered different prolonged releases without altering the composite bioactivity. All these modifications are summarized in <figure>Figure 4</figure>. </p>
</text>
