<text id="autogum_interview_doc778" title="part0_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Communist Party candidate Shona Bracken, Toronto Danforth" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-07" dateModified="2007-12-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Communist_Party_candidate_Shona_Bracken%2C_Toronto_Danforth" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Communist Party candidate Shona Bracken, Toronto Danforth</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, October 7, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shona Bracken</hi> is running for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Communist%20Party%20of%20Ontario">Communist Party</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ontario%20general%20election,%202007">Ontario provincial election</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toronto—Danforth">Toronto—Danforth</ref>. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref> interviewed her regarding her values, her experience, and her campaign.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>First of all, I’m a keen supporter of the “people’s agenda” put forward by our Party, and participating in this election is a very good way to publicize and to win more supporters for the policies we advance. As a youth activist, I am particularly concerned about education and other social issues relevant to youth and students – issues like rolling back and eliminating tuition, ending the ‘corporatization’ of our campuses, and lowering the voting age to 16. Toronto-Danforth is a predominantly working class, culturally diverse community and what is why I volunteered to carry our party flag in this riding.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>I am one of the youngest candidates (from any of the political parties) running in this election anywhere in the province. Naturally, then, I lack political experience. What I lack in experience however, is more than made up by my enthusiasm and fresh approach to the big social and economic issues facing Ontario today, and into the future. I am completing an under-graduate program in Sociology at Glendon College of York University. I have an elected position on my Students’ Union as the Director of External Affairs, and also serve on the executive of the Canadian Federation of Students-Ontario.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why? What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?</hi></p>
<p>Peter Tabuns, the incumbent MPP representing the NDP in the legislature, is obviously the odds-on favourite to win re-election. His party however has continued to water-down its reformist policies in an attempt to ensconce itself into the political ‘mainstream’. The NDP has long since abandoned a principled anti-capitalist or socialist program, and that’s why I think it is important to put forward a Communist alternative.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>It’s hard to reduce everything down to three – there are so many vital issues facing us. But you asked, so here goes:</p>
<list type="ordered"><item>Job &amp; Economic Justice – to reverse the de-industrialization of Ontario, secure more well-paid, unionized jobs, and raise the minimum wage to $15/hour.</item>
<item>A future for youth – We need to make education a right, not a privilege. Student debt is out of control and Ontario has the second highest tuition fees in the country. First year student are entering Ontario universities with never-before-seen tuition levels. Ultimately, a comprehensive funding formula needs to be put in place to make higher education free, and public schools need the necessary resources to prepare students for higher education, regardless of whether or not they live in a wealthy neighbourhood.</item>
<item>Peace &amp; Disarmament – I think this really is a provincial issue… we need a legislature at Queen’s Park that’s willing to tell Ottawa to “Get out of Afghanistan Now!”; to cut military spending by 50%; and to ban military recruitment from our schools and campuses.</item></list>
</text>
