<text id="autogum_whow_doc454" title="Avoid Being Ripped off by a Contractor" shortTile="avoid-being-ripped" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2010-05-20" dateModified="2018-11-08" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Avoid-Being-Ripped-off-by-a-Contractor" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Avoid Being Ripped off by a Contractor</head><p>Employing a contractor always involves a certain amount of risk. You can significantly decrease your chances of being ripped off by by one just by taking all the steps listed below. Just by reading number one and you could save yourself time, money and trouble.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Learn what the common scams are: <figure rend="Get-a-Patent-Step-6-Version-3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>"Today Only" discounts.  If a contractor ever tells you the price is available for "today only", it's time to show him the door.  Quite often they'll provide you a story that by signing today you're entitled to a "model home" or "advertising discount".</item>
<item>The story centers around the need to use your home as a model to advertise their services in the neighborhood. They mark their prices up just to give you this false discount.  Don't be fooled.  This is an old trick used to pressure homeowners into making a quick decision. This is your money we're talking about!  Quickly ask these salespeople to leave!</item>
<item>Avoid contractors who ask for more than a third of the money up front. Or even any money upfront at all; they shouldn't need any kind of payments from you until the work is completed.</item></list></item>
<item>Avoid high pressure salespeople representing the contractor.  You should never feel pressured into making a decision about choosing your contractor.  If you ever feel that a contractor or salesman is pressuring you, ask them to back off.  If they persist, it's time to look for another contractor.  High pressure usually leads to a bad decision when remodeling.  A qualified, reputable professional would never pressure anyone into a project. <figure rend="Develop-Critical-Thinking-Skills-Step-12-Version-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Beware of "Door-To-Door" contractors.  These people may not be contractors at all.  Never allow them into your home until you have checked them out thoroughly!  This can't be stressed enough.  It has been recently reported that two men claiming to be contractors entered into a home, and while one took the homeowner on a pretend inspection, the other was going through purses and picking up items that could be sold quickly. <figure rend="Get-Out-of-a-Lease-Step-3-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Some contractors working in your area may put out flyers or come to your door soliciting additional work in the area.  These contractors could be honest, reputable people.  But you shouldn't invite them in.  Instead, politely ask them for their business card and the name, address and telephone number of the people they are doing work for in the neighborhood.  Then make an appointment with that homeowner to take a look at the quality of their work. <figure rend="Be-a-National-Delegate-(USA)-Step-9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Disputes can still arise, even when dealing with an ethical contractor. Draw up and agree on the scope of work and produce a Bill of Quantities that clearly lists all the materials and tasks to be performed.  The Bill of Quantities should also list a Rate(cost) per metre / m² / m³, etc. That way if there are any variations or extras, you can use the rates to determine the cost of these extras.  Make use of "variation orders" or VOs, a written agreement that quantifies any changes to the originally agreed scope of work which must be signed by both parties. <figure rend="Be-a-Secret-Agent-Step-9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make use of a construction contract - Contracts are normally available through the relevant building institutes.  These contracts normally protect the interests of both parties. <figure rend="Succeed-in-Network-Marketing-Step-5-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure that they have licenses and insurance before any work is performed and are following city, state and federal codes to complete the work to which you have agreed on.</item>
<item>Always shop around between contractors when trying to find the right one for the job.</item></list>
</text>
