<text id="autogum_whow_doc570" title="Read a Dog&apos;s Pedigree" shortTile="read-dogs-pedigree" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2017-09-23" dateModified="2019-09-05" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Read-a-Dog%27s-Pedigree" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Read a Dog's Pedigree</head><p>If you're the proud owner of a pedigreed dog, it's important to understand all of the detailed information found on its certificate. And if you're thinking about buying a dog from a breeder, you'll want to see its pedigree and verify the information found on it. The dog's official name, show titles, and registration number are commonly found on its pedigree. The document will also list similar information for the dog's ancestors. It is increasingly common for them to also include DNA and health identification, so make sure to check the certificate for this information, too.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Tracing a Dog's Lineage</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find the dog's registered name and birth date. The dog's official name, as recorded by a kennel or other organization, will definitely appear on the pedigree. Usually it will appear as the first name on the left or right corner, along with the date of birth. <figure rend="Read a Dog's Pedigree Step 1 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Identify the dog's ancestors. Most of the time, the names of the dog's parents will be just to the right. A pedigree should list the names of both the dam (mother) and sire (father). Depending on the pedigree, you may also see the dog's grandparents farther to the right, then the great-grandparents, and so on. <figure rend="Read a Dog's Pedigree Step 2 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>A proper pedigree should list the official names of all of the ancestors. Depending upon the pedigree report and the known ancestry, this could go back for just 3 or 4 generations, or may go back several.</item></list></item>
<item>Determine whether your dog has been inbred, line-bred, or outcrossed. Pay attention to the names of the dog and its ancestors. If you see repeated names, it is a sign that the ancestors were closely related. Breeders maintain and perfect the characteristics associated with particular breeds by carefully selecting which dogs to mate. <figure rend="Read a Dog's Pedigree Step 3 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Inbreeding means that very closely related dogs have mated, such as a son and mother, father and daughter, or brother and sister.</item>
<item>Linebreeding means that a dog's sire and dam have a close ancestor in common.</item>
<item>Out crossing occurs when there are no common ancestors in 3 to 4 generations.</item>
<item>Breeders and owners often highly value inbreeding or linebreeding traced to a notable ancestor.</item></list></item>
<item>Check for DNA numbers. Since DNA testing has become easier and more widespread, it is increasingly common for numbers identifying a dog's genetic makeup to appear on a pedigree. If these are available, they should be found next to the dog's name. <figure rend="Read a Dog's Pedigree Step 4 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Each dog whose DNA has been officially tested and registered (with a kennel, for example) will have an identifying number.</item></list></item>
<item>Study the stud book numbers. A pedigree may also list when a dog was bred, and which of the dam's litters the dog comes from. These are known as stud book numbers. If you pay attention to the dam's birth date, you can also determine how old she was when she had the litter. <figure rend="Read a Dog's Pedigree Step 5 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, if the dog's pedigree lists a stud book date of 2/2016, and the dam's date of birth is 5/2013, you can determine that she was not quite 3 years old when she had the litter.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Interpreting Special Information</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Look for show records. If the dog or its ancestors were awarded in any notable competitions, these will probably be listed on the pedigree along with each dog's name. These may simply be recorded as a series of abbreviations. <figure rend="Read a Dog's Pedigree Step 6 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, you may see the abbreviation “FCI,” signifying the Fédération Cynologique Internationale World Championship.</item>
<item>If you are unfamiliar with any of the abbreviations, ask the breeder or kennel association to explain.</item></list></item>
<item>Decode any title abbreviations. Many breeds can be awarded special titles that recognize highly desirable traits. These can vary from breed to breed, and can be difficult to interpret unless you are very familiar with the breed. Just ask the breeder or kennel association to explain if you aren't sure what the titles mean. <figure rend="Read a Dog's Pedigree Step 7 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The pedigree for a German Shepherd, for example, may list titles for things like tracking, herding, and obedience.</item>
<item>The titles may appear simply as abbreviations, however, like “BH,” “FH2,” and “SchH2.”</item>
<item>You can check the websites of organizations like the American Kennel Club and the United Kennel Club for lists of common title and show award abbreviations. You can also ask your breeder or use their website to help you identify titles or acronyms that may be common in your dog's breed.</item></list></item>
<item>Study any health information. Thanks to DNA testing and careful breeding records, pedigrees can include information about any health issues that are a concern for a dog's breed. This information can include whether or not a dog and its ancestors have been tested for genetic diseases that are known to be a problem for the breed. <figure rend="Read a Dog's Pedigree Step 8 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Health characteristics may be listed along with each dog's name and other identifying information, or separately.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Recognizing Certifications</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Verify that the pedigree has an official seal. Pedigrees contain quite a bit of information that can determine a dog's value, eligibility for competitions, etc. Certification from a recognized kennel association, such as the AKC (American Kennel Club) helps prove that the pedigree is accurate and trustworthy. <figure rend="Read a Dog's Pedigree Step 9 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you plan to show or breed your dog in the future, you will need these records. Keep them on file, and make sure you get the most accurate, up-to-date reports for these purposes.</item></list></item>
<item>Double-check the registration number. If the pedigree is certified by a kennel association, it will include an official number identifying the dog. Contact the association and ask to cross-check the number. They may also be able to confirm other information found on the pedigree so that you can verify its accuracy and legitimacy. <figure rend="Read a Dog's Pedigree Step 10 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't be alarmed by a conditional registration. Some pedigrees may be marked as “conditional” if DNA information shows there is an unknown ancestor. This does not necessarily mean that the dog cannot be considered purebred. The kennel association may also allow the conditional status to be removed after a certain number of generations. <figure rend="Read a Dog's Pedigree Step 11 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Conditional pedigrees may have a different seal or coloring to identify them as such.</item></list></item>
<item>Check to see if your dog's pedigree is registered. Not all breeders will pay the fees to register a dog for you. Your AKC paperwork may be accurate, but not active or filed. Ask your breeder or check the AKC website to see if your dog has been registered. <figure rend="Read a Dog's Pedigree Step 12.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
