<text id="autogum_interview_doc316" title="part3_John Reed on Orwell, God, self-destruction and the future of writing" shortTile="partjohn-reed-orwell" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-18" dateModified="2015-01-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Reed_on_Orwell%2C_God%2C_self-destruction_and_the_future_of_writing" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But they're not like that anymore, are they?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  I don't know.  I mean, now it seems like a lot of places have taken on that model.  You have all this stuff out there, something hits, and then everything goes behind that.</p>
<head id="On_Christopher_Hitchens,_Orwell_and_9/11_as_inspiration">On Christopher Hitchens, Orwell and 9/11 as inspiration</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why did you decide to take on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George%20Orwell">Orwell</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  I went to school at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List%20of%20public%20elementary%20schools%20in%20New%20York%20City">P.S. 41</ref>.  I read Orwell over and over again and of course as a kid, I liked it.  But I didn't really understand what about it that also depressed me.  It's kind of a bludgeon for revolutionary thinking.  On a number of levels, Orwell encourages you to think that you're not as smart as the pigs--that revolution is doomed to failure.  I don't know if that's exactly what Orwell meant, but that's certainly how it's framed in school.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How it reads in general?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Really how it's used.  It's the paradigm of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cold%20War">Cold War</ref> and it was used to promote the Cold War.  In fact, the phrase "Cold War" is Orwell's term.  He was very aware of what was happening with this.  I don't know if he would have liked that it ended up being a real tool for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Central%20Intelligence%20Agency">CIA</ref> to push the Cold War agenda--I don't think he would have liked it.  But that's what happened, and at the end of his life he was involved with some pretty conservative people.  Whether or not it was entirely his own doing or he was a weak, lovelorn old man is another question.  I think probably some of both.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher%20Hitchens">Christopher Hitchens</ref> called you an "Osama bin Ladenist.”  How do you react to that label?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Honestly, I didn't really expect it to be so thrilling to me, but I loved it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I photographed many of the New York academics who are featured in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20Horowitz">David Horowitz</ref> book, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Professors:%20%20The%20101%20Most%20Dangerous%20Academics%20in%20America">The Professors:  The 101 Most Dangerous Academics in America</ref></hi>, and every single one of them held it up as this badge of honor.  They all received emails like, "How did you get in there?"  It gave them stature that they may not have had before.  Is it the same?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Yeah, I mean it's just also completely so absurd.  We got all this press for Snowball's Chance, and of course it was all based on whether people were conservative or progressive.  They either liked me based on their politics or didn't like me based on their politics.  Hitchens didn't read the book.  In fact, that's the only thing that makes me a little bit bitter, that he called me a "bin Ladenist" without having read the book.  But yeah, I don't mind.  It's just so completely absurd.</p>
</text>
