<text id="autogum_interview_doc871" title="part11_Wikinews interviews World Wide Web co-inventor Robert Cailliau" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-07-22" dateModified="2014-09-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_World_Wide_Web_co-inventor_Robert_Cailliau" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>This trend started to worry me with e-mail first.  Because of spam most <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet%20service%20provider">ISPs</ref> stopped relaying mail and I began to have some trouble sending e-mail while on travel.  To send mail you have to know the local smtp server.  But which hotel receptionist can tell you that?  They stare blankly at you, incapable of understanding that you do not use web mail, i.e. that you do not have your messages on a server.</p>
<p>Money is virtual, it is a number on a computer in a bank somewhere.  We trust the bank: nobody has gold coins in a sock under the mattress.</p>
<p>But we have been working on the banking establishment for a few centuries.  The last time we had a great crash (depression of 1929) not only a large number of people died of hunger, but it helped bring about the most totalitarian state we ever witnessed (the Third Reich).  Since those days we have learned a lot, painfully and with lots of mishaps.</p>
<p>Therefore now we think that we can trust the banks and the economists with our money.  The breakthrough came from government controls and international conventions.</p>
<p>With our data it is now as it was with money about two centuries ago:  everything is in the hands of uncontrolled private companies, without any legal framework, to say nothing of international agreements.</p>
<p>But my data are a part of myself.  I want to know how my data are managed, by whom, where, and with what guarantees.  Money I may lose but then I grow my potatoes in my garden.</p>
<p>You speak of a web-Renaissance.  That would be a brilliant light that would let us see that in the information-driven era we need to build new social structures, new forms of creating trust and we need more transparency in the processes of society.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi>: The principle behind wikis such as Wikipedia provides similar functionalities to early web browsers that were web editors at the same time. To which extent is this analogy correct?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Robert Cailliau</hi>: The one great difference, maybe, is that wikis run on servers, but I can of course put a wiki on my home computer or laptop.  It's not really <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WYSIWYG">wysiwyg</ref> but that is not so important.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi>: Do you see wikis as a viable long-term model, or do you expect something else to emerge? On the subjects of wikis, do you refer to Wikipedia?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Robert Cailliau</hi>: I use the Wikipedia often.  I also contribute here and there.  A very great work, looked at with a lot of jealousy.  In almost all comments about the Wikipedia I perceive in the background some jealousy and intolerance.</p>
<p>There seems to be a strong reaction from those who derive their prestige from "secret" knowledge and consequently find it rather scandalous that everything is now not only lying around to be read but also often debunks their prejudices.</p>
</text>
