<text id="autogum_academic_doc183" title="Polycaprolactone-Based Mimetic Antimicrobial Peptide Copolymers Vesicles as an Effective Drug-Carrier for Cancer Therapy" shortTile="polycaprolactonebased" author="Yusheng Qian, Xinyu Zhou, Jing He, Chuncai Zhou" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4360/11/11/1783/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Cancer is one of the most important and deadly diseases worldwide. Reports from the World Health Organization show that almost 1 in 6 deaths worldwide in 2018 were due to cancer. Chemotherapy is a common approach for cancer treatment; it uses drugs to kill cancer cells. However, various limitations affect the efficiency of chemotherapy. For example, most chemotherapeutics possess poor aqueous solubility, harm normal cell toxicity due to the lack of selectivity, and cause multidrug resistance. To handle these shortcomings, researchers have proposed nano-particles as novel drug carriers to help patients cope with cancer. Nanoparticles, like vesicles, nanotubes, micelles, nanofibers, and nanosheet are typically commonly formed by amphiphilic copolymers via self-assembly. Nanoparticles can encapsulate drugs via physical entrapment or solubilization to achieve various advantages, including controlled drug release, decreased cytotoxicity, increased aqueous solubility, and targeted action site. Thus, nanoparticles have opened the door for developing effective drug delivery schemes and have shown substantial potential for applications in life-threatening disease treatments, such as cancer therapy. </p>

<p>Chemotherapy usually causes a decline in immunity, causing cancer patients to suffer from bacterial infection or threatening their lives. Therefore, avoiding bacterial infection is essential during cancer therapy. As a kind of novel antibacterial agent, antimicrobial peptides (AMPs) have gained increasing attention over the past few decades. AMPs exhibit excellent antibacterial capability and a unique antibacterial mechanism. AMPs achieve their bactericidal effect by physical disruption of bacterial membranes; however, inducing bacterial drug resistance presents difficulty. Research illustrates that such a unique antibacterial mechanism is relevant to specific AMP structures, including cationic moieties such as lysine and hydrophobic moieties such as phenylalanine. Lots of AMPs are amphiphilic peptides, namely, they are composed of hydrophobic and hydrophilic residues. AMP-nanoparticles can be prepared in an aqueous solution through self-assembly of these AMPs. AMP assemblies are ideal drug delivery systems exhibiting both drug release and antibacterial capabilities during cancer treatment. Our group has reported several amphiphilic block AMPs containing lysine and phenylalanine. These AMPs exhibit high bactericidal efficiency and low cytotoxicity. Vesicles formed by these AMPs have good performance when carrying drugs. </p>

<p>Motivated by the excellent properties and promising applications of AMP nanoparticles, synthetic amphiphilic AMP–mimetic polymers are proposed. These amphiphilic copolymers stimulate the structural features of AMPs, that is, cationic and hydrophobic moieties. Amphiphilic copolymers not only possess good properties, such as a unique bactericidal mechanism, the capability for self-assembly into nanoparticles that are similar to those of natural AMPs, but also show more convenient synthesis strategy than natural AMPs. In previous work, Zhou et al. have reported the minimal inhibition concentration (MIC) of amphiphilic copolymers was less than 32 μg/mL against both Gram-negative and Gram-positive bacteria. The broad antibacterial capability has been proved, which will play a vital role in cancer therapy. </p>

<p>In our previous work, a series of amphiphilic mimicked AMP copolymers, PCL16-<hi rend="italic">b</hi>-Kn, which can inhibit both Gram-negative and Gram-positive bacteria. In the present work, we studied the self-assembling behavior of these block copolymers in aqueous solutions. The morphologies and sizes of nanoparticles were characterized by transmission electron microscopy (TEM) and dynamic light scattering (DLS), respectively. Critical vesiculation concentrations (CVCs) were also studied. Drug delivery potential was investigated by in vitro and intracellular doxorubicin (DOX)-release experiments. Based on the results, amphiphilic diblock copolymers PCL16-<hi rend="italic">b</hi>-Kn could serve as efficient drug carriers for cancer treatment. Given the excellent antibacterial properties and low cytotoxicity of PCL16-<hi rend="italic">b</hi>-Kn in previous works, such diblock copolymer nanoparticles can be ideal “armed” drug delivery systems for applications in nanomedical fields. </p>
</text>
