<text id="autogum_interview_doc382" title="part3_Wikinews interviews Mark Bunker, producer of anti-Scientology website &amp;apos;XenuTV&amp;apos;" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-05" dateModified="2016-03-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Mark_Bunker%2C_producer_of_anti-Scientology_website_%27XenuTV%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Do they actually run camps associated with that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: R2-45 camps? Never heard of it. DM loves guns but there's no camps for shooting.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What is the next step we should take in raising the general public's awareness of the atrocities of the "Church" of Scientology. Also, besides www.xenutv.com, what are some other, reputable, citable sources of information on these abuses?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: There are plenty of great sites starting with the granddaddy of them all — www.xenu.net.  Professor David Touretzky's various sites are well researched and important resources. <hi rend="italic">Stop-Narconon</hi> and such. My favorite book on Scientology is <hi rend="italic">Bare-Faced Messiah</hi>. It and many others can now be read on the web. I'd like to do audiobook versions of them for people to download. Where, oh where, is the time, however.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why does Scientology accuse people of crimes when they are asked questions?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: Hubbard put it into writing. "Always attack - Never defend." There are policy letters where he ordered people never to answer questions about Scientology but instead twist it around to the crimes of the critic. So when you see that happening in my videos, you are hearing Hubbard's words come through the Scientologist's mouth, which is one of the reasons I never get mad at them.  This is what they are taught. They literally can't think for themselves.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why do you think Scientology dangerous? From a European (French) point of view there are many strange organizations in the United States (Nazi party, many religious groups). Why is Scientology your fight?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: I think Scientology is dangerous to individuals who find their realities stripped. I think it's dangerous to families when they are broken up by disconnection. I think it's dangerous to society when they write laws that our politicians back to attack psychiatry. Anytime they stop free speech, I think that's bad in general. Scientology is my fight because others were too afraid to take them on. I hate bullies. Scientology (while dangerous) acts like a big school yard bully. Now if that bully in 4th grade had a crack legal team and a gang of devoted followers who would do dirty tricks to send you to jail, a mental ward or the grave -- he would have been a real threat! Scientology also brings together my general interest in cults, sci-fi and Hollywood in a unique way. I never expected to pick a fight with a dangerous cult but someone had to stand up to them. I thought I could help.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">And that's part of the reasons you support 'Anonymous' and — apart from DDoS — their actions?</hi></p>
</text>
