<text id="autogum_reddit_doc114" title="Due to Very High Demand, I’m Releasing my Prom Pics" shortTile="due-very-high-demand" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-04-30" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8g0gw0" speakerList="#SammyBelskus, #anchises868" speakerCount="2">
<head>Due to Very High Demand, I’m Releasing my Prom Pics</head>
<sp who="#SammyBelskus">
<p><ref target="https://imgur.com/gallery/2Ggv3bX">Cool Picture</ref> So I posted two days ago my progress, stating I had hit my goals for my birthday and that prom was that night. Many (many) people saw and upvoted that post, and lots of comments said they wanted to see picture of me and my date from prom. At about 300 upvotes I said if it got to 1000, I would post them. Apparently you weirdos really want these pics because I got like 3k upvote by the end of the day ;) So anyway here you go. I felt so cool in my new suit. First time wearing a suit. I’ll brag a bit. I think I looked the best there. My suit was freaking awesome. The black on black on maroon (matching Rachel’s dress) was definitely a very good choice. Couldn’t have said all that stuff if I was still 290. Prom was a blast. Great way to end my birthday. All the pics are at my friend’s enormous house Also with Rachel. So we didn’t get to slow dance at prom because we missed the two songs while we were hanging outside (drying all the sweat). When I took her home, I pulled in to the cul de sac, blasted out favorite song (Saturn by Sleeping at Last), and said “never did get that dance.” So we danced in the street and I asked her out after. She said yes. So we’re goin off-roading and hiking on Saturday, with a picnic. <ref target="https://imgur.com/gallery/BkumtK9">Prom Pics</ref> In the back-to-back bros pic: Blondie is like the funnest guy I’ve ever known and has been like my best friend for the past 4 years. super supportive of me with my diet but he’s better with like emotional comfort I guess Blue Jacket is also one of my best friends. I go shooting with him all the time. He tells me I look good every time he see’s me, unless I’ve plateaued or gained weight. He knows. Rayban is also my best friend. He was the first one to actually believe I could date Rachel. No one else did until like 2 weeks ago. The Chinaman (or Asian-American for the more PC crowd. Or those who like The Big Lebowski) is also my best friend and has been the one keeping me accountable. He asks my weight like every other day and pushes me to stay strong and reach my goals in a timely manner. Probably my greatest asset in this whole thing The other guy is my twin. He’s been great in this </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#anchises868">
<p>As good as the progress pics are in seeing the changes keto has let you make to your body, I don't think they do near the justice to your transformation that the prom pics do. </p>
<p>You, your date, and the others look happy (for lack of a better word). I can see the effect your transformation has had on your psychology written all over your face, and that's something that progress pics never seem to. </p>
<p>Plus, it helps that you rocked that tux! </p>
<p>You done good, kid. You done good. </p>
</sp>
</text>
