<text id="autogum_voyage_doc105" title="Manitouwadge" shortTile="manitouwadge" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=162767" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Manitouwadge</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.manitouwadge.ca/">Manitouwadge</ref></hi> is a township in <ref target="Northern%20Ontario">Northern Ontario</ref>. It has about 2100 people (2011).</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>"Manidoowaazh" means "Cave of the Great Spirit" in Ojibwe. </p>

<p>While mining was at the forefront of Manitouwadge's economic activity, forestry also plays a significant part in the town's economy. The town is also turning itself into a retirement community, offering some of the lowest housing prices in the country.</p>

<head>History</head>
<p>Manitouwadge (Manidoowaazh in Ojibwe, meaning "Cave of the Great Spirit") was part of the range of the nomadic Ojibwe indigenous people. </p>

<p>The town was founded by Noranda (now part of Xstrata) in the early 1950s to support the company's Geco copper mine. Other mine in Manitouwadge is the Willroy mine, named after two of the "Weekend Prospectors", William Dawidowich and Roy Barker.</p>

<p>In the early 1980s, gold was discovered at Hemlo, near the intersection of highways 614 and 17, about 50 km (31 mi) south of the town. Noranda acquired the mining rights to a significant portion of the ground in that area, and built the Golden Giant Mine. It offered housing in Manitouwadge to many of the employees of the new mine, and the town boomed.</p>

<p>When the Geco mine closed in 1995, Manitouwadge's population decreased significantly. After peaking at nearly 4000 people in the early 1990s, it decreased to less than 3000 by 2001. With the closing of the Golden Giant Mine in 2006, the population dropped to 2,100 by 2011.</p>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Manitouwadge Airport</hi> ( YMG ), 1 Mississauga Drive, ☏ +1 807-826-4041 . No scheduled traffic. </item>
</list>


<head>By car</head>
<p>Manitouwadge is at the north end of Highway 614, 331 km (206 mi) east of Thunder Bay and 378 km (235 mi) north-west of Sault Ste. Marie.</p>

<p>From Highway 17 (east of <ref target="Marathon%20%28Ontario%29">Marathon</ref>, west of <ref target="White%20River%20%28Ontario%29">White River</ref>), take Highway 614 north.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bob's Taxi &amp; Delivery Service,</hi>, +1 807 826-1420</item>
</list>


<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Eco-tourism is promoted here; there are at least four small waterfalls in the immediate area.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>
<p>Hunting, fishing and golf are the main summer attractions open to vacationers and residents. There is a nine-hole golf course. There is a fully equipped gym, a large outside track, and a family pool.</p>

<p>Trails for hiking in the summer and trails for snowmobilers in the winter are also abundant. There are ten runs for downhill skiing and two locations with cross-country ski trails managed by the Northern Trails Ski Club. From the top of the ski hill, you can see the whole town. Whether or not you want to is up to you.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">High Falls of the Pic River</hi>, Lemay Road. 30-m-high falls. Hike may be steep for those with mobilty difficulties. From Manitouwadge, drive about 60 km on the Industrial Road, a crushed gravel road, then leave the main road and get on a rough two-track and go a further 5.4 km to the falls - a 4WD is required for this part. Take the first left, and then keep to the left. There is a sign at the first branch directing you towards High Falls.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Perry Lake Trail</hi>.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Friends Bakery &amp; Coffee Shop</hi>, 200 Manitou Rd W, ☏ +1 807 826-1376 . M-F 5AM-10PM, Sa Su 6AM-10PM. Cafe and bakery with sandwiches, lunches.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Village Pizza &amp; Subs</hi>, 26 Huron Walk, ☏ +1 807 826-2626 . M-F 10AM-7PM, Sa-Su 9AM-6PM.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Audrey's Restaurant</hi>, 56 Huron Walk, ☏ +1 807 826-2891 . M-Sa 9AM-8PM, Su 9AM-2PM. Pizzas, vegetarian dishes, pierogies...</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">KG's Bar &amp; Lounge</hi>, 6 Mississauga Dr, ☏ +1 807 826-4554 . Bar with pool tables and patio.</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Select Inn</hi>, 43 Manitou Rd East, ☏ +1 807 826-4949 . Free continental breakfast, a fitness room and Wi-Fi. Rooms feature a microwave, a coffee maker, iron and mini fridge. From $95.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Turner's Northwoods Adventures</hi>, 371 Manitou Road, ☏ +1 807 826-1224 , toll-free: +1 866-417-8687 , ✉ turnersnorthwoods@gmail.com . Offers rooms, RV hookups, and camping.</item>
</list>
</text>
