<text id="autogum_academic_doc479" title="Nexus between Air Pollution and Neonatal Deaths: A Case of Asian Countries" shortTile="nexus-between-air" author="Asim Anwar, Muhammad Ayub, Noman Khan, Antoine Flahault" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4148/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Data and Methodology</head><head> Empirical Model</head>
<p>
The study has employed a similar empirical model as the one that studied the association between climate change and infectious diseases. The present study has extended the framework by associating climate change, air pollution (PM2.5), and socio-economic variables causing neonates deaths due to acute respiratory infection. This study has used panel data of 12 Asian countries from 2000 to 2017. The empirical model is mentioned below:

(1)

where <hi rend="italic">M</hi> denotes the number of neonates deaths due to acute respiratory infection, <hi rend="italic">CV</hi> signifies the climate variables (application of mean temperature as a proxy for <hi rend="italic">CV</hi>) and air pollution (PM2.5), while <hi rend="italic">D</hi> signifies socio-economic variables, i.e., income, education, and population density. The socio-economic determinants have been added in the model to check the rationality of the results. We describe the climate variables (air pollution and temperature) as non-linear. The objective behind introducing the climate variables in quadratic form is to determine the number of neonatal deaths caused by respiratory disease patients as non-linear in climate variables or otherwise. The study has estimated a static model where the current number of neonates’ deaths is not dependent upon the previous year number of deaths. The motive behind using the static model is that the data available are annual. Thus, the static model is expressed as:

(2)

The study employs the panel dataset method to evaluate the effects of air pollution (PM2.5) and climate change (temperature) on the neonate deaths due to acute respiratory infection. It is important to state here that the present data structure does not permit to analyze the random effects. According to, the fixed-effect model is a suitable specification if the analysis is focused on a given number (N) of units so that statistical inference is conditional on the particular set of (N) unities, which in our case, are 12 countries highly vulnerable to climate change (N = 12). On the other hand, random-effect models require the assumption of uncorrelated explanatory variables and a time-invariant unobservable component of the model, which is assumed to be random (for example,). In other words, the random effect model would require that units were selected randomly from a large number of possibilities, as is the case when the units are individuals or households. The static model is elaborated below as:

(3)

The study uses a panel dataset where each variable in Equation (3) refers to country <hi rend="italic">i</hi> at time <hi rend="italic">t</hi>, while <hi rend="italic">D</hi><hi rend="italic">it</hi> in Equation (2) denotes socio-economic factors (Gross Domestic Product (GDP) as a measure of income, education level, and population density), PM2.5 refers to air pollution (mean annual exposure (micrograms per cubic meter)), <hi rend="italic">temp</hi><hi rend="italic">it</hi> is used as a proxy for climate change, and ε<hi rend="italic">it</hi> is the error term. The study measures the neonatal deaths due to acute respiratory infections per 1000 inhabitants as the dependent variable with reference to retrieved data from United Nation International Emergency Fund (UNICEF) database. The data for other variables, like temperature (yearly average of monthly mean temperature of respective countries), GDP per capita (as a proxy for national income), secondary school enrollment (as a proxy for national educational level), and population density (people per sq. km of land area) are retrieved from the World Bank dataset. </p>
</text>
