<text id="autogum_news_doc039" title="International Paralympic Committee holds first press conference" shortTile="international-paralympic" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-08-27" dateModified="2016-08-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/International_Paralympic_Committee_holds_first_press_conference" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>International Paralympic Committee holds first press conference</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, August 28, 2012</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/London">London</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/England">England</ref> — Yesterday, the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/International_Paralympic_Committee">International Paralympic Committee</ref> (IPC) held their first formal press conference as part of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2012_Summer_Paralympics">2012 Summer Paralympics</ref>.  Approximately 60 media representatives attended and had the opportunity to ask questions of Craig Spence, IPC President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Philip_Craven">Philip Craven</ref>, Chairman of the London Organizing Committee of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Olympics">Olympic</ref> and Paralymic Games (LOCOG) <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sebastian%20Coe">Sebastian Coe</ref>, and LOCOG Director of Communications and Public Affairs Jackie Brock-Doyle following a short speech on the history of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Paralympics">Paralympic Games</ref>.</p>
<p>The reporters asked a variety of questions. A <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UK">British</ref> journalist asked about having ATOS as a sponsor given the negative history the business has had with disability services in the country. The IPC responded by saying this is an issue that should be taken up by the relevant British government agency.  </p>
<p>A <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> reporter asked if the high cost of technology for participating in disability sport at the elite level would leave <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Oceania">Oceania</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Asia">Asia</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Africa">Africa</ref> behind. Craven said historically, the IPC has worked on increasing disability sport participation; they were now working on changing that to developing disability sport around the world.  He highlighted efforts by the IPC to bring down the cost of wheelchairs and prostheses as these are sporting equipment for participation in disability sport. He also said they had donated 4,000 wheelchairs to help spread disability sport.</p>
<p>A <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada">Canadian</ref> journalist from the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vancouver%20Sun">Vancouver Sun</ref></hi> asked about the lack of substantial coverage of the Games in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/North_America">North America</ref>. Craven responded by saying he was disappointed by <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> coverage and the IPC has been aware of the problem for years. He contrasted the situation in the United States with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">France</ref>, where the public successfully put pressure on the rights-holding network to improve the coverage of the Games.</p>
<p>Another reporter asked about Paralympic social media usage during the Games.  Craven responded that while not a big user of it himself, the IPC embraced social media. Spence said the IPC encouraged everyone involved to use it; 47 Paralympians have video blogs, and the Opening Ceremonies will be covered while they happen.</p>
<figure><caption>Craig Spence at the International Paralympic Committee press conference Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Laura_Hale">Laura Hale</ref>.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>Sir Philip Craven at the International Paralympic Committee press conference Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Laura_Hale">Laura Hale</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>Sebastian Coe at the International Paralympic Committee press conference Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Laura_Hale">Laura Hale</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>Jackie Brock-Doyle at the International Paralympic Committee press conference Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Laura_Hale">Laura Hale</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>International Paralympic Committee holds first press conference with roughly 60 journalists in attendance Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Laura_Hale">Laura Hale</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>International Paralympic Committee holds first press conference with roughly 60 journalists in attendance Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Laura_Hale">Laura Hale</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>International Paralympic Committee holds first press conference with roughly 60 journalists in attendance Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Laura_Hale">Laura Hale</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>International Paralympic Committee holds first press conference with roughly 60 journalists in attendance Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Laura_Hale">Laura Hale</ref>.</caption></figure>
</text>
