<text id="autogum_interview_doc054" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Steve Burke, U.S. Democratic Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-12-11" dateModified="2019-08-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Steve_Burke%2C_U.S._Democratic_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">So far you have filed to run in the New Hampshire primary.  Do you plan on filing for any other primaries?</hi></item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">SB</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Yes we are working in other states to be known and have signed up for Louisiana. Money is always a problem in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/grassroots">grassroots</ref> campaign.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What do you hope to accomplish with this campaign?</hi></item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">SB</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  That a voice be heard that is different than what is there now. The same old, same old get you the same old with no chance of bringing the county back home to where we have full employment, everyone getting along, pulling together regardless of color, race or religion.  We are Americans all, living on a small rock just hanging out in space.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What are your thoughts on the job <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref> has done as president? Specifically, what would you have done differently?</hi></item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">SB</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I will not slam an other Democrat who is doing what he feels is correct. I would do things differently for sure.
<p><p>A.  I believe in making friends not enemies.</p>
<p>B.  No sanctions, I consider them an act of war.</p>
<p>C.  Trade with every[one] on the planet. It is good for [us] and the products we have to sell — jobs.</p>
<p>D.  Healthcare needs to be tweaked; move it in line with the health plan the congress has and a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Single-payer%20healthcare">single payer</ref>.</p></p></p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">In your opinion, what are the most important issues facing America and how will you deal with these as president?</hi></item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">SB</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Make friends. You see how <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China">China</ref> is doing it by helping all around the world along with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Russia">Russia</ref>. War and the blood of our young and our treasury is causing us to be bled to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/third%20world">third world</ref> status. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Islamic%20fundamentalism">Radical Islam</ref> — work with a coalition of nations with the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Nations">United Nations</ref> and root out that nest of vipers once and for all. Rebuild those countries devastated by war as was done after <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/World_War_II">World War II</ref>.</p>
<figure><caption>Martin Luther King, Jr. delivers his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/I%20Have%20a%20Dream">I Have a Dream</ref> speech. Image: National Archives and Records Administration.</caption></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">If elected, what would constitute a successful presidency for you?</hi></item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">SB</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Make friends around the world, fair trade, full employment here at home. New plants opening up.  I have a plan for that. Where we finally answer Reverend <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin%20Luther%20King,%20Jr.">Martin Luther [King, Jr.]</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/I%20Have%20a%20Dream">I Have a Dream</ref>.</p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What exactly is the plan?</hi></item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">SB</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  We have a precedent set with the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/General_Motors">General Motors</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/General%20Motors%20Chapter%2011%20reorganization">bailout</ref>. All the closed factory and manufacturing buildings around the country need to be used. Let's find the people with skills to open them up and get them running. The government will have a startup fund to lend, so we can be self sufficient again. By closing some of our <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List%20of%20United%20States%20military%20bases">military bases</ref> around the world that money can be used in this country and the military brought home to help secure our borders. Remember we are bleeding money and must stop it or we are done. One of the best things I feel for all our young is to have a military draft for a two year period of their lives. It teaches them order and how to get along and live with people of all colors and religions.  Add a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Civilian%20Conservation%20Corps">CCC</ref> type of organization to that and give them a choice.  Then add a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G.I.%20Bill">GI</ref> type of benefits to that. As a correction officer I saw the hopelessness of prisoners who could not read or write but were smart.  If the government uses its money and talent not just on early intervention but in all grades to help these kids who have trouble in school reading and writing etc. Americans right now feel a sense of no one cares and we are going nowhere. Lack of jobs, money, housing. If you are married William then you know money in marriage is the big problem not sex.  We have people with ideas in this country.  Let's use them to make our country self sufficient again. Let's show the country through leadership that we are moving forward together towards a goal. No more making scapegoats out of each other. Those in office have a hunger for more and more money because they have a need???? Well so do those working or having a business. Let's not tax them to death. We all want to have the good life.  Let's work towards that goal. I see the problems and know there are answers by setting goals, direction and leadership. Sorry if I got off on a rant. But you asked.</p>
</text>
