<text id="autogum_voyage_doc180" title="Hakka phrasebook" shortTile="hakka-phrasebook" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=13891" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Hakka phrasebook</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Hakka</hi> (客家话 Hak-kâ-fa/Hak-kâ-va) originated in China but is also spoken in <ref target="Hong%20Kong">Hong Kong</ref> and <ref target="Taiwan">Taiwan</ref>, and among overseas Chinese, especially in <ref target="Southeast%20Asia">Southeast Asia</ref>. In this article, the Hong Kong dialect of the Hakka language will be used.</p>

<head>Brief overview</head>
<p>The Hakka (客家 Kèjiā, IPA: [hak₃ ka₃₃] ) people migrated South from Northern China over the centuries to settle in southern <ref target="Jiangsu">Jiangsu</ref> and <ref target="Hunan">Hunan</ref>, western <ref target="Fujian">Fujian</ref>, eastern <ref target="Guangdong">Guangdong</ref>, and various other areas, due to wars, famine, natural disasters, and political persecution.</p>

<p>Hakka comes from the words '客' "guest" and '家' "families" which derives from an official term during the Qing Dynasty (1644-1911) for the program of resettlement of the coastal areas of Guangdong after evacuation orders imposed during the reign of Emperor Kangxi. These settlers whose language was different to the original inhabitants were given this appellation to show they were not indigenous to the areas they became settled in. The indigenous inhabitants (<hi rend="italic">punti</hi>) had generally occupied the more fertile basins, so the incoming Hakka often settled in the more inaccessible valleys and mountainous or hilly terrain.</p>

<p>In some areas, the Hakka built <hi rend="italic">tulou</hi> (土楼, tǔlóu), earth and straw round houses. These fascinating, centuries-old buildings are home to a whole clan and are easily defended. The largest groups of <ref target="Fujian%20Tulou">tulou, in Fujian</ref>, are now on the <ref target="UNESCO%20World%20Heritage%20List">UNESCO World Heritage List</ref>. Though less well known internationally, Hakka people in other areas built different types of walled villages such as <hi rend="italic">wei</hi> (围, wéi) and <hi rend="italic">weilongwu</hi> (围龙屋, wéilóngwū).</p>

<p>To a considerable extent, Hakka have their own culture, different from their neighbours. In Neal Stephenson's novel <hi rend="italic">Ream De</hi>, much of which takes place in <ref target="Xiamen">Xiamen</ref>, one character is a Hakka lass from a tea-growing mountain area, and she is sometimes called a "big-foot woman" in reference to the fact that, unlike most other Chinese, the Hakka never adopted the custom of foot-binding. </p>

<p>The Hakka language (客家话; Kèjiāhuà) shares a common vocabulary with Southern languages such as <ref target="Cantonese">Cantonese</ref>, <ref target="Teochew">Teochew</ref> and the many dialects of Fujian, and there are regular sound correspondences to the historical sound system of Middle Chinese. In terms of pronunciation, it has some features in common with <ref target="Cantonese">Cantonese</ref> and some with <ref target="Mandarin">Mandarin</ref>, though it's not mutually intelligible with either dialect.</p>

<head>Pronunciation guide</head>

<p>The most accessible Hakka speakers are found in Hong Kong and Taiwan. Most of them will be dual language speakers, in Hong Kong, they are able to understand and speak Cantonese, whilst on the mainland of China and on Taiwan, they will also speak Mandarin, with those from Guangdong province typically being trilingual in Hakka, Cantonese and Mandarin. There is no standard form of Hakka and regional variations in local dialects can be surmounted by understanding the gist of the spoken sentence and knowing some sound correspondences that the user will encounter. That said, many people consider the dialect spoken in <ref target="Meizhou">Meizhou</ref> to be the prestige dialect of Hakka.</p>

<p>There are some sounds in Hakka which do not occur in English. The following pronunciation guide aims to rhyme English words with the sounds found in the Hakka syllable. Please note they are approximations, you may require a Hakka speaker to guide your pronunciation.</p>

<head>Vowels</head>

<p>The vowels can be long or short. Long vowels occur in open syllables, where there are no endings. Short vowels occur in syllables which end in nasals (-m, -n or -ng) or stops (-p, -t or -k).</p>

<p>In some dialects there is a vowel which we represent as ii, which does not occur in standard English. It is a retroflex i, the closest sound is almost like <hi rend="italic">ir</hi> in "shir" when saying English 'sure'. In the Hong Kong dialect, these sounds become -i or -u.</p>

<head>Tones</head>

<p>The tone changes known as sandhi does occur, but the change in the pitch is not as great as found in other Chinese languages.</p>

<head>Some Sound Correspondences between dialect of the Hakka Language</head>

<p>Apart from tonal differences, there are small variations in pronunciations from place to place. The following details some of the more commonly found differences, which may be helpful to the user when hearing other speakers from different areas.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">h</hi> is sometimes pronounced as <hi rend="bold">s</hi>, especially when there is a vowel -i- in the syllable. E.g. <hi rend="bold">兄</hi> <hi rend="bold">hiung1</hi> may be pronounced <hi rend="bold">siung1</hi>.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">au</hi> is sometimes pronounced as <hi rend="bold">o</hi>. E.g. 好 <hi rend="bold">hau3</hi> / <hi rend="bold">ho3</hi></p>

<p><hi rend="bold">ai</hi> is sometimes pronounced as <hi rend="bold">e</hi> E.g. 雞 <hi rend="bold">gai1</hi> / <hi rend="bold">ge1</hi></p>

<p>Some Hakka dialects has the -u- medial, so you may hear words like 光 <hi rend="bold">gong1</hi> pronounced as <hi rend="bold">guong1</hi> (gwong1).</p>

<head>Basics</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Hello. : . (<hi rend="italic"> </hi>)</item>
<item> Hello. (<hi rend="italic">informal</hi>) : . (<hi rend="italic"> </hi>)</item>
<item> How are you? : ? (<hi rend="italic"> ?</hi>)</item>
<item> Fine, thank you. : . (<hi rend="italic">Simungi </hi>)</item>
<item> What is your name? : ? (<hi rend="italic"> ?</hi>)</item>
<item> My name is ______ . : ______ . (<hi rend="italic"> _____ .</hi>)</item>
<item> Nice to meet you. : . (<hi rend="italic"> </hi>)</item>
<item> Please. : . (<hi rend="italic"> </hi>)</item>
<item> Thank you. : . (<hi rend="italic"> </hi>)</item>
<item> You're welcome. : . (<hi rend="italic"> </hi>)</item>
<item> Yes. : . (<hi rend="italic"> </hi>)</item>
<item> No. : . (<hi rend="italic"> </hi>)</item>
<item> Excuse me. (<hi rend="italic">getting attention</hi>) : . (<hi rend="italic"> </hi>)</item>
<item> Excuse me. (<hi rend="italic">begging pardon</hi>) : . (<hi rend="italic"> </hi>)</item>
<item> I'm sorry. : . (<hi rend="italic"> </hi>)</item>
<item> Goodbye : . (<hi rend="italic"> </hi>)</item>
<item> Goodbye (<hi rend="italic">informal</hi>) : . (<hi rend="italic"> </hi>)</item>
<item> I can't speak <hi rend="italic">name of language</hi> [well]. : [ ]. (<hi rend="italic"> [ ]</hi>)</item>
<item> Do you speak English? : ? (<hi rend="italic"> ?</hi>)</item>
<item> Is there someone here who speaks English? : ? (<hi rend="italic"> ?</hi>)</item>
<item> Help! : ! (<hi rend="italic"> !</hi>)</item>
<item> Look out! : ! (<hi rend="italic"> !</hi>)</item>
<item> Good morning. : . (<hi rend="italic"> </hi>)</item>
<item> Good evening. : . (<hi rend="italic"> </hi>)</item>
<item> Good night. : . (<hi rend="italic"> </hi>)</item>
<item> Good night (<hi rend="italic">to sleep</hi>) : . (<hi rend="italic"> </hi>)</item>
<item> I don't understand. : . (<hi rend="italic"> </hi>)</item>
<item> Where is the toilet? : ? (<hi rend="italic"> ?</hi>)</item>
</list>


<head>Problems</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Leave me alone. : . (<hi rend="italic"> .</hi>)</item>
<item> Don't touch me! : ! (<hi rend="italic"> !</hi>)</item>
<item> I'll call the police. : . (<hi rend="italic"> .</hi>)</item>
<item> Police! : ! (<hi rend="italic"> !</hi>)</item>
<item> Stop! Thief! : ! ! (<hi rend="italic"> ! !</hi>)</item>
<item> I need your help. : . (<hi rend="italic"> .</hi>)</item>
<item> It's an emergency. : . (<hi rend="italic"> .</hi>)</item>
<item> I'm lost. : . (<hi rend="italic"> .</hi>)</item>
<item> I lost my bag. : . (<hi rend="italic"> .</hi>)</item>
<item> I lost my wallet. : . (<hi rend="italic"> .</hi>)</item>
<item> I'm sick. : . (<hi rend="italic"> .</hi>)</item>
<item> I've been injured. : . (<hi rend="italic"> .</hi>)</item>
<item> I need a doctor. : . (<hi rend="italic"> .</hi>)</item>
<item> Can I use your phone? : ? (<hi rend="italic"> ?</hi>)</item>
</list>
</text>
