<text id="autogum_news_doc033" title="2013 IPC Alpine Skiing World Championships preparations underway" shortTile="-ipc-alpine-skiing" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-02-13" dateModified="2019-08-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2013_IPC_Alpine_Skiing_World_Championships_preparations_underway" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>2013 IPC Alpine Skiing World Championships preparations underway</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, February 16, 2013</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Ramon Moliner, Ivan Tibau, Mariona Masdemont and Enric Ticó at Tuesday's flag exchange Image: <ref target="http://www.lamolina2013.cat">IPC Alpine Skiing World Championships La Molina 2013</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>Preparations are underway ahead of the 2013 IPC <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Para-alpine_skiing">Alpine Skiing</ref> World Championship, with a flag exchange taking place Tuesday, volunteer recruitment ongoing, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Paralympic%20Committee">USParalympics</ref> unveiling a new uniform for their team, skiers like the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref>'s Jon Lujan actively training for the event and other skiers competing in preparation for the Championships in a World Cup event Wednesday.</p>
<p>Tuesday in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/La_Molina_(ski_resort)">La Molina</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Spain">Spain</ref>, the president of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ferrocarrils%20de%20la%20Generalitat%20de%20Catalunya">Governmental Railways of Catalonia</ref>, Enric Ticó, and the mayor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alp,%20Spain">Alp</ref>, Ramon Moliner, were gifted with flags by representatives of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/International_Paralympic_Committee">International Paralympic Committee</ref> (IPC) and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Generalitat%20of%20Catalonia">Catalan Government</ref> at a ceremony in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Museum%20and%20Study%20Center%20of%20Sport%20Doctor%20Melcior%20Colet">Colet Museum of Barcelona</ref> at one of the first official events ahead of the 2013 IPC Alpine Skiing World Championship, which starts next week. As of Wednesday, event organisers were still seeking volunteers to assist with running the Championship. The opening ceremonies are scheduled for next Tuesday.</p>
<p>Entering the event, skiers had the opportunity to qualify through eight <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IPC%20Alpine%20Skiing%20World%20Cup">World Cup</ref> events held with only two disciplines on the program, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giant%20Slalom">Giant Slalom</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slalom%20skiing">Slalom</ref>. The first four were held in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sestriere">Sestriere</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Italy">Italy</ref>, with the most recent four all being held in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St.%20Moritz">St. Moritz</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Switzerland">Switzerland</ref>. Standing female <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">French</ref> skier Marie Bochet has won six World Cups ahead of the World Championships and is considered by event organizers as a favorite in the standing group. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Russia">Russian</ref> standing skier Alexey Bugaev is also considered a favorite by organisers as he won two Slalom and one Giant Slalom World Cup competition.  In the women's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/sit-ski">sit-ski</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">German</ref> Anna Schaffelhuber is considered the favorite having prepared for the Championships by winning five of the eight World Cup events.  On the men's sit-ski side, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Japan">Japanese</ref> Takeshi Suzuki and Swiss Christoph Kunz both earned three World Cup victories in the lead up to this competition.  In the women's visually impaired group, Slovak Henrieta Farkasova will enter the competition with five World Cup victories.  On the men's side, Spanish <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jon_Santacana_Maiztegui">Jon Santacana</ref> is favored to win with three Giant Slalom and one Slalom victory during this year's World Cup events in the lead up to the World Championships.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UK">British</ref> Combined Services Disabled Ski Team coach Mark Scorgie has noted that this year's European ski season has been problematic with weather interfering with most competitions.  Poor weather conditions continued Wednesday Rogla IPC Alpine World Cup, with the first Giant Slalom run canceled because of high winds.</p>
<p>The World Championships includes over 270 skiers, guides, coaches and support personnel from 28 countries including Spain, France, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia">Australia</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ukraine">Ukraine</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Netherlands">Netherlands</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Croatia">Croatia</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Finland">Finland</ref>, Switzerland, Japan, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/South_Korea">Korea</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mexico">Mexico</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Turkey">Turkey</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Belgium">Belgium</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Norway">Norway</ref>, Russia, Britain, Germany, Italy, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada">Canada</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Slovakia">Slovakia</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Czech_Republic">Czech Republic</ref>, United States, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Austria">Austria</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_Zealand">New Zealand</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sweden">Sweden</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hungary">Hungary</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/South_Africa">South Africa</ref>..</p>
<p>The Spanish team includes blind skier Jon Santacana and his guide <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miguel%20Galindo%20Garces">Miguel Galindo</ref>, and blind skier <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gabriel%20Gorce">Gabriel Gorce</ref> and his guide <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arnau%20Ferrer">Arnau Ferrer</ref>.  Both vision-impaired skiers are scheduled to compete in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Downhill%20skiing">Downhill</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Super%20G">Super G</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Super%20Combined">Super Combined</ref>, Giant Slalom, and Slalom competitions.  Also on the Spanish team are <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LW2%20(classification)">LW2 classified</ref> standing skier Úrsula Pueyo, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LW12%20(classification)">LW12-1 classified</ref> sit skier <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Óscar%20Espallargas">Óscar Espallargas</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LW10%20(classification)">LW10-1 classified</ref> sit skier Nathalie Carpanedo who qualified as a wildcard entry. Pueyo, Espallargas, and Carpanedo are all scheduled to compete in the Slalom and Giant Slalom competitions. Accompanying the team are to be coaches Javier Gutierrez, Jordi Carbonell, and Andres Gomez, medical staff including Pablo Marquez and Josep Barrachina, and technical staffer Josep Bort.</p>
<figure><caption>Jones competing in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Super%20giant%20slalom%20skiing">Super G</ref> at the last year's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IPC%20Alpine%20Skiing%20World%20Cup">IPC</ref> Nor-Am Cup Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Bidgee">Bidgee</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>The United States team consists of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Seattle">Seattle</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Washington">Washington</ref>-based vision-impaired skier Mark Bathum and his <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Colorado_Springs,_Colorado">Colorado Springs</ref>-based guide Jessica Smith; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Park%20City,%20Utah">Park City</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Utah">Utah</ref>-based vision-impaired skier <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Danelle%20Umstead">Danelle Umstead</ref> and guide Rob Umstead; retired <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/US%20Army">Army</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clarksville,%20Tennessee">Clarksville</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tennessee">Tennessee</ref>-based <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heath%20Calhoun">Heath Calhoun</ref>; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brooklyn,%20New%20York">Brooklyn</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York">New York</ref>-based Ralph Green; Colorado Springs-based <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allison%20Jones%20(skier)">Allison Jones</ref>; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palmer,%20Alaska">Palmer</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Alaska">Alaska</ref>-based Andrew Kurka; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burlington,%20Vermont">Burlington</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Vermont">Vermont</ref>-based Stephen Lawler; retired <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/US%20Marines">Marine</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Littleton,%20Colorado">Littleton</ref>, Colorado-based Jon Lujan; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Farmington,%20New%20Mexico">Farmington</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_Mexico">New Mexico</ref>-based <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alana%20Nichols">Alana Nichols</ref>; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wenham,%20Massachusetts">Wenham</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Massachusetts">Massachusetts</ref>-based Laurie Stephens; Park City, Utah-based Stephani Victor; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franconia,%20New%20Hampshire">Franconia</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_Hampshire">New Hampshire</ref>-based Tyler Walker; and retired <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/US%20Coast%20Guard">Coast Guard</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Campton,%20New%20Hampshire">Campton</ref>, New Hampshire-based <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chris%20Devlin-Young">Chris Devlin-Young</ref>.</p>
</text>
