<text id="autogum_interview_doc375" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Australian Statistician Brian Pink" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-19" dateModified="2008-04-30" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_Statistician_Brian_Pink" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="eCensus">eCensus</head>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : I thought that we might look at some of the things that actually happened during the past year, firstly just things that have happened with the Bureau, and probably one of the biggest things that happened last year was the release of 2006 Census data. That was the first eCensus?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BP</hi>: It was, yes.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : And I read that about 10% of households used it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BP</hi>: Yes, just a little under 10%. It was the first time, both in Australia and New Zealand that the national Census has included the ability for people to respond electronically. We didn't push it too strongly, because there are a lot of challenges in moving to an eCensus and running it as complementary to the traditional pen-and-paper census, and I think both Australia and New Zealand - New Zealand was about 7% and Australia was between 9 and 10% - were very pleased with the level of response, and the level of feedback from the community here in Australia was that those that completed their census forms online thought that it was a very positive experience, and so I think we've positioned ourselves well for 2011 to try and encourage and be perhaps a little more on the front foot of encouraging more Australians to complete the census online rather than the traditional pen-and-paper, but it'll only be after the event that we'll know how successful we've been.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Did you see any significant differences between how people responded between the paper and the electronic census forms?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BP</hi>: I'm told that the quality of the responses in the electronic census were slightly higher than with pen-and-paper, and it's possible - it's very difficult to know, but it's possible that the sequencing, which is one of the things that people found attractive in the electronic instrument, so that, you know, you were taken straight from the last question to the next relevant question that you needed to answer. I think that may have had a little bit of an impact on the quality because people felt they've moved through the questionnaire more quickly.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Are there any other innovations in the works for the 2011 census, or is it still fairly nebulous?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BP</hi>: No, I think the 2011 census, as I said, will have a traditional pen-and-paper and obviously an electronic lodgement option as well, I think 2011 will be very much a repeat of what we've done in 2006, but we may see a bigger proportion of the responses moving from pen-and-paper to electronic.</p>
<head id="ABS_Year_Books">ABS Year Books</head>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : The other thing that's happened in the past year is the release of the 2008 Year Book, and in fact the release of all the Year Books from 1908 to 2008 on the ABS web site.</p>
</text>
