<text id="autogum_interview_doc869" title="part9_Wikinews interviews World Wide Web co-inventor Robert Cailliau" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-07-22" dateModified="2014-09-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_World_Wide_Web_co-inventor_Robert_Cailliau" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi>: What part or period of the history of the World Wide Web did you enjoy most? Which were the most exciting times?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Robert Cailliau</hi>: Enjoy?  Only afterwards, except the first conference.  There was a euphoric atmosphere that I have seldom experienced.  And because I started it myself, it was extremely satisfying.</p>
<p>The most exciting period was from end 1991 to end 1994.  It was the early period where we sensed very clearly where we wanted to go but had to instill that vision in others.
It lasted until the end of WWW at CERN in December 1994.  I cannot relate the whole story here, it is told in detail in the book "How the Web was Born".</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi>: If you could go back into time and change one thing about the start of the WWW, what would it be?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Robert Cailliau</hi>: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isambard%20Kingdom%20Brunel">Isambard Kingdom Brunel</ref>, one of the greatest engineers of all times, wrote in 1844 at the height of the railway mania:</p>
Here the whole world is railway mad.  I am really sick of hearing proposals made. I wish it were at an end. I prefer engineering very much to projecting, of which I keep as clear as I can...
<p>The dreadful scramble in which I am obliged to get through my business is by no means a good sample of the way in which work ought to be done...  I wish I could suggest a plan that would greatly diminish the number of projects; it would suit my interests and those of my clients perfectly if all railway work were stopped for several years to come.</p>
<p>I thought often of that reflection:  we advanced far too fast with far too many developers who ran away in far too many different directions without much thinking.
I don't want to be Cartesian here, but it would have been better if we had more time to build on our ideas before letting the beast loose.</p>
<hi rend="bold">We advanced far too fast with far too many developers who ran away in far too many different directions without much thinking. ... Especially the geeks in the U.S. often behaved like cowboys: shoot first, think later.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Robert Cailliau</p>
<p>Especially the geeks in the U.S. often behaved like cowboys:  shoot first, think later.  Features were implemented that looked attractive on first sight but turned out to be incompatible with other ones.  For example the famous frames, that we still have not got rid of.
People failed to understand the advantage of separating content from presentation, which we had on the NeXT in some sense.  Especially graphic artists refused this and that put us back by about five years.</p>
<p>If a careful study were made it might well show that we lost much more time and effort managing excesses than we would have spent in a more considerate and paced development.
I often had the impression I was running like mad to escape from drowning in a tsunami.</p>
</text>
