<text id="autogum_whow_doc099" title="Unbrick the HTC One X" shortTile="unbrick-htc-one-x" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-06-14" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Unbrick-the-HTC-One-X" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Unbrick the HTC One X</head><p>When your HTC One X becomes bricked, you may experience force-close errors, freezing issues, and problems with powering your device off and on. If you’ve managed to brick your HTC One X, you can unbrick your device by either performing a hard reset, or by reversing the effects of any new updates that caused your device to brick in the first place.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Performing a Hard Reset</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Verify that your HTC One X is fully charged. A full charge will help ensure that your device will not power down at any point during the reset process and cause further complications.</item>
<item>Back up all personal data, if possible. A hard reset will wipe and erase all data from the memory of your device.
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Back_Up_an_Android_Phone_on_the_Google_Cloud">Sync your personal information with Google’s servers</ref>, or connect your HTC One X to your computer using a USB cable so you can transfer personal data to your computer.</item></list></item>
<item>Tap on “Settings,” then tap on “Power.<hi rend="bold">”</hi>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are unable to access the menu on your device due to software problems associated with bricking, skip ahead to step #5.</item></list></item>
<item>Remove the checkmark next to “Fast Boot.<hi rend="bold">”</hi></item>
<item>Power off your device.</item>
<item>Press and hold the Volume Down key, then press and hold the Power button.</item>
<item>Continue pressing both keys until the device powers on.</item>
<item>Release the Power button. The Bootloader options menu will display on-screen.</item>
<item>Use the volume keys to navigate to and highlight “Factory Reset.<hi rend="bold">”</hi></item>
<item>Press the Power button to make your selection. Your HTC One X will reset, restore the original factory settings, and will be un-bricked.</item></list>
<head>Reversing New Updates</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Power off your device.</item>
<item>Press and hold the Volume Down key, then press and hold the Power button.</item>
<item>Continue pressing both keys until the device powers on.</item>
<item>Release the Power button. The Bootloader options menu will display on-screen.</item>
<item>Use the volume keys to navigate to and highlight “Recovery Mode.<hi rend="bold">”</hi></item>
<item>Press the Power button to make your selection. Your HTC One X will boot into recovery mode.</item>
<item>Use the volume keys to highlight “wipe data factory reset,” then press the Power button.</item>
<item>Navigate to and highlight “wipe cache partition,” then press the Power button.</item>
<item>Press the back button, then select “advanced.<hi rend="bold">”</hi></item>
<item>Scroll to and select “wipe dalvick cache.<hi rend="bold">”</hi></item>
<item>Press the back button until you return to the recovery mode menu.</item>
<item>Scroll to and select “reboot system now.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> Your HTC One X will reboot, and any recent updates you applied to your device will now be removed.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If your HTC One X became bricked after applying new updates, follow the steps outlined in method two prior to performing a hard reset as outlined in method one. In some cases, reversing new updates can unbrick your device.</item>
<item>Attempt to unbrick your device before taking your HTC One X to a repair shop or contacting the manufacturer for repairs. If your device became bricked as a result of rooting, your warranty will be voided with the manufacturer, and you may have to pay out of pocket for repairs.</item></list>
</text>
