<text id="autogum_interview_doc862" title="part2_Wikinews interviews World Wide Web co-inventor Robert Cailliau" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-07-22" dateModified="2014-09-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_World_Wide_Web_co-inventor_Robert_Cailliau" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Something I do miss are the "next-previous" functions of the NeXT browser.  Current browsers only permit you to follow a link and then to run back and forth over the path you took ("back" and "forward").  The NeXT browser had the additional function of following the next link of the previous page ("next").  That allowed me to make a page which was a list of pages to be looked at and then to walk that "path" with a click per page.  It was a simple way to establish a path and save it, totally independently from the target pages and the servers.  A kind of "digest".</p>
<p>I know, it's possible to do this with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Javascript">Javascript</ref>, but it is not easy and you can't pass such a page in a simple way to just anyone.</p>
<p>We also had <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/vector%20graphics">vector graphics</ref>.  I'm afraid that SVG has failed, at least I do not see any sites that use it extensively.</p>
<p>Style sheets were also incorporated, not very advanced, but the idea was there.  CSS did break through.</p>
<p>Today I use mainly <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Safari%20(web%20browser)">Safari</ref> because it uses CSS best and above all for the typography.  Even <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mozilla%20Firefox">Firefox</ref> can learn from Safari's typography.  Why is it that so few programs handle text well?  Why is typography so lousy on the screen?</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tabbed%20browsing">Tabbed browsing</ref> is a concession to those who can't cope with a multitude of separate windows.  Don't really need it.  The first browsers always opened a linked page in a new window.  But Windows does not use windows:  it prefers full-screen.  Mosaic was one of the first browsers that used a single window.  Why do it simple when it's possible to complicate things?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi>: Search engines have made the mass of data now on the WWW easily searchable. How initially did you foresee the data being indexed?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Robert Cailliau</hi>: Not at all! Or by hand. We had the "Virtual Library" or VL, the idea of indexing and classifying pages about a subject by voluntary work of a specialist in that subject.  A kind of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikipedia">Wikipedia</ref>, but with only the links:  the content was distributed outside the VL.  The VL had a certain success, but demanded a lot of work.  The appearance of search engines made the VL unimportant. </p>
<p>The web broke up into servers.  The original "atom" of the web was the page, now it is the server.  Servers link very rarely to other servers and then almost always warn you: "You will now leave our site!".  In that kind of structure you need a search engine otherwise you can't find anything.  But search engines do not let you find your way in the web:  they give you a reference, not a path to follow to get there.</p>
</text>
