<text id="autogum_interview_doc324" title="part11_John Reed on Orwell, God, self-destruction and the future of writing" shortTile="partjohn-reed-orwell" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-18" dateModified="2015-01-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Reed_on_Orwell%2C_God%2C_self-destruction_and_the_future_of_writing" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It's an odd concept.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  I don't really think of myself as a born-again, and they of course insist on later baptism.  I don't know.  I'm sort of currently leaning towards the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baptist%20church">Baptist church</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Southern%20Baptist">Southern Baptist</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Maybe.  I have a lot of Southern--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  They're one of the least intolerant.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Well, that's interesting.  I don't know; I haven't decided--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I went through a Southern Baptist phase when I lived in Georgia.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Oh, did you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Yeah, yeah.  The Southern Baptist convention is probably the most conservative out there.</hi></p>
<head id="On_politics">On politics</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  If you were forced to choose, which war would you prefer to fight in, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraq%20War">Iraq</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Afghanistan%20War">Afghanistan</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Which one would I rather fight in?  Well, for whom?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  On the side of the United States.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Iraq or Afghanistan...God, that's tough man.  I think Afghanistan.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Afghanistan?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Well, at least we had an endgame.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hillary%20Clinton">Hillary</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  I think Hillary.  My reasoning is completely ridiculous: I distrust men who are that skinny.  You and I are both lean, but if I told you, you've got to go take this stump out to the backyard, and I gave you an axe, I'd be pretty confident you could do it.  Obama doesn't look like he could do it to me.  [both laugh]  There's something about that I mistrust.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  If you remain that lean on the campaign trail, when they're having all those--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  There's something about it I distrust, a guy who can't lift a hammer.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  [<hi rend="italic">laughs</hi>]</hi></p>
<head id="On_self-destruction_and_survival">On self-destruction and survival</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How would you choose to die?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  How would I choose to die?  I don't know.  Most men stop being afraid of dying.  Then, when they have kids, suddenly they're afraid of it again.  But not for themselves, for their kids.  So I don't really care, just as long as my kids are provided for.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You think that most men, pre-parenthood, lose their sense of mortality and their fear of it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  I think you just get tired of being afraid of it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Were you ever afraid of it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Yeah, I was afraid of it in my early twenties; and as a kid, I just remember being really, really afraid of dying, and it being incomprehensible and depressing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: Did that affect your behavior?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Well, my daughter, too.  We had a lizard die, and that was a big deal.  She was asking these questions, "Is it gonna be another lizard?"  You know, she has all of these--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  "Where does it go?"</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Yeah, she has a lot of really valid questions.  I don't know; I also don't feel that we understand everything.  For all the people who praise Shakespeare, Shakespeare is still really quite extraordinary.  The sense that I have of Shakespeare is he does understand that on some level, we as human beings, our bodies, are like the top of an iceberg that you can see.  Then there's all this other stuff under the water that you can't see.  That's my feeling about it.  I'm not that afraid of it anymore because I feel like there's all this other stuff under the water.  But it does worry me--</p>
</text>
