<text id="autogum_bio_doc079" title="Stephen G. Weber" shortTile="stephen-g-weber" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-07-12" dateModified="2019-09-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen_G._Weber" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Stephen G. Weber</head>Not to be confused with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steven_Weber_(professor)">Steven Weber (professor)</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Stephen G. Weber</hi> is a professor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chemistry">chemistry</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Translational_medicine">clinical translational science</ref> at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Pittsburgh">University of Pittsburgh</ref>. He researches analytical separations theory and its application, and has developed "green" techniques for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Molecular_recognition">molecular recognition</ref> and microextractions. He is particularly interested in the identification of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peptides">peptides</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dipeptides">dipeptides</ref>, and their effects on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neurochemistry">neurochemistry</ref>. He has received a number of awards, including the 2016 Dal Nogare Award for "contributions to the fundamental understanding of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chromatography">chromatographic process</ref>".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-LCGC-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Education</head>
<p>Weber attended <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Case_Western_Reserve_University">Case Western Reserve University</ref>, receiving his BA in Chemistry and Biology in 1970.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-LCGC-1">[1]</ref> He then worked with Irving  Sunshine at the Cuyahoga County Coroner’s Office, in the Forensic Toxicology  group.  After enlisting in the U.S. Navy, he helped to establish a drug  analysis lab in the Great Lakes Naval Hospital at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Lakes_Naval_Station">Great Lakes Naval Station</ref>. He returned to university in 1974.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Pittsburgh-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>For his doctorate, Weber worked with William Purdy, first at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Maryland">University of Maryland</ref> and then at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/McGill_University">McGill University</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Pittsburgh-2">[2]</ref> He received his Ph.D. from McGill University in 1979.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-LCGC-1">[1]</ref> His research at McGill involved the development of an electrochemical immunoassay using an electrochemical detector.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Pittsburgh-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Cashin-Garbutt-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Career</head>
<p>In 1979, Weber joined the Department of Chemistry at the University of Pittsburgh,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Pittsburgh-2">[2]</ref> where he is currently a Professor of Chemistry and Clinical Translational Science.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Cashin-Garbutt-3">[3]</ref> He has served in a number of capacities at the university, including becoming Director of  Graduate  Studies  for  the  Chemistry Department in 2001.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Tsarevsky-4">[4]</ref> He has published over 200 journal articles, and has served on the editorial boards of  <hi rend="italic">Analytical  Chemistry</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Trends  in  Analytical  Chemistry</hi>  and  the  <hi rend="italic">Journal  of  Chromatography</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Pittsburgh-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Research</head>
<p>A major focus of his research is analytical separations theory and its application. His research group develops analytical techniques for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Molecular_recognition">molecular recognition</ref> and molecularly selective microextractions, and utilizes  “green” separation procedures using <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aqueous_solutions">aqueous solutions</ref> and nonvolatile <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polymer_chemistry">polymeric systems</ref>.  They have developed  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thin_films">thin films</ref> for solid-phase micro extraction (SPME).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Tsarevsky-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Weber develops electrochemical detectors for use with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liquid_chromatography">liquid chromatography</ref> techniques.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Yeung-5">[5]</ref> An important area of application is the identification of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peptides">peptides</ref>, which help to control the body.  Some of the systems which neuropeptides influence include pain, mood, social and emotional behavior, responses to stress, and memory.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Cashin-Garbutt-3">[3]</ref>  Understanding how peptides affect <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neurochemistry">neurochemistry</ref> and other biological systems has important implications for medicine and pharmaceutical development.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-LCGC-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Weber-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>Dipeptides can be present in the brain at sub-picomole levels.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Weber-6">[6]</ref>  To work effectively at this level, techniques must be highly sensitive and selective.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Tsarevsky-4">[4]</ref>     Weber and his colleagues work on techniques to sample minute quantities from brain fluid and from single living cells. They are developing specialized sampling protocols with the goal of obtaining minute amounts of material from living organisms with minimal damage.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Cashin-Garbutt-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Ou-7">[7]</ref></p>
<head>Awards and honors</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>2016, Dal Nogare Award, Chromatography Forum of the Delaware Valley<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-LCGC-1">[1]</ref></item>
<item>2015, Palmer Award, Minnesota Chromatography Forum<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Palmer-8">[8]</ref></item>
<item>2012, Provost’s Award for Excellence in Mentoring, University of Pittsburgh<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Mentoring-9">[9]</ref></item>
<item>2008, Pittsburgh Award, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Chemical_Society">American Chemical Society</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Tsarevsky-4">[4]</ref></item></list>
</text>
