<text id="autogum_whow_doc501" title="Make a Personal Organiser" shortTile="make-personal-organiser" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2008-01-04" dateModified="2018-10-05" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-a-Personal-Organiser" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make a Personal Organiser</head><p>Staying organized is very important, so read carefully on how to make a personal organizer, which helps you keep up-to-date.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Get an empty book, or staple colourful papers together to make a book. It doesn't have to be too fancy, though. A regular personal organizer is clean, neat and always has a title. <figure rend="PersonalOrganizer Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make a contents page. It looks very mature. <figure rend="PersonalOrganizer Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make a schedule for the day on the first page. Repeat it everyday or make a new one for each day. It is your decision. Make sure it's very neat. Use rulers if you want to make the schedule in a table or a chart. If it includes diagrams or anything complicated, do it in pencil. <figure rend="PersonalOrganizer Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make a budget with income and expenditure.</item>
<item>Get a calculator and somehow get it to stay there or you can buy a book that have calculators stapled in them. You can't glue the calculators, so try stapling them with a sharped-front stapler. <figure rend="PersonalOrganizer Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep your school timetable in any of the pages. Then you can bring the organizer to school and see which lessons you have next and at what time. <figure rend="PersonalOrganizer Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make a snack chart. It always comes in useful. Take a different piece of paper and write down a list of what snack and what time. Also write down the time when you have breakfast, lunch and dinner. If you want to make diagrams, flow-charts, tables or anything else, then you can. It's best if you make a checklist. <figure rend="PersonalOrganizer Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make a list of other personal things like, taking a shower, brushing your teeth, doing homework, etc. It's the most important thing to do when you have an organizer. <figure rend="PersonalOrganizer Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do fun things in an organizer, but don't make it too fancy and decorated with sequins and beads. For example, you can make a special page of "friendship" and glue pictures of your friends and their names underneath. Be creative. <figure rend="PersonalOrganizer Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make as many pages you want and make sure everything is neat. If there is a mistake, rub it in white ink if its in pen, if not, then rub it with an eraser. Try not to get the organizer too fat. If the book is filled up, get another book. Staple them together or just have them separate. <figure rend="PersonalOrganizer Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure you don't lose it!</item>
<item>Make the organizer pages colour-coded. You can stick a little paper above the pages and label what the page is about.</item>
<item>Don't be afraid to use a ruler for the lines. Its better to spend a little more time making it neat then not understanding what you have written before.</item>
<item>Don't decorate the book so much. An organizer is always neat and clean. Avoid getting it wet.</item>
<item>Follow your organizer ALL the time. Keep it as your "pocket-book" which means keeping it in your pocket and taking it everywhere you go.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>When you are writing times, make sure the times are correct. If plans change, then don't rip out the whole page and ruin your book. Cross it with white ink and write the new plan.</item></list>
</text>
