<text id="autogum_bio_doc217" title="Robert Blake (Medal of Honor)" shortTile="robert-blake-medal" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-08-04" dateModified="2019-10-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Blake_%28Medal_of_Honor%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Robert Blake (Medal of Honor)</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Robert Blake</hi> was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Union_Navy">Union Navy</ref> sailor during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Civil_War">American Civil War</ref> and a recipient of America's highest military decoration, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Medal_of_Honor">Medal of Honor</ref>. Blake was the second <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/African_American">African American</ref> to perform a Medal of Honor action; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Harvey_Carney">William Harvey Carney</ref> was the first. Blake was the first African American to actually <hi rend="italic">receive</hi> a Medal of Honor - his was presented to him in 1864, while Carney did not receive his until 1900. But, because Carney's Medal of Honor action occurred first, Carney, not Blake, is usually credited with being the first African American Medal of Honor recipient.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Robert Blake was born into slavery in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virginia">Virginia</ref>. In June 1862, his owner's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plantations_in_the_American_South">plantation</ref> was burned during a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Union_Navy">Union</ref> naval expedition up the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santee_River">Santee River</ref>. About 400 slaves from the plantation, including Robert Blake, were taken as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Contraband_(American_Civil_War)">contraband</ref> onto Union ships and sent to North Island in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Winyah_Bay">Winyah Bay</ref>. While on North Island, Robert Blake answered a call for twenty single men to serve on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/USS_Vermont_(1848)">USS<hi rend="italic">Vermont</hi></ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Hanna-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-enlist-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>By December 25, 1863, Blake had been transferred to the gunboat <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/USS_Marblehead_(1861)">USS<hi rend="italic">Marblehead</hi></ref> and was serving as a steward to Lieutenant Commander <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Worsam_Meade_III">Richard Worsam Meade</ref>. Early that morning, in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stono_River">Stono River</ref>, the <hi rend="italic">Marblehead</hi> came under fire from a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Confederate_States_of_America">Confederate</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Howitzer">howitzer</ref> at Legareville on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johns_Island,_South_Carolina">Johns Island</ref>. As Lieutenant Commander Meade jumped from his bed and ran onto the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quarter_deck">quarter deck</ref> to give the order to return fire, Blake followed behind him, handed him his uniform, and urged him to change out of his night clothes.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Hanna-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Blake then went to the ship's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gun_deck">gun deck</ref> and was immediately knocked down by an exploding Confederate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shell_(projectile)">shell</ref>. The explosion had killed a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Powder-boy">powder-boy</ref> manning one of the guns. Blake had no assigned combat role and could have retreated to relative safety below decks, but he instead chose to take over the powder boy's duties. He stripped to the waist and began running powder boxes to the gun loaders. When Lieutenant Commander Mead asked him what he was doing, he replied "Went down to the rocks to hide my face, but the rocks said there is no hiding place here. So here I am, Sir."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Hanna-1">[1]</ref> The Confederates eventually abandoned their position, leaving a gun behind. For his actions during the firefight, Blake was awarded the Medal of Honor four months later, on April 16, 1864.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-citation-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Blake was later promoted to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seaman_(rank)">seaman</ref> and re-enlisted for another term in the Navy. During his second enlistment, he served again on the USS <hi rend="italic">Vermont</hi>. Nothing is known of his further life.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Medal of Honor citation</head>
<p>Rank and organization: Contraband, U.S. Navy. Entered service at: Virginia.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-enlist-2">[2]</ref> G.O. No.: 32, April 16, 1864. Accredited to: Virginia.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-citation-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Citation:</hi></p>
<p>On board the U.S. Steam Gunboat <hi rend="italic">Marblehead</hi> off Legareville, Stono River, 25 December 1863, in an engagement with the enemy on John's Island. Serving the rifle gun, Blake, an escaped slave, carried out his duties bravely throughout the engagement which resulted in the enemy's abandonment of positions, leaving a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Limbers_and_caissons_(military)">caisson</ref> and one gun behind.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-citation-3">[3]</ref></p>
</text>
