<text id="autogum_interview_doc757" title="part0_Interview with Innocent Watat, City Council candidate for Wards 3 &amp; 4 in Brampton, Canada" shortTile="partinterview-innocent" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-21" dateModified="2007-06-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Innocent_Watat%2C_City_Council_candidate_for_Wards_3_%26_4_in_Brampton%2C_Canada" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Interview with Innocent Watat, City Council candidate for Wards 3 &amp; 4 in Brampton, Canada</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 21, 2006</hi></p>
<p>The upcoming <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brampton%20municipal%20election,%202006">2006 Brampton municipal election</ref>, to be held November 13, features an array of candidates looking to represent their wards in city council or the council of the Peel Region.</p>
<p>Wikinews contributor Nick Moreau contacted many of the candidates, including <hi rend="bold">Innocent Watat</hi>, asking them to answer common questions sent in an email. This ward's incumbent is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bob%20Callahan">Bob Callahan</ref>; Balbir Babra, Manny Bianchi-Morfino, Dolly Khokhar, Maria Peart, Tim Turcott, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sheila%20White%20(politician)">Sheila White</ref>.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> List the three most important issues in your campaign.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi></p>
<p>- Gap between council actions and concerns of Bramptonians.</p>
<p>- Community safety and security and relationship between Police and the community mostly the relationship between the Police and the visible minorities' community</p>
<p>- Infrastructure and public transit concerns</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What one election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi>My ward is overwhelmingly and increasingly populated by a multi-ethnic and multi cultural immigrants from around the world. Beside the infrequent public transit issues which are the main concern for these settlers, I think that the most relevant issue here is safety because of the stigma leading to discriminatory profile from Police. Of course these newcomers in the city are not today part of the main discussions at the council chamber although they are significantly part of the future of the city.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What qualities or experiences do you possess, that make you more desirable than the incumbent?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi>I am a young, dynamic, dedicated and passionate Bramptonian willing to push this great city to a deserved place as a Canadian model of multi-cultural and multi ethnicity integration. I would use my positive energy and the new vision to develop our community by making it safer, cleaner, lively, exotic and vibrant.</p>
<p>I am resolved to turn into my obligations all the concerns of the people of Brampton.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent your ward on council?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I strongly feel that I could bring something new to my wards and to the council chamber. I also think it is time for change; it is the time to see some new faces and to have a council that strictly reflects the reality of the population, a chamber that really works for the benefit of the population. I am an advocate of a maximum of three terms by councilor and I still cannot believe that we do have councilors who are there for more than 15 years now. There is no doubt that issues of the 1980s or the 1990s are well out of date. There are new realities on the field today, and I am bringing that vision with me. This vision is beyond what the incumbent of ward 3, 4 has to offer. He has done his time, if he really loves our city, he needs to give the chance to fresh mind to continue what he has started while he can calmly enjoy a deserved retirement.</p>
</text>
