<text id="autogum_interview_doc864" title="part4_Wikinews interviews World Wide Web co-inventor Robert Cailliau" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-07-22" dateModified="2014-09-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_World_Wide_Web_co-inventor_Robert_Cailliau" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Robert Cailliau</p>
<p>Tim, who had a longer experience with the internet world, convinced me that the web could only survive if all the code was freely available for everyone who wanted to tinker with it.  In 1992-1993 I then worked patiently for some 6 months with CERN's Legal Service to draft a document that put the source code into the public domain.  This also implied working to convince the management, up to the Directors, of the need to do so.  The result was the document signed on 30 April 1993 that gave the WWW technology to the world.</p>
<p>During the same period I also perceived that the web as a technology had very many aspects.  Tim drew what he called the "metro": a diagram of the relationships between the existing systems (FTP, SMTP, HTTP, ...) in the form of a stylised map resembling that of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London%20Underground">London Underground</ref>.  That made me think that we needed to deal with a lot more hard computer science than our small team of four or five could intellectually handle.  Therefore I began to toy with the idea of an international conference on WWW technologies.  Tim was not convinced, but I went ahead.</p>
<p>NCSA (the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National%20Center%20for%20Supercomputing%20Applications">National Center for Supercomputer Applications</ref> in the U.S.) had just released <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mosaic%20(web%20browser)">Mosaic</ref>, first for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/X%20Window%20System">X-Window</ref>/<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unix">Unix</ref> systems, then for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Macintosh">Mac</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Personal%20computer">PC</ref>.  Their group not only had a lot more people, but their leader, Joseph Hardin, was a sociologist of my age.  I suspected that he was thinking along the same lines, and I was right:  when I  launched the call for papers for the first WWW conference in December 1993, I did so just one day before NCSA would have done the same thing.
It was a Friday and on Saturday Hardin phoned me at home to discuss the matter.  Fortunately our relations were good and he was also very fair by teaming up with my conference in the end.
But our team at the time was very weak:  NCSA had a big success with Mosaic and they could easily have used their weight to wipe us off the map.</p>
<p>It was also a time to understand how underdeveloped our idea of Europe here is.  We know that we have to live together on this assembly of peninsulas, but when we have to pull in the same direction then that is politically rather difficult.</p>
<p>Finally for two years I worked quite hard contributing to the setting up of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World%20Wide%20Web%20Consortium">Web Consortium</ref>.  Even afterwards that took much effort and a lot of my time.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi>: There are some fun anecdotes about the beginning of the World Wide Web. We've just offered you a virtual beer, but the idea of the WWW started with a beer too, in this case with a (real) beer with Tim Berners-Lee, right? And there is a reason that the original WWW-logo is green, right? Why is it not called world-wide web, with a hyphen? Are there other anecdotes you want to share with our readers?</p>
</text>
