<text id="autogum_academic_doc440" title="Forest Understorey Vegetation: Colonization and the Availability and Heterogeneity of Resources" shortTile="forest-understorey" author="Xiangping Su, Minhuang Wang, Zhiqun Huang, Songling Fu, Han  Y.H. Chen" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1999-4907/10/11/944/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Understorey vegetation comprises a major component of plant diversity, which contributes to the structural complexity of forests, heterogeneous habitats for other biotic groups, water holding capacity, and nutrient retention. Although understorey vegetation often contributes relatively a small portion to the biomass of overall forest ecosystems, it plays a critical role in nutrient cycling and energy flow due to the high turnover rates of understorey vegetation. Several studies have revealed that the abundance, diversity, and composition of understorey vegetation change temporally with stand development following stand-replacing disturbances, and that the forest overstorey strongly mediates understorey vegetation. However, the potential mechanisms involved with the responses of understorey vegetation to both stand development and overstorey are not yet fully elucidated. </p>

<p>Environmental or resource heterogeneity have long been recognized as promoting species coexistence and thus species diversity. The availability of resources increases the abundance of organisms, and high abundance tends to be positively related to species diversity. Understorey vegetation inhabits resource-limited environments, as the overstory asymmetrically influences the consumption of space, light, water, and nutrients. Through an analysis of the published literature, Bartels and Chen showed that understorey plant diversity increases with both resource heterogeneity and quantity in forests on a global scale. Nevertheless, it remains unclear how forest stand development, overstorey composition and diversity, and non-stand replacing disturbances affect understorey resource heterogeneity and quantity, and consequently influence understorey vegetation abundance and diversity. An improved understanding of the key driving factors and associated mechanisms of understorey vegetation abundance and diversity is of great significance for the conservation of biodiversity and sustainability of ecosystem service functions. </p>

<p>For this review, we initially introduce the primary drivers of understorey vegetation, abundance, and diversity. Subsequently, we examine the mechanisms behind understorey abundance and diversity. Then, we explore how these drivers and mechanisms may be altered due to climate and site conditions. Lastly, we compare the abundance and diversity response patterns of understorey vegetation under different forest management practices and associated mechanisms. In the first section, we focus on the patterns of understorey vegetation abundance and diversity that are impacted by stand age (colonization time), overstorey composition and diversity, and non-stand-replacing disturbances. In the second section, we examine how these three drivers modify the understorey quantity and heterogeneity of light, soil nutrients, soil moisture, and substrates, and in turn, affect understorey abundance and diversity. In the third section, we assess how local climate and site conditions modify understorey resource quantity and heterogeneity, and consequently impact understorey abundance and diversity. In the fourth section, we compare the effects of clearcutting and those of partial harvesting on the abundance and diversity of understorey vegetation, and examine the mechanisms involved that affect the patterns of these attributes in managed forests. In particular, we stress the need to understand multivariate relationships among the drivers including colonization time (i.e., stand age following stand-replacing disturbance), disturbance regimes, overstorey composition and diversity, the quantity and heterogeneity of understorey resources (e.g., light, nutrients, water, and substrates), and the abundance and diversity of understorey vegetation (<figure>Figure 1</figure>). </p>
</text>
