<text id="autogum_whow_doc174" title="Think in Another Language" shortTile="think-another-language" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-09-23" dateModified="2019-08-02" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Think-in-Another-Language" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Think in Another Language</head><p>Thinking in another language can be more useful than you think! It can be a great way to perfect your second language, to learn a new language quicker or to raise your grades in a certain language in school. Of course, you have to know the basics of the language before you can start thinking in it.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Immerse yourself in the language. Learning by immersion is one of the best ways to pick up a language. The more you're exposed to the language, the more likely you are to begin thinking in that language. Try going to places you're likely to find people speaking the language, or surrounding yourself with the language by changing the language on your electronics, subscribing to newspapers written in the language, reading books and watching movies in another language, and so on.</item>
<item>Resist the urge to use your first language. Immersing yourself in a new language can be quite challenging at first, but avoid using your first language as a crutch. Try saving it for when you really need it, because every time you use your first language, you're further off from thinking in another language. For instance, turn off subtitles while watching movies in another language, and try to understand it naturally.</item>
<item>Befriend someone who speaks another language. Find someone who speaks your new language as a first language and get in touch with them. As you interact with them over time, you'll find yourself thinking in their language. If you can't find anyone where you live, try <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Find_a_Penpal">getting a penpal</ref>. There are several avenues to find one online, so search websites to find someone else looking for a penpal, and write to them.</item>
<item>Force yourself to think in the language. If it's been a while and you still can't get yourself to think in another language, try forcing yourself to let go of your old language. If you notice yourself thinking in your first language, scrap the thought or continue with the language you're trying to learn.. If you've  tried this and are still failing, it is likely that you just don't know the language well enough, and need more practice.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you're having an exam in your second or third language, make sure to read a book in it the day before and write in it as often as possible.</item>
<item>Little things make a big difference. Try purchasing calendars, inspirational posters, cooking recipes and so on in the language you're trying to learn.</item>
<item>If you're trying to learn a second language along with your children, get children's books and talking toys using the language, watch kids' TV in the language with them and remember to speak the language to them.</item></list>
</text>
