<text id="autogum_interview_doc718" title="part3_Author of My Billion Year Contract reflects on life in elite Scientology group" shortTile="partauthor-billion" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-01-13" dateModified="2012-10-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Author_of_My_Billion_Year_Contract_reflects_on_life_in_elite_Scientology_group" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">NM</hi>: <hi rend="italic">Opening Skinners Box: Great Psychological Experiments of the Twentieth Century</hi> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lauren%20Slater">Lauren Slater</ref></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Lucifer%20Effect">The Lucifer Effect: How Good People Turn Evil</ref></hi> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip%20Zimbardo">Phil Zimbardo</ref></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mistakes%20were%20made%20(but%20not%20by%20me)">Mistakes Were Made (But Not by Me)</ref></hi> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carol%20Tavris">Carol Tavris</ref></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> It is understandable that the act of writing down your experiences on paper could be a cathartic process but - why publicize it as a book?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NM</hi>: As I write in my Preface the book was written almost two years ago, but the fear of publishing books on the subject of Scientology, got it no where in the area of publishing, Scientology is too frightening and scares even large publishing houses.  I even got turned away by a "Print on Demand" – where I pay for it myself.  They were just to frightened of repercussions on them as a company and on the staff as individuals.</p>
<p>But one night, an old friend who had been in Scientology for 36 years and had reached the highest most level in Scientology (Operating Thetan Level 8) arrived at my door suicidal.  I knew I had to do more.  For the past 10 years I had been dealing with Mentally Troubled individuals one on one, but this woman brought to my door the fact that what I was doing wasn’t even cracking the egg of mental abuse.  So I took my book off the shelf and my husband and I started our own publishing company.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Did you fear publicizing your experiences could subject you and your family to the Scientology practice of "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fair%20Game%20(Scientology)">Fair Game</ref>" ?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NM</hi>: Of course.  In my particular case they had already interrogated me to the point of psychotic meltdown, and there wasn't much more they could do to me.  I hear the clicks on my phone, I’ve gotten the private investigator with the CIA past placed on my car.  I’ve had people show up.  But as long as I am truthful and don't make things worse than they were, nor better than they were, this is America, land of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freedom%20of%20speech">Free Speech</ref>.  While working to get the book out (in those two months) I came to learn of 3 more deaths of people who experienced mental breakdowns while under the care of Scientologist, it only spurred me on.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Have you experienced anything from Scientology after publicizing your story that you feel is retribution or a form of Fair Game?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NM</hi>: I'm never certain if it is coincidence or not, but yes little things, not like the others that are coming out now and testifying at court cases.  I also think Scientology is a little busy with just being declared a Fraud by the Government of France, Belgium has been preparing their law suit and should be coming out shortly.  Here in America, the current head of Scientology and the corporation have just been served with a lawsuit on human trafficking.  An eight year old boy was signed up with the Sea Org (Billion Year Contract) and he was put to work scrubbing pots and pans from that young age.  I know of under aged children who signed Billion Year Contracts, they were promised their High School educations, which they never got, but those children were 13 or 14 – this is an 8 year old boy.  Senator Xenophon in Australia has just stood up and asked for a government inquiry to the human abuses of Scientology.  His documentation includes part of my book. Yes there are many things they can do to me, but I am tired of them Mentally and otherwise abusing people to the point of suicide. </p>
</text>
