<text id="autogum_interview_doc902" title="part1_Interview with Reggie Bibbs on his life with neurofibromatosis" shortTile="partinterview-reggie" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-28" dateModified="2010-04-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Reggie_Bibbs_on_his_life_with_neurofibromatosis" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: Neurofibromatosis is a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genetic%20disorder">genetic disorder</ref> that causes <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tumor">tumors</ref> to grow throughout the body and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/nervous%20system">nervous system</ref>. The tumors grow anywhere on the body. NF-2 is when the tumors grow on the inside and on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vestibulocochlear%20nerve">hearing nerves</ref> and the eyes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: How are you affected?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: I have NF-1 and the tumors are outward, they call this disfigurement and it has affected my legs and the left side of my face.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">(interviewer directs the camera)</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: How did you find out you had NF?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: I was eight months old, and that's when we found out about neurofibromatosis. At that time they were calling it "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Friedrich%20Daniel%20von%20Recklinghausen">von Recklinghausen</ref> disease". My mom took me to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shriners%20Hospitals%20for%20Children">Shriners Hospital</ref>, they examined me and that's when they told her, I had <hi rend="italic">von Recklinghausen</hi> disease or neurofibromatosis. They found a small tumor on my heel and a small tumor on my eye and one in my mouth, on the roof of my mouth.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: Was it painful?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: At that time I remember my mom telling me, that the tumor on my leg was really painful, because she would cry when she would try to put shoes on my feet.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: How did your mom react to finding out you had neurofibromatosis? Did she know anything about it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: My mom didn't know anything about it until I was diagnosed. And they saw my mom's arm and they said, you know, this right here is a tumor and this is where it came from. And they said it is the same type of tumor. She was very hurt, you know, she asked the doctors if it was something she did. Because she thought that is was something she did during the pregnancy that caused this disfigurement.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: What causes NF?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: NF is caused by a defective gene. And this gene is defective and it is telling the body to grow tumors.</p>
<head id="Growing_up">Growing up</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: What was it like growing up, as a child in elementary school?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: Growing up and going to elementary and being a child was really difficult, because you knew that you looked different from all of the other kids. And they all were wearing the right shoes and I had to wear different shoes. And I just looked different from anyone I had ever seen.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: Was your face as disfigured as it is now?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: Well, yes, my eye was really a lot different growing up, but my lip and the left side of my cheek ... that was, you know, really noticeable. And it was really difficult going to school because there were a lot of kids that used to make fun. And there were some that were nice.</p>
</text>
