<text id="autogum_academic_doc364" title="Screen-Printed Voltammetric Biosensors for the Determination of Copper in Wine" shortTile="screenprinted-voltammetric" author="Liliana Norocel, Gheorghe Gutt" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1424-8220/19/21/4618/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The presence of metallic contaminants in wines is attributed to many endogenous and exogenous factors. The mineral content of wine depends on soil, location, grape varieties, weather or environmental conditions, and wine practices. The main source may be the vineyard sprays and particularly the use of Bordeaux mixture (a copper-based vineyard spray), which significantly contributes to high levels of copper ions in the must (in excess of 20 mg/L in two cases investigated by the Australian Wine Research Institute). However, fermentation usually eliminates much of this excess through binding of the metal to yeast and removal with the lees. Another source would be the contact of a wine with copper or copper alloys during winemaking; furthermore, the addition of copper sulfate to correct sulfidic off-odors is arguably a major cause of copper instability. Certain heavy metals, including copper, can form insoluble salts and can induce additional casse. The presence of copper in high concentration in wine causes the so-called copper casse, which can already be installed at concentrations of 0.5 mg Cu/L, having a negative effect on the organoleptic properties of the wine. Excess of copper ions determined before bottling can be removed from the wine by the addition of potassium ferrocyanide. Therefore, by avoiding wine quality degradation, the determination of these ions has economic benefits for wine producers. Nowadays, most existing methods used for heavy metal trace analysis include spectrophotometric (AAS—atomic absorption spectrometer, ICP/MS—inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometry, ICP/AES—inductively coupled plasma atomic emission spectrometry), voltammetric, and chromatographic methods, which can detect analytes at very low concentrations. However, all these classic techniques are generally costly and laborious, so it is necessary to develop new methods that eliminate these disadvantages. Biosensor systems are relatively recent achievements that allow rapid, inexpensive, and in situ quantitative analytical determinations, providing solutions for food analysis in terms of specificity and time savings. Electrochemical biosensors are often preferred due to simplicity and miniaturization. From this point of view, the use of screen-printed electrodes not only solves the problem of cost efficiency, but also satisfies the portability requirement, contributing to the progress towards decentralized analysis. There are numerous studies on the detection of copper ions with biosensors by the specified means, but most of them are developed around the analysis of these ions in water or foods. Only a few studies can be applied in the determination of the copper content of wine, despite the fact that the presence of this element has a great impact on the quality and safety of this product. Numerous scientific papers studied the use of bovine serum albumin (BSA) in terms of the mechanism of adsorption and the interactions of the protein with different electrode materials. A series of investigations were particularly focused on the interactions between BSA and copper; these studies are useful for understanding the biological phenomena related to the formation of covalent bonds. Several investigations used the metal–protein interaction to design electrodes for electrochemical detection of heavy metals. An interesting experiment regarding the binding of Cu (II) ion to BSA was achieved by ion-selective electrode potentiometry, and the results offered more attractive features than some traditional methodologies. The immobilization of proteins on the electrode is important for the development and performance of biosensors and has been investigated in numerous studies. The characterization of metal binding to metalloproteins is vital for our understanding of the relationship between structure and function. Fundamental for metal binding activity is the intrinsic binding constant, which is a parameter that describes the affinity with which metal ions are bound to specific protein sites. The central tenet of the strategy is the presentation of the metal to the protein in the form of well-characterized, low-molecular-weight chelates to prevent metal hydrolysis and nonspecific binding. Further, this strategy permits the determination of the number of specific metal binding sites and provides insights into the amino acid ligands involved in binding. Among the immobilization methods applied for the specified recognition element, a simple method is photoreactive immobilization, performed by benzophenone irradiation at the 350 nm wavelength. Benzophenone (Ph2CO) is activated by UV light in the range 350–360 nm, and its reaction mechanism is as follows: The carbonyl oxygen forms a ketyl radical when exposed to UV light and then abstracts the hydrogen from a C–H bond in a nearby molecule, followed by C–C bond formation between Ph2CO and the attacked molecule. Advantages of Ph2CO include chemical stability, activation in a UV range that does not damage proteins or cells, and stability in ambient light. The purpose of this study was to develop a biosensor with practical significance for determining the copper content of wine, using as biological element, BSA protein, immobilized by a photoreactive compound, namely benzophenone, and an electrochemical transducer providing a cyclic voltammogram response. Furthermore, the results obtained by the voltammetric method for 40 wine samples were compared with the reference method, namely AAS (atomic absorption spectrometer), to confirm the efficiency of the developed electrochemical biosensor. The novelty of this biosensor is a new method to determine copper ions in wine which solves the problem of high cost and portability. </p>
</text>
