<text id="autogum_whow_doc445" title="Keep Your Apartment Warm" shortTile="keep-apartment-warm" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2007-10-29" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Keep-Your-Apartment-Warm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Keep Your Apartment Warm</head><p>Winter can get pretty cold. While we put on a cheerful face by playing hockey and having snowball fights, at the end of the day, we’re all dependent on our furnaces and heating systems to get us through those dark, cold months.However, winter is only as cold as you want it to be – with a few easy-to-implement winter apartment heating tips, you’ll be able to keep warm and toasty when the temperature drops below the freezing mark.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Close Your Windows – And Keep Them Closed</hi>The biggest single source of radiant heat loss in your apartment is most likely your windows (especially if they are old, single-pane windows). It may seem like an obvious tip, but check all of the windows in your apartment to make sure they are closed and locked during the winter. As well, try to avoid opening the windows at all, if possible.Even if you keep your windows closed, however, warm air can still escape:<hi rend="bold">*</hi>Between the window frame and the wall;<hi rend="bold">*</hi>Around the edges of a loose pane or through cracks in the glass.To prevent warm air from escaping through the window frame, you can install durable metal or plastic weather-stripping between the window sash and frame. Typically, these types of weather-stripping will last for several years and do not interfere with the regular use of the window. <figure rend="Keep Your Apartment Warm Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Cover Any “Leaky” Windows</hi>To prevent air from escaping around the edges of a loose pane, caulk or tape around the edge of the loose pane where it meets the framework of the sash. Alternatively, you can cover “leaky” windows with a thin sheet of plastic to try to keep the warm air in and the cool air out. These simple “window kits” can make a big difference in reducing any drafts throughout your apartment.Always get permission from your landlord before installing anything or modifying your apartment windows. Your landlord might even pay for and make the installations for you, depending on the situation. <figure rend="Keep Your Apartment Warm Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Draft-Proof Your Doors</hi>Just like your windows, keeping your apartment door closed as much as possible during the winter will help keep the heat where it belongs – in your apartment instead of in the hallway.You can also draft-proof your doors with weather-stripping and caulking. Warm air can easily escape between the door frame and the wall – if this is the case in your apartment, caulk between the frame and the wall. In most apartments, the vast majority of warm air is lost under the bottom of the door. Installing a door sweep or a draft-stopper to prevent air from moving under the door can prevent this loss and keep your apartment warm. These supplies can be found inexpensively at any hardware store.In addition to keeping your apartment comfortable, weatherproofing your doors and windows will also save a lot of energy as you won’t be using as much heat to keep your apartment warm. <figure rend="Keep Your Apartment Warm Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Don’t Block Your Radiators</hi>Finally, if your apartment has radiators, they should always be kept clean – any amount of dirt and dust sitting on top of them will absorb some of the heat that is being produced. You should also remove any radiator covers when the heat is on, as covers can block the airflow through the radiator in addition to absorbing heat.Be sure to also move your furniture so that all chairs, couches, bookcases, entertainment units, desks, beds, etc. aren’t too close to your radiators or heating convectors. Don’t let your drapes or curtains cover them either, as they will divert heat to the windows (and therefore out of your apartment if they aren’t properly sealed) instead of into the rest of the room. <figure rend="Keep Your Apartment Warm Step 4.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>While you can’t avoid the cold entirely, following these easy tips should keep you a little bit warmer this winter and give you a nice, cozy apartment to come home to after a fun snowball fight or game of hockey outside with your friends. Keep yourself warm by not going in and out plan your trips so you keep your habitat warmer and cooler year round.</item>
<item>Use a smoke pen or a stick of incense to make a plume of smoke and look for leaks around windows and switch and outlet plates.</item>
<item>Insulation and weather stripping helps contain heat and keep the temperature consistent, but it doesn't create heat. You will still need a working heat source to keep warm.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always get permission from your landlord before installing anything or modifying your apartment windows or doors. You may use blankets to keep some of the cold drafts out as well.</item></list>
</text>
