<text id="autogum_whow_doc616" title="Discover Your Unique Blueprint" shortTile="discover-unique-blueprint" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-12-11" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Discover-Your-Unique-Blueprint" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Discover Your Unique Blueprint</head><p>What is a Blueprint? Formally, when people refer to a blueprint they associate it with a drawing (a layout) used to construct a design created by architects and/or engineers. According to Wikipedia, “the blue-print process was characterized by light colored lines on a blue background, a negative of the original. The process was unable to reproduce color or shades of grey.” Less formally a blueprint is referred to simply as a plan.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>In order for you to be able to distinguish a better life for yourself you have to recreate your plan and get rid of the grey areas in your life.  Creating a plan allows you to focus on the things that are important and it is virtually impossible to do if you are stuck in the grey areas of your life. The grey areas in your life are thoughts of uncertainty, thoughts of worthlessness, thoughts of wanting to be successful but fearful. Too often those grey areas are the blueprint of people’s lives. They plan their lives around what others think of them.</item>
<item>Now that you understand what blueprint you are working with, let’s take a look at your life. Evaluate areas in your life that need a plan. I want you to write down or type as many areas in your life that you feel could use a plan. It could be your planning a vacation, living a healthier lifestyle, spending more time with family, starting a new business, whatever your area is write it down so you can hold yourself accountable for it. Now, write down the why. Why do you need to create a plan for that vacation? It could be you just spontaneously decided to go to Jamaica but you haven’t saved up for it. Living a healthier lifestyle, you’ve been putting it off for weeks, months, maybe years. You know you’ve been wanting to do it but don’t have a plan of execution.</item>
<item>Last but not least, you’ve been wanting to go after your passion and your dreams but don’t have a plan of execution. You’ve conducted a ton of research, attended hundreds of networking events, made great contacts but you are not taking any action. Why not? Could it be you are paralyzed by the fear of success? Fear of success, what does that mean exactly? The fear of success is wanting to go after a desire but afraid of the process. Some people believe they don’t have the right to be successful. They live their lives with the thought of being mediocre is sufficient. They remain in the shadows of other people’s successes. Well what if you gave success a try? You could not only see but reap the benefits of going after your heart’s desire.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>So let’s summarize it this way, basically a blueprint is a plan that is derived from, characterized from, a negative of the original and unable to reproduce shades of grey. Interesting right? So, if your life was like a blueprint, you should what, recreate yourself from your original self, produce a plan that is unable to reproduce any shades of grey.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Most people hold back, afraid to take chances, afraid to step out into their greatness. It’s not that they didn’t have goals and dreams everybody wants more. When something happens to them they began to believe that’s the way it is and they don’t know how to change it. So what do they do, they keep you from yours. Just keep moving forward and stop caring what others think about your dreams. You have to do what is right for you.Don’t let that be your story. Create your own story, create your own future. Where are you going with your life? What is your Why? Why do you do what you do? What moves you? What drives you? What makes you want to be better? What is the purpose behind what you want to do? Who are you doing this for? These are the questions that you have to ask yourself. You have to find your why and when you find your why, why you want to be successful then you have to find a way to make it happen. When you find your why you will decide you don’t have an option to quit. When you find your why you will find that you are in charge of your destiny. Find out your why and go after it like your life depends on it. Like you are running for your life.</item></list>
</text>
