<text id="autogum_interview_doc662" title="part5_Gay Talese on the state of journalism, Iraq and his life" shortTile="partgay-talese-state" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-27" dateModified="2019-01-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gay_Talese_on_the_state_of_journalism%2C_Iraq_and_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How could there not be?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  Sometimes it leads to marriage. Sometimes it's just affairs. Sometimes it involves just dealing with bar girls in Okinawa or Leone or Sicily or somewhere.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Sure.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  Not so now. This is the first war like that, in Iraq.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Have you been there?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  No, I haven't been there. I'd like to go.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why haven't you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  Well, I have to have somebody that will give me credentials.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That shouldn't be too hard for you.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  Sure it is, because you think <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Time Magazine</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Newsweek Magazine</hi>....?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <hi rend="italic">Esquire</hi>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi> <hi rend="italic">Esquire</hi>?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <hi rend="italic">Esquire</hi> does political reporting.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  It so happens there is someone that's working on such a thing right now for me. I haven't heard from them yet.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What would be the difficulties for you in achieving that? It seems like you would just have to make a phone call.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  You very much overrate whatever stature you think I have. I mean there are people that are there. The New York Times has probably fifteen, twenty people there. And they're not going to underwrite me as a freelancer. People want staff now. Obviously you have to be covered by health and all this....</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I think you're underrating your stature.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  The point is, I'm not there, okay. We can talk all morning about this, but the point is I am now working on something. But I'm trying to get back to what I was saying before, whether or not I'm there, I'm now here. Will I be there? Maybe. But there are stories. I mean I'm quoting myself as to what kind of stories. The television shows American troops kicking down doors and I wonder: who fixes the doors?  The other day I was on an airplane coming back from Bogotá and I sat next to a guy, an American, who was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Green%20Beret">Green Beret</ref> guy years ago. Well now he's in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baghdad">Baghdad</ref> as one of these civilian contractors. He has a company and he invited me to go with this company. That's my little thing that I have in the offing. But he told me that the worst thing, not kicking down the doors, but they go in there and they open the locks of what we'll call the hope chests of women who hope to marry. The soldiers go in and they just break open the locks of these women's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hope%20chest">hope chests</ref> or whatever you call them and that is really the ultimate insult. It's like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rape">raping</ref> the women right there. And this stuff goes on all the time. Well you could write about that. And no one writes about that.</p>
</text>
