<text id="autogum_bio_doc536" title="Despina Khatun" shortTile="despina-khatun" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-10-31" dateModified="2019-08-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Despina_Khatun" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Despina Khatun</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Theodora Megale Komnene</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greek_language">Greek</ref>: Θεοδώρα Μεγάλη Κομνηνή), also known as <hi rend="bold">Despina Khatun</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Persian_language">Persian</ref>: دسپینا خاتون‎; from the Greek title <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Despot_(court_title)">Despoina</ref></hi> and Mongol title <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Khatun">Khatun</ref></hi>, both meaning "Lady, princess, queen"), was the daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_IV_of_Trebizond">John IV of Trebizond</ref>, who married the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aq_Qoyunlu">Aq Qoyunlu</ref> ruler <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uzun_Hasan">Uzun Hasan</ref> in 1458. She became the mother of Martha (Halima) who became the mother of first <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Safavid">Safavid</ref> king, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shah_Ismail_I">Shah Ismail I</ref>.</p>
<p>Some older writers refer to her as "Catherine". Charles Diehl has shown that it was based on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_du_Fresne,_sieur_du_Cange">DuCange's</ref> misunderstanding of the Mongol title "Khatun" as "Catherine".
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>John IV agreed to the marriage only if his daughter was allowed to continue her <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orthodox_Christian">Orthodox Christian</ref> religion, a condition which Uzun Hasan agreed upon. Despina was famous for her extreme beauty amongst the Greek women. She was accompanied by a group of Orthodox Christian priests and was allowed to build Orthodox churches in Iran. Uzun Hasan strengthened his anti-Ottoman alliance by this marriage and gained the support of many Greek, Armenian and Georgians. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Marriage between Christians and Muslim rulers, although uncommon, was not unprecedented. Speros Vryonis provides several examples from the Sultanate of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seljuk_Turks">Seljuk Turks</ref>, beginning with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kilij_Arslan_II">Kilij Arslan II</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> A later example is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_VIII_Palaiologos">Michael VIII Palaiologos</ref> marrying off his illegitimate daughters <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euphrosyne_Palaiologina_(daughter_of_Michael_VIII)">Euphrosyne</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maria_Palaiologina">Maria</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nogai_Khan">Nogai Khan</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abaqa_Khan">Abaqa Khan</ref> respectively. Previous Emperors of Trebizond had married off his female relatives, most notably <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexios_III_of_Trebizond">Alexios III</ref>, during whose reign two of his sisters and two of his daughters were married to rulers of neighboring Muslim states.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>In Western Europe, Theodora inspired the myth of the "Princess of Trebizond", a fixture of tales of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Damsel_in_distress">damsels in distress</ref> as well as of a possible grand Crusade against the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Turks">Ottoman Turks</ref>. The legend inspired several artists, including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pisanello">Pisanello</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacques_Offenbach">Jacques Offenbach</ref>.</p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>Theodora was acknowledged as the daughter of John IV, but there is some mystery about who her mother was: no primary source names her mother, and John IV had two wives, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bagrationi,_wife_of_John_IV_of_Trebizond">Bagrationi</ref>, a daughter of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_I_of_Georgia">Alexander I</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> and the daughter of a Turkish sultan, whom John married sometime before November 1437.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> Because the first allusion to Theodora is dated to February 1451, when the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byzantine_Empire">Byzantine</ref> diplomat <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Sphrantzes">George Sphrantzes</ref> came to Trebizond seeking a bride for his Emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constantine_XI_Palaiologos">Constantine XI Palaiologos</ref> and we do not know how old she was at the time, either woman could be her mother.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> In 1458 she was married to Uzun Hasan, Khan of the Turkoman tribe of Aq Qoyunlu; her uncle <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_of_Trebizond">David</ref> gave her away at the marriage.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<head>Political marriage</head>
<p>At the time of marriage, the Empire of her father John faced a serious threat. Constantinople had fallen to the Ottoman sultan, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mehmet_II">Mehmet II</ref> in 1453. In 1456, Mehmet ordered his governor Chetir, to capture Trebizond; the attack failed, but John was forced to pay tribute to Mehmet to prevent further attacks.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> Mehmet gradually annexed the last Palaiologian possessions in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morea">Morea</ref>, completing the task with the conquest of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mistra">Mistra</ref> on 29 May 1460.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref> An alliance with the powerful Aq Qoyunlu tribe, who were the Ottomans' most powerful rival, appeared more than beneficial. </p>
<p>Trebziond and the Aq Qoyunlu had a history of co-operation, for they had concluded a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Political_marriage">political marriage</ref> in the past: Theodora's great-great aunt had married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qara_Osman">Qara Osman</ref>, emir of the Aq Qoyunlu.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref> Theodora was famed for her beauty. An unknown Venetian traveller wrote, "it was common opinion that there was at that time no woman of greater beauty; and throughout all Persia the fame of her great beauty and supreme charm spread."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref> Uzun Hassan eagerly agreed to be the protector of Trebizond, as well as making other concessions, in return for Theodora's hand. News of Theodora as the Princess of Trebizond who was married to the powerful Uzun Hassan spread to the West, and helped to foster stories of Princess of Trebizond. </p>
<p>However this alliance failed to help John's successor, his brother David. Mehmed II, the Ottoman ruler, marched on the imperial city of Trebizond in 1461. Uzun Hassan initially supported the Trapuzentines, but he was persuaded by the Ottomans to abandon Trebizond. After securing the eastern border, Mehmed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siege_of_Trebizond_(1461)">attacked Trebizond</ref>, which surrendered 15 August 1461, ending the polity.</p>
<head>Late life</head>
<p>After the fall of Trebizond, David was put in house arrest. In 1463, David was discovered attempting to send a secret letter to Theodora, which gave <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mehmed_II">Mehmed II</ref> the needed excuse to get rid of David once and for all. He considered this letter a conspiracy to recapture the land of Trebizond with the help of Aq Qoyunlu and had David, his sons and his nephew executed on 1 November 1463.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref></p>
<p>Despite the death of her uncle, Theodora continued to influence her husband in foreign affairs. According to Anthony Bryer, she was the moving force behind diplomatic overtures to Venice in 1465-1466, and to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen_III_of_Moldavia">Stephen III of Moldavia</ref> in 1474.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Bryer-146-15">[15]</ref> When the Venetian diplomat <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caterino_Zeno">Caterino Zeno</ref> came to the court of Uzun Hassan in 1473, one of the first persons he met was Theodora. He revealed to the woman that they were related, and on the basis of this she provided him unparalleled access to her and Uzun Hassan during his stay.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[16]</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franz_Babinger">Franz Babinger</ref> states she was present at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Erzincan_(1473)">Battle of Erzincan</ref>, where she urged her husband to pursue the defeated army of Mehmed II in order to utterly destroy him.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-17">[17]</ref></p>
<p>After the death of Uzun Hassan in 1478, not much is known about her. She was buried at St. Georges Church in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diyarbakr">Diyarbakr</ref>, where her tomb was shown to an Italian visitor in 1507. However the structure was damaged in 1883 and no longer can be seen.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Bryer-146-15">[15]</ref></p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>By Uzun Hasan, Theodora had several children:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Bryer-146-15">[15]</ref></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Yakub, who is not the son of Uzun Hasan who succeeded him as ruler of the Aq Qoyunlu; Bryer believes he was killed by another wife of Uzun Hasan soon after his death in 1478;</item>
<item>Marta (also called Halima), who married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shaykh_Haydar">Shaykh Haydar</ref> in 1471/1472; Martha became the mother of first Safavid king, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shah_Ismail_I">Shah Ismail I</ref>, who established Shia Islam as the state religion.</item>
<item>Two other daughters. These Caterino Zeno met in Damascus, where they conversed in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pontic_Greek">Pontic Greek</ref>.</item></list>
</text>
