<text id="autogum_interview_doc796" title="part1_CanadaVOTES: CHP candidate Steven Elgersma running in Haldimand—Norfolk" shortTile="partcanadavotes-chp" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-09-18" dateModified="2010-06-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CanadaVOTES%3A_CHP_candidate_Steven_Elgersma_running_in_Haldimand%E2%80%94Norfolk" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Another policy says, section 7 of the 'Charter of Rights' should be amended to qualify the term "everyone" with the words, "including the pre-born child from the moment of conception" as having the right to life, liberty and security of the person. The criminal code must be amended to recognize the personhood of all human beings, from conception to natural death, ensuring their rights under the Constitution. These are only a few out of a few hundred policies a government has to deal with. But these are all Biblical principles which the CHP defends. If there were no CHP Candidate, we could not vote our convictions, and for the Christian principles we hold dear.</p>
<p>In the Spectator of Sep. 16 we could read the often used quote, "Those who do not learn the lessons of history are doomed to repeat them." Parties that rule God out as Supreme Ruler, who will not consider him as King of kings and Lord of lords, who are not based on Christian principles, but instead are based on the 'shifting sands' of public opinion, are repeating the same mistakes of the past. History has proven over and over again that if we live in harmony with God and his commandments, he will shower us with blessings, but the converse is also true.</p>
<p>I am running because I want to stand up for the truth, as opposed to do what seems expedient. I am running because the CHP policies are as good as and better than all others, and which would benefit all Canadians the most, based on the Word of God, the promises of God, borne out by well established history.</p>
<p>I would like to see a fairer and more democratic way of voting, such as Proportional Representation. That way each vote would count. The 'First Past the Post' system we have now should be scrapped in favor of the Mixed Member Proportional. The Conservatives and Liberals are not in favor of it, because they are more interested in power and majority Parties. I wished that this would change soon.</p>
<p>Well, I went on long enough. It is not that I have no opinion or am not interested in the important issues that politicians are to be concerned about, and we will have to address them, but we must be ruled by God and his Biblical principles in order to be the recipients of his blessings. The Bible says, "Blessed is the nation whose God is the Lord."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Previous to this campaign, have you been politically involved? How will you apply your previous work/volunteer/life experience to serving your constituents?</hi></p>
<p>Yes, I ran as a Candidate before, and we will have to face the same issues again, for nothing has changed for the better, but only got worse.</p>
</text>
