<text id="autogum_voyage_doc110" title="Boston/Outer Neighborhoods" shortTile="bostonouter-neighborhoods" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=150948" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Boston/Outer Neighborhoods</head>

<p>The <hi rend="bold">Outer Neighborhoods</hi> of <ref target="Boston">Boston</ref> are four distinct neighborhoods that have been consolidated here for the visitor. These areas are a bit further from the city center and can take a little planning to investigate, but gems abound for the adventurous! Many Bostonians prize the residences in these areas for their suburban feel while remaining within city limits.</p>

<head>Hyde Park</head>
<p>The southernmost neighborhood of Boston, Hyde Park is home to a diverse range of people, housing types and social groups. The area was established in the 1660s and grew into a hub of paper and cotton manufacturing in the eighteenth century. The extension of rail lines from Boston in the 1850s spurred the area's residential development.</p>

<p>Hyde Park was once home to the first all African-American army unit, the 54th Massachusetts Infantry Regiment. They assembled and trained at Camp Meigs in Readville. The area would later briefly become a race track during dawn of the 20th century, before being used as an air combat testing facility during WWI. Today it is a series of light industrial buildings near the Neponset river.</p>

<head>Mattapan</head>
<p>Historically a section of neighboring Dorchester, Mattapan became a part of Boston when Dorchester was annexed in 1870. Predominantly residential, Mattapan is a mix of public housing, triple deckers, and single-family homes. Mattapan Square, where Blue Hill Avenue, River Street, and Cummins Highway meet, is the commercial heart of the neighborhood, home to banks, law offices, restaurants, and retail shops. Mattapan now has the largest Haitian community in Massachusetts, and is also largely made up of African Americans and immigrants from other Caribbean countries.</p>
<head>Roslindale</head>
<p>Roslindale is a primarily residential neighborhood six miles southwest of downtown Boston. Originally part of Roxbury, and after seceding in 1851—the town then voted in 1873 to be annexed to the City of Boston. Roslindale grew residentially as a classic streetcar suburb. Railways were built after the American Civil War, which spawned a new round of commercial development. In the 1920s, Roslindale Village took the shape it has today, with tree-lined Adams Park at its center. </p>

<p>That tree lined park surrounded by local businesses remains attractive to Bostonians in the 21st century. This walkable area has become a haven for those priced out of JP and other areas affected by gentrification issues. Even here prices have seen dramatic rises recently, and residents are working together to maintain the fabric of their community.</p>

<head>West Roxbury</head>
<p>Founded in 1630, West Roxbury is nine miles from downtown Boston, and was originally used as farm land by the then independent town of Roxbury. Seceding in 1851, West Roxbury was annexed by Boston in 1874. Due to this quirk of history, it's often confused with Roxbury, although the two are not connected and don't share a border.</p>

<p>This neighborhood's claim to fame is that it once played host to an experimental Utopian community during the mid 19th century. Called <hi rend="italic">Brook Farm</hi>, members (like Nathaniel Hawthorne) were inspired by the ideals of Transcendentalism, a religious and cultural philosophy based in New England. Ultimately the experiment was financially unsuccessful, although many members looked back on their experience positively. Unfortunately all buildings from this era have since been lost to fire, but the grounds are now a park and available for tours.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>The car is the premiere way to get around in these neighborhoods. You will be further from the city center, so traffic and congestion will be (comparatively) less of an issue. On street parking is cheap and easy to find. Most attractions here are further apart and not well served by public transit. While not necessary, a car will make your life easier while here.</p>

<head>By public transit</head>
<p>Forest Hills station on the Orange line in Roslindale is the only option for direct rapid transit into the city. The next closest option is the Ashmont–Mattapan High Speed Line, a historic trolley and part of the Red line. The last stop on this line serves Mattapan. Used by locals daily, the current rolling stock was built at the end of WWII and is a tourist attraction for any train enthusiast.</p>

<p>Other than those two options, you're going to need to ride the commuter rail. For Hyde Park and Mattapan, take a train from South Station on the Fairmount, Franklin, or Providence/Stoughton lines. For Roslindale or West Roxbury get on the Needham line, also from South Station.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Parish of Christ Church</hi>, 1220 River St (Hyde Park), ☏ +1 617 361-2457 . </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Historic French’s Opera House</hi> (Riverside Theatre Works), 45 Fairmount Ave (Hyde Park), ☏ +1 617 361-7024 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Theodore Parker Church</hi>, 1859 Centre St (West Roxbury), ☏ +1 617 325-4439 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Westerly Burial Ground</hi> (Westerly Burying Ground). </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Forest Hills Cemetery</hi>, 95 Forest Hills Ave (T: Forest Hills), ☏ +1 617 524-0128 . 7AM-dusk daily. Take in a festival, light lanterns, or visit the grave of E.E. Cummings in this 275 acre greenspace. free. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Millennium Park</hi>, 300 Gardner St (West Roxbury), ☏ +1 617 635-4505 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Brook Farm Historic Site</hi>, Baker Street (West Roxbury), ☏ +1 617 698-1802 . </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Holy Name Church</hi>, 1689 Centre St (West Roxbury), ☏ +1 617 325-4865 . Free. </item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">George Wright Golf Course</hi>, 420 West Street (Hyde Park), ☏ +1 617-364-2300 . Named for baseball Hall of Famer and Cincinnati Reds shortstop George Wright. The golf course is a Donald Ross-designed course and is considered one of his finest designs.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Chez Vous</hi>, 11 Rhoades St (Mattapan, T: Morton Street), ☏ +1 617 825-6877 . M Tu 6PM-9PM, W 7PM-10PM, F 8PM-midnight, Sa noon–midnight, Su noon–6:30PM. Roller rink, also billiard and arcade. $5–10.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Laser Quest</hi>, 1580 VFW Pkwy (West Roxbury), ☏ +1 617 325-1005 . M-Th noon-9PM, F Sa noon-11PM, Su noon-8PM.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ron's Gourmet Ice Cream and Twentieth Century Bowling Alley</hi>, 1231 Hyde Park Ave (Hyde Park, T: Fairmount), ☏ +1 617 364-5274 . M-Th 7:30AM-10PM, F 7:30AM-11PM, Sa 8AM-11PM, Su 9AM-10PM. Grab a cone, a rickey, and get in some candlepin bowling at this stalwart bastion of New England traditions. Ice cream is made with high quality ingredients and can be enjoyed by connoisseurs. Tons of kids in here all the time, so the staff knows how to handle them. Bowling $4 per person per game, shoe rental $2.50. Ice cream $3-6.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sky Zone</hi>, 91-B Sprague St (Hyde Park, T: Readville), ☏ +1 857 345-9693 . Su M 10AM-8PM, Tu-Th 3PM-8PM, F 2PM-11PM, Sa 10AM-midnight. Boston's first (and only) trampoline park.</item>
</list>
</text>
