<text id="autogum_academic_doc177" title="Intelligent Image-Based Railway Inspection System Using Deep Learning-Based Object Detection and Weber Contrast-Based Image Comparison" shortTile="intelligent-imagebased" author="Jinbeum Jang, Minwoo Shin, Sohee Lim, Jonggook Park, Joungyeon Kim, Joonki Paik" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1424-8220/19/21/4738/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Facility Inspection Algorithm</head><head> 3.1. Overview</head>
<p>
The proposed system automatically inspects structural defects of railway environment. Most facilities installed in the tunnel, such as overhead rigid conductors, are used to supply electric power into the train through its pantograph. Conventional inspection systems detect all candidates of wears and cracks using single image-based processing methods. The conventional image processing-based approach provides an acceptable detection accuracy for a small FoV images. However, it is difficult to distinguish whether detected region is a real defect or not if the image contains complicated frequency components or complex background. Moreover, single image-based systems cannot detect defects caused by structure’s shape deformation and loss of components since most overhead lines and supporters consist of durable metal materials unlike tunnel walls. </p>

<p>To solve these problems, the proposed system inspects structures and facilities related with overhead lines using a pair of images as shown in <figure>Figure 3</figure>. The image sets are acquired using the line scan camera at the same spots but at different times. We assume that the reference image set  is acquired before the target image set , and they have no defects such as deformation and loss based on human inspection. The target image set is the one to be inspected. The main objective of the proposed system is to detect deformed regions for maintenance of overhead conductors by comparing two images acquired at different times. We exclude cracks on the tunnel wall as inspect subject in the proposed system since they are simply extracted by single image-based inspection systems. </p>

<p>The proposed system consists of three functional steps: (i) image reconstruction using registration based on phase correlation and image composition, (ii) facility detection using deep learning-based object detection, and (iii) facility inspection using image comparison approach based on Weber contrast. In this section, we describe each step of the proposed system in the following subsections. </p>

<head> 3.2. Image Reconstruction</head>
<p>
Given a pair of reference and target images, the proposed system first reconstructs each image. As shown in <figure>Figure 3</figure>, positions between corresponding facilities in the same driving section are not initially aligned because of various problems such as different speed and jittering of the camera. In addition, some parts of facilities are often divided into two neighboring frames in the image acquisition process. </p>

<p>The proposed system registers two images using phase correlation. More specifically, disparity or motion vector between two images is estimated by computing correlation in the frequency domain. It is more efficient to coarsely register two large-scale images than spatial domain-based motion estimation methods because of simple multiplication of fast Fourier transformation (FFT). The motion vector  obtained by maximizing the phase correlation is defined as

(1)

where  and  respectively represent the <hi rend="italic">i</hi>-th frame acquired without temporal synchronization, and  and  the Fourier and its inverse transformation operations, respectively. Superscript ‘*’ indicates the conjugate of a complex number and ‘·’ a pixel-by-pixel multiplication. In the proposed method, we translate  by the horizontal motion value  to prevent deformation of  in which we should inspect facilities. The positions of facilities are coarsely aligned by translating  using phase correlation as shown in <figure>Figure 4</figure>a. </p>

<p>Once  is translated, we lose the left and right parts of the image. When we obtain the negative motion value, the translated version of  has an empty space in the left-side region. The right-side region with the intensity values is naturally lost as shown in <figure>Figure 4</figure>a. To fill the empty space, the proposed system reconstructs the image by attaching some parts of the neighboring frame as shown in <figure>Figure 4</figure>a,b. We then respectively generate the final reconstructed images  and  by attaching appropriate regions of the neighboring images onto  and  since the left-side facility of  is sometimes lost in the image acquisition process. Although some regions are duplicated, we can prevent from skipping the inspection of the regions. The lost region in  is used when reconstructing neighbor frames at the previous or next inspection stage. </p>

<head> 3.3. Facility Detection Using Convolutional Neural Network</head>
<p>
To automatically inspect railway facilities, we should find out their positions and classify types of them since each type has different risk management standard for a deformed area. A simple approach is to define absolute positions of all facilities in advance. However, it is inefficient since we should change the facility positions whenever the reference image set is replaced by new ones. </p>
</text>
