<text id="autogum_interview_doc634" title="part3_Wikinews holds a follow-up interview with Kevin Baugh, president of the Republic of Molossia" shortTile="partwikinews-holds" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-05-01" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_holds_a_follow-up_interview_with_Kevin_Baugh%2C_president_of_the_Republic_of_Molossia" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN (Joseph Ford)</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Molossia has its own systems of measurement and dates. Tell us about them.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">President Baugh:</hi> Our dates are based from the year that Molossia was founded, back in 1977, thus today is 29 April 2008 XXXI. Founder's Day, the day Molossia was founded, was 26 May 1977.</p>
<p>Our measurement system is called the Kokintz System, named for Professor Kokintz of Grand Fenwick.  All of the units of measurement are based of things unique to Molossia. The basic unit of length, the Norton, is based on the length of my hand. The basic unit of volume, the Simms, is equal to a can of Diet Pepsi, my favorite drink. The basic unit of weight, the Fenwick, is based on a tube of Cookie Dough, and the basic unit of temperature, the Zenda, is based on the height of the First Lady. We like to keep things interesting.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN (Joseph Ford)</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Molossia also has its own time zone. Tell us about it.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">President Baugh:</hi> Again, to keep things interesting, we devised our own time zone, Molossian Standard Time. It is 39 minutes ahead of Pacific Standard Time and 21 minutes behind Mountain Standard Time.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN (Joseph Ford)</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Can people visit Molossia?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">President Baugh:</hi> Yes, absolutely!  We love have tourists visit. We have thus far had 14 non-family visit Molossia in the past year, our first ever arriving in spring 2007 XXX.  A visit to Molossia takes about an hour, during which I take all visitors on a tour of our country and tell them about Molossia and micronations in general. Cookie dough is served, too, of course, and I stamp passports. It is very important, though, that all visitors contact our government, to arrange a date and time for the visit.  Please do not show up unannounced!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN (Joseph Ford)</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Are there any tourist attractions in Molossia? What can a visitor see and do while in your nation?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Presdient Baugh:</hi> Yes, we do have a few sights to see. Visitors can see Republic Square, the Peace Pole, the micronation direction sign, Norton Park, the Molossia Railroad, and the Tower of the Winds. A visit to Molossia is always interesting, if for no other reason than it's "the country just up the street on the right".</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN (Joseph Ford)</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Are you planning on expanding Molossia's borders in the near future?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">President Baugh:</hi> We would love to do so, but I think we are about as big as we can be right now.  Of course, should our country ever had a large economic windfall, then we will certainly expand.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN (Joseph Ford)</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Molossia is one of the world's most serious and well known micronations. In under ten years, it has gained the attention of the media and respect of thousands. Where do you see your country in another ten years?</hi></p>
</text>
