<text id="autogum_voyage_doc263" title="Dallas-Fort Worth International Airport" shortTile="dallasfort-worth" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=123860" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Dallas-Fort Worth International Airport</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.dfwairport.com">Dallas/Fort Worth International Airport</ref></hi> ( DFW ) is one of the busiest airports in the <ref target="United%20States">United States</ref>. Equally positioned between <ref target="Dallas">Dallas</ref> and <ref target="Fort%20Worth">Fort Worth</ref>, DFW is a great airport to fly into. Don't forget that as you drive out of the airport, you will have to pay a toll to leave. DFW is the chief hub of American Airlines, which controls well over 80% of all the flights.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>The airport was designed in the 1960s to allow for people to park next to their gate and make a short walk to their plane. However, modern security requirements and the hub-and-spoke system have made its long narrow semi-circular terminals somewhat inefficient. Recent improvements including a people-mover tram system (inside security) and renovated terminals have overcome this challenge to make DFW a great connecting airport. Also, the terminal layout with 4 semi-circular terminals and 1 squared one means that the airport has multiple security checkpoints and shorter lines.</p>

<p>The largest selection of restaurants and shops are in Terminal D, while A, B, C, and E have a few decent restaurants spread throughout. An ongoing renovation of the older terminals will improve the selection. Part of A has been completed.</p>

<head>Flights</head>


<p>DFW International has 5 terminals. <hi rend="bold">Terminals A, B, and C</hi> handle domestic flights, while <hi rend="bold">Terminal D and E</hi> handles international and domestic flights. All terminals are connected by a quick rail system inside security and buses outside of security. <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.aa.com">American Airlines</ref></hi> and its affiliate <hi rend="bold">American Eagle</hi> has a dominant position at DFW airport and occupies all of Terminals A, B, and C and parts of D and E, though exact locations can change due to an ongoing renovation of 5 of the terminals. A Terminal F, which will be in the current Express South parking lot, is in planning.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Terminal A</hi>- American Airlines</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Terminal B</hi>- American Eagle</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Terminal C</hi>- American Airlines</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Terminal D</hi>- AeroMexico, American Airlines/American Eagle, Avianca, British Airways, Cayman Airways, Emirates, ETIHAD, Interjet, Japan Airlines, Korean Air, Lufthansa, QANTAS, Qatar Airways, Sun Country Airlines, <ref target="http://www.texassky.com">Texas Sky</ref> (for flights to Del Rio &amp; Victoria); <ref target="http://flybranson.com">VIA Airlines</ref> (to Branson, Missouri), and Volaris.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Terminal E</hi>- Air Canada, Alaska Airlines, American Eagle, Delta Air Lines, Frontier Airlines, JetBlue, Spirit Airlines, United Airlines, WestJet.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">DFW Corporate Airport Terminal</hi>- <ref target="http://www.boutiqueair.com">Boutique Airlines</ref> (To Clovis &amp; Carlsbad, New Mexico, and to Greenville, Mississippi); <ref target="http://iflysouthern.com">Southern Airways Express</ref> (Harrison, El Dorado and Hot Springs, Arkansas); and other private VIP flights. The corporate air terminal is located behind the American Airlines cargo terminal north of Terminal A. This terminal is not connected with the other terminals or from the main toll road that connects to the other terminals (International Pkwy). It is only accessed by the service road outside of the toll gates. Therefore, Boutique Air &amp; Southern Airways Express provide a shuttle from the other airline terminals to their terminal on request.</item>
</list>


<p>Note: If you're traveling with <ref target="http://www.southwest.com">Southwest</ref> they only land and take off at <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.dallas-lovefield.com/">Dallas Love Field</ref></hi> ( DAL ), another airport closer into downtown Dallas. They do not offer flights into or out of Dallas Ft Worth International Airport. <ref target="http://www.alaskaair.com">Alaska Airlines</ref> and <ref target="http://www.delta.com">Delta/Delta Connection</ref> offer flights to both airports.</p>

<head>Arrive</head>
<p>For those arriving on international flights, <ref target="http://www.cbp.gov/xp/cgov/travel/">Immigration and Customs</ref> process usually takes 15–30 minutes, but can take over an hour at peak times. The busiest times are in the afternoon.</p>

<head>Transfer</head>
<p>Like all airports in the United States, there are no special transit facilities for international transfers. That means that if you are arriving from an international flight and have an immediate connection, you will still have to pass through Customs and Immigration. For details of entry and visa requirements see <ref target="United%20States%20of%20America%23Get%20in">get in section of United States page</ref>.</p>

<head>Private aviation</head>
<p>Dallas is home to the third highest number of Fortune 500 companies in the United States behind only <ref target="New%20York%20City">New York City</ref> and <ref target="Houston">Houston</ref>, making it a one of the busiest regions for business and luxury aviation in the country. It's also frequently used by business jets as a refueling stop for cross-county and intercontinental flights. Although private planes typically use Dallas Love Field (FAA: DAL) and other <ref target="https://www.aircharteradvisors.com/private-jet-hire/texas/dallas/airports/">DFW-area airports focused on private aviation</ref>, Dallas Fort-Worth International is still used by corporate aircraft, fractionally owned aircraft, and jet card programs.</p>

<ref target="https://www.dfwairport.com/corporateaviation/"><hi rend="bold">DFW Corporate Aviation</hi></ref> operates the only private terminal at KDFW, located to the northside of the passenger terminals opposite the Express North Parking Lot. The terminal is accessible via N Service Rd and E 16th St/N 24th Ave behind the American Airlines Cargo terminal. <ref target="https://w3.ameriflight.com/"><hi rend="bold">Ameriflight</hi></ref> is the only charter operator at KDFW, however, air charter brokers including <ref target="https://www.allianceaircharter.com/"><hi rend="bold">Alliance Air Charter</hi></ref> and <ref target="http://www.privatejetsdallas.com/"><hi rend="bold">Private Jets Dallas</hi></ref> offer access to charter planes throughout Texas and across the country for private flights to/from DFW International, with planes ranging from single and twin-engine propeller aircraft, to luxury Gulfstreams and business jets. Private flights may experience a bit of a taxi upon arrival, but will enjoy quick departures from Runway 17R.

<head>By car</head>
<p>The main way most travelers get to DFW is by driving to the airport. The <ref target="Dallas-Fort%20Worth%20Metroplex">Dallas-Fort Worth Metroplex</ref> has grown up around the airport to the point that major expressways form a complete (though oddly-shaped) loop around the airport, with a spiderweb of freeways and toll roads going in all directions. Routes to the airport are noted on road signs 10 miles or more from the airport, though the numerous multilevel interchanges will make it difficult to just head to the airport without looking at a map or using a GPS device. If you go by car, you cannot avoid the tolls, so have some cash with you.</p>

<p>While there are many different parking areas and 5 terminals, all the terminals and the express and garage parking are on International Parkway, a toll road that goes from the north entrance to the south entrance and connects to all the major highways. The <hi rend="bold">North Entrance</hi> connects to the DFW Connector, a several mile long interchange of SH 121, 114, and 26, as well as Interstate 635. A recently completed $1 B construction untangled what was a confusing and disjointed mix of highways that often hopelessly congested. However, the redesigned interchange eliminated the exit to the airport loop road for using the North Remote parking lot from International Parkway, so you should take Texas Trail exit from 121/114 from the west or Freeport exit on 114 from the east. The <hi rend="bold">South Entrance</hi> meets with an SH 183 near interchanges with SH 360 to the west and President George Bush Turnpike (PGBT) to the east. South remote parking and the car rental center are both easily reached from the south entrance before the toll plaza.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> From <hi rend="bold">Downtown Dallas</hi> take I-35E north to S.H. 114/183 ("Airport Freeway"). When 114 and 183 split, you have a choice to go the north or south entrance of the airport. SH 183 (Airport Freeway goes to the south entrance, while 114 goes the north entrance.</item>
<item> From <hi rend="bold">Downtown Fort Worth</hi> take SH 121 to SH 183 (Airport Freeway). When 121 and 183 split, you can either take 121 to the north entrance or 183 to the south entrance.</item>
<item> From <hi rend="bold">Collin County or anywhere north</hi> take either SH 121 (toll road in Collin Co) to the north entrance or PGBT to 114 westbound to the north entrance.</item>
<item> From <hi rend="bold">Arlington and anywhere south</hi> take either SH 360 or PGBT north to the south entrance interchange.</item>
<item> From <hi rend="bold">Denton or further north</hi> take either I-35W south to SH 114 eastbound or I-35E to SH 121 toll road south bound to the north entrance.</item>
</list>
</text>
