<text id="autogum_interview_doc788" title="part3_Eurovision &amp;apos;73 winner Anne Marie David discusses her four-decade career and the Contest, past and present" shortTile="parteurovision--winner" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-02-15" dateModified="2012-02-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eurovision_%2773_winner_Anne_Marie_David_discusses_her_four-decade_career_and_the_Contest%2C_past_and_present" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">AMD</hi>: I had the immense joy of working a lot of time and also living over there, and for me it was the discovery of an immense culture, well beyond what I could have imagined. It was an encounter with a people, the Turkish people, whom we don't make the effort to know in depth. Most of the time there are too many clichés that are in no way reflections of what these people truly are... I am not talking about the leaders, I'm talking about the citizens of a country. I learned about them, to understand them, to exchange with them, in all their diversity, and God knows that in matters of diversity Turkey knows what it's talking about. I spent rare moments there surrounded by Turks, Armenians, Greeks, and Jews sitting at the same table and speaking the same language, the language of love and friendship... In all the whole world it's the same thing. All is well except when politics or religion intervene.</p>
<head id="Eurovision_'79">Eurovision '79</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> In 1979, you decided to compete for a spot at the Eurovision final again, this time for France. Why did you want to go back a second time? Considering your past success, were you fairly confident that you would end up being the French representative that year?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AMD</hi>: It was a taste for risk that guided me, but a measured risk, because 'Winner of the Grand Eurovision Prize 1973' is a lifetime title that one does not risk losing if one takes another chance. The place [you received] remains [that] place. When I accepted [the opportunity] to try representing France in 1979, I knew that the rules of the game were different than the ones in Luxembourg. Winner [from] 1973 or not, it didn't change [things] much since one needed to pass through a selection process. I played the game like everyone else and it was the public who voted for the 12 semi-finalists. Unfortunately television was on strike, and the finale could not be held as planned. The 12 semi-finalists were therefore viewed by a jury of professionals, and I was retained. But I respected the rule all the way to the end, and above all French television <hi rend="italic">never</hi> modified the rule until the final candidate selection. I would have appreciated that France 3 [<hi rend="italic">Editor's note: The current television station broadcasting Eurovision in France</hi>] respects the rule of the game the same way this year... and that <hi rend="italic">all</hi> the candidates win or lose in loyal fashion, by respecting the rule. This will not be the case and I regret that... [<hi rend="italic">Editor's note: After decades of public voting to select France's finalist, France 3 selected their artist internally this year despite originally calling for finalists.</hi>]</p>
</text>
