<text id="autogum_interview_doc774" title="part1_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Family Coalition Party candidate Ray Scott, Algoma-Manitoulin" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-01" dateModified="2010-06-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Family_Coalition_Party_candidate_Ray_Scott%2C_Algoma-Manitoulin" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Where MSAs are being used around the world, huge cost savings are being realized. More importantly, research shows these cost savings are not resulting in a decline in people’s health. The cost savings achieved through MSAs will be re-invested in healthcare areas such as long term care, pharmacare and expensive medical technologies. Lastly, the MSA plan is the only party plan that provides an incentive for eating well, quitting smoking and getting exercise: take care of your body, and you will stay away from the doctor and avoid paying the Liberal Health Tax. Further, unused portions of MSAs can be rolled into RRSPs.</p>
<p>The shortage of healthcare professionals will be dealt with by increasing compensation packages to attract doctors and nurses to the province. These compensation packages are needed to win over doctors and nurses in the international bidding war to Ontario. Prioritizing the provincial budget will pay for the big expense of winning the bidding war for healthcare expenses. This means cuts in other government areas will be necessary.</p>
<p>Issue #2: Farming</p>
<p>The Family Coalition Party has always believed that the family farm is one of the basic building blocks of Ontario’s economy. The FCP will propose “Right to Farm” legislation. The farming sector must be free to operate responsibly, without interference regarding standard farm operating practices. The FCP will continue to support the responsible use of approved chemicals in agriculture. Lastly, I propose an “Adopt-a-Steer” program so that farmers can sell their meat locally at a value-added price. Under our current system, farmers receive the smallest fraction of the cost of beef that people pay at the store. If I want to buy my neighbour’s meat, I should be able to, and it is good for the farmer.</p>
<p>Issue #3: Infrastructure</p>
<p>The infrastructure of roads, bridges and water systems is crumbling in Ontario. Investment in safety sensitive infrastructure areas is essential. I propose the creation of reserve accounts in municipal budgets for water systems, for example. These accounts need an initial cash infusion from the provincial government over the short term until the reserve accounts are self-sustaining through a portion of property tax rates.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly?</hi></p>
<p>The first thing I would do is introduce legislation banning sex-selection abortions. Even China has a law like this. Ontario should not be second to China for anything when it comes to human rights.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are the property taxes in your riding at a fair level for the amount of services received in the municipality?</hi></p>
<p>Most people do not believe they receive good value for the property taxes they pay. In general, people used to pay $1.00 and got $1.30 in services. Now we pay $1.00 and get $0.70 back in services. The FCP is committed to freezing the education portion of property tax rates. We will remove the education portion of taxes from agricultural lands. Concerning Market Value Assessment increases, if a significant increase is required, it must be phased in over time. Halting provincial downloading that forces higher expenses on municipalities and towns can also relieve property taxes. Lastly, property taxes going up are also a response to the pressures of an aging population with a shrinking tax base, so we either need to lower our expectations of government and pay less taxes; or have more babies.</p>
</text>
