<text id="autogum_whow_doc540" title="Convince Your Parents to Get You a Pet if You Already Have Many" shortTile="convince-parents" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2013-03-12" dateModified="2018-12-11" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Convince-Your-Parents-to-Get-You-a-Pet-if-You-Already-Have-Many" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Convince Your Parents to Get You a Pet if You Already Have Many</head><p>Everyone's been there--that moment when you're browsing the Internet and you come across a video of some lucky duck that owns a guinea pig, rat, dog, or something else. You instantly want one, and the quest to convince our parents begins! But... you already have a Fido or a Priscilla. Follow this guide to help convince your parents anyway!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Research thoroughly. Although this is a given, you must be prepared to show off in front of your parents and impress them with your extensive knowledge. Not to mention, if you give improper care to your pet, it will be unhappy and mean. This won't make anyone happy. <figure rend="Convince Your Parents to Get You a Pet if You Already Have Many Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Prepare your information in a report- but be ready to answer any questions! Also, be sure to say anything that will indicate that the pets you already have will not affect your new furry-or feathered- friend.
<list type="unordered"><item>Cats are a very controversial topic, especially if you're getting a smaller pet. If you have a cat, try to convince your peers that your new pet will be far from danger.</item>
<item>If you're asking for a bigger pet, such as a dog, try to come up with strategies to prevent conflict between the two. <figure rend="Convince Your Parents to Get You a Pet if You Already Have Many Step 2.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Try to be as responsible as possible. Make some kind of deal with with your parents; for example, if you keep your room clean and do all the things a perfect angel child will do, they'll consider getting you a pet. #*Never explicitly say, "Get me a pet." It's everything that you'll do stacked up on top of each other that'll help convince a parent. <figure rend="Convince Your Parents to Get You a Pet if You Already Have Many Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pay for everything! If your parents have to fork over $200 to buy you a pet, that is almost a guarantee you will get a no. Save up--if you aren't willing to spend some cash on your friend, maybe you shouldn't have him/her after all. <figure rend="Convince Your Parents to Get You a Pet if You Already Have Many Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find out why your parents don't want you to have this certain pet. If your parent has a serious reason that you can't get a pet, like if you want a dog, but you already own one that hates other dogs, and for some reason you can't separate them, then try suggesting another pet, like a ferret, hedgehog, or hamster. <figure rend="Convince Your Parents to Get You a Pet if You Already Have Many Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't cry, scream, or act immature if they say no. Just come up with a reason to counter their no.</item>
<item>If it's not the right time, make it wait. Observe your peer's behavior. If they are cheery, it's a perfect time to ruin their day!</item>
<item>Don't nag, but <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Persistent">be persistent</ref>. Parents will almost always say no, and then maybe even try to ignore your request.</item>
<item>If a recent pet has passed away and you're looking for a replacement to fill that empty space in your heart, it would be a good time to ask.</item>
<item>Sometimes your parents just won't break, so sometimes, you have to give it time. Sometimes maybe even a year, but if you really want the pet, you will still want it when the time comes to bring it up again.</item>
<item>Politely ask, and if they say no, wait two to three days before asking again.</item>
<item>If you already have a pet, and don't take full responsibility of it, take more responsibility so you can show your parents that you are responsible enough for another one.</item>
<item>Do all your chores and everything before they ask. They will immediately think you are more responsible.</item>
<item>Come up with good reasons why you should have both, but make sure that there are no counter arguments to your reasons because of there are then it might seem like your parents know more than you about getting pets and just say no and remember not to forget about your other pet(s) if you do get a new one because of you do then your parents might give away one or all of your pets.</item>
<item>If you have other animals try to clean, bathe, feed and spend time with them and maybe they will see how responsible you can be.</item>
<item>Be very responsible and show off in front of your parents whether that means picking up trash or cleaning up the dishes to keeping your room tidy but do it without being asked. Don't just do it for a day, keep at it hard wok pays off.</item>
<item>Find what animal you want, then research all about it, frequently throw facts about the animal to them but not to often that your annoying, then find a good time to ask. If they say no, ask why then solve the problems. Ask again a few days later, no again? Make a speech!</item>
<item>If there are any animals in the house hold that are not yours, try taking care of it for a week or two, this will show your parents that you are able to take care of another pet.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Remember never to get bored of your pets. Don't forget about your old pet because you're excited about a new one--they're all living creatures and deserve equal care and respect.</item></list>
</text>
