<text id="autogum_voyage_doc494" title="Chiapas" shortTile="chiapas" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=7091" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Chiapas</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Chiapas</hi> is a state in <ref target="Yucat%C3%A1n%20and%20the%20South">southern Mexico</ref>.</p>

<p>Chiapas is about as far south as you can get in Mexico. It borders <ref target="Guatemala">Guatemala</ref> on the southeast, the Pacific on the southwest, and the states of Oaxaca, Veracruz, and Tabasco from west to northeast. </p>

<head>Cities</head>
 

<list type="unordered">
<item> – the state capital: large, hot, relatively modern (Sam's Club, Office Depot, Wal-Mart), and home to one of the world's great zoos.</item>
<item> – a nice fishing village on the pacific coast of the state. Cheap palapas available.</item>
<item> – the oldest Spanish city in Chiapas.</item>
<item> – surprisingly sophisticated.</item>
<item> – gateway to the Mayan ruins of Toniná</item>
<item> – also known as <hi rend="bold">Jovel</hi>, 2,200m, beautiful, Mayan, lots of handicrafts, small ex-pat community.</item>
<item> – Tsotsil indigenous village.</item>
<item> </item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> – Mayan ruins</item>
<item> – Mayan ruins</item>
<item> – Mayan ruins</item>
<item> – Maya ruins</item>
<item> – Waterfall</item>
<item> – Waterfall</item>
<item> – Canyon and Reservoir (includes Christmas Tree Falls)</item>
<item> </item>
<item> – Ecotourism in the heart of the tallest mangroves in North America</item>
<item> </item>
</list>


<head>Suggested reading</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="italic">The Lawless Roads</hi> by Graham Greene. Graham Greene describes his journey to <ref target="San%20Cristobal%20de%20las%20Casas">San Cristobal de las Casas</ref> through Chiapas and <ref target="Tabasco">Tabasco</ref> in the 1930s. ( )</item>
<item> <hi rend="italic">The Power and the Glory</hi> by Graham Greene. A whiskey priest, a corrupt church, and Chiapas all set in one of Greene's most powerful books. ( )</item>
</list>


<head>Talk</head>
<p>Most people will speak Spanish, but this is less common among the indigenous peoples, where Tsotsil and Tseltal are the most common languages. Very few who can speak English, almost always very badly.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>It has a small international airport in the state capital, <ref target="Tuxtla%20Guti%C3%A9rrez">Tuxtla Gutiérrez</ref>, and is also connected by highways (some are toll roads, or <hi rend="italic">cuota</hi>) with the surrounding states and Guatemala.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>The easiest way to get around within cities is probably by private car, taxi, or <hi rend="italic">colectivo</hi>. Colectivos are small vans or buses that are very cheap and follow specific routes. The main destinations on the route of each colectivo are listed on the right side of its windshield, though it is sometimes hard to tell if it is really going your way. Asking the driver usually works, but don't expect him or her to speak English.</p>

<p>Outside of cities, the best way to get around is by private car, bus (slow, with frequent stops), colectivo (a little more expensive than in the city), taxis, or pickups (<hi rend="italic">camionetas</hi>). Taxis outside of cities charge very high rates if it is not their regular route, so make sure the driver knows you do not want a "<hi rend="italic">viaje especial</hi>" (special trip). Sharing taxis is very common, and almost universal outside cities. The pickups that are for public transportation are usually identifiable. Try to get a seat in the cab, unless you enjoy being pressed against a large group of sweaty locals in the hot sun. Pickups are also fairly slow and make frequent stops, but they are faster than the bus.</p>

<head>Volunteering</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Volunteer as a Human Rights Observer in the autonomous Zapatista communities contact <hi rend="italic">Capise</hi> (brigadas@capise.org.mx) for short (5 days) activities or for longer volunteership contact <hi rend="italic">Frayba</hi> <ref target="http://www.frayba.org.mx/index.php"></ref>.</item>
<item> Participate as a volunteer or group coordinator on <hi rend="bold">sustainable projects in Maya communities</hi>. The NGO <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.natate.org">NATATE A.C.</ref></hi> focuses on the following fields: alternative technologies, waste management, water(capture and filtering), Education, reforestation, construction. Opportunities are available for short and long term voluntary service.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mole</hi>: Like happiness sauce. Made from several or many varieties of chili peppers.</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pozol</hi>. Chocolate/maize drink from Chiapas.</item>
</list>


<head>Stay safe</head>

<p>Like any other city and remote location in the world has its problem, but be aware of your personal belongings all the time, and do not walk with jewelry and expensive objects in sight. Chiapas is usually in secure state, where the warmth of people will make you feel at home.</p>

<head>Go next</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Oaxaca%20%28state%29">Oaxaca</ref> - 10 hours on the bus</item>
<item> <ref target="Guatemala">Guatemala</ref> - About 10 hours to Guatemala City.</item>
<item> <ref target="Tabasco">Tabasco</ref> -</item>
<item> <ref target="Campeche">Campeche</ref> - About 10 hours on the bus.</item>
<item> Regular flights to <ref target="Mexico%20City">Mexico City</ref>, <ref target="Guadalajara">Guadalajara</ref> and other major destinations in Mexico,</item>
</list>
</text>
