<text id="autogum_whow_doc113" title="Check Internet Data Usage in MTNL" shortTile="check-internet-data" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2012-10-02" dateModified="2019-03-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Check-Internet-Data-Usage-in-MTNL" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Check Internet Data Usage in MTNL</head><p>By providing excellent telephone and broadband services in Bombay and Delhi at affordable price, MTNL has become the choice of many people. Many people take internet plans limited to a few GB data usage and hence it becomes necessary for them to regularly keep themselves updated with their data usage details. Below are given some easy steps to do so.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Login to MTNL website for this. Just type <ref target="http://register.mtnldelhi.in/jsp/customer/Login.jsp">http://register.mtnldelhi.in/jsp/customer/Login.jsp</ref> in the address bar of your web browser and press Enter. <figure rend="Check Internet Data Usage in MTNL Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>As a web page requesting for username and password comes up  have your land line telephone number(through which you are accessing internet) and Customer Account number with you. Customer Account number can be found on your telephone bill under the title C/A no. <figure rend="Check Internet Data Usage in MTNL Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Enter your telephone number as your Username and Customer Account number as your Password. Click on Login. While entering telephone number as username DON'T enter STD code in the beginning. For example: if your telephone number is 27051744 and customer account number is ********** (it is a unique 10 digit numeric code), then your username is:27051744 and password is **********.The site provides you with the option to use Virtual Keyboard as well in case you don't have a keyboard with you. <figure rend="Check Internet Data Usage in MTNL Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>As  a new web page opens up find links like: Home, My info, Email Account, Usage information, Customer Care etc. <figure rend="Check Internet Data Usage in MTNL Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on Usage Information. <figure rend="Check Internet Data Usage in MTNL Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>View your usage limit, unbilled usage, total free and other important details. Also you will be shown the duration for which this data is presented. You can change this duration to obtain similar statistics for other duration also. Now click on Search. <figure rend="Check Internet Data Usage in MTNL Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The result will be displayed in tabular form showing all the details of your upload, download and total data volume. Start and end time (date wise) is also shown. <figure rend="Check Internet Data Usage in MTNL Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Read, note down or download these details as per your convenience. Download button is provided in the bottom. <figure rend="Check Internet Data Usage in MTNL Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>After completing your work  log out from this website. <figure rend="Check Internet Data Usage in MTNL Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Log out after your work is over to ensure security of your account.</item>
<item>Enter your Username and Password carefully.</item>
<item>While entering telephone number as username DON'T enter STD code in the beginning.</item>
<item>Change the password if you wish to increase your account security.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Remember put "@a" at end of your phone number for eg. If your number is 28581515 type it as 28581515@a. This is because this is how the MTNL saves our number in their database.</item>
<item>Your password will be your C.A number. Refer to your MTNL bill or call MTNL office to know your CA number.</item>
<item>If you got error that your Password is wrong please don't give that same password many times because it will cause your number getting locked. And it will be pain to unlock it again</item>
<item>If you don't understand anything then don't proceed ask MTNL customer care for any help</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Internet Connection</item></list>
</text>
