<text id="autogum_bio_doc257" title="Koahou" shortTile="koahou" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-11-17" dateModified="2018-04-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Koahou" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Koahou</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Koahou</hi> (died 1826) was a Hawaiian high chief who succeeded his father <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kamanawa">Kamanawa</ref> as one of the chief counselors of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kamehameha_I">Kamehameha I</ref>.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>He was the son of High Chief <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kamanawa">Kamanawa</ref> and High Chiefess Kekelaokalani.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEFornander1880320-1">[1]</ref>
His father Kamanawa, along with Koahou's uncle  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kameʻeiamoku">Kameʻeiamoku</ref>, were known as the "royal twins" and helped <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kamehameha_I">Kamehameha I</ref> come to power and served him as advisors.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEKuykendall196553-2">[2]</ref>
His mother Kekelaokalani was the daughter of High Chief Kauakahiakua, son of Lonomakahonua and Kahapoohiwi,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEKamakau1992127-3">[3]</ref> and High Chiefess <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kekuiapoiwa_I">Kekuʻiapoiwa I</ref>, the former wife of King Kekaulike of Maui.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Wilcox-4">[4]</ref>
His siblings included two brothers: Noukana and Amamalua, a sister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peleuli">Peleuli</ref>, who became one of the wives of Kamehameha I, and a half-sister Piʻipiʻi Kalanikaulihiwakama.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEKamakau1992221-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>After the death of his father and the passing of the last of the four warrior chiefs that supported Kamehameha I, the sons of the four were chosen to replace them in the Council of Chiefs. They included Koahou, son of Kamanawa, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hoapili">Hoapili</ref>, son of Kameʻeiamoku, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keeaumoku_II">Kahekili Keʻeaumoku</ref>, son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keeaumoku_Pāpaiahiahi">Keʻeaumoku Pāpaʻiahiahi</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Naihe">Naihe</ref>, son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keaweaheulu">Keaweaheulu</ref>. They were given the same honors, rights and powers that their fathers had held including any lands that were originally awarded to them as spoils of Kamehameha's conquest.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEKuykendall196553-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEKamakau1992190-6">[6]</ref></p>
<figure><caption>Rev. Artemas Bishop, 1857</caption></figure>
<p>Koahou would continue to serve Kamehameha I's successor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kamehameha_II">Kamehameha II</ref> and briefly served under the child monarch <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kamehameha_III">Kamehameha III</ref>. His principal place of residence was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hilo">Hilo</ref>, which was called <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hilo_Bay">Byron's Bay</ref> by the foreigners at the time after <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Byron,_7th_Baron_Byron">George Byron, 7th Baron Byron</ref> who brought the bodies of King Kamehameha II and Queen <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kamāmalu">Kamāmalu</ref> back from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London">London</ref> aboard <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HMS_Blonde_(1819)">HMS <hi rend="italic">Blonde</hi></ref>. Even after the arrival of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Missionaries_to_Hawaii">missionaries</ref>, Koahou never converted to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christianity">Christianity</ref> or if he ever did, he didn't take their religious teaching very seriously. On December 25, 1825, Rev. Artemas Bishop complained how Koahou's behavior and continual practice of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polygamy">polygamy</ref> were discouraging the natives of Hilo from converting:</p>
<p>Preached morning and evening at the usual place of worship. The house was filled, and good attention paid in general to the word. But it is to be regretted, that no better example is set, and, in general, no more countenance given to religious things, by Koahou, the principal chief at this place. He still retains three wives, and revels in all the abominations of heathenism, while neither he, or his people, are often at church. Such an example, from a principal chief, has a pernicious effect upon the common people, and accordingly, there are found more open opposers among the natives at this, than at any other station....<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBishop182752-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>Koahou died in 1826, at a place called Punahou, near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hilo">Hilo</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEKamakau1992305-8">[8]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEKameʻeleihiwa1992102-9">[9]</ref>
It isn't known whether he left any descendants or what happened to his lands and properties after his death, but they were probably inherited by his sister Peleuli and her descendants.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEKameʻeleihiwa1992107-10">[10]</ref></p>
<head>Ancestry</head>
</text>
