<text id="autogum_reddit_doc148" title="Day 6" shortTile="day-" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-03-31" dateModified="2018-03-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/88lrq8" speakerList="#Folkcharm, #crypto_soup" speakerCount="2">
<head>Day 6</head>
<sp who="#Folkcharm">
<p>TL;DR: Please leave OTC advice for managing opioid-withdrawal-induced RLS, it's my primary symptom and it's a total monster. Quit cold turkey on Monday; no time off work, which requires pretty strict focus (I'm a programmer). It's tough for me to make an exact estimate on my dosage because I used pills rather than measuring out my kratom, but weighing several unfilled capsules and several filled capsules, it looks like I was on 11-ish grams two times daily, sometimes a third thrown in for good measure. I've taken kratom pretty constantly for about 2 years; at my highest I was at (again, weighing the pills) 14-ish grams 3 times a day. I don't feel any psychological side-effects. I don't like people and I keep to myself, mostly, anyways. I've been reading a lot, playing video games, anything to keep my mind off of RLS, which has been my major symptom. I have been taking gabapentin 300 mg 2x daily; afternoon and night. My last pill is staring me in the face - don't want to break through one set of withdrawals and into another. I can tell I'm going to need it to sleep tonight. I see a doctor for the first time in over a decade on the 17th. If I can't manage the RLS tomorrow night, I will likely go back on a small dose of kratom at night to stave it away until I can see a doc, and hopefully get some ambien or... something. Anything to keep the RLS away. So that's why I'm making this post... I have some agmatine I never really used... will that kill the RLS? I hear magnesium works, I'm getting dressed to go get some now. Exercise keeps it off /while/ I'm exercising and no longer. The gaba keeps it dull enough for about 30 minutes - enough to get a reprieve or to try and fall asleep. Hot showers help while I'm in the shower and no longer - to be honest, I might spend most of tomorrow in a hot shower if it won't go away. Could really use some help with some OTC solutions for opioid-induced RLS, my good people. Thanks for reading!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#crypto_soup">
<p>Get your doc to prescribe you clonidine. Was a life saver for me during oxy WD. Kept the RLS and other symptoms at bay during the night. </p>
<p>Also, this may sound goofy, but get yourself a bar of Irish spring soap. Stick it under your sheets at the bottom of your bed near your legs. Watch as it helps take away a lot of the RLS. The science behind it apparently is that the magnesium inside the soap will help settle your leg muscles if it’s close by to them. No joke - google it. </p>
<p>Hope this helps</p>
</sp>
</text>
