<text id="autogum_academic_doc343" title="Robust Analysis of PM2.5 Concentration Measurements in the Ecuadorian Park La Carolina" shortTile="robust-analysis-pm" author="Wilmar Hernandez, Alfredo Mendez, Angela Maria Diaz-Marquez, Rasa Zalakevic" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1424-8220/19/21/4648/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Robust Data Analysis</head>
<p>
This section is divided into three parts. First, a statistical summary of the data is presented. Second, a nonparametric inferential analysis is performed. Finally, the section ends using robust estimators to analyze measures of centralization and dispersion of the data of the variables under study. The latter is justified by the fact that robust estimators are relatively insensitive to small changes in the data. </p>

<head> 4.1. Statistical Summary of the Dataset</head>
<p>
In accordance with, in this research work, there is a set of data that is going to be analyzed in order to properly interpret the relationships between them. Furthermore, in this subsection, different types of graphs will be used with the intention of showing a simple transmission of the analysis and conclusions. Here, it has been considered that these graphs will allow a simple comparison between the data and, on the other hand, highlight differences between the variables under study. According to, these graphs make a clear and precise representation of the consequences. </p>

<p>To perform the analysis, a graph of each of the datasets was first considered, where these were treated as if they were a time series (see <figure>Figure 4</figure>). The order in which the data was collected is represented on the abscissa axis, while the value of the data is represented on the axis of the ordinates. </p>

<p><figure>Figure 4</figure> shows the collected data separated by the lines that are parallel to the park, which are represented by the letter , and the lines that are perpendicular to the park, which are represented by the letter  (see <figure>Figure 1</figure> and <figure>Figure 2</figure>). The results of the PM2.5 measurements that are represented in this figure are the observations of the variables represented in <figure>Figure 1</figure>, which have been explained in Section 2. </p>

<p>From <figure>Figure 4</figure>, it can be seen that the variable , which is the one with the most data, and the variable  are the ones with the greatest fluctuations, while the variables  and  behave in a more linear way and with less variations, although the values of  are lower than those of . The other two variables,  and , apparently behave analogously to each other and different from the rest. Below, a statistical summary of the data is shown in Table 1. This table includes measures of central tendency, variability, and shape. </p>

<p>When comparing the summary statistics presented in Table 1 with those presented in, it can be said that the difference between both studies is that in, the skewness and kurtosis were not studied. However, in this article, it is important to study these third and fourth moments, because it is important to analyze whether the data comes from heavy-tailed distributions. According to, heavy-tailed distributions are those probability distributions whose density tails are not bounded by the normal density tails. </p>

<p><figure>Figure 5</figure> shows the multiple box-plot of data from each variable, and <figure>Figure 6</figure> shows the empirical  confidence intervals for the median, including both the mean and the median of the data. </p>

<p>Based on the previous figures, at first sight it is observed that the sizes of the six variables under study are different, with  having almost double the observations compared to each of the rest of the variables. In addition, it is observed that the means are higher than the medians in all cases, except for . The aforementioned indicates the existence of extreme values on the right, which is corroborated by the multiple box-plot shown in <figure>Figure 5</figure>. </p>

<p>In addition, the values of the standard deviation shown in Table 1 confirm that the variability of  is similar to the variability of , that the dispersion of the values of  and  is small, and that there is some similarity between the fluctuations of  and the fluctuations of . </p>

<p>Moreover, it can be seen that all the variables present a great lack of normality due to the high skewness values. All the skewness values shown in Table 1 are positive, so the distributions are lengthened to the right. The lack of normality is reaffirmed for most of the variables, since almost all the kurtosis values are much greater than 3, in particular the kurtosis values of  and . </p>

<p>Next, in order to see the trends of the variables under study, the technique of moving average (MA) was used. The MA technique was used to soften the data of the time series, in order to reduce the influence that each individual data had. </p>
</text>
