<text id="autogum_reddit_doc135" title="Old school Dragon Ball fan thinking about getting back into series" shortTile="old-school-dragon" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-04-30" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8g2o9z" speakerList="#TheInfamousMaze, #sxales" speakerCount="2">
<head>Old school Dragon Ball fan thinking about getting back into series</head>
<sp who="#TheInfamousMaze">
<p>I'm old school, like Rising Sun/Toonami old school, and I don't know what's been going on lately but my friends are saying super is awesome and I've been seeing these anime figures where Goku and Vegeta have blue hair and then Goku has pink hair and I'm like what the fuck? Goku literally looks like black rose from dot hack IMOQ. And then I heard DB GT wasn't Canon and I was like what the fuck?? And my head exploded and then I had to get all of my brains off the floor and put them back into my head, and then FINALLY I made this post. If I was to start it from the very beginning, to get the most out of super, should I read the Dragon Ball Manga and DBZ manga this time or should I re-watch Dragon Ball and DBZ, but not GT and then Super? Or should I watch Kai instead? Which movies are canon? Is most stuff dubbed now or are there still things that are better to watch in Japanese? Thanks guys. Also I heard there were colored comics in Japanese? I'm learning Japanese and I can probably read them so what's that about? Which ones are colored? And are there any like normal comic size releases or American comic adaptations? (Also known as floppies)</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#sxales">
<p>The leanest route (anime): </p>
<p>1. {Dragon Ball} </p>
<p>1. {Dragon Ball Kai} (all parts--MAL breaks this into 2 series and an OVA) </p>
<p>1. {Dragon Ball: Ossu! Kaettekita Son Gokuu to Nakama-tachi!!} </p>
<p>1. {Dragon Ball Super} </p>
<p>Since Kai is just a remastered and limited filler version DBZ so you can substitute it if you have a high nostalgia for DBZ otherwise Kai is about half as long. </p>
<p>The movies: Battle of The Gods and Resurrection F can be watched as standalone before Super in the timeline if you want (bearing in mind that early arcs of Super cover the same stories). None of the other movies were based on the manga Toriyama's stories so it is doubtful that they are canon. </p>
<p> </p>
<p>There is also prequel manga &lt;Jaco the Galactic Patrolman&gt; which comes before Dragon Ball chronologically but only serves to introduce a few characters for Super. It can be skipped without missing much but it is only 1 volume long. </p>
<p>Super is done for now; although, the manga &lt;Dragon Ball Super&gt; is still running. The series will probably continue once enough chapters gets released so that the series can run without catching up too quickly. </p>
<p>Dragon Ball and Dragon Ball Z were not separate in manga so &lt;Dragon Ball&gt; covers the entire story up to the end of DBZ and can be found in color. </p>
<p>I assumed you were more interested in the anime than the manga but just in case you want to read it all, the leanest route for the manga (IMO it is best to read in the order they were released and not in chronological order): </p>
<p>1. &lt;Dragon Ball&gt; </p>
<p>1. &lt;Dragon Ball: Ossu! Kaettekita Son Gokuu to Nakama-tachi!!&gt; </p>
<p>1. &lt;Ginga Patrol Jaco&gt; </p>
<p>1. &lt;Dragon Ball Super&gt; </p>
<p>Although, everything but Jaco has been animated. </p>
</sp>
</text>
