<text id="autogum_voyage_doc82" title="Lansdowne (Pennsylvania)" shortTile="lansdowne-pennsylvania" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=19071" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Lansdowne (Pennsylvania)</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.lansdowneborough.com">Lansdowne</ref></hi> is in <ref target="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Lansdowne, commonly confused with <ref target="Lansdale">Lansdale</ref>, Pennsylvania, is a small, quaint town located thirty minutes outside the city of <ref target="Philadelphia">Philadelphia</ref>. Lansdowne is 1.2 square miles in size with a population of a little over 11,000. Lansdowne is very community-based, with many community groups, such as boys and girls clubs, boys scout and girl scout troops, American Legion Posts, and many more. Lansdowne also has many places of worship and private and parochial schools. Lansdowne might be small on area and population, but it is bulging at the seams with history.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<p>The 101 Media, and 102 Sharon Hill trolleys both run through Lansdowne along with the Media/Elwyn Line train, 109, 113, and Route 30 buses as well as various other forms of SEPTA. It is easy to figure out how to ride SEPTA through their website: <ref target="http://www.septa.org/"></ref></p>

<p>You can also drive into town and park your car in one of the many parking lots and begin your walking tour throughout one of many historic districts.</p>

<p>You can fly into Philadelphia International Airport and rent a car or take a taxi, if you do not live within driving distance.</p>

<head>See</head>
<p>Lansdowne provides walking tours throughout its historic districts.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lansdowne Train Station</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lansdowne Borough Hall</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lansdowne Friends Meeting</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Henry Albertson Subdivision Historic District</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">World War One Monument</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">World War Two Monument</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lansdowne Park National Historic District</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sycamore Tree Park</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Trinity United Methodist</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Penn Wood High School</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">First Presbyterian Church of Lansdowne</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">St. John's Episcopal</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">St. Philomena's Catholic Church</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lansdowne Baptist</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Twentieth Century Club</hi>, <ref target="http://www.twentiethcenturyclub.com/"></ref>. Hosts several wonderful live plays by the <ref target="http://www.celebrationtheater.com/">Celebration Theater</ref>. Tickets for these wonderful performances are only $17 for adults, $15 for students and seniors, and $12 for children.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<p>Other than exploring the beautiful history of Lansdowne, there are plenty of activities to participate in.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lansdowne Arts Festival</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lansdowne Symphony Orchestra</hi>. Is a 75-piece orchestra which has been performing for over 50 years. Tickets $15 for adults, $12 for seniors, and $5 for students.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lansdowne Folk Club</hi> has folk music concerts.</item>
</list>


<p>There are also nine lovely borough parks:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hoffman Park</hi>, Scottdale Road. 8 acres with baseball and soccer fields, basketball courts, four tennis courts, pavilion, swings bathrooms and picnic tables.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hays Park</hi>, Nyack and Sayers Avenues. 1.2 acres with basketball courts, tot-lot toys, swings, slide and picnic tables.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Interboro Park</hi>, Cedar and Walnut Aves. 3 acres with basketball courts, tot-lot toys, swings and slide.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Belmont Park</hi>, Belmont and Plumstead Aves. 3.9 acres with basketball courts, swings, slide, tot-lot toys and big toys.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sycamore Park</hi>, LaCrosse and Wycombe Aves. 1 acre meditative setting with benches. Home of the symbol of Lansdowne, its 300 year old Sycamore tree.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Reservoir Park</hi>, Greenwood and Ardmore Avenue. 1.4 acres, undeveloped.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pennock Woods</hi>, Pennock Terrace. 6.5 acres of County open space with Lansdowne Bird Sanctuary.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Shrigley Woods</hi>, Scottdale and Hilldale Rds. 6.5 acres of undeveloped County open space.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Marlyn Park</hi>, Willowbrook and Marlyn Aves. 3 acres, passive park.</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Antiques</hi> - Two well-stocked antique stores downtown.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lansdowne Avenue</hi> has many small shops including nail salons, clothing shops, flower shops, dollar stores, convenience stores, gift shops, and other small businesses.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Farmer's market</hi>. Held weekly.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>
<p>Most of the restaurants are small, family-owned and very inexpensive.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mesquite BBQ Restaurant</hi>, 21 N Lansdowne Ave.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mission Burrito</hi>, 32 S Lansdowne Ave.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Great Wall Chinese Restaurant</hi>, 7 N Lansdowne Ave.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Best Quality Pizza</hi>, 208 N Wycombe Ave.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Paul Revere Pizza House</hi>, 193 Shadeland Ave.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Empire Diner</hi>, 106 E Baltimore Ave.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cafe Harlem</hi>, 717 Church Ln.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">B's Que Shot Lounge</hi>, 527 E Baltimore Ave.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pizza Paradise</hi>, 525 S Wycombe Ave.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lansdowne Chinese Restaurant</hi>, 10 N Lansdowne Ave.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Doc's Deli</hi>, 61 Hartley Rd.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Danny's Corner Tavern</hi>, 65 N Union Ave.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Colonial Kitchen</hi>, 103 N Union Ave.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Jerry's Bar</hi>, 707 E Baltimore Ave.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lansdowne Diner</hi>, 2 N Lansdowne Ave.</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>

<p>Lansdowne is a dry town, but the city of Philadelphia, which is only thirty minutes away, has a great night life.</p>

<p>There are also several beer distributors and liquor stores bordering Lansdowne on all sides.</p>

<head>Sleep</head>

<p>There are no hotels located directly in Lansdowne, but there are several very close by in <ref target="Upper%20Darby">Upper Darby</ref> and <ref target="Philadelphia">Philadelphia</ref>.</p>

<head>Cope</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lansdowne Public Library</hi>, <ref target="http://www.lansdownepubliclibrary.com/"></ref>.</item>
</list>


<head>Connect</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Borough Hall</hi>, 12 E. Baltimore Ave, ☏ +1 610 623-7300 , fax: +1 610 623-5533 . Mon—Fri 9am-4pm.</item>
</list>
</text>
