<text id="autogum_bio_doc052" title="Ron Jaffe" shortTile="ron-jaffe" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-07-21" dateModified="2019-01-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ron_Jaffe" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ron Jaffe</head><p><hi rend="bold">Ron Jaffe</hi> is an American photographer.  He has photographed six U. S. Presidents, legislators, dignitaries and well-known celebrities in the fields of entertainment and sports.</p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>Jaffe was born and raised in Alabama.  He moved to Los Angeles at the age of 18 to attend Pasadena City College with the goal of becoming a teacher.  Jaffe became interested in photography when he accompanied a fellow student on a shooting assignment.  The experience exposed Jaffe to a field he had never considered and he began to pursue his new interest with a passion.  He continued his coursework and became a teacher with the Pasadena Unified School District, but after a few years, decided to pursue his hobby as a profession.</p>
<head>Career</head>
<p>By the early 1970s, Jaffe was working full-time as a freelance photographer.  He shot fashion publicity photos and commercial ads for his primary clients, which included the designers Barco of California, Jag Swimwear, and DeWeiss.  In 1974, Jaffe also began teaching photography at the university level as professor of photography at Chapman College – World Campus Afloat, aboard a ship travelling to South America, Africa and Europe.</p>
<p>In 1977, Jaffe signed a contract with Elson Alexandre where over the next two decades he photographed more than 37,000 formal and casual portraits of corporate executives, doctors, attorneys, judges as well as family photos of the company’s clients.  During this period Jaffe also shot many celebrity portraits on an independent contractor basis capturing unique images of cowboy stars from Dale Robertson, and Gene Autry to Chuck Connors, Indian Iron Eyes Cody<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ref1-1">[1]</ref> and Roy Rogers.</p>
<p>For the last 20 years Jaffe has shot over 500 episodes of high-profile television shows such as <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cold_Case">Cold Case</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CSI_Miami">CSI Miami</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CSI_New_York">CSI New York</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Friends">Friends</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/How_I_Met_Your_Mother">How I Met Your Mother</ref></hi>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ref2-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ref3-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ref4-4">[4]</ref> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mad_Men">Mad Men</ref></hi>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ref5-5">[5]</ref> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rules_of_Engagement_(TV_series)">Rules of Engagement</ref></hi>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ref6-6">[6]</ref> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suddenly_Susan">Suddenly Susan</ref></hi>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_West_Wing"><hi rend="italic">The</hi> <hi rend="italic">West Wing</hi></ref>, and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Without_a_Trace">Without a Trace</ref></hi>, and current shows including <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Castle_(TV_series)">Castle</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CSI_Crime_Scene_Investigation">CSI Crime Scene Investigation</ref></hi>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ref7-7">[7]</ref> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hit_the_Floor_(TV_series)">Hit the Floor</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jane_the_Virgin">Jane the Virgin</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NCIS_(TV_series)">NCIS</ref></hi>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ref8-8">[8]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ref9-9">[9]</ref> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NCIS:_LA">NCIS: LA</ref></hi> and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scorpion_(TV_series)">Scorpion</ref></hi>.   His work on episodic crime dramas involve not only shooting the show during taping, but all props, photos used in the storyline and all crime scene photos showing the circumstances of crime scene investigation for evidence.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ref10-10">[10]</ref>  In essence, Jaffe actually becomes the forensic photographer of episodic dramas.</p>
<p>In all, Jaffe has shot programs that have aired or are currently airing on the ABC, NBC, CBS,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ref11-11">[11]</ref> FOX, AMC, VH1, MTV, A&amp;E, The CW, and CMT networks.  Because of his work on these shows Jaffe has been nominated twice for the Publicists Guild of America’s Excellence in Stills Photography Award.</p>
<head>Awards</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>California Museum of Science and Industry Certificate of Achievement for Outstanding Photographer in the documentary category (1974)</item>
<item>the 1975 Photographer West Award;</item>
<item>Black &amp; White Spider Award (2005)</item>
<item>Certificate of Achievement in Recognition of Outstanding Photography Judges Choice award for Los Angeles Advertising Photographers of America (2006)</item>
<item>Honorary Color Master Fine Art (2007)</item>
<item>Photo Journalism Photography Masters Cup (2008)</item>
<item>International Publicist Guild – nomination for Excellence in Stills Photography award (2008 and 2010)</item>
<item>Second International Color Awards (2013)</item></list>
</text>
