<text id="autogum_whow_doc011" title="Send Books to Someone in Prison" shortTile="send-books-someone" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2009-12-08" dateModified="2019-04-26" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Send-Books-to-Someone-in-Prison" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Send Books to Someone in Prison</head><p>If you know someone who is in prison, giving them access to books can immensely help them pass the time, continue to learn and think, and just cheer them up. Although many prisons only allow books to come from authorized vendors such as book stores or prisoner support organizations such as the Prisoner's Literature Project, some will allow individuals to send books as well.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Look up the prison online. See if there is any information online regarding restrictions, sending information, packaging information, or a mailing address for the prison. If you are in contact with the prisoner you would like to send books to, he or she may also have information for you.  <figure rend="Send Books to Someone in Prison Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Know the prisoner's ID number as it needs to go on the first line after the prisoners name in order for them to get the books. The address label must list the name and ID number for the prisoner, the name of the prison, and the prison's mailing address, which is either the location of the prison or a PO Box.  <figure rend="Send Books to Someone in Prison Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Check for the prison regulations on sending things to inmates. Many prisons have regulations limiting number of books that can be sent, restricting books with sex scenes, not allowing used books, or not allowing hardcover books. These restrictions vary from place to place and even prison to prison, so be sure to check first. If there are none present, look for a telephone number to call or email address to email the prison. <figure rend="Send Books to Someone in Prison Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Telephone or email them if you don't find details. Consider finding out the following: <figure rend="Send Books to Someone in Prison Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Explain that you would like to send books to a prisoner</item>
<item>Explain who you are and your relationship with the prisoner</item>
<item>Explain what the books are</item>
<item>Ask if this is permitted and if so, what restrictions are in place, if any</item>
<item>Confirm a postal address and any packaging requirements</item></list></item>
<item>If you get a positive answer, follow the instructions that were given to post your books or other reading material. <figure rend="Send Books to Someone in Prison Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you get a negative response, don't give up yet. There are still several options to consider: <figure rend="Send Books to Someone in Prison Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Write to an association that helps prisoners, such as the Prisoner's Literature Project, being sure to include the name, location, and ID number of the prisoner in your letter.</item>
<item>Contact any educational institution that is in contact with and aids prisoners.</item>
<item>Ask the prisoner you are sending books to for more information on restrictions or which vendors they may know are authorized.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Many prisons only allow books to come from an authorized vendor such as a book store or organization. If you are not allowed to send books as an individual, ask which vendors will be allowed to bring books into the prison and contact those vendors.</item>
<item>Remember that prisons are worried about security. For these reasons they may require paperbacks only, new books only, or have a limit on the number of books that can be sent at a time.</item>
<item>If you go through a service that specializes in books for prison inmates, they will likely already have a good grasp of what titles are allowed and which are not. They will already have in stock titles that are sure to be approved.</item>
<item>Be sure to carefully follow all restrictions that are in place, as well as putting the prisoner's ID number on any packages or letters. Even a small mistake in following restrictions can cause all your books to be destroyed or sent back.</item></list>
</text>
