<text id="autogum_interview_doc438" title="part1_Psychiatrist Dr. Jerald Block tells Wikinews about addiction to the Internet" shortTile="partpsychiatrist" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-10-21" dateModified="2017-05-30" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Psychiatrist_Dr._Jerald_Block_tells_Wikinews_about_addiction_to_the_Internet" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What do you want to see governments do in response?</hi></p>
<p>The government can help by channeling interest into the topic and more research through the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Centers%20for%20Disease%20Control%20and%20Prevention">CDC</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NIH">NIH</ref>, and special investigative bodies.  At present, the game and porn industry has no stake in seeing research conducted and it is not clear who does.  As a result, there is little money budgeted to exploring the issue using the standard methods we use in science.  Then, ironically, it is claimed that there are no "good" studies...well, of course not -- there is no money to pay for them.</p>
<p>Actually, though, there have been some good studies...if you understand their limitations.  For example, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nick%20Yee">Nick Yee</ref>'s work is interesting but his sampling methods are clearly non-random.  We also have several consulting firms, like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nielsen">Nielsen</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NPD%20Group">NPD</ref>.  They have done some huge RANDOM studies which they issue news releases on.  However, research which documents things like some recent ones from NPD...that some 4- 5 million people play 45+ hours per week in the USA and buy around two new titles each week... are sold for thousands of dollars and inaccessible via libraries.  They are written for the game industry to clarify their sales strategy and target consumers, not for the medical community, and almost entirely unavailable to clinicians.</p>
<p>I do not believe the government should get into mandating content, censorship, or any of that.  It is a waste of time, money, and resources.  I do think, however, that the government should phase in a requirement that games or the computer's OS come with the ability to limit access to porn or games, as the computer's owner directs.  People should be able to ask the system to budget or cut themselves off of games or porn, as they wish.  The limits could be around time and/or content and would be reversible, with time, effort, or money.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What advice would you give to someone who is addicted to the Internet, assuming treatment is unavailable?</hi></p>
<p>Advice...  I do not have generic advice -- it really is case specific.  Obviously, the patient needs to figure out how serious they are about wanting to "cut back" and then what, specifically, is stopping them.   With excessive porn use, often I prescribe <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SSRI">SSRIs</ref> or related medications.  We need to develop clear protocols to treat computer-related pathology.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why do you think there is a lack of major studies or official policy on Internet addiction?</hi></p>
<p>Major studies cost lots of money.  In the USA, any study needs to pay for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Institutional%20review%20board">IRB</ref>, the researcher's time, the technology, the statistical analysis, the fixed costs, etc..  In addition, this is complicated in the USA since there are few funding sources with a clear mandate to research this topic.  Those that do exist are often intertwined with ethical or political agendas which pull investigators away from conducting unbiased research.  Finally, I think what research dollars are available have been distracted by a secondary issue:  the concept that violent media creates violent people.  This may (or may not) be true but, at best, the effect size seems to be small and costs in addressing it are huge.  It seems to me that a more immediate and dangerous issue is that of compulsive computer use.</p>
</text>
