<text id="autogum_interview_doc717" title="part2_Author of My Billion Year Contract reflects on life in elite Scientology group" shortTile="partauthor-billion" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-01-13" dateModified="2012-10-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Author_of_My_Billion_Year_Contract_reflects_on_life_in_elite_Scientology_group" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You speak in the book about the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psychology">psychology</ref> term <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cognitive%20dissonance">cognitive dissonance</ref>, which you describe as "the feeling of uncomfortable tension, which comes from holding two conflicting thoughts at the same time. This can cause an individual to fight within their minds to somehow make it make sense." (p. 54) Do you still experience cognitive dissonance when reflecting on your experiences in Scientology? Why and how so?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NM</hi>: I no longer experience Cognitive Dissonance when reflecting on my experiences in Scientology.  I have done further study of it and find it to be a common human ailment.</p>
<p>"Cognitive Dissonance is a state of tension that occurs whenever a person holds two cognitions (ideas, attitudes, beliefs, opinions) that are psychologically inconsistent such as 'Smoking is a dumb thing because it could kill me' and 'I smoke two packs a day.' Dissonance produces mental discomfort, ranging from minor pangs to deep anguish; people don’t rest easy until they find a way to reduce it." (<hi rend="italic">Mistakes Were Made, But Not By Me</hi>, Carol Travis.)</p>
<p>I experienced several levels of Cognitive Dissonance while in Scientology.  They say Church on the door, but the day to day operations are not those of a church – those contrary thoughts were assuaged for years because of the Hubbard Policy – Religion 1970, wherein he stated something like we are a religion for accountant and attorneys, nothing about our daily operations will change.  That plus the line that I was often given and gave to others new to the Church –it’s not a faith, it is an Applied Religious Philosophy, non-denominational in nature, you can still belong to your own church and be a Scientology.</p>
<p>That held my discomfort together until years later I read the Messianic Program, wherein Hubbard laid out the steps to make himself the next Messiah for planet earth.</p>
<p>Another cognitive dissonance was why are we attempting to destroy and take over the entire field of mental health, if we are a church, well the same answer, we aren’t really a church.</p>
<p>When LRH [L. Ron Hubbard] himself wrote to me that he wished he had never gone the "Church" route at all, it made me happy and erased the tension of the Cognitive Dissonance.</p>
<p>Why were the prices so high?  If we were supposed to Clear the Planet, and help make the world a better place, then why did we charge so much?  Very few people could afford that level of money and still survive and raise a family.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> In the book you write, "I have studied the research done on the power that groups can hold over individuals and the mindsets and peer pressures that got me to that place." (p. 92.) What types of resources did you use for this study? Can you recommend any references for others wishing to learn about this topic?</hi></p>
</text>
