<text id="autogum_bio_doc580" title="Alexander Lauder of Blyth" shortTile="alexander-lauder" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-02-28" dateModified="2016-05-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_Lauder_of_Blyth" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Alexander Lauder of Blyth</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">Sir Alexander Lauder of Blyth</hi>, Knt. (died 9 September 1513) was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Provost_of_Edinburgh">Provost of Edinburgh</ref> almost continually from 1500 to 1513. He was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Commissioner#Scotland">Commissioner</ref> to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parliament_of_Scotland">Scottish Parliament</ref>, 1504–06, and an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Auditor_of_the_Exchequer_in_Scotland">Auditor of the Exchequer in Scotland</ref>. He appears to have been on terms of intimacy with the King, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_IV_of_Scotland">James IV</ref>, with whom he played cards and to whom he occasionally lent money.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> "He led the men of Edinburgh to join the King's host" at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Flodden">battle of Flodden</ref>, and fell there.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Whitson,_Sir_Thomas_1932,_p10-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>He was the second son of at least four of Sir Alexander Lauder of Haltoun, Knt., who died at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haltoun_House">Haltoun House</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ratho">Ratho</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Midlothian">Midlothian</ref> in July 1507.  The <hi rend="italic">Exchequer Rolls</hi> mention this Alexander Lauder, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burgess_(title)">Burgess</ref> of Edinburgh, with his elder brother Sir George Lauder of Whitslaid, as 'senescallos', or stewards, of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kirkcudbrightshire">Kirkcudbrightshire</ref>, 'in their part'.</p>
<head>Burgess &amp; Provost of Edinburgh</head>
<p>On 7 January 1498/9, Alexander Lauder, Burgess of Edinburgh, was one of the witnesses to an Instrument of Resignation by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patrick_Hepburn,_1st_Earl_of_Bothwell">Patrick Hepburn, 1st Earl of Bothwell</ref>. Others included Robert, Archbishop of Glasgow, George Hepburn, Provost of Lincluden, William Borthwick, Rector of Whitsome, and Adam Hepburn, burgess of Edinburgh.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Described as son of Sir Alexander Lauder of Hatton [sic], he was granted, as Alexander Lauder, Burgess of Edinburgh, a Letter under The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Privy_Seal_of_Scotland">Privy Seal of Scotland</ref> on 18 January 1500, of "the custumyre of Edinburgh" including wool, skins, hides, cloth "and all maner of merchandis", for his lifetime.</p>
<p>Whitson<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Whitson,_Sir_Thomas_1932,_p10-2">[2]</ref>   states that this Sir Alexander Lauder was Provost from April 1500 till October, or possibly <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michaelmas">Michaelmas</ref>, 1501. He again held that office from Michaelmas 1502 till 1504, and from 1505 to 1513. He is noted also as holding concurrently the office of Justice-Depute with the provostship in 1508 and 1512, if not consecutively. George Touris of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inverleith">Inverleith</ref> was appointed caretaker Provost on 19 August 1513, when Lauder left for Flodden.</p>
<head>Landed proprietor</head>
<p>He acquired considerable lands. In 1506 he had a charter under the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Seal_of_Scotland">Great Seal of Scotland</ref></hi> confirming to him certain lands of Norton in the barony of Ratho, the lands of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bruntsfield">Brownisfield</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burgh_Muir">Burgh Muir</ref> of Edinburgh, and the lands of Redheuchis in the barony of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colinton">Colinton</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The Privy Seal</hi> records on 19 September 1508, at Edinburgh, "A Lettre [was] maid to Alexander Lauder, provost of Edinburgh, his ayris and assignais: That forsamekly as all and hail the landis of Thirlstane Manys, Ernyscluch, Egrop, Wyndpark, the Heuch, Blyth, Tullois and Simprin, liand in the lordschip of Lauderdale within the schirefdome of Beruik," which had pertained to William Maitland of Lethington, which by the Lords of Council's decree had returned to the King's hands and his father's in non-entry for the space of over thirty years past, in default of entry fees etc being paid; and for the good and thankful service done to His Highness by Alexander Lauder and for other reasonable considerations moving His Grace, he gives, grants and assigns to the said Alexander, his heirs and assignees, all males, all the above lands and fermes, profits etc. etc., to be held of His Highness by charter in due form etc., whereafter he assumed the territorial designation "of Blyth".</p>
<head>Knight &amp; Justice-depute</head>
<p>Alexander Lauder of Blyth, Provost of Edinburgh, was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knight">knighted</ref> before 11 October 1510, when he was described as such, and on which date he endowed a chaplainry in the church of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Giles'_Cathedral">St. Giles</ref>. He is on record as an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Auditor_of_the_Exchequer_in_Scotland">Auditor of the Exchequer in Scotland</ref> in 1512.</p>
<p>Pitcairn notes that "Alexander Lauder of Blyth, knight, Provost of Edinburgh and 'Justiciarius deputatis'" signed a verdict at a murder trial on 31 September 1512.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Marriage &amp; death</head>
<p>He married before December 1506 Janet (d. between 1533 - Oct.1534), daughter and heiress of John Paterson, Burgess of Edinburgh.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>The death of Sir Alexander Lauder, Provost of Edinburgh, "slain at Flodden"  is recorded in <hi rend="italic">The Exchequer Rolls</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref>  As he was a Custumar of Edinburgh, his "relict" Janet Paterson, was, with Margaret Crichton, relict of the other Custumar George Halkerston, allowed the honour of signing off the city's returns to the Exchequer for 1513-1514.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
</text>
