<text id="autogum_whow_doc466" title="Clean a Slate Hearth" shortTile="clean-slate-hearth" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-01-26" dateModified="2019-07-02" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Clean-a-Slate-Hearth" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Clean a Slate Hearth</head><p>If you have a slate hearth around your fireplace and it’s been there for more than 2 months, it’s probably a little dirty. Slate hearths need to be cleaned regularly to prevent and remove the grime and stains that build up on them. Luckily, it’s pretty easy to clean your slate hearth, as long as you have some ordinary household cleaning supplies and a few specialty items from a home improvement store.
</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Performing Routine Cleaning</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Sweep, dust, or vacuum the slate to remove any loose dirt. Remove any dust, ash flakes, or other debris items from the surface of the slate hearth before you proceed to clean it with the dish soap mixture. You can also use a dry mop if you have one. <figure rend="Clean a Slate Hearth Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure you remove any dust or dirt in the grout trenches between the slabs of slate as well.</item></list></item>
<item>Make a cleaning solution out of water and dish soap. Mix a few drops of mild dish soap into a bucket filled halfway with warm water. Use a long wooden spoon to stir this mixture together until the dish soap is completely mixed with the water. <figure rend="Clean a Slate Hearth Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Use a mild dish soap to avoid inadvertently damaging the slate on your hearth.</item>
<item>You can also use an all-purpose surface cleaner if you don’t have any mild dish soap.</item>
<item>Avoid using a bucket that’s too small. You should mix the dish soap with at least  of water.</item></list></item>
<item>Scrub the slate with a cloth or mop soaked in the soapy water mix. Dip your cloth or mop into the mixture, then ring it out slightly to get rid of excess moisture. Then, scrub the slate using circular motions to clean it. <figure rend="Clean a Slate Hearth Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don’t apply too much pressure when you go to scrub the slate. If a gentle once-over isn’t enough to clean off any dirt and grime on your hearth, use a more powerful cleaning solution instead.</item>
<item>Pay special attention to the corners, as this is where a lot of grime can build up unnoticed.</item></list></item>
<item>Rinse the slate with clean water to get the soap off of it. Spray small amounts of water onto the slate with a spray bottle in order to rinse the hearth without making a mess. You can also use a sponge soaked in clean water if you don’t have a spray bottle handy. <figure rend="Clean a Slate Hearth Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You should also allow the hearth to air dry overnight if you intend to polish it after you clean it.</item></list></item>
<item>Use a clean towel to dry any excess moisture off of your hearth. You can use any ordinary towel to dry the slate, so long as it’s clean. If you plan to do any further cleaning, allow the hearth to air dry overnight first. <figure rend="Clean a Slate Hearth Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Get as much of the water off of the slate as possible. Any excess moisture left on the slate may cause water stains.</item></list></item>
<item>Wipe down the slate with teak oil to polish your hearth. Use a soft cloth to apply a thin layer of teak oil to the surface of the slate. Then, use a second clean cloth to remove any excess oil from the surface. <figure rend="Clean a Slate Hearth Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can buy reasonably priced teak oil at most large hardware stores.</item>
<item>You can also use slate oil instead of teak oil, although the former is usually more expensive and a bit harder to find in stores.</item>
<item>Teak oil also helps hide scratches on your hearth, making it easier to seal.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Removing Stains</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Make a cleaning solution out of hydrogen peroxide and water. Mix equal portions of water and hydrogen peroxide in a small spray bottle. If you don’t have a spray bottle, you can also mix these ingredients in a bucket and use a sponge to apply it. <figure rend="Clean a Slate Hearth Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can also use a mixture of equal parts of baking soda and hydrogen peroxide to provide stronger cleaning power.</item>
<item>You may also use 1 part rubbing alcohol with 8 parts water as an alternative.</item></list></item>
<item>Spray your mix of water and hydrogen peroxide onto the stain. Apply a thin layer of the water and peroxide mixture directly to the surface of the stain. Let the mixture sit for 5-10 minutes before proceeding. <figure rend="Clean a Slate Hearth Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Avoid spraying this mixture near any colored grout, since the bleach in the mixture can discolor your grout.</item></list></item>
<item>Scrub the stain with a soft scrub pad or brush. Scrub in a circular motion without applying too much pressure in order to clean the slate without damaging it. If you used baking soda and hydrogen peroxide instead of the water mixture, use a moist cloth to scrub the slate. <figure rend="Clean a Slate Hearth Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Refrain from using steel wool, as this might cause damage to the slate.</item></list></item>
<item>Allow the slate to air dry after you’ve scrubbed the stain clean. There’s no need to wipe the solution off of the slate after you’re done. For best results, allow the slate to dry overnight before putting anything on it or using the fireplace. <figure rend="Clean a Slate Hearth Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use a Trisodium Phosphate (TSP) mix on tougher stains. Make a cleaning paste out of TSP and water, carefully following the manufacturer’s instructions for use. Spread the paste onto a sponge and use that sponge to scrub the slate. Finally, soak a separate clean sponge in water and use it to remove any residue from the slate surface. <figure rend="Clean a Slate Hearth Step 11.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This method is particularly useful if the stains on your slate were caused by smoke or soot.</item>
<item>You can also use a commercial fireplace cleaner to help remove soot and smoke residue.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Clean the slate around your fireplace every 2-3 months to prevent the buildup of grime and stains, even if the hearth doesn’t look dirty.</item>
<item>Seal the slate with stone and tile sealer to help protect it against moisture and stains.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Avoid using acidic cleaners, like vinegar, since they can etch and damage the slate.</item>
<item>Don’t let water pool up on your slate since the water will absorb into it.</item></list>
<head>Things You’ll Need</head>
<head>Performing Routine Cleaning</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Water</item>
<item>Dish soap</item>
<item>Cloth or mop</item>
<item>Bucket</item>
<item>Spray bottle</item>
<item>Towel</item>
<item>Teak oil</item></list>
<head>Removing Stains</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Water</item>
<item>Hydrogen peroxide</item>
<item>Spray bottle</item>
<item>Soft scrub pad or brush</item>
<item>Trisodium Phosphate</item>
<item>Sponge</item></list>
</text>
