<text id="autogum_whow_doc451" title="Measure Square Footage" shortTile="measure-square-footage" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2006-01-21" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Measure-Square-Footage" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Measure Square Footage</head><p>Knowing how to measure square footage can be very useful for real estate rental and sale purposes, and it can also help you ace your next geometry test. To measure the square footage of a space, separate the space into manageable parts, find the square footage of all those different parts (usually by multiplying length times width), and add the square footage of all separate parts together to find the square footage of the overall space.
</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Find the Square Footage of a Space</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Break down the area into manageable parts. If you're having trouble finding the square footage, then it's probably because you're not working with a neat area with just one length and one width. The space might have squares jutting off in different places and could be shaped erratically. All you have to do is split up the space into even squares or rectangles. To find the square footage, or the area, of the entire space, you'll need to find the square footage of the individual spaces and then add them all together. <figure rend="Measure Square Footage Step 1.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Draw faint lines separating the different sections.</item>
<item>Label them A, B, and C for your convenience.</item></list></item>
<item>Measure the length and width of the first space. Using a ruler or measuring tape, find the length and width of the first space you've created, Space A. <figure rend="Measure Square Footage Step 2.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The length of the space is , and the width is .</item></list></item>
<item>Multiply the length of the first space by the width of the first space. To find the square footage -- or the area -- of the space, just multiply the length times the width, just as you would do with any rectangle. <figure rend="Measure Square Footage Step 3.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Ex: . x . = 180 square feet</item></list></item>
<item>Measure the length and width of the second space. Let's say that the length of Space B is  and the width of Space B is . <figure rend="Measure Square Footage Step 4.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Multiply the length of the second space times the width of the second space. This will lead you to find the square footage of the second space. Here's how you find the square footage of Space B: <figure rend="Measure Square Footage Step 5.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Ex: . x . = 200 square feet.</item></list></item>
<item>Measure the length and width of the third space. Let's say that the length of Space C is  and the width of Space C is . <figure rend="Measure Square Footage Step 6.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Multiply the length of the third space times the width of the third space. This will lead you to find the square footage of the third space. Here's how you find the square footage of Space C: <figure rend="Measure Square Footage Step 7.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Ex: . x . = 700 square feet</item></list></item>
<item>Add the square footages of the three spaces. Once you find the sum of the square footages of the three spaces, you'll know the square footage of the entire space. Here's how you do it: <figure rend="Measure Square Footage Step 8.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Square footage of Space A + square footage of Space B + square footage of Space C = square footage of the entire space</item>
<item>180 + 200 + 700 = 1080 square feet</item></list></item></list>
<head>Learn a Few Tricks for Finding Square Footage</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find the approximation of square footage. If you're looking for an approximation of square footage, you can also try measuring the outside of your home and then subtracting any areas that won't be factored in to the square footage, such as the porch stairs or garage. <figure rend="Measure Square Footage Step 9.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Ceiling and floor tiles are often one square foot in size. You can simply count these to get a close approximation of the total square footage.</item></list></item>
<item>Find the square footage of a space that's shaped like a half-circle. If there's a part of your house that's shaped like a half of a circle, you can find the square footage of the circle by finding the area of the space as if it were a full circle and then dividing it by half. To do this, simply measure the long line that cuts the "circle" in half to get the diameter. <figure rend="Measure Square Footage Step 10.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Next, divide that number by 2 to get the radius (r) and plug the result into the equation A = πr2.</item>
<item>Finally, divide by 2 to get the area, or square footage, of the half circle.</item></list></item>
<item>Find the square footage of a space that's <hi rend="italic">almost</hi> regularly shaped. If you're measuring a space that is almost fully a square or a rectangle, with only a small square or rectangular part missing, then measure the square footage of the entire space as if the missing part was filled in. Then, find the square footage of the missing part and subtract it from the overall square footage to find the square footage of the space. This will save you time. <figure rend="Measure Square Footage Step 11.360p.mp4"></figure></item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
