<text id="autogum_bio_doc451" title="Thomas Tresham (died 1605)" shortTile="thomas-tresham-died" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2004-11-27" dateModified="2019-07-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Tresham_%28died_1605%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Thomas Tresham (died 1605)</head>For other people with the same name, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Tresham_(disambiguation)">Thomas Tresham (disambiguation)</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Sir Thomas Tresham</hi> (1543 – 11 September 1605<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Pevsner-1">[1]</ref>) was a prominent <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Recusancy">recusant</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catholic">Catholic</ref> landowner in Elizabethan Northamptonshire. He died two years after the accession of James VI and I. <figure rend="Rushton Triangular Lodge.jpg"></figure></p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Tresham was brought up in the Throckmorton household. He inherited large estates at the age of 15, from his grandfather and namesake <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Tresham_I">Thomas Tresham I</ref>, establishing him as a member of the Catholic elite. He was widely regarded as clever and well-educated, a correspondent of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Cecil,_1st_Baron_Burghley">William Cecil</ref>, the Secretary of State to Queen <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_I_of_England">Elizabeth</ref>, and Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Hatton">Christopher Hatton</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Chancellor">Lord Chancellor</ref>.</p>
<p>Well-read, Tresham dedicated much of his life to collecting books. He was much disliked, however, for an enclosure policy towards common land. Following a riot which destroyed some of his hedges, he had 50 people executed.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Tresham was picked as sheriff for Northamptonshire in 1573 and was knighted at the Queen's Royal Progress at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kenilworth">Kenilworth</ref> in 1575.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Pevsner-1">[1]</ref> He frequently entertained large numbers of friends and acquaintances and pursued an aggressively reforming estate policy. His recusancy, Jesuit connections and arguments for the state's lack of jurisdiction in matters of conscience made him the subject of official attention, and he was imprisoned several times and fined heavily.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> At a time when Queen Elizabeth was anxious about the Catholic threat posed by Spain and by her cousin <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary,_Queen_of_Scots">Mary, Queen of Scots</ref>, Catholics were made targets for persecution by their spiritual loyalty to another temporal power (the Pope, and by extension, the Catholic King of Spain). Between 1581 and 1605, Tresham paid penalties totalling just under £8,000. (equivalent to £1,750,000 in 2018)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-inflation-UK-4">[4]</ref>. These heavy financial demands were, in reality, overshadowed by the expense of his building projects and his insistence on making advantageous marriages for his six daughters, bringing with them sizeable dowries (£12,200). His credit was thus impaired, and the ill-advised involvement of his son, Francis, in the Earl of Essex's rebellion, cost him over £3,000. As a Catholic who had Jesuit links, and who argued for an individual's right to act according to his conscience unmolested, he was tarred with the brush of disloyalty, a mark he fiercely rejected. Ultimately, his son Lewis successfully ate through what little family money was left.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>He left three notable buildings in Northamptonshire, the extraordinary <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rushton_Triangular_Lodge">Rushton Triangular Lodge</ref> and the unfinished <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lyveden_New_Bield">Lyveden New Bield</ref>, both of which embody the strength of his faith. The Triangular Lodge bears witness to Tresham's fidelity to the doctrine of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trinity">Trinity</ref>. There was also a more personal connection: above the door we find the inscription 'Tres testimonium dant' ('the three bear witness', or, perhaps, 'Tres bears witness'). 'Tres' may be a moment of self-reference; it was his wife's pet name for him.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> Tresham himself was the architect of these designs, and the extant family papers in the British Library reveal some of his plans. His sense of civic responsibility in local society, occasioned by his gentility and the expectations of his rank and family practice, led him to begin building the Market House at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rothwell,_Northamptonshire">Rothwell</ref> in 1577, thought to be a sessions house and decorated with the arms of other local families.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> Sir Thomas was a considerable landowner at his death in 1605, but his estate had £11,000 of debt (equivalent to £2,410,000 in 2018)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-inflation-UK-4">[4]</ref>.</p>
<head>Marriage and children</head>
<p>In 1566, he married Muriel, a daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Throckmorton">Sir Robert Throckmorton</ref> and Elizabeth Hussey. The Throckmorton family was a wealthy Catholic family from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coughton_Court">Coughton Court</ref> in Warwickshire and Tresham had been Sir Robert's ward.</p>
<p>Thomas and Muriel had eleven children, including;</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_Tresham">Francis</ref> (d. December 1605)</item>
<item>Mary (d. 13 October 1664); married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Brudenell,_1st_Earl_of_Cardigan">Thomas Brudenell, 1st Earl of Cardigan</ref></item>
<item>Elizabeth; married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Parker,_4th_Baron_Monteagle">William Parker, 4th Baron Monteagle</ref></item>
<item>Frances; married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Stourton,_10th_Baron_Stourton">Edward Stourton, 10th Baron Stourton</ref></item>
<item>Catherine;  married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sir_John_Webbe,_2nd_Baron_of_Odstock">Sir John Webbe, 2nd Baron of Odstock</ref></item></list>
<p>His elder son, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_Tresham">Francis</ref>, inherited the titles, estate, and debt, and became embroiled in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gunpowder_Plot">Gunpowder Plot</ref> later that year along with his cousins <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Catesby">Robert Catesby</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Wintour">Thomas Wintour</ref>. Imprisoned for his actions, Francis met an early death in
December 1605, avoiding certain execution. Nevertheless, he was decapitated after his death and his head displayed as that of a notorious traitor. His role in the Plot has been the subject of debate by historians and it has been largely accepted that he was the author of the famous 'Mounteagle Letter'. However widely agreed his authorship of the letter to his relative, it remains conjectural.</p>
</text>
