<text id="autogum_bio_doc488" title="David Powel" shortTile="david-powel" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-10" dateModified="2019-06-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Powel" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>David Powel</head><p><hi rend="bold">David Powel</hi> (1549/52 – 1598) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wales">Welsh</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church_of_England">Church of England</ref> clergyman and historian who published the first printed history of Wales in 1584.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Powel was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Denbighshire">Denbighshire</ref> and commenced his studies at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Oxford">University of Oxford</ref> when he was 16, sometime between 1566 and 1568. Whilst his initial college membership is not known, it is known that he moved to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesus_College,_Oxford">Jesus College</ref> when it was founded in 1571.  He obtained his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bachelor_of_Arts">B.A.</ref> degree on 3 March 1573 and is thought to have been the college's first graduate.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ODNB-1">[1]</ref> He obtained his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Master_of_Arts_(Oxbridge_and_Dublin)">M.A.</ref> on 6 July 1576. Before Powel graduated, he had been named as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vicar">vicar</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ruabon">Ruabon</ref>, Denbighshire and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rector_(ecclesiastical)">rector</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfyllin">Llanfyllin</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Montgomeryshire">Montgomeryshire</ref>. He became vicar of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meifod">Meifod</ref> in place of his Llanfyllin position in 1579, and was also the holder of two <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prebend">prebends</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Asaph_Cathedral">St Asaph Cathedral</ref>. After further study, he obtained degrees of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bachelor_of_Theology">B.Th.</ref> on 19 February 1583 and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doctor_of_Theology">D.Th.</ref> on 11 April 1583. He was then private chaplain to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Sidney">Sir Henry Sidney</ref>, president of the Council in the marches of Wales, from about 1584 to 1586.  He died in 1598 in Ruabon, where he was buried.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ODNB-1">[1]</ref> One of his sons was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gabriel_Powell">Gabriel Powell</ref>, also a clergyman, and a strident anti-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_Catholic">Catholic</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Works</head>
<p>Powel made a significant contribution to developing and preserving Welsh culture and to the growth of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protestantism">Protestantism</ref> in Wales.  He was a supporter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Morgan_(Bible_translator)">William Morgan</ref>'s efforts to translate the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Welsh_Bible">Bible into Welsh</ref>. He kept the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Privy_Council">Privy Council</ref> informed about illegal books circulating amongst Roman Catholics in Wales.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ODNB-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>He was a respected scholar and was associated with geographers such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Dee_(mathematician)">John Dee</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Hakluyt">Richard Hakluyt</ref>. In 1573, Powel took over the task of preparing for publication an English translation (by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Humphrey_Llwyd">Humphrey Llwyd</ref>) of some <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cronica_Walliae">medieval Welsh chronicles</ref>, upon which John Dee had been working before leaving England.  Powel expanded Llwyd's work in its scope and detail, with the help of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Cecil,_1st_Baron_Burghley">Lord Burghley</ref> providing access to some further documents, making his own contributions clear by typographical distinctions. The resulting publication in 1584, <hi rend="italic">The Historie of Cambria, now called Wales</hi>, was the first printed history of Wales.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ODNB-1">[1]</ref> The work remained an important source for medieval Welsh history for several centuries thereafter.  It also popularised the legend that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Madoc">Prince Madoc</ref> had discovered America in about 1170, a tale used to justify English encroachments on the territory of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spanish_America">Spanish America</ref> (for example in Hakluyt's <hi rend="italic">Discourse on Western Planting</hi>).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ODNB-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Powel also published a volume with editions of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ponticus_Virunnius">Ponticus Virunnius</ref>'s <hi rend="italic">Historia Britannica</hi>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gerald_of_Wales">Gerald of Wales</ref>'s <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Itinerarium_Cambriae">Itinerarium Cambriae</ref></hi> ('Journey through Wales', 1191) and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Descriptio_Cambriae">Descriptio Cambriae</ref></hi> ('Description of Wales', 1194), but omitted Gerald's negative comments about the Welsh. The volume was dedicated to Sidney.  He is also said (by the later lexicographer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Davies_(Mallwyd)">John Davies</ref>) to have worked on an unpublished Welsh dictionary.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ODNB-1">[1]</ref></p>
</text>
