<text id="autogum_voyage_doc385" title="Plymouth (Minnesota)" shortTile="plymouth-minnesota" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=27884" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Plymouth (Minnesota)</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.plymouthmn.gov">Plymouth</ref></hi> is a city located in the heart of <ref target="Minnesota">Minnesota</ref>. This city is place that has a good solid community and friendly people. Plymouth has a lot to offer both its residents and its travelers. They are known for having affordable housing, low crime rates and most importantly an active outdoor culture. Plymouth was also Money Magazine's best place to live in 2008. If Plymouth was ranked as the number one place to live, it must be a really great place to travel to as well.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>The Minneapolis/St. Paul International Airport is only fifteen miles from Plymouth. There are numerous taxis in Plymouth taking travelers to and from their destinations. Automobiles are the most common type of transportation for travelers who are staying in the city and need to get around.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>Interstate 494 runs through the city and connects to Interstate 94 just north of Plymouth in the city of Maple Grove. U.S. Highway 169 runs along the eastern edge of town.</p>

<head>See</head>

<p>Something special in Plymouth that all travelers to the city should see is its open-air amphitheater. The Hilde Performance Center is located right in Plymouth and holds numerous summer concerts. This is definitely a fun and exciting place that all tourists should visit during the course of their trip. </p>
<p>In February, Plymouth hosts its annual Fire and Ice Festival. Attendees can play mini-golf, basketball and go bowling, all right on the ice. </p>

<head>Do</head>

<p>Plymouth has a lot to offer tourists when it comes to its parks and recreation. The city of Plymouth has the Recreation Division, the Park Maintenance Division, the Plymouth Creek Center and Field house, and the Plymouth Ice Center. The city has done a lot over the years to spruce up its recreation division. The Recreation Division offers many programs, classes and events for people of all ages.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sky Zone Minneapolis</hi>. - located in Plymouth</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>

<p>Shopping is a fun thing to do in Plymouth. With the Mall of America nearby, going shopping is always an option if you want something fun to do on your trip here. </p>

<head>Eat</head>

<p>There are a ton of restaurants and places to eat in Plymouth. There are full-service restaurants like Chili's and T.G.I Fridays. There are Chinese and Thai restaurants. Like most places, Plymouth has a plenty of fast-food restaurants to choose from as well.</p>

<head>Sleep</head>

<p>There are a lot of hotels in Plymouth and all are reasonably priced. Some hotels are: Radisson Hotel and Conference Center, the Country Inn and Suites, the Comfort Inn, and the Red Roof Inn and Suites.</p>

<head>Connect</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Plymouth Library</hi>, 15700 36th Ave N (at Vicksburg Ln), ☏ +1 612 543-5825 . M-Th 9AM-9PM, F-Sa 9AM-5PM, Su noon-5PM. Local branch of the Hennepin County Library. Free wi-fi.</item>
</list>
</text>
