<text id="autogum_interview_doc318" title="part5_John Reed on Orwell, God, self-destruction and the future of writing" shortTile="partjohn-reed-orwell" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-18" dateModified="2015-01-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Reed_on_Orwell%2C_God%2C_self-destruction_and_the_future_of_writing" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Was there a moment where your switch was flicked, where you were like, "I've had enough." Was there a breaking point?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  For me it was 9/11.  You had these armies of people covered in chalk walking past our apartment.  I had had the idea for the book--I had a title in my head, Snowball's Chance, walking along <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lafayette%20Street">Lafayette Street</ref> on September 10th.  I mentioned it to my wife; she said, "Uh, I don't know, it doesn't sound too great."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  [chuckles]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  But I was sure that there was something good about it. And then 9/11 happened.  I sat there watching TV for three days, like everyone else, riding my bike with a gas mask on and getting cartridges for my wife and brother.</p>
<figure><caption>Reed at the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2007_Brooklyn_Book_Festival_showcases_borough's_continued_literary_tradition">Brooklyn Book Festival</ref>.Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Did you really?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Yeah, you know, I have a lot of really strong memories from that period.  The one that is with me right now is there was a policeman…we were downtown, so we had to go past this checkpoint. I was wearing a gas mask from minute one, because I just could feel that this was not good, the stuff that was in the air.  He looked at me--you know, most of the cops would make fun of us for wearing gas masks, because they heard that it was safe--this one cop was standing there, looked at us and said, "Do you know something that I don't know?"  And of course, we did know something, which is that the city officials were lying to us.  I always think back on that guy, and I wonder--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is he dead?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Yeah. Who knows?  But anyway--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Or suffering--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Two or three days after 9/11, I realized Snowball's Chance meant that Snowball came back to the farm.  I had pretty much the whole book in my head at that moment.  I wrote it over the course of about two weeks, sitting there writing nonstop, writing what I already knew was there--catching it on paper.  Was my rage directed then at Orwell?  More it was like my creative energy was just into this thing.  In retrospect, I realized what it was.  A lot of the book mocks Orwell and ups his very dry delivery; all of that stuff is creative impetus.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Orwell forms such a fundamental basis for so much <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neoconservative">neoconservative</ref> thinking, almost as an ideological text.  Like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Outsiders%20(novel)">The Outsiders</ref> forms our sense of what a rebel is to a degree, and Orwell gives us a worldview of--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Yeah, I think that's it exactly.  Right when 9/11 happened, that period was over.  Animal Farm was looking forward into a fifty-year period, and suddenly that period was over.  That paradigm was over at that moment.  That's when it seemed like open game to me.  I was actually pretty pissed at Orwell, once I figured all that out, because the Cold War mentality had largely gotten us into that mess.</p>
</text>
