<text id="autogum_interview_doc141" title="part1_North Korea&amp;apos;s rising tensions: Wikinews interviews Scott Snyder and Dr Robert Kelly" shortTile="partnorth-koreas" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-04-04" dateModified="2015-09-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/North_Korea%27s_rising_tensions%3A_Wikinews_interviews_Scott_Snyder_and_Dr_Robert_Kelly" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Are South Korean citizens carrying on their day to day lives as normal?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RK</hi>: Yes, they are. This is not like the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cuban%20Missile%20Crisis">Cuban Missile Crisis</ref> when people were emptying the store shelves and building bunkers in their basements. My students are coming and going like normal. Indeed, South Koreans' composure is very impressive.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SS</hi>: Yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Is North Korea becoming further isolated in the world?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RK</hi>: Yes, it is. Threatening nuclear war is a genuine escalation that would alienate any state. Importantly though, NK is already fairly isolated. And because China, its main aid supplier, does not cut it off, further isolation has few practical impacts.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SS</hi>: North Korea is increasingly politically isolated but it is comparatively more economically and informationally connected than it was a decade ago.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>   Is the South Korean military well-prepared to deal with any conflicts with the North Korean military?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RK</hi>: Yes. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republic%20of%20Korea%20Army">ROKA</ref> [Republic of Korea Army, of South Korea] is a modern, well-trained, well-groomed force with substantial technical and organization superiority over the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Korean%20People's%20Army">KPA</ref> [Korean People's Army, of North Korea]. To date, the South Koreans have not responded to Northern provocation in order to avoid escalation, not because they are incapable. SK conventional superiority is augmented further by US assistance.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SS</hi>: South Korea will decisively win most direct conventional engagements with the North, but is vulnerable in selected theaters where North Korea perceives a lack of readiness or a tactical advantage.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Is the closure of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kaesong">Kaesong</ref> by North Korea, evidence of further escalating tensions between the two nations?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RK</hi>: Yes and no. It is important, because it is a source of hard currency for the North, so its closure suggests that the North is willing to carry genuine costs over this feud. On the other hand, the SK media identified the closure of Kaesong early as a marker of NK seriousness, saying very openly that if NK did not close the facility, they did not really mean what they were saying. In other words, NK was, I think, goaded into closing Kaesong in the war of words, not as a part of any larger strategic plan.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SS</hi>: Thus far, it is a symbolic evidence of potential for escalating tensions, but has not yet resulted in material changes.  Let's see how the situation plays out over the next couple of days.  Kaesong will only become vulnerable when operations halt and when financial transfers connected to failure of operations become operative.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  North Korea has moved one of its missiles that carries a large range missile to its East Coast, is this a serious move?</p>
<figure></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">RK</hi>: I don't think it's as serious a move as the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Media">media</ref> has made it out to be. First of all they just moved one [missile]. Second of all, it's not clear that North Korea actually has nuclear warheads that are small enough to actually put on top of missiles; they tell us this but nuclear weapons are actually pretty heavy, which is why <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Nuclear_missiles">nuclear missiles</ref> are frequently quite large, so moving the weapon there doesn't necessarily mean it's pointed at the United States or <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tokyo">Tokyo</ref> which I suppose would be the likely targets. It's not clear that it's necessarily a nuclear missile and it's not being fueled or anything so far as I know so again it's sort of more of the same... bluffing...sort of talking around the issue and sort of saying things that don't actually have genuine consequences so my sense is it's more of a war of words.</p>
</text>
