<text id="autogum_interview_doc016" title="part4_Wikinews attends 2018 Bangalore ComicCon" shortTile="partwikinews-attends" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2018-11-21" dateModified="2019-07-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_attends_2018_Bangalore_ComicCon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Do you mind if I take a photo of yours?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">ROS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Yeah, by all means!</p>
<head id="Interview_with_English_comic_book_writer_Dan_Watters">Interview with English comic book writer Dan Watters</head>
<figure><caption>Comicbook writer Dan Watters.Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Acagastya">Agastya</ref>.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>Wikinews</caption></figure><p> Thank you for agreeing to the interview.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Agastya</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  So, would you mind telling us about yourself?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Dan Watters</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Um, Okay. I'm Dan Watters. I am currently writing <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lucifer%20comic%20book">Lucifer</ref></hi> for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vertigo">Vertigo Comics</ref>. And <hi rend="italic">Deep Roots</hi> for Vault Comics. I've done series for <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Assassin's%20Creed">Assassin's Creed</ref></hi>, for <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wolfenstein">Wolfenstein</ref></hi>. <hi rend="italic">Limbo</hi> was my first book, at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Image%20Comics">Image Comics</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How old are you and when did you start writing comics?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DW</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I am 27. And my first book came out in 2015. So for about three years, I have been doing it professionally.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What drew you into comics, and who was the major influence for you to start writing comics?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DW</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Oh man! I originally thought I was gonna get into film-making, but that's such a slow and arduous process, and sort of relinquish control to so many people because of such a big team and everything, that I sort of fell into comics as something where you, where the writer has a little bit more control, like, directly. Major influence-wise, I was a huge fan of old-school Vertigo stuff: say, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sandman%20(DC%20Comics)">Sandman</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic">Lucifer</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Swamp Thing</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Doom Patrol</hi>: those were the books that really made me want to write.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What was your first job like?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DW</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  My first comics job? [...] Ah, well, Caspar Wijngaard the artist and I pitched <hi rend="italic">Limbo</hi> to Image Comics, in-person at a festival, a ComicCon, in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UK">UK</ref> called Thought Bubble, and, we got the go ahead, to go away and make that book, but we were brand-new, we had no idea of what we were doing. And we entirely had to essentially work, or feel our way through. So we weren't doing a book that had an editor, or had other people in charge. It was just the two of us making this book, which was just amazing and terrifying, but such a sort of trial by fire as far as these things go so there's no one to tell us how to do things things, but it was great, I mean, really happy how the book came out.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How has the times changed since then?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DW</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Well, now I am working with a, because I have done a lot of work stuff on licensed works, doing stuff which is other people's properties: so be it big franchises, like <hi rend="italic">Assassin's Creed</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Wolfenstein</hi> where it's very well established things that you have to sort of, you know, there's certain fan expectations in that and things that you need to, things you need to have. To something like <hi rend="italic">Lucifer</hi> which I am doing now, which is a spin-off of <hi rend="italic">Sandman</hi>, so it's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neil%20Gaiman">Neil Gaiman</ref> worlds, that I'm writing. And so it's a big difference between writing from something that's entirely your own and you can do anything with it; and writing something that's someone else's that has the weight of history, you know, has a weight of series history behind it. But, I enjoy all of it.</p>
</text>
