<text id="autogum_academic_doc634" title="The S2 Subunit of QX-type Infectious Bronchitis Coronavirus Spike Protein Is an Essential Determinant of Neurotropism" shortTile="s-subunit-qxtype" author="Jinlong Cheng, Ye Zhao, Gang Xu, Keran Zhang, Wenfeng Jia, Yali Sun, Jing Zhao, Jia Xue, Yanxin Hu, Guozhong Zhang" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1999-4915/11/10/972/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Coronaviruses (CoVs) are single-strand plus RNA viruses, which belong to the order <hi rend="italic">Nidovirales</hi>. CoVs normally infect epithelial cells such as respiratory epithelial cells, intestinal epithelial cells and kidney epithelial cells, which causes respiratory or intestinal tract diseases with various levels of severity. Human coronavirus 229E (HCoV-229E) is a main cause of the common cold, while severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV) and Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV) cause severe respiratory disease that can be life-threatening to humans. However, some CoVs-like mouse hepatitis virus John Howard Mueller strain (MHV-JHM) infect oligodendrocytes, astrocytes and microglia and cause acute encephalomyelitis. Additionally, human coronavirus OC43 (HCoV-OC43) can also reach the central nervous system (CNS) by intranasal inoculation in BALB/c mice, which causes encephalitis. The release of cytokines such as TNF-α, interleukin-1β (IL-1β) and interleukin-6 (IL-6) is closely associated with encephalitis. Infectious bronchitis virus (IBV) belongs to the gamma-coronavirus group (γ-CoV), which causes a highly contagious, acute viral respiratory disease of chickens that has caused great economic losses in the poultry industry. At present, QX-type IBV is epidemic worldwide; it can damage the respiratory, digestive and urogenital systems of chickens. Besides, because of severe damage of respiratory mucosa, infected chickens are susceptible to secondary infection by mycoplasma, bacteria, or other pathogens causing high mortality. </p>

<p>All CoV virions encode a set of four structural proteins, namely; spike glycoprotein (S), small envelope protein (E), membrane glycoprotein (M) and nucleocapsid proteins (N). S protein belongs to the class I fusion proteins, located at the surface of the virion. The trimeric S glycoprotein is a class I fusion protein and mediates attachment to the host receptor. S is typically cleaved by a host cell furin-like protease into two separate polypeptides named S1 and S2. S1 makes up the large receptor-binding domain of the S protein, while S2 forms the stalk of the spike molecule. There is an extra furin cleavage site (furin-S2′ site) upstream of the fusion peptide in the S2 subunit of some CoVs, which has been reported to influence the mechanism of invasion of host cells by CoVs. When the original sequence PTKR/S of SARS-CoV was replaced with RRKR/S, SARS-CoV could invade susceptible cells while no longer relying on cathepsin L. Additionally, after the S2′ site mutated into the furin-S2′ site of the MHV-A59 strain, MHV can fuse with susceptible cells in the early endosome, but not lysosome, without requiring lysosomal enzymes such as MERS-CoV. As for IBV, the furin-S2′ site is a determinant of cellular adaptation of the IBV-Beaudette strain. If this motif is lacking, the IBV-Beaudette strain, which is normally the only IBV strain able to adapt to the Vero cell line, can no longer grow in these cells. </p>

<p>Most basic research on IBV performed to date has been based on the IBV-Beaudette strain; therefore, much remains unknown about the pathogenic mechanism of QX-type IBV. Here, we rescued a mutant QX-type IBV with the furin-S2′ site and compared the pathogenicity of the mutant IBV with its parental virus. We also further investigated the tissue and cell tropism. Finally, we clarified the biological significance with an immunoprotection experiment. The function of S protein in QX-type IBV was demonstrated, which is more valuable for poultry than research about the IBV-Beaudette strain. </p>
</text>
