<text id="autogum_whow_doc612" title="Be Yourself and Impress Others" shortTile="yourself-impress" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2013-03-02" dateModified="2018-12-19" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be-Yourself-and-Impress-Others" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be Yourself and Impress Others</head><p>You may not know, but you should always be yourself, even when you're trying to impress everyone. This can be hanging out with many people or dressing to show who you are. Need some help? Read below on how to do so.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Create yourself! You may not know who you are, what you like, what you want to do in life, but this is okay. Create yourself, don't find yourself, create yourself. Create your own personality, but be yourself. Creating your personality doesn't mean copying others, but you can always get influence. Have confidence, a good sense of style and a contagious smile. <figure rend="Decide-on-a-Partner-Type-Step-1-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Dress to impress. Bring out who you are in your own fashion sense. Don't throw on an outfit everyday -- spend time on how you want to bring out yourself in each outfit. <figure rend="Be-Beautiful-(for-Gay-Men)-Step-19-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remain who you are. You may change, and always will, but you will always be yourself. Know that if you are being yourself, and someone doesn't like you, they're not right. Ignore them and know that there are many other people you can impress, you don't need to impress anyone. Be yourself, everyone's going to get judged anyway, sometime in their life. <figure rend="Believe-in-Yourself-Step-13-Version-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find the real friends. Don't use someone as a friend just to act popular. This is very common. Find the real friends, the ones that you think will really be there for you, and not your popularity. <figure rend="Dress-Nice-Everyday-(for-Girls)-Step-22-Version-4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try making as many friends as possible. Smile at everyone, compliment them, and start talking to them more. Once this happens, you may have a sleepover or hang out sometime, this can lead to a whole new friendship. <figure rend="Get-a-Boy-in-Middle-School-to-Like-You-Step-6-Version-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do what you like, and only you. Don't do drugs to be cool and don't be someone you're not to fit in. Nobody can make you do anything, and you are your own person. Nobody can own you, and never let them. <figure rend="Believe-in-Yourself-Step-14-Version-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Never be shy. This will make some people think you're sad, and others may think you have a low self esteem. Smile at people, keep your chin up and be friendly. <figure rend="Get-Over-an-Embarrassing-Moment-Step-11-Version-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be confident. Have great posture and do what you want. Don't be shy and never bully someone. <figure rend="Be-Pretty-if-You-Are-Unfortunate-With-Your-Looks-Step-1-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find your talents and make it shine. Acting? Dancing? Whatever it is, perform, take classes or join clubs. Find something to make new friends and impress people that way. <figure rend="Feel-Confident-With-Your-Special-Talents-Step-14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>You are finished! Remember that if you do have more friends, or impressed more people, know to stay who you are. Never judge people and know that even if you are trying to impress everyone, not everyone may be impressed, they're not worth it. You are. So, have confidence, keep your head up and smile. <figure rend="Tell-a-Guy-You-Like-Him-Step-9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Know that not everyone will love you, and that's okay.</item>
<item>Never change for someone.</item>
<item>Keep your true friends.</item>
<item>Remain who you are.</item>
<item>Don't act like you're the best, but have confidence.</item>
<item>Don't try too hard to become a different person.</item>
<item>Find who is worth it.</item></list>
</text>
