<text id="autogum_voyage_doc103" title="Gloucester (England)" shortTile="gloucester-england" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=12863" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Gloucester (England)</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.gloucester.gov.uk/">Gloucester</ref></hi> is the county town of <ref target="Gloucestershire">Gloucestershire</ref> in <ref target="England">England's</ref> <ref target="West%20England">West Country</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>The City of Gloucester is the furthest inland port in the UK, situated beside the River Severn. It inspired the old English nursery rhyme:</p>

<p>'Dick Whittington', born around 1350, a well-known character through the pantomime story, has connections with Gloucester. The story is based on the real-life Richard Whittington, who, unlike his pantomime character, was not poor, being the third son of Sir William Whittington of Gloucester. The traditional tale has a 'poor' Dick going to London to seek his fortune, but he eventually becomes Lord Mayor of London.</p>

<p>A traditional rhyme is associated with this episode, as follows:</p>

<p>"Turn again, Whittington,</p>
<p>Once Mayor of London,</p>
<p>Turn again, Whittington,</p>
<p>Twice Mayor of London,</p>
<p>Turn again, Whittington,</p>
<p>Thrice Mayor of London!"</p>

<p>The city is also known for 'The Tailor of Gloucester', a children's novel by Beatrix Potter that was first published in 1903. It is traditionally read to children on Christmas Eve, just before bedtime.</p>

<p>It was a main <ref target="Roman%20Empire">Roman</ref> city, <hi rend="bold">Glevum</hi>—Roman tunnels and fortifications exist underneath the city centre and can be visited through the museum.</p>

<head>Language</head>

<p>As a provincial British town, you will almost certainly need to be able to speak English to get around in Gloucester. There is a sizable immigrant population in Gloucester from Pakistan, Bangladesh, Poland and the Czech Republic and so you may have more luck with these people should you speak one of their languages. Gloucester also has a large (for the region) black (mainly of Caribbean origin) community.</p>

<p>The Tourist Information Office has literature in most major languages, including Japanese.</p>

<p>Generally, the Gloucester accent is clear to understand and isn't peppered with dialect terms. However, understandably for the area, there is a West Country 'burr'and tourists whose experience of English accents is limited to either Cockney or Queen's English may notice this. The 'burr' becomes more pronounced more westerly, in nearby Forest of Dean,</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>Gloucester is well served by the motorway system and can easily be accessed by junctions 11, 11a and 12 on the M5. It also lies on the A38 and is easily accessible from <ref target="Wales">Wales</ref> (Gloucester is the most southerly point on the River Severn with a bridge—apart from the motorway Severn Bridges near <ref target="Bristol">Bristol</ref> and <ref target="Newport%20%28Monmouthshire%29">Newport</ref>). Because Gloucester was a major Roman city, it has very good A road connections throughout Gloucestershire and the Cotswolds.</p>

<head>By train</head>

 has good railway connections (Platform 1/3 at Gloucester is Europe's longest) and has daily direct connections to <ref target="London">London</ref>, <ref target="Cardiff">Cardiff</ref>, <ref target="Bristol">Bristol</ref> and <ref target="Birmingham%20%28England%29">Birmingham</ref>. Nearby <ref target="Cheltenham">Cheltenham</ref> has more stopping trains, so it may be necessary to get a train to Cheltenham and change trains for Gloucester. Trains between Cheltenham and Gloucester operate every half hour and take around 10 minutes.

<head>By bus</head>

<p>Gloucester is a large hub for buses and coaches. The has many regular coaches (mainly operated by National Express) to all major airports and cities (there are several coaches to and from London daily) in the UK. A Megabus service to and from London also operates from outside the bus station.</p>

<p>Gloucester was built up around the River Severn. It has a sailing heritage. It is possible to visit Gloucester via river or the Gloucester Sharpness Canal via boat.</p>

<p>A park and ride service is available see, <ref target="http://www.parkandride.net/gloucester/gloucester_frameset.shtml">National Park and Ride Directory</ref>.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>Nearby Staverton hosts ( GLO ), which has regular flights to <ref target="Jersey">Jersey</ref>. There are also many private aircraft there, which can be chartered.</p>

<ref target="https://birminghamairport.co.uk">Birmingham Airport</ref> ( BHX ) and <ref target="https://www.bristolairport.co.uk/">Bristol Airport</ref> ( BRS ) are each only a couple of hours' drive (north and south respectively) and offer a wide range of destinations, both inside and outside of Europe.

<p>It can take several hours to drive to the London airports (<ref target="Heathrow">Heathrow</ref> ( LHR ), <ref target="Gatwick">Gatwick</ref> ( LGW ), <ref target="https://www.london-luton.co.uk/">Luton</ref> ( LTN ) and <ref target="Stansted">Stansted</ref> ( STN )).</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>Stagecoach operates most of the local bus services and between Gloucester and Cheltenham. There are many bus services to the Forest of Dean, South Wales, Gloucestershire, the South West and the Midlands.</p>

<head>By bicycle</head>
<p>There are several cycle routes around Gloucester and it is possible to have a fairly stress-free cycle ride around the city and its suburbs. There are also cycle routes to Cheltenham and to Bristol.</p>

<head>By foot</head>
<p>The centre of Gloucester is quite compact and flat so you can easily walk around it.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>The best way to get to the countryside around Gloucester is by car.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Gloucester Cathedral</hi> (Cathedral Church of St Peter and the Holy and Indivisible Trinity), 12 College Green, GL1 2LX, ☏ +44 1452 528095 , ✉ reception@gloucestercathedral.org.uk . The city's cathedral and an important landmark. Completed in 1499, this Gothic building has a beautiful design and heritage. In popular culture, the cathedral is well-known for being used for filming in several of the Harry Potter movies. Free. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Gloucester Docks</hi>. 18th century, a popular tourist attraction, with numerous museums and shops/pubs. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Baker's Jewellers</hi> (Baker G A &amp; Son), 5 Southgate St, GL1 1TG, ☏ +44 1452 522926 . One of the most unusual 'action' time clocks you are likely to see in a city centre. It dates back to Edwardian times and has five figures which represent England, Scotland, Wales, Ireland and Olde Father Time.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Prinknash Abbey</hi>, Cranham, GL4 8EX. With its monastery, bird park and Roman Mosaic. This latter is a full-size copy of the original mosaic on the floor of a Roman villa at nearby Woodchester, now in a churchyard. The original is thought to have been created in c.325 AD. It has been unearthed periodically several times, but the last time it was on view to the public, in 1973, it produced so much interest and traffic congestion in the town that it was decided never to unearth it again. Devastated by the possibility that no-one else would see it ever again, two local builders spent ten years working on the reconstruction. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Eastgate Viewing Chamber</hi>. The Eastgate Viewing Chamber is the remains of the Roman settlement. While it can be viewed at street level from outside of Boots, there are also tours from Museum of Gloucester that can be booked.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Severn Bore</hi>. Probably one of the most famous tidal bores. It is of particular interest to surfers. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">College Court</hi>.</item>
</list>
</text>
