<text id="autogum_whow_doc588" title="Live in a World Full of Preconceptions" shortTile="live-world-full-preconceptions" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2016-05-23" dateModified="2018-12-14" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Live-in-a-World-Full-of-Preconceptions" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Live in a World Full of Preconceptions</head><p>Your family, your neighbors, everybody has these preconceptions. You might ask yourself, "How should I behave?" "What clothes should I wear?" "Who should I be like?" "How much should I score?" "Which college should I go to?" and so on and so forth. But now, you have decided that you are done with thinking about these questions. You want to live free. You want to learn to appreciate the small things in life. You want to be madly in love with life. If this describes what you want, then this wikiHow will help teach you how to live in a world full of preconceptions.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Have a cause for hope, or a reason to live. Have something to look forward to. It might be to travel the world, or buy a motorcycle and ride cross country, or maybe you want to learn about different cultures.
<list type="unordered"><item>Find beauty in the most odd and imperfect things - from an old, wrinkle faced woman bent over a fire, to a tiny flower growing on a hillside.</item></list></item>
<item>Learn to calm down. Take it in from one ear and let it out through the other. These days, you don't really see anyone who is not willing to get into a fight. When you get stuck in an argument, take a deep breath. Listen to what the other person has to say. Think it through. Ask yourself: does what they said make sense? Are they correct? Are you wrong?
<list type="unordered"><item>If you do find sense in what they say, let them know. Accept your fault. If you find yourself to be the correct one, then don't yell to make your point. Be calm. Explain your view to the person. If they refuse to understand, hope that they eventually will.</item></list></item>
<item>Be understanding. Understand one another, understand the needs of others, and understand the complications in the matter. See the situation through the other person's point of view. Just this one step would make you a happy person. But don't be disappointed if the other person fails to show understanding for your matter. Not everyone is like you.</item>
<item>Live free. Break society's rules. If your elders tell you that it's unladylike to wear shorts, don't listen. People will always tell you what to do and what not to do because they all consider themselves better than others, and they think that their ideas and what they think is what is correct. Despair not, for that should not bother you. You are the maker of decisions your life. You can do what you love to do and what you know is right.</item>
<item>Remember that no one is broken too bad. There's always that glue to fix you up. Your job is to find that glue.</item></list>
</text>
