<text id="autogum_news_doc583" title="Wikinews interviews Spanish Paralympic swimmer Marta Gómez" shortTile="wikinews-interviews" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-08-09" dateModified="2013-08-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Spanish_Paralympic_swimmer_Marta_G%C3%B3mez" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Spanish Paralympic swimmer Marta Gómez</head>
<figure><caption><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> interviews <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marta%20Gómez%20(swimmer)">Marta Gomez</ref>. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:LauraHale">Laura Hale</ref>.</caption></figure><figure><caption>Marta Gomez at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Madrid–Barajas_Airport">Madrid–Barajas Airport</ref> yesterday Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:LauraHale">Laura Hale</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, August 11, 2013</hi></p>
<p>Thursday at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Madrid–Barajas_Airport">Madrid–Barajas Airport</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> interviewed <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Spain">Spanish</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Paralympics">Paralympic</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Swimming">swimmer</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marta%20Gómez%20(swimmer)">Marta Gomez</ref>, who is scheduled to compete at the 2013 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IPC%20Swimming%20World%20Championships">IPC Swimming World Championships</ref> that start on Monday in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Montreal">Montreal</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada">Canada</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  This is Laura Hale, I'm interviewing Marta Gómez, a Spanish Paralympic swimmer going to the 2013 IPC Swimming World Championships in Montreal. Are you going to Montreal and what strokes and distances are you competing in?</p>
<hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marta%20Gomez">Marta Gomez</ref></hi>: I'll swim the 100 meter and 400 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/freestyle%20swimming">freestyle</ref>, and the 200 individual <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/medley%20swimming">medley</ref>. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Voy a nadar los 100 [metros] y 400 libres, y los 200 estilo giro.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Have you won any medals at previous championships? ((es))Spanish language: ‍¿Vas a ganar alguna medalla?</p>
<hi rend="bold">Marta Gomez</hi>: In 2011, at the European Championships in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Berlin">Berlin</ref>, I won 3 bronze. ((es))Spanish language: ‍En Europeo 2011, en Berlín, gané 3 bronces.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Do you think you will win any medals in Montreal? ((es))Spanish language: ‍¿Tienes medalla en Montreal?</p>
<hi rend="bold">Marta Gomez</hi>: I will try to fight for a medal in the 400 freestyle which is my main event, but, well, [if I swim well and feel well] my options are clearer, but until you swim nothing is clear. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Voy a intentar luchar por la medalla en el 400 libres que es mi prueba principal, pero bueno, hay que ¿sentir? y nadarlos; la ¿? serán mis opciones más claras, pero hasta que no se nade no hay nada claro.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  You've competed at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2012_Summer_Paralympics">previous Paralympic Games</ref>? In <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/London">London</ref>?</p>
<hi rend="bold">Marta Gomez</hi>: Yes. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Sí.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  And you didn't win any medals?</p>
<hi rend="bold">Marta Gomez</hi>: No, I didn't win any medals. ((es))Spanish language: ‍No. Fui de cima en Londres.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What's the difference preparing for London to the World Championships? ((es))Spanish language: ‍¿Cuál es la diferencia de la preparación para Londres para el Campeonato del Mundo?</p>
<hi rend="bold">Marta Gomez</hi>: That I have improved many aspects of technical level [like?] performance, and especially the psychological aspect that after London I have faced other competitions and I feel much more confident about myself and I have become more competitive. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Que yo he mejorado muchos aspectos tanto a nivel de técnica como de rendimiento, y sobre todo el aspecto psicológico que a raíz de Londres he afrontado las competiciones de otra manera y me siento mucho más segura de mí misma y me he vuelto más competitiva.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Are you a swimmer with a visual impediment? You cannot see...? ((es))Spanish language: ‍-¿De qué categoría eres?</p>
<hi rend="bold">Marta Gomez</hi>: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/S13%20(classification)">S13</ref>. ((es))Spanish language: ‍S13.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  When you swim, can you see the swimmers next to you? ((es))Spanish language: ‍¿Cuando nadas, se puede ver a los nadadores a tu lado?</p>
<hi rend="bold">Marta Gomez</hi>: Depending on the race, you will always be able to — some races like in short distances like the 100 meter <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/breaststroke">breaststroke</ref> and 100 meter freestyle as it is too short to lose sight of your rivals, but for example in 400 meters, yes, but I can only see from the sides. I cannot see all the swimmers. In the 800 meters, seeing swimmers in the race is impossible: I fail to see them. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Depende de la prueba, siempre va... la de velocidad en pruebas cortas... por ejemplo en 100 [metros] brazas y 100 libres al ser tan cortas no vas tan pendiente de los rivales, pero por ejemplo en 400 sí que puedo ver más pero solamente a las que tengo a los lados, no puedo ver a todas las nadadoras, a las 8 nadadoras de la serie es imposible, no alcanzo a verlas.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  When you swim, do you mostly think about your own race because you cannot fully see everyone? Do you race more against yourself because you can not see? ((es))Spanish language: ‍¿Nadas más contigo misma o por no poder ver? ¿más tu prueba?</p>
<hi rend="bold">Marta Gomez</hi>: Yes, of course. Not being able to see your rivals you have to concentrate on your event because you may have nobody to [watch?], you may have a slight reference but you have to swim against yourself. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Sí, claro. Al no poder ver a las rivales te tienes que ¿dedicar? a hacer tu prueba porque no tienes a lo mejor a nadie en quién fijarte, puedes tener una ligera referencia pero tienes que nadar tu prueba y nadar contigo misma.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Why did you choose swimming as opposed to athletics or <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Goalball">Goalball</ref> or some other sport?</p>
<hi rend="bold">Marta Gomez</hi>: I have only practiced swimming since childhood, I've always liked the water and it's been the only sport I've practiced because I think it's a sport where you feel a lot of freedom and don't have any architectural barriers or anything. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Yo solo he practicado la natación desde pequeña, siempre me ha gustado mucho el agua y ha sido el único deporte que he practicado porque me parece un deporte en que sientes mucha libertad y no tienes ningún tipo de barreras arquitectónicas ni nada.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Gracías. ((en))Spanish language: ‍Thank you.</p>
<hi rend="bold">Marta Gomez</hi>: De nada. ((en))Spanish language: ‍You're welcome.
</text>
