<text id="autogum_reddit_doc140" title="Could the OASIS be real?" shortTile="oasis-real" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-03-31" dateModified="2018-03-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/88lrqn" speakerList="#AGuyNamedJacob, #Destabilised" speakerCount="2">
<head>Could the OASIS be real?</head>
<sp who="#AGuyNamedJacob">
<p>I’ve both seen the movie and read the book, and (probably like most of you) the only thing i want in life right now is for the OASIS to be a thing. I’ve been thinking and reading up about it, and here’s some conclusions I’ve came to. (Keep in mind, I’m not a game designer, these are just my thoughts). 1)  <hi rend="bold">The World</hi>  The OASIS is basically just a gigantic VR MMO. We already have MMO’s, and i don’t see how hard it would be to convert one over to VR. We already see VR multiplayer experiences such as Rec Room and VR chat. The only problem i see is a server overload, where so many people are on at once that no one can join. My solution to this would be to split each planet (or maybe each sector on each planet) into its own server, so the entire OASIS wouldn’t crash. The open world wouldn’t be a problem seeing as we also have things like Skyrim for the VR. 2)  <hi rend="bold">The Technology</hi>  The tech in RPO is probably the most believable thing. VR companies are already working on wireless VR headsets and haptic gloves, so things such as haptic suits and treadmills that simulate walking don’t sound so far off. The most far out thing about the OASIS is it’s extremely life-like graphics, which VR systems don’t have just yet, but are entirely possible. 3)  <hi rend="bold">The Singular OASIS</hi>  The idea of a single OASIS is far-fetched. Many companies will try to make their own OASIS’s, and on top of that, there’ll probably not be one VR console to rule them all, like in RPO. Personally, i see this as a good thing, because it will prove healthy competition for the OASIS that will be the most popular. (Think Apple and Microsoft, Xbox and PlayStation, or Uber and Lyft). 4)  <hi rend="bold">The Pop-Culture References</hi>  In RPO, a big part of the OASIS is the constant stream of Pop culture. (Think copyrighted songs and characters). For one OASIS to have access to every piece of 80’s culture is ridiculous (Unless this OASIS is made after the copyright wears off, and they can use it freely), although possible. Even then, users could possibly use mods to get things that can’t be put in the vanilla game. Different video games, movie companies, and musicians would want to cash in on the VR craze and might be willing to have their things used in the OASIS. These are just some of my thoughts, but like i said, I’m not an expert on any of it. Please post your thoughts or updates for a real OASIS comments. Thanks for reading my ideas. </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#Destabilised">
<p>There’s a game called Secondlife which has been around for many years. It’s probably the closest thing to the OASIS in terms of its scale, being whoever you want to be, creating the world you live in, in-game economy etc. When you search RP1 on Google there’s even an ad for Secondlife! </p>
<p>In terms of copyright in SL, I’m sure there is a cease and desist procedure in place but lots of real world brands are on board and make a profit in game already, if a user number of say 500K was to jump to billions I’m sure they’d soon realise it’s the best place to sell your product. Much like the jump to online shopping and the advertising that came with this, companies are now spending more money on social media ads than real life ads. </p>
<p>The founders (Linden Labs) have also recently released a VR version called Project Sansar which pretty much moves Secondlife into the world of VR, looks like a really interesting place. </p>
<p>In terms of people living inside an online virtual world, I guess we’re already doing that stuck to our phones constantly...wearing the device on our faces everyday (excl Tues and Thurs) ;) probably isn’t that far away. </p>
<p>I guess there’s also the problem of people actually being on board with VR. 3D TVs were groundbreaking at the time and yet now they seem like a gimmick. The sheer about of people logged into the OASIS makes sense because they had to, as a means of survival - but getting the general population on board without a reason would take many years and I’m sure there would be some insane data breach revelation before that time came anyway haha. People aren’t as honest as Wade - as we’ve seen with the latest Facebook scandal. </p>
<p>Sorry for the long post, it’s 1am and I’m feeling profound. Let’s have a discussion! </p>
</sp>
</text>
