<text id="autogum_bio_doc470" title="Thomas Beard" shortTile="thomas-beard" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-06-23" dateModified="2019-10-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Beard" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Thomas Beard</head>
<figure><caption>Thomas Beard</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thomas Beard</hi> (died 1632) was an English clergyman and theologian, of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Puritan">Puritan</ref> views. He is known as the author of <hi rend="italic">The Theatre of Gods Judgements</hi>, and the schoolmaster of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oliver_Cromwell">Oliver Cromwell</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Huntingdon">Huntingdon</ref>.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>He was, it is believed, a native of Huntingdon, but the date of his birth is unknown. He received his education at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesus_College,_Cambridge">Jesus College, Cambridge</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> where he was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sizar">sizar</ref> and matriculated in 1584. He graduated B.A. in 1588, M.A. in 1591, B.D. in 1602 and D.D. in 1614.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Venn-2">[2]</ref> He became rector of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kimbolton,_Cambridgeshire">Kimbolton</ref> in 1595. On 21 January 1598 he was collated to the rectory of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hengrave">Hengrave</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suffolk">Suffolk</ref>, which he held for a very short time, moving as rector to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aythorp_Roothing">Aythorp Roothing</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Essex">Essex</ref>, later in the year. In 1605, Beard became master of Huntingdon hospital and grammar school, where he remained for twenty years.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Venn-2">[2]</ref> It was at this school that Cromwell was educated from around 1604, and was prepared for entrance to Cambridge; he acted in Beard's school plays, and Beard became a friend of the Cromwell family.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> In March 1614, Beard asked Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Bruce_Cotton">Robert Bruce Cotton</ref> for the rectory of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conington,_South_Cambridgeshire">Conington</ref>, being tired of teaching. He held various rectories with his teaching job, in the end at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wistow,_Cambridgeshire">Wistow</ref> where he settled in 1618 for the rest of his life. In 1626, Beard also held a popular lectureship at Huntingdon.</p>
<p>In 1628, when <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Neile">Richard Neile</ref> went before the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Commons_of_England">House of Commons of England</ref> accused of anti-puritan practices, Beard was summoned as a witness against him. Cromwell's speech in the debate on the subject covers his likely testimony (the parliament was dissolved before Beard could testify). Beard had been appointed in 1617 to preach a sermon on the Sunday after <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Easter">Easter</ref> in London, in which, according to custom, he was to recapitulate three sermons previously preached before the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_mayor">lord mayor</ref> from an open pulpit in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spital_Square">Spital Square</ref>. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Alabaster">William Alabaster</ref> was the preacher whom Beard had to follow, but he announced his intention of exposing Alabaster's support of certain tenets of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Popery">popery</ref>. On Cromwell's account, Neile as Beard's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diocesan_bishop">diocesan bishop</ref> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diocese_of_Lincoln">diocese of Lincoln</ref>) told him not to preach against Alabaster; and reprimanded him later when on the advice of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_Felton_(bishop)">Nicholas Felton</ref> he did so.</p>
<p>In 1630 he was made a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Justice_of_the_peace">justice of the peace</ref> for the county. He was married, and had children by Mary Heriman; they were married 9 July 1628. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Wedlake_Brayley">Edward Wedlake Brayley</ref> in his <hi rend="italic">Beauties of England and Wales</hi> recorded the inscription on a brass in the nave of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/All_Saints'_Church,_Huntingdon">All Saints' Church, Huntingdon</ref>, to Beard's memory. In 1633 Archbishop <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Laud">William Laud</ref> succeeded in putting the lectureship down.</p>
<head>Works</head>
<p>Beard's earliest and most famous book first appeared in 1597;<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> a work in the tradition of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Foxe">John Foxe</ref>'s <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Acts_and_Monuments">Acts and Monuments</ref></hi>, it was popular, plagiarised and pirated.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> It was itself translated, in part, from the <hi rend="italic">Histoires memorables des grans et merveilleux jugemens et punitions de Dieu</hi> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean_de_Chassanion">Jean de Chassanion</ref> (1531–1598), a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Huguenot">Huguenot</ref> pastor from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monistrol-sur-Loire">Monistrol-sur-Loire</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> from which it derives its account of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bullet_catch">bullet catch</ref> trick.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>Chassingnon's book provided hundreds of the examples, while Beard added in a scattering from other sources closer to home: Foxe, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Stowe">John Stowe</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raphael_Holinshed">Raphael Holinshed</ref>, pamphlets and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ballad">ballads</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> Beard's exposition of the workings of Providence against sinners and persecutors has been called "theatrical moralism".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> It was in the <hi rend="italic">Theatre of Judgement</hi> that first appeared an account of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Marlowe">Christopher Marlowe</ref>'s death; Beard takes Marlowe to be the first modern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atheist">atheist</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref> Other editions followed in 1612 and 1631, with additions, and a fourth edition in folio of 1648.</p>
<p>In 1625 he published a work on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_as_Antichrist">Pope as Antichrist</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref> Beard left in manuscript an <hi rend="italic">Evangelical Tragoedie: or, A Harmonie of the Passion of Christ, according to the four Evangelistes</hi>. A Latin comedy <hi rend="italic">Pedantius</hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref> has been attributed to him, but also to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_Hawkesworth">Walter Hawkesworth</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anthony_Wingfield_(MP_for_Ripon)">Anthony Wingfield</ref> and (by modern scholars) to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Forsett">Edward Forsett</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref></p>
</text>
