<text id="autogum_academic_doc598" title="Mitotane Concentrations Influence the Risk of Recurrence in Adrenocortical Carcinoma Patients on Adjuvant Treatment" shortTile="mitotane-concentrations" author="Soraya Puglisi, Anna Calabrese, Vittoria Basile, Filippo Ceccato, Carla Scaroni, Chiara Simeoli, Massimo Torlontano, Salvatore Cannavò, Giorgio Arnaldi, Antonio Stigliano, Pasqualino Malandrino, Laura Saba, Barbara Altieri, Silvia Della Casa, Paola Perotti, Paola Berchialla, Giuseppina De Filpo, Letizia Canu, Paola Loli, Giuseppe Reimondo, Massimo Terzolo" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2077-0383/8/11/1850/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
The present study confirms that a remarkable number of patients with ACC who are operated on with radical intent are destined to relapse. ACC recurrence portends a worse prognosis and has a huge impact on quality of life; therefore, investigators have considered the use of adjuvant mitotane therapy following surgical operation. However, a limited number of often small-sized studies reporting the outcome of adjuvant mitotane is available.  </p>

<p>In the present study, we explored the relationship between target mitotane concentrations and patient outcome using the TTR, analogous to warfarin treatment. Some previous studies used the peak mitotane level, which cannot give an adequate representation since it is a measurement at a single point in time. In other studies, the percentage of mitotane measurements in a range was used, but this method has the caveat of being strongly dependent on the number of available measurements. This may introduce a bias when comparing patients with different durations of follow-ups, which may be quite prolonged in the case of adjuvant therapy. Moreover, there is no evidence to define what percentage level identifies a good exposure to mitotane. These methodological issues may have contributed to the discrepancy in the literature concerning adjuvant treatment. In the present study, we calculated the TTR, which in our opinion gives a more adequate representation of chronic exposure to mitotane, and analyzed the results in a multivariate analysis without predefining arbitrary cutoff values. We found an inverse relationship between the TTR and risk of ACC recurrence, implying that the greater the TTR, the lower the risk. This finding supports the clinical value of mitotane monitoring and the concept of target doses in the adjuvant setting. Although it is plausible that lower mitotane concentrations may be effective in an adjuvant treatment, we analyzed only the level of 14 mg/L, because this was the target in our practice.  </p>

<p>The time needed to achieve target mitotane concentrations also has an impact on the risk of ACC recurrence: a longer time was associated with higher risk. This is consistent with the concept that mitotane is a slow-acting drug in relation to the achievement of significant plasma levels. Due to the very cautious dose titration in the starting phase of treatment employed in many centers, the time needed to get into the target range was exceedingly long. We identified a time point at 17 months to achieve target concentrations, which significantly differentiates patients for their risk of recurrence. The present findings call for a change in practice, aiming for a faster rise in mitotane levels and strengthening the value of mitotane monitoring. However, the potential danger of a rapid increment in mitotane dosing, which may result in important toxicity with consequent loss of compliance to treatment, should be considered. </p>

<p>We found only a weak relationship between mitotane dose and its plasma concentrations during the first phase of treatment, and this finding is in agreement with the concept that individual differences in mitotane metabolism and other still unknown factors influence plasma concentrations. Interestingly, higher doses were employed in men and in patients with greater BMI and these novel findings matter for clinical practice.  </p>

<p>In our cohort, toxicity associated with adjuvant mitotane was acceptable, though we acknowledge the fact that due to the study inclusion criteria we did not capture the patients who eventually discontinued mitotane in the first six months. Severe toxicity leading to permanent treatment discontinuation was recorded in only five patients on chronic therapy, and this is likely due to the low doses (median dose of 2 g/day) used to continue treatment in the maintenance phase. Thus, the present study shows that a few patients cannot tolerate adjuvant mitotane following the first months of treatment, proving than a careful follow-up is necessary. Despite mitotane having a reputation for being a challenging drug to manage, adjuvant mitotane treatment is feasible when patients are managed in expert centers. However, some patients were unable to tolerate the drug, exhibiting neurological toxicity even when exposed to “normal” mitotane concentrations, confirming the relevance of individual factors in mitotane metabolism.  </p>

<p>Strengths of the present study are the thorough characterization of adjuvant mitotane treatment of ACC patients following surgical removal of the tumor and the large data set, considering the rarity of the disease. This allowed for the capture of details of mitotane treatment that were not available in previous studies and led to observations that may be useful to informing future practice. However, we should acknowledge the limits of a retrospective analysis, and that our results are not generalizable to patients who discontinue treatment within six months for intolerability or patients with early ACC recurrence. The inclusion criteria of the study produced an immortal time of six months that may have enriched our series of a higher number of low-risk ACC compared to recently published series. </p>
</text>
