<text id="autogum_voyage_doc99" title="Guadalajara" shortTile="guadalajara" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=13516" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Guadalajara</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://portal.guadalajara.gob.mx/">Guadalajara</ref></hi> is the capital of the central state of <ref target="Jalisco">Jalisco</ref> in <ref target="Mexico">Mexico</ref>, and the second-largest city in the country, with about a million and a half citizens (known as "Tapatíos"). It is considered a colonial city, though much of its architecture dates from the independence period. Although it has a far more relaxed feel than <ref target="Mexico%20City">Mexico City</ref>, the city center can still seem a bit stuffy and dusty, especially during rush hour when the sun is out. All in all, however, it is a lovely city and contains many nice areas for walking, not just in the center.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>Guadalajara is Mexico's second largest city, and one of the fastest-growing metropolitan areas in the country. This growth has been driven in part by the booming electronics industry in the industrial outskirts of the city. Other important and growing industries are pharmaceuticals, food processing, and fashion.</p>

<head>Orientation</head>

<p>Guadalajara proper is divided into four districts corresponding approximately to the northwest, northeast, southwest, and southeast quarters of the city. At the center of everything is the main area of interest to tourists, the <hi rend="bold">Centro Histórico</hi>, or the historic downtown. Most of your time will probably be spent here. It is filled with colonial-era buildings and, famously, also boasts several important mural paintings by Jalisco-born José Clemente Orozco, one of Mexico's most important artists.</p>

<p>Outside the Centro Histórico are:</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sector Hidalgo</hi>— in northwest of the Centro Histórico, Hidalgo is a largely residential sector encompassing the financial district and the <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.gcc.com.mx/">Country Club Guadalajara</ref></hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sector Libertad</hi>— northeast of the Centro Histórico, Sector Libertad is mostly given over to industrial use. However, the southwest part of the sector, close to the Centro Histórico, boasts a traditional market (<hi rend="bold">Mercado Libertad</hi>) and the <hi rend="bold">Plaza de los Mariachis</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sector Juárez</hi>— southwest of the Centro Histórico, Sector Juárez is a shoppers' paradise: it boasts two shopping malls (<hi rend="bold">Centro Magno</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Galerias</hi>), as well as the popular <hi rend="bold">Minerva</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Chapultepec</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Zona Rosa</hi> shopping areas.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sector Reforma</hi>— southeast of the Centro Histórico, Reforma is also a mostly industrial sector, but visitors will no doubt be interested in the pleasant, tree-filled <hi rend="bold">Parque Agua Azul</hi>, as well as the <hi rend="bold">Tianguis Cultural de Guadalajara</hi>, a street market where alternative clothing and articles such as spiked belts, black trenchcoats, military uniforms, used books and trading cards are for sale at good prices.</item>
</list>


<p>Still further from central Guadalajara are several suburbs (<hi rend="italic">municipios</hi>) that are cities in their own right. Several of these are also of interest to visitors, including:</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tlaquepaque</hi>—about 30 minutes by car southeast of the Centro Histórico, downtown Tlaquepaque is a charming streetscape redolent of old Mexico. An important arts and crafts center, Tlaquepaque has a vibrant shopping district where you can buy local pottery and handicrafts, as well as many lovely restaurants, art galleries, and a regional ceramics museum.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tonalá</hi>— immediately east of Tlaquepaque, Tonalá contains Guadalajara's main bus station, handicraft shops and markets, and the large <hi rend="bold">Parque Solidaridad</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Zapopan</hi>, a large, busy suburb southwest of Guadalajara, is famous for the old-fashioned charm of its downtown, its active nightlife fueled by the three large private universities within the city limits (<hi rend="bold">Universidad Autónoma de Guadalajara</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Tecnológico de Monterrey</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Universidad del Valle de Atemajac</hi>), its proliferation of modern shopping malls that will make American suburbanites feel right at home, and—by contrast—also large expanses of pristine nature, such as the <hi rend="bold">Bosque de Colomos</hi> and the gargantuan <hi rend="bold">Bosque La Primavera</hi>.</item>
</list>


<p>The 275-diagonal bus route runs from Tlaquepaque through the Centro to Zapopan, providing convenient access to all of these outer districts.</p>

<head>History</head>

<p>The co-founders of Guadalajara were Doña Beatriz de Hernández and Governor Cristobal de Oñate. In the Plaza de los Fundadores there is a monument in honor of both of them.</p>

<p>Guadalajara, and Jalisco in general, were the epicenter of the <hi rend="bold">Cristero Wars</hi> (1926-1929)—a rebellion by Catholic guerrillas against the secularizing reforms of President Plutarco Calles. One of the first armed conflicts of the rebellion took place in Guadalajara in the <hi rend="bold">Santuario de Nuestra Señora de Guadalupe</hi> on August 3, 1926, where a group of several hundred Cristeros engaged in a shootout with federal troops. Guadalajara was attacked (unsuccessfully) by the Cristero armies in March of 1929.</p>

<p>In the 1950s, Avenida Juárez was widened to create today's arterial road of Juárez-Vallarta which you see today. A famous part of that work was the moving of the central telephone exchange without the disruption of service. Pictures of this feat of engineering can be seen in the <hi rend="bold">City Museum</hi> <hi rend="italic">(Museo de la Ciudad)</hi>.</p>

<p>In April 1992, Sector Reforma was rocked by a huge explosion of gasoline, when a gasoline pipeline leaked into the sewers over a period of days until the fumes finally detonated. Some 200 Tapatíos were killed and several thousand injured. The explosion affected mostly the working-class and industrial areas on the south side of the city.</p>

<p>In May 1993, Cardinal Juan Jesús Posadas Ocampo of Guadalajara was killed at the Guadalajara airport. Though at the time the murder was thought to have been some sort of politically motivated assassination, subsequent investigations favor the theory that the cardinal was caught by mistake in drug-related violence, his motorcade having been mistaken for that of a drug lord. Cardinal Ocampo is buried beneath the high altar of the <hi rend="bold">Catedral de Guadalajara</hi>, probably because it was first suspected that the motives for his murder were political, rather than accidental.</p>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Aeropuerto Internacional de Guadalajara Miguel Hidalgo y Costilla</hi> ( GDL ) (South of city along the Guadalajara-Chapala Highway). Airlines serving GDL include <ref target="http://www.aeromexico.com">AeroMexico</ref>, <ref target="http://www.alaskaair.com/">Alaska Airlines</ref>, <ref target="http://www.aa.com/">American Airlines</ref>, <ref target="http://www.copaair.com/">Copa Airlines</ref>, <ref target="http://www.delta.com/">Delta</ref>, <ref target="http://www.interjet.com.mx">Interjet</ref>, <ref target="http://www.united.com">United</ref>, <ref target="http://www.vivaaerobus.com">VivaAerobus</ref>, and <ref target="http://www.volaris.mx">Volaris</ref>. A taxi from the airport to anywhere will cost M$220 (<ref target="Mexico%23Currency">pesos</ref>), but many hotels offer airport pickups that can be cheaper. There is also a bus that stops at the bottom of Terminal 1 which goes to the <hi rend="bold">Old Bus Station</hi> <hi rend="italic">(Central Camionera Vieja)</hi> close to the Centro Histórico and costs M$7. To get to the bus station, take a right upon exiting the airport and follow the signs to the "Terminal Terrestre." Walk past the police station and FedEx building. Pay when getting on the bus. A taxi down to the Laguna de Chapala area, around <ref target="Ajijic">Ajijic</ref> or <ref target="Chapala">Chapala</ref>, will cost about M$380. At the airport, always buy the taxi chit from the booth before exiting the terminal, then present it to the licensed driver.</item>
</list>
</text>
