<text id="autogum_voyage_doc245" title="Doune" shortTile="doune" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=9980" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Doune</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Doune</hi> is a village in <ref target="Stirlingshire">Stirlingshire</ref>, some 8 miles (13 km) north-west of <ref target="Stirling">Stirling</ref>. The reason to come here is to visit the castle, en route to the Trossachs.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<p>First Scotland East Bus 59 runs from Stirling hourly M-Sat (every 2 hours Sun) via Blair Drummond to Doune, continuing to Callander. There's nothing direct from Dunblane, you have to double back via Stirling.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>The castle is a short walk from the village.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Doune Castle</hi>, ☏ +44 1786 841742 . Daily Apr-Sept 09:30-17:30, Oct-Mar 10:00-16:00. An imposing Medieval castle sited on a wooded bend where a tributary joins the River Teith, across a bridge. The site is defended on three sides by the ground sloping steeply down to the rivers, and the approach from the north is defended by earthworks. The castle is entered through a narrow gateway and a 46 ft (14 m) long vaulted passageway that leads to a large central courtyard. Off this, steps lead up to the Great Hall which is connected by arched servery hatches and a door to the massive kitchen. An enclosed staircase from the courtyard reaches the timber panelled Lord's Hall and other apartments. Doune Castle was a location used in the film <hi rend="italic">Monty Python and the Holy Grail</hi> and in the television series' <hi rend="italic"><ref target="Game%20of%20Thrones">Game of Thrones</ref></hi> and "Outlander".</item>
</list>

 Adult £9, Concession £7.20, Child £5.40.

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hill of Row</hi> (south east of Doune). high ground with remains of stone circle and a statue of David Stirling, founder of the SAS </item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://www.douneanddunblaneshow.co.uk">Doune and Dunblane Show</ref></hi> is an agricultural show and Highland Games, held on the first Saturday in July. The next event is Sat 4 July 2020 at Keir Mains, a mile south of Dunblane and 3 miles east of Doune. From M90 terminus jcn 11 take B824 west.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Doune Hillclimb</hi>, Buchany FK16 6FG (a mile west of Doune on A84). This is the on-road version of hill climb with a tarmac track and cars that look like conventional racers, not the offroad bike version. This hillclimb course is 1476 yards / 1350 m; the track record is just under 35 secs. There are meetings of the British Hill Climb Championship in June and Sept each year and of the Scottish Championship in April. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Blair Drummond Safari Park</hi> is two miles south on A84, see <ref target="Stirling">Stirling</ref>.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">L'Angolino</hi>, 47 Main St FK16 6BW, ☏ +44 1786 841850 . W-F 17:00-21:00, Sa Su 12:00-21:00. Friendly enjoyable Italian restaurant.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Buttercup Cafe</hi>, 7 Main St FK16 6BJ, ☏ +44 1786 842511 . Daily 09:00-16:00. Cheery cafe, can get busy with slow service, dog-friendly.</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>
<p>The Red Lion is the village pub, see "Sleep".</p>

<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Woodside Hotel</hi>, Stirling Rd, FK16 6AB. 3-star eleven room hotel. B&amp;B double from £80.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Red Lion Inn</hi>, Balkerach Street FK16 6DF. 3-star six room pub hotel. B&amp;B double £80.</item>
</list>


<head>Go next</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Dunblane">Dunblane</ref> for its cathedral.</item>
<item> <ref target="Callander">Callander</ref> for the Trossachs.</item>
<item> <ref target="Stirling">Stirling</ref> for the imposing castle.</item>
</list>
</text>
