<text id="autogum_academic_doc457" title="Trichothecenes in Cereal Grains – An Update" shortTile="trichothecenes-cereal" author="Nora  A. Foroud, Danica Baines, Tatiana  Y. Gagkaeva, Nehal Thakor, Ana Badea, Barbara Steiner, Maria Bürstmayr, Hermann Bürstmayr" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6651/11/11/634/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Molecular Mechanisms of Trichothecene Resistance</head><head> 4.1. Trichothecene Resistance at the Ribosome</head>
<p>
Owing to the ubiquitous and essential activities of the ribosome, its structure is highly conserved within phylogenetic domains, making it a reliable target for pathogens. The ribosome can resist the effect of trichothecenes if a point mutation occurs at the tryptophan (W) residue within the highly conserved W-finger of Ribosomal Protein L3 (RPL3). Mutations at this site also confer resistance to other “antibiotics” [e.g., anisomycin, 211], that bind the A-site of the peptidyl transferase center. The W-finger projects directly into this site, and the RPL3 protein coordinates aa-tRNA accommodation, peptidyl transfer and translocation steps during protein translation. Only a few substitutions of the tryptophan in this position are viable, including substitutions with other aromatic residues, or with cysteine or arginine. Studies in yeast show that the W255C substitution increases affinity to aa-tRNA, and while this mutation is non-lethal, it does result in reduced translation efficiency. </p>

<p>It is not known whether W-finger mutations occur as a natural resistance mechanism in plants, although in vitro translation assays demonstrated that ribosomes isolated from the FHB-resistant cultivar, Frontana, exhibit a higher tolerance to DON than those isolated from the susceptible cultivar Cassavant. Transgenic expression of modified <hi rend="italic">RPL3</hi> has had mixed results. It was determined that the expression of the tomato RPL3 gene with a modified W-finger (W258C) had a minimal effect on the ability of transgenic tobacco to tolerate DON. Additionally, transgenic plants were found to preferentially utilize the wild-type RPL3 (except at sub-lethal concentrations of DON) and these observations were corroborated using yeast transformants. On the other hand, transgenic expression of a W258C modified rice <hi rend="italic">RPL3</hi> conferred DON tolerance in tobacco protoplasts, as well as FEB resistance in maize. It has also been suggested by Di et al. that expression of a truncated <hi rend="italic">RPL3</hi> from yeast could reduce DON toxicity in cereals by drawing the toxin away from the functional wild-type RPL3. The authors expressed truncated yeast RPL3 (ΔL3) in wheat and found that, in addition to an increase in the expression of the endogenous wheat RPL3 gene, transgenic plants displayed a reduction in FHB symptoms as well as DON accumulation. </p>

<p>In a similar study, the same group had earlier reported that co-expression of ΔL3 together with a Pokeweed Antiviral Protein (PAP) in tobacco cells resulted in increased expression of the host <hi rend="italic">RPL3</hi> gene, and this was coincident with improved DON tolerance. In this context, it is interesting that the up-regulation of different components of the ribosome has been observed directly in response to exogenous DON applications in wheat. In a transcriptomics study by Foroud et al., DON induced higher expression of ribosomal components, but only in the resistant genotypes, which incidentally were generated through a process that provides selection pressure for trichothecene resistance. There are many potential explanations for this up-regulation, though at this stage only speculation can be offered, and it is also unknown whether there is a direct link with this expression pattern and resistance in these genotypes. It should be noted, however, that changes in ribosomal gene expression have been reported in different plant-pathogen interactions (e.g.,), and importantly, according to the ‘ribosome filter hypothesis’ alterations in ribosomal composition or specialized ribosomes are thought to bias incorporation of specific mRNAs to translation. Thus, the filter hypothesis offers the possibility that the reported DON-induced changes in ribosomal gene expression might coordinate defense-related translation rather than conferring ribosomal resistance to the toxin. </p>
</text>
