<text id="autogum_interview_doc575" title="part0_Interview with Brazilian blogger Ricardo Serran Lobo" shortTile="partinterview-brazilian" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-01-13" dateModified="2012-05-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Brazilian_blogger_Ricardo_Serran_Lobo" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Interview with Brazilian blogger Ricardo Serran Lobo</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 18, 2006</hi></p>
<p>Ricardo Serran Lobo is a Brazilian blogger who writes about his famous neighbor,  the politician <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roberto%20Jefferson">Roberto Jefferson</ref>, head of the Brazilian Labor Party in the Brazilian Congress of Deputies. Jefferson has become a major figure in the ongoing Brazilian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/mensalão%20scandal">mensalão scandal</ref> revolving around corruption and bribery.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Vizinho do Jefferson</hi>  quickly became very popular among Brazilians, describing the routine of Jefferson, while providing information about politics and fresh news about the scandal. Lobo's blog got third place in the <ref target="http://www.thebobs.com/thebobs05/bob.php?site=allsuggestions_log&amp;tsrid=417">Best Of Blogs</ref> contest run by Deutsche Welle International.</p>
<p>Lobo gets an intimate look at the center of Brazilian politics by living in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brasilia">Brasilia</ref>, near  residences of parliamentarians (including Roberto Jefferson), public buildings and the Brazilian Chamber of Deputies. Or, as he says in his blog: "near the eye of the hurricane," a reference to the recent political crisis. </p>
<p>At first, Lobo began describing the daily activities of his famous neighbor deputy Roberto Jefferson. As the crisis moved on, he began to describe the political events regarding it. His writings evolved to not only what is going on with Jefferson, but what is going on in Brazilian Congress, and has interviewed politicians, including Roberto Jefferson himself.</p>
<p>The blog tries to be informative, with a lot of humour (common with Brazilians), and some protests against the bad habits of Brazilian politics in general.</p>
<p><ref target="http://www.vizinhodojefferson.blogger.com.br/"><hi rend="bold">Jefferson's neighbor, the blog,</hi></ref> is an example of citizen journalism and it shows that ordinary people can compete with professional media.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<head id="Personal_questions">Personal questions</head>
Wikinews: Our interviewee is the Brazilian Ricardo Serran Lobo. He is usually known as the  <hi rend="italic">Vizinho do Jefferson</hi> (Jefferson's neighbor), because of his personal weblog about politics, which became very popular during the  "mensalão" crisis in  Brasil.
<p>Ricardo Lobo: Good afternoon! My name is Ricardo, I am a publicity man and teacher of web writing, and speaker of the Information Era and Digital Communication, 44.</p>
Wikinews: Are you from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brasília">Brasília</ref>?
<p>Ricardo Lobo: No. I am from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/São%20Paulo%20(city)">São Paulo</ref> and from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santa%20Catarina%20(island)">Santa Catarina</ref> in my heart.</p>
Wikinews: How long have you been living in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brasília">Brasília</ref>?
<p>Ricardo Lobo: I have been living for five years in Brasília. All these years I have been a neighbor of the ex-deputy Roberto Jefferson.</p>
<head id="The_blog">The blog</head>
Wikinews:  What was your aim at starting a blog
<p>Ricardo Lobo:  The blog was born without any aim. In fact it was a joke with a college friend  of mine and my cousin. They knew that I lived next door to the deputy [Roberto Jefferson] and they asked me every day about the journalists staying out in front of his door at his building.</p>
<p>Ricardo Lobo:  So, I began to write the blog, it was closer to the "making of"  a journalistic coverture, describing the confusion and the changes of routine caused by the journalists who staying under my window, waiting for something happens.</p>
</text>
