<text id="autogum_academic_doc664" title="Beneficial Effects of Leucine Supplementation on Criteria for Sarcopenia: A Systematic Review" shortTile="beneficial-effects" author="Francisco  M. Martínez-Arnau, Rosa Fonfría-Vivas, Omar Cauli" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6643/11/10/2504/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Materials and Methods</head>
<p>
This study was designed and developed according to the preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analysis (PRISMA) guidelines, an evidence-based set of minimum items for assessing the benefits and harms of a given healthcare intervention. </p>

<head> 2.1. Literature Search</head>
<p>
We searched the literature in various electronic bibliographic databases (PubMed/Medline, Embase, EBSCO, Cochrane databases, Lilacs, and Dialnet) for all entries up until 30 March 2019, without applying any publication age limitations. The reference lists of all the relevant articles were manually cross-referenced in order to identify any additional articles. The primary search terms used for all six databases were ‘leucine’ and ‘sarcopenia’, as well as one of the following terms: ‘older’, ‘elderly’, ‘disease’ or ‘trial’. </p>

<head> 2.2. Inclusion and Exclusion Criteria</head>
<p>
To answer our research questions, we applied the following inclusion criteria to each of the considered manuscripts: (1) It was acknowledged as an original article; we included experimental studies (randomised and placebo-controlled trials) and observational studies (cohort, cross-sectional, and case-control studies); (2) it was a full text published either in English, Portuguese, or Spanish; (3) at least one of the sarcopenia criteria was measured: Muscular mass and/or muscular strength and/or physical performance; (4) a description of how sarcopenia was evaluated was defined in the methods section; (5) the concentration of leucine used in the intervention was specified or could be calculated. Studies performed in animals, case-report studies, letters to the Editor, abstracts from conferences, books, PhD theses were excluded. </p>

<head> 2.3. Data Collection and Analysis</head>
<p>
Details of the manuscripts identified in the literature search were uploaded into a web-based system, which was used to manage the screening process and remove any duplicate citations. In order to determine which studies would be included, three members of the review team independently screened the titles and abstracts of these articles and the full texts were retrieved based on our inclusion and exclusion criteria. Two reviewers independently extracted the following data from each article: The country in which the study was conducted, number of participants, age of the participants at the time of inclusion, sex of the participants, amount of leucine administered, co-administration of other substances, sarcopenia evaluation methods, and the main and secondary outcomes of the study. Any disagreement between the reviewers regarding the papers and data extracted from them was resolved by the third author. </p>

<head> 2.4. Assessment of Bias</head>
<p>
We assessed the risk of bias in each randomised and placebo-controlled study according to the Cochrane Review guidelines, which cover the following bias domains: Selection bias (random sequence generation and allocation concealment), performance bias (blinding of participants and personnel), detection bias (blinding the outcome assessment), attrition bias (incomplete outcome data), and reporting bias (selective reporting). The judgments were made independently by two researchers (FM-M–A and R-F-V), with any discrepancies resolved with the third author (OC). </p>
</text>
