<text id="autogum_whow_doc015" title="Create a Dance Moms Audio Swap" shortTile="create-dance-moms" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-03-01" dateModified="2019-06-26" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Create-a-Dance-Moms-Audio-Swap" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Create a Dance Moms Audio Swap</head><p>If you've ever seen one of the "Dance Moms" performances, you'll already know that they dance to certain music that fits the performance. Do any search on YouTube for "Dance Moms Audio Swap", and you'll come across a collection of videos of performances that have been changed and cut. In just the same way, you can create a Dance Moms Audio Swap. And although less frequently done, you can also use audio swapping in other ways than Dance Moms Audio Swaps.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Preparation</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Get the device(s) needed. This is a mobile method, so you will need an Apple device (or some device with iMovie on it). This includes: Mac (computers/laptops), iPhone, iPod and iPad. <figure rend="Create a Dance Moms Audio Swap Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get the apps needed. The apps you will need are: <figure rend="Create a Dance Moms Audio Swap Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>iMovie (this may be free in some cases)</item>
<item>Video download and player - Titan (sometimes just called "Free Video") (free or premium).</item></list></item></list>
<head>Creating</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open "Video Download". At the bottom should be a "Browser" tab. Tap that. Scroll up. There is a URL bar and a Google Search bar. In Google, search for a Dance Moms number you'd like to use. <figure rend="Create a Dance Moms Audio Swap Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tap the video. Scroll up and tap and hold the URL of the video. A list menu should come up. <figure rend="Create a Dance Moms Audio Swap Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tap "Download As" and tap the name bar to type. You can also just download the video without renaming it. You'll be able to see the video by the thumbnail, so it doesn't really matter what you name it. <figure rend="Create a Dance Moms Audio Swap Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>After downloading the video(s), go to "Videos" at the bottom of the application. Your videos will come up. Tap and hold the video you want to audio swap. Tap "Save to camera roll". <figure rend="Create a Dance Moms Audio Swap Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>It can be easy to forget or maybe think you can skip this step, but it is essential, so don't overlook it.</item></list></item>
<item>Open iMovie. Tap the create button ("+"). Tap "Movie". On the design "Simple", tap "Create". <figure rend="Create a Dance Moms Audio Swap Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tap the media icon in the top left of your work area. You should be on "Video" in the tabs at the bottom of the app. Tap "all" and choose the video that you downloaded. Tap an arrow that signifies "use". <figure rend="Create a Dance Moms Audio Swap Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tap the tab "Audio" at the bottom. Choose your song. Choose the "use" arrow. <figure rend="Create a Dance Moms Audio Swap Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>In your iMovie studio, tap the video. Choose the sound icon. Turn the sound to 0%. <figure rend="Create a Dance Moms Audio Swap Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remove all parts of the video that are <hi rend="italic">not</hi> dancing (the audience, judges, etc.). You can do this by: <figure rend="Create a Dance Moms Audio Swap Step 11.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>1. Putting the white work bar line where you are splitting the dance and part that should be taken out. This should be done twice unless the part that is being taken out is at the beginning or end.</item>
<item>2. Tapping the part to be removed and tapping "Delete".</item></list></item>
<item>Choose parts of the dance to move around if you want to change the dance. This works the same as parts to be removed (Step 9). Separate parts of the dance. Duplicate them. Hold them in to move them to a different part of the dance. <figure rend="Create a Dance Moms Audio Swap Step 12.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Note: When you are moving a part, it can only be placed at separations or at the beginning or end.</item>
<item>If there is a part of the dance that you would like to remove, but the clip is too short, shorten the part attached to it.</item></list></item>
<item>Fix your song, if it needs to be amended. For example, split it, duplicate it, shorten it, and so on. <figure rend="Create a Dance Moms Audio Swap Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tap the back arrow at the top left of your screen. Your work should already be saved. Name your work. <figure rend="Create a Dance Moms Audio Swap Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Publish your work. This step is optional. <figure rend="Create a Dance Moms Audio Swap Step 15.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>To play the full song (it gets cut off when the video is too short), duplicate the video to be longer. Once the song reaches its end, or where you would prefer it to stop, you can remove duplications of the video while keeping the song long.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>People may not like your work. If they don't, just politely tell them that you wanted to create an audio swap, and if they don't want to watch it, they don't have to. Say it politely though!</item></list>
<list type="unordered"><item>Your work will never be completely perfect––remember, that doesn't make it a bad audio swap.</item>
<item>You will get better. A first audio swap may not be as good as others––yet.</item></list>
</text>
