<text id="autogum_voyage_doc248" title="Nizhny Novgorod" shortTile="nizhny-novgorod" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=24672" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Nizhny Novgorod</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Nizhny Novgorod</hi> (<ref target="Russian%20phrasebook">Russian</ref>: Ни́жний Но́вгород <hi rend="italic">NEEZH-nee NOHV-guh-ruht</hi>), colloquially shortened to <hi rend="italic">Nizhny</hi>, is <ref target="Russia">Russia</ref>'s fifth largest city, ranking after <ref target="Moscow">Moscow</ref>, <ref target="Saint%20Petersburg">Saint Petersburg</ref>, <ref target="Novosibirsk">Novosibirsk</ref> and <ref target="Yekaterinburg">Yekaterinburg</ref>. It had a population in 2018 of 1.26 million. It is the economic and cultural center of the vast <ref target="Volga%20Region">Volga</ref> economic region, and also the administrative center of <ref target="Nizhny%20Novgorod%20Oblast">Nizhny Novgorod Oblast</ref> and <ref target="Volga%20Region">Volga Federal District</ref>.</p>

<p>From 1932 to 1990 the city was known as Gorky (Го́рький), after the writer Maxim Gorky. Following the fall of the Soviet Union, the old name was restored.</p>

<p>Do not confuse Nizhny Novgorod with <ref target="Novgorod">Novgorod</ref> (or, fully, Veliky Novgorod), which is a different city. In particular, do not shorten the name Nizhny Novgorod to Novgorod.</p>

<head>Districts</head>
<p>The city is divided by the river Oka into two major parts: the <hi rend="bold">Upper city</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Verkhnyaya</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Nagornaya chast</hi>) on the hilly right side and the <hi rend="bold">Lower city</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Nizhnyaya</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Zarechnaya chast</hi> — what literally means "the part over the river") on the left bank of the river. The Upper city is the old historical part of Nizhny Novgorod, whereas the Lower city is larger, newer and consists of more industrial districts.</p>

<head>History</head>
<p>The city was founded by Grand Duke George II of Russia in 1221 at the confluence of two most important rivers of his principality, the Volga and the Oka. Its name literally means <hi rend="italic">Newtown the Lower</hi>, to distinguish it from <ref target="Novgorod">the older Novgorod</ref>. A major stronghold for border protection, Nizhny Novgorod fortress took advantage of a natural moat formed by the two rivers.</p>

<p>Along with Moscow and Tver, Nizhny Novgorod was among several newly founded towns that escaped Mongol devastation on account of its insignificance and grew up into important centers of Russian political life during the period of Tatar yoke. For a short period of time it was the capital of the Suzdal Principality and competed with Moscow for the power in the region. However the competition with Moscow was lost and in 1392 the city was incorporated into Muscovy. Nizhny Novgorod Kremlin was built in 1508-1511 (under supervision of the Italian fortress engineers) and became one of the strongest Russian citadels. There is a legend saying that the project was initially developed with participation of Leonardo da Vinci. However there is no documented proof of Leonardo's work for that project, the only thing the legend is based on is the striking resemblance of Leonardo's sketches and the actual Kremlin schemes. The fortress was strong enough to withstand Tatar sieges in 1520 and 1536.</p>

<p>In 1612, the so-called <hi rend="italic">national militia</hi>, gathered by a local merchant Kuzma Minin and commanded by Knyaz Dmitry Pozharsky expelled the Polish troops from Moscow, thus putting an end to the Time of Troubles and establishing the rule of the Romanov dynasty.</p>

<p>In 1817, the Makaryev Monastery Fair, one of the liveliest in the world the 16th-18th centuries, was transferred to Nizhny Novgorod, which thereupon started to attract numerous visitors and by the mid-19th century it turned Nizhny Novgorod into trade capital of the Russian Empire.</p>

<p>Under the Soviet period, the trade connections of the city were abandoned and Nizhny Novgorod became an important industrial centre instead. During the communist time the city was closed to foreigners to safeguard the security of Soviet military research. The physicist and the Nobel laureate Andrei Sakharov was exiled there during 1980-1986 to limit his contacts with foreigners.</p>

<head>Climate</head>


<p>The climate in the region is humid continental and it is similar to the climate in <ref target="Moscow">Moscow</ref>, although colder in winter, which lasts from late November until late March with a permanent snow cover.</p>

<head>By train</head>

<p>The train station in Nizhny Novgorod is in the northern part of the city centre, near the Metromost Bridge. It is reachable via the metro. The main hall of the train station is beautiful and includes a chandelier as well as soviet-style mosaics symbolizing the life of Russian people.</p>

<p>All Trans-Siberian trains from Moscow except for train 99/100 (which goes via <ref target="Yaroslavl">Yaroslavl</ref> instead) stop at Nizhny Novgorod.</p>

<p>When searching timetables and fares on the <ref target="http://pass.rzd.ru/">RZD website</ref>, enter "Nizhniy Novgorod" as the station for Nizhny Novgorod.</p>

<p>There are several options for train travel from <ref target="Moscow">Moscow</ref> including high speed <ref target="http://sapsan.su/">Sapsan</ref> trains (3½ hours, 1200-1700 руб ) and slower late night trains (7 hours, from 700 руб ). Trains are generally cheaper if purchased in advance. Most trains from Moscow arrive depart from Moscow's Kursky or Yaroslavsky train stations.</p>

<p>There are 2 daily overnight trains to/from <ref target="Saint%20Petersburg">Saint Petersburg</ref> (15-16 hours, from 900 руб ).</p>

<p>There are also direct train connections with <ref target="Vladimir">Vladimir</ref>, <ref target="Dzerzhinsk">Dzerzhinsk</ref>, <ref target="Kazan">Kazan</ref>, <ref target="Samara">Samara</ref>, <ref target="Kirov">Kirov</ref> (6-7 hours, from 550 руб ), <ref target="Yaroslavl">Yaroslavl</ref> (9 hours, from 450 руб ), <ref target="Kungur">Kungur</ref> (16 hours, from 1200 руб ), <ref target="Yekaterinburg">Yekaterinburg</ref>, (20 hours, from 1400 руб ), <ref target="Novosibirsk">Novosibirsk</ref> (40 hours, from 2500 руб ), <ref target="Irkutsk">Irkutsk</ref> (69 hours, 10000 руб ), <ref target="Astrakhan">Astrakhan</ref>, <ref target="Simferopol">Simferopol</ref>, <ref target="Novorossiysk">Novorossiysk</ref> (52 hours, from 1900 руб ), <ref target="Vladivostok">Vladivostok</ref>, <ref target="Beijing">Beijing</ref>, <ref target="Ulaanbaatar">Ulaanbaatar</ref>, and many other cities. Suburban commuter trains connect Nizhny Novgorod with towns within 200 km of the city.</p>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Nizhny Novgorod (Strigino) International Airport</hi> ( GOJ ) (located 20km southwest of the city centre). The airport serves over 1.2 million passengers per year. There are regular flights to many major Russian cities including <ref target="Moscow">Moscow</ref>, <ref target="Saint%20Petersburg">Saint Petersburg</ref>, <ref target="Samara">Samara</ref>, <ref target="Surgut">Surgut</ref>, and <ref target="Yekaterinburg">Yekaterinburg</ref>, as well as international flights to <ref target="Tashkent">Tashkent</ref>, <ref target="Yerevan">Yerevan</ref>, <ref target="Osh">Osh</ref>, <ref target="Prague">Prague</ref>, <ref target="Dushanbe">Dushanbe</ref>, and <ref target="Dubai">Dubai</ref>. In addition, Dexter Air Taxi operates flights on small planes to nearby cities in Russia such as <ref target="Kirov">Kirov</ref> and <ref target="Perm">Perm</ref>.</item>
</list>

 

<head>By car</head>
<p>Nizhny Novgorod is situated on the M7/E30 road. The road is in decent condition, although with traffic it can take anywhere from 4 to 8 hours to drive to/from <ref target="Moscow">Moscow</ref>.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>There are several stops for buses arriving in Nizhny Novgorod; however, departing buses leave from either Kanavinskaya bus station, near the railway station, for buses going to points north and west, and the main bus station (Avtovokzal) near pl. Lyadova, for the buses going to points south and east.</p>

<p>Buses are generally uncomfortable and slower than the trains.</p>

<ref target="http://www.mrtrans.ru/">MR Trans</ref> operates buses to/from Moscow (9 hours, 600-1000 руб ), <ref target="Yoshkar-Ola">Yoshkar-Ola</ref>, <ref target="Kazan">Kazan</ref>, <ref target="Cheboksary">Cheboksary</ref>, and other nearby cities.
</text>
