<text id="autogum_interview_doc699" title="Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Family Coalition Party candidate Bill McMaster, Lambton—Kent—Middlesex" shortTile="ontario-votes--interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-26" dateModified="2013-03-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Family_Coalition_Party_candidate_Bill_McMaster%2C_Lambton%E2%80%94Kent%E2%80%94Middlesex" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Family Coalition Party candidate Bill McMaster, Lambton—Kent—Middlesex</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 26, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill McMaster</hi> is running for the Family Coalition Party in the Ontario provincial election, in the Lambton—Kent—Middlesex riding. Wikinews' Nick Moreau interviewed him regarding his values, his experience, and his campaign.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process?</hi></p>
<p>Partly because I have always been interested in to politics of the country, and because I do not believe in the Progressive Conservatives School funding program. I felt that as a conservative, I could not support it. The Family Coalition Party best represents my political views at this time.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>I live in the riding.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have?</hi></p>
<p>Limited. Church politics, local hockey politics</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>I am not afraid to ask the hard questions or challenge a position even if it causes controversy</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why?</hi></p>
<p>The conservative or the liberal. The conservative because he IS one of the good guys, although he has to follow the agenda of the leader, and the liberal because she is the incumbent.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?</hi></p>
<p>I am the only candidate willing to speak openly against abortion and the marriage issues.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding?</hi></p>
<p>Health care, education, and farming.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you?</hi></p>
<p>Yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>The Family Coalition Party has a platform for Health and Education. Has started a platform for farming, but believes that farmers voices are needed, not just politicos.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly?</hi></p>
<p>Cut taxes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are the property taxes in your riding at a fair level for the amount of services received in the municipality?</hi></p>
<p>No.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How can the province lead the way in stimulating job creation?</hi></p>
<p>Cut taxes across the board and put more money in peoples pockets.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What are your views on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mixed%20member%20proportional%20representation">mixed member proportional representation</ref> (MMP) referendum?</hi></p>
<p>I'm unsure, but leaning toward no, only for the reason that I believe there are better ways than the one proposed.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What role, if any, does “new media” play in your campaign, and the campaign of your party? (websites, blogs, Facebook, YouTube videos, etc) Do you view it as beneficial, or a challenge?</hi></p>
<p>I have a lot of support from www.freedominion.com, a site of principled conservatism. Other candidates for the party are also members there, and the owner is running for the Freedom Party.</p>
<p>The other sites are helpful as far as finding out information, but freedominion is still by far the best source of information, and you are required to provide proof of what you post.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Of the decisions made by Ontario's 38th Legislative Assembly, which was the most beneficial to your this electoral district? To the province as a whole? Which was least beneficial, or even harmful, to your this riding? To the province as a whole?</hi></p>
<p>Of the decisions made by Ontario's 38th Legislative Assembly, which was the most beneficial to your  this electoral district? To the province as a whole? Which was least beneficial, or even harmful, to your this riding? To the province as a whole?</p>
<p>I don’t know if any were beneficial, I know the health care tax and the largest tax increase in Ontario’s history was certainly detrimental as it hurt the auto sector in this area. Schools have been closed, and hospitals have cut essential staff but created more management.</p>
<p>As far as anything coming from the liberal camp, I don’t see much in the way of benefits.</p>
</text>
