<text id="autogum_voyage_doc83" title="Eastern Circuit" shortTile="eastern-circuit" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=10360" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Eastern Circuit</head>


<p>The <hi rend="bold">Eastern Circuit</hi> (道東 <hi rend="italic">Dōtō</hi>) covers the eastern half of the northern <ref target="Japan">Japan</ref>ese island of <ref target="Hokkaido">Hokkaido</ref>.</p>

<head>Regions</head>

<p>The Eastern Circuit is composed of the following four subprefectures:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Okhotsk</hi> – it was renamed from the earlier Abashiri Subprefecture on 2010</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tokachi</hi> – the region is dominated by the Tokachi Plain, a major agricultural area</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kushiro</hi> – the region is dominated by the Kushiro Plain, a major agricultural area</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Nemuro</hi> – the region is dominated by the Nemuro Plain, a major agricultural area</item>
</list>


<head>Cities</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> (釧路市 <hi rend="italic">Kushiro-shi</hi>) – the largest city in the Circuit with 200,000 people</item>
<item> (網走市 <hi rend="italic">Abashiri-shi</hi>) – fishing town famous for drift ice and infamous for its prison</item>
<item> (北見市 <hi rend="italic">Kitami-shi</hi>) – the onion capital of Japan</item>
<item> (紋別市 <hi rend="italic">Monbetsu-shi</hi>)</item>
<item> (根室市 <hi rend="italic">Nemuro-shi</hi>) – at the easternmost tip of Hokkaido</item>
<item> (帯広市 <hi rend="italic">Obihiro-shi</hi>) – the main city in the Tokachi Plain, a large</item>
</list>

<p>agricultural area</p>

<head>Towns</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> (美幌町 <hi rend="italic">Bihoro-chō</hi>) – gateway to the <ref target="Akan%20National%20Park">Akan National Park</ref></item>
<item> (斜里町 <hi rend="italic">Shari-chō</hi>) – gateway to Shiretoko National Park and home of onsen village <hi rend="bold">Utoro</hi></item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
</list>


<head>National Parks</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> (阿寒摩周国立公園 <hi rend="italic">Akan Mashu Kokuritsu Kōen</hi>) – known for the crystalline mountain lakes of <hi rend="bold">Akan</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Kussharo</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Mashu</hi></item>
<item> (大雪山国立公園 <hi rend="italic">Daisetsuzan Kokuritsu Kōen</hi>), – Japan's largest national park named after its "Great Snowy Mountains"</item>
<item> (釧路湿原国立公園 <hi rend="italic">Kushiro-shitsugen Kokuritsu Kōen</hi>)</item>
<item> (知床国立公園 <hi rend="italic">Shiretoko Kokuritsu Kōen</hi>) – the most inaccessible and least explored of Japan's national parks</item>
</list>


<head>Understand</head>
<p>The most sparsely populated region in all Japan, this vast area is nearly 40,000 km² in size. While the easternmost part is largely flat, rural and filled with endless cow pastures, much of the circuit is ringed with mountains.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<ref target="Kushiro">Kushiro</ref>, <ref target="Monbetsu">Monbetsu</ref> and <ref target="Ozora%23By%20plane">Ōzora, Memanbetsu</ref> (near <ref target="Abashiri">Abashiri</ref>) have regional airports.

<head>Get around</head>

<p>Here, if anywhere in Japan, a <hi rend="bold">rental car</hi> will come in handy. Train coverage is severely lacking (many lines have been terminated due to a lack of customers) and buses are infrequent, inconvenient and expensive.</p>

<head>Do</head>
<p>Eastern Hokkaido has beautiful coastline, wonderful outdoor hot springs, and remote hiking. Some combination of these should make for a satisfying visit.</p>

<head>Eat</head>
<p>Hokkaido on the whole is good for seafood — if you're on the coast — and dairy, and the east is no exception. In central Hokkaido, near Asahikawa and Furano, there are a plethora of melon stands, though by foreign standards, Japanese melons are exceedingly expensive.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pork Bowl</hi> (豚丼 Buta-don). Pork bowl with sightly bigger pork. <ref target="Obihiro">Obihiro</ref> is originated, it is possible to eat in Tokachi whole area.</item>
</list>
</text>
