<text id="autogum_news_doc112" title="Zimbabwe opposition agrees to join government" shortTile="zimbabwe-opposition" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-01-30" dateModified="2014-04-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Zimbabwe_opposition_agrees_to_join_government" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Zimbabwe opposition agrees to join government</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, January 30, 2009</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Flag of the Movement for Democratic Change.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>President Mugabe will share control of Zimbabwe's security forces under the agreement. Image: Jeremy Lock.</caption></figure>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Morgan_Tsvangirai">Morgan Tsvangirai</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Movement%20for%20Democratic%20Change">Movement for Democratic Change</ref> (MDC) has agreed to join a government of national unity in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Zimbabwe">Zimbabwe</ref>. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Robert_Mugabe">Robert Mugabe</ref> will remain as president, while Tsvangirai is set to be sworn in as prime minister on February 11. </p>
<p>Despite the agreement, Tsvangirai and other MDC members expressed disappointment over the terms of the unity government. "We are not saying that this is a solution to the Zimbabwe crisis," Tsvangirai told reporters. "Instead, our participation signifies that we have chosen to continue the struggle for a democratic Zimbabwe in a new arena."</p>
<p>Among the MDC's concerns is the home affairs ministry, which oversees the police and security forces. Under the power sharing agreement, Mugabe and Tsvangirai will share control of this ministry, and the MDC says Mugabe could use that power to quell dissent as he had in the past.</p>
<p>Tsvangirai signed the agreement to take part in a unity government at a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Southern%20African%20Development%20Community">Southern African Development Community</ref> (SADC) summit in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Pretoria">Pretoria</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/South_Africa">South Africa</ref>. Opposition leaders had been pressing Mugabe to relinquish control of the home affairs ministry and release imprisoned political activists as part of the power sharing deal. But Tsvangirai's party said they were pressured into accepting the deal by the SADC, who refused to condemn Mugabe.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kenya">Kenyan</ref> Prime Minister <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Raila_Odinga">Raila Odinga</ref> called on the SADC to stop "treating Mugabe with kid gloves" at the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/World_Economic_Forum">World Economic Forum</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Davos">Davos</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Switzerland">Switzerland</ref>. "We hold the view that SADC could do more in trying to help the people of Zimbabwe resolve the crisis," said Odinga. "SADC should stand up and tell Mr. Mugabe enough is enough. It is time for him to leave."</p>
<p>Meanwhile, Western countries such as the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> remained skeptical regarding the prospect of true power sharing. U.S. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Department%20of%20State">State Department</ref> spokesman Robert Wood told reporters in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Washington,_D.C.">Washington</ref>, "If and when there is a government in place in Zimbabwe that reflects the will of the Zimbabwean people, the United States will then look to see what we can do to continue to help." </p>
<p>Mugabe claimed victory in a runoff election in June 2008 which was widely seen by the international community as flawed. Earlier in March, Tsvangirai had garnered more votes than Mugabe in the general election, but the electoral commission said the opposition candidate did not receive a required majority of the votes. Tsvangirai then dropped out of the June runoff, claiming his supporters had been attacked and intimidated by state officials.</p>
<p>Regional heads of government have been trying to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2008–2009%20Zimbabwean%20political%20negotiations">negotiate a coalition government</ref> since the election. Neither side had been able to come to an agreement over the distribution of cabinet posts. Tsvangirai sought a constitutional amendment to recreate the post of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prime%20Minister%20of%20Zimbabwe">Prime Minister</ref>, whilst Mugabe had wished to maintain his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zimbabwe%20African%20National%20Union%20–%20Patriotic%20Front">Zimbabwe African National Union – Patriotic Front</ref> (ZANU-PF) party's hold on the main offices of state.</p>
<p>In the past year, Zimbabwe's economy has gone into freefall, with inflation so high as to be effectively unmeasurable, and an outbreak of cholera that has resulted in over 60,000 cases reported and over 3,100 killed. 6.9 million people, more than half the country's population, is in need of emergency food aid, according to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Nations">United Nations</ref>.</p>
</text>
