<text id="autogum_academic_doc429" title="Reproduction of Distinct Varroa destructor Genotypes on Honey Bee Worker Brood" shortTile="reproduction-distinct" author="Wenfeng Li, Cheng Wang, Zachary  Y. Huang, Yanping Chen, Richou Han" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2075-4450/10/11/372/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The honey bee is one of the most important economic insects. By providing the essential pollination services for crops and wild plants, honey bees play a vital role in the sustainable development of modern agricultural industries and the global ecosystem, and produce a wide range of benefits for human well-being. There is now mounting evidence indicating that the honey bee colony numbers in Western Europe and the US are in decline, which results in a severe pollination crisis and threatens crop production. Multiple factors have been proposed driving force behind the global honey bee colony losses, where colony-associated parasites and pathogens are specifically emphasized. Among them, it is believed that <hi rend="italic">Varroa destructor</hi>, an obligate ectoparasite of honey bees, is the most threatening to bee health. </p>

<p><hi rend="italic">V. destructor</hi> had been misclassified to be another honey bee <hi rend="italic">Varroa</hi> parasite, <hi rend="italic">V. jacobsoni</hi> Oudemans for decades until 2000. <hi rend="italic">V. destructor</hi> originally parasitizes the Asian honey bees, <hi rend="italic">Apis cerana</hi>, but successfully switched its host to the European honey bees, <hi rend="italic">A. mellifera</hi> likely in the Far East in the first half of the last century. The infestation of <hi rend="italic">A. mellifera</hi> colonies by <hi rend="italic">V. destructor</hi> was initially found in East and South Asia in the 1950s, and then spread to the rest of the world shortly after, excluding Australia. Unlike in its original host, <hi rend="italic">V. destructor</hi> has posed a deadly threat to the survival of the new host <hi rend="italic">A. mellifera</hi>, which lacks the resistant mechanisms as seen in <hi rend="italic">A. cerana</hi>, due to long-term coevolution. There are at least seven haplotypes of <hi rend="italic">V. destructor</hi> identified based on a 458 bp fragment of the mitochondrial <hi rend="italic">CO-I</hi> gene, including Korea, Japan/Thailand, Nepal, Vietnam, China, China 2, and Sri Lanka haplotypes, and much greater genetic variation among <hi rend="italic">V. destructor</hi> (18 haplotypes) has been revealed using the concatenated mtDNA sequences (2700 bp). However, only two of them, the Korea haplotype and the Japan/Thailand haplotype, have been found to infest the new host <hi rend="italic">A. mellifera</hi>. Mites of Korea haplotype have globally spread on <hi rend="italic">A. mellifera</hi>, while the Japan/Thailand haplotype has a more restricted distribution and only been reported in Japan, Thailand, and North and South America. </p>

<p>The life cycle of <hi rend="italic">V. destructor</hi> can be divided into two phases, the phoretic phase and the reproductive phase. In the phoretic phase, <hi rend="italic">Varroa</hi> females parasitize honey bee adults, and are previously thought to feed on the host hemolymph, but recently found to consume the fat body. Reproduction of <hi rend="italic">Varroa</hi> mites only happens inside the sealed honey bee brood cells during the reproductive phase. Drone brood cells are more attractive to mites compared to worker brood, but much less available in natural colonies, as they are reared only during swarming season. The ability to reproduce on worker brood emerges as a critical adaption to the new host, remarkably facilitating the development of <hi rend="italic">Varroa</hi> population and causing greater damage to <hi rend="italic">A. mellifera</hi> colonies. In fact, <hi rend="italic">Varroa</hi> mites that infest <hi rend="italic">A. mellifera</hi> colonies are able to reproduce as effectively on worker brood as on drone brood. </p>

<p>In contrast, <hi rend="italic">V. destructor</hi> has been found to reproduce exclusively on the drone brood and remain sterile on the worker brood of the original host <hi rend="italic">A. cerana</hi>. This phenomenon is considered crucial for the tolerance of <hi rend="italic">A. cerana</hi> towards <hi rend="italic">V. destructor</hi>, and the balance of the host-parasite relationship. The high susceptibility of immature workers to <hi rend="italic">Varroa</hi> infestation has been proposed as another resistant mechanism. However, more and more studies have raised different arguments on this issue. By both direct observations of natural infestation and artificial inoculation, many studies showed that <hi rend="italic">V. destructor</hi> are capable of reproducing on the worker brood of <hi rend="italic">A. cerana</hi>. It should be pointed out that the haplotypes of <hi rend="italic">Varroa</hi> mites used in the above studies were different. Interestingly, the mites that reproduced on <hi rend="italic">A. cerana</hi> worker brood were either the Korea haplotype or the Japan/Thailand haplotype, which are found to infest <hi rend="italic">A. mellifera</hi>; while those that were considered sterile on the <hi rend="italic">A. cerana</hi> worker brood were neither Korea haplotype nor Japan/Thailand haplotype. On the other hand, <hi rend="italic">Varroa</hi> mites derived from <hi rend="italic">A. cerana</hi> colonies in southwestern China and northern Vietnam, which were both identified to be Vietnam haplotype, were almost infertile in the worker cells of local <hi rend="italic">A. mellifera</hi> colonies after artificial inoculation. These findings suggest that the genetic variation among <hi rend="italic">Varroa</hi> mites themselves might determine their reproductive capability on worker brood hosts, and mites of different haplotypes show varying reproductive capability on the worker brood of the same honey bee species, but further studies are needed to confirm this. </p>
</text>
