<text id="autogum_bio_doc561" title="Sebastián de Belalcázar" shortTile="sebastian-de-belalcazar" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2003-09-08" dateModified="2019-10-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sebasti%C3%A1n_de_Belalc%C3%A1zar" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Sebastián de Belalcázar</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sebastián de Belalcázar</hi> (Spanish pronunciation:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Help:IPA/Spanish">[seβasˈtjan ðe βelalˈkaθaɾ]</ref>; 1479/1480 – 1551) was a Spanish <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conquistador">conquistador</ref>. De Belalcázar, also written as <hi rend="bold">de Benalcázar</hi>, is known as the founder of important early colonial cities in the northwestern part of South America; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quito">Quito</ref> in 1534 and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cali,_Colombia">Cali</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pasto">Pasto</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Popayán">Popayán</ref> in 1537. De Belalcázar led expeditions in present-day Ecuador and Colombia and died of natural causes after being sentenced to death in Cartagena, at the Caribbean coast in 1551.</p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>He was born <hi rend="bold">Sebastián Moyano</hi> in the province of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Córdoba,_Spain">Córdoba</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spain">Spain</ref>, in either 1479 or 1480. He took the name Belalcázar as that was the name of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Belalcázar,_Spain">the castle-town</ref> near to his birthplace in Córdoba.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Leon-1">[1]</ref>:157  According to various sources, he may have left for the New World with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Columbus">Christopher Columbus</ref> as early as 1498, but <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juan_de_Castellanos">Juan de Castellanos</ref> wrote that he killed a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mule">mule</ref> in 1507, and fled Spain for the West Indies due to fear of punishment, and as a chance to escape the poverty in which he lived.</p>
<head>Americas</head>
See also: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spanish_conquest_of_the_Chibchan_Nations">Spanish conquest of the Chibchan Nations</ref>
<p>He was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Encomienda">encomendero</ref> in Panama in 1522.  He entered <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicaragua">Nicaragua</ref> with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francisco_Hernández_de_Córdoba_(founder_of_Nicaragua)">Francisco Hernández de Córdoba</ref> in 1524 during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spanish_conquest_of_Nicaragua">conquest of Nicaragua</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Leon-1">[1]</ref>:157 and became the first mayor of the city of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/León,_Nicaragua">León</ref> in Nicaragua.  He remained there until 1527, when he left for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Honduras">Honduras</ref> as a result of internal disputes among the Spanish governors.  Briefly returning to León, he sailed to the coast of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peru">Peru</ref>, where he united with the expedition of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francisco_Pizarro">Francisco Pizarro</ref> in 1532.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Leon-1">[1]</ref>:157,260</p>
<head>Conquest of Ecuador</head>
<figure><caption>Plaque of Sebastián de Benalcázar in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quito">Quito</ref>, Ecuador</caption></figure>
<p>In 1534, while commanding the settlement of San Miguel for Francisco Pizarro, Sebastian set off to conquer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quito">Quito</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ecuador">Ecuador</ref>, without orders from Pizarro.  Quito had been the northernmost city of the Inca Empire, but while Belalcázar defeated the Inca general <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rumiñawi_(Inca_warrior)">Rumiñahui</ref>, the local population secreted the city treasure away. Belalcázar then founded the new city of Quito with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diego_de_Almagro">Diego de Almagro</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baltasar_Maldonado">Baltasar Maldonado</ref>, honoring Pizarro by naming it in full "San Francisco de Quito".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Prescott-2">[2]</ref>:226</p>
<p>His battles, though, were not entirely honourable. At a village called Quinche near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Puritaco">Puritaco</ref>, he found that all the men were away fighting with the national army. To make an example of these people (and to vent his frustration at finding so little treasure), he ordered all the women and children to be slaughtered.
'A feeble excuse to justify cruelty unworthy of a Castilian', was the verdict of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antonio_de_Herrera_y_Tordesillas">Herrera</ref>, the official Chronicler of the Conquest, to Belalcázar's excuse that this was done to terrify other natives into returning to their homes.</p>
<head>Conquest of Colombia</head>
<figure><caption>Statue of Sebastián de Belalcázar in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colombia">Colombian</ref> city of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cali">Santiago de Cali</ref></caption></figure>
See also: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spanish_conquest_of_the_Muisca">Spanish conquest of the Muisca</ref>
<p>Moving northward into present day <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colombia">Colombia</ref> in search of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/El_Dorado">El Dorado</ref></hi> in 1535, he entered the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cauca_River">Cauca River Valley</ref>, founding the southwestern Colombian cities of  Santiago de <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cali">Cali</ref> in 1536, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pasto">Pasto</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Popayán">Popayán</ref> (next in importance after <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quito">Quito</ref>) in 1537.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Andagoya-3">[3]</ref> Crossing overland to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magdalena_River">Magdalena River Valley</ref>, he entered the highlands of central Colombia, which had also been reached by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gonzalo_Jiménez_de_Quesada">Gonzalo Jiménez de Quesada</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nikolaus_Federmann">Nikolaus Federmann</ref>, a German, in 1539. The three presented their dispute before King and Holy Roman Emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_V,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">Charles V</ref>. The King granted Belalcázar rule of the area with the title of governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Popayán">Popayán</ref> and the honorary title of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adelantado">adelantado</ref> in May 1540.  As so often happened among the conquistadors, land squabbles developed again, this time between Belalcázar and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pascual_de_Andagoya">Pascual de Andagoya</ref> (1495–1548), who also claimed the governorship of Popayán.  Belalcázar successfully defended his lands, and took over some of Andagoya's.  He then intervened in a disagreement between supporters of the families of Pizarro and Almagro in Perú.  In 1546, he ordered the execution of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jorge_Robledo_(conquistador)">Jorge Robledo</ref>, who governed a neighboring province in yet another land-related vendetta. He was put to trial in absentia in 1550, convicted and condemned to death for the death of Robledo, and other offenses pertaining to his constant involvement in the various wars between other conquistadors. A victim of his own ambition, he died in 1551 before he could begin the voyage back to Spain to appeal the decision, in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cartagena,_Colombia">Cartagena</ref>, Colombia.</p>
</text>
