<text id="autogum_voyage_doc498" title="Huai'an" shortTile="huaian" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=127302" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Huai'an</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Huai'an</hi> (淮安, Huái'ān) is in the northern part of <ref target="Jiangsu">Jiangsu</ref>.</p>

<head>By plane</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Huai'an Lianshui Airport</hi> (淮安涟水机场) (22km northeast of the city center), ☏ +86 517 81666666 . Domestic destinations include <ref target="Beijing">Beijing</ref>, <ref target="Changchun">Changchun</ref>, <ref target="Chongqing">Chongqing</ref>, <ref target="Dalian">Dalian</ref>, <ref target="Fuzhou">Fuzhou</ref>, <ref target="Guangzhou">Guangzhou</ref>, <ref target="Guiyang">Guiyang</ref>, <ref target="Hangzhou">Hangzhou</ref>, <ref target="Kunming">Kunming</ref>, <ref target="Nanning">Nanning</ref>, <ref target="Ningbo">Ningbo</ref>, <ref target="Qingdao">Qingdao</ref>, <ref target="Shanghai">Shanghai</ref> (Pudong Airport), <ref target="Shenyang">Shenyang</ref>, <ref target="Shenzhen">Shenzhen</ref>, <ref target="Shijiazhuang">Shijiazhuang</ref>, <ref target="Taiyuan">Taiyuan</ref>, <ref target="Tianjin">Tianjin</ref>, <ref target="Wenzhou">Wenzhou</ref>, <ref target="Xiamen">Xiamen</ref>, <ref target="Xi%27an">Xi'an</ref> and <ref target="Zhengzhou">Zhengzhou</ref>. International destinations include <ref target="Hong%20Kong">Hong Kong</ref>, <ref target="Taipei">Taipei</ref>, <ref target="Bangkok">Bangkok</ref> and <ref target="Siem%20Reap">Siem Reap</ref>.Ground transportation:Express buses are available to two locations, one being the Dingli International Hotel, the other being the intersection of Datong Road and North Xiangyu Avenue.Regular buses, which stop at numerous stops, are available to Lianshui County.Taxis are also available.</item>
</list>

 

<head>By train</head>

<p>Huai'an is served only by regular trains. High-speed rail will not become an option until around September 2019. In the meantime, you may consider catching a high-speed train to <ref target="Xuzhou">Xuzhou</ref> and then catching a regular train to Huai'an from there.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Huai'an Station</hi> (淮安站), 18 Zhujiang Road, Huaiyin District, Huai'an (淮安市淮阴区珠江路18号) (public bus routes 1, 7, 11, 12, 16, 17, 47, 101, 107, 111, and Huaiyin 210). In the city's north, not far from the Huai'an North Bus Station.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Huai'an South Station</hi> (淮安南站), 1 Xiamen Road, Qingjiangpu District, Huai'an (淮安市清江浦区厦门路1号) (public bus routes 28, 29, 30, 33, 38, 58, 507, and y33). In the city center.</item>
</list>


<p>A third railway station, to be known as Huai'an East Station (淮安东站), is currently being constructed in the city's eastern suburbs. In the future, this will be the main station for high speed trains.</p>

<head>By bus</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Huai'an Central Bus Station</hi> (淮安汽车总站), 69 North Huaihai Road, Qingjiangpu District, Huai'an (淮安市清江浦区淮海北路69号) (public bus routes 1, 4, 5, 7, 15, 16, 18, 22, 26, 31, 33, 34, 36, 93, 100, 116, q26, y100, y15, and y33). In the city center. This is Huai'an's busiest bus station. Buses are available to a wide range of destinations both within and beyond the region.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Huai'an North Bus Station</hi> (淮安汽车北站), 167 Zhujiang Road, Huaiyin District, Huai'an (淮安市淮阴区珠江路167号) (public bus routes 5, 12, 16, 37, 39, 107, 116, Huayin 201, Huaiyin 202, Huaiyin 203, Huaiyin 205, Huaiyin 206, Huaiyin 207, Huaiyin 208, Huaiyin 210, and Huaiyin 212). In the city's north. This is Huai'an's second busiest bus station. Buses are available to a wide range of destinations, though not as many as are available from the Central Bus Station.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Huai'an South Bus Station</hi> (淮安汽车南站), 296 South Huaihai Road, Qingjiangpu District, Huai'an (淮安市清江浦区淮海南路296号) (public bus routes 1, 9, 11, 12, 20, 21, 27, 35, 46, 48, 79, 83, 505 Inner Circle, 505 Outer Circle, 507, 515, and 535). In the city's southwest. This bus station mainly serves destinations in Jiangsu and neighbouring provinces such as <ref target="Shandong">Shandong</ref>, <ref target="Anhui">Anhui</ref> and <ref target="Zhejiang">Zhejiang</ref>.</item>
</list>

 

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Huai'an East Bus Station</hi> (淮安汽车东站), 2 Huaxi Road, Huai'an District, Huai'an (淮安市淮安区华西路2号) (public bus routes 8, 10, 20, 65, 67, Huai'an 201, Huai'an 202, Huai'an 203, Huai'an 204, Huai'an 204, Huai'an 205, Huai'an 206 and Huai'an 207). In the city's southeast. This bus station mainly serves destinations in Jiangsu and neighbouring provinces such as <ref target="Shandong">Shandong</ref>, <ref target="Anhui">Anhui</ref> and <ref target="Zhejiang">Zhejiang</ref>.</item>
</list>

 

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Zhenhuai Building (old city gate)</hi> (镇淮楼), 2 Zhenhuai Road East, Huai'an District, Huai'an (淮安市淮安区镇淮楼东路2号) (take bus nos 10, 20, 60, 61, 63, 65, 66, 67, 69, 606, or 618 and get off at the Zhenhuai Building bus stop). 7:30-18:30. The Zhenhuai Building was constructed during the 12th century as a libation hall for the Jin army. In the 19th century, the building was rebuilt and given its present name, which literally means 'building that controls the Huai River', reflecting the fact that flooding of the river was a serious issue at the time. There is a small museum in the building. ¥10.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Zhou Enlai Memorial Hall</hi> (周恩来纪念馆), 2 Yonghuai Road, Huai'an District, Huai'an (淮安市淮安区永怀路2号) (take bus nos 8, 10, 63, 67, or 618 and get off at the Huai'an Foreign Languages School bus stop, or take a tram on Line 1 and get off at either the Memorial Hall Station or the Huaxi Road Station), ☏ +86 517 85912365 . Summer: 08:30-17:00; other seasons: 08:30-16:30. Contains exhibitions about the life and work of Zhou Enlai, one of the most prominent political figures in China during the 20th century. Free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Zhou Enlai's former residence</hi> (周恩来故居), 7 Fuma Lane, Huai'an District, Huai'an (淮安市淮安区驸马巷7号) (take bus nos 62, 65, 619 or y65 and get off at the bus stop named Zhou Enlai's Former Residence), ☏ +86 517 85912365 . Summer: 08:30-17:00; other seasons: 08:30-16:30. Zhou Enlai was born in this house in 1898 and lived here for the first 12 years of his life. Free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The place where Zhou Enlai studied as a child</hi> (周恩来童年读书旧址), 174 Caoyun Road West, Qinghe District, Huai'an (淮安市清河区漕运西路174号) (take bus no. 30 and get off at the bus stop named after this place), ☏ +86 517 85912365 . This was a family school operated by Zhou Enlai's elder relatives. Zhou Enlai attended classes here with his younger brother and his two younger sisters. Free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Huai'an Government House</hi> (淮安府署，淮安府衙), 38 Dongmen Street, Huai'an District, Huai'an (淮安市淮安区东门大街38号) (take bus 69 and get off at either Shangban Street 上板街 or Caoyun Xiaoqu 漕运校区), ☏ +86 517 85131181 . 08:30-18:00. This is one of the very few surviving examples in China of a prefecture-level yamen. The complex was first built in 1370 and was restored several times after being damaged by fires. ¥60.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Wu Cheng'en's former residence</hi> (吴承恩故居), 12 Datong Lane, Old Hexia Town, Huai'an District, Huai'an (淮安市淮安区河下古镇打铜巷12号) (take bus nos. 62, 65, 69, or y65 and get off at Zhuxiang Street 竹巷街, then walk about 500 metres down the street until you come to Datong Lane), ☏ +86 517 85181895 , ✉ wcegj@163.com . Summer: 08:30-18:00, winter: 08:30-17:30. Wu Cheng'en, the acclaimed author of <hi rend="italic">Journey to the West</hi>, lived here during the Ming Dynasty. ¥40.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">China Water Transport Museum</hi> (中国漕运博物馆), Caoyun Square, Huai'an District, Huai'an (淮安市淮安区漕运广场) (TAKE bus 69 and get off at Caoyun Xiaoqu 漕运校区, the museum is opposite Huai'an Government House.), ☏ +86 517 85839097 , ✉ cybwg@qq.com . 08:30-12:00, 13:30-17:30. Huai'an has long been important port on the Grand Canal. This museum tells the story of Huai'an's role in the transportation of grain to the imperial capital. ¥50.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Huai'an Zoo</hi> (淮安动物园), 198 Jiankang Road West, Qingjiangpu District, Huai'an (淮安市清江浦区健康西路198号) (catch bus nos. 22 or 86 to get to the north gate or bus nos. 3, 5, 22, 48 or 86 to get to the south gate), ☏ +86 517 83963924 . 08:00-16:30. This zoo was established in 1958 and moved to the present location in 2012. It has imported animals and native animals. ¥30.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Wentong Pagoda</hi> (文通塔), 46 Ximen Street, Huai'an District, Huai'an (淮安市淮安区西门大街46号) (the pagoda is in the middle of a park along side the Wentong High School; catch bus nos. 65 or y65 and get off at the bus stop named Pharmaceutical Company 医药公司). The Wentong Pagoda was built in 708, at which time it was known as the Zunsheng Pagoda. It was renamed the Wentong Pagoda in 1629 following a major renovation. In 1668 an earthquake caused severe damage to the pagoda and it had to be almost completely rebuilt.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Huai'an Museum</hi> (淮安市博物馆), 1-146 Jiankang Road West, Qingjiangpu District, Huai'an (淮安市清江浦区健康西路146-1号) (take bus nos 4, 16, 32, 86, 88 or 116 and get off at either Jiankang Road West 健康西路 or the South Campus of the No. 1 Elementary School of Huaiyin Teacher's College 一附小南校区), ☏ +86 517 83645659 , ✉ hasbwg@163.com . 09:00-12:00, 13:30-17:30. A museum about the history and culture of Huai'an. Free.</item>
</list>
</text>
