<text id="autogum_whow_doc145" title="Communicate Better and Not Argue" shortTile="communicate-better" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2010-05-23" dateModified="2018-08-24" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Communicate-Better-and-Not-Argue" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Communicate Better and Not Argue</head><p>Everybody argues once in a while, but for some people to stop is a lot harder than others. Teenagers especially tend to argue a lot with their family. Hopefully this article will help to stop it.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Discover the key things that tick you off. If there are a few specific issues that make you angry, find a way to discuss these with your family. Do not do this forcefully, but instead calmly, saying why it is that it frustrates you. Let your family have their input also, and find a way to avoid these situations that make you so annoyed. <figure rend="Communicate Better and Not Argue Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try to spend more time with the person that you argue most with; whether it be sibling or parent. At first this may be hard, and you may find yourself at first having even more arguments due to the increased amount of time you are spending with them. However, perseverance will definitely pay off; you will learn what you have in common with this person and develop a stronger bond with them that allows you to avoid arguments, or if they arise, to sort them out effectively. <figure rend="Communicate Better and Not Argue Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take a deep breath. When somebody says something and you feel the burst of anger inside, take a deep breath and look downwards. Count to ten, calmly ignoring them. Then answer what they have said collectively without rudeness. Change the topic craftily if possible! This will take time - but it is something that once learnt, will always help you. <figure rend="Communicate Better and Not Argue Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Walk out. If an argument is getting out of hand or you cannot seem to master the breathing technique, walk out of the room. Your family may find this rude so make sure to explain before or afterward about why you are doing this. <figure rend="Communicate Better and Not Argue Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you have walked out, or the issue is nagging you, think of a way to discuss it with your family, once both of you are calm. Say what happened in your perspective and don't make it long. Don't be aggressive. If they interrupt, try not to flare up, just continue calmly. Listen to what they have to say and keep in mind that they probably felt similar to you. Neither of you are probably completely right. Then apologise. If they approach you first, listen, listen, listen. <figure rend="Communicate Better and Not Argue Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Apologize. If arguments do happen, it is NOT weak to be the first to apologize. In fact, this is one of the hardest things to do. Apologizing, if you do it properly without the whole '(glare) "sorry" (walk out of the room)' thing, will help you to get things into perspective. You may realize your mistakes and hopefully, this will prevent them in the future. You may also find that when apologizing, the other person will respect you for this and admit what they have done wrong also. Make sure you have cooled down before apologizing as well! Otherwise, the whole thing might start all over again. <figure rend="Communicate Better and Not Argue Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Never give up. Do not try to do everything at once and just take it step by step. <figure rend="Communicate Better and Not Argue Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not feel under pressure to solve this immediately - you are not the only one and in time, you will be able to see a change.</item>
<item>Keep trying</item>
<item>Respect everybody in your family for who they are</item>
<item>Remember your family loves you</item></list>
</text>
