<text id="autogum_interview_doc203" title="part4_BDSM as business: Interviews with Dominatrixes" shortTile="partbdsm-business" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-28" dateModified="2008-01-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BDSM_as_business%3A_Interviews_with_Dominatrixes" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Body%20language">Body language</ref>, or how they’re reacting.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do they talk about with you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Oh, it can be a various number of things.  Just about everything.</p>
<head id="The_psychology_of_S&amp;M">The psychology of S&amp;M</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you feel like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Therapist">therapists</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Definitely.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  Absolutely.  My last client—and I feel kind of bad, because he was willing to take a picture for you with a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bondage%20hood">hood</ref> on, but I got really into the session and I wasn’t thinking about you!  I’m sorry!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>] That’s okay.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  But, <hi rend="italic">he</hi> has an S&amp;M relationship with his wife, and he has seen Mistresses in the past, and he said that he needs a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Masturbation">masturbation</ref> therapist.  “I’m masturbating too much and I’m not able to please my wife when she wants to be pleased, and I want you to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Discipline%20(BDSM)">discipline me</ref>!”  That was an hour and a half session.  We talked about his masturbation for half an hour, and I asked him, “Now you’re not going to go out…when are you going to masturbate next?”  He said, “Not this week.”  And I was like, “Yeah!”  To be honest, it’s different for everyone and I don’t care.  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>] I don’t <hi rend="italic">personally</hi> care when people masturbate, to be quite honest.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Giggles</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  But he felt like this was not the relationship he wanted with his wife, he wanted to tell me about it, and he didn’t want to talk about his wife in session.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you ever get bored listening?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  Oh, no!  I find it fascinating because everybody is so…</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  I think if you’re really into it, you never get bored.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  I get bored when people are <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arrogance">arrogant</ref>.  Sometimes people will top from the bottom, and that bores me.  Or if they are not honest.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Yeah, if they are not honest.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is it pretty obvious when they are not being honest with you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  I think so.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Yeah, when you’re doing session you are definitely capable of finding out when they are being honest with you.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  I ask them questions, and sometimes when I feel like that, I’ll start interrogating them so that they’ll make a mistake because I want to really know what is going on in their head if they are not letting me know.  That kind of pisses me off a little bit.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Exactly.</p>
<p>[<hi rend="italic">Rebecca comes in and tells Alex she has a client for her to meet, so she has to leave shortly</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  I’m probably going to have a session, it sounds like.  But I just wanted to make that point about checking in where people’s heads are at; that’s something that is very important to me.  I think that is for a lot of people, although I don’t want to make generalizations because people are in the industry for a lot of different reasons.  But for me, I find it fascinating where they start out, where they finish.  Like this guy who was just here, he wants to come back on a regular basis and discipline himself.  He wants to make his life better; he wants to become a better person.  You don’t get people who come in here that often saying that.</p>
</text>
