<text id="autogum_interview_doc602" title="part7_Wikinews interviews John Wolfe, Democratic Party presidential challenger to Barack Obama" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-05-19" dateModified="2013-09-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_John_Wolfe%2C_Democratic_Party_presidential_challenger_to_Barack_Obama" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>And the misinformation gets out there. It gets out there because of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Fox_News">Fox News</ref>, but it also gets out there because Obama doesn't educate the people and if people knew that, he could change public opinion if he would just educate them to that.  But he doesn't do it because he's too timid. His whole life has been one where he reaches consensus until he gets along. He goes along and gets along. He's never had to take a hard stance or anything like that. And that may be why he got elected. It could be that the American people would have rejected him if he'd been an assertive <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/African%20American">African American</ref> man who took hard stances on hard issues, and was very dogmatic. And I think that's unfortunate because some of a lot America might react that way.</p>
<head id="Policy">Policy</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Let's get into policy a little more. How can high energy costs be reduced?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wolfe</hi>: Well, the only way to do that is you're going to have to try to find <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alternative%20energy">alternate sources of energy</ref>. You've got to make cars that are more fuel efficient. You have to have homes that heat better, that are better insulated. You have to get people to do the things that [President] <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jimmy_Carter">Jimmy Carter</ref> told us to do 35 years ago. If people started doing that more, it would be a lot better. Now we've already cut down on some of our energy consumption, but we definitely need to do it more. I think that it's a shame that gasoline costs as much as it does and it's a shame that the oil companies have as much power as they do. It's a shame that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ExxonMobil">Exxon</ref> made like 10 billion dollars in one quarter.  That's just really pathetic, and they have all the power, all the tax breaks, all the lobbyists, all the political pull. They're growing bigger and bigger at our expense.</p>
<figure><caption>President Jimmy Carter, pictured in 1980, remarked during a <ref target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/President%20Carter's%20Address%20to%20the%20Nation%20on%20Proposed%20National%20Energy%20Policy">1977 speech on energy policy</ref> that "we must prepare quickly for...strict conservation and to the use of coal and permanent renewable energy sources, like solar power." He listed ten principles for a "national energy plan".Image: Marion S. Trikosko.</caption></figure>
<p>One way to do it too would be to cut down. I think there needs to be some sort of, on the energy futures and things like that, they need to really be careful that people aren't allowed to run up the price of oil through speculation like they did during 2008. There just wasn't that much going on in the economy at that time. We were sort of having the onset of a recession and the energy demand worldwide was falling in 2008, yet the price of a barrel of oil went in March of 2008 to $48.00 to about $147.00 at the end of July.  So that sort of thing needs to be investigated and any sort of speculative activities that gives rise to that needs to be regulated.  I mean, there was no reason for it to triple like that.</p>
</text>
