<text id="autogum_interview_doc906" title="part5_Interview with Reggie Bibbs on his life with neurofibromatosis" shortTile="partinterview-reggie" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-28" dateModified="2010-04-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Reggie_Bibbs_on_his_life_with_neurofibromatosis" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="Raising_awareness_and_his_campaign">Raising awareness and his campaign</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: What are you doing personally to raise awareness about NF?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: I am trying to get better at going to a lot of the activities that we have in our town. The Renaissance festival, the Rolly Derby. I'm trying to make myself visible for people to get a chance to see me and to see that I like the same things that they like and once you get over the outward appearances then I'm a pretty good person to know.</p>
<figure><caption>Reggie Bibbs at a Houston Astros baseball game, wearing his "Just Ask" neurofibromatosis campaign T-shirt.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: I heard you went to your first baseball game this year. Why didn't you go to a baseball game before?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: The reason why I've never gone to a baseball game before this year I was just afraid of going by myself and afraid of what people would say. And so I went to my first game with my friend and I really was surprised. I've learned a lot that I have to give people a chance. And when I went people were really really nice to me. And I was just really impressed. And it made me want to do more because people were very accepting to me and same at other places and they would actually come up to me and make the first move and shake my hand and just give me words of encouragement. And since that first game it makes me want to go and do more. With each place I go I find acceptance.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: What would you say to somebody who sees you, who doesn't know you, doesn't know about neurofibromatosis, what would you tell them to do?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: I would tell them, for anyone that have never seen me, or have never heard of NF, if they would just ask, and try to give it a chance. Just ask, you know, 'what is this', just give it a chance. It may be NF for someone and it may not, but try to put yourself in that person's shoes, try to think about how would you feel. The person may not have NF, they may have some other disorder, but we all need acceptance, we all need a chance.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: You talked about telling these people (coughs) to just ask. You have a T-shirt on, tell me about the T-shirt.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: The T-shirts came about for that reason. I would see a lot of people that would look at me, and some would look at me like they admire me, some would look like 'I wonder if I should ask', and they don't know. They don't know it's ok with me to ask, and I said 'I would like to let people know, I don't mind questions', and that's why I came up with the 'Just Ask' campaign.</p>
</text>
