<text id="autogum_interview_doc359" title="part5_Creator of website satirizing Glenn Beck on winning domain name case" shortTile="partcreator-website" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-11-09" dateModified="2019-02-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Creator_of_website_satirizing_Glenn_Beck_on_winning_domain_name_case" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Ultimately, the website's purpose was to shine a light on Glenn Beck's style, and to reflect it right back at him.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> How did you feel when you first found out that Glenn Beck had begun to take legal actions with regard to your website?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">E-H</hi>: Well, it certainly didn't make me very happy, but at the same time, it confirmed what I suspected.</p>
<p>It didn't make me happy because, obviously, nobody likes to be sued.  It also made me unhappy because I saw it as a direct assault on free speech.</p>
<p>Of course, it confirmed my suspicions that Glenn Beck's claims to be a champion of the constitution are false claims.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Why did you register alternate domain names: "DidGlennBeckRapeAndMurderAYoungGirlIn1990.com", and "gb1990.com"? Will you maintain the website at those locations?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">E-H</hi>: As I said about the original domain - I wanted to register the meme as the domain, and that's what I referred to as the "statement" domain. The "question" domain came about because the entire concept of the meme is not to try and convince people that Beck raped and murdered; but how the supposed rumour that he did is a direct parody of the techniques he himself uses.</p>
<p>I thought that the question form would serve the meme better, so I went ahead and registered it; and as soon as I did, I changed the website to the question instead of the statement (in the title and header for the page).</p>
<p>When the domain dispute was filed, I registered gb1990.com, as well as gb1990.net. I did this partly because if he managed to get the question or statement domains taken down, I would have a backup in place. Also, it's a lot easier to type "gb1990" than either of the long versions, so that was a part of it as well. I made gb1990.com the primary domain for the website, and parked the other two on top. I put gb1990.net as a mirror on my second server, in case something happened to the first.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You wrote in your November 6 letter to Beck, "It bears observing that by bringing the WIPO complaint, you took what was merely one small critique meme, in a sea of internet memes, and turned it into a super meme." Media commentators have written that Beck's actions in the case trigged the "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Streisand%20effect">Streisand effect</ref>". Do you think this happened here? What do you mean when you say Beck created a "super meme"?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">E-H</hi>: I definitely think the Streisand effect came into play. Even before I got the website up and running, Farkers had already spread the meme - asking questions on Yahoo Answers, for example. So it definitely got attention out there; but the traffic to the site dropped off drastically after the first couple of days. It wasn't until people posted news about the legal threats to Reddit, Fark, Digg, and many blogs that I saw spikes in traffic. The major spikes in traffic to the site have all come from updates about where the legal fight stood. For example, when a thread went green (public) on Fark.com, traffic to my servers nearly overwhelmed them for a couple of hours. When we posted my brilliant lawyer Marc Randazza's responses to the original WIPO complaint, traffic was high for a couple of days. In each case, it dropped down to a relatively low level when news was sparse.</p>
</text>
