<text id="autogum_bio_doc383" title="Moses of Mardin" shortTile="moses-mardin" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-04-27" dateModified="2019-07-30" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moses_of_Mardin" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Moses of Mardin</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Moses of Mardin</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Latin">Latin</ref>: <hi rend="italic">Moses Mardenus</hi>) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syriac_Orthodox">Syriac Orthodox</ref> priest and bishop who played a significant role in printing the first Syriac bible and served as perhaps the first Syriac teacher/scholar in Europe.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Moses was born in the village of Qaluq near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mardin">Mardin</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tur_Abdin">Tur Abdin</ref> region. Moses is first mentioned in 1549 as an envoy of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syriac_Orthodox_Church">Jacobite</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patriarch_of_Antioch">Patriarch of Antioch</ref>, Ignatius Abdullah I Stephan, to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rome">Rome</ref> to seek the means to print Syriac copies of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Testament">New Testament</ref>. His mission also included negotiations of unity with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catholic_Church">Catholic Church</ref> in anticipation of the Patriarch's arrival.</p>
<p>Whilst in Rome, Moses stayed in the monastery of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Stephen_of_the_Abyssinians">St Stephen of the Abyssinians</ref> where <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johannes_Potken">Johannes Potken</ref> had printed the first <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ge'ez">Ge'ez</ref> book, <hi rend="italic">Psalterium David et Cantica aliqu</hi>. Here he printed a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syriac_language">Syriac</ref> manuscript with the assistance of the Cardinals <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Marcellus_II">Marcello Cervini</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reginald_Pole">Reginald Pole</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean_du_Bellay">Jean du Bellay</ref>. However the manuscript produced was defective as the printers did not understand the language.</p>
<p>In 1550, Moses travelled to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Venice">Venice</ref> to meet <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guillaume_Postel">Guillaume Postel</ref> to promote the idea of printing a Syriac copy of the New Testament which Postel had been working on since 1537. Despite this Postel could not help print it as he did not have the characters to print in Syriac.</p>
<p>In 1552, Moses then returned to Rome where he taught Syriac to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andreas_Masius">Andreas Masius</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Albrecht_Widmannstetter">Johann Albrecht Widmannstetter</ref> among others. Upon the advice of Masius, he left Rome in the company of Cardinal Pole as he was returning to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_England">England</ref>, to meet Johann Jacob Fugger in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Augsburg">Augsburg</ref>. However, whilst staying in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dillingen_an_der_Donau">Dillingen</ref> he met <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Albrecht_Widmanstetter">Johann Albrecht Widmanstetter</ref>, then chancellor of the Austrian lands. Both sharing the same goals of printing a Syriac copy of the New Testament, Widmanstetter travelled with Moses to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vienna">Vienna</ref> where they convinced <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ferdinand_I,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">Ferdinand I</ref> to fund their project. Thus one thousand copies of the Syriac version of the New Testament was printed in 1555 and Moses himself received half of which to distribute in the East.</p>
<p>Moses remained in Europe until 1562 before returning to the East; however before departing he sold 250 copies on the European market. In 1578, he is mentioned returning to Rome as a bishop accompanied by the deposed patriarch <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ignatius_Nemet_Allah_I">Ignatius Nemet Allah I</ref>. In 1581, Moses was appointed Professor of Syriac at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/College_of_the_Neophytes">College of the Neophytes</ref>.</p>
<p>
Mushe of Mardin (16th cent.) [Syr. Orth.]
Priest, scribe, and bp. A native of the village of Qāluq, in the region of Ṣawro, near Mardin, Mushe was sent by Patr. ʿAbdullāh I bar Sṭephanos to Rome, where he arrived with a few mss. in or shortly before 1549. The aim of the mission was to search for Syriac printed books or for opportunities to produce them. Whether Mushe was additionally entrusted with the delicate task of improving relations between the Syr. Orth and the Roman Catholic Church remains disputed. Mushe lived in Rome and traveled through Europe until some time after 1556.</p>
<p>In Rome, he established contacts with some of the earliest Western scholars interested in Syriac. Among them were Guillaume Postel, Johann Albrecht Widmanstetter, and Andreas Masius. He collaborated with Widmanstetter in the publication of the first edition of the Syriac NT, which appeared in Vienna in 1555 and whose Syriac typeface derived from Mushe’s handwriting. Mushe served as Masius’s Syriac teacher in Rome, and the latter frequently consulted him, in particular while he was preparing his Syrorum Peculium, a Syriac glossary that was included in vol. 6 of the Antwerp Polyglot (1571). Mushe and Masius corresponded in Syriac; a number of letters, belonging to the period 1553–55, are preserved. Masius also translated into Latin a profession of faith that Mushe is said to have made in 1552 and which Masius included in one of his later publications; its exact status remains unclear.</p>
<p>During his time in Europe, Mushe copied many Syriac mss. Several of these are extant, including the remarkable ms. London, Brit. Libr. Harley 5512, which contains parts of the Roman Missal in Latin, written in Serṭo script, along with three Syriac Anaphoras. Mushe wrote it for the bp. of the Abyssinian Convent (San Stefano) in Rome, where he often resided, and it shows his interest in, and familiarity with, the Catholic liturgy.</p>
<p>After 1556 Mushe returned to the Middle East, where he copied some further mss. (among them Michael Rabo’s Chronicle, probably from the author’s autograph) and where the (solely honorific?) title of metropolitan bp. was conferred on him. He returned to Rome, probably in the company of Patr. Niʿmatullāh, following the latter’s abdication, in 1578. In Rome he copied and annotated several more Syriac and Arabic mss. He died in or shortly after 1592, possibly in Rome.</p>
<p><ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Mushe-of-Mardin==">https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Mushe-of-Mardin==</ref> References ==</p>
</text>
