<text id="autogum_interview_doc425" title="part4_&amp;quot;Avast ye scurvy file sharers!&amp;quot;: Interview with Swedish Pirate Party leader Rickard Falkvinge" shortTile="partavast-ye-scurvy" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-06-19" dateModified="2015-10-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/%22Avast_ye_scurvy_file_sharers%21%22%3A_Interview_with_Swedish_Pirate_Party_leader_Rickard_Falkvinge" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>So, as they apparently make a profit today, I expect that to continue.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Do you feel that the music industry in its current form will still be needed in a world where non-commercial copying is permitted?</hi></p>
<p>It's not so much if they are needed where non-commercial copying is permitted, rather if they are needed when they're not necessary any more to be the middle man between consumer and artist.</p>
<p>The music industry <hi rend="italic">will</hi> lose its current chokepoint, because they don't add any value to the end product any longer. They will probably survive as a service bureau for artists, but they will not be able to control distribution.</p>
<p>It's actually quite simple: if they get their act together and provide a service that people want to buy, they will remain. If not, they will vanish. Today, they have legislated that people must buy their service regardless of whether it adds value or not, and that's not gonna hold in the long term.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why fight against intellectual property laws, instead of focusing your energy on creating freely licensed content, such as Creative Commons films or open source software?</hi></p>
<p>I want to raise the issue a level, to show that it's not about payment models or what level of control the copyright holder chooses to exert over his or her work.</p>
<p>Let me put it this way: we have achieved the technical possibility of sending copyrighted works in digital, private communications. I can send a piece of music in e-mail to you, I can drop a video clip in a chat room. That technology is not going away, leaving us with two choices.</p>
<p>So — <hi rend="italic">if</hi> copyright is to be enforced — if you are to tax, prohibit, fee, fine, or otherwise hinder the transmission of copyrighted works in private communications, the only way to achieve that is to have all private communications constantly monitored. It's really that large.</p>
<p>Also, this is partly nothing new. We've been able to do this since the advent of the Xerox copier — you could photocopy a poem or a painting and put it in a letter in the mail. Again, the only way to discover or stop that would have been for the authorities to open all letters and check their content.</p>
<p>So we're at a crossroads here. Either we, as a society, decide that copyright is the greater value to society, and take active steps to give up private communications as a concept. Either that, or we decide that the ability to communicate in private, without constant monitoring by authorities, has the greater value — in which case copyright will have to give way.</p>
<p>My choice is clear.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">The Pirate Bay was shut down and re-opened days later on a Dutch server. According to a Swedish newspaper report, traffic has doubled since then. How long do you think the cat and mouse game will continue?</hi></p>
</text>
