<text id="autogum_bio_doc233" title="John Gore (Royal Navy officer, died 1790)" shortTile="john-gore-royal-navy" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-01-04" dateModified="2019-05-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Gore_%28Royal_Navy_officer%2C_died_1790%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>John Gore (Royal Navy officer, died 1790)</head>For other people with the same name, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Gore_(disambiguation)">John Gore</ref>.
<figure><caption>John Gore by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Webber">John Webber</ref>, 1780</caption></figure>
<p>Captain <hi rend="bold">John Gore</hi> (c. 1730–10 August 1790) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/British_American">British American</ref> sailor who circumnavigated the globe four times with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_Navy">Royal Navy</ref> in the 18th century and accompanied <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Cook">Captain James Cook</ref> in his discoveries in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pacific_Ocean">Pacific Ocean</ref>.</p>
<head>History</head>
<p>Although little is known about John Gore before his service with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_Navy">Royal Navy</ref>, it is believed he was born in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Great_Britain">British</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colony_of_Virginia">Colony of Virginia</ref> in either 1729 or 1730. He first appears in the record books in 1755, joining <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HMS_Windsor_(1695)">HMS <hi rend="italic">Windsor</hi></ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portsmouth">Portsmouth</ref> as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Midshipman">midshipman</ref>.</p>
<p>Five years later Gore took his lieutenant's exam and was appointed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Master's_mate">master's mate</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HMS_Dolphin_(1751)">HMS <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi></ref>. Aboard the <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> Gore circumnavigated the globe twice—first under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Byron">John Byron</ref> and then <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samuel_Wallis">Samuel Wallis</ref>. His experience in the Pacific Ocean and on extended navy expeditions led to him being called up to join <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Cook">James Cook</ref>'s mission to record the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1769_Transit_of_Venus_observed_from_Tahiti">Transit of Venus in Tahiti</ref> and search for <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terra_Australis">Terra Australis</ref></hi> in 1768 aboard <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HMS_Endeavour">HMS <hi rend="italic">Endeavour</hi></ref>. On <hi rend="italic">Endeavour</hi>, Gore was initially third-in-command (i.e. 3rd Lieutenant) behind Cook (1st Lieutenant) and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zachary_Hicks">Zachary Hicks</ref>
(2nd Lieutenant). After the death of Hicks on the return voyage to England on 26 May 1771, Gore became second-in-command (2nd Lieutenant)
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Gore had previously been part of the Royal Navy crew aboard Wallis's <hi rend="italic">Dolphin</hi> that had "discovered" Tahiti and he became valuable to Cook for his knowledge of the island. In 1769 Gore became the first recorded person on the expedition to shoot and kill a person of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Māori_people">Māori</ref> descent, following an altercation over a piece of cloth as the <hi rend="italic">Endeavour</hi> charted the coast of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Zealand">New Zealand</ref>. Later, on 14 July 1770 Gore became famous for being the first person to shoot and kill a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kangaroo">kangaroo</ref> (for scientific research) as the expedition made its way up the eastern seaboard of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Australia">Australia</ref>.</p>
<p>Returning to England, in 1772 Gore joined the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Botanist">botanist</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joseph_Banks">Joseph Banks</ref> (who had also been on Cook's first Pacific voyage) in a private scientific expedition to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iceland">Iceland</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hebrides">Hebrides</ref>. Gore and Banks may have become friends as evidence shows that Banks was the executor of Gore's will. The trip did not return until after Cook had sailed on his second Pacific voyage.</p>
<p>However, in 1776 Gore answered the call from Cook and the admiralty once again and joined <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HMS_Resolution_(1771)">HMS <hi rend="italic">Resolution</hi></ref> as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First_Lieutenant">First Lieutenant</ref> for Cook's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Third_voyage_of_James_Cook">third voyage</ref>. As the <hi rend="italic">Resolution</hi> explored the Pacific in search of the famed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Northwest_Passage">Northwest Passage</ref>, Gore would sight the American continent of his birth from the west coast. Later, following Cook's death in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hawaii">Hawaii</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Clerke">Charles Clerke</ref>, captain of <hi rend="italic">Resolution's</hi> sister ship <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HMS_Discovery_(1774)">HMS <hi rend="italic">Discovery</hi></ref> took command. Gore then assumed command of <hi rend="italic">Discovery</hi> in Clerke's place. When Clerke himself died shortly after, Gore took responsibility for the entire expedition (unaware that his place of birth had <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Declaration_of_Independence">declared its independence</ref> from Great Britain two years previously) and brought the ships home to England on 4 October 1780—more than a year after assuming command. He was formally promoted to the post of captain on 2 October 1780.</p>
<p>In recognition of his achievements <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Webber">John Webber</ref>, who had previously painted Cook, took Gore's portrait as the navy made him an honorary <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Post-captain">post-captain</ref>. Moving further in the footsteps of Cook, he was offered the late Captain's vacant rooms at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greenwich_Hospital_(London)">Greenwich Hospital</ref>. In 1790, having circumnavigated the globe four times, he died on 10 August.</p>
<head>Legacy</head>
<p>Gore was survived by a son, John (born 1774) who was also a Royal Navy Officer, who reached the rank of captain on 19 July 1821, retiring in that rank on 1 October 1846, later promoted to Retired Rear Admiral on 8 March 1852 and dying in 1853.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> He moved to Australia in 1834 as one of the first free settlers. Little is known of his mother (John Gore senior's wife), Ann Gore, although she is known to have received a Royal Navy widow's pension from 1790.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> His son (that is, John Gore senior's grandson), Graham Gore, continued the expeditionary heritage, perishing in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Franklin">John Franklin</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franklin's_lost_expedition">ill-fated attempt</ref> to navigate the Northwest Passage, nearly 70 years after his grandfather had attempted the same.</p>
<p>Gore Point and the Gore Peninsula in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alaska">Alaskan</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kenai_Fjords_National_Park">Kenai fjords</ref> were named for John Gore by Captain <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nathaniel_Portlock">Nathaniel Portlock</ref>, a fellow veteran of Cook's third voyage who explored the Pacific Northwest of America in the late 18th century. There are also several Australian and New Zealand sites named after John Gore.</p>
</text>
