<text id="autogum_interview_doc696" title="part0_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Family Coalition Party candidate Carita Murphy-Marketos, Sudbury" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-04" dateModified="2013-03-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Family_Coalition_Party_candidate_Carita_Murphy-Marketos%2C_Sudbury" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Family Coalition Party candidate Carita Murphy-Marketos, Sudbury</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 4, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Carita Murphy-Marketos</hi> is running for the Family Coalition Party in the Ontario provincial election, in the Sudbury riding. Wikinews' Nick Moreau interviewed her regarding her values, her experience, and her campaign.</p>
<p>Carita did not answer "What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?"</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>I chose to involve myself in the political process when approached by a person locally who was keenly interested in respect for life, from conception to natural death, the preservation of the traditional family and freedom to act in accordance with one’s conscience in addition to the individual’s right to speak out against actions and activities that one is not in agreement with.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why?</hi></p>
<p>My stance is not in opposition to any party it is in support of the principles of life, freedom of speech and the preservation of traditional marriage thus, the traditional family, which is the heartbeat of our nation.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?</hi></p>
<p>I may not be the most desirable candidate, however I have gained considerable support for having the ‘courage’ to stand up and speak for the unborn and for values that contribute to a strong and healthy society. My entire career life has been spent working with people in the medical, sales and teaching fields in an administrative, managerial and front-line worker capacity. This intimate association with people of all ages and from all walks of life has deepened my sensitivity to the needs and concerns of members of society. I care!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>The voters in my riding are passionately against abortion, they believe that same-sex marriage is an abomination and that the family is the nucleus of a strong and healthy society.</p>
<p>Health care delivery is a concern. The FCP will not use public funds for abortion, euthanasia and sex-change operations. The FCP supports expansion of programs for midwives (in teams with doctors), nurse practitioners and physician-assistants for salaried service, in rural areas and in those communities where the local Hospital Board deems it necessary.</p>
</text>
