<text id="autogum_reddit_doc123" title="[GIVEAWAY] Hey guys Glorious PC Gaming Race here! We are doing some research into gaming mice and we are also giving away free mousepads to the /r/MouseReview community! (Open worldwide)" shortTile="giveaway-hey-guys" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-04-30" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8g31lm" speakerList="#UtopiaDystopia, #woox13" speakerCount="2">
<head>[GIVEAWAY] Hey guys Glorious PC Gaming Race here! We are doing some research into gaming mice and we are also giving away free mousepads to the /r/MouseReview community! (Open worldwide)</head>
<sp who="#woox13">
<p>Hey guys! Owner of **<ref target="https://www.pcgamingrace.com">PCGAMINGRRACE.com</ref>** here. For those of you that don't know we are a PC gaming peripherals company, that started out with <ref target="https://www.pcgamingrace.com/collections/glorious-large-gaming-mouse-pads-mats">large size mousepads</ref> and then transitioned into the Mechanical Keyboard scene with our <ref target="https://www.pcgamingrace.com/products/gmmk-full-customized">GMMK keyboard</ref>. And as some of you may have already picked up on it - we are working our way into the mouse realm, and are gathering some knowledge on what you guys would like to have. Realistically its pretty much impossible to make the "*final mouse*", but we will instead make several models of shapes and sizes of mice that can hopefully satisfy everyones need. We are also working on a solution to have a way for everyone to test out the shape of the mouse before committing to a particular shape (or having to go to a store and test). But all in all that will take some time, and you guys can keep track of our progress with our periodic updates on this sub or <ref target="https://www.reddit.com/r/gloriouspcgamingrace/">our sub</ref>. -----------------------------------------------------------  <hi rend="bold">GIVEAWAY</hi>  ------- And of course, we are giving away of <ref target="https://www.pcgamingrace.com/collections/glorious-large-gaming-mouse-pads-mats">5 of our gaming mousepads</ref>, to 5 members of /r/mousereview (worldwide, free shipping). Winner will be able to select which mousepad they would like to receive if they win.  <hi rend="bold">How to enter:</hi>  1. Comment here on which mouse you currently use and why. 2. Sign up here so we can generate and contact the winner: https://goo.gl/forms/gXzaWi3D3sMqCizM2  <hi rend="bold">Contest ends 11:59PM 3rd May 2018 (Central Time (US &amp; Canada)). Winners will be announced May 5th on this thread and contacted via e-mail. Winners will be randomly selected.</hi>  EDIT: Entries closed. Thanks for everyone that entered. Will post results soon :) EDIT: Winners are: /u/Pcmasterraces /u/kroms /u/Grizzza /u/kokopiez /u/Xiotox Winners have all been contacted via PM/email. If we do not hear anything back from one of the winners, we will select a new one! Thanks everyone for participating. </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#UtopiaDystopia">
<p>Zowie FK1 </p>
<p>Positive: </p>
<p>- Good shape and size that feels comfortable for my 20x10cm hand ( I like having a choice in size with the other models fk2, fk1+) </p>
<p>- Good plastic coating that I prefer over rubberised because of durability and feel. </p>
<p>- Flexible cable that doesn’t interfere </p>
<p>- Smooth, large mouse feet </p>
<p>- Low force actuation middle-mouse button </p>
<p>- Good build quality with only a slight mouse wheel rattle when shaking) </p>
<p> </p>
<p>Improvements I would like: </p>
<p>- I would prefer lighter mouse one and two clicks using omron switches instead of huano (for this reason I prefer the Logitech G Pro for MOBA RTS </p>
<p>- Would prefer the Pixart 3360 sensor instead of the 3310 </p>
<p>- The price is far too high for the features compared to the competition </p>
</sp>
</text>
