<text id="autogum_fiction_doc349" title="The Tin Woodman of Oz A Faithful Story of the Astonishing Adventure Undertaken by the Tin Woodman, Assisted by Woot the Wanderer, the Scarecrow of Oz, and Polychrome, the Rainbow's Daughter" shortTile="tinwoodmanozfaithfulstory" author="Baum, L. Frank (Lyman Frank)" type="fiction" dateCollected="2019-10-22" sourceURL="http://gutenberg.readingroo.ms/9/6/960/960.txt">
<head>Polychrome's Magic</head>

<p>On this morning, which ought to be the last of this important journey, our friends started away as bright and cheery as could be, and Woot whistled a merry tune so that Polychrome could dance to the music.</p>

<p>On reaching the top of the hill, the plain spread out before them in all its beauty of blue grasses and wildflowers, and Mount Munch seemed much nearer than it had the previous evening. They trudged on at a brisk pace, and by noon the mountain was so close that they could admire its appearance. Its slopes were partly clothed with pretty evergreens, and its foot-hills were tufted with a slender waving bluegrass that had a tassel on the end of every blade. And, for the first time, they perceived, near the foot of the mountain, a charming house, not of great size but neatly painted and with many flowers surrounding it and vines climbing over the doors and windows.</p>

<p>It was toward this solitary house that our travelers now directed their steps, thinking to inquire of the people who lived there where Nimmie Amee might be found.</p>

<p>There were no paths, but the way was quite open and clear, and they were drawing near to the dwelling when Woot the Wanderer, who was then in the lead of the little party, halted with such an abrupt jerk that he stumbled over backward and lay flat on his back in the meadow. The Scarecrow stopped to look at the boy.</p>

<p>"Why did you do that?" he asked in surprise.</p>

<p>Woot sat up and gazed around him in amazement.</p>

<p>"I--I don't know!" he replied.</p>

<p>The two tin men, arm in arm, started to pass them when both halted and tumbled, with a great clatter, into a heap beside Woot. Polychrome, laughing at the absurd sight, came dancing up and she, also, came to a sudden stop, but managed to save herself from falling.</p>

<p>Everyone of them was much astonished, and the Scarecrow said with a puzzled look:</p>

<p>"I don't see anything."</p>

<p>"Nor I," said Woot; "but something hit me, just the same."</p>

<p>"Some invisible person struck me a heavy blow," declared the Tin Woodman, struggling to separate himself from the Tin Soldier, whose legs and arms were mixed with his own.</p>

<p>"I'm not sure it was a person," said Polychrome, looking more grave than usual. "It seems to me that I merely ran into some hard substance which barred my way. In order to make sure of this, let me try another place."</p>

<p>She ran back a way and then with much caution advanced in a different place, but when she reached a position on a line with the others she halted, her arms outstretched before her.</p>

<p>"I can feel something hard--something smooth as glass," she said, "but I'm sure it is not glass."</p>

<p>"Let me try," suggested Woot, getting up; but when he tried to go forward, he discovered the same barrier that Polychrome had encountered.</p>

<p>"No," he said, "it isn't glass. But what is it?"</p>

<p>"Air," replied a small voice beside him. "Solid air; that's all."</p>

<p>They all looked downward and found a sky-blue rabbit had stuck his head out of a burrow in the ground. The rabbit's eyes were a deeper blue than his fur, and the pretty creature seemed friendly and unafraid.</p>

<p>"Air!" exclaimed Woot, staring in astonishment into the rabbit's blue eyes; "whoever heard of air so solid that one cannot push it aside?"</p>

<p>"You can't push this air aside," declared the rabbit, "for it was made hard by powerful sorcery, and it forms a wall that is intended to keep people from getting to that house yonder."</p>

<p>"Oh; it's a wall, is it?" said the Tin Woodman.</p>

<p>"Yes, it is really a wall," answered the rabbit, "and it is fully six feet thick."</p>

<p>"How high is it?" inquired Captain Fyter, the Tin Soldier.</p>

<p>"Oh, ever so high; perhaps a mile," said the rabbit.</p>

<p>"Couldn't we go around it?" asked Woot.</p>

<p>"Of course, for the wall is a circle," explained the rabbit. "In the center of the circle stands the house, so you may walk around the Wall of Solid Air, but you can't get to the house."</p>

<p>"Who put the air wall around the house?" was the Scarecrow's question.</p>

<p>"Nimmie Amee did that."</p>

<p>"Nimmie Amee!" they all exclaimed in surprise.</p>

<p>"Yes," answered the rabbit. "She used to live with an old Witch, who was suddenly destroyed, and when Nimmie Amee ran away from the Witch's house, she took with her just one magic formula--pure sorcery it was--which enabled her to build this air wall around her house--the house yonder. It was quite a clever idea, I think, for it doesn't mar the beauty of the landscape, solid air being invisible, and yet it keeps all strangers away from the house."</p>

<p>"Does Nimmie Amee live there now?" asked the Tin Woodman anxiously.</p>

<p>"Yes, indeed," said the rabbit.</p>

<p>"And does she weep and wail from morning till night?" continued the Emperor.</p>

<p>"No; she seems quite happy," asserted the rabbit.</p>

<p>The Tin Woodman seemed quite disappointed to hear this report of his old sweetheart, but the Scarecrow reassured his friend, saying:</p>

<p>"Never mind, your Majesty; however happy Nimmie Amee is now, I'm sure she will be much happier as Empress of the Winkies."</p>

<p>"Perhaps," said Captain Fyter, somewhat stiffly, "she will be still more happy to become the bride of a Tin Soldier."</p>
</text>
