<text id="autogum_interview_doc042" title="part3_Wikinews interviews Rocky De La Fuente, U.S. Democratic Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-03-29" dateModified="2016-12-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Rocky_De_La_Fuente%2C_U.S._Democratic_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<hi rend="bold">I . . . have been subjected to a disappointingly unfair process by which the Party has not even remotely provided an equal chance to other candidates and me.</hi>
<p>I also have been subjected to a disappointingly unfair process by which the Party has not even remotely provided an equal chance to other candidates and me. This isn't unique to the Democratic Party. Both Parties dramatically favor their "politically privileged" member[s]; those individuals who have served their respective Parties for a long time and raised serious money on behalf of their Party.</p>
<p>If I detailed all of the "behind the scenes" inequities that I and others candidates like me have endured, you'd be shocked. Perhaps that will be another legacy of this campaign as I am inclined to bring these issues to light and have the courts decide whether the practices should be continued. That might be a greater benefit to the People than even serving as president of the United States.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Are you disappointed by the results of the primaries thus far?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">De La Fuente</hi>: I am disappointed by the treatment I have received such as being denied the courtesy of automatic ballot access that's afforded "politically privileged" candidate[s], having votes mysteriously disappear from election results, having State Parties in caucus states withhold location information, list me as "Other" and refuse to provide areas for my preference groups to form, etc. However, I am not disappointed by the results under those circumstances.</p>
<p><figure><caption>De La Fuente examines his notes during the Lesser-Known Candidates Forum. Image: Marc Nozell.</caption></figure></p>
<p>Despite this type of treatment, I have successfully qualified to participate in the primaries and caucuses in a combination of 48 states and territories. I have also already amassed more votes than former Senator <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Rick_Santorum">Rick Santorum</ref>, current Senator <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lindsey_Graham">Lindsey Graham</ref>, former Governor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jim%20Gilmore">Jim Gilmore</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Virginia">Virginia</ref>, former New York Governor <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/George_Pataki">George Pataki</ref> and Louisiana Governor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bobby%20Jindal">Bobby Jindal</ref> combined. After <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arizona%20Democratic%20primary,%202016">Arizona</ref>, I passed <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Carly_Fiorina">Carly Fiorina</ref>'s vote total and I'm rapidly closing in on former Governor <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mike_Huckabee">Mike Huckabee</ref>'s, current Governor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chris%20Christie">Chris Christie</ref>'s and current Senator <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rand%20Paul">Rand Paul</ref>'s vote totals.</p></p>
<p>While those candidates have suspended their campaigns, an independent <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NPR">NPR</ref> article recently noted my performance as somewhat of a phenomenon given that my campaign is predominantly self-funded and enjoys absolutely zero Party support or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Super%20PAC">Super PAC</ref> money. Conversely, these candidates all received massive support from the Republican Party in terms of the visibility and support they were given. Most also have benefited from the monetary support of conservative Super PACs.</p>
<p>I'm not sharing this information to brag but rather to provide a context for how the Parties have insulated themselves with a set of rules that preclude legitimate candidates such as me from having an equal opportunity to be heard and have an impact. Why not let the People choose?</p>
</text>
