<text id="autogum_academic_doc300" title="The Indentation-Induced Pop-in Phenomenon and Fracture Behaviors of GaP(100) Single-Crystal" shortTile="indentationinduced" author="Yi-Jui Chiu, Sheng-Rui Jian, Jyh-Wei Lee, Jenh-Yih Juang" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-666X/10/11/752/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The III–V zincblende GaP is one of the most widely utilized substrates for fabricating various semiconducting and magnetic thin films. From the viewpoint of device applications, it is thus of crucial importance to fully recognize the response of substrates due to mechanical stresses introduced during fabrication processes, which might cause the contact-induced damage and cracking. Accordingly, in order to implementing the important functional components of the devices on the GaP substrates, an accurate measurement of its mechanical characteristics is highly demanded. </p>

<p>Nanoindentation has been proved to be a powerful tool for studying the fundamental mechanical properties (for instance, the hardness and Young’s modulus) of various nanostructured materials, biomaterials, and thin films. Combining the nanoindentation with microscopic techniques, the nanoindentation-induced shear band formation in bulk metallic glasses, dislocation nucleation in GaN films, and phase transition in single-crystals Si and Ge had been extensively investigated to reveal the underlying mechanisms in great detail. For instance, it was indicated that in many nanoindentation measurements, the materials often exhibits a characteristic feature called the “pop-in” event characterized by a sudden displacement burst at a nearly constant indentation load, which acts as a trigger signifying the onset of plastic deformation. On the other hand, the “pop-in” behaviors have been attributed otherwise to the crack nucleation and the delamination phenomena. In some cases, it has been also interpreted as the manifestations of the dislocation activity depending strongly on the crystal structure of the test materials, temperature, the shape of indenter tip and indenter angle. Furthermore, the correlations between pop-in behaviors and dislocation activities of materials have been widely studied by combining microstructural observations with the cross-sectional transmission electron microscopy in recent years. </p>

<p>For the nanoindentation responses, the single “pop-in” behavior is often observed in the zincblende-structured, such as GaAs and InP single-crystals. Whereas the multiple “pop-ins” has been ubiquitously identified in the hexagonal-structured materials, such as GaN thin films and ZnO single-crystal. However, although pop-in phenomenon in the loading segment was cited in the zincblende-structured GaP single-crystal, the features were not as apparent, presumably due to the sensitivity of testing module used in their indentation measurements was force module, which often resulted in serrated loading curve and blurred the feature of pop-in events. Herein, in this study, the mechanical properties and indentation-induced deformation behaviors of GaP(100) single-crystal were investigated by using continuous stiffness measurements (CSM) nanoindentation module to unveil the fundamental aspects of plasticity and mechanisms of local dislocation activities. Using the classical dislocation theory, we also estimated the number of indentation-induced dislocation loops formed at the initial stage of nanoscale deformation in GaP(100) single-crystal. Moreover, the Vickers indentation-induced fracture behaviors and mechanisms of GaP(100) single-crystal will be discussed, as well. </p>
</text>
