<text id="autogum_academic_doc486" title="Immune-Inflammatory Responses in Atherosclerosis: The Role of Myeloid Cells" shortTile="immuneinflammatory" author="Dimitry  A. Chistiakov, Dmitry  A. Kashirskikh, Victoriya  A. Khotina, Andrey  V. Grechko, Alexander  N. Orekhov" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2077-0383/8/11/1798/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Atherosclerosis is a common pathology that affects large and medium arteries leading to a variety of cardiovascular events that can also be fatal, therefore representing a serious public health problem. Atherosclerosis is characterized by progressive lipid deposition in the arterial wall, plaque induction and possible further progression to the state of so-called unstable plaque. Advanced plaques usually acquire a fibrous cap that separates the plaque from the surrounding milieu and plays a stabilizing role. Destabilization of plaques leads to their rupture with subsequent thrombus formation that can lead to dangerous events such as acute coronary syndrome (ACS) and stroke. Advanced complicated plaques are also characterized by the formation of the necrotic core, pathological vascular remodeling, plaque neovascularization and calcification. </p>

<p>Elevated low-density lipoprotein (LDL) is known to be associated with atherosclerosis and is identified as the major source of lipids accumulating in atherosclerotic plaques. Circulating modified LDL has increased atherogenicity in comparison to native LDL. Chemical modification of LDL likely plays a prominent role in atherosclerosis development. Besides elevated LDL, chronic inflammation is now considered as another crucial pro-atherogenic mechanism that can even precede lipid entry into the arterial intima.  </p>

<p>It has been proposed that disturbances of hemodynamic forces that are especially likely to occur at atheroprone sites of blood vessels, such as bends or bifurcations, can cause local activation of endothelial cells (ECs). Consequently, ECs acquire a pro-inflammatory phenotype and start expressing different pro-inflammatory molecules, such as monocyte chemotactic protein 1 (MCP1) (also known as chemokine (C-C motif) ligand 2; CCL2), intercellular adhesion molecule 1 (ICAM-1) and vascular cell adhesion molecule 1 (VCAM-1), all of which attract monocytes to the activated endothelium. The imbalance of monocyte/macrophage polarization towards the preferential pro-inflammatory phenotype and a lack of normal inflammation resolution are also present in atherosclerosis. Phagocytic macrophages actively participate in lipid accumulation by engulfing lipid droplets and give rise to foam cells. Dendritic cells (DCs) contribute to the local inflammatory response through antigen presentation and cytokine signaling processes. If the inflammatory process reaches a resolution, repair processes begin, and the plaque can become stable. However, failure to resolve the inflammatory response can result in the formation of the most dangerous unstable plaque that can cause thrombosis. </p>

<p>Therefore, a variety of immune cells are involved in atherosclerosis initiation and progression. In this review, we consider main subsets of pro- and anti-inflammatory immune cells of myeloid origin that contribute to atherogenesis. </p>
</text>
