<text id="autogum_whow_doc390" title="Paint over Silicone Caulk" shortTile="paint-over-silicone" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-10-30" dateModified="2019-10-31" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Paint-over-Silicone-Caulk" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Paint over Silicone Caulk</head><p>Silicone caulk is tricky to paint over because the paint just beads up and doesn’t stick to the surface well to cover it up. This is a nuisance if you want to do something like repaint a wall where silicone has been used to fill gaps between the wall and trim, for example. However, don’t give up just yet, there are a couple of different ways you can paint over silicone caulk. Prime the caulk with a shellac spray and paint over it for a quick and easy option that can be painted over after about an hour. Remove the caulk altogether and replace it with paintable silicone caulk or cover it up carefully with a new layer of paintable silicone caulk if you have the time.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Priming with a Shellac Spray</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Purchase a can of shellac spray primer. Go to a home improvement center or paint shop and look for the spray cans of primer. Buy a can that says it is a shellac spray primer for any surface.
<list type="unordered"><item>Shellac spray primer will stick to just about anything, so it is the best primer to use to cover up silicone caulk to get it ready to paint over.</item></list></item>
<item>Shake the can up and down 10-12 times to mix it well. Take the lid off the can of primer. Hold the can tightly in your hand and shake it vigorously up and down at least 10 times to mix it up thoroughly.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you don’t shake up the primer to mix it, it won’t stick to the silicone caulk well.</item></list></item>
<item>Spray over the caulk you want to paint over in small bursts. Point the spray nozzle of the can at the silicone caulk, holding it about  away. Press down the cap and release it to shoot short bursts of the primer onto the caulk, working your way along it, until you have completely covered it.
<list type="unordered"><item>If there is anything around the caulk that you don’t plan on painting over later, cover it with blue painter’s tape so you don’t get primer on it.</item></list></item>
<item>Wait 45 minutes for the shellac primer to dry. Let the primer dry for at least 45 minutes so it is ready to receive a coat of paint. Get your paint ready during this time if you want to.
<list type="unordered"><item>Double-check the instructions on the can of primer you bought to see what the drying time is. Most shellac primers are ready to be recoated in 45 minutes or less, but different brands might have different wait times.</item></list></item>
<item>Paint over the primed area with the paint of your choice. Apply 1-2 coats of whatever paint you want to use on top of the primed silicone caulk. Any kind of paint can be applied over shellac primer, such as latex or oil-based paints.
<list type="unordered"><item>You typically only need 1 coat of paint to cover up the shellac primer. However, if you let the first coat dry and can still see the primer underneath, apply a second coat.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Using Paintable Caulk</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Buy a tube of paintable silicone caulk. Go to a hardware store or home improvement center and look for the caulk. Purchase a tube of silicone caulk that says it is paintable.{{greenbox: <hi rend="bold">Tip</hi>: If you want to use paintable silicone caulk, the best way to do so is to remove the old caulk and start over. However, if you are short on time you can also try carefully applying a new layer of paintable caulk over the existing non-paintable one.}}
<list type="unordered"><item>You will also need a caulking gun to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Caulk">apply the caulk</ref>. If you don’t already have one, you can buy one at the same store you purchase the caulk from.</item></list></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Remove_Silicone_Caulking">Remove the silicone caulk</ref> that is already there if you can. Use a silicone caulk remover and putty knife to get rid of the existing caulk if you have the time. It will be easiest to apply new silicone caulk if the area is totally free of the <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Remove_Old_Caulking">old caulk</ref>.
<list type="unordered"><item>Caulk remover softens the caulk so it is easier to scrape out. You can buy it at the same store you purchased the paintable caulk at.</item></list></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Use_a_Caulking_Gun">Use a caulking gun</ref> to apply a new bead of paintable silicone caulk. Cut the tip of the tube of paintable caulk off and put it in your caulking gun. Aim the tip at the beginning of the crack you want to refill. Gently squeeze the trigger of the caulking gun while slowly dragging the tip along the crack to apply an even bead.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you don’t have steady hands, you can put painter’s tape on either side of the crack and pull it up as soon as you are done caulking so you are left with an even bead.</item></list></item>
<item>Apply a thin bead of paintable silicone caulk over the old caulk as an alternative. Clean the surface with rubbing alcohol first to remove any oils. Apply a new bead of the paintable silicone caulk over top of the old caulk that is slightly wider so it sticks to the clean surfaces on either side.
<list type="unordered"><item>It’s important to make the new bead wider than the old one or it will not stick. Nothing sticks well to silicone, not even more silicone.</item></list></item>
<item>Wait 24 hours before painting over the new caulk. Let the paintable caulk dry for at least 24 hours so it is fully cured and ready to paint. Paint over it with the paint of your choice.
<list type="unordered"><item>Double-check the instructions on the tube of paintable caulk you purchased. Most caulk dries fully within 24 hours, but always defer to the manufacturer’s instructions.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Things You’ll Need</head>
<head>Priming with a Shellac Spray</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Shellac spray primer</item>
<item>Paint</item>
<item>Painter’s tape (optional)</item></list>
<head>Using Paintable Caulk</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Silicone caulk remover</item>
<item>Putty knife</item>
<item>Caulking gun</item>
<item>Paintable silicone caulk</item>
<item>Paint</item>
<item>Painter’s tape (optional)</item></list>
</text>
