<text id="autogum_reddit_doc027" title="I have a warrant for not doing my community service, terrified I’ll go to jail if I go to court. Thoughts?" shortTile="warrant-doing-community" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-05-31" dateModified="2018-05-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8nnads" speakerList="#crookiesandfilth, #maddomesticscientist" speakerCount="2">
<head>I have a warrant for not doing my community service, terrified I’ll go to jail if I go to court. Thoughts?</head>
<sp who="#crookiesandfilth">
<p>So first, I’ve never been to jail, and I’ve never had any serious charges on my record, just a few speeding tickets here and there. About 2 years ago, I was pulled over for speeding, the cop said he car smelled like marijuana and I consented to a search (I had no idea at the time I could have said no). I let him know there was a marijuana bowl in the glove box. I ended up getting a ticket for it (possession of drug paraphernalia, which looks so much worse on paper). At court, they said I was required to do community service. I did a few hours at a place in my city, but received no guidance on the job and was just expected to know what I was doing. I ended up not finishing my 40 hours. I went back to court and they gave me an extension. I called some places and most of them didn’t take community service, only volunteers (makes no sense). So I got another extension. Then I had a lot of life stuff happen, and didn’t do it again. Now I have a warrant bc it was never completed so I will have to go in front of a judge again. I have generalized anxiety disorder and am absolutely terrified I will go to jail so I keep continuing to put it off. Will I go to jail? I honestly would just like to plead guilty and pay the fine, I know it will be on my record and all of that but I just want to move on so I don’t have to keep dealing with the court system.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#maddomesticscientist">
<p>You might get lucky. Might. I doubt it but you never know. I've seen luckier things happen during my criminal years. It tends to piss them off if they give you multiple chances to do your community service and you keep not doing it. I can tell you that from experience. I got sentenced to a year in jail myself for it. I only had to serve 3 months of that though. Out of all the shenanigans I pulled that should have landed me in jail, blowing off the community service is what got me. </p>
<p>You may want to get your stuff in order before you go to court and prepare for the worst. </p>
</sp>
</text>
