<text id="autogum_voyage_doc424" title="Penticton" shortTile="penticton" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=27239" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Penticton</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.penticton.ca/">Penticton</ref></hi> (The 'Peach City') is a beautiful spot in the south <ref target="Okanagan">Okanagan</ref> nestled between two lakes: The 155-km-long Okanagan Lake to the north, and the smaller Skaha Lake to the south. Tourism in Penticton is largely seasonal. In the summer tourists double Penticton's population to 60,000. In the winter things used to be very quiet, but now that World Cup Freestyle Skiing stops at local Apex Mountain every winter, the winter scene is picking up.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>This area has been inhabited for thousands of years by the Salish group of <hi rend="bold">First Nations</hi> people. They called their settlement in this area <hi rend="italic">Snpinkten</hi> which translates as 'a place to stay forever' and gives Penticton its name. The first non-native settler Thomas Ellis preempted land in Penticton in 1869 and started a very successful cattle ranch. With the arrival of engineering marvel <hi rend="bold">Kettle Valley Railway</hi> the boom in Penticton had begun. Penticton became a municipality in 1908, and a city in 1948.</p>

<p>Penticton's climate is well suited for agriculture, and thousands of fruit trees were planted all along the west and east bench areas overlooking Okanagan Lake. From cherries in early July to apples and pears in early September, Penticton has always been a large producer and exporter of non-citrus tree fruit. Many local oldtimers decry the trend of ripping out perfectly healthy and productive <hi rend="bold">orchards</hi> for the more lucrative vineyards which supply grapes for the regions more than thirty <hi rend="bold">boutique wineries</hi>. Today Penticton's two largest industries are tourism and the growing wine industry, which threatens to eclipse the fruit production industry.</p>

<p>Penticton's climate and geography is a northern, four-seasons version of what some call <hi rend="bold">Mediterranean</hi>. Large clay banks, benches, and scrubland skirt the mid-level mountains that frame the valley on the east and west sides. Summers are hot with an average temperature of 27°C, and peaks of 35-40°C are not unheard of. The large size of Okanagan Lake tempers the climate in winter which sees an average high of 0.9°C in January. It can and does snow occasionally, but generally only during December and January will it accumulate in modest quantities. You can check the snow level with a quick glance to the mountains, which will have a white apron about half to three-quarters of the way up. Penticton gets about 2000 hours of sun per year, which is a higher average than <ref target="Rio%20de%20Janeiro_%28city%29">Rio de Janeiro</ref>.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>Most travellers will arrive in Penticton by automobile. Highway 97 is the major north-south route through the city. Travel times are about 4 hours from <ref target="Vancouver">Vancouver</ref>, 8 hours from <ref target="Calgary">Calgary</ref> and 5 hours from <ref target="Seattle">Seattle</ref> or <ref target="Spokane">Spokane</ref>. Penticton is a 40-minute drive south from <ref target="Kelowna">Kelowna</ref>. The US/Canada border crossing to the south on Highway 97 is open 24 hours a day; other border crossings in this region are closed overnight.</p>

<head>By bus</head>

<p>BC Transit operates <ref target="https://bctransit.com/south-okanagan-similkameen/schedules-and-maps/route-overview%3Froute%3D60">Route 60</ref> which runs once in each direction between Osoyoos and Kelowna, stopping in Penticton, on weekdays.</p>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Penticton Regional Airport</hi> ( YYF ). Is a small airport with domestic flights from <ref target="Vancouver">Vancouver</ref>. It is at the south end of town off Hwy 97. U.S. and some international flights will land in <ref target="Kelowna">Kelowna</ref>, 60 km to the north. Most international flights will land in Vancouver where an alternate mode of transportation will be needed to reach Penticton. There are no scheduled commercial flights between Kelowna and Penticton; however, you may charter a flight with <ref target="http://www.carsonair.com/">Carson Air</ref> or <ref target="http://www.southernskies.ca/">Southern Skies</ref>.</item>
</list>




<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.aircanada.ca">Air Canada Express</ref></hi> provides air service to Vancouver.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Southern Skies Aviation</hi>, Penticton Airport, ☏ +1 250 492-0074 . provides aircraft charters for transportation and sightseeing</item>
</list>



<head>By car</head>

<p>This is your best bet if you wish to visit the area's many wineries, which are generally out of town a ways. Car rentals:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Best Choice Car Rentals</hi>, 249 Westminster Ave., ☏ +1 250 490-3339 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.bcbudget.com">Budget Car and Truck Rentals</ref></hi>, two locations: 188 Westminster Ave West, Penticton Airport, +1 250 493-0212.</item>
</list>


<head>By bus</head>
<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.busonline.ca/regions/pen/%3Fp%3D2.txt">BC Transit</ref></hi> operates a local bus service in Penticton with five regular routes and a night route. Service ends at 7PM for regular routes and 10PM for the night route. There is no service on Sundays except for the <hi rend="bold">Lake-to-lake</hi> shuttle. Fares are $1.75 which includes a 90-minute transfer. Ask the operator, as they generally will not offer one.</p>

<head>By taxi</head>
<p>Penticton has two cab companies, Courtesy Taxi (☏ +1 250-492-7777 ) and <ref target="http://www.klassickabs.ca">Klassic Taxi</ref> (☏ +1 250-492-6666 ), who run computerized dispatch. Both companies provide luxury cars and six passenger vans. They also recently introduced the wheelchair vans.</p>

<head>On foot and bike</head>
<p>Penticton's compact size lends itself to biking or even just walking around. It will take about 15 minutes to bike from lake to lake, and just over an hour for the same journey on foot. There are walking and biking trails on both sides of the River Channel, and a painted bike lane on a major north-south corridor of the city.</p>

<p>Bike rentals:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="http://www.bikebarn.ca"><hi rend="bold">Bike Barn</hi></ref>, 300 Westminster Ave, +1 250 492-4140. <hi rend="italic">$35/day</hi>.</item>
<item> <ref target="http://www.freedombikeshop.com"><hi rend="bold">Freedom the Bike Shop</hi></ref>, 533 Main Street, +1 250 493-0686. <hi rend="italic">from $40/day</hi>.</item>
</list>


<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Leir House Cultural Centre</hi>, 220 Manor Park Ave, ☏ +1 250 492-7997 . 10AM-4PM. This beautiful 1927 house was once a nurses' residence but now serves as the home of the Penticton Arts Council. Open to the public year round. Worth a visit to see the grounds, with vintage stone walls and a relaxing gazebo. Free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Munson Mountain Park</hi>, Munson Mountain Rd (from town, head east on Vancouver Ave and follow the signs). The home to the large 'Penticton' sign (a la 'Hollywood') that greets travelers coming in to town from the north. The sign was created with thousands of small white stones. The original stones have since been replaced with letters made of concrete. The park itself affords visitors with stunning 360 degree panoramas of the South Okanagan valley. Views to the south are accessed by an easy paved trail to the lookout. The panoramic views require walking up the hill, but there are plenty of benches to rest at and take in the view.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Penticton Art Gallery</hi> (formerly the Art Gallery of the South Okanagan), 199 Marina Way, ☏ +1 250 493-2928 . Tu-F 10AM-5PM, Sa-Su 11AM-4PM. Contains a modest permanent collection of work by local and area artists as well as <hi rend="bold">bone carvings</hi> by traditional Inuit artists. Also features moving exhibits and other special events. $2 for adults Tu-F, free otherwise.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Penticton Museum &amp; Archives</hi>, 785 Main St, ☏ +1 250 490-2451 . Tu-Sa 10AM-5PM. Features over 8000 artifacts, photographs, and documents that tell the story of Penticton's pioneers days, as well as local First Nations pieces. Located in the same building as the Penticton Regional Library. There is a gift shop on site. Suggested donation $2.</item>
<item> The <hi rend="bold">Penticton Roundabout</hi> (junction of Front Street, Ellis Street, Marina Way, and Vancouver Hill) features changing art installations. A work nicknamed <hi rend="italic">Frank</hi> (actually called <hi rend="italic">The Baggage Handler</hi>) was moved because of vandalism and controversy with local puritans due to the anatomical correctness of the piece. Today you can see <hi rend="italic">Frank</hi> at his permanent home at <hi rend="bold">Red Rooster Winery</hi>, and the roundabout has a less contentious piece.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">S.S. Sicamous</hi>, 1099 Lakeshore Dr West (the west end of Lakeshore Drive), ☏ +1 250 492-0403 , ✉ mail@sssicamous.com . 9AM-9PM in high summer, shorter hours at other seasons. This paddlewheeler was the last commercial ship to operate on Okanagan Lake. Built in 1914 and retired in 1936, the large ship now spends its days drydocked on the edge of Okanagan Lake. The ship is open daily for tours in the summer, and includes a large HO scale model railway on the main deck, depicting the local Kettle Valley Railway. The smaller <hi rend="italic">S.S. Naramata</hi> rests just behind the Sicamous. Adults $6, seniors and youth $4.50, children 7-13 $3.50, children 6 and under free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Peach</hi>, foot of Winnipeg St on Okanagan Lake. A concession stand shaped and painted as a giant peach. While it isn't that interesting in and of itself, it has an interesting history and is one of the most photographed spots in town. Film buffs may recognize it from the movie <hi rend="italic">My American Cousin</hi> which was filmed in the Penticton Area. This is the second Peach, as the first was pushed into the lake during the 1990 <hi rend="bold">Peachfest</hi> riot (The riot was an isolated incident, Penticton is really quite safe.)</item>
</list>
</text>
