<text id="autogum_whow_doc415" title="Have a Memorable Birthday" shortTile="memorable-birthday" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-10-20" dateModified="2019-07-09" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Have-a-Memorable-Birthday" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Have a Memorable Birthday</head><p>Everybody hopes to have a memorable birthday, so why not make that a reality? After all, our birthday memories tend to hold a special place in our hearts. Want to make your upcoming birthday something you can look back on with fondness? You can easily make that dream come true. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Choosing the Perfect Destination</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Choose a site in nature. For making your birthday a memorable one, you need to do something different. Start with a perfect place where you can celebrate! Try choosing a beautiful hill station, or a station by the side of the waterfalls, which will completely change and cheer up your mood, and a place where you can enjoy the eternal beauty of nature. By celebrating your birthday there, you will get the completely awesome experience that you want to have! <figure rend="Have a Memorable Birthday Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Throwing a party at a restaurant is another common way that we choose to celebrate our birthdays. Thus, we get the same experience. By having a change in the way of celebration, you get a different experience and perhaps a memorable one! <figure rend="Have a Memorable Birthday Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Decide on the place at least 20 days before your birthday event, so that you get enough time for other preparations. <figure rend="Have a Memorable Birthday Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Avoid party halls. Maybe you have decided on the place (say a hill station) and you are celebrating there at a restaurant. Don't celebrate there in the party hall! Choose a place from where you can see the picturesque scenes of nature. Remember that fun and enjoyment, in your unique celebration, is linked with nature, so make sure you aren't celebrating away from it. <figure rend="Have a Memorable Birthday Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Many restaurants have such arrangements where you can enjoy the nature too, along with your celebration. <figure rend="Have a Memorable Birthday Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Although you will go at a perfect natural destination, celebrating at a party hall won't give you the different experience that you want to have. Keep this in mind when deciding on a destination. <figure rend="Have a Memorable Birthday Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Decide on the right time. If you like to celebrate at night, you may go with that. Usually, people like to celebrate their birthday at night, but if you want to have something different, go with a party in the daytime.  <figure rend="Have a Memorable Birthday Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Giving Out Invitations</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Decide whom to invite. Usually, we prefer to invite our friends and family. In order to have a good and quality time with everybody, choose to invite only the people who can make you happy and comfortable. <figure rend="Have a Memorable Birthday Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Inviting someone just for the sake of formality doesn't work. The only person who is concerned about your birthday is you, so invite only those whom you really want to have with you on your birthday. Inviting people unwillingly will just spoil your mood and you won't be able to enjoy anything. <figure rend="Have a Memorable Birthday Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Create a card. By using a card rather than inviting people via the phone or email, you can have beautifully illustrated cards that will entice people to join you in your celebration. <figure rend="Have a Memorable Birthday Step 10.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Decorating and Getting Food</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Set up a daytime party. Since you are celebrating at a natural destination, you don't need much decoration. Your background should already be full of beauties of nature! If you want to give off a birthday feeling, you can use balloons of your favorite colors, but don't just stick them anywhere. You can just fly them in the sky (use balloons that fly high in the sky). You will really enjoy it, and your party guests will also love the scenes and will ultimately enjoy it. <figure rend="Have a Memorable Birthday Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Set up a nighttime party. You can use beautiful night lamps, lanterns, or balloons that light up. Again, don't stick them in the sky; let them fly in the sky and enjoy the lovely scene! <figure rend="Have a Memorable Birthday Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Choose a different dish. Choose a dish that is new, and something that everybody will love to have. You can have a wide variety of dishes and delicacies! <figure rend="Have a Memorable Birthday Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure that you have something sweet and delicious to serve. For example, you can have the yummy and delicious Italian Gelato that will add sweetness to everything! <figure rend="Have a Memorable Birthday Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you have decided to have some games for fun, then don't plan a heavy dish. If you do, nobody will want to play the games after having food. In that case, you can have light snacks. <figure rend="Have a Memorable Birthday Step 15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Add a cake and candles. A birthday is incomplete without cake and candles! Have a printed cake that would attract everybody's attention to the cake. Have a flavor that everybody will certainly enjoy. Have different candles that will probably catch everybody's attention. <figure rend="Have a Memorable Birthday Step 16.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do a good deed. Try distributing your old toys and clothes among the children of an orphanage, or any other random act of kindness. By doing this, you will really get that satisfaction and peace that one gets after doing an act like this. <figure rend="Have a Memorable Birthday Step 17.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you have an environment-friendly nature, then plant trees and help save the environment. <figure rend="Have a Memorable Birthday Step 18.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remember that happiness increases when you make others happy! <figure rend="Have a Memorable Birthday Step 19.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure that your arrangements and ways are decided at least five days before your birthday.</item>
<item>Believe in doing something different and you will surely love the change!</item>
<item>Make others happy on your birthday and you will ultimately be happy yourself!</item>
<item>Enjoy everything and don't be sad if you miss  out on anything.</item></list>
</text>
