<text id="autogum_interview_doc295" title="part1_Shimon Peres discusses the future of Israel" shortTile="partshimon-peres" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-01-06" dateModified="2013-08-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Shimon_Peres_discusses_the_future_of_Israel" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Below is <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref>'s interview with Shimon Peres, the President of Israel.</p>
<head id="Israeli_technology">Israeli technology</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">David Shankbone: One of your big initiatives in technology has been <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nanotechnology">nanotechnology</ref>.  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">President Shimon Peres</hi>: Yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: What made you focus on nanotechnology as a sector for Israeli investment?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: Well, nanotechnology is not a vocation but a dimension.  It’s a new dimension and it <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List%20of%20nanotechnology%20applications">concerns all walks of life</ref>, not limited to one, from the military to the civilian.  Everywhere you turn around you can see the eventual effect of nano.  It also raises some of the most complicated moral issues because until now the human race knew how to build.  It didn’t know how to grow.  What we did is collected wood and stones and steel and glass and we built from up to down.  Structure.  Now, what is common to both building a structure is the smallest particular, the nanometer.  The minute you can manage it, you can begin to make things grow.  And that’s a tremendous change; it is also a tremendous dilemma for humanity.  Now actually, like on many other occasions, we discover the nano from the negative side.  The bomb.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: The bomb?</hi></p>
<figure><caption>The now disused Koffler <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Particle%20accelerator">particle accelerator</ref> at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Weitzmann%20Institute">Weitzmann Institute</ref>, one of Israel's most accomplished institutions of higher learning in the sciences.Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: Yes.  The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuclear%20bomb">nuclear bomb</ref>.  The nuclear bomb was to release the hidden powers of a combination or dispersion of nanostructures.  The minute you dismantle an existing structure, then you create a lot of energy and you create new dimensions and new measurements.  I mean the size has nothing to do with power.  You can, say, take a nuclear bomb where the core is six or seven kilos of plutonium and you can destroy a city.  Why can’t you build a city with the six kilos?  Same story. And the answer is clear.  It was easier to destroy because then you don’t have to control the nanostructure.  It’s simple when you want explosions; then, fission or fusion does not matter.  The minute you want to build, you have to control the nano, and for a very long time we couldn’t, we weren’t able to see the nano, it is so small.  No microscope could grasp it.  The size of a nano is like 1/100th of a single hair, which is unbelievable.  Or if you want to, to compare the nanometer with the meter is to compare an orange to the globe.  Same proportion.  That’s nothing.  And the minute they discovered the microscope, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electronic%20microscope">electronic microscope</ref> that can see the nanostructure, we can begin to build.  And to build with materials and powers and combinations that we weren’t aware of.  And then you can create a lot of things, like I said, on the military side.  But  it doesn’t make sense to chase it in modern warfare.  It’s not armies against armies.  It’s strength against, the strength of a collective army against the strength of an individual terrorist.  It does not make sense to take an F-16 that costs $40-50 million and chase a terrorist.  Nano enables you to miniaturize everything.</p>
</text>
