<text id="autogum_news_doc324" title="After visa snags, all-girl Afghan team honored for &apos;courageous achievement&apos; at international robotics competition" shortTile="visa-snags-girl-afghan" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-07-18" dateModified="2017-08-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/After_visa_snags%2C_all-girl_Afghan_team_honored_for_%27courageous_achievement%27_at_international_robotics_competition" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>After visa snags, all-girl Afghan team honored for 'courageous achievement' at international robotics competition</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday, July 21, 2017</hi> </p>
<p>A group of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Afghanistan">Afghan</ref> teenagers was awarded a silver medal for "courageous achievement" on Tuesday in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/For%20Inspiration%20and%20Recognition%20of%20Science%20and%20Technology">FIRST</ref> Global Challenge <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Robotics">Robot</ref> Olympics in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daughters%20of%20the%20American%20Revolution%20Constitution%20Hall">Daughters of the American Revolution Constitution Hall</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Washington_D.C.">Washington D.C.</ref> The six-member Afghan team, which consists entirely of girls, had been denied visas to enter the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> until last week, drawing notice from critics of U.S. President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Donald_Trump">Donald Trump</ref>'s policies regarding <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Islam">Muslims</ref> traveling to the U.S. The President later personally took action to allow the team into the country.</p>
<p>According to Afghan Ambassador to the United States <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hamdullah%20Mohib">Hamdullah Mohib</ref>, the participation of this team in this science competition shows progress in Afghanistan's response to nearly <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War%20in%20Afghanistan%20(2001–14)">two decades of military conflict</ref>.</p>
<figure><caption>The first FIRST Global robotics competition was held this week in Washington D.C. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Navy">United States Navy</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>The FIRST Global competition (For Inspiration and Recognition of Science and Technlogy) was founded by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dean%20Kamen">Dean Kamen</ref> to encourage interest in applied science, technology, engineering, and mathematics in young people.  This year's theme was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/water%20security">water security</ref>.  For the contest, the robots were required to recognize, pick up, carry, and deposit balls colored blue and orange to represent water and pollution, respectively.  Teams from different countries were arranged in groups of three, and groups faced off in pairs.  The group whose three robots collectively earned the most points won that match.  According to the Afghan team's coach, Alireza Mehraban, in their first matchup, the Afghan team's robot, named "Better Idea of Afghan Girls," scored one or two points for the three-nation alliance with the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gabon">Gabonese</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Estonia">Estonian</ref> teams. This year, the European team won the competition overall, with the silver medal going to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Poland">Poland</ref> and the bronze to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Armenia">Armenia</ref>.</p>
<p>"We are so interested because we find a big chance to show the talent and ability of Afghans," team member Rodaba Noori told the press, "to show that Afghan women can make robots too and we can improve in this section — [the] robotics section.  We were so interested because we hadn't long or enough time to get ready for competition but we came to United States and now we are here because of Trump intervention."</p>
<p>The team arrived in Washington D.C. after many difficulties.  They were twice denied visas to enter the United States.  Even applying for a visa required the entire team to travel about 500 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/mile">miles</ref> (800 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/kilometre">km</ref>) from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herat">Herat</ref>, their home, to the capital in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kabul">Kabul</ref>, through territory controlled by the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Taliban">Taliban</ref>.  They made the trip twice and were turned down both times. President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Donald_Trump">Donald Trump</ref> personally asked the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20National%20Security%20Council">United States National Security Council</ref> to help the girls enter the country. After some interplay between the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/US%20State%20Department">State</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/US%20Department%20of%20Homeland%20Security">Homeland Security</ref> Departments, the girls were granted "parole" status on the grounds that their entry would be a "significant public benefit." The President has drawn both praise for helping the girls enter the U.S. and criticism for his travel ban, which does not cover Afghanistan, and for the atmosphere of hostility toward <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Islam">Muslims</ref> that critics blame for denying them entry in the first place.</p>
<p>Citing privacy rules, U.S. officials have not said why the team was initially denied visas, but Afghan Ambassador <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hamdullah%20Mohib">Hamdullah Mohib</ref> says there were concerns they would attempt to remain in the United States or in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada">Canada</ref> after the contest.   Afghanistan is not one of the nations covered by President Trump's travel ban, but teams from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sudan">Sudan</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iran">Iran</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Libya">Libya</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Yemen">Yemen</ref>, which are covered, are among the 163 teams in the competition. There were also two <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Syria">Syrian</ref> teams scheduled to compete, one national and one made up of refugees. Syria and all refugees are covered by the ban. The Syrian refugee team listed their country as "Hope" on the backs of their shirts and named their robot "Robogee." Teams from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Morocco">Morocco</ref> and Iran both had difficulties getting themselves or their robots across the U.S. border. Team Estonia had to rebuild their robot entirely after the original disappeared in transit.</p>
<p>"Seventeen years ago, this would not have been possible at all," said Ambassador Mohib. "They represent our aspirations and resilience despite having been brought up in a perpetual conflict. These girls will be proving to the world and the nation that nothing will prevent us from being an equal and active member of the international community."</p>
<p>Every team in the contest was sent a collection of robot parts roughly four months in advance of the competition.  The Afghan team's supplies were delayed, leaving them only two weeks left to assemble their robot and only one day to test it before packing it up to mail to the competition site.</p>
<p>The competition ended on Tuesday. This is the first FIRST Global competition, and the organization plans to hold the contest in a different country every year. Next year's competition is scheduled to take place in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mexico_City">Mexico City</ref>.</p>
</text>
