<text id="autogum_interview_doc695" title="part3_RuPaul speaks about society and the state of drag as performance art" shortTile="partrupaul-speaks" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-06" dateModified="2019-02-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/RuPaul_speaks_about_society_and_the_state_of_drag_as_performance_art" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Has the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraq%20War">Iraq War</ref> affected you at all?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RP:</hi>  Absolutely.  It’s not good, I don’t like it, and it makes me want to enjoy this moment a lot more and be very appreciative.  Like when I’m on a hike in a canyon and it smells good and there aren’t bombs dropping.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think there is a lot of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/apathy">apathy</ref> in the culture?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RP:</hi>  There’s apathy, and there’s a lot of anti-depressants and that probably lends a big contribution to the apathy.  We have <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/iPods">iPods</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GPS">GPS</ref> systems and all these things to distract us.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you ever work the current political culture into your art?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RP:</hi>  No, I don’t.  Every time I bat my eyelashes it’s a political statement. The drag I come from has always been a critique of our society, so the act is defiant in and of itself in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/patriarchy">patriarchal</ref> society such as ours.  It’s an act of treason.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do you think of young performance artists working in drag today?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RP:</hi>  I don’t know of any.  I don’t know of any.  Because the gay culture is obsessed with everything straight and femininity has been under attack for so many years, there aren’t any up and coming drag artists.  Gay culture isn’t paying attention to it, and straight people don’t either.  There aren’t any drag clubs to go to in New York.  I see more drag clubs in Los Angeles than in New York, which is so odd because L.A. has never been about club culture.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/An_interview_with_gossip_columnist_Michael_Musto_on_the_art_of_celebrity_journalism">Michael Musto told me</ref> something that was opposite of what you said.  He said he felt that the younger gays, the ones who are up-and-coming, are over the body fascism and more willing to embrace their feminine sides.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RP:</hi>  I think they are redefining what femininity is, but I still think there is a lot of negativity associated with true femininity.  Do boys wear eyeliner and dress in skinny jeans now?  Yes, they do.  But it’s still a heavily patriarchal culture and you never see two men in Star magazine, or the Queer Eye guys at a premiere, the way you see Ellen and her girlfriend—where they are all, ‘Oh, look how cute’—without a negative connotation to it.  There is a definite prejudice towards men who use femininity as part of their palette; their emotional palette, their physical palette.  Is that changing?  It’s changing in ways that don’t advance the cause of femininity.  I’m not talking frilly-laced pink things or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hello%20Kitty">Hello Kitty</ref> stuff.  I’m talking about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/goddess">goddess</ref> energy, intuition and feelings.  That is still under attack, and it has gotten worse.  That’s why you wouldn’t get someone covering the RuPaul album, or why they say people aren’t tuning into the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Katie%20Couric">Katie Couric</ref> show.  Sure, they can say ‘Oh, RuPaul’s album sucks’ and ‘Katie Couric is awful’; but that’s not really true.  It’s about what our culture finds important, and what’s important are things that support patriarchal power.  The only feminine thing supported in this struggle is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pamela%20Anderson">Pamela Anderson</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jessica%20Simpson">Jessica Simpson</ref>, things that support our patriarchal culture.</p>
</text>
