<text id="autogum_interview_doc839" title="part9_ACLU President Strossen on religion, drugs, guns and impeaching George Bush" shortTile="partaclu-president" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-30" dateModified="2019-02-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/ACLU_President_Strossen_on_religion%2C_drugs%2C_guns_and_impeaching_George_Bush" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Criminal%20justice">criminal justice system</ref> is a rehabilitative system?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  That’s not what I think it is now.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is that what it should be?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  I think the purpose of the criminal justice system should be—yeah, that would be great, if it could be done.  But its primary purpose is to promote safety, to reduce crime.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How does it do that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  Believe me, I’m not an apologist for the criminal justice system.  I think it’s in a terrible state, in part because quite a few years ago the official policy, at least at the federal level, and the states certainly seem to be in the <hi rend="italic">avant-garde</hi> on this, was to not be focused on rehabilitation but to be focused on retribution.  The federal sentencing guidelines, I believe, explicitly endorse a retributive purpose for the criminal justice system.  I disagree with that.</p>
<head id="Decriminalization_of_drugs_and_suicide">Decriminalization of drugs and suicide</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are you an active member of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NORML">NORML</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  I don’t know.  I certainly support their goals and I have spoken at their conventions.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you believe in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decriminalization%20of%20non-medicinal%20marijuana%20in%20the%20United%20States">decriminalization of marijuana</ref>?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  Absolutely, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drug%20liberalization">and everything</ref>. For adults.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Can you give me your case for that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  Sure, it’s official ACLU policy, which I wholeheartedly endorse.  I think it was well summarized by one of our board members years ago when the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crack%20epidemic">crack cocaine epidemic</ref> was starting, and somebody said we should re-examine our policy which opposed the criminalization of substances for adults.  Maybe we should re-examine it in light of this new dangerous drug.  And we did re-examine and unanimously re-affirmed.  In the course of that debate, one Board member said, “We believe that every consenting adult should have the right to imbibe, ingest, inhale or insert whatever he or she wants into his or her own body. It’s a matter of individual freedom of choice.”  Does that mean they should do it?  Not necessarily, not any more than somebody should smoke or drink or eat <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/McDonald's">McDonald’s</ref> hamburgers.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Should <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Legal%20views%20of%20suicide">suicide be legal</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  Absolutely.  The idea of government making determinations about how you end your life, forcing you, which could be considered cruel and unusual punishment in certain circumstances, and Justice Stevens in a very interesting opinion in a right-to-die raised the analogy.  But you said before you turned on the tape that you typically ask people how they would want to die, which is <hi rend="italic">very</hi> interesting.  I mean, of the zillions of questions I have been asked, nobody has ever asked me that!  It’s very rare I am asked a question that I have never been asked before.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So how would you like to die?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  Well, the first thing that occurred to me was: I want to have the choice.  That was the very first thing that occurred to me, because I know how through personal experiences, through vicarious experiences, through reading the complaints in our law suits where we have challenged the absolute restrictions on compassion and dying, people are essentially tortured.  And I don’t want that to happen.  And I don’t want my loved ones tortured by watching that happen.</p>
</text>
