<text id="autogum_whow_doc267" title="Conduct a Healthcare Risk Assessment" shortTile="conduct-healthcare" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2012-10-31" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Conduct-a-Healthcare-Risk-Assessment" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Conduct a Healthcare Risk Assessment</head><p>Covered entities under the U.S. Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA) of 1996, are health plans, healthcare clearinghouses, and any healthcare provider who transmits health information in an electronic form. Covered entities need to comply with the HIPAA Privacy and Security Rules in order to avoid penalties. One of the Security Rule’s main requirements is the performance of a risk analysis. The Security Rule stipulates that a risk analysis should be documented but it doesn’t require any specific format for it. This article will present several steps of how to conduct a proper healthcare risk assessment.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Define the Scope of the Risk Analysis. There are different types of risk analysis methods depending on its scope. The scope of the healthcare risk assessment includes the potential risks and vulnerabilities to the confidentiality, availability and integrity of all ePHI that a covered entity creates, receives, maintains, or transmits. <figure rend="Conduct a Healthcare Risk Assessment Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Gather Current Documentation. A covered entity should gather and document information on where ePHI is stored, maintained and transmitted. This can be done by checking current and past projects, auditing documents. <figure rend="Conduct a Healthcare Risk Assessment Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Identify Potential Threats and Vulnerabilities. This step is essential to determining the level of risk. All anticipated threats (natural, environmental or human) and vulnerabilities should be documented in category lists and analyzed afterwards. <figure rend="Conduct a Healthcare Risk Assessment Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Analyze Current Security Measures. All security measures that a covered entity uses to protect ePHI should be documented. Security measures can be divided into technical – related to the software and hardware in the network - and non-technical – related to management and operations. This step will reveal whether the covered entity has enough security safeguards in place. <figure rend="Conduct a Healthcare Risk Assessment Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Determine the Likelihood and Impact of Threats. The covered entity has to analyze each threat and vulnerability combination in order to determine the probability a threat can occur. The likelihood of threat occurrence can be defined as low, medium and high or can be a numeric representation. The threat impact should also be defined by using a similar rating system. <figure rend="Conduct a Healthcare Risk Assessment Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Determine the Risk Level. Make a risk level matrix using the identified likelihood and threat impact. Choose a rating system such as the low, medium and high rating system. Add an action description to each risk level, which will clarify to management what actions should be taken to prevent or minimize this risk and when. <figure rend="Conduct a Healthcare Risk Assessment Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Identify New Security Measures. After identifying the risk level, covered entities have to think what security measures need to be taken to reduce risks. When defining new security measures, it is important to take into account factors such as the measures’ effectiveness, legislative or regulatory requirements and other organization’s policies.  Like each of the previous steps, this step should also be diligently documented. <figure rend="Conduct a Healthcare Risk Assessment Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>EPHI can be found in various electronic media so covered entities should consider all forms of media containing ePHI in their analysis. Examples of such media are hard drives, floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, smart cards, personal digital assistants (PDA), transmission media, and portable electronic storage media.</item>
<item>Take into account all possible threat outcomes. The most common impacts as a result of exploited vulnerabilities are loss or corruption of ePHI, disclosure or unavailability of ePHI, loss of software or hardware inventory,and loss of reputation.</item></list>
</text>
