<text id="autogum_bio_doc563" title="John Barnewall, 3rd Baron Trimlestown" shortTile="john-barnewall-rd" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-05-30" dateModified="2019-10-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Barnewall%2C_3rd_Baron_Trimlestown" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>John Barnewall, 3rd Baron Trimlestown</head><p><hi rend="bold">John Barnewall, 3rd Baron Trimleston</hi> (died 25 July 1538), was an Irish nobleman,  judge and politician. He was the eldest son of Christopher Barnewall, 2nd <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baron_Trimlestown">Baron Trimlestown</ref> and his wife Elizabeth Plunket, daughter of Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Fitz-Christopher_Plunket">Thomas Fitz-Christopher Plunket</ref> of Rathmore,  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Chief_Justice_of_the_King's_Bench_in_Ireland">Lord Chief Justice of the King's Bench in Ireland</ref> and his second wife Marian Cruise.  He succeeded his father as 3rd Baron about 1513.</p>
<p>His ancestors came to Ireland originally with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_II_of_England">Henry II</ref> and received large grants of land in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/County_Cork">County Cork</ref>. However,  at  the first favourable opportunity the old proprietors, the O'Sullivans, rose and murdered the whole family save one young man, who was absent studying law in England. He ultimately returned to Ireland and settled at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drimnagh">Drimnagh</ref>, near Dublin.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>The subject of our sketch rose to high office in Ireland under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VIII">Henry VIII</ref>; he was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knighted">knighted</ref>  around 1513,  and received grants of land near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunleer">Dunleer</ref>. He was unusual among the Irish nobility in his time both in his legal ability  and his willingness to hold judicial office. O'Flanagan suggests that in becoming a judge he wished to follow the distinguished example of his maternal grandfather, Chief Justice Plunket.  He was made <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Attorney_General_for_Ireland">Attorney General for Ireland</ref> in 1504, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solicitor_General_for_Ireland">Solicitor General for Ireland</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serjeant-at-law_(Ireland)">King's Sergeant</ref> shortly after, a justice of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Court_of_King's_Bench_(Ireland)">Court of King's Bench</ref> in 1514, Deputy Treasurer and then <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Treasurer_of_Ireland">Lord Treasurer of Ireland</ref> in 1524 and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Chancellor_of_Ireland">Lord Chancellor of Ireland</ref> in 1534. O'Flanagan praises him as an expert on finance as well as law, but adds somewhat cynically that his greatest talent was for looking after his own interests, as evidenced by the substantial grants of lands at Dunleer made to him by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English_Crown">English Crown</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>In 1536, under the command of  the  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Treasurer_of_Ireland">Lord Treasurer</ref>,  Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Brabazon_(Lord_Justice_of_Ireland)">William Brabazon</ref>, he made an incursion into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Offaly">Offaly</ref>, and drove back the O'Conor clan, who were then ravaging the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anglo-Irish">Anglo-Irish</ref> settlements. The next year, commissioned by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Privy_Council_of_Ireland">Privy Council of Ireland</ref>, he negotiated  successfully with the O'Neills.  During the Rebellion of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Silken_Thomas">Silken Thomas</ref>,  he was one of the Irish  nobles whose loyalty to the Crown was considered to   dubious,  but it seems that these  suspicions were not strong enough for any action to be taken against him.</p>
<p>He died  on 25 July 1538.</p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>He was four times married.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-IrishBio-4">[4]</ref> Only the names of his first and second wives are known for certain: they were  Janet (or Genet)  Bellew of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bellewstown">Bellewstown</ref>,   and Margaret, daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patrick_FitzLeones">Patrick FitzLeones</ref>,   who was three times <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Mayor_of_Dublin">Lord Mayor of Dublin</ref> between 1477 and 1495; her mother was a member of the influential FitzEustace family. He had at least  three children- </p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Patrick Barnewall, 4th Baron Trimlestown.</item>
<item>Elizabeth Barnewall, who married three times:  her husbands were  George Plunkett, Christopher Eustace and William Darcy.</item>
<item>Catherine Barnewall, who married Patrick Hussey, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baron_Galtrim">Baron Galtrim</ref>, and had four children, including James, Baron Galtrim, and Mary, who married Oliver Plunkett.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></item></list>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patrick_Barnewall_(Solicitor_General)">Patrick Barnewall</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solicitor_General_for_Ireland">Solicitor General for Ireland</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Master_of_the_Rolls_in_Ireland">Master of the Rolls in Ireland</ref>, was his nephew, the son of his sister  Alison who married their  cousin Roger Barnewall of Kingsland.</p>
</text>
