<text id="autogum_interview_doc819" title="part4_Satanism: An interview with Church of Satan High Priest Peter Gilmore" shortTile="partsatanism-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-04" dateModified="2018-10-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Satanism%3A_An_interview_with_Church_of_Satan_High_Priest_Peter_Gilmore" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What would be their motivation for doing something for society and not for themselves?  Would there even be a motivation?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  Oh, absolutely!  It’s up for you to choose your own preferences.  By being self-centered you can select your own values.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Like, I get value out of what I am doing for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikimedia">Wikimedia</ref>, even though it’s for free, there is still a value…</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  Absolutely!  What you’re doing, David, is a Satanic example.  The whole point of Satanism is again to choose your values, and if you become somebody that really feels you want to work for hospitals for free—a number of our members work for animal organizations because we generally cherish animals and think they are far less polluted than people with values that are anti- their nature.  So, Satanists are often very giving.</p>
<p>Because our values come from the self, people who try to tell themselves that they must be selfless, they can't really understand why you would be giving if you’re a selfish person.  But I think that’s more a revelation of their <hi rend="italic">own</hi> natures, meaning if they didn't have some external force making them being nice to people, they would be bastards!   We Satanists, because we are relaxed, we love our lives, we love people who enrich our lives and things that are around us that we enjoy, we can be really giving.  Gods can be beneficent!  So when you are your own God, you can be happy to give!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How would a Satanist define evil?</hi></p>
<hi rend="bold">[W]e believe that as animals that are social, we have a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/social%20contract">social contract</ref>.  When we deal with other people, our approach is that we want to have maximum freedom, and maximum responsibility without infringing on people as much as possible.</hi>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evil">Evil</ref> is whatever is harmful to you and the things you most cherish.  It's that simple.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Some people have a compulsion to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Rape">rape</ref>, and it harms them to not act upon it.  If it was harmful for somebody to not go out and rape somebody, how would a Satanist address that situation?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  We then have to go into the realm of society, and we believe that as animals that are social, we have a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/social%20contract">social contract</ref>.  When we deal with other people, our approach is that we want to have maximum freedom, and maximum responsibility without infringing on people as much as possible.  So we would set up laws so we really don't have to spend all of our time defending our territory, being in some kind of castle keep situation.  So anyone who is going to go out and assault undeserving people, is someone we would deem a criminal and have them locked up or dealt with in whatever way seems most appropriate, whether it’s therapy, whether it’s drugs, or if they can't control themselves, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Capital_punishment">execution</ref>.</p>
</text>
