<text id="autogum_interview_doc545" title="part3_Wikinews interviews Jeff Jacobsen, creator of LisaMcPherson.org" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-12" dateModified="2012-12-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Jeff_Jacobsen%2C_creator_of_LisaMcPherson.org" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : If the campaigners are presenting genuine arguments, why has there not been more action from governments (in particular the United States)?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.J.</hi>: Short answer: Because governments sometimes suck?:) But really, on xenutv.com there's an interview with Ray Emmons of the Clearwater Police. He said he compiled a lot of information about Scientology, then presented it to the feds. Their response; "will they come after me?". So he got nowhere. Part of it is actual fear. Part of it is the "religious cloaking" where the government doesn't want to be seen going after a religion. Part of it is incompetence, imho [In My Humble Opinion]. But remember there <hi rend="bold">have</hi> been governmental charges against Scientology, even in the Lisa McPherson case.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Church of Scientology has fought and won legal actions, juries cannot be that easy to sway?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.J.</hi>: I can't think of many cases that Scientology actually won. You'd have to give me a couple of cases. Generally, Scientology sues in civil court to harass and intimidate, not even to win anyway. So I'd need a specific case to discuss here I guess...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Did you actually know Lisa? Or any of her family?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.J.</hi>: No, I first heard of Lisa about one year after she died. I have met her cousin, her aunts and uncle. They are all very nice. Lisa's mom died about one month after Lisa did. Her brother and dad died several years before she did.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Isn't it disrespectful of Lisa's memory to use her memory for purposes so clearly counter to her known beliefs?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.J.</hi>: My question there; what were her beliefs when she was being held against her will in her last days? My suspicion is she changed her mind about Scientology. I know I would have. But her friend, Kelli Davis, said she had talked to Lisa not long before she died, and Kelly thought that Lisa was implying that she was leaving Scientology. So my opinion is that Lisa's beliefs in her last days was that Scientology sucked and I will go with that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Is it possible to bring murder or manslaughter charges against the Church of Scientology again?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.J.</hi>: IANAL [I am not a lawyer] but there's no statute of limitations for murder.  I hope that will happen some day.  Perhaps some of the people involved will come forward with information compelling to a prosecutor</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Do you know any details about the 2004 settlement with Lisa's relatives? Is it true that they have not yet received any money from this settlement with the Church of Scientology?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.J.</hi>: On lisamcpherson.org is a statement from Lisa's family after their "settlement" of the civil suit. I do not know for sure. I believe the court case is still listed as active. As far as whether they were paid, I do not know. The assumption was that it was over though.</p>
</text>
