<text id="autogum_whow_doc114" title="Activate Verizon Internet" shortTile="activate-verizon" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-10-02" dateModified="2019-03-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Activate-Verizon-Internet" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Activate Verizon Internet</head><p>This wikiHow teaches you how to activate Verizon internet services.  When you sign up for Verizon internet services, they send you a welcome letter or email, and an installation package.  The welcome letter contains your Service Ready Date (SRD), and your order number.  You can activate your services at anytime after your Service Ready Date.  You should always activate your internet before activating any additional services you ordered through Verizon.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Connect a Coaxial cable from an outlet to the router.  Find a location near a coaxial wall outlet.  Connect a coaxial cable from the wall outlet to the coaxial input on the back of the router that came with your installation package.  If you ordered internet speeds of 100 mbps or higher, you will also need to connect an ethernet cable from an ethernet outlet to the WAN port on the back of your router.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you don't have a coaxial wall outlet, use the barrel connector that came with the package to connect the coaxial cable connected to the router to the coaxial cable that carries services to your home.</item></list></item>
<item>Plug the router into an electrical outlet and power it on.  Connect the AC adapter that came with the router the the AC in port on the back of the router.  Plug the router into an electrical outlet. Allow up to 15 minutes for the router to activate.  It will power on and off during this process.  When the lights on the front are solid white, and the lights on the back are solid green, the router is ready.
<list type="unordered"><item>Different routers may have a slightly different setup process.</item></list></item>
<item>Connect your computer to the router using an ethernet cable.  A wired connection will provide the most reliable connection.  To connect your computer to your router using a wired connection, connect an ethernet cable to an ethernet port on your computer and then connect it to one of the four yellow ethernet ports on the back of the router.</item>
<item>Locate the wireless information on the router.  There is a label on the router that contains both the wireless network name and password.  It's most likely located on the side of the router.  This is label contains the information you need to connect to your router using a wireless connection.</item>
<item>Connect your wireless devices.  To connect to the internet using a wireless connection, select the wireless connection listed on the router's label from the list of available networks.  Enter the password on the router's label when prompted.  The password is case sensitive.  Read <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Connect-to-a-Wireless-Internet-Connection">"4 Ways to Connect to a Wireless Internet Connection"</ref> to learn more about how to connect to a wireless connection using different devices.
<list type="unordered"><item>Some routers offer a 2.4 ghz internet connection, and a 5 ghz internet connection.  2.4 ghz is a slower connection, but offers greater range.  5 ghz is faster and more suitable for video streaming and gaming.</item></list></item>
<item>Go to <ref target="https://activate.verizon.com">https://activate.verizon.com</ref> in a web browser.  You can use any web browser on your PC, Mac, or mobile device.</item>
<item>Log in to the Verizon activation page.  If you already have a Verizon account, click or tap <hi rend="bold">User ID and Password</hi> to log in with your user ID or email, and password.  Follow the instructions to finish the activation process.  If you do not yet have a Verizon account, click or tap <hi rend="bold">Order number and ZIP code</hi>.  The order number is included in the confirmation email or letter that was sent to your from Verizon.  Enter the green portion of the order number as displayed on the website.  Follow the instructions to set up a Verizon account and complete your activation.</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
