<text id="autogum_whow_doc450" title="Make a Small Apartment Appear Larger" shortTile="make-small-apartment" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2010-01-18" dateModified="2018-03-01" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-a-Small-Apartment-Appear-Larger" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make a Small Apartment Appear Larger</head><p>Have you ever felt that your apartment is too small? Or perhaps just smaller than you’d like? There’s no need to feel cramped – there are many tactics you can use to make a small apartment feel like a comfortable, cozy home.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Clear the clutter. If you’re struggling with a small space, the first step is to get organized! When you have your belongings neatly arranged and out of sight, your space will feel orderly and open. Try mounted wall shelves and storage ottomans to make the most of the space you have – anything that can pull double duty will help make your apartment feel more spacious and organized. <figure rend="Wake Up When You Are Very Tired Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Decorate with soft, light hues. Dark, warm colors are often used to make a home feel cozy and intimate, but these colors unfortunately also make rooms feel smaller. To make your apartment feel larger, use light, cool colors for an open, airy effect. Soft blues and greens are the most effective, but any light, cool color will add space to your apartment. For the optimum effect, use a monochromatic color scale, and tie all your decorations into a specific color family. If you can paint your apartment, make sure the walls are also painted in similarly light colors – light walls will have the largest effect on making the room feel larger. <figure rend="Make a Small Apartment Appear Larger Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Open up floor space. Move furniture out of walkways, and remove unnecessary furniture. A few large, useful pieces will help make your space feel larger and cozier. Move tall furniture against the wall. When you fill a room with multiple small pieces of furniture, the space begins to feel cramped and uninviting. The end goal is to show as much floor as possible. If new furniture is an option, invest in pieces that offer open space underneath, to make the room feel even larger. <figure rend="Give Your Room a Makeover Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use light to your advantage. Light-filled rooms will make your apartment feel much larger. Choose accessories that emit and reflect light. Floor and table lamps may take up too much space, but track lighting or wall-mounted sconces can provide extra light and elegance to a room. Hang mirrors on walls that are opposite windows to reflect light into the space and provide extra oomph to the room – space will also be reflected, resulting in a room that feels larger. <figure rend="Accessorise Your Room Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Go in the attic and see which walls are supporting walls.  A wall that does not support anything can be removed to increase space.  Be prepared to redo the flooring afterwards. <figure rend="Accessorise Your Room Step 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>By following these tactics for decorating a small space, your apartment home will feel comfortable and more spacious. You’ll have a creative space that suits all your needs, and lends a refined elegance to any events you hold in your home.</item>
<item>TGM Associates is an investment advisory firm with a focus on multifamily properties. TGM acquires, sells and manages apartment properties throughout the U.S.  TGM strives to provide the highest level of resident services and quality on-site management as part of a continual commitment to provide residents with a well-maintained apartment community and a comfortable place to live.</item></list>
</text>
