<text id="autogum_news_doc704" title="Amended USA Freedom Act draws questions from civil liberties groups" shortTile="amended-usa-freedom" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-05-09" dateModified="2015-09-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Amended_USA_Freedom_Act_draws_questions_from_civil_liberties_groups" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Amended USA Freedom Act draws questions from civil liberties groups</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, May 11, 2014</hi></p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/USA%20Freedom%20Act">USA Freedom Act</ref>, introduced in to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_House_of_Representatives">US House of Representatives</ref> as HR 3361 and to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_Senate">US Senate</ref> as S. 1599, on Thursday passed out of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House%20Permanent%20Select%20Committee%20on%20Intelligence">House Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence</ref> and on to the House floor. <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foreign%20Policy">Foreign Policy</ref></hi> reported the bill was "the most aggressive NSA reform bill under consideration in Congress", however, after amendment, the bill has been questioned for extending the Patriot Act and the reduction of reform to Section 702 of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act.</p>
<figure></figure>
<p>The USA Freedom Act had the stated goal of ending the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mass%20surveillance%20in%20the%20United%20States">bulk collection</ref> of Americans' metadata, ending the secret laws created by the FISA court, and introducing a "Special Advocate" to represent public and privacy matters before the FISA court.</p>
<p>In May 2014, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/US%20House%20Judiciary%20Committee">US House Judiciary Committee</ref> posted a "Manager's Amendment" on its website. Title VII of the Amendment read "Section 102(b)(1) of the USA Patriot Improvement and Reauthorization Act of 2005 (50 U.S.C. 1805 note) is amended by striking 'June 1, 2015' and inserting 'December 31, 2017'", extending the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/USA%20PATRIOT%20Act">USA PATRIOT Act</ref> through the end of 2017. A number of organizations have taken stances against the Patriot Act, for example, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American%20Library%20Association">American Library Association</ref> became so concerned it urged its members to defend <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Free_speech">free speech</ref> and protect patrons' <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/privacy">privacy</ref> against the Act.</p><p>
According to Deputy Attorney General <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James%20M.%20Cole">James Cole</ref>, even if the Freedom Act becomes law, the NSA could continue its bulk collection of American's phone records. He explained that "it's going to depend on how the [FISA] court interprets any number of the provisions" contained within the legislation. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jennifer%20Granick">Jennifer Granick</ref>, Director of Civil Liberties at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stanford%20Law%20School">Stanford Law School</ref>, stated: </p><p>The Administration and the intelligence community believe they can do whatever they want, regardless of the laws Congress passes, so long they can convince one of the judges appointed to the secretive <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foreign%20Intelligence%20Surveillance%20Court">Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court</ref> (FISC) to agree. This isn't the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/rule%20of%20law">rule of law</ref>. This is a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/coup%20d'etat">coup d'etat</ref>.</p>
<p>Cynthia Wong of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Human_Rights_Watch">Human Rights Watch</ref> (HRW) expressed concern that "the bill does not address needed reforms to surveillance programs that affect millions of people outside US borders.” This being a key problem that plagues <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Global%20surveillance%20disclosures%20(2013–present)">US surveillance activities</ref> according to HRW.</p>
<p>Mike Rogers, a defender of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Global%20surveillance%20disclosures%20(2013–present)">NSA's surveillance practices</ref> and the chairman of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House%20Intelligence%20Committee">House Intelligence Committee</ref>, called the proposed amendments a "huge improvement". On the other hand, USA Freedom Act co-author and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Senate%20Committee%20on%20the%20Judiciary">Senate Committee on the Judiciary</ref> Chairman <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patrick%20Leahy">Patrick Leahy</ref> commented that he "remain concerned that the legislation approved today does not include some of the important reforms related to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/national%20security%20letter">national security letter</ref>s, a strong special advocate at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FISA%20Court">FISA Court</ref>, and greater transparency. I will continue to push for those reforms when the Senate Judiciary Committee considers the USA FREEDOM Act this summer."</p>
</text>
