<text id="autogum_academic_doc194" title="Modelling and Analysis of Plate Heat Exchangers for Flexible District Heating Systems" shortTile="modelling-analysis" author="Serafym Chyhryn" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/21/4141/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 6. Conclusions</head>
<p>
Flexible operation of DH systems entails significant variations in parameters of DH transmission systems. Defining optimal parameters for the transmission system is the key to maintain sufficient heat quality and minimal operation costs. Even in a relatively small DH system, precise modelling of each individual component can become crucial as the optimization problem includes such models as constraints. Precise modelling of PHX is the most critical for the operation of a transmission system. The better the model fits the reality, the less control effort is required at the heat transfer station afterwards and, therefore, secondary temperature deviations from setpoints will be minimal, especially when demand is unpredictable and flexibility is provided (altering of setpoints). This also means that the primary return temperature and mass flow will be more predictable. Poorly performing models can cause frequent control actions, which result in oscillations in the system, as was seen from the experimental part of this work. </p>

<p>Both mass flows and temperatures affect heat transfer capability of plate heat exchangers. Thus, at various demands plate heat exchangers will produce different return temperatures, which in its turn affects the efficiency of a power-to-heat source (e.g., the heat pump). Especially, this has a greater effect when mass flows and temperatures vary across a wide range, and PHXs, as well as their respective distribution systems, differ significantly in their design (for instance, rating) and demand patterns. </p>

<p>Analysis of heat transfer through DH PHXs has shown that the temperature dependent component of FCC for water has nearly linear behaviour. This persists for the whole range of possible temperatures and covers most of the design correlations, as well as for a large range of pressure since it does not affect thermophysical properties of DH water. This behaviour allows approximating it as a linear function of temperature  where  and  are fixed and defined by the design, which was validated experimentally on a laboratory PHX. </p>

<p>The described linear approximation eliminates the use of lookup tables for thermophysical properties for the calculation of OHTC and, therefore, removes the iterative process from the optimization problem. The approximation use is not limited to district heating only and can be applied whenever the temperature dependent component of FCC for a fluid exhibits linear behaviour. </p>

<p>Correlation estimation procedures, outlined in the experimental part of the work, enables finding the most suitable correlation for a particular PHX from temperature and mass flow measurements. This can be used in practice when inspection of a PHX model is performed. It shows that the correlation accuracy can be further improved by relating its coefficient to one (or several) of the varying parameters. </p>

<p>The two operational optimization study cases show that variable correlation models with linearized temperature dependence perform generally better than the original fixed-temperature thermophysical models, having the same computation time and higher accuracy. The proposed models require at least a two-times lower computation time than variable temperature thermophysical models, while having the same accuracy. </p>

<p>The choice between the models described is made depending on their performance for a specific system and engineering judgement. These, due to some models, are not being consistently good at all heat demands. In real systems, however, with dozens of heat exchangers and multiple power-to-heat sources, the optimization (non-linear control) problem would result in a large number of simulations if all constraints must be satisfied within one optimization interval (time step). Besides, the delays in a DH transmission system can reach a dozen of hours, therefore yielding an enormous number of optimization time steps within the given time horizon. Thus, computational performance is critical. </p>

<p>Detailed modelling and control of power to heat sources, i.e., the coupling units between the sectors, is of high interest, which will be the focus of future work.
 </p>
</text>
