<text id="autogum_academic_doc346" title="An Optimisation Approach for Long-Term Industrial Investment Planning" shortTile="optimisation-approach" author="Hür Bütün, Ivan Kantor, François Maréchal" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/21/4076/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 6. Conclusions</head>
<p>
This work proposes an MILP framework, PIIP, which combines the efforts in process integration and long-term investment planning. The method takes advantage of PI, by modelling the energy and resource flows in detail, including heat cascade, mass and energy balances. A novel investment planning formulation is proposed and integrated with PI, capturing all investment actions, such as commissioning and decommissioning of utility systems, while considering external exchanges via pipeline. </p>

<p>The method is applied to a large case study, with eight industrial plants from different sectors and a district neighbouring an industrial cluster, for a time horizon of twenty years. When the investment budget and period are not limited, all investments improving the operating cost are made in the first year, to maximise benefits from the operating cost savings as long as possible. Heat pumps and cogeneration engines are preferred over industrial boilers in all sites where their integration is possible. In inter-plant exchanges, priority is given to heat sharing with the district, as this option is more profitable because of lower industrial energy prices relative to residential ones. In addition, heat sharing over long distances with a single pipeline is preferred over investing in multiple pipelines connecting smaller nearby sites. When seasonality is taken into account, given the variations in the district demand, the investment decisions change drastically. A larger amount of heat is shared between the industrial cluster and the district resulting in less heat sharing between the industrial plants. Based on interactions between plants, different investment options become favourable. Thus, in the cases where energy demand varies greatly throughout a year, it is crucial to consider seasonality, to obtain the optimal selection and planning of the investments. </p>

<p>To simulate a more industrially-realistic scenario (i.e., refurbishment planning of plant infrastructure), an investment budget is imposed and the investment period is restricted to the first five or ten years, with the possibility of transferring budget from one year to the next. As the yearly budget does not allow for large early investments, they occur over the whole investment period. Some large investments found in the optimal solution without budget restrictions no longer appear, as annual budgets would need to accumulate for several years, making other solutions more attractive. As the investment strategy becomes more conservative (i.e., lower annual budget in a longer investment period), competition between investment in energy conversion technologies and inter-plant steam pipes increases, as parallel investments are not feasible. Although in the studied case, investment in energy conversion technologies receives priority over pipelines, the solution is dependent on the case study, energy profiles, prices and distances. </p>

<p>A strategy is proposed to generate multiple investment options using parametric optimisation by setting an upper limit for piping investment and varying it, and the results are compared with a single optimal solution. The parametric optimisation strategy not only generates 30 solutions in shorter time, but also finds solutions with better economic and environmental KPIs. Thus, in the case of industrial applications, it is better to generate multiple optimal solutions instead of trying to reach the global optimum. In all solutions ranking highly in economic and environmental KPIs, industrial excess heat is shared with the district. Thus, it is crucial to consider symbiosis options with a nearby heat consumers in industrial retrofit applications, which is often overlooked. </p>

<p>The optimal solution using the proposed method without investment restrictions leads to a ~463 M€ increase in the NPV of the system and 7748 kt CO2 savings compared to the baseline, owing to operating cost benefits of investment decisions. Applying a budget limit on the investment cost with an investment period of five and ten years results in 5% and 13% decrease in NPV and 9% and 12% decrease in CO2 savings compared to the solution without any budget limitation but they still provide significant improvement compared to the baseline. Although more conservative investment planning strategies result in slightly lower savings in the operating cost, they still lead to reductions of ~50 M€, or, in other words, a payback time of less than two years for the investments. </p>

<p>The method presented in this work provides a holistic strategy for investment planning of large industrial cases in long time horizons. Additional constraints can easily be integrated to customise it according to the limitations of the industrial clusters on the investment budget and periods. Future work includes adding stochasticity in the energy prices and cost of energy conversion technologies, as well as in the production capacity of plants and population of districts nearby. In addition, the objective function can be modified to optimise for an environmental objective instead of using a purely economic one.
 </p>
</text>
