<text id="autogum_interview_doc848" title="part1_CanadaVOTES: Liberal Sandra Gardiner running in Perth—Wellington" shortTile="partcanadavotes-liberal" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-09-25" dateModified="2019-07-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CanadaVOTES%3A_Liberal_Sandra_Gardiner_running_in_Perth%E2%80%94Wellington" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Previous to this campaign, have you been politically involved? How will you apply your previous work/volunteer/life experience to serving your constituents?</hi></p>
<p>I became politically active when my children's child care centre was threatened with closure 4 years ago.  I organized a group of parents from the Day Care and we were successful in preventing this closure.  This lead me to become involved in many other activities.</p>
<p>I think that having first hand experience working within the Health Care System will be a crucial part to my work as a Member of Parliament and making decisions when it comes to Health Care.  Being a woman and a mother also contributes to how I will make my decisions.</p>
<p>Finally I am a creative thinker.  I am always coming up with new solutions for old problems.  I believe that Canadians are looking for politicians with ideas and a vision for the future.  Canadians want a Prime Minister who cares about the future of Canada and cares about all Canadians.  I think Canadians are tired of the negative attack ads and rhetoric.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">As you campaign around your riding, it's likely that some issues are mentioned more often by voters, than other issues. What would you say are the three hottest topics this election, in your riding?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">The Economy</hi> which would include job losses we have experienced and the ripple effect that has been felt as a result.  How well agriculture has been performing is also a part of our local economy here.  We have the third largest pork producing region in Canada.  Their industry has suffered greatly over the last few years.  The beef industry has also experienced hard times.  Agriculture is the largest movement of economic activity in and out of this riding daily.  1 in 3 jobs are tied to agriculture in this riding.  We have watched a large number of manufacturing jobs leave this riding over the last couple of years.  We have the local issue funding of the University of Waterloo Site in Stratford.  The Federal Government has not committed to the $10 million requested to assist with the project.  This is a contentious issue for local residents.  Funding of the University will have a profound economic effect on this region.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Arts and Culture</hi> is the second issue that has been brought up at the door.  Many are deeply concerned over the cuts to the programs in recent months.  They are also concerned about the future of Arts and Culture under the Harper government should he be successful in winning a majority government.</p>
<p>I have to say I have had a number of comments over the <hi rend="bold">timing of the election</hi> and <hi rend="bold">constituents not feeling that the election was necessary</hi>.  They would state that they felt that parliament was working and the election could have waited until the fixed date October 2009.  Most are undecided in how to vote or there is a sense of voter apathy.</p>
</text>
