<text id="autogum_academic_doc709" title="Exploring the Enablers of Strategic Orientation for Technology-Driven Business Innovation Ecosystems" shortTile="exploring-enablers" author="Ta-Kai Yang, Min-Ren Yan" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5779/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Discussion</head><head> 5.1. Theoretical Contributions</head>
<p>
This study selects three representative case companies from a nation-wide database of the Ministry of Science and Technology in Taiwan to observe the impacts of different strategic orientations on the innovation ecosystem at the corporate level. By comparing the companies of different countries selected as subjects for previous studies, this study identifies how the meanings of innovation ecosystems vary from one country to another. For example, Rao and Jimenez observed the innovation ecosystems of Apple and Google, which both digitally link the elements of innovation ecosystems. According to their study, consumers, users, and developers can foster synergy on online platforms, and generate network externalities that increase the value of software and hardware innovation. Other studies also found that some innovation ecosystems are university-based, thus, universities are regarded as a source of innovation. The university-enterprise relationship plays an important role in technological success, such as the Technical University of Madrid. In Finland, the government integrates resources to build an innovation ecosystem powered by national technological policies, and boosts the close collaboration between industry and university through investments in education, R&amp;D, corporate technology innovation, entrepreneurship, and corporate export capability enhancement. Many well-known global startups, such as RAVIO Mobile and PAPTIC, have sprung up in Finland, which indicates the positive impact of government support on innovation ecosystems. Taiwan features a high-tech centered SME ecosystem; in an industrial environment dominated by small and medium-sized enterprises, only enterprises with critical strategic thinking and enhanced ability can drive the development of the ecosystem. This study further finds that market orientation, interaction orientation, and entrepreneurial orientation can generate a positive reinforcing causal loop on the overall innovation ecosystem.  </p>

<p>More specifically, when an organization has market orientation, it means that the organization has market intelligence and responds to it, and such response will deliver superior customer value and more two-way communication, which will have positive reinforcing effect on the development of new products and new businesses. Interaction orientation represents the belief in customers, value co-creation with customers, and interaction with customers to solve common problems jointly. Therefore, market orientation has positive reinforcing effect on the development of new products and businesses, as well as technological innovation. Entrepreneurial orientation will increase the exploratory activities of enterprises, and such orientation emphasizes the process of strategic decision-making and the stakeholder-centered business philosophy. It also attaches importance to risky investments in resources of unknown environments, or the introduction of new products/services to meet customers’ future needs, thereby, exerting positive reinforcing effect on technological innovation and investment in technological innovation.  </p>

<p>Further, this study also finds that the development of new businesses should be divided into phases, such as Mosey’s view on new to market products, meaning new product development and new market development are two elements of technological innovation, new business development, and market size. Technological innovation will have positive impact on the development of new products, and new businesses will not develop until the performance of new product developments are improved (e.g., product novelty and speed of product development). The development of new businesses must be in line with the market by collecting information on customers and competitors, in order that products and services can effectively meet customer needs, indicating that the company is starting to develop a new market. </p>

<p>In summary, this study contributes to the literature addressing the role of strategic orientation in innovation ecosystem literature by developing and empirically testing a theoretical framework informed by systems thinking. </p>

<head> 5.2. Managerial Implications</head>
<p>
In practice, understanding the strategic orientations of an enterprise is critical to the impact of its innovative ecosystem. This study proposes the following suggestions for business managers. First, companies must develop market-oriented thinking, as market orientation can produce a positive reinforcing effect on industry sales and economic performance. If a company focuses on boosting its economic performance, it must have access to marketing intelligence, and establish internal and external communication mechanisms, in order that intelligence can be fully understood internally and disseminated within the enterprise, thus, enabling the company to be responsive to market demands. Therefore, managers must be sensitive to the market, and be responsive through internal communication and coordination. </p>

<p>Second, when an enterprise fosters interaction-oriented thinking, it will have a positive reinforcing effect on the development of new products, services, and business models. Therefore, an enterprise must understand its consumers, allow them to be part of product development, and adopt customer value management methods to interact with consumers, thus, tightening the link between new product development and the market. </p>

<p>Finally, when an enterprise develops entrepreneurial orientation, it contributes to continuous investment in technological innovation; therefore, enterprises must foster the proactive innovation spirit and dare to take risks. Enterprises can apply the results of this study as a map for an innovation ecosystem model to understand how different kinds of strategic thinking impact the link between innovation activities and market activities. </p>
</text>
