<text id="autogum_whow_doc264" title="Test a Business Continuity Plan" shortTile="test-business-continuity" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-07-22" dateModified="2017-10-07" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Test-a-Business-Continuity-Plan" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Test a Business Continuity Plan</head><p>A plan is as good as its implementation.If we do not execute the plan, the very purpose of the plan is defeated. In case of a business continuity plan, there is a twist in the tale. This is because a Business Continuity Plan comes into use only when a situation calls for it. Otherwise, it remains a plan. So, it is important to test the plan at regular intervals to make sure that it serves the purpose. The testing is also an indication of the emergency preparedness.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Study the plan thoroughly and ensure that it is updated. <figure rend="Apply-for-an-Entrepreneurial-Grant-Step-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>In case you want the testing to reveal the gaps, then you may skip the above step. <figure rend="Be-Debt-Free-Step-3-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>However, in order to get the most out of the testing exercise, it is always better to ensure that the plan is updated. For instance, telephone numbers might have undergone a change or there could be people movements. <figure rend="Be-a-Successful-Entrepreneur-Step-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Having updated the plan, the next step is to plan the testing itself. <figure rend="Survive High School Step 13 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Write out the clear objective of the testing plan along with details about who all are required to be part of the testing exercise, what is their role, type of testing exercise that you are envisaging, what are the expected outcomes. <figure rend="Write-a-Blog-Post-Step-12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Having done the above, decide if you want to opt for a desktop exercise (where you simulate a real life scenario in a meeting hall or a conference room) or you would like to do it on a real time basis. <figure rend="Write-a-Blog-Post-Step-3-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>For the testing exercise, it is also crucial to inform all the stakeholders well in advance so that they are prepared. <figure rend="Succeed-in-Network-Marketing-Step-10-Version-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep the top management team informed so that employees take the testing plan with all the seriousness that it deserves. <figure rend="Market a Product Step 18.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Communicate the venue in advance along with the date and ensure that there are no last minute cancellations. Testing a Business Continuity Plan is serious business that can't be delegated lower down the line. <figure rend="Raise-Money-Online-Step-11-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be mentally prepared for the challenges - indifferent responses, last minute cancellations etc and focus on the broader goals. <figure rend="Develop-Critical-Thinking-Skills-Step-16-Version-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>It is advisable to have one or two sponsors for this exercise - like the Marketing director or Operations director or HR director who can add value and positional influence to the testing exercise. <figure rend="Prepare-a-Power-of-Attorney-Step-8-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Generally the duration of the testing exercise depends on a number of factors but in general, you can have a 1-day session for a desktop testing exercise. <figure rend="Prepare-a-Power-of-Attorney-Step-2-Version-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>It is advisable to have the testing exercise off-site but often due to cost factors and logistical constraints, the testing is done at the relevant location. <figure rend="Become a Software Engineer Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>3-days prior to the testing date, send an executive summary of the testing plan to all stake holders. <figure rend="Write-a-Grant-Proposal-Step-22-Version-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have the case studies ready at hand that describe the sequence of hazardous events taking place. <figure rend="Write-a-Grant-Proposal-Step-16-Version-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>On the scheduled date, begin the testing by clarifying the objectives clearly in the opening session. <figure rend="Write-a-Blog-Post-Step-15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Explain to the audience that this is neither a fact finding mission or a fault finding mission but an attempt to ensure that the business continuity plan is fit for purpose. <figure rend="Develop-a-Relationship-With-a-Customer-Step-8-Version-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have one resource dedicated for capturing the data on a spread sheet live when the testing is in progress. <figure rend="Do-a-Background-Check-Step-6-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Let there be one more resource who documents the proceedings in minute details. (this is not a stenographer/typist's job as most people seem to believe). <figure rend="Do-a-Monthly-Budget-Step-11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Please note that documentation is not only important but also all minor details need to be documented. <figure rend="Start-a-Letter-Step-4-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Following the completion of the testing plan, it is important to give a break and request all to reassemble after 30 minutes. During this period, capture the key lessons from the exercise. <figure rend="Be-Punctual-Step-11-Version-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Seek feedback from audience to add value to the document. <figure rend="Open-a-Restaurant-Step-27.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>You can ask open ended questions like - What went wrong , what went well etc and use the answers to enrich the document. <figure rend="Succeed-in-Network-Marketing-Step-4-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do not run down any feedback. <figure rend="Defend-Against-Appropriation-of-Name-or-Likeness-Claims-Step-14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>In the closing session, thank the people for spending their time. <figure rend="Get-Business-Loans-Step-10-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Insist on a top management team member address the group and share their thoughts and provide assurance that the feedback will be used to rebuild the plan more effectively. <figure rend="File-Bankruptcy-in-the-United-States-Step-7-Version-4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Post testing, communicate the gaps to the group via Email and also inform them about how these gaps have been used to update the plan. <figure rend="Obtain-a-Copy-of-Your-Birth-Certificate-in-Ohio-Step-14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Update the plan, archive the earlier versions and communicate the new plan to all stakeholders with the revision number and date. <figure rend="Write-a-Biographical-Sketch-Step-10-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do seek management feedback (You ask and you will get it !) <figure rend="Negotiate-an-Offer-Step-1-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>It may be worthwhile to do a random check on the next period for testing the plan (perhaps after 6 months) and also if we can do a real time simulation.For example allow operations at a site to come to a grinding halt by way of artificially created hazard and then work at testing the plan. This will need buy-in from the top team. <figure rend="Track-a-MoneyGram-Money-Order-Step-9-Version-5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
