<text id="autogum_whow_doc516" title="Make an Ad Campaign of a Clothing Range" shortTile="make-ad-campaign" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-08-13" dateModified="2018-07-18" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-an-Ad-Campaign-of-a-Clothing-Range" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make an Ad Campaign of a Clothing Range</head><p>Whether you design clothes and sell them, or if you are a fashion retailer, you need to capture the attention of your potential customers. this is quite hard, however, knowing that there are fashion empires coming up by the dozen. You need to have a clever ad campaign to come off on the top.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Identify your target audience. Different groups of consumers will have different tastes, and you will have to cater for each of these tastes. If you stock items for many age groups, you have to come up with a range of ad campaigns, if resources allow, of course.</item>
<item>Come up with a theme. Most reputable fashion stockists have a very unique theme, and most of them are formulated depending on the seasons. For instance, if you are stocking items for winter, you could bring a theme such as Narnia, and set up various props, showing the White Queen dressed in luxury winter outfits. This however may not appeal to a more mature audience, thus going back to the issue of knowing your target audience.ensure that you spend as much time as possible in the formulation of the theme, as it will eb the first thing that catches a potential client's eye.</item>
<item>Hire a stylist to help you out. You may not have resources to splurge on an A-list stylist, but ensure you get someone who has vast experience in the field of fashion. They will know which clothing items are on trend but are still in line with your theme for the ad campaign, thus making the ad campaign quite popular.</item>
<item>Be unique. Try something that others have not done before. For instance, rather than hiring professional models to model the outfits, choose people from your locality. This will show that you are very rooted in the community and it will save save you a lot of money since most will consider appearing on TV and magazines as being payment enough.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Check out as many magazines, websites and shows touching on fashion ,check the ad campaigns they have from various fashion empires and try to get some inspiration from them.</item>
<item>Read online reviews and get to see what consumers think about them.This will give you a rough idea of what your target audience would like to see.</item>
<item>If you are unable to settle on just one theme, make a mash-up of these themes. However, do not include too many themes as it will seem disorganized and not serious.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not copy an entire ad campaign from another fashion houses. This just shows your potential clients that you have no originality and may also get you in trouble with authorities in regards to copyright violations.</item></list>
</text>
