<text id="autogum_interview_doc759" title="part2_Interview with Innocent Watat, City Council candidate for Wards 3 &amp; 4 in Brampton, Canada" shortTile="partinterview-innocent" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-21" dateModified="2007-06-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Innocent_Watat%2C_City_Council_candidate_for_Wards_3_%26_4_in_Brampton%2C_Canada" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>In collaboration with Bramptonians, we must ensure that the recreation aspects are well considered through parks, recreation centers, and cultural programs.</p>
<p>The city must remain safe, secure, clean, lively and vibrant at all time.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> The Rose Theatre recently launched. What are your thoughts on this facility? Have you had a chance to tour it yet?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi>The Rose Theatre is the sort of actions that I would encourage as city councilor. Of course beyond this sort of infrastructure, we must always seek and keep in mind the wellbeing of our population. The culture sense that the Rose brings is certainly part of the wellbeing of Bramptonians. However, we must ensure that each of us in the city can really have a stake of that well-being.</p>
<p>I have toured the facility and enjoyed with my daughter a kid show and was also in the crowd few days ago for a splendid comedy show. Rose Theatre is definitely the way to go. But we must notice how long it took to the previous council chamber to offer to this city what it really deserves. That must be said loudly.</p>
<p>We need to diversify actions that would ensure that each Bramptonian actually have something to cherish, make him comfortable to live and raise his children in Brampton. I do believe that the downtown core of Brampton is missing many other things. There is a clear urban development missing; as far as I am concerned, the Rose Theatre must be the beginning of a long development program of our downtown. I would make sure, as city councilor that we continue in this path with more depth.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> The province has strongly encouraged the development of high-density residences near the downtown. Do these buildings fit in with your vision of the downtown? How much say should other levels of government have in urban planning?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> The good thing materializes by the new Rose Theatre must not be the only downtown development action. Our downtown must be revitalized and the high-density residences and precisely the high rise condominium buildings must be the next steps. Downtown Brampton must be the center of the city and the biggest center of attraction in many ways. Today we are really millions miles away of that vision.</p>
<p>As city councilor along with Bramptonians and all levels of government I would deeply work to revive our downtown core. High rise and high density residences are definitely part of my vision and Brampton must be before 2010 well into it in order to fully fit in this twenty first century.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How do you feel about Brampton's rate of expansion? Council recently capped the annual amount of new development; do you agree completely with this decision, would you have slowed development even further, or not have imposed a cap at all?</p>
</text>
