<text id="autogum_voyage_doc80" title="Erzurum" shortTile="erzurum" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=11086" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Erzurum</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Erzurum</hi> is a city in <ref target="Eastern%20Anatolia">Eastern Anatolia</ref>, and is the hub for visiting eastern <ref target="Turkey">Turkey</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Erzurum is the highest major city (population: 360,000 according to 2000 census) in Turkey, situated at an altitude of about 2000 metres above sea level. Combined with the distance to the sea, this makes the climate of this area the harshest in Turkey with the temperatures in long, heavily snowy, and bitterly cold winter regularly below -30°C at nights (and no warmer than -15°C during the day). Wet summers in Erzurum are around 30°C in the day time and chilly at night, although temperatures dropping down to freezing point during summer are becoming rarer and rarer each year, probably with the advance of global warming.</p>

<p>The city hosted the international <hi rend="bold">2011 Winter Universiade</hi> (“university olympic games”) <ref target="http://www.universiadeerzurum.org/"></ref>.</p>

<head>By train</head>

<p>The <hi rend="italic">Doğu Express</hi> runs daily from <ref target="Ankara">Ankara</ref> to Erzurum, departing at 18:00 and arriving 20 hours later around 14:00. This train continues to <ref target="Kars">Kars</ref>, taking another 4 hours. The return train leaves Kars around 08:00 and Erzurum around noon. There are couchettes, a sleeping car (maybe) and a buffet. The main stops along the route are <ref target="Kayseri">Kayseri</ref>, <ref target="Sivas">Sivas</ref>, and <ref target="Erzincan">Erzincan</ref>, for details see <ref target="http://www.tcddtasimacilik.gov.tr">Turkish Railways</ref> website. </p>

<p>In summer 2019 a tourist train plies between Ankara and Kars, with a two hour stop in Erzurum for sightseeing. You're tied to the tourist itinerary without flexibility of stopover. The accommodation is in standard sleeping cars: these have been provided by pulling sleeping cars off the conventional trains, so the travel experience on those has been degraded.</p>

<p>A high-speed railway line is under construction from Ankara towards Erzurum and Kars. This will greatly reduce journey times when the first section to Sivas opens, perhaps in 2020.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Erzurum railway station</hi> (Erzurum Garı) (At the northern end of city centre).</item>
</list>


<head>By plane</head>
 <hi rend="bold">Erzurum Airport</hi> ( ERZ ) (10 km from city center). Daily flights from <ref target="Istanbul">Istanbul</ref> (by Onur Air, Turkish Airlines, and Pegasus) and direct flights from <ref target="Izmir">Izmir</ref>, <ref target="Ankara">Ankara</ref>, and <ref target="Antalya">Antalya</ref>. In winter, there are also flights from Russia and Ukraine.
 

<head>By bus</head>

<p>Most bus services use Erzurum Otogar, which is about 10 km away from the city centre. Take a local bus or taxi to the centre.</p>

<p>Buses from <ref target="Trabzon">Trabzon</ref> in the north, on the <ref target="Eastern%20Karadeniz">Black Sea coast</ref>, take around 4½ and cost 30 TL (but, if you don't look too much like a tourist, it might be possible to bargain it down to 25 TL), while buses from <ref target="Diyarbakir">Diyarbakır</ref> in the south take a little more than 6 hours and have the standard fare of 50 TL, which might be bargainable down to 35 TL.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<p>Erzurum is a pretty small city, and you can cover most of it by foot, unless you are thinking of heading out and around the city, in which case, most public buses and taxis will be able to get you there.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Twin Minaret Madrasa</hi> (Çifte Minareli Medrese). Built as a theological school a few years before 1265, it takes its name from the two fluted minarets that crown the monumental façade. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Citadel of Erzurum</hi>. Situated on the top of the hill in the middle of the city centre. The 3 TL admission fee allows you to explore the grounds as well as to climb up the minaret/clock tower, and visit the citadel masjid. It's worth the effort to climb up the clock tower as it gives you a commanding view of the city and the surrounding mountains.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Palandöken Ski Center</hi>. Only 10 minutes away from city centre by public bus. </item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> In summer you can hike up to the top of Palandöken (3,150 m above sea level) for fantastic views. There is a road (first paved up to some of the hotels, then a dirt road) up to the very top, but it is possible to take shortcuts when hiking. There are no marked trails, but the directions are clearly visible. It is good to start early to allow time to enjoy the views.</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Oltutaşı</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Oltu stone</hi> in Turkish) — This is a kind of amber which is extracted only in Oltu, a town near Erzurum. It is mostly chipped into jewelry, with different levels of quality and correspondingly different levels of prices. Look around in Erzurum. <hi rend="bold">Taşhan</hi> is the best place to shop for Oltutaşı and it is also an interesting traditional building.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Silver</hi> — In jewelry shops in the center or on <hi rend="italic">Taşmağazalar</hi> street, fancy authentic silver jewelry can be found.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>

<p>Stockbreeding is widespread in the region, and there is little chance to cultivate vegetables and fruits in this high and cold land. Therefore traditional food is mainly dependent on meat.</p>

<p>The city is also known for different types of local cheese that is hard to find elsewhere in Turkey.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Kadayıf dolması</hi> — A must-taste local dessert of Erzurum cuisine. It is made from <hi rend="italic">kadayıf</hi>, a sweet pastry that is lots of thin fibres of flour put together. Walnuts are stuffed in the <hi rend="italic">kadayıf</hi> and the stuffed <hi rend="italic">kadayıf</hi> is first fried, then cooled and finally ready to serve with addition of a sweet sauce. It may be sampled in virtually every restaurant in Erzurum, but some of the best can be tried in a specialist restaurant, <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.kadayifcimuammerusta.com.tr/">Muammer Usta</ref></hi></p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Döner</hi> — Typical Turkish <hi rend="italic">döner</hi> is really made well and should be tasted in <hi rend="bold">[http://www.donercihacibaba.com.tr/online-rezervasyon/ankara/ Hacı Baba Restaurant</hi> (10AM-10PM) İsmetpaşa Cad. No : 15, +90 442 234 40 33.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Cağ kebap</hi> — local kebab of Erzurum, that you can have in <hi rend="bold">Gelgor Restaurant</hi>. It is made with lamb meat and the preparation is like <hi rend="italic">döner</hi>, but unlike <hi rend="italic">döner</hi>, instead of a vertical axis, the meat is cooked on a horizontal axis.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Güzelyurt Restaurant</hi> — A very nice old restaurant right in the city center on Cumhuriyet Caddesi. You can have a good Turkish meal with some Turkish raki and enjoy the atmosphere. <ref target="http://guzelyurtrestaurant.com/"></ref></p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Hmmburger</hi> — A very tiny small hamburger place. Hamburgers are really delicious.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Coffeebox</hi> — A local coffeeshop, with various pasta options and nice coffees.</p>
</text>
