<text id="autogum_whow_doc618" title="Get a Religious Girl to See Past Agnostic or Atheistic Beliefs" shortTile="religious-girl-see" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2008-05-22" dateModified="2019-08-15" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get-a-Religious-Girl-to-See-Past-Agnostic-or-Atheistic-Beliefs" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get a Religious Girl to See Past Agnostic or Atheistic Beliefs</head><p>Have you ever had trouble getting a date with someone who is religious because of your views? Showing respect for the person's beliefs, understanding your differences, and figuring out what you have in common are key when it comes to dating a religious girl. In the end, it's up to you decide whether your spiritual divide is a dealbreaker or something you can live with.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Find a woman of faith you like.</hi> Remember people with religious faith vary as much as atheists and agnostics. Find one who has the characteristics you're looking for in a girlfriend and would consider you as a boyfriend. Remember while many such women would consider dating a person outside her faith, others would not--or <hi rend="italic">cannot</hi>. <figure rend="Get a Religious Girl to See Past Agnostic or Atheistic Beliefs Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Show respect for her beliefs. This doesn't mean attending religious services or <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Stop_People_From_Trying_to_Convert_You_to_Another_Religion">converting</ref>. You just have to make sure that they know that you are accepting of her faith. Do <hi rend="italic">not</hi> demand or ask her to do things outside of her religious faith. <figure rend="Get a Religious Girl to See Past Agnostic or Atheistic Beliefs Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Respect and understand cultural, family, or community differences. For some girls and women, dating outside the community can be <hi rend="italic">extremely difficult and threatening</hi> to her family, friends, and house of worship. If she is an immigrant or first-generation citizen, this is especially true. Be sensitive to the fact girls and women will often encounter a lot of resistance. This may even mean accepting a chaperone on a date, meeting only at school, or being formally approved by the family members. <figure rend="Get a Religious Girl to See Past Agnostic or Atheistic Beliefs Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Serve the <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Find_a_Community_Service_Program">community</ref>. Community service is a key part of nearly all religions. She may be satisfied knowing that you follow the moral codes of her religion, even if you do not believe exactly in what she believes in. Anyway, it's a good thing to do anyway. <figure rend="Get a Religious Girl to See Past Agnostic or Atheistic Beliefs Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be incredibly <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Kind">kind</ref> to her. Treat her with respect. This is obviously a key part of getting anyone to like you, of any belief. <figure rend="Get a Religious Girl to See Past Agnostic or Atheistic Beliefs Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be patient. It may take time to convince a religious woman that you are honest in your intentions and sincere in your tolerance, so take your time. <figure rend="Get a Religious Girl to See Past Agnostic or Atheistic Beliefs Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Know when to decide if religion is a deal-breaking issue. If you go beyond casual boyfriend and girlfriend relationships, realize that issues of faith can become more serious--or not. When considering marriage or civil union, the issue of faith becomes increasingly more important as you may start a family. Sometimes, this becomes truly a problem, and marriage cannot be a viable option. But not always, as families sometimes blend beliefs. In either case, it has to be a joint decision by the couple. Seek marital counseling if such problems become too much. <figure rend="Get a Religious Girl to See Past Agnostic or Atheistic Beliefs Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are atheist or agnostic, be respectful of those who have faith in religion. It might not be your belief, but be tolerant of others.</item>
<item>If you are interested in the basic tenets on her faith, do some quick Wikipedia research on key figures, deities, and other various beliefs in her religion.</item>
<item>Most people like to have relationships with people they have things in common with. There is no point in having a relationship with someone who thinks completely differently than you.</item>
<item>Think about it and admit it. One of you thinks that the other is completely wrong. If there is such a gap in your way of thinking, then it's probably not a good idea to pursue a "relationship" that has a huge chance of not working out.</item>
<item>Statements like,"Aren't Christians (or whatever religion she is)supposed to be kind to all people, even those who don't share your beliefs?" can be helpful if the girl is rude to you about religion. But realize it's not going to help you if you're a jerk, and then tell her not to be.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't lie to her. You'll compromise your integrity in <hi rend="italic">your</hi> beliefs, and if she realizes you are faking interest in her religion, she'll probably dump you.</item>
<item>Don't convert unless you honestly feel this is the choice for you.</item>
<item>If she is sincere in her beliefs, she probably won't really be happy in the long term with anyone who does not share them.  Are you more interested in making her happy, or in trying to make yourself happy?</item></list>
</text>
