<text id="autogum_interview_doc312" title="part5_Interview with Sue Gardner of the Wikimedia Foundation" shortTile="partinterview-sue" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-19" dateModified="2012-01-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Sue_Gardner_of_the_Wikimedia_Foundation" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">SG:</hi>  Yes, exactly (re London bombings). I am not sure how noticed that was. For the mainstream media, that was when they woke up to the power of collaborative media themselves. It was certainly the wakeup call for the BBC, who made a lot of changes to their newsgathering process based on the events of that day. I think the most interesting question for Wikinews is what uniquely you can do, that no-one else can. And I think your greatest strength may lie in coverage of really large breaking news events—the [2004] <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2004_Indian_Ocean_Tsunami">tsunami</ref>, the London bombings, Virginia Tech.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Matt: A lot of attention has been given to improving Wikipedia. Do you think more attention is needed for the other projects? If so, which ones do you think need more attention?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SG:</hi>  I think that in a way, that question looks at WMF through the wrong end of the telescope. I don't think the best question is 'do the other projects need more attention'—I think the best question is 'what do our readers need from us, and how can we best give it to them.' I think Wikiquotes, for example, will always be smaller than Wikipedia in terms of readership, and that's fine. Wikinews, I think, needs to chart a path that may be quite different from Wikipedia. And Commons is an entirely different beast as well. So they are all quite different, with different needs.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Dodge: What advice can you give to aspiring journalists, based on your experiences at the CBC?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SG:</hi>  Hm. I think it's an incredibly exciting time to be a journalist. The best advice I could give people is to find excellent, curious, brilliant journalists to learn from. They might be here, or in a conventional newsroom; it doesn't matter. Journalism is a craft and the best way to learn it is to surround yourself with really good teachers. I was lucky at the CBC</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Brian: "Above all, the central question about the Wikinews effort is its credibility. "Making a newspaper is hard... Someone who wants to do it but doesn't really know how hasn't solved the problem by gathering a lot of other people who don't know, either." This is a quote from a former editor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Encyclopædia%20Britannica">Encyclopædia Britannica</ref>, have we proven him wrong?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SG:</hi>  I think most definitely, you have proved him wrong. Journalism is not a profession: it is not like being a surgeon or a lawyer. There was an uneasy attempt to professionalize it with the advent of j-schools etc., post-Watergate. But at its heart, it's just a craft. And that means that it can be practiced by anyone who is sensible and intelligent and thoughtful and curious, who bothers to learn the rules and do it carefully. I go back to the morning of Virginia Tech—the morning I decided I wanted to work here. The conversation on the talk page that day was extremely thoughtful. I remember thinking to myself that if my own newsroom had been having a conversation that intelligent (I was offsite that day), I would have been delighted. So yes, IMO you absolutely have proved <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert%20McHenry">Robert McHenry</ref> wrong. And you will continue to.</p>
</text>
