<text id="autogum_academic_doc182" title="Biocompatible Polymer Materials with Antimicrobial Properties for Preparation of Stents" shortTile="biocompatible-polymer" author="Kateřina Škrlová, Kateřina Malachová, Alexandra Muñoz-Bonilla, Dagmar Měřinská, Zuzana Rybková, Marta Fernández-García, Daniela Plachá" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2079-4991/9/11/1548/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Biofilms</head>
<p>
As mentioned above, the most common problems of stents are due to their clogging due to the formation of biofilm and adhesion of biological substances that pass through the stent. Biofilm represents the most widespread way of microbial growth in nature and is critical for the development of clinical infections. It is produced by bacteria and host products that tend to adhere to different surfaces. They create huge colonies known as biofilms. Existence in biofilms is for them more advantageous because biofilm provides protection for their cells, maintains a homeostasis, and creates a barrier that isolates bacteria from the surroundings. There is extensive communication between bacteria and the effective horizontal transfer of resistance and virulence genes that make bacteria very resistant. Thus, bacteria cells in biofilm are more resistant to toxic substances, UV radiation, mechanical damage, bacteriophages, or predators. They are also more resistant to the immune system and antibiotics in a human or animal body. The surface of the material is very quickly occupied by bacteria because the host products create a biofilm on the material that helps to bind the bacteria. This process takes place in five stages, as can be seen in <figure>Figure 3</figure>. </p>

<p>Biofilms affect many medical applications and are a serious medical problem at the present time. They are found, for example, in catheters, stents, contact lenses, and many other implants. Biomaterials at risk of attaching bacteria together with corresponding body fluids and major components of the host products for bacterial growth are classified in Table 1. The biofilm’s high resistance to antibacterial agents results in a great risk of infection and therefore creates a very hazardous situation for patient health. Microbial cells that live in biofilms have greater resistance to antimicrobial substances than cells that live alone in planktonic form. Due to this resistance, the treatment of biofilm infections is very difficult. Infected implants must be removed from the patient’s body. This procedure is usually expensive and dangerous for patients because surgical procedures can cause other complications. Millions of implants and catheters are used for treatment every year. Table 2 shows examples of implants prone to the infections of biofilms.  </p>

<p>For this reason, new materials are being developed to reduce the risk of biofilm formation and infection. These materials are based on polymer composites or polymers with surfaces modified with an antimicrobial agent. In addition, other options based on physical surface properties such as surface roughening, or vice versa smooth surface, super hydrophobic, etc. should be considered.  </p>
</text>
