<text id="autogum_bio_doc381" title="Ridwan Pasha" shortTile="ridwan-pasha" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-10-10" dateModified="2017-11-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ridwan_Pasha" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ridwan Pasha</head><hi rend="bold">Warning:</hi> Page using <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Infobox_officeholder">Template:Infobox officeholder</ref> with unknown parameter "religion" (this message is shown only in preview).<hi rend="bold">Warning:</hi> Page using <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Infobox_officeholder">Template:Infobox officeholder</ref> with unknown parameter "place of burial" (this message is shown only in preview).
<p><hi rend="bold">Riḍwān ibn Muṣṭafā ibn ʿAbd al-Muʿīn Pasha</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turkish_language">Turkish</ref> transliteration: <hi rend="italic">Ridvan Pasha</hi>; died 2 April 1585) was a 16th-century <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman</ref> statesman. He served terms as governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gaza_Sanjak">Gaza</ref> in the early 1560s and in 1570–1573, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yemen_Eyalet">Yemen</ref> in 1564/65–1567, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Habesh_Eyalet">Habesh and Jeddah</ref> in 1573–1574 and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anatolia_Eyalet">Anatolia</ref> in 1582/83 until his death. During his term in Yemen, Ottoman authority largely collapsed. Ridwan Pasha was the progenitor of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ridwan_dynasty">Ridwan dynasty</ref>, which chose <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gaza_City">Gaza</ref> as its family headquarters, and where members of the dynasty ruled almost consecutively until 1690.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<head>Early career</head>
<p>Ridwan was the son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kara_Şahin_Mustafa_Pasha">Kara Şahin Mustafa Pasha</ref>, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bosnian_people">Bosnian</ref> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Six_Divisions_of_Cavalry">kapikulu</ref></hi> (slave of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sublime_Porte">Sublime Porte</ref>) and later statesman,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Watenpaugh84-2">[1]</ref> who served gubernatorial terms in the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eyalet">eyalets</ref></hi> (provinces) of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Erzurum_Eyalet">Erzurum</ref> (1544–1545), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diyarbekir_Eyalet">Diyarbakir</ref> (1548), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yemen_Eyalet">Yemen</ref> (1556–1560) and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Egypt_Eyalet">Egypt</ref> (1562/63–1565/66).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Blackburn521-3">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[3]</ref> Early in his career, Ridwan was made <hi rend="italic">defterdar</hi> (treasurer) of Yemen,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Zeevi40-5">[4]</ref> after gaining the recommendation of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahmud_Pasha_(governor)">Mahmud Pasha</ref>. In the following years, he was assigned <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sanjak-bey">sanjak-bey</ref></hi> (district governor) of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gaza_Sanjak">Gaza</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Blackburn521-3">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Zeevi40-5">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Governor of Yemen</head>
<p>In November 1564,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Blackburn521-3">[2]</ref> after paying a bribe of 50,000 gold pieces,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Nahrawali202-6">[5]</ref> he was appointed <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beylerbey">beylerbey</ref></hi> (governor-general) of Yemen, replacing Mahmud Pasha,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Blackburn521-3">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Zeevi40-5">[4]</ref> who bribed the Sublime Porte to gain the governorship of Egypt.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Clark16-7">[6]</ref> According to historian Clive Smith, the large sum that Ridwan Pasha paid for the governorship was attributed to his expectation of accumulating large wealth as governor of the province.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Nahrawali202-6">[5]</ref> His predecessor Mahmud Pasha had governed Yemen for seven years, during which he and his subordinates ruled corruptly, plundering the province's gold and extorting the local inhabitants.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[7]</ref> Prior to his dismissal, Mahmud Pasha had succeeded in persuading the Sublime Porte to divide Yemen into two separate provinces: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sana'a">Sana'a</ref>, which consisted of the interior highlands, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tihama">Tihama</ref>, which consisted of the province's central and southern coastal plains. According to the 16th-century Arab chronicler al-Nahrawali al-Makki, Mahmud Pasha's motivation was to leave Ridwan Pasha to govern  the restive highlands, while virtually appointing a subordinate of his to Tihama with its lucrative <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Red_Sea">Red Sea</ref> ports.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Hathaway83-9">[8]</ref> The Sublime Porte may have agreed to the division out of the belief that a single governor for each of Yemen's two regions would serve to help the Ottomans prevent Portuguese attempts to control Yemeni ports and ensure Ottoman control over the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coffee">coffee</ref> trade, which was primarily cultivated in the highlands.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Hathaway83-9">[8]</ref></p>
<p>In 1565, Ridwan Pasha reached a deal with the Sublime Porte in which his trade of Yemeni spices through <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeddah">Jeddah</ref> to Egyptian markets would be exempted from taxation in lieu of his annual gubernatorial salary.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Nahrawali202-6">[5]</ref> In this case, "spices" was synonymous with coffee, the trade of which, since the mid-16th century, financed the salaries of the Ottoman garrisons in Yemen. The coffee was grown in areas dominated by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ismailism">Ismaili</ref> (a sect of Shia Muslims) tribes. Ridwan co-opted the chief Ismaili <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Da'i_al-Mutlaq">da'i</ref></hi> (missionary), giving him and his family several <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iltizam">tax farms</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Hathaway84-10">[9]</ref></p>
<p>As intended by Mahmud Pasha, the division of Yemen highly restricted Ridwan Pasha's personal financial ambitions because his rule was effectively limited to the fortresses of Sana'a and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saadah">Saadah</ref>, with no control over the Red Sea ports. He thus sought to renegotiate a deal made by his father, Kara Shahin Mustafa (r. 1556–1560), with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zaidiyyah">Zaydi</ref> (a sect of Shia Islam) imam, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al-Mutahhar">al-Mutahhar</ref>, calling for extending taxation to the Zaidi-dominated northern highlands, where al-Mutahhar ruled virtually autonomously. Al-Mutahhar refused Ridwan Pasha's demands and opened a rebellion against Ottoman authority in 1566.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Clark16-7">[6]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Hathaway84-10">[9]</ref> By January 1567, all of Sana'a province with the exception of the fortresses of Sana'a and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/`Amran">Amran</ref> had been conquered by al-Mutahhar's Zaidi tribesmen. Ridwan Pasha then called for a truce with al-Mutahhar, whose forces blocked all the roads to Sana'a to prevent the intervention of a potential Ottoman relief force.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Clark16-7">[6]</ref></p>
<p>Ridwan Pasha was dismissed from Yemen in April 1567,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Blackburn521-3">[2]</ref> and was replaced by Hasan Pasha.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[10]</ref> His dismissal prompted him to head for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constantinople">Constantinople</ref>, capital of the empire, to argue his case with the Sublime Porte. He was consequently reprimanded and imprisoned. However, his incarceration was relatively short and he was pardoned in November 1567 when it was discovered that Mahmud Pasha had intercepted and concealed letters from Ridwan Pasha to the Sublime Porte, alerting the imperial authorities of the volatile situation in Yemen; Ottoman authority had largely collapsed in Yemen during Ridwan Pasha's governorship.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Blackburn521-3">[2]</ref> The concealed letters were discovered after Mahmud Pasha was assassinated in Egypt.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Blackburn521-3">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Later career and death</head>
<p>In 1570/71, Ridwan Pasha was reappointed <hi rend="italic">sanjak-bey</hi> of Gaza.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Blackburn521-3">[2]</ref> Ridwan Pasha was then appointed <hi rend="italic">beylerbey</hi> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Habesh_Eyalet">Habesh and Jeddah</ref>, which included parts of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ethiopian_Empire">Abyssinia</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hejaz">Hejaz</ref>, in March 1573. He remained in Gaza for a few months after his reassignment to ensure that arrangements he made with the Sublime Porte regarding the transferring of tax revenues or grain harvests from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qasr_Ibrim">Qasr Ibrim</ref> and its territories to Habesh Eyalet from Egypt Eyalet were confirmed. He demanded further concessions from the Sublime Porte to redirect grain harvests from Egypt to the coffers of Habesh's treasury in June 1574.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Annales-12">[11]</ref> He was dismissed from Habesh in July 1574.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Blackburn521-3">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Sometime following his dismissal from Habesh, he served terms as <hi rend="italic">beylerbey</hi> of Diyarbakir and then <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basra_Eyalet">Basra</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Zeevi40-5">[4]</ref> In 1579, he was a commander in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman–Safavid_War_(1578–90)">Ottoman military campaign</ref> against the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Safavid_Empire">Safavids</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caucasus_Mountains">Caucasus Mountains</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Blackburn521-3">[2]</ref> As a reward for his service,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Zeevi40-5">[4]</ref> the Sublime Porte appointed Ridwan Pasha to the major <hi rend="italic">eyalet</hi> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anatolia_Eyalet">Anatolia</ref> in late 1582 or early 1583.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Blackburn521-3">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Zeevi40-5">[4]</ref> He died in office on 2 April 1585.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Blackburn521-3">[2]</ref> Ridwan Pasha and his brother Bahram Pasha (died 1586), also an Ottoman statesman, were buried in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mausoleum">mausoleum</ref> situated in the garden of a mosque in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aleppo">Aleppo</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Watenpaugh84-2">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Watenpaugh90-13">[12]</ref> The mausoleum was restored in 1924 by Abdullah Bek al-'Ilmi, a descendant of Bahram Pasha.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Watenpaugh90-13">[12]</ref> It is unclear why Ridwan Pasha chose to be buried in Aleppo.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Watenpaugh84-2">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Legacy</head>
<p>Ridwan Pasha (or his kinsmen) evidently made <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gaza_City">Gaza</ref> the headquarters of his family, although the reason why is not provided in the biographies of Ridwan Pasha and Kara Shahin Mustafa which were written by their contemporaries. Ridwan Pasha's son, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ahmad_ibn_Ridwan">Ahmad Pasha</ref>, succeeded him as <hi rend="italic">sanjak-bey</hi> of Gaza, a post he held for roughly 30 years, after which his sons and grandsons virtually inherited the governance of the district. Ridwan Pasha became the progenitor of a dynasty bearing his name, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ridwan_dynasty">Ridwan dynasty</ref>, whose members governed Gaza almost consecutively between 1570 and 1690.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Zeevi40-5">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[13]</ref></p>
</text>
