<text id="autogum_interview_doc840" title="part10_ACLU President Strossen on religion, drugs, guns and impeaching George Bush" shortTile="partaclu-president" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-30" dateModified="2019-02-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/ACLU_President_Strossen_on_religion%2C_drugs%2C_guns_and_impeaching_George_Bush" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You wouldn’t want a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terri%20Schiavo">Terri Schiavo</ref> situation?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  That was an ACLU case; we represented her husband there.  It has to be consenting, but there are measures we can take, and precautions we can take, so there it should be regulated.  I say the same thing about drugs.  You wouldn’t want to have regulation the way we do for food and alcohol, but <hi rend="italic">absolute</hi> prohibition is completely inhumane and counter to the most fundamental autonomy of who you are.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So you have the choice, what is your choice?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  My choice would be to take a sleeping pill, I guess, or maybe <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morphine">morphine</ref> would have the same effect, to peacefully pass from this Earth when I have made a decision that I can no longer live in this state of comfort and dignity that makes <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meaning%20of%20life">life meaningful</ref> to me.</p>
<head id="War_and_threats_to_humanity">War and threats to humanity</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do you think is the greatest threat to humanity right now?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  By that do you mean human existence, or something more subtle?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  However you interpret the question.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  The greatest threat to humanity…  Boy.  The reason why I am pausing is I live so much of my life looking at one set of threats, so I’m not usually asked the comparative question.  See, you’re again getting me out of my box.  I’m usually asked what is the greatest danger to civil liberties, and I don’t have so much hubris to necessarily say, “The greatest threat to humanity is threats to our freedom.”  I guess I would have to take it as the most literal threat.  For many years  I managed to perhaps delude myself that there wasn’t a serious threat of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuclear%20holocaust">nuclear holocaust</ref>, and I don’t think that anymore.  I’m very afraid with reports of Iran having nuclear capabilities, or even individual terrorist groups or terrorist cells having access  to weapons of mass destruction.  That really scares me.</p>
<figure></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How has the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraq%20War">Iraq War</ref> affected your world view?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  It’s made me very concerned about—even more concerned than I always have been—about the future of the world and the future of this country, because I think it’s not only the war itself, but obviously the ripple effects, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraq%20insurgency">insurgency</ref>, the recruitment for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al-Qaida">Al-Qaida</ref> and terrorist groups.  The disenchantment with what I thought and think our country should stand for, but in the world it no longer does stand for: human rights, democracy and justice.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Have you seen a precipitous drop?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  It’s catastrophic.  The damage.  I’m not speaking as a civil libertarian, I’m speaking as a member on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Council%20on%20Foreign%20Relations">Council on Foreign Relations</ref>, looking at what my colleagues in the international human rights movement are telling me, and they meet with the most brutal dictators who say, “I’m just doing what <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George%20W.%20Bush">George Bush</ref> is doing.”</p>
</text>
