<text id="autogum_news_doc611" title="NASA&apos;s InSight Lander makes it to Mars" shortTile="nasas-insight-lander" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2018-11-25" dateModified="2018-12-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NASA%27s_InSight_Lander_makes_it_to_Mars" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>NASA's InSight Lander makes it to Mars</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 29, 2018</hi></p>
<p>On Monday shortly before noon <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US">US</ref> west coast time (2000 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UTC">UTC</ref>), <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NASA">NASA</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/InSight%20lander">InSight lander</ref> successfully touched down on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elysium%20Planitia">Elysium Planitia</ref> on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mars">Mars</ref>. It sent a signal beep and image of the surface of Mars to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jet_Propulsion_Laboratory">Jet Propulsion Laboratory</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/California">California</ref>.</p>
<figure><caption>Artist's rendition of the InSight Lander showing the solar panels in their open position after landing, heat flow instrument in the deployed position, and seismometer. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NASA">NASA</ref>/<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jet_Propulsion_Laboratory">JPL</ref>-Caltech.</caption></figure>
<p>The lander used <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/aerobraking">aerobraking</ref> with a heat shield, then a parachute and finally rockets to achieve a soft landing on the surface. It used similar entry, descent, and landing sequence to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Phoenix_(spacecraft)"><hi rend="italic">Phoenix</hi> spacecraft</ref>.</p>
<p>Insight project manager Tom Hoffman said, "We hit the Martian atmosphere at 12,300 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/miles%20per%20hour">mph</ref> [miles per hour; 19,800 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/kilometres%20per%20hour">kilometres per hour</ref>], and the whole sequence to touching down on the surface took only [six and a half] minutes [...] During that short span of time, InSight had to autonomously perform dozens of operations and do them flawlessly — and by all indications, that is exactly what our spacecraft did."</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">InSight</hi> stands for <hi rend="italic">Interior exploration using Seismic Investigations, Geodesy and Heat Transport</hi>. The lander's two-year mission is to assess what Mars is like underground, determining the planet's heat flow and listening to the reverberations of groundquakes and meteorite impacts.</p>
<p>Acting director of NASA's Planetary Science Division Lori Glaze said, "We've studied Mars from orbit and from the surface since 1965, learning about its weather, atmosphere, geology and surface chemistry [...] Now we finally will explore inside Mars and deepen our understanding of our terrestrial neighbor as NASA prepares to send human explorers deeper into the solar system."</p>
<p>InSight is expected to begin its mission in a few months, once it has placed the equipment on the surface of Mars. Its solar panels are now open, catching sunlight and powering the spacecraft. It is equipped to drive a device up to 16 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/foot%20(unit)">feet</ref> (5 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/metre">meters</ref>) down into Mars's surface, a record for Mars probes. This is to help characterize heat flow from the planet. Insight also has ultra sensitive seismometers which it is to use to detect Mars earthquakes for the first time.  By recording the seismic waves from these quakes, InSight would help scientists infer things about the interior of Mars, such as how seismically active it is. InSight has as single <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/seismometer">seismometer</ref>, with which NASA plans to assess signals from different types of vibrational wave, triangulate their sources, and so derive information about the planetary interior. </p>
<p>InSight was launched May 5 of this year and traveled reportedly 301,223,981 miles (somewhat over 484,773,000 kilometres) between planets followed by two suitcase-sized cube satellites called <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mars%20Cube%20One">Mars Cube One</ref>, individually MarCO-A and MarCO-B, which relayed information to Earth during the landing process.</p>
<p>Previous successful landers on Mars include <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Viking%201">Viking 1</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Viking%202">Viking 2</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mars%20Pathfinder">Pathfinder</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spirit%20rover">Spirit</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Opportunity%20rover">Opportunity</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic">Phoenix</hi>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Curiosity%20rover"><hi rend="italic">Curiosity</hi></ref>. Of these, only <hi rend="italic">Curiosity</hi> is still in communication with Earth, after NASA lost communication with <hi rend="italic">Opportunity</hi> in June. InSight's landing spot in the Elysium Planitia is about 600 km from <hi rend="italic">Curiosity'</hi>s landing site in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gale%20(crater)">Gale Crater</ref>.</p>
</text>
