<text id="autogum_academic_doc299" title="HYBRID: Ambulatory Robotic Gait Trainer with Movement Induction and Partial Weight Support" shortTile="hybrid-ambulatory" author="Eloy Urendes, Guillermo Asín-Prieto, Ramón Ceres, Rodrigo García-Carmona, Rafael Raya, José L. Pons" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1424-8220/19/21/4773/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Related Work</head>
<p>
Wearable exoskeletons that can induce musculoskeletal movement, and therefore help the user perform a healthy gait pattern, are a very popular way of using robotic devices for rehabilitation. Most of them, like Ekso Bionics, HAL, Vanderbilt exoskeleton, or ReWalk are 4DoF (degrees of freedom) lower-limb exoskeletons, and actuate both the hip and knee on the sagittal plane. Recent studies have demonstrated that training using HAL is effective in improving ambulatory mobility for patients with stroke or spinal cord injury. Robotic training led to an improvement in walking parameters and in balance abilities, with increases in the WISCI-II score. Similar results have been achieved using Ekso Bionics. Other devices such as MindWalker, CUHK-EXO, or XoR2 include hip rotation. These ambulatory exoskeletons need crutches to provide stabilization and control the lateral balance during movement. This setup is infeasible for patients that lack good upper body strength or biomechanical coordination. On top of that, they introduce the risk of falls and produce fatigue. These factors make such exoskeletons impractical for many users. </p>

<p>This problem could be avoided by using PBWS (partial body weight support) solutions that unload part of the patient’s body weight by suspending them. This way, the percentage of body weight that the lower body must support during rehabilitation therapy can be tightly controlled. Such strategies have the potential to improve the locomotive capabilities of people with motor deficit by minimizing the muscular effort required and simultaneously reducing the forces and pressures exerted over the user’s skeletal system. Several studies have proved the huge benefits that PBWS solutions have on clinical practice. </p>

<p>However, PBWS was traditionally implemented using fixed structures with either treadmill or rigid frames. Recent solutions have seen the introduction of robotic gait trainers that can combine assisted leg movement with partial weight suspension. This way, crutches are not needed and falls can be totally avoided. These two features are considered mandatory for patients with systemic motor deficit. </p>

<p>Devices like Lokomat, GaitTrainer LOPES, ALEX or C-ALEX integrate an exoskeleton for particular body regions with treadmill and PBWS systems. These solutions enable reproducible and intense therapy sessions while logging objective measures to assess the exercise’s results. These devices are limited in the sense that the patient remains in place, and therefore their proprioception, posture, and dynamic balance systems are not being properly trained and receive conflicting stimuli. </p>

<p>To address these shortcomings, new ambulatory training systems which allow a higher freedom of movement from the patient have been designed, such as WalkTrainer Nature-gaits, SUBAR, EXPOS, the device presented in, MLLRE, or MOPASS. However, solutions such as these present several drawbacks, like the inability to easily move the patients from their wheelchairs to standing position. On top of that, these trainers cannot generate a gait movement synchronized with the system’s absolute speed or force the patient to maintain a posture conductive to put on an exoskeleton—a process involving important physical effort and lengthy preparation times. </p>

<p>This work tries to bridge this gap by presenting an innovative self-propelled ambulatory system for gait rehabilitation with lower body movement induction, PBWS and body stabilization designed for clinical environments, named HYBRID (Hybrid Technological Platform for Rehabilitation, Functional Compensation and Training of Gait in SCI Patients). Our solution enables practitioners to easily transfer patients from a wheelchair to standing position, suspend their weight, and provide assisted gait patterns extracted from healthy users, all while offering safety and comfort. This system is easy to use for both users and practitioners. </p>

<p>The developed system has been financed by the Spanish <hi rend="italic">Plan Nacional</hi>, with support from interested partners like the <hi rend="italic">Hospital Nacional de Parapléjicos de Toledo</hi> (HNPT) and the <hi rend="italic">Instituto Nacional de Educación Física</hi> (INEF), and has received input from other experts in the fields of rehabilitation and gait analysis, helping to focus on the more relevant design issues. </p>
</text>
