<text id="autogum_interview_doc205" title="part6_BDSM as business: Interviews with Dominatrixes" shortTile="partbdsm-business" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-28" dateModified="2008-01-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BDSM_as_business%3A_Interviews_with_Dominatrixes" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Does that make you feel uncomfortable?  Are there some times where you are like, “I don’t want to punish the Jew.” </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  It all depends on the person and how they are taking it.  During session you can tell whether it is going too far, or whether it is something that is very emotional for a person.  You both have to go into it understanding that it <hi rend="italic">is</hi> a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roleplaying">role play</ref>.  And a lot of times they’ll tell me, “Look, it’s okay, you can call me this, this and that.  It’s fine.”</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  With experiences like that, do you experience personal growth and contend with your own hang-ups or why certain things bother you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  It really <hi rend="italic">does</hi>.  It’s surprising how much you learn about yourself and another person.  A lot of things you learn from here—which for some people is surprising—you apply to your own life.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Can you given an example?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Well, you learn to be more open-minded to people.  More understanding to a man’s needs rather than, “This is the way you’re <hi rend="italic">supposed</hi> to be.  This is the way <hi rend="italic">society</hi> has made you.  You can’t <hi rend="italic">be</hi> a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sissy">sissy</ref> maid, you have to be the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Machismo">macho man</ref> all the time.”  You know?  It makes you understand that there are multiple sides to everybody rather than what you see is what you get.  I have worked here for a few months and I am still surprised by the people who come in.</p>
<p>[<hi rend="italic">Rebecca comes in and asks if we will leave The Blue Room for Alex’s session and go to The Gold Room to continue the interview</hi>]</p>
<head id="Psychology_II">Psychology II</head>
<figure><caption>Mistress Veronica in The Gold Room at Rebecca's Hidden Chamber.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is it important for you to know the motivations of the clients?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  It is something you need to be aware of and something you need to be able to tell during your session.  You feel it, you sense it, by speaking with someone and dealing with someone in that way, you are able to tell whether it is an actual problem that they have.  They are very open with us and they tell us a lot of things.  You are in constant discussion.  It’s not just the physical aspect of S&amp;M, where there’s the whipping and spanking, it’s also very verbal.  You are constantly talking to each other and there’s a lot of times where you can tell whether it’s just a regular fetish or whether it is an actual psychological problem these people have.  And there have been a few people like that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Can you give an example?</hi></p>
</text>
