<text id="autogum_interview_doc645" title="part3_Popular soap opera &amp;apos;The Young and the Restless&amp;apos; celebrates 35 years on the air" shortTile="partpopular-soap" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-25" dateModified="2014-04-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Popular_soap_opera_%27The_Young_and_the_Restless%27_celebrates_35_years_on_the_air" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Melody Thomas Scott</hi>: Like it or not, reality television is enjoying its trend right now. It's in a category of its own and can't really be compared to our show or any other daytime drama. I love my <hi rend="italic">Survivor</hi> and real-life crime shows as much as the next guy, but I don't see it as a conflict of viewer choices. The only event I can think of that had a huge impact in the ratings was the O.J. Simpson trial. Everyone was glued to their televisions to watch that circus. Unfortunately, all of daytime programming took a huge hit, with some viewers never returning to their soaps. But that was across the board and affected all of the programming at that time.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Michelle Stafford</hi>: I don't think it's bad for business because we are still employed, and it doesn't seem to be affecting us.  I don't watch those shows so I can't have too much of an opinion on them.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tricia Cast</hi>: Yes, I said it 20 years ago on the <hi rend="italic">Donahue</hi> show. We're lucky to have jobs because reality programming is a threat to scripted shows everywhere.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi>: What do you feel is the one major reason for the show staying at the top of the ratings for 19 years? Do you feel you contributed to the show's ratings strength in some fashion?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Melody Thomas Scott</hi>: Ed Scott. Now I can finally say it! [editor's note: Ed Scott is the former producer of Y&amp;R, and Melody Thomas Scott's husband] Of course without the individual excellence of our writing staff, performers, and every other area such as set decoration, lighting, camera work, etc., it wouldn't get the viewers' attention. The contributions of all the talented people we are lucky enough to have makes our show the unique piece of art that it is.  Synergy!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Michelle Stafford</hi>: Oh God, yes, of course! [<hi rend="italic">laughs</hi>] No. It's a group thing. It's a group endeavor for a show like this. One person doesn't carry it. I think not a lot people leave the show.  The production value is really great. There are extremely talented people who work on our show and I'm not just talking about actors, I'm talking about the crew [as well].</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tricia Cast</hi>: As a whole the show sparkles. The Young and the Restless is the <hi rend="italic">best show</hi> on daytime. It's been number one with and without me.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi>: Do you feel Y&amp;R, through its longevity and popularity, has influenced other shows? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Melody Thomas Scott</hi>: One would think so, but I have not yet seen another show equal to our production values.  I think they have tried, but have not succeeded. Maybe they just don't know how!</p>
</text>
