<text id="autogum_voyage_doc2" title="Boston/Dorchester" shortTile="bostondorchester" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=4381" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Boston/Dorchester</head>


<p>So, you've decided to visit <hi rend="bold">Dorchester</hi>. Congratulations! Boston's largest neighborhood had long been written off, dismissed as “too dangerous” by those who had never set foot here. But longtime residents — or “Dot Rats” — have always known what the rest of <ref target="Boston">Boston</ref> is beginning to rediscover. An area close to downtown and the ocean, replete with beautiful parks, charming old architecture, and good public transit. An area with a diverse and inclusive population, and additionally one of the more affordable spots in Boston. When you consider these assets as a whole, it should come as no surprise that many are giving the neighborhood a second look.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Due to Dorchester's large size it can be helpful for the traveller to think of it in two halves, north and south. The northern half is more traditionally urban. Houses are packed tightly together, people walk everywhere, all accompanied by the traffic and street noise one might expect. Due to its proximity to downtown, the majority of new development is taking place here as well. A huge cineplex, mall expansion, and many new condos are under construction as of 2016. The southern half, by contrast, continues to retain a more suburban feel. City lots are a bit roomier, large condo buildings become less common while trees become more prevalent. Driving is slightly less stressful and even necessary in some areas. Stitching these two halves together is Dorchester Ave. Running from <ref target="Boston/South%20Boston">South Boston</ref> to <ref target="Milton%20%28Massachusetts%29">Milton</ref>, Dot Ave is by far the neighborhood's most powerful connector of people and places. Yes, the big draw here is JFK Presidential Library, but to really experience Dorchester you should allow some time to investigate the people and places along this main street.</p>

<head>Neighborhoods</head>
<p>Again, Dorchester is huge. If it were an independent city, it would be the 4th largest in the state. Consider this a severely abridged list of just a few of the areas you may be interested in visiting. Also take these names with a pinch of salt. In a place this old, it can feel like every intersection has a special name or used to be called something else.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ashmont:</hi> The general area around Ashmont station has been transformed in recent years, showcasing a rebuilt train station in 2011 and several new shops and restaurants. The residential hills to the east and west of the station have deep Irish-American roots, and boast some of the finest houses anywhere in the city. The Kennedys' family home was in this area. Ashmont is also one of the few areas in the south Dorchester where some mid-rise buildings have been going up. It remains to be seen what type of impact they will have on the neighborhood. You might also hear this area called Ashmont Hill or Peabody Square. Another neighborhood, Adams Village, is very close by and has a similar Irish color.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fields Corner:</hi> A variety of cultures meet and shop in this bustling commercial district. Conveniently clustered shops selling a vast array of goods draw shoppers from nearby African-American, Vietnamese, and Irish enclaves. During the warmer months the community park is in almost constant use with kids playing baseball, neighborhood festivals, or families barbecuing. This area could also be considered the center of the Vietnamese community in Boston. You can find many Vietnamese restaurants, places of worship, and community centers in the vicinity.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lower Mills:</hi> On the shores of the Neponset River and functioning as Boston's southern gateway, Lower Mills is decidedly upmarket. Once the heart of chocolate manufacturing in the region, many picturesque old factory buildings have been painstakingly restored and converted into hundreds of luxury condos. Following the arrival of new residents, new and old retailers alike have wasted no time updating their offerings in order to cater to this expanding community. Lower Mills is also a great area to get outdoors. Bike or walk along miles of trails and paved paths to check out some of the best green space Boston has to offer.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">South Bay:</hi> Not an official neighborhood per se, but worth noting with all the construction going on in the area. This part of Dorchester is by far its largest commercial district. Anchored by big box stores like Target, Home Depot, and Best Buy among many others. Its proximity to South Boston and the <ref target="Boston/South%20End">South End</ref> make it a neighborhood crossroads of sorts, and developers are pouring money in. It's surprisingly easy to drive here, due to the large parking lot and interstate highway nearby.</item>
</list>


<head>By public transit</head>

<p>The T's <hi rend="bold">Red Line</hi> runs frequent service to much of Dorchester. Trains run about every 8 minutes, more during rush hour and less often at night. <hi rend="bold">JFK/UMass</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Savin Hill</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Fields Corner</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Shawmut</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Ashmont</hi> stations all provide the neighborhood with convenient links to downtown Boston. Be aware that the Red Line splits into two separate branches at JFK/UMass, so make sure you board an Ashmont bound train! JFK/UMass also provides Dorchester with its only connection to several South Shore commuter rail lines. Trains on the <hi rend="bold">Greenbush</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Kingston</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Middleborough/Lakeville</hi> lines stop here. On the western border with <ref target="Boston/Roxbury">Roxbury</ref>, the <hi rend="bold">Fairmount</hi> commuter rail has stations at <hi rend="bold">Newmarket</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Uphams Corner</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Four Corners/Geneva</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Talbot Avenue</hi>. This line runs on an infrequent schedule, around once an hour, but the city planned to increase service by 2018.</p>

<p>Ashmont station is the terminus of the Red Line, as well as the <hi rend="bold">Ashmont-Mattapan High Speed Line</hi>. This is a quaint 1940s era trolly system that locals continue to use everyday as they go about their business. The trolley stops in <hi rend="bold">Cedar Grove</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Butler</hi> before continuing on to Milton and <ref target="Boston/Outer%20Neighborhoods">Mattapan</ref>. Ashmont is also the largest bus depot in Dorchester. From here the <hi rend="bold">#21</hi>, <hi rend="bold">#22</hi> and <hi rend="bold">#23</hi> busses run to different points along the <hi rend="bold">Orange Line</hi>. Lines <hi rend="bold">#215</hi>, <hi rend="bold">#217</hi>, <hi rend="bold">#240</hi>, <hi rend="bold">#245</hi> are less frequent and run to <ref target="Quincy%20%28Massachusetts%29">Quincy</ref> and Milton. While the <hi rend="bold">#27</hi> runs to Mattapan. There are a few other bus connections from Fields Corner and JFK/UMass that also run to the Orange Line. There is even a bus (<hi rend="bold">#18</hi>) that runs up and down Dorchester Ave, but good luck with that. There are no bus connections from Savin Hill or Shamut stations.</p>
</text>
