<text id="autogum_voyage_doc299" title="Eastern Cape" shortTile="eastern-cape" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=10357" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Eastern Cape</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.visiteasterncape.co.za/">Eastern Cape</ref></hi> is in <ref target="South%20Africa">South Africa</ref> and stretches along the Indian Ocean between <ref target="Western%20Cape">Western Cape</ref> and <ref target="KwaZulu-Natal">KwaZulu-Natal</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>The Eastern Cape province includes the former "homelands" of Transkei and Ciskei. With a long coastline on the Indian Ocean it offers great beaches as well as several very interesting National Parks. Its population is mainly Xhosa-speaking and the province is home to several of South Africa`s most important persons in the fight against Apartheid (e.g. Nelson Mandela, Thabo Mbeki, Steve Biko and Oliver Tambo). It's still a poor province especially in the former homelands but beautiful and not so touristy.</p>

<head>Regions</head>

<p>The Eastern Cape can be divided in the following regions:</p>

<head>Cities</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> - The capital of the Eastern Cape</item>
<item> - the largest city in the province is connected to the rest of the country by flights, motorways and rail.</item>
<item> - the second largest city is accessible by plane, car and train and is the starting point for traveling to the former Transkei and <ref target="Wild%20Coast">Wild Coast</ref>.</item>
<item> - heart of the Settler Country offering traditional atmosphere.</item>
<item> (formerly called Umtata) - the main city in the former Transkei.</item>
<item> - the capital of the Karoo desert and a national heritage site.</item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> - backpackers haven with two famous hostels and a great atmosphere.</item>
<item> - high up in the Amathole mountain range, surrounded by indigenous forests with hiking trails and waterfalls.</item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
</list>


<head>National parks</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> At least 400 elephants all sizes, great accommodation, book through parks Board, 30 mins by car from <ref target="Port%20Elizabeth">Port Elizabeth</ref></item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Book through the Parks Board</hi>) phone: <hi rend="italic">+27</hi> 21 423 8005. Wonderful coastal scenery with great hikes and walks, nice accommodation, between <ref target="Plettenberg%20Bay">Plettenberg Bay</ref> and <ref target="Humansdorp">Humansdorp</ref> including the famous <hi rend="bold">Otter Trail</hi>.</item>
</list>


<head>Other nature reserves</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> , <ref target="http://www.ecparks.co.za"></ref></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Commando Drift Nature Reserve</hi>, 60 km east from Cradock. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Dwesa and Cwebe Nature Reserve</hi>, dutywa. Two small reserves separated by the Mbashe River, next to the Indian Ocean near Elliotdale.</item>
</list>


<head>Private game reserves</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kragga Kamma Game Park</hi>. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Seaview Game &amp; Lion Park</hi>, ☏ +27 42 378-1702 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Schotia Safaris Game Reserve</hi>, ☏ +27 42 235-1436 . Huge stock of game with free roaming lions. One gets the safari feeling here without paying through the nose. Ggame drive, meal and drink R600pp or staying overnight, with evening and morning drive, meals and drinks for R1200pp..</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Shamwari Game Reserve</hi>, ☏ +27 42 203-1111 . The most well-known and luxurious of the private game reserves in the Eastern Cape. </item>
</list>


<head>By car</head>

<p>The main motorway in the province is the N2. It runs along the coast from <ref target="Cape%20Town">Cape Town</ref> via the <ref target="Garden%20Route">Garden Route</ref>, <ref target="Port%20Elizabeth">Port Elizabeth</ref>, the Transkei and further through <ref target="KwaZulu-Natal">KwaZulu-Natal</ref> and <ref target="Mpumalanga">Mpumalanga</ref>. The road condition is mainly excellent except in the Transkei (<hi rend="italic">Do not travel the Transkei portion of the N2 at night as the potholes can be deep and there are often stray animals ie cows and goats wandering around</hi>).</p>

<h4>From <ref target="Cape%20Town">Cape Town</ref></h4>
<p>Follow the N2 via the <ref target="Overberg">Overberg</ref> and into the <ref target="Garden%20Route">Garden Route</ref></p>

<h4>From <ref target="Gauteng">Gauteng</ref>, <ref target="Free%20State">Free State</ref>, <ref target="Limpopo">Limpopo</ref> and <ref target="Mpumalanga">Mpumalanga</ref></h4>
<p>Follow the N1 toll road south until <ref target="Colesberg">Colesberg</ref>, then follow the N9 from there towards <ref target="Graaff-Reinet">Graaff-Reinet</ref> and <ref target="George">George</ref> or follow first the N9 and then the N10 towards <ref target="Port%20Elizabeth">Port Elizabeth</ref>. Avoid driving the N9 and N10 at night as game often wander onto the road at night and accidents are not uncommon. A full grown kudu or other large antelope can cause some severe damage to you and your vehicle.</p>

<head>By plane</head>

<ref target="Port%20Elizabeth">Port Elizabeth</ref> and <ref target="East%20London">East London</ref> are the main national airports both with several flights daily to other South African destinations, but no international flights.

<head>By train</head>

<ref target="http://www.southafricanrailways.co.za/">Spoornet</ref> operates regular trains from <ref target="Johannesburg">Johannesburg</ref> to both <ref target="Port%20Elizabeth">Port Elizabeth</ref> and <ref target="East%20London">East London</ref>. There is also a once-weekly service from <ref target="Cape%20Town">Cape Town</ref> to <ref target="East%20London">East London</ref>, a daily service between <ref target="Grahamstown">Grahamstown</ref> and Alicedale and a weekend-only service between <ref target="East%20London">East London</ref> and <ref target="Mthatha">Mthatha</ref> (via Amabele).

<head>By car</head>

<p>Definitely the best option if you are more than two as several regions and some of the National Parks aren't accessible by public transport. Road Conditions are mainly good but get informed before you start. Car rental is available in larger cities and along the popular resorts of the Garden Route.</p>

<p>Be careful of wild animals, especially monkeys, on the road. Be especially careful if driving at night.</p>

<head>By bus</head>

<p>The main companies cross the Eastern Cape on their way from <ref target="Cape%20Town">Cape Town</ref> to <ref target="Durban">Durban</ref>. There are other main routes from <ref target="Port%20Elizabeth">Port Elizabeth</ref> and <ref target="East%20London">East London</ref> to <ref target="Johannesburg">Johannesburg</ref>.</p>

<p>The Baz Bus traverses the province on its <ref target="Cape%20Town">Cape Town</ref> - <ref target="Port%20Elizabeth">Port Elizabeth</ref> - <ref target="Durban">Durban</ref> run ; <ref target="Port%20Elizabeth">Port Elizabeth</ref> is a compulsory overnight stop.</p>

<p>Minibus services are available for local transport between neighbouring towns (and also on several longer distances).</p>

<head>By train</head>

<p>With the limited range of railways this isn't really a viable option for touring the province. However, the route from <ref target="Grahamstown">Grahamstown</ref> to Alicedale is very scenic and well worth doing. The newly opened line from <ref target="East%20London">East London</ref> to <ref target="Mthatha">Mthatha</ref> also traverses some dramatic scenery through the <ref target="Wild%20Coast">Wild Coast</ref>.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Port%20Elizabeth">Port Elizabeth</ref>: the provincial capital and major transportation hub</item>
<item> <ref target="East%20London">East London</ref>: Gateway to the Wild Coast</item>
<item> <ref target="Grahamstown">Grahamstown</ref>: University town with a colonial English atmosphere</item>
<item> <ref target="Graaff-Reinet">Graaff-Reinet</ref>: a national heritage site and the classical example of an inland town.</item>
<item> <ref target="Wild%20Coast">Wild Coast</ref>: spectacular scenery and only a few tourists make this an out-off-the-beaten track destination</item>
<item> <ref target="Morgan%27s%20Bay">Morgan's Bay</ref>: Seaside village with magnificent cliffs that plunge into the sea.</item>
<item> <ref target="Kei%20mouth">Kei mouth</ref>: Southern gateway to the <ref target="Wild%20Coast">Wild Coast</ref> via one of South Africa's two remain pontoon car ferries.</item>
<item> <ref target="Tsitsikamma%20National%20Park">Tsitsikamma National Park</ref>: not as spectacular as some of the other National Parks it offers superb coastlines, whale watching and excellent hiking.</item>
<item> <ref target="Addo%20Elephant%20National%20Park">Addo Elephant National Park</ref>: famous for the elephants this park is after the unification with Zuurberg NP one of South Africa`s largest. Also has lion.</item>
<item> <ref target="Mountain%20Zebra%20National%20Park">Mountain Zebra National Park</ref> - small, but only very few people there. See the endangered Mountain Zebras.</item>
</list>
</text>
