<text id="autogum_reddit_doc086" title="I (29m) have never dated and am looking for a wife" shortTile="m-never-dated-looking" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-04-30" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8g3zl9" speakerList="#faradaysdream, #kingrazor001" speakerCount="2">
<head>I (29m) have never dated and am looking for a wife</head>
<sp who="#kingrazor001">
<p>I've never been in any sort of romatic relationship before. When I was 12 I had a "girlfriend" and we kissed one time. I've never actually dated anyone. I'm personally not interested in dating for the sake of dating. My end goal is to be married. I have no clue where to start. I haven't had a female friend since high school. Where do I even begin? I don't plan on going around asking strangers to marry me or anything, but like I said I don't care about getting into the dating scene for the sake of dating alone. Any advice?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#faradaysdream">
<p>It’s cool to have the goal of dating be marriage...but its probably not a good plan to just randomly marry the first girl that cooperates. </p>
<p>If a person doesn’t have options, they’ll settle for less than they deserve because lack of options breeds desperation. </p>
<p>You need to create options for yourself. Do you have male friends? Do you go out often?(not to bars...do you have hobbies? Rock climbing, ultimate frisbee, board games, etc?). If you’re not meeting men and women, you need to get out more...take up new hobbies. Join a meet up group for hiking or something. </p>
<p>If you meet a lot of women but find that none of them want to date you or be your friend...then you might need to spend some time working on yourself. Become the best version of yourself. Start working out (if you don’t already), get a different haircut, practise talking to more people (maybe you’re socially awkward?)....make yourself more desirable to women. </p>
<p>What I’m trying to say is...have fun. Do things that interest you, and you’ll be interesting to others. Work on becoming a great friend, and a good listener....because a key component to any marriage is friendship. My husband is my best friend. Dress in flattering clothing...if you don’t know if you’re looking good, go to the mall and get help with buying fashionable clothes. </p>
<p>Envision your perfect wife...think of all of the traits she would have. Then think about the kind of man she would want to marry. The kind of man she’d respect and admire...and become that man. </p>
<p>I did that to meet and marry my husband....but I had to (authentically) become the type of person he would want to be with (I hadn’t met him yet...I liked his type though). </p>
<p>Anyway, it’s not as complicated as it sounds...but self improvement, or changing your habits (to meet more people) is challenging. But it’s worth it :)</p>
</sp>
</text>
