<text id="autogum_academic_doc718" title="Teachers Co-Designing and Implementing Career-Related Instruction" shortTile="teachers-codesigning" author="Anssi Salonen, Sirpa Kärkkäinen, Tuula Keinonen" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2227-7102/9/4/255/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Discussion</head>
<p>
The teachers explained how difficult it is to integrate careers in science education and needed novel educational methods to overcome this challenge. Thus, their goals and interests (cf.) and their need for change led them to co-designing an educational innovation. They wanted to involve the researcher and a real professional in designing the instruction combining science knowledge with the career of a dentist and her explanations about the chemistry issues with teeth. It was important for them to include this information in their local curriculum as proposed in previous research. The teachers experienced a high sense of ownership and agency towards the instruction, even though they were not involved in all phases of the co-design process. The results of teachers’ high ownership and agency aligns with the students’ perception of a successfully implemented co-designed career-related instruction. </p>

<p>The teachers highlighted the visual and informative appearance of the co-designed scenario and agreed that the virtual and personal contact with the dentist through video engaged students in following science inquiries. Thus, the design and other ideas of the co-designers were supported. Retrospective interviews revealed that they have continued to use and develop the scenario further. In addition, they have shared it and discussed it with their colleagues. This is a sign of feeling ownership as Pierce et al. argues. </p>

<p>When teachers are free to implement the co-designed scenario and the rest of the learning unit in their own way, it promotes their autonomy and further experiences of agency, which is particularly important when the teachers are used to high autonomy in their work. After all, the results of the co-design process show that the teachers participated in all the phases except creating videos for the scenario and career-related activities. However, the teachers need the freedom to change everything in the scenario and learning unit and in this case, they used this possibility a few times when they felt it was necessary. The teachers perceived that it was easy to implement the scenario and it was successful. Nevertheless, in such a co-design process teacher can lose some aspects, for example, feelings of control and autonomy, but gain others such as a professional’s viewpoint and new knowledge. In the end, the teachers appreciated that the learning unit was relevant and interesting for the students, but they were also interested in the students’ perceptions. </p>

<p>The results reveal that the students found that the scenario starting the instruction was relevant for them personally and for society. Their perceived high vocational relevance, particularly with vocational knowledge, suggests that it is possible for this kind of instruction to correct possibly existing career stereotypes. According to the teachers and students, it seems that the problem assigned to the students personally by the dentist had an impact on students’ interest in the following learning activities. Earlier studies confirm that these kinds of real-world connections and student-scientist partnership are relevant and increase students’ interest in science. The results and previous research reveal it is not always easy or possible to create and implement this kind of authentic environment. However, the artificially created interaction between students and professional in the designed instruction helps with the problem of resources and access to experts. </p>

<p>Even though the career of a dentist probably was familiar to the students before, the students perceived that they learned more about the skills and responsibilities needed in the career. Thus, career-related instruction gives students new knowledge, not only about scientific topics, but also about careers and needed working life skills and responsibilities in a career. All these raise students’ career awareness and gives them accurate perceptions of STEM careers, which is assumed to increase the number of students choosing STEM studies and careers. Considering that generally Finnish secondary school students are not that interested in science studies or science-related careers, their future career aspirations were moderate. The students’ interest in the scenario was high and it might raise their interest towards learning science. </p>

<p>As said, teachers, but also students, appreciated the scenario’s attributes and appearance. Something new and different always arouses interest. Videos, connection with a professional, freedom to choose and create inquiries, and using creativity in reporting results makes science learning relevant and interesting for the students and involves them in scientific processes and decision making. Without the career introduction and interaction with the professional, students might learn the same scientific knowledge and skills but lose connections and understanding how and why their knowledge and skills are relevant outside the school context. </p>
</text>
