<text id="autogum_news_doc564" title="Wikinews Shorts: February 20, 2014" shortTile="wikinews-shorts-february" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-02-18" dateModified="2014-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_Shorts%3A_February_20%2C_2014" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews Shorts: February 20, 2014</head><p>A compilation of brief news reports for<hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 20, 2014</hi>.
</p>
<hi rend="italic">Contribute to Wikinews by <ref target="//en.wikinews.org/w/index.php?title=Main_Page&amp;action=edit">expanding</ref> these briefs or <ref target="//en.wikinews.org/w/index.php?title=Main_Page&amp;action=edit&amp;section=new&amp;preload=Template:New_Wikinews_Shorts_item">add a new one</ref>.</hi>
<head id="Ukrainian_truce_established">Ukrainian truce established</head>
<figure><caption>Kiev's Independence Square before violence erupted. Image: Noobuster007.</caption></figure>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ukraine">Ukraine</ref>'s President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Viktor_Yanukovych">Viktor Yanukovych</ref> declared a truce after a violent evening in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kiev">Kiev</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maidan%20Nezalezhnosti">Independence Square</ref>. There was brief peace just five days ago when protesters agreed to unblock downtown streets. That was soon broken as violence occurred when interior ministry troops, special "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berkut%20(Ukraine)">Berkut</ref>" security forces, and police officers confronted protesters. </p>
<p>So far 26 people, including protesters and ten police officers, have been killed in Independence Square clashes. This is the most violence the country has seen since it gained independence 20 years ago.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sources</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Nick Paton Walsh, Greg Botelho and Victoria Butenko. "<ref target="http://www.cnn.com/2014/02/19/world/europe/ukraine-protests/index.html?hpt=hp_t1">Truce declared in bloodied Ukraine, but will it last through talks?</ref>" —<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CNN">CNN</ref></hi>, Wed February 19, 2014</item>
<item>Ian Traynor and Harriet Salem. "<ref target="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/feb/19/ukraine-black-day-protest-kiev">Ukraine suffers 'black day' that will never be forgotten</ref>" —<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Guardian">The Guardian</ref></hi>, Wednesday 19 February 2014</item></list>
<head id="Facebook_plans_to_purchase_messaging_service_for_US$16_billion">Facebook plans to purchase messaging service for US$16 billion</head>
<figure><caption>WhatsApp logo Image: WhatsApp Inc..</caption></figure>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Facebook">Facebook</ref> yesterday announced a plan to purchase <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WhatsApp">WhatsApp</ref> for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_dollar">US$</ref>16 billion. Facebook's plan says it will pay US$12 billion in stocks and US$4 billion in cash. All parties are still waiting regulatory approval. The deal could potentially be worth US$19 billion with US$3 billion more being offered to employees. Employees who remained at Facebook for four years would be offered restricted stock. </p>
<p>WhatsApp is a messaging service where users can send text, picture, and video messages using their data plans, instead of their messaging plan. The company has over 450 million world-wide active users, with about 70 percent of those users being active daily. WhatsApp adds about one million new users per day. Facebook founder <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mark_Zuckerberg">Mark Zuckerberg</ref> said the app will not change for users.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sources</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Julianne Pepitone. "<ref target="http://www.nbcnews.com/tech/mobile/facebook-buy-whatsapp-whopping-16-billion-n34031">Facebook to Buy WhatsApp for a Whopping $16 Billion</ref>" —<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NBC_News">NBC News</ref></hi>, February 19, 2014</item>
<item>Allstair Barr. "<ref target="http://www.usatoday.com/story/tech/2014/02/19/facebook-buys-whatsapp/5617657/">Facebook agrees to buy WhatsApp for $16 billion</ref>" —<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/USA_Today">USA Today</ref></hi>, February 19, 2014</item></list>
<head id="Australia_releases_confidential_information_of_thousands_of_refugees">Australia releases confidential information of thousands of refugees</head>
<p>The records of around 10,000 asylum-seekers in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia">Australia</ref> were made available by the Australian government until <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Guardian">The Guardian</ref></hi> made authorities aware yesterday the data was freely accessible. Confidential refugee files were accessed, featuring the  names, nationalities, locations, and arrival information. Paul Power, chief executive of the advocacy group Refugee Council of Australia, said the situation risked those in refugee centers in Australia, as well as their families. </p>
<p>In a speech delivered last November, Immigration Minister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scott%20Morrison%20(politician)">Scott Morrison</ref> said that the Australian government was responsible for protecting the identities of refugees. Now the
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Department%20of%20Immigration%20and%20Border%20Protection">Department of Immigration and Border Protection</ref> is being called to account for its role under Australia's privacy laws, including negligence.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sources</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item> "<ref target="http://www.japantoday.com/category/world/view/australia-mistakenly-publishes-asylum-seekers-names-other-personal-details">Australia mistakenly publishes asylum seekers' names, other personal details</ref>" —<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Japan%20Today">Japan Today</ref></hi>, February  19, 2014</item>
<item>Oliver Laughland, Paul Farrell and Asher Wolf. "<ref target="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/feb/19/asylum-seekers-identities-revealed-in-immigration-department-data-lapse">Immigration Department data lapse reveals asylum seekers' personal details</ref>" —<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Guardian">The Guardian</ref></hi>, February 18, 2014</item></list>
</text>
