<text id="autogum_interview_doc747" title="part2_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green Party candidate Lloyd Helferty, Thornhill" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-07" dateModified="2013-04-19" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Green_Party_candidate_Lloyd_Helferty%2C_Thornhill" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>The Green Party in essence, is attempting to bring a measure of direction and purpose back into the Political realm by re-establishing a set of base “values” from which we can move forward and agree upon as common goals for human society, and this, I believe, is where the electorate is missing the point.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly?</hi></p>
<p>My priority, if elected, would be to halt all expansion / new development on our more essential lands and work at bringing in a form of Land Value Taxation.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are the property taxes in your riding at a fair level for the amount of services received in the municipality?</hi></p>
<p>No. Property taxes are likely not high enough for the new developments, for they are a burden on the downstream (or upstream) services [like the electrical, water and sewer networks].  The initial development charges were not high enough to cover all of the costs of expanded services for these new developments, so it is likely that tax rates would need to be higher for the newer developments, however we also now have a situation where the older developments are undergoing the slow decay of their built infrastructure, which will potentially require a complete overhaul of their services [primarily water and sewage systems, but also roads and other hard infrastructure], which may require the intervention of the Province to assist these communities in undertaking upgrades.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How can the province lead the way in stimulating job creation?</hi></p>
<p>The province must vocally and monetarily encourage a shift in the direction we are headed with respect to the manufacturing sector.  Our reliance on the traditional automobile manufacturing sector for a large chunk of our economy can only be detrimental to the prospects for jobs as the entire industry haemorrhages in North America for lack of innovation.  We need to diversify our economy into new energy technology and value-added goods and services rather than taking a narrow view and only making our province “attractive to investors” and relying on corporations to provide the employment opportunities.  The government should become much more proactive in helping to establish new companies by providing ‘seed money’ and business expertise where necessary to encourage entrepreneurs to move faster toward creating the infrastructure necessary to make our society more sustainable.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What are your views on the mixed member proportional representation (MMP) referendum?</hi></p>
<p>I am completely in favour of the system. MMP will guarantee Green representation at Queen's Park. Something that is long overdue.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What role, if any, does "new media" play in your campaign, and the campaign of your party? (websites, blogs, Facebook, YouTube videos, etc) Do you view it as beneficial, or a challenge?</hi></p>
</text>
