<text id="autogum_news_doc364" title="After Eurovision win, Norwegians show their patriotism on Constitution Day" shortTile="eurovision-win-norwegians" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-05-17" dateModified="2014-05-19" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/After_Eurovision_win%2C_Norwegians_show_their_patriotism_on_Constitution_Day" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>After Eurovision win, Norwegians show their patriotism on Constitution Day</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, May 17, 2009</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Oslo schoolchildren taking part in the Children's Parade at the Royal Palace on 2005's Constitution Day. People from all over Norway celebrated the national holiday today with festivals and parties.</caption></figure>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander%20Rybak">Alexander Rybak</ref>'s win for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Norway">Norway</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eurovision%20Song%20Contest%202009">Eurovision Song Contest</ref> on Saturday evening was well-timed; it was on the eve of Norway's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norwegian%20Constitution%20Day">Constitution Day</ref>. </p>
<p>Constitution Day, observed on May 17, commemorates the first Norwegian constitution drafted at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eidsvoll">Eidsvoll</ref> in 1814. Now it celebrates Norwegian independence as a whole, which was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dissolution%20of%20the%20union%20between%20Norway%20and%20Sweden%20in%201905">granted by Sweden</ref> in 1905.</p>
<p>Eurovision win aside, Norwegians don't necessarily need a good reason to celebrate Constitution Day; the Norwegian people are some of the most patriotic in Europe and the iconic <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flag%20of%20Norway">national flag</ref>, red with a white and indigo blue Scandinavian cross, can be seen waving from buildings and in the hands of most Norwegians at festivals and parties.</p>
<p>Prime Minister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jens%20Stoltenberg">Jens Stoltenberg</ref>, on a visit to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Spain">Spain</ref>, was greeted by 2,000 Norwegian expatriates waving flags in the town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Torrevieja">Torrevieja</ref>, where he gave a speech, giving warm greetings in both Spanish and Norwegian. Stoltenberg noted that 40,000 Norwegians live in Spain, roughly 1% of Norway's current population, and was impressed by the turnout not only from Norwegian citizens but also from Spanish people who also helped celebrate Norway's Constitution Day. Stoltenberg was later joined by Spanish and Norwegians at the old sailor's church in Torrevieja, where he placed a wreath commemorating fallen Norwegian sailors.</p>
<figure><caption>Boy Scouts, a symbol of Norwegian patriotism, march with Norwegian flags down Karl Johans gate in the 2005 Constitution Day parade.</caption></figure>
<p>In Norway, the annual Oslo <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norwegian_Constitution_Day#Children.27s_parades">Children's Parade</ref>, a national institution, occurred in the morning with children from all 111 of Oslo's schools taking part. The children walked with brass bands playing festive music up Oslo's main street, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karl%20Johans%20gate">Karl Johans gate</ref>, to the Royal Palace where they were warmly greeted by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norwegian%20Royal%20Family">Royal Family</ref>. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haakon,%20Crown%20Prince%20of%20Norway">Crown Prince Haakon</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mette-Marit,%20Crown%20Princess%20of%20Norway">Crown Princess Mette-Marit</ref>, who greeted children in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asker">Asker</ref> earlier in the morning, toured the Oslo ward of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grünerløkka">Grünerløkka</ref> in the afternoon. All celebrations in Norway went off with few errors, the most notable being the delay of trains using the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oslo%20Tunnel">Oslo Tunnel</ref>, in which a helium balloon floated into the tunnel, causing a brief scare for train operators.</p>
<p>Celebrations for Norway's Constitution Day occurred all over the world, from a gathering in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shanghai">Shanghai</ref> hotel where 300 Norwegians feasted on imported traditional Norwegian foods, to a street parade in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brisbane">Brisbane</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Australia">Australia</ref>, where the police had to stop traffic for the revelers. Norway's neighbor <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sweden">Sweden</ref> was especially happy on Constitution Day, where Norwegian-Swedes dressed in folk costumes and held up copies of the newspaper <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Expressen">Expressen</ref></hi>, who deemed Norway's winning Eurovision song "the best winner since <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ABBA">ABBA</ref>" and published a large headline in Norwegian, stating "We look forward with you."</p>
<p>Constitution Day will end with Norway's new national hero Rybak, deemed "Alexander the Great" in the Norwegian newspapers, arriving at Oslo's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oslo%20Airport,%20Gardermoen">Gardermoen airport</ref> at 9:25 p.m. local time (1925 UTC). Record crowds are expected to greet him, as he invited everyone via <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norwegian%20Broadcasting%20Corporation">state television</ref> to the airport for his trip home.</p>
</text>
