<text id="autogum_voyage_doc217" title="French cuisine" shortTile="french-cuisine" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=151061" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>French cuisine</head>


<p>Many people of <ref target="France">France</ref> regard their <ref target="food">cuisine</ref> to be the best in the world. France is the origin of the <hi rend="italic">Guide Michelin</hi> rating system, and ties <ref target="Japan">Japan</ref> (which has twice the population) for the highest number of stars in the guidebook.</p>

<p>French cuisine has set a standard for <ref target="fine%20dining">fine dining</ref> around the world, and menus in high-end Western restaurants are often printed in French.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>French cuisine has roots back to the <ref target="Roman%20Empire">Roman Empire</ref>. Influenced by <ref target="Italian%20cuisine">Italian cuisine</ref> as well as local traditions, <hi rend="italic">haute cuisine</hi> was created in <ref target="Paris">Paris</ref> during the Early Modern times. The French Revolution put an end to guilds and the privileged noble class, expanding fine cooking and dining to common people.</p>

<p>While foreign cuisines such as <ref target="Mexican%20food">Mexican food</ref>, <ref target="American%20fast%20food">American fast food</ref> and <ref target="Chinese%20food">Chinese food</ref> have been less successful in France than in other parts of Europe, they can be found in Paris and the other more cosmopolitan cities. <ref target="North%20African%20cuisine">North African</ref>, Vietnamese and <ref target="Middle%20Eastern%20cuisine">Middle Eastern cuisine</ref>s are among those that have been imported from former French colonies and taken root in the former mother country. At least some North African food has been fully assimilated, as a survey in the 1990s found that couscous was the most popular French food (so described by the respondents) in France.</p>

<p>Conversely, French cuisine has also influenced the cuisines of its former colonial possessions, with the cuisines of <ref target="Quebec">Quebec</ref> and <ref target="Louisiana">Louisiana</ref> having a strong French influence, albeit with the incorporation of many local North American flavours and ingredients, and a modified version of the French baguette has been widely adopted in <ref target="Vietnam">Vietnam</ref> for use in the ubiquitous <hi rend="italic">bánh mì</hi> sandwiches.</p>

<head>Meals</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Breakfast</hi> (<hi rend="italic">petit déjeuner</hi>) in France isn't the most important meal of the day, and is usually very light. The most typical breakfast consists of a coffee and a croissant or some other "viennoiserie", but since it implies going to the boulangerie early in the morning to buy fresh croissants, it's typically reserved for somewhat special occasions. On normal days most people have a beverage (coffee, tea, hot chocolate, orange juice) and either toast ("tartines" made of baguette or toast bread with butter and jam/honey/Nutella) that can be dipped in the hot beverage, or cereals with milk. People who eat healthy may go for fruit and yoghurt. As a general rule, the French breakfast is mostly sweet, but anything can change and you can have savoury breakfasts everywhere today.</p>

<p>Both <hi rend="bold">lunch</hi> (<hi rend="italic">déjeuner</hi>) and <hi rend="bold">dinner</hi> (<hi rend="italic">dîner</hi>) are traditionally full meals. They often consist of an appetiser (<hi rend="italic">entrée</hi> or <hi rend="italic">hors d'œuvre</hi>), a main dish (<hi rend="italic">plat</hi>), and a dessert (<hi rend="italic">dessert</hi>) or cheese. Restaurants usually serve dinner between 19:30 and 21:30.</p>

<head>Ingredients</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Bread">Bread</ref></hi> (<hi rend="italic">pain</hi>) is the classical side order in France. The <hi rend="italic">baguette</hi>, a plain wheat roll, is the archetypal bread.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Cheese">Cheese</ref></hi> (<hi rend="italic">fromage</hi>) comes in hundreds of varieties, and can be included in most dishes. It often makes up a dessert. Here is a far from exhaustive list of what one can find:</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Bleu des Causses</item>
<item> Livarot</item>
<item> Roquefort</item>
<item> Bleu du Vercors</item>
<item> Morbier</item>
<item> Saint Nectaire</item>
<item> Boulette d'Avesnes</item>
<item> Maroilles</item>
<item> Salers</item>
<item> Brie de Meaux</item>
<item> Munster</item>
<item> Sainte Maure de Touraine</item>
<item> Brie de Melun</item>
<item> Murol</item>
<item> Selles-sur-Cher</item>
<item> Broccio</item>
<item> Neufchâtel</item>
<item> Saint Marcellin</item>
<item> Camembert</item>
<item> Ossau-Iraty</item>
<item> Sainte Maure de Touraine</item>
<item> Cantal</item>
<item> Pelardon</item>
<item> Tomme de chèvre</item>
<item> Chaource</item>
<item> Pérail</item>
<item> Tomme des Cévennes</item>
<item> Comté</item>
<item> Picodon</item>
<item> Valençay</item>
</list>



<ref target="Vegetarianism">Vegetarianism</ref> has made broad strides in the first two decades of the 21st century, and while restaurants with at least one veggie option used to be the exception they are now the rule. Meanwhile more and more <hi rend="italic">cartes</hi> feature at least one vegan (<hi rend="italic">végétalien</hi>) item.

<head>Regional dishes</head>
<p>Every French region has dishes all its own. These dishes follow the resources (game, fish, agriculture, etc.) of the region, the vegetables (cabbage, turnip, endives, etc.) which they grow there. Here is a small list of regional dishes which you can find easily in France. Generally each region has a unique and widespread dish (usually because it was food for the masses):</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cassoulet</hi> (<ref target="Southwest%20France">Southwest France</ref>) : beans, duck, pork &amp; sausages</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Choucroutes</hi>, or sauerkraut (<ref target="Alsace">Alsace</ref>) : stripped fermented cabbage + pork</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fondue Savoyarde</hi> (central Alps) : melted/hot cheese with white wine</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fondue Bourguignonne</hi> (<ref target="Burgundy">Burgundy</ref>) : pieces of beef (in boiled oil), usually served with a selection of various sauces.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Raclette</hi> (central Alps) : melted cheese &amp; potatoes/meat</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pot-au-feu</hi> (found all over France) : boiled beef with vegetables</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Boeuf Bourguignon</hi> (Burgundy) : slow cooked beef with red wine gravy</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Gratin dauphinois</hi> (<ref target="Rh%C3%B4ne-Alpes">Rhône-Alpes</ref>) : oven-roasted slices of potatoes with sour cream and cheese</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Aligot</hi> (Aveyron) : melted cheese mixed with a purée of potatoes</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bouillabaisse</hi> (fish + saffron) (<ref target="Marseille">Marseille</ref> and the <ref target="French%20Riviera">French Riviera</ref>). Don't be fooled! A real bouillabaisse is a really expensive dish due to the amount of fresh fish it requires. Be prepared to pay at least €30 per person. If you find restaurants claiming to serve bouillabaisse for something like €15 per person, you'll find it to be of a very poor quality.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tartiflette</hi> (<ref target="Savoie">Savoie</ref>) : Melted Reblochon cheese, potatoes and pork or bacon.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Confit de Canard</hi> (south west) : Duck Confit, consists of legs and wings bathing in grease. That grease is actually very healthy and, with red wine, is one of the identified sources of the so-called "French Paradox" (eat richly, live long).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Foie Gras</hi> (south west) : The liver of a duck or goose. Although usually quite expensive, foie gras can be found in supermarkets for a lower price (because of their purchasing power) around the Christmas season. It is the time of year when most foie gras is consumed in France. It goes very well with Champagne.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Moules marinières</hi> (found anywhere there's a coast) : Mussels steamed in white wine, garlic and shallots, normally served with crusty bread and French fries (<hi rend="italic">moules-frites</hi>, which are Belgian in origin). There are numerous regional varieties. Add cream and sometimes lardons, then you've got <hi rend="italic">moules <ref target="Normandy">normandes</ref></hi>. Ditch the wine and cook in cider, and enjoy <hi rend="italic">moules <ref target="Brittany">bretonnes</ref></hi>. Or throw in tomatoes and <hi rend="italic">herbes de Provence</hi> (savory, marjoram, rosemary, thyme, oregano) for <hi rend="italic">moules à la <ref target="Provence-Alpes-C%C3%B4te%20d%27Azur">provençale</ref></hi>.</item>
</list>
</text>
