<text id="autogum_interview_doc119" title="part5_Wikinews interviews specialists on China, Iran, Russia support for al-Assad" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-09-15" dateModified="2015-10-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_specialists_on_China%2C_Iran%2C_Russia_support_for_al-Assad" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<figure><caption>File photo of interviewee Farideh Farhi. Image: Farideh Farhi.</caption></figure>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Kamrava</hi>: No. While sectarianism may be the lens through which some of the Syrian rebels see their fight against the government, ultimately the contest is over state power and capitalizing on opportunities created by the Arab uprisings in general; and, the Syrian civil war in particular. Sunni–Shia 'alignments' have nothing to do with it.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Posch</hi>: Usually, the Sunni–Shia divide is something Iranians and Saudis play up in order to put pressure on one another; usually, they were also able to deescalate. Syria, however, is the game-changer — for the simple reason that nobody believes the Saudis would control the post <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Al-Qaeda">Al-Qaeda</ref> Networks in Syria. What Iran fears is an increase of the most-radical Sunni anti-shiism, the so called takfiris, spilling over onto Iranian territory.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Farhi</hi>: The Sunni governments in the region are working hard to use sectarian tensions as an instrument to fan popular resentments, in the region, towards Shi'ite Iran. But, the rivalry is actually political; and, has to do with the fears rivals have of what they consider — I think wrongly — to be Iran's hegemonic aspirations in the region.</item></list>
<p>Sectarianism is an instrument for shaping regional rivalries, and not the source of problems, in the region.</p></p>
<head id="Russia">Russia</head>
<figure><caption>Former Russian president <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dmitry_Medvedev">Dmitry Medvedev</ref>, meeting Syrianan president Bashar al-Assad, on a visit to Syria in 2010. Image: Russian Presidential Press and Information Office.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Russia is one of Syria's biggest arms suppliers. Do you think this means Russia's interest lies in economic benefit, as opposed to the humanitarian crisis?</p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Blank</hi>: Although Russia sells Syria weapons, Russia's main interest has nothing to do with humanitarianism or economics.</item></list>
<p>Rather, its main interests are to force the US to accept Russia as an equal — so that <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Moscow">Moscow</ref> has an effective veto power over any further American actions of a strategic nature there and elsewhere — and second, to restore Russia's standing as an indispensable great power in the Middle East without whom nothing strategic can be resolved.</p>
<p>It should be noted that in neither case is Russia actively interested in finding solutions to existing problems.  Rather, it seeks to create a bloc of pro-Russian, anti-American states and maintain simmering conflicts at their present level while weakening US power.</p></p>
<figure><caption>File photo of interviewee William Martel. Image: William Martel.</caption></figure>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Martel</hi>: Russia's principal interests in Syria are twofold. First, Moscow's support is geopolitical in design. It is designed precisely to undermine and weaken American influence in the Middle East and globally. The extent to which Russia can undermine American influence directly helps to bolster Russia's influence. For now, Russia is such a vastly diminished power — both politically, economically, militarily, and technologically — that Russian policymakers are pursuing policies they believe will help to reverse Russia's strategic decline.</item></list>
<p>Second, Syria is Russia's strongest ally in the region, if not the world, while Syria is the home to Russia's only foreign naval base.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Farhi</hi>: Syria is Russia's only solid strategic ally in the Middle East. Syria, in effect, is a Russian client. Russia's interests lie in maintaining that foothold, and perhaps extending it.</item></list>
<p>It also has a concern regarding the civil war in Syria spawning what it considers to be extremist Islamist activities, which it has had to contend with within its own borders.</p></p>
</text>
