<text id="autogum_whow_doc530" title="Register an Animal" shortTile="register-animal" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-02-18" dateModified="2019-09-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Register-an-Animal" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Register an Animal</head><p>If you have some sort of disability, you may want or need a support animal to help you in your day-to-day life. The 2 main types of support animals are service animals and emotional support animals. These different types of support animal are subject to different laws and certification requirements. However, once you know what this necessary certification is, getting the right paperwork for your animal is a breeze.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Qualifying for a Support Animal</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Determine what type of support animal you need. Service dogs are individually trained to perform critical daily functions for people with physical or psychiatric disabilities. Emotional support animals (ESA), on the other hand, are not trained, but instead offer support for individuals suffering from psychiatric or emotional disabilities. <figure rend="Register an Animal Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Most individuals with service dogs suffer from a severe disability, such as blindness or asthma, that makes it very difficult to perform major life tasks. These dogs are then trained to help the individual perform that major life task (e.g., helping a person with limited sight get around in public).</item>
<item>The Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA) defines “disability” very broadly, so don't feel like yours isn't a “real” disability just because it's not as bad as someone else's. Anything that makes a normal function of life difficult qualifies as a disability.</item></list></item>
<item>Have a doctor formally diagnose your disability. Although this isn't required by law, a doctor will be able to tell you whether obtaining or training a service dog is the best thing for you. If you don't already have a dog, the doctor may also be able to refer you to a reputable provider of properly trained service animals. <figure rend="Register an Animal Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Note that you're not required to obtain a service dog from a professional training program. You can also train your own service dog yourself, if you feel up to the task.</item></list></item>
<item>Be prescribed an emotional support animal for any mental health issues. ESAs are not covered by the ADA, but they are still protected by other laws that prevent discrimination against disabled individuals. In order for your animal to be covered, though, it needs to have been formally prescribed to you by a mental health professional. <figure rend="Register an Animal Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This prescription can be in the form of a formally written letter from your therapist or counselor, stating that the presence of your ESA is necessary for your mental or emotional health.</item>
<item>The Fair Housing Act (FHA) says that landlords cannot bar your ESA from living with you, while the Department of Transportation also requires airlines to allow passengers with mental and emotional disabilities to fly with their ESAs.</item></list></item>
<item>Make sure your animal is well-behaved enough to be a support animal. Apart from the particular training that service dogs are required to have, the only other behavioral requirement for support animals is that they not behave inappropriately in public. This can include behaving aggressively, biting or scratching other dogs or people, toileting inappropriately, or otherwise disrupting business. <figure rend="Register an Animal Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If your support animal is not well behaved, businesses can then legally bar you and your animal from entering the premises, since the animal constitutes a “direct threat” or “fundamental alteration” to their business.</item></list></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Train_a_Dog">Train your dog</ref> to do a vital function, if you want it to be a service dog. Remember, service dogs must be able to do a specific task, not just provide emotional support. If you already own a dog, teach it to help you perform a major life task in order to have it qualify as a service dog. <figure rend="Register an Animal Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This task can be something as simple as helping you cross the street if you have limited vision or barking for assistance when you have trouble breathing.</item>
<item>Note that this type of training can be very time-consuming, sometimes taking several years. If your disability is particularly urgent, you may be better off just buying a dog that has already been trained.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Getting the Right Paperwork</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Get certification for your ESA from a mental health professional. Have your therapist, counselor, or psychiatrist write you a formal letter stating that you have a mental or emotional disability and that having your ESA is necessary for your mental health. If possible, have your doctor write this letter on a professional letterhead to give it an added layer of legitimacy. <figure rend="Register an Animal Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you don't have a formal therapist, or your therapist is unwilling to write you a letter, you may be able to use an online mental health service to acquire this type of letter. However, be very careful when using this type of service, since many of these types of websites may be scams.</item></list></item>
<item>Carry this letter with you so you can use it as documentation for an ESA. You'll need to provide this letter to a landlord or airline employee who asks to see your ESA's certification. Just to be safe, keep a scanned copy of this letter in your home while carrying the other copy with you at all times. <figure rend="Register an Animal Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Note that this is the only documentation the law requires ESAs to have.</item></list></item>
<item>Avoid paying a website to “register” your support animal. Apart from having a formal letter from a mental health professional, support animals are not required by law to be certified or registered to any database. Websites that try to sell this type of certification are usually trying to sell to people who don't actually know the law, so just steer clear of them. <figure rend="Register an Animal Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Oftentimes, people will pay to “register” their pets as support animals because they think it's required or they think it makes their support animal look more official. In reality, anyone who understands the law will probably think the person using this type of certification doesn't actually qualify for a support animal.</item></list></item>
<item>Be aware that you don't need to show documentation for a service dog. According to the ADA, business owners and employees are not allowed to demand documentation for your service dog. Instead, they're only allowed to ask if the animal is required because of a disability and what task the animal has been trained to do. <figure rend="Register an Animal Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Owners and employees are also not allowed to demand that the dog demonstrate its task or ask about the nature of your disability.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
