<text id="autogum_reddit_doc122" title="Your favorite and/or most memorable dungeons?" shortTile="favorite--memorable" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-04-30" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8fzz32" speakerList="#LaMystika, #Xantrox" speakerCount="2">
<head>Your favorite and/or most memorable dungeons?</head>
<sp who="#LaMystika">
<p>Since it's now on my mind, I wanna share some of my favorite and/or most memorable dungeons in JRPGs: Shinra Building (Final Fantasy VII): still one of my favorite dungeons ever and it just felt...  <hi rend="bold">organic</hi>  and not a place that just exists because the plot demands it. It's a perfect modern take on the final castle... only it's like 6-8 hours in. Ultimecia's Castle (Final Fantasy VIII): Still one of my favorite final dungeons ever. The bosses, the gimmick, and that music... it just had an air of finality to it a lot of games lack. Nortune Sewers (Xenogears): mostly for the atmosphere. Redrum lurking in the sewers added tension to that entire scenario. Dead Sea (Chrono Cross): not gonna lie, the first time I went here and saw that time had just  <hi rend="bold">stopped</hi>  creeped me out. That image of the waves frozen in time is in my head to this day. Club Zodiac (Persona 2 Eternal Punishment): the most shining example of the rumor system in action; you can literally make this dungeon easy or difficult solely on whether or not you wanna spread a rumor about it. Sumaru TV (Persona 2 Eternal Punishment): the reason why I like Eriko's route more. I liked the puzzle of it, since it was based on the Eight Trigrams. Also, I liked the weird thumping club music that played during it. Zhaoyang Village (Shadow Hearts): the first village in the game and it set the tone for how the rest of the game was gonna go. A village of cannibals? Walking on corpses as you go deeper into it (with those sound effects)? Creepy af. Las Vegas (Shadow Hearts From the New World): the whole motif was just exciting since you're basically getting involved in a gang fight in a hotel. I thought it was cool rolling up in random rooms and kicking gangsters' asses, and that finale was good, too. Chichen Itza and Machu Picchu (Shadow Hearts From the New World): I still remember these two because they're based on actual places, and their themes started playing in my head as I typed this. E.S.S. Zenethra (Tales of Xillia): the dungeon itself is nothing special; I put it here because I love its jazz theme. It rented space in my head  <hi rend="bold">immediately.</hi>  Artorius' Throne (Tales of Zestiria): I think this is the best looking final dungeon of the modern Tales games and it's not even close. It also looks  <hi rend="bold">different</hi>  from all of them. The Berseria equivalent isn't nearly as good, but there's a reason for it. Sword Valley, Mechonis Field, and Agniratha (Xenoblade): Sword Valley just  <hi rend="bold">sounds</hi>  metal af, Mechonis Field  <hi rend="bold">is</hi>  metal af (down to the battle theme), and Agniratha is one of the most depressing parts of the game in context. Haunted Mansion (The Last Story): a totally optional area and yet I thought it was super cool. It had one of the best boss fights in the game, and the party banter during the entire quest is just  <hi rend="bold">tremendous.</hi>  And finally... Persona 5's Palaces. They're all great. Even Mementos. Sorta. This got super long, but what are your thoughts?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#Xantrox">
<p>Definitely Osohe Castle from Mother 3. Its layout is pretty fun, and the best part is that you get to visit it several times throughout the main story, each time discovering new places and entrances. Enemies have cool designs, and the ghosts are chill dudes. </p>
<p>Another one is the Volcano in Paper Mario 64. Very fun place, the atmosphere is amazing, lots of interaction with the scenario, and a pretty cool Boss.</p>
</sp>
</text>
