<text id="autogum_voyage_doc323" title="Low German phrasebook" shortTile="low-german-phrasebook" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=132776" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Low German phrasebook</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Low German</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Low Saxon</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Plattdüütsch</hi>) is a Germanic language spoken by about 5 million people world-wide. Most people living in northern <ref target="Germany">Germany</ref> and eastern <ref target="Netherlands">Netherlands</ref> (the Low Saxon language spoken in the Netherlands is considered a different language called Dutch Low Saxon, more information at <ref target="Dutch%20Low%20Saxon%20phrasebook">Dutch Low Saxon phrasebook</ref>) use it as a second language. The language that will be treated on this page is thus the Low Saxon dialect spoken in northern Germany. Low German is an official dialect. Historically, it used to be the first language of the <ref target="Hanseatic%20League">Hanseatic League</ref> during the Middle Ages, and thus it had a certain prestige that came to vanish during the 16th century. Low German has also had a significant influence on such Scandinavian language as <ref target="Danish%20phrasebook">Danish</ref>, and even more <ref target="Swedish%20phrasebook">Swedish</ref>. It also had a certain influence on the development of the modern <ref target="Dutch%20phrasebook">Dutch</ref> language as well as on <ref target="German%20phrasebook">High German</ref>.</p>

<p>Low German is not a unified language, but rather an 'aggregate' of similar dialects having a common origin and common intelligibility, but sometimes showing few phonological and lexical differences. It took time to provide Low German with an efficient writing style; several were proposed and used. The 'SASS writing style' (<hi rend="italic">Sass'sche Schrievwies</hi>), first proposed in 1935 by German linguist Johannes Sass, has now officially been recognised and is the most used one. It is the writing system used on the Low German Wikipedia and on official writings in Low German.</p>

<head>Difficulties</head>

<p>Since Low German is not a unified dialect, it sometimes differs from one dialect to the other. However, the Low German dialects from western Germany are the easiest to understand, as they show a certain level of uniformity. Eastern dialects are often harder to understand, and they often contain more High German words or general influence. The Plautdietsch language, spoken in former Prussia, is a daughter-language of Low German, but is still understandable if you speak Low German.</p>

<p>Another even bigger hardship if you're trying to practice your Low German is the fact that most people in Northern Germany, whether Low German-speakers or not, will be more inclined to speak either English or High German with a stranger, rather than a dialect.</p>

<head>Situation within Low German dialects, and relation to other languages</head>

<p>Within the Low German speaking area (that is to say, the north of Germany, especially the Länder of Westphalia and Lower Saxony), there are often differences between the dialect people speak. A word can be the same when written, but pronounced in two different ways. Low German dialects from the West are however considered to be 'purer' than those from the eastern Germany, especially the dialect from Hamburg and Bremen. These two cities were historically - and are still nowadays - at the heart of the Low German historical speaking area. East-Frisian Low German (Oostfrees'sch Plattdüütsch - Ostfriesisches Plattdeutsch in High German) is the direct descendant of the Old Saxon language, the historical ancestor of Low German and sister language of Old English (Anglo-Saxon).</p>

<p>Low German's ancestor Old Saxon was the language of the Saxon tribes that didn't go to England. With genetic - and linguistic - insight, it is the English's closest sister language (with Frisian). However, 1,000 years of evolutions of both languages got the English and Low German to differ significantly. Loads of similarities remained though, but no mutual intelligibility is possible with long speeches between both languages. Only a couple of words are easily recognizable, whereas other words are spelled the same but pronounced differently such as: <hi rend="italic">"he drinkt en Glas Water"</hi> which corresponds to English <hi rend="italic">"he drinks a glass of water"</hi> which should sound relatively understandable to an English-speaker, once you see it spelled out.</p>

<p>But Low German is most known in Germany to be mutually intelligible with Dutch, and in fact both languages share more than a simple similarity in basic vocabulary or grammar. Historically, Middle Low German and Middle Dutch grew together in a kind of linguistic continuum across the northern regions of Germany and the South of the Netherlands and Belgium. The Saxons and the Dutch lived in mutual intelligibility, and this allowed the two languages - despite a few grammatical and phonetic differences - to grow together and to have a certain influence on each other. Even the writing system of Low German was highly influenced by Dutch, especially the way it treats long vowels. Some vocabulary of modern Low German still contains a certain Dutch influence, such words as <hi rend="italic">trecken</hi> (to pull), <hi rend="italic">wachten</hi> (to wait) or <hi rend="italic">Wiel</hi> (a wheel) displaced their Low German rivals <hi rend="italic">tehn</hi>, <hi rend="italic">töven</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Rad</hi> out of Dutch influence. This doesn't mean that <hi rend="italic">trecken</hi>, <hi rend="italic">wachten</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Wiel</hi> aren't of Low German origin, they simply came to be the most common words (at least in the western parts of the Low German-speaking area) for <hi rend="italic">to pull</hi>, <hi rend="italic">to wait</hi> and <hi rend="italic">a wheel</hi> because of their resemblance with their Dutch counterparts.</p>

<head>Pronunciation</head>
<p>Low German has some vowel sounds that are not known in many other languages so they may be hard to learn.</p>

<head>Short vowels</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> a : like 'a' in "calm", (but shorter)</item>
<item> e : like 'e' in "pen"</item>
<item> i : like 'i' in "pin"</item>
<item> o : like 'o' in "fork"</item>
<item> u : like 'oo' in "too" (but shorter)</item>
<item> ä : (Umlaut, transcribed as 'ae') like 'e' in "ten", 'a' in "band"</item>
<item> ö : (Umlaut, transcribed as 'oe') like 'i' in "Sir" (not a sound in English)</item>
<item> ü : (Umlaut, transcribed as 'ue') like 'ew' in "EWWW (disgust)"</item>
<item> y : same as 'ü', but also consonant "j" in words of foreign origin ("Yacht")</item>
</list>


<p>Umlauts are usually (but not always) stressed.</p>

<head>Long vowels</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> a, aa, ah : like 'aa' in "Afrikaans"</item>
<item> e, ee, eh : like 'a' in "day"</item>
<item> ie, ieh : like 'ea' in "sea"</item>
<item> o, oo, oh : like 'o' in "ago"</item>
<item> u, uu, uh : like 'oo' in "too"</item>
<item> ä, ää, äh : somewhat similar to ee, like 'a' in "day" without the 'i' sound at the end</item>
<item> ö, öö, öh : similar to 'e' in "mercy"</item>
<item> ü, üü, üh : like 'ü' in German "München", but longer</item>
</list>
</text>
