<text id="autogum_interview_doc478" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Australian Paralympic wheelchair basketballer Shelley Chaplin" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-01-03" dateModified="2014-06-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_Paralympic_wheelchair_basketballer_Shelley_Chaplin" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> No, not the gold! Not yet! Two silvers and a bronze!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I was sure you'd be saying "I've already got the silver and the bronze. Give me the gold!"</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> Yeah, that's exactly what I was saying! No, I think we just had a young team and...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Well, the team's pretty much the same one as in Athens isn't it?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> No! There was probably only four players from Athens that were the same. We've got a lot of young players that are just sort of coming into their own in wheelchair basketball, so.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What I noticed was when I looked over the statistics of basketball over the time you've been playing, the scores have been going up. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> Yes. I think that's partly to do with that we changed to a size six ball, so we went to a women's ball. Until 2006 we were still playing with a size seven, which is a men's ball. So we changed that. I think that helped with our statistics, 'cause it's easier for women to handle the ball and stuff like that. I also think there's been a big increase in the professionalism of wheelchair basketball internationally, so you have a lot of people who are training every day for this. Whereas I know leading into Athens not everyone was training full time. But now everyone's a full time athlete.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  So you are a full time athlete?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> Yep, I was. Leading into <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2012_Summer_Paralympics">London</ref> I was. So from halfway through 2011 till the Paralympics — so, probably a year — I was a full time athlete. So we trained three times a day, five days a week. Play on the weekends.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  So you got a grant from the government?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> Yep, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Australian%20Sports%20Commission">Australian Sports Commission</ref> supports us. And so does <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basketball%20Australia">Basketball Australia</ref> obviously. [...]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  That's pretty intense though. Have you taken a break since then?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> Yeah, since London I haven't played any basketball. Been doing a lot of different things.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Like what?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> Just gotten into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/handcycle">hand cycling</ref> actually.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Oh okay.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> Yeah, so myself and one of my team mates, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leanne%20del%20Toso">Leanne del Toso</ref>, who was in London as well, we have decided to do a fund raiser. So we're going to ride around the perimeter of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Fiji">Fiji</ref>. And so it's 550 kilometres in ten days. So I'm going to be on a hand cycle, and Leanne, who can walk, is going to be on a real bike. She has really weak legs. So we're going to do that. Raise some money and awareness for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Women's_sports">women in sport</ref>.</p>
</text>
