<text id="autogum_academic_doc623" title="Impact of Vitamin D Deficit on the Rat Gut Microbiome" shortTile="impact-vitamin-d" author="Iñaki Robles-Vera, María Callejo, Ricardo Ramos, Juan Duarte, Francisco Perez-Vizcaino" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6643/11/11/2564/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The gut microbiota is an ecological community constituted by a large number of bacteria, archaea, protists, fungi and viruses. The microbiota produces multiple metabolites that may cross the intestinal barrier and exert biological effects. The microbiota also impacts on the integrity of the gut barrier. Gut barrier dysfunction may result in bacterial translocation from the intestines with increased plasma lipopolysaccharides (LPS). Multiple studies have found a relationship between the microbiota and adequate metabolic, hormonal and immunologic homeostasis. Gut dysbiosis, i.e., an altered composition of the intestinal microbiota in disease is associated with poor health outcomes. Dysbiosis may be treated with probiotics, i.e., live strains of selected bacteria, or prebiotics, food components that modulate the microbiota. Multiple metabolic, cardiovascular, and respiratory diseases including type 2 diabetes mellitus, obesity, systemic and pulmonary hypertension, atherosclerosis, heart failure and chronic respiratory diseases have been linked to impaired gut microbiota. Dysbiosis is frequently characterized by: (a) lower microbial diversity and richness, (b) changes in the relative abundance of phyla with an increased <hi rend="italic">Firmicutes</hi> to <hi rend="italic">Bacteroidetes</hi> ratio (F/B), and (c) changes in short chain fatty acids (SCFA) producing bacteria with a relative increase in lactate-producing bacteria and a relative decrease in acetate- and butyrate-producing bacteria. </p>

<p>Vitamin D is produced from dermal exposure to sunlight or from the diet and is converted in the liver into 25-OH-cholecaciferol or calcifediol (25OHVitD), whose measure serves as an indicator of the vitamin D status. This is further metabolized mainly in the kidney into 1-α,25-dihydroxycholecalciferol, the most active form, also named calcitriol, which activates the vitamin D receptor (VDR). Vitamin D deficiency, which causes rickets and osteomalacia, is very common worldwide due to insufficient solar light exposure and/or a reduced dietary intake. Besides this well-known regulatory role in the calcium-phosphorus and bone homeostasis, vitamin D is also involved in the control of other physiological processes, such as cellular growth, intracellular metabolism and innate and adaptive immunity. Vitamin D deficiency has also been related to infection, cancer and respiratory and cardiovascular diseases. Immune cells and peripheral tissues can also synthetize calcitriol and express VDR. Thus, vitamin D has been proposed to have immunomodulatory properties and insufficient vitamin D levels may lead to dysregulation of immune responses. Moreover, vitamin D is able to induce the expression of antibacterial proteins and exert antibiotic effects in a variety of cell types. </p>

<p>We hypothesized that a deficiency in vitamin D induces changes in the gut microbiota. </p>
</text>
