<text id="autogum_reddit_doc063" title="My (31F) coworker (29F), who is my superior, asked if she could crash at my house on certain days" shortTile="f-coworker-f-superior" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-04-30" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8g3bel" speakerList="#K8Simone, #lostmitten" speakerCount="2">
<head>My (31F) coworker (29F), who is my superior, asked if she could crash at my house on certain days</head>
<sp who="#lostmitten">
<p>I have been working for this particular company for almost 9 years. When I first started, I was very green, so I required a fair amount of training in all aspects that this company specializes in. It's a very male dominated industry, so she and the admin lady are the only ladies at this company other than myself. When I first started, she was going through some personal issues and her negative feelings were seeping into the work life. Long story short, she was not a nice person to me at the beginning. But as the personal issues disappeared or were solved, her attitude changed a fair amount. By that I mean that she became pleasant enough to not consider quitting on a daily basis because of her. However, one thing did not change throughout the years: her cheapness and ingratitude. A favor I’ve done for her quite a few times over the years is give her rides to random places. I never get as much as a please or thank you, let alone a beer or offered some money. Now, this is something I wouldn’t say about (or expect it from) someone who offers at least some amount of reciprocity, but there is no reciprocity. Ever. In 2017, she moved outside the city to a town at least an hour away from work. She typically works from home at least one day a week, and stays with friends during other days in order to minimize the amount of commutes. Except now the friends’ situations have changed and my coworker is looking for other people to use for sleeping. I say "use" because she freely admitted that's what she's doing. As you may have guessed, I’m one of those “lucky” people. I live with my fiancé, who when asked what his thoughts were on the request, gave a resounding no – he hated having roommates. Plus, he knows my coworker personally. So here we are now – I spent the entire weekend stressing and being anxious about how to say no. I’m very worried that she will make being coworkers awkward and will revert to being mean and rude to me. Any thoughts on how to word my declining her request? TL;DR: My (31F) work superior (29F) has asked if she could crash at my and fiance’s house, and she’s not welcome. I’m having trouble saying no. </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#K8Simone">
<p>&gt;Any thoughts on how to word my declining her request? </p>
<p>“Ooo, it’s just really not a good time right now.” (Which is technically true and she doesn’t need to know that it’ll never be a good time. </p>
<p>If she asks for details, oh you don’t want to bore her with all your problems. </p>
</sp>
</text>
