<text id="autogum_academic_doc220" title="Enhancement of Viscoelastic and Electrical Properties of Magnetorheological Elastomers with Nanosized Ni-Mg Cobalt-Ferrites as Fillers" shortTile="enhancement-viscoelastic" author="Siti  Aishah Abdul Aziz, Saiful  Amri Mazlan, U Ubaidillah, Muhammad  Kashfi Shabdin, Nurul  Azhani Yunus, Nur  Azmah Nordin, Seung-Bok Choi, Rizuan  Mohd Rosnan" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1944/12/21/3531/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Magnetorheological elastomer (MRE) is one of the smart materials consisting of micron size magnetic particles embedded in rubber matrix. The rheological properties of MRE can be tuned continuously and reversibly by the external magnetic field. This kind of smart material has potential applications including dampers, sensors, and actuators for vibration systems. Currently, researchers in the field of MRE are mainly focused on the effect of different elastomer matrices, types of magnetic particles, the effect of the particle sizes, and the shapes of the magnetic particles. Silicon rubber (SR) has been widely used in MRE fabrication as the matrix due to its softness which can lead to a high MR effect. Meanwhile, carbonyl iron particles (CIPs) have been widely used in MRE fabrication due to their high magnetic saturation, high permeability, and low remanence. In addition, additives and fillers also have been introduced in MRE fabrication to strengthen the interaction between the matrix and the CIP and hence improve mechanical, rheological, and electrical properties. On the other hand, a few researchers endeavored to fabricate MRE using the nanoparticles as magnetic particles to achieve large surface area, stable chemical reaction, and easy surface modifications. Mordina et al. introduced two types of different shapes of CoFe2O4, spherical and fiber in silicon-based nanocomposites, and found that the nanofibers enhanced the magnetic saturation as low as 5 wt.%, but the saturation tended to decrease at a higher loading of 10 wt.% due to the low formation of interconnected network of nanofibers. Despite this, by implementing the nanoparticles as an additive or filler in MRE, the magnetic and rheological properties of MRE can be appropriately tuned. Commercially available additives such as carbon black, graphite, ester, oils, and carbon nanotubes have been used in MRE fabrication and have proven to enhance various performances of MRE as compared to the original MRE without these additives. Aziz et al. introduced a few types of multiwall carbon nanotube (MWCNTs) as an additive in MRE fabrication. The results demonstrated that with the addition of 0.1 wt.% of MWCNTs, the magnetic saturation of MRE is slightly changed, as the saturation of MRE is increased up to 4%. In a similar work, Poojary et al. fabricated MRE with different percentages of carbon nanotube (CNT), 0.1 wt.% to 0.5 wt.%, as additives and found that the stiffness and loss factor was the highest with the addition of 0.25 wt.% CNT, whereas MRE without CNT exhibited the highest MR effect of 48%. Padalka et al. synthesized Fe, Co, and Ni nanowires and fabricated 10 wt.% of each in MRE composite. Their study focused on the strain and frequency with compression mode showing that MRE with Fe and Co exhibited the highest MR effect at 1% strain and tended to drop at 2% strain. Meanwhile, Yu et al. used the nanoparticles for MRE fabrication as a coating material for the damping applications. They synthesized CIPs which were coated with Fe nanoflakes and demonstrated that the MR effect and damping properties increased up to 162% and 65%, respectively, with the incorporation of 6% CIP-Nano-Fe. </p>
</text>
