<text id="autogum_academic_doc539" title="Measurement of the PMSM Shaft Position with An Absolute Encoder" shortTile="measurement-pmsm" author="Tomasz Rudnicki" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2079-9292/8/11/1229/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Recent advances in car design have been driven, in part, by the dynamic development of electric drives. The most promising advance in this respect seems to be the permanent magnet synchronous motor (PMSM) due to its low weight, small size, high efficiency, and high torque. Electric motors with permanent magnets NdFeB simplify the motor structure. The motor stator is usually similar to the stator of induction motors and the rotor contains permanent magnets. The magnets and the armature winding are positioned so that the electromotive force (EMF) generated as a result of rotation is sinusoidal. A characteristic feature of PMSM motors is a wide range of speed control. Permanent magnet motors lack commutators, so the weight of the drive design is significantly transferred toward the electronic control of the electric motor. Motors with permanent magnets demonstrate high efficiency, high torque, and low weight, all of which are highly important for vehicle design.  </p>

<p>In order to obtain a smooth regulation of the rotational speed of the drive system with a PMSM, the angle of the motor shaft must be measured correctly. Errors in the measurement of the shaft angle cause unstable operation of the motor, jerking, or excessive current consumption, which can even damage the PMSM. Therefore, it is very important that the position measured by the encoder is correct. Unfortunately, the encoder works in conditions of strong interference, which means the central unit must check and correct the measured position by the encoder at all times. This allows for smooth speed control and stable operation of the PMSM. Detection of information loss error for the incremental encoder was presented in. There are also methods of sensor less control of the PMSM, but due to the high precision of the control, the article focused on the control system using an absolute encoder. In conventional position sensorless permanent magnet (PM) machine drives, the rotor position is obtained from the phase-locked loop (PLL) with the regulation of spatial signal in estimated back electromotive force (EMF) voltages. Due to the sinusoidal distribution of back-EMF voltages, a small-signal approximation is assumed in the PLL in order to estimate the position. In the sensorless control method, the stator current is measured to estimate the speed of the motor. When the PMSM sensorless control is used in an electric vehicle, it sometimes causes another problem. When the motor is running in steady state and is suddenly given a large load that has reverse torque direction, a problem will arise. Therefore, an original method was proposed that obtained good results when the PMSM is operating in such adverse conditions. </p>
</text>
