<text id="autogum_interview_doc606" title="part11_Wikinews interviews John Wolfe, Democratic Party presidential challenger to Barack Obama" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-05-19" dateModified="2013-09-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_John_Wolfe%2C_Democratic_Party_presidential_challenger_to_Barack_Obama" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<figure><caption>Wolfe sifts through his papers during the December 2011 Lesser-known candidates forum.Image: Marc Nozell.</caption></figure>
<p>So people that try to classify that as some sort of welfare that's exploding the budget is just disingenuous, especially when you figure the fact that Social Security surplus is just on book. It's on budget, so therefore, the surplus works to actually reduce the deficit and therefore brings borrowing costs for the government down. So, Social Security has had a very good impact all the way around, and it's something that's actually worked to keep people out of poverty. Now, I mean ten percent of the people are in poverty, if we didn't have social security, 40 percent of the older people would be in poverty. But the Republicans want to undo what works well. Not just the Republicans necessarily, but <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blue%20Dog%20Democrats">Blue Dog Democrats</ref> and the business class, the elite want to undo what works well for the people, which is Social Security, and they want to keep a failed healthcare system that's uncompetitive in the world economy. I mean it's amazing the upside perspective these people have.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What are your views on immigration?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wolfe</hi>: Well I think we need a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/guest%20worker%20program">guest worker program</ref> and let's do it. I mean right now we got crops ripening in the field and in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Alabama">Alabama</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Georgia_(U.S._state)">Georgia</ref>, people not there to harvest. Let the Mexicans come in, or the people from down below, the southern, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Latin_America">Latin American</ref> folks who want to come to the United States. Let them come in and work under a guest worker program just like [former] President [George W.] <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/George_W._Bush">Bush</ref>, [Senator John] <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_McCain">McCain</ref>, and Obama always wanted to do. Then when the harvest is over they can go back home with their money and help their families. That's the way it should work.</p>
<p>We do need agricultural workers, and I think we need workers in the domestic area, and there's other places where the illegal immigrants are needed as well in restaurant work, hotel work, and some type of domestic work, because they've done a lot of the work that Americans wouldn't do. But we do have to keep tabs on it and the guest worker program is the best way to do it. And I think if you are worried about the factories, and the construction jobs that may be going to illegals, then the easiest way to remedy that and the parties won't do it because they're both too deep in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chamber%20of%20Commerce">Chamber of Commerce</ref> money, but all you have to do is to give the businesses that play by the rules the right to sue the ones that don't under the series of unfair uncompetitive practices under the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal%20Trade%20Commission">FTC rules</ref>. If you would just give the affected businesses, standing to sue, which I don't think they have right now, then the whole thing would end. But they won't do that. It would be the surest way to solve the problem.</p>
</text>
