<text id="autogum_whow_doc143" title="Lead by Communicating" shortTile="lead-communicating" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-10-11" dateModified="2019-02-19" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Lead-by-Communicating" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Lead by Communicating</head><p>Lead by communicating effectively with people. Everyone should, but leaders of organizations/teams and managers/coaches of areas, departments and such definitely need to get out of the den/office and into the work or sport places, etc. You never know what ideas might emerge when two people in different parts of the organization are talking about improving things that they’re doing. Great things can be birthed...</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Don’t waste time roaming the sidelines: Avoid sliding into the background.  Get into your field of endeavor at school, plant or the office—not spying, looking/watching from a distance—losing opportunities because you are off the front lines of work, play or school. While your team, technicians, producers, sales force are in action, be out there communicating. Be an "enthusiast/cheerleader" if that might work. Continually engage the entire collection of teams—at each level, bottom to top. <figure rend="Become-a-Congressperson-Step-15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Talk with production and sales people; not just their managers. Pump customer service for their input on business through the customers' eyes. Prime the office-mates, warehouse-men, and others—individually and in groups, communicating together. Tune in to ideas and build on them. <figure rend="Become-a-Software-Engineer-Step-5-Version-2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Relational management builds relationships: synergistic energies/connections with minds and emotions of the employees. It primes the feeling of loyalty to the business and a vestment in the desire to improve the processes and mechanisms. Individuals tend to be more accountable to the management with whom they have relationships beyond just their daily work duties, particularly when the individuals are fully-valued.</item></list></item>
<item>Ask helpful, reasonable questions and openly receive the friendly answers. Listen to what your coworkers are seeing in their part of the work, school or game. Listen to what they are thinking and analyze  thoughts with a high level of empathy. <figure rend="Have-a-Good-Job-Interview-Step-9-Version-3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Learn what is happening out there in the trenches! What was or is each of the other team or company marketers doing that you could latch on to and extend as well? What trends, strengths and weaknesses does each man see in the competition?</item>
<item>Try "walking the floor", discussing in classrooms or patrolling the practice field where you can learn from the employees on the line what really is going on and how to improve things.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Get outside your comfort zone</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Circulate, meet new faces and idea sets.—Find out what everyone is thinking and dreaming. Do this all the time even if associates are uncomfortable going around the room and meeting others. This is fun, engaging, and expanding to the soul and to the mind. You will likely find that you improve understandings, enthusiasm and social flexibility and also develop facility in targeting critical insights, then capitalizing upon them. <figure rend="Learn-a-Language-Step-5-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Work together, to hone your short-/medium-/long-term goals and put legs under your plans, hands-on. Encourage teammates to give you the input and feedback that's needed to make the right calls, decisions. <figure rend="Survive-High-School-Step-1-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Cash in the value of insight gained by talking to formalize and expand plans—big and small—that you can press into execution successfully. Prime the idea flow by constantly talking with different people, by listening to what they say and then by working together to crystallize their view of a super path forward. It isn’t your place to draw up the "vision" of (and for) your enterprise all on your own. The team wins when everyone is talking to and engaging with a variety of team members. Honor the knowledge that each great idea starts with a conversation between two people and grow using the natural feed of energy by that continuing relationship. <figure rend="Pass-Final-Exams-Step-12-Version-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Talk business with people in your team or office, by talking with all of them in groups and many individually, some every day. Know what they’re doing to improve, what they’re thinking about the business, what their ideas are. <figure rend="File for Divorce in Texas Without a Lawyer Step 17.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Personalize your efforts</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Trust your people. "Friends" give you the feedback and insight that will help you grow the business. Show that you trust their expertise in their jobs, in all the different aspects that come together to make your organization succeed. Your team can’t excel without everyone believing, contributing and sharing their ideas and thoughts. <figure rend="Delegate-Step-4-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Encourage people to be talking to each other about good ideas for improving various phases of practices, production, the organization -- and to bring it to your attention.  <figure rend="Run-for-Congress-Step-5-Version-3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Show that you are grateful for suggestions, perhaps cash awards, plaques, etc.</item>
<item>Give credit for changes to the contributors. Avoid characterizing their new ideas, suspend judgment. Putting ideas together is where creative thinking (synthesizing) and innovation comes from.</item></list></item>
<item>Don't spend much time standing around with comfortable acquaintances, people you already know at trade shows and conventions, dinners, banquets, etc. <figure rend="Motivate-Teens-Toward-Better-Grades-Step-2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Get out and engage in fresh ideas by opening yourself to alternative views. Let the breeze of change cleanse the stasis of your enterprise.—Bring to your core the realization that the life and vitality of your company walks hand-in-hand with its ability to:
<list type="unordered"><item>Grasp, envision, and integrate many facets of meaningful change—from local to global—using such things as i-shops or i-malls.</item></list></item></list></item></list>
<head>Vitalize electronic communications</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Adapt vibrant communication technologies: phones, email, voice-mail, conference calls, Skype/visual conversations, videos,... all the above, it works for you. <figure rend="Learn-a-Language-Step-7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Create advantages, using social networking. Realize that in order to be able to contribute to communicating in very effective ways, it often takes person-to-person/eye-to-eye contact/real arms-length conversations: <hi rend="italic">Motivated people fulfilling needs are the building blocks of innovation</hi>. <figure rend="Barter-Step-20.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you don't do a lot of advertising, you can build gratitude and loyalty by doing your best to show concern. Then, ask customers to tell others about your promptness, fine capabilities, great results, desired services, etc. Fulfill needs and solve problems right where you are using electronic devices to communicate to the fullest.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always take the time to talk to the people with whom you do business, actually talking with people and remembering them, make notes—not just chatting about business or the weather, but about life/family, etc.</item>
<item>Quality management (QM) works well when it uses lower level process information derived from conversation to communicate and formalize how best to improve the organization. (Make sure to draw from group conversations as well as individual conversations.)</item></list>
</text>
