<text id="autogum_whow_doc534" title="Buy Exotic Pets" shortTile="buy-exotic-pets" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-07-31" dateModified="2017-01-09" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Buy-Exotic-Pets" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Buy Exotic Pets</head><p>Buying exotic pets can be tricky. The price, location, and the type are all very important. That is why it is necessary to observe all of the factors in buying an exotic pet. Here are some tips that will guide you into buying exotic pets the right way!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Choose a Type</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>First, you must of course choose a kind of exotic pet to buy. This can be your favorite animal, or maybe just an animal that you think is interesting.</item>
<item>Once you have your type of animal picked out, research them and make sure you know what they are like and how to take care of one. Make sure you are very up-to-date with feeding, housing, and loving them.</item></list>
<head>Find a Buyer</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find a store or person that sells the type of animal that you want. Make sure to go to a place that has a good reputation and isn't sketchy. And if you do buy an animal from a questionable seller, then be prepared for sick and/or injured animals. Make sure to watch their health closely if you choose to buy from them.</item>
<item>Check with your state laws to make sure that the animal you want isn't illegal to own as a civilian.</item></list>
<head>Price</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>For exotic pets, prices can easily add up to a big sum. Make sure that the animal you want fits into your budget. Don't buy an expensive animal knowing that you don't have the money to take care of it properly. Your animal will suffer because of you, and you won't be happy with your purchase.</item></list>
<head>Location</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Buying an exotic pet is a little risky when it comes to location. You could be buying an animal from within your city, or you could be travelling the world. It all depends on how rare/endangered they are.</item>
<item>Make sure you have plans for getting them safely to your home.</item></list>
<head>Know What They Need</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>It is very important to understand your exotic pet's needs. Make sure you have the time and money to take care of them. This is why it is important for you to research your animal before you actually get them.</item>
<item>Every exotic pet is unique in their own way. They aren't like taking care of a cat or dog. They are much more high maintenance.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>It is a good idea to have your animal's habitat already set up before they arrive at home. This way, it will save you the time and hassle later.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Never, ever, ever buy an animal, regardless of the type, (yes, even insects/amphibians/reptiles!) off of the internet. Craigslist, Ebay, Amazon, etc. are all examples. Often, the seller will lie to you about the animal's breed, health, age, gender, etc.</item></list>
</text>
