<text id="autogum_voyage_doc491" title="Taal Volcano" shortTile="taal-volcano" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=168606" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Taal Volcano</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Taal Volcano</hi> is a complex <ref target="volcano">stratovolcano</ref> in the province of <ref target="Batangas">Batangas</ref>, <ref target="Philippines">Philippines</ref>. The volcano, together with the lake and its approximately radius, forms the larger <hi rend="bold">Taal Volcano Natural Park</hi>, officially the <hi rend="bold">Taal Volcano Protected Landscape</hi> (TVPL). </p>

<p>The nearest town, and the usual base for trips to the volcano, is <ref target="Tagaytay">Tagaytay</ref> in <ref target="Cavite">Cavite</ref> province. <hi rend="bold">Talisay</hi>, within the park boundaries, is the nearest town at the Batangas side; the boats on the package tours depart from there, but it's possible to get there without going to Tagaytay.</p>

<p>The scenic historic town of <ref target="Taal">Taal</ref> is covered in a separate article; it was built some distance away after a volcanic eruption wiped out an older town in 1755.</p>

<head>Cities and towns</head>
<p>Taal Volcano is often said to be only the Volcano Proper and the surrounding lake, but the park covers also some towns and cities (not necessarily including the central settlement or downtown) within an approximately radius</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> — The main gateway to Volcano Island. It is a small town, with few sights in itself, except for the volcano.</item>
<item> — Another town to the west of Talisay, again with a few sights</item>
<item> — A smaller city, with a medium-sized downtown with an old church at its middle. Tanauan's designated tourism zone, with some lakeside resorts, once has the original town that was destroyed by the 1755 eruption.</item>
<item> — Batangas's largest city and economic center. Our Lipa guide also covers the lakeside towns of:</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> — Rural municipality with a town center bordering Lipa. Northward towards the lake are some inland resorts, some with views of the lake. The original town of Lipa used to be in here until the 1755 eruption.</item>
<item> — A lakeside town, with some resorts, and a park at the lakefront. To the east of the town is Marian Orchard, a serene religious site at the middle of the jungle running down the slopes to the lakeshore.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> — Has Mount Maculot, a peak popular with beginner hikers. The town is really small, and not much to see, but it has plenty of inland resorts.</item>
</list>

<ref target="Tagaytay">Tagaytay</ref> in Cavite province is the usual base for trips to the volcano, but our guide only covers the park area within Batangas province and the two towns where the boats depart, Talisay and Laurel, which are too small to have their own guides.

<head>Understand</head>

<p>Taal Volcano is best known as the world's smallest <ref target="volcano">volcano</ref>, and one known example of "a lake with a volcano with a lake". It is an active volcano, with a history of 33 recorded eruptions. It is the second most active volcano in the Philippines, after <ref target="Mount%20Mayon">Mount Mayon</ref>, and is one of the <ref target="http://www.sveurop.org/gb/program/program.htm">"Decade Volcanoes"</ref>.</p>

<p>Taal Volcano is part of a chain of volcanoes that have existed since prehistoric times, resulting from the subduction of the Eurasian Plate and Pacific Plate.</p>

<p>Trips to the volcano usually start from <ref target="Tagaytay">Tagaytay</ref>, a highland city in <ref target="Cavite">Cavite</ref> with other picturesque landscapes nearby. Package tours to Taal Volcano are available from the city. Taal Volcano is also one of the provincial symbols of Batangas, appearing on the new provincial seal and flag.</p>

<p>The volcano and the lake form the larger <hi rend="bold">Taal Volcano Natural Park</hi>, officially the <hi rend="bold">Taal Volcano Protected Landscape</hi> (TVPL), which is designated as a national park since 1967. The national park covers an area within a radius of about from the caldera lake.</p>

<head>History</head>
<p>Taal Volcano is an active volcano, with its earliest recorded eruption in 1572. The lake and the volcano were first named as <hi rend="italic">Bonbon</hi> (or <hi rend="italic">Bombón</hi>), which also gave the historical names of the present-day town of <ref target="Taal">Taal</ref> and the province of <ref target="Batangas">Batangas</ref>.</p>

<p>Taal Volcano's most destructive eruptions occurred in 1755 and 1910. The very destructive 1755 eruption destroyed the original downtown of <ref target="Taal">Taal</ref>, now part of the little town of San Nicolas, as well as the original town center of present-day <ref target="Lipa">Lipa</ref>, now part of the town of Mataasnakahoy, and is well recorded in an account by a Spanish priest. Ash and mud from the 1755 eruption were also carried by storms into the village of Caysasay (present-day Taal) and as far as Balayan.</p>

<head>Landscape</head>

<p>The volcano proper forms the <hi rend="bold">Volcano Island</hi>, composed of seven volcanic cones and the caldera lake. Taal Lake also forms the volcano, making the system complex. Volcanic activity can be noticed through changes in Taal Lake; some fish kill incidents on the lake are blamed on volcanic activity, though overcrowded fish pens (<hi rend="italic">baklad</hi>) are often the cause.</p>

<p>From Tagaytay, Taal Volcano, alongside Taal Lake, dominate the landscape, with the dormant cone Binintiang Malaki being the most prominent. The volcano is covered by vegetation up to the tree line at the crater lake. On the base are some villages relying on fishing in Taal Lake and agriculture in the fertile soil of Volcano Island.</p>

<head>Flora and fauna</head>
<p>Taal Lake is home to the <hi rend="italic">tawilis</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Sardinella tawilis</hi>), a species of sardine endemic to the lake. It is often served as a local dish in the surrounding area, but overfishing is threatening the <hi rend="italic">tawilis</hi> population, so it was designated an endangered species in 2019 by the International Union for the Conservation of Nature (IUCN), and a closed season is implemented to allow the fish to increase in number.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>Taal Volcano is one of the most accessible in Luzon island, and many tourists, local and foreign, go here, usually in package tours from Tagaytay. Peak season traffic can be high, and tours can get fully booked. It is possible to just see the volcano and the lake without getting further into Volcano Island, or have a do-it-yourself tour, avoiding completely Tagaytay where the package tour providers are based and getting directly into the boats in Talisay or Laurel.</p>

<p>The nearest airport is in <ref target="Ninoy%20Aquino%20International%20Airport">Manila</ref>, and the closest seaport is in <ref target="Batangas%20%28city%29%23By%20boat">Batangas City</ref>. From either way, there is public transportation into the jump-off points.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>Most visitors will come to Tagaytay by car, and there, they will purchase the tour packages to Taal, but it's possible to get into the towns directly without dealing with the tour operators.</p>

<p>Talisay can be reached directly via <hi rend="bold">Talisay-Tanauan Road</hi>, which can be accessed from STAR Tollway at Tanauan. From Tagaytay, <hi rend="bold">Talisay-Tagaytay Road</hi> runs through jungle at the mountain slopes down to the lakeside, where it joins Talisay-Tanauan and Talisay-Laurel roads. Talisay-Tagaytay and Talisay-Tanauan roads are both numbered as Route 421, but the route number signs don't say where you should turn to Talisay town proper, so from Tagaytay, watch for signs that point to Tanauan.</p>
</text>
