<text id="autogum_voyage_doc423" title="Marquette (Michigan)" shortTile="marquette-michigan" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=21483" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Marquette (Michigan)</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.mqtcty.org/">Marquette</ref></hi> is a city in the <ref target="Upper%20Peninsula">Upper Peninsula</ref> (U.P.) of the state of <ref target="Michigan">Michigan</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Whenever talking to a Marquette resident, you'll eventually hear reference to <hi rend="bold">"the Lake"</hi>. This nearly always means Lake Superior. Other, smaller lakes nearby and elsewhere in the U.P. are referred to by their names, e.g., Silver Lake, Teal Lake.</p>

<p>Marquette is a university town, and shares some sensibilities with other college towns around the country. This also means that many, although by no means all, of the young adults are university students.</p>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sawyer International Airport</hi> ( MQT ), ☏ +1-906-346-3308 . A former U.S. Air Force base converted to civilian use. Direct flights from Chicago, Detroit, and Minneapolis. </item>
</list>


<head>By bus</head>
<p>It is possible to take the Greyhound into Marquette.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>If you drive up from the Lower Peninsula, take US-2 along the southern shore of the U.P. for a scenic drive. With a few local exceptions, all highways in the U.P. are 2-lane. Passing lanes have been added along US-2 and M-28, to help traffic flow.</p>

<p>Driving in the Upper Peninsula during winter can be treacherous, but the county crews do a good job of clearing, salting, and sanding the major roadways, as do the crews in Marquette. Side streets can be very slippery if snow-covered.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>For the most part one would want to take a car, especially in winter when snow or ice covers everything.</p>

<head>By bicycle</head>
<p>In the summer you can rent bicycles from some of the local bike shops. Marquette has several bike paths, one of which runs alongside the lake from Presque Isle Park to the intersection of M-28 and US-41. Biking on M-28. Additionally, the back roads around town are rather pleasant and the traffic isn't too harsh.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lakeshore Bikes</hi>, 505 N Lakeshore Blvd, ☏ +1 906 228-7547 . has bike rentals available.</item>
</list>


<head>By bus</head>
<p>There is also county-wide <ref target="http://www.marq-tran.com/">bus service</ref>, which runs a few fixed routes and also offers door to door service.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Beaumier Heritage Center</hi>, Gries Hall, 7th St and Lee Dr.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">DeVos Art Museum</hi>, Tracy &amp; 7th Street. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Marquette Maritime Museum</hi> (next to the Coast Guard station). Tour the lighthouse while you're here. You must make an appointment beforehand. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Marquette Regional History Center</hi>, 145 W. Spring Street, ☏ +1-906-226-3571 . M-T,Th-F 10AM-5PM W 10AM-8PM Sa 10AM-3PM.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lake Superior</hi>. You can view the lake at many spots around Marquette's east side.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Iron ore boats</hi> in the Upper Harbor are a sight to behold; you can see them docked at the Upper Harbor ore dock, next to Presque Isle Park during the upper Great Lakes shipping season.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fall colors</hi>: In September and October, the forests are filled with a variety of reds, yellows and oranges as the maple, birch, aspen, and other leafed trees get ready for winter.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Arch and Ridge Streets Historic District</hi>. </item>
</list>


<head>Outdoors</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The UP 200</hi> (sled dog race), ☏ +1 906-228-3072 or +1 906-362-3785 . Every winter this race is held and the start is immediately followed by fireworks off of the dock in downtown.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Paddling Michigan</hi>, ☏ +1-877-228-5447 . offers kayak outings around the U.P., including trips to Pictured Rocks National Lakeshore.</item>
</list>
<head>Skiing</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Marquette Mountain</hi>. offers several runs for alpine skiing, just south of Marquette's city limits. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Noquemanon Trail</hi> (Cross Country Ski Race). This race goes from Ishpeming to Marquette.</item>
</list>


<head>Hiking</head>
<p>Hiking opportunities are abundant, with many hikes heading up the big hills in the area that overlook the lake. One can hike up Sugarloaf Mountain or Hogback Mountain and then hike back down to the Lake for a relaxing lounge on the beach. For additional trails, not yet listed here, see City of Marquette's list public trails on its <ref target="http://www.mqtcty.org/exploring.html">website</ref>.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sugarloaf Mountain</hi>. This is a good, short hike north of town. Two routes are maintained: one route is a steeper climb, and the other ascends more gradually. Both routes include staircases over rock outcroppings, especially near the summit. The view from the top is spectacular - a great photo spot. Also one of the best places for autumn foliage viewing.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Presque Isle Park</hi>. A city-owned area with boat slips, picnic areas, trails, a sheltered pavilion, and a refreshment shop. Presque Isle Park is flanked by the Upper Harbor to the south, and by Lake Superior to the east and north, and northwest. It's a city park but feels much bigger. The trail around the perimeter of the island meanders through the woods, occasionally popping out for breathtaking views of cliffs and the lake. Presque Isle Park is found by following Lake Shore Drive northward, just past the north harbor ore dock. The refreshment shop is closed in the winter, as is the one-lane, one-way road around the "Island," as the park is known locally, but remains open to snow-showing, cross-country skiing, and hiking in the winter months.</item>
</list>


<head>Biking</head>
<p>Marquette has challenging trails for freeride mountain biking.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Follow the bike path from Presque Isle Park, all the way to south Marquette. This path was added within the last 10 years or so, and has become very popular. Just be prepared to share it with pedestrians and the occasional rollerblader.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Oar to Shore</hi> (mountain bike race). In the summer, Marquette is host to the Ore to Shore mountain bike race.</item>
</list>

<p>For good riding advice, stop by Lakeshore Bikes or the Quick Stop Bike Shop. Guys at both shops are avid riders and will be happy to point you in the right direction.</p>

<head>Fishing</head>
<p>You can fish Lake Superior, the inland lakes, and many creeks and streams. Licensing, minimum length of caught fish, and fish limits are regulated by the Michigan DNR, which publishes a fishing guide <ref target="http://www.michigan.gov/dnr/0%2C4570%2C7-153-10364_63235-274824--%2C00.html"></ref>.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Uncle Ducky's Charter Fishing</hi>, 434 East Prospect St, ☏ +1-877-228-5447 . Fishing trips on Lake Superior. Otherwise you can fish off of the breakwall downtown, which is accessible from the Coast Guard station off of Lakeshore Drive (just north of downtown), or one of the inland lakes and streams.</item>
</list>
</text>
