<text id="autogum_interview_doc360" title="part6_Creator of website satirizing Glenn Beck on winning domain name case" shortTile="partcreator-website" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-11-09" dateModified="2019-02-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Creator_of_website_satirizing_Glenn_Beck_on_winning_domain_name_case" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>I think that if Beck had never started the legal action, this meme would have died out after a couple of weeks. It might have popped up in the occasional place, but I don't think it would have lasted the more than two months it has.</p>
<p>By super meme, I just mean that there are so many memes out there. Some are specific to a certain site; some have a very short life and die quickly; some continue at a very low level. This meme, however, just took off. So many people were posting it on some many unrelated threads on Fark that moderators were banning people for it). I've seen people post this meme in places where few memes go - on news sites, blogs: anywhere people comment, this meme will pop up.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You also wrote in your letter to Beck, "In this context of this WIPO case, you denigrated the letter of First Amendment law." How would you like Beck to act differently in the future with regard to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First%20Amendment%20to%20the%20United%20States%20Constitution">First Amendment to the United States Constitution</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">E-H</hi>: Beck's WIPO complaint revolves around trademark issues. His claim is that the domains violate the trademark he has in his name. I don't believe that was his ultimate motivation in trying to get the domain; I think he was trying to stifle free speech. I think he looked at <hi rend="italic">Hustler v. Falwell</hi> and decided he couldn't win against my legally-protected right to mock him, but that he might be able to use other means to get my point of view shut down. 
(It's easy to come to this conclusion if you look at the legal documents I posted on gb1990.net/legal - and I posted everything I got)</p>
<p>What I'd like Beck to do differently is simply realize that the chilling effects of trying to have speech you disagree with shutdown would ultimately
affect his rights as well. I disagree with many of the things he says, and hope to put pressure on him to change his techniques; but ultimately, I would never wish to stifle his first amendment rights. There's a difference between disagreeing with someone, mocking them, and trying to intimidate them to stop talking.</p>
<hi rend="bold">As regards the application of the <hi rend="italic">Hustler v. Falwell</hi> case to this case, I think the overall application was fair: Parody and satire are protected forms of free speech.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Eiland-Hall</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> In the final decision in the <hi rend="italic">Beck v. Eiland-Hall</hi> case, the WIPO arbitrator cited the U.S. Supreme Court case, <hi rend="italic">Hustler Magazine v. Falwell</hi>. Are you familiar with this Supreme Court case? What are your thoughts on how it was applied to your case?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">E-H</hi>: I am familiar with the case; and in fact, it helped me sleep at night during the past couple of months. I think it is a very important case on the topic of first amendment rights as regards parody and satire. I strongly believe that humour should be used to point out the ridiculous - that's one of the reasons that the Daily Show is so popular and successful. They do it very well.</p>
</text>
