<text id="autogum_academic_doc451" title="Active Case Finding for Tuberculosis through TOUCH Agents in Selected High TB Burden Wards of Kolkata, India: A Mixed Methods Study on Outcomes and Implementation Challenges" shortTile="active-case-finding" author="Abhijit Dey, Pruthu Thekkur, Ayan Ghosh, Tanusree Dasgupta, Soumyajyoti Bandopadhyay, Arista Lahiri, Chidananda Sanju S V, Milan  K. Dinda, Vivek Sharma, Namita Dimari, Dibyendu Chatterjee, Isita Roy, Anuradha Choudhury, Parthiban Shanmugam, Brojo  Kishore Saha, Sanghamitra Ghosh, Sharath  Burugina Nagaraja" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2414-6366/4/4/134/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
This is one of the first mixed methods studies to assess the “care cascade” and to explore the challenges associated with the implementation of ACF for TB in India. Our study has a few key findings. First, the ACF activity had a low PTBP detection rate with only three out of 1000 apparently healthy individuals enumerated during house-to-house visits having symptoms that were suggestive of TB. Second, there was high attrition of PTBP prior to diagnosis with only two out of three PTBP who were referred actually visiting the health facility. Third, among PTBPs who undergo the diagnostic test, the sputum positivity rate was high, with one out of four having been diagnosed with TB. Fourth, the NNS for one TB patient was relatively high. Fifth, the stigma about TB, suspicion about TA, lack of support from political leaders, and low salary for TAs were the major challenges in conducting house-to-house visit for identifying the PTBPs. Sixth, wage loss, apprehension about the diagnosis, substance abuse, and male dependency of females for seeking care at health facilities were the major challenges for PTBPs to visit the referred health facility.  </p>

<p>We further discuss our study findings in detail. First, the study had a low rate of PTBP detection, whereas the previous studies on ACF have consistently shown high rates of PTBP detection. The TAs failed to individually enquire about symptoms that are suggestive of TB from all those who were enumerated. As the ACF activity was conducted during the daytime, the symptoms of individuals who were away from home were enquired about by speaking to adult informants. Studies in the past have shown that the detection rate of PTBP may be low if the symptoms are not elicited individually. The informants might not be aware of the TB symptoms and thus, could have failed to identify the PTBPs among those who were absent during the interview. As explored in the qualitative study, the other potential reasons for low rate of PTBP detection are hesitancy to disclose the details of TB symptoms due to stigma and distrust about TAs. Some other studies also revealed similar findings.  </p>

<p>The second finding is the high attrition rate among PTBPs referred to health facilities for TB diagnosis. Previous studies have also reported similar findings with attrition rates ranging from 39% to 80%. The rate was high in spite of repeated house visits by TAs to counsel and encourage PTBPs to visit the health facility. The qualitative interviews provided good insight about potential reasons for such high attrition. The wage or work loss due to travel and visits to health facilities during the day time was one of the major reasons. Among females, the attrition rate was high as they were dependent on male family members to visit the health facility. Difficulties in counselling PTBPs with alcohol and other substance abuse also contributed to the attrition. The other important issue was general distrust and unhappiness about the public health system among the public. Thus, these reasons warrant the provision of financial support and assistance to PTBPs to undergo diagnostic tests.  </p>

<p>Third, the rate of TB diagnosis among those PTBPs visiting a health facility was high. This could be due to the fact that only those with perceived need reached the health facility. Though PTBPs were identified by ACF activity, the decision to visit largely depended on the severity of symptoms and thus mimicked the passive case finding. Also, the TAs might have given more preference to referral and linkage of PTBPs with severe and multiple symptoms rather than those with mild symptoms. </p>

<p>Fourth, the overall yield of ACF was low and NNS for TB was high. Previous studies have reported lower NNS on mass screening in high burden TB settings. A potential reason for high NNS might be the low detection and high attrition rate of PTBPs. Although the NNS is high, the activity is still worthwhile as it indirectly sensitizes households on TB symptoms and thus creates awareness in the community. Regular visits to the same community (six days a week) is gradually leading to good rapport building with the community. This might improve the overall case detection in the community and contribute to TB control efforts.  </p>

<p>The study has several strengths. First, it was conducted under programmatic settings and reflects the field realities. Second, we used a mixed methods design, which provided considerable insights into challenges involved in the implementation of ACF and enabled us to interpret the quantitative results. Third, the study has a relatively large sample size and there was no selection bias as we included all the individuals who were enumerated during the study reference period in 60 wards where ACF is implemented. Fourth, we used double data entry and validation using EpiData software and thus data entry errors were minimized. Fifth, we adhered to STrengthening the Reporting of Observational studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) and COREQ guidelines for reporting the study’s findings. </p>
</text>
