<text id="autogum_reddit_doc082" title="Question Megathread" shortTile="question-megathread" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-04-05" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="http://redd.it/89xtdw" speakerList="#Shigeyama, #ZaharBot" speakerCount="2">
<head>Question Megathread</head>
<sp who="#ZaharBot">
<p>The thread for all your random Alchemist Code (global) questions! Feel free to ask away, but remember that the questions are 100% answered by volunteers so don't expect an instant answer! Patience is key. Several questions can be answered by reading the <ref target="under reconstruction">beginner guides resource thread</ref> -----------------  <hi rend="bold">F.A.Q.</hi>  --------  <hi rend="bold">Where/How can I unlock X's Master Ability/Job+?</hi>  You can only unlock Job+'s by farming special job tokens from special events that are (currently) run at different times. You also need to farm special job+ items to master those jobs. Master abilities can be earned in 1 of 3 ways. From story chapters (story characters), from equipping specific weapons (usually farmed) or from reaching level 80 on a character and completing special story dungeons. Not every character gets a master ability. For Job+, you must first get the job to Job Level 11 (not job mastered). Second, to master the Job+ you will need to farm 60/80 tokens for up to 6 special items for the character to use.  <hi rend="bold">Where can I farm X's character shards?</hi>   <hi rend="bold"> Caris: [Hard] Ch 1: Ep 4 [2-10] </hi>  Lamia [Hard] Ch 1: Ep 4 [2-8]  <hi rend="bold"> Zangetsu [Hard] Ch 1: Ep 2 [3-2] </hi>  Lucian [Hard] Ch 1: Ep 4 [1-9]  <hi rend="bold"> Lofia [Hard] Ch 1: Ep 4 [2-9] </hi>  Reida [Hard] Ch 2: Ep 2 [3-9]  <hi rend="bold"> Chihaya [Hard] Ch 2: Ep 1 [2-4] </hi>  Rahu [Hard] Ch 2: Ep 2 [2-10]  <hi rend="bold"> Freed [Hard] Ch 2: Ep 2 [3-1] </hi>  Reagan [Hard] Ch 2: Ep 1 [2-5]  <hi rend="bold"> Zahar [Hard] Ch 1: Ep 2 [3-9] </hi>  Chloe [Hard] Ch 1: Ep 2 [3-10]  <hi rend="bold"> Vettel [Hard] Ch 1: Ep 3 [3-7] </hi>  Yomi [Hard] Ch 1: Ep 3 [1-10]  <hi rend="bold">Last 2 must be accessed through story for now</hi>  More to be added SOONTM. -------------  <hi rend="bold">Where can I farm elemental/rainbow shards?</hi>  Elemental and rainbow shards cannot be farmed. They are awarded as bonuses from log in campaigns, from clearing missions/milestones and as bonuses for doing certain number of summons on the 5/9 step banners. You will never be able to farm them like you can farm specific character shards.  <hi rend="bold">When will X event come back?</hi>  We don't know, Gumi is sticking to their own schedule.  <hi rend="bold">WILL START HANDING OUT BANS TO PEOPLE WHO DON'T READ THIS</hi>   <hi rend="bold">What's the best place to farm X/Y/Z item?</hi>  Outside of specific event's for farming items, if the item can be farmed in Edgar's Chapter (so chapter 2) it will usually be the better place to farm it. For example, Escape the Alkaroid is by far the best place to farm Sacred Lion Swords.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#Shigeyama">
<p>I never played Sacred Stone Memories before...will I be able to play through the first Chapters of the event if I start participating when it comes out now? Also are there any free units you can unlock in it?</p>
</sp>
</text>
