<text id="autogum_reddit_doc077" title="Long post - Throw ragers while your parents are out of town and yo're still in high school. Police show up 7 times, ridiculous shit happens." shortTile="long-post--throw" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-04-30" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8fzy1u" speakerList="#DeadFetusConsumer" speakerCount="1">
<head>Long post - Throw ragers while your parents are out of town and yo're still in high school. Police show up 7 times, ridiculous shit happens.</head>
<sp who="#DeadFetusConsumer">
<p>Ok, don't actually. But, this post is inspired by <ref target="https://www.reddit.com/r/Drugs/comments/8fu5gs/long_post_dont_throw_ragers_when_your_parents_are/?utm_content=title&amp;utm_medium=hot&amp;utm_source=reddit&amp;utm_name=Drugs">this one</ref>. So! To preface. I'm 16 years old at the time in this one too(wow how the time passes!), parents gone on a vacation for a couple of weeks, sister also gone. HOME FREE for TWO WEEKS IN THE SUMMER. Fuck. Yes. So, after a wicked drug fuelled game of Manhunt (hide and go seek) in the local giant provincial park with mystery boxes containing MDMA, alcohol, energy drinks, snacks and so forth, we planned for the party of a lifetime. The PARTY OF THE FRUITS. This party was.... fucking nuts. One rule: bring a fruit. Dress fruit themed. Idk, be fruity. Other rules: BYOB, smoke outside don't be a dick, etc. Me being the edgy teen I am, never having thrown a party and liking my parties, I plan the fuck out of this. We move all breakables, valuables, everything out of the main rooms and lock them in separate rooms. This was a  <hi rend="bold">very good idea</hi> . Half inspired by Project X, we(I) say fuck it. Lets have an open invite. Facebook event is all set up, 200+ people invited, about 60 on the 'going' list. One girl I made sure to not invite, Haley, because I know she's a fucking disaster and would start trouble. Lemme tell you about Haley - this fucking trainwreck of a human. By the end of grade 12 she has fucked 53 dudes. No that's not a typo. FIFTY FUCKING THREE guys. How do I know this? Well in her attempt at fucking me (tbh I would've if she wasn't sleepin around so much) she showed me the long ass list of dudes she has plowed. She's the reason there's locks on the bathrooms at schools. Yah, that kinda girl. Things are looking fucking wicked though. This is gonna be hype. We have quality speaks and subs set up, beer pong table outside, hot tub ready, etc.! So, the backyard has a swimming pool and hot tub. The swimming pool is built into the ground and about 2 meters deep. It's COMPLETELY empty aside from some couches and chairs we put in the bottom for people to sit on. My back yard isn't huge and there's only like 3 meters of walkway from the edges of the pool. This is... a recipe for disaster. My friends have a bet that it'll get shut down by 12:00. We'll see about that. 9:00 rolls by, few close friends start showing up. Drinks start popping, fruits are being amassed onto the center table, shits looking good. It's chill, good vibes. My friend (a literal urban legend of a human), a 220+ lb steroided 6'3" mass of love is 'security' for the house. Shits going good. He spends most of the night chilling the hot tub while on some nice MDMA (bad idea, I know). 10:00 rolls by. Ok we're at like 30 people, mostly people I know. Dope. 11:00. Ok, shits getting wild. Easily at 60+ people now, house and backyard are getting fucking crammed. Can hardly walk through my hallway there's so many people. Who are these people? Shit 11:30 Meeting new people, lots of people asking "Who are you!". "I'm the host" "Oh shit, wild party man!" It's around this time where stuff is getting a little out of control. People are littering the streets in front and behind my house, walking around, open bottles, smoking weed, loud as fuck, dear god. aaaaaaand would you look at that. Fucking Haley is here with her group of fuccbois. God damnit, who invited her?? (I later found out it was my friend Thomas who did. Thanks, Thomas). She's in the downstairs bathroom doing lines of coke off a folding mirror. Sigh. 12:00 rolls by. NO POLICE YET. Fucking wild. By this point there's easily 100+ people. No joke, EVERYWHERE there's just fucking people. A group of Asian dudes are just chillin, drinking, playing with my dog. A bunch of hood ass Russian dudes (I knew 2 of em) chilling by the front foyer and starting to yell at this group of Latin dudes. Aw fuck. I'm running around, thankfully sober, trying to keep things somewhat tidy.  <hi rend="bold">CRACK</hi>  I hear this fucking huge ass bang from my front foyer. It's the Russian and Latin dudes beefing. HARD. One of the Russian bastard has a nasty ass metal baton that he whipped out. What the fuck!?!? I hurriedly tell em to fuck off outside if they're going to fight. Thankfully they do go outside, though I don't think they fought. Back outside, see some brave ass people just diving onto the couch set in the pool. How no one fell in and cracked their head is beyond me. At this point, police have shown up, informing me of a noise complaint. I tell em yah, I'll shut it down. They leave, only to return about 30 minutes later due to another complain. Remember the steroided friend I told you about? He's adept at dealing with police and handles shit for me with them. Great guy! "Dude, I don't mean to alarm you, but some dude downstairs has a gun" a friend says to me. "????... fucks sake." I go slyly check out who it is. It's some Armenian dude that I remember earlier talking about stealing a TV. Hee haw fucko, thankfully I hid that shit. Still, sketching me the fuck out. Next I remember seeing a buncha dudes repping colors. At least like 6-10 of em. This is NOT good. Another friend comes up to me. "Yo, FOB is here" (a local gang). Fuuuuuuuuuuuuuuuuuck meeeee. It's about 1:30 at this point, shit is going buck wild. Police have been here about 4 times now, threatening to raid the place. Holy heck this is out of control. I need people out sooon. So, me being me, this skinny ass 6 foot pasty white dude, goes up to this ripped ass black dude repping colors. Here's how our exchange goes. "yo man, I'm DeadFetusconsumer, how you this??" "fucking lit party man, I'm Dez" "glad you like it. Anyways, I'm shutting down here soon though so I've gotta ask people to start leaving" This big ass FOB guy stops. Stares me in the eye for a quick seconds and pipes up. "Cool man, sounds good." He turns around "EVERYONE, GET THE FUCK OUT OF HERE" ..... holy shit. This blessed man just saved my ass. People quickly start funneling out and I'm ecstatic at this point. Dez just save my little ass. Anyways 3:00 is approaching, police have come about 6 times now, people have scrambled, running around, slowly evacuating. Around 20 of us left, slowly cleaning up. I then check downstairs. Bad mistake. 5-6 people just chilling in my basement, including the notorious Haley, and a dude pacing around with a knife in his hand. Oh fuck me silly. I alert my friends to this disaster and we quickly evacuate the house now. This time it's me calling the police. The exchange goes something like this. "Yeah 9/11 I have something to report at a house party" "Is it at ------------ address?" "... Yep!" "Okay, officers will be there in about 5 minutes" Sure enough, within 5 minutes theres a couple of cars of officers poppin up. I tell them the situation - there's a couple of coked out people, one with a knife, in my basement. So these officers just storm in, thunderfuck them right out and save the night. Thanks, police, you guys have been chill as fuck. Blessed. So now it's about 4:30, only a handful of us remain. We're just cleaning up, laughing, telling stories, generally mindblown. Then we hear a thing.  <hi rend="bold">BRAP BRAP BRAP BRAP BRAP</hi>  We look over, and there's someone at the window! Who the fuck could it be...?!?! Party is OVER! Ho and behold, it's fuckin Haley again. Thotamus rex never planned a return route I guess and needs to crash somewhere. "I need somewhere to sleep" "Find somewhere else, there's no room and no beds" "Pleeeeease, I'm 30km from home" "Nah sorry". So she loiters about for a good 15 minutes for leaving. To where? I don't know. So, now it's time to look at the aftermath... this is where shit gets real. The list of broken things includes: a toilet paper holder. The list of stolen things includes: none of my shit. Holy hell, I'm the luckiest cunt alive. After a bunch of cleaning up and profound apologies to the neighbors who insisted they ''hardly heard anything!'', I'm almost home free! In fact, the only evidence there was a party was a shovel and beer bottle found in the bed of my dads truck, to which he greatly questioned why the hell there was a shovel and beer bottle found in the bed his truck. My parents did find out there was a party, but didn't think it was more than 20 people or so. Thank you, blessed neighbors. I think my parents were so believing since they know I don't drink (little do they know, I love my boutique psychedelics!) Sorry this is a trainwreck of a read. I'll edit it down in a bit. If this gets enough love, I'll post the less eventful but more disastrous story of Party of the Fruits 2.0 where $1200+ of my money got stolen and where I was way too high on 2C-B. Peace and love ya'll &lt;3 </p>
</sp>
</text>
