<text id="autogum_interview_doc394" title="part7_The Raveonettes on love, death, desire and war" shortTile="partthe-raveonettes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-16" dateModified="2010-12-23" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Raveonettes_on_love%2C_death%2C_desire_and_war" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You're forced to choose between having either <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/India">India</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China">China</ref> blown off the face of the Earth, and if you don't choose, they both go.  They are equal in population according to the 2000 census in each country, with each having roughly 1.2 billion people.  Which do you choose, and why?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  You would choose India because your grandparents are from China!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  No!  I would choose China!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  Really?!  You would blow up your grandparents?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  Yup! [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  ['<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  God!  That's so rude!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  No, to me, India is a democracy, it's the world's largest democracy and I've been there.  I found it be a really spiritual place.  Some of the most intelligent people I have ever met are from India.  And China, I have to say, not so much.  I have only been to the countryside.  My grandfather is Chinese as well; I'm a quarter Chinese.  I just think they are more barbaric by their culture....</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Shaking his head</hi>]  We're never going to tour China now....</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Giggles</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You would go with China too, then?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  I'm not going to choose...you can blow them both up!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Really?  They'll all go?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  Well, I mean, I don't know, come on...I'll go with Sharin, then.  We'll keep India.</p>
<head id="On_love">On love</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Sharin, you have a choice between either dating a man who is losing it hair and he tries to style the remaining hair artistically to cover it up, or you have a choice of dating a man with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gynecomastia">man boobs</ref>--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  What boobs?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Breasts</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  Oohhh</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Who would you go for more?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>] What kind of question is that?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  It's a psychological test?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Isn't every question?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  I would probably...hmmm...hair!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You'd go for the hair?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  Yeah!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  I'd go for the boobs.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  I'd go for the hair.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You'd go for the man boobs?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  Absolutely!  I actually knew a guy, he lost a bet and he had to have breasts for a year.  He was a magician.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Like a masectomy bra?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  No, he got <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Breast%20implants">silicon</ref>...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Oh!  He went through an operation?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  Yeah!  And actually his breasts were pretty nice.  We used to...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When I was in college I had a couple of friends who were rave kids--they also went to my college--and the guy walked around with very large breasts, and our friend Koo would follow him on the street and after he passed people who noticed his large breasts she would go up and say, "Would you let that man babysit your children?" to see the reactions from people.  "Do you trust him?"  It was surprising, because the people who looked the most uptight generally responded with things like, "Yeah, sure, he doesn't seem so bad."  But the people who looked the most <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hippie">hippie</ref> and free--this was in Boulder--would say things, "I don't know!  What's wrong with him, why does he have breasts?"</hi></p>
</text>
