<text id="autogum_interview_doc743" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Christoph Bals of the NGO Germanwatch after conclusion of climate conference" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-12-24" dateModified="2009-03-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Christoph_Bals_of_the_NGO_Germanwatch_after_conclusion_of_climate_conference" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">CB</hi>: We shouldn't think that the problem is just in the U.S., even if it is to be seen most clearly there. Many of us [Germans / Europeans] don't realize what the necessary emission cuts mean. If we really want to achieve greenhouse gas reductions of the magnitude I have just described, we first need to become conscious of the fact that the wealth of the industrial nations is build on CO2. From the steam engine over coal power plants, the chemical industry up to cars and airplanes, the whole model of wealth is built up on fossil fuels and thus also CO2 emissions. Up until now more wealth also meant more emitted CO2. We now need to move towards an almost emission free model of wealth in large steps. And the role of leader seems to fall to Europe. If Europe manages to show it, the chances of the large newly industrialized nations following that lead rise enormously.</p>
<head id="Possibilities_for_individuals_to_act">Possibilities for individuals to act</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: Finally I, and perhaps the readers as well, are interested in how people at home can take a positive influence on the process?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CB</hi>: Well first, there is the possibility to engage yourself politically, working in an NGO like Germanwatch being the only option in that. What is encouraging in this area are the notable things that have already been achieved by an informed public. To name an example, the planning of multiple coal power plants has been stopped in recent times, just as well thanks to public pressure.</p>
<p>It should also be clear to everyone, that every banknote is also a ballot paper, with which you can decide for more or less emissions. For almost any way of spending money - be it groceries or mobility - there are climate compatible and non compatible choices. I can fly or take the train, or - if the later is not possible - at least compensate the warming effects via sites such as atmosfair.de.</p>
<p>But even when I save money, it's up to me if it works for or against climate sustainability. For every investment possible, by now there are also options that support the protection of the climate - often without needing to forgo returns. The money I put on the bank is used for investments and projects that contribute to or undermine the sustainability of our economic system.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: Does that mean the demand for a climate compatible life style?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CB</hi>: It's not about one climate compatible life style. It's more of a case of a climate compatible variant needing to be developed for each of the different life styles that exist in our society. The people in our society don't need to become uniform. Some will focus on protecting the climate through technical innovations and will bring their house up to the most recent level of efficiency, and massively use renewable energies. Others will see an increase in wealth in not having a car, instead buying a "Bahncard 100" <hi rend="italic">[This is a flat rate for a years rail travel in Germany, at a cost of 3500 Euro, ed.]</hi> which also lets you take your kids along for free, and focus on a slower more conscious life. We don't need to prescribe one life style, what is necessary is to advance every life style variant in a climate compatible way</p>
</text>
