<text id="autogum_voyage_doc519" title="Marsabit" shortTile="marsabit" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=21491" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Marsabit</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Marsabit</hi> is a city in <ref target="Kenya">Kenya</ref>.</p>

<head>See</head>
<p>Marsabit is on a plateau that rises above the surrounding rocky plains. There is increased rainfall here so the area is very green compared to the surrounding desert. Marsabit National Reserve is meant to protect part of this forest and large herds of elephants can be seen around the crater lakes in the park--definitely worth seeing. Also, short hikes from the center of town to the two hills with visible towers give panoramic views of the countryside.</p>

<head>Buy</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">DIKUS Ltd</hi>, 60500-262 (along marsabit - moyale highway), ☏ +254728534608 , ✉ kunnielle@yahoo.com . It is an ultra modern shopping stop that stocks mostly foodstuffs. you can feel closest to home with familiar brands and almost anything you'd need available in stock. they are the leading stockists of both local and international brands of consumables. it is the only place you'd get genuine cigarettes. they have very friendly staff who would even go an extra mile to source for you what they don't have in stock ensuring that you get everything under one roof.</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chicho</hi> is a new hotel that targets foreign travellers and locals. It has ultra-modern rooms that are all ensuite. The management makes it feel very homely and you can also get quality local dishes at the restaurant. It is on the main road from Shell Petrol Station towards the post office and along the way the sign post is visible.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Jay Jay's Hotel</hi> (rooms from Ksh 250/night). There is a courtyard and restaurant on the second floor. There is a shared bathroom and showers, but no running water. Water has to be requested at the office and a bucket is brought to you. If you would rather use a latrine - asking the watchman in front of the building for the key to the Choo (latrine in Swahili) which is around the side of the building has been sometimes successful.</item>
</list>


<p><hi rend="bold">Jinjimana's</hi> is a smaller hotel nearby. It is a bit cheaper (Ksh 150/night) has clean rooms, a shared latrine and a shower with heated water! For outsiders Ksh 50 to take a shower.</p>

<head>Go next</head>
<p>Trucks leave everyday day south for <ref target="Isiolo">Isiolo</ref> or all the way to <ref target="Nairobi">Nairobi</ref> and north to <ref target="Moyale">Moyale</ref> on the border with <ref target="Ethiopia">Ethiopia</ref>. A ride in the cab of a truck can cost around US$20. Most trucks do a two-day drive to <ref target="Nairobi">Nairobi</ref> with an overnight stop in Isiolo. There is also a bus that leaves early in the morning every few days from infront of the Modern Hotel. A seat is Ksh 1000 and should be bought the night before if possible because it seems to fill up fast. Be ready for you pack to be tied ontop of the bus. The road to Isiolo is unpaved and very bumpy. Also there are rumors of bandits along the stretch just before reaching <ref target="Archer%27s%20Post">Archer's Post</ref>. Police also stop the bus at every check point and often demand bribes. </p>
</text>
