<text id="autogum_interview_doc434" title="part1_Ahmedi of Iran&amp;apos;s PDKI discusses Kurdistan&amp;apos;s general strike and the democratic future of Iran" shortTile="partahmedi-irans" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-07-15" dateModified="2009-11-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ahmedi_of_Iran%27s_PDKI_discusses_Kurdistan%27s_general_strike_and_the_democratic_future_of_Iran" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What's the place of federalist liberal democracy in a post-theocratic Iran? Should it be concerned mostly with relieving ethnic tensions? Is overcentralization a fundamental problem of the Iranian state?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Loghman Ahmedi</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> It is our firm belief that democracy and federalism will solve many of Iran’s internal and external problems. Iran’s destructive foreign policies are a reflection of the nature of the Islamic Republic, that is to say, its undemocratic nature. Iran’s ethnic and national diversity holds the key to democracy in Iran because this diversity can function as the best form of checks and balances to decentralize power in the country for the twin aim of safeguarding liberty and democracy internally and to turn Iran into a constructive regional and international member of the world community. A decentralized, federal and democratic Iran, unlike the Islamic Republic of today, will not export and support fundamentalism and terrorism. Given Iran’s lack of democratic traditions and a host of other factors, it is the country’s diversity that can be conducive to democracy.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why hasn't the PDKI signed onto the Iran Solidarity group that was formed in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Europe">Europe</ref> earlier this week?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Loghman Ahmedi</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> To my knowledge, the organizers of this campaign have not approached our party. But our party has in different statements and actions expressed its solidarity with the brave people that are standing up against the regime. At the same time, I have to underline that it is important for us that our support and solidarity is not interpreted as support for the “reformist” faction of the regime. We support the political struggle for liberty and democracy in Iran. This should be differentiated from taking sides in the regime’s factional infighting between “conservatives” and “reformists”. Whatever their differences, these factions are all defenders of the Islamic system of government, which is antithetical to liberty and democracy.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">You first left Kurdistan over twenty years ago. Can you comment on how the situation for Iranian Kurds has changed since then?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Loghman Ahmedi</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> During the past 30 years, cultural oppression and discrimination, deliberate state policies to keep Kurdistan in a state of economic underdevelopment, torture, executions, arbitrary imprisonment and “disappearances” of political activists and civilians have been part and parcel of the lives of the Kurds. So it would be more adequate to speak of continuity rather than change. Furthermore, what is new to the picture is the spread of narcotics among the Kurdish youth, which we believe is a deliberate policy by the regime to destroy the fabric of the Kurdish society and, hence, to prevent organized resistance in Kurdistan.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How would you characterize the strike that's underway in Iranian Kurdistan now? Is it closely tied to the movement against Ahmedinejad in the Persian cities of Iran, or is it more a purely Kurdish phenomenon?</hi></p>
</text>
