<text id="autogum_academic_doc640" title="The Association Between Health Conditions, Consciousness, Involvement, and Knowledge and Dietary Supplement Intake among University Students in South Korea" shortTile="association-between" author="Jinkyung Choi" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/20/4028/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
This study found that more than half of respondents have taken DSs, and out of these groups, almost half were taking the aforementioned supplements during the course of the research. This result is similar to the outcome of the KNHANES, which indicated that about 42% of Korean adults have taken a DS at least once in their life. Interestingly, the most important driver of DS consumption is recommendation from family members. College students’ behaviors, such as valuing their peers’ opinions, were in line with adolescent behaviors. A previous study found that most college students who took DSs were usually recommended to by family and friends. This study also found similar outcomes. University students are still in the transition stage between adolescence and adulthood and may therefore continue to need extra care from their families. Adolescents are a most vulnerable and easily misinformed population, who are targeted by the DS industry. Suggestions from friends also considerably influence the health behaviors of university students, who tend to emulate their peers. DS consumption is likewise prompted by the desire to promote general health. The transition from high school to college may result in alterations to dietary behaviors because of dramatic changes in surrounding environments. To compensate for lifestyle adaptations, college students may consume DSs to maintain overall well-being. </p>

<p>The current work found that nutritional information on product packaging was the most important factor for the consideration of DS purchase. Consumers search for information when they make decisions because of the many choices and products that are available to them. An intriguing finding in this research is that although the respondents’ knowledge levels were low, they still carefully examined nutritional information on packaging, suggesting that some information can be misleading or some other reasons for consumers. Abundant information on DS products may confuse consumers, especially those who have low knowledge of these commodities. Many previous studies confirmed that knowledge level and health behaviors are irrelevant to consumers’ decision to purchase products; that is, purchase is based on perceptions rather than objective evidence. Hence, education that cultivates adequate knowledge about DSs is needed. </p>

<p>Recommendations from others accounted for the second most influential factor for DS consumption for the same reasons discussed in regard to family and peer influence. The most commonly consumed DSs were multivitamins, consistent with the findings of another study. Meanwhile DS users and non-users significantly differed in terms of DS intake, but no such difference was found in connection with other health-related behaviors. </p>

<p>DSs can be beneficial to one’s health; if an individual is driven to take these products out of concern for his/her well-being, then such behavior may motivate other healthful habits, such as regular exercise. However, no differences were found between DS users and non-users. The relationship between stress and food intake is a well-known phenomenon. Food intake increases and shifts toward unhealthy choices when people are exposed to stressful conditions. Concerns have been raised regarding the possibility that DSs will encourage individuals to eat less healthy food or pursue unhealthy lifestyles. DS users may rely solely on supplements and neglect other health behaviors that may bring about positive health outcomes. </p>

<p>The prevalence of DS consumption has been attributed to health conditions and health consciousness. This study postulated that health consciousness significantly affects DS consumption, but general health conditions and health consciousness were viewed in a neutral manner by both the DS users and non-users. These individuals were highly confident about their health and physical strength. Given that DSs are dispensed without the need for a prescription and are available to all individuals who may have different health conditions, the benefits of such products may be minimal, and their efficacy remains controversial. Therefore, although the DS users may have been aware of the potentially weak efficacy of DSs, they also held positive perceptions of the benefits of consuming these supplements. This positivity might have stemmed from advertisements that deliver highly persuasive messages in a fiercely competitive DS market. The result can also be attributed to the DS users understanding that supplement consumption helps them keep pace with the demands of campus life, which is known to present easy access to rapidly available snacks, regardless of the health condition and consciousness of students. </p>

<p>Given that involvement is difficult to measure, information search behaviors were used instead. These behaviors were significantly more prevalent among the DS users than non-users. Involvement is related to certain manners of conduct because DS purchase requires considerable cognitive effort, in contrast to food purchase. As previously mentioned, the DS users and non-users exhibited no difference in terms of health conditions and consciousness. Thus, individuals in need of DSs look for information and are finally led to purchase these supplements. </p>
</text>
