<text id="autogum_news_doc189" title="Iranian news agency reproduces The Onion article" shortTile="iranian-news-agency" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-09-29" dateModified="2012-10-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iranian_news_agency_reproduces_The_Onion_article" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Iranian news agency reproduces The Onion article</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 29, 2012</hi></p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fars%20News%20Agency">Fars News Agency</ref> (FNA), an <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iran">Iranian</ref> news agency, yesterday reported an article from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">US</ref> satirical news website <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Onion">The Onion</ref></hi> as fact. The article reports "a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Gallup%20Organization">Gallup</ref> poll" suggesting "the overwhelming majority of rural white Americans" would prefer to vote for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mahmoud_Ahmadinejad">Mahmoud Ahmadinejad</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/President%20of%20Iran">President of Iran</ref>, as opposed to US <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/President_of_the_United_States">President</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref>. <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi> article reports "77 percent of rural <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caucasian%20race">Caucasian</ref> voters" saying they would prefer to drink beer with Ahmadinejad or attend a baseball game with him.  <figure rend="FARS News Agency 'Gallup Poll Rural Whites Prefer Ahmadinejad To Obama' - 2012-09-28.JPG"></figure></p>
<p>Fictional <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/West_Virginia">West Virginia</ref> resident Dale Swiderski is reported by the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Chicago,_Illinois">Chicago</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Illinois">Illinois</ref> based website saying about Ahmadinejad: "I like him better". 'Swiderski' is also quoted as saying the Iranian President "takes national defense seriously, and he'd never let some gay protesters tell him how to run his country like Obama does."</p>
<p>In Iran, <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/homosexuality">homosexuality</ref> is a criminal offence which can carry a penalty of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Incarceration">incarceration</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Capital_punishment">capital punishment</ref>. Just over five years ago, when he participated in a debate at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Columbia%20University">Columbia University</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York,_New_York">New York</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York">New York</ref>, Ahmadinejad stated "In Iran we don't have homosexuals like in your country".</p>
<p>The FNA copied <hi rend="italic">The Onion'</hi>s article verbatim and in its entirety, excluding part of a sentence saying Ahmadinejad was "a man who has repeatedly <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holocaust%20denial">denied</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Holocaust">the Holocaust</ref> and has had numerous political prisoners executed". However, the Iranian news service did not attribute <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi> as its source.</p>
<p>The FNA's error has made international headlines, including in the United States, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada">Canada</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Kingdom">United Kingdom</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia">Australia</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/India">India</ref>.</p>
<p>A link to the FNA article page redirects to an error message which reads: "Error For Your Request. Not Exist This Story." However, <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi> included a link to a screenshot of the FNA's page on their original article, accompanied by a message telling readers to "visit our Iranian subsidiary organization" for more information on the story.</p>
<p>There are no reports of the article being republished in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Persian%20language">Persian</ref>. The FNA has yet to comment on the incident. However, <hi rend="italic">The Onion'</hi>s editor Will Tracy humourously remarked their website "freely shares content with Fars and commends the journalists at Iran's Finest News Source on their superb reportage".</p>
<p>This is not the first time <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi> has caused the mistaken belief of their material being accurate. In a November 2007 interview with <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi>, <hi rend="italic">The Onion'</hi>s Editorial Manager Chet Clem recounted an incident in which the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beijing%20Evening%20News">Beijing Evening News</ref> reproduced a story from <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi> created in 2002, copied entirely verbatim, headlined "Congress threatens to leave DC unless new capitol is built". When the error was highlighted to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China">Chinese</ref> newspaper, Clem said "their response was not to print a correction, but just to say that some newspapers in America make money by printing lies." In a separate incident, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Christianity">Christians</ref> forwarded a story on the Internet from <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi> saying children were converting to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Satanism">Satanism</ref> as a result of reading the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harry%20Potter">Harry Potter</ref> book series.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BBC_News_Online">BBC News Online</ref></hi> also reported an instance of two newspapers in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bangladesh">Bangladesh</ref> apologising over their publication of an article <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moon%20landing%20conspiracy%20theories">disputing</ref> the validity of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Apollo_program">moon landings</ref>, originally written by <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi>.</p>
This story has updates
See <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iranian_news_agency_apologises_for_reproducing_The_Onion_article">Iranian news agency apologises for reproducing The Onion article</ref>, October 1, 2012
</text>
