<text id="autogum_interview_doc273" title="part2_Dublin travel agents occupy offices against closure" shortTile="partdublin-travel" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-08-02" dateModified="2012-03-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dublin_travel_agents_occupy_offices_against_closure" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Cullen said that a chance for a peaceful resolution to the situation, without the involvement of the Gardai, was up to Thomas Cook management. "Thomas Cook have the chance to come to the table and talk to us. It's in their hands, they still have the chance to come back."</p>
<hi rend="bold">We were not in any position to consult with senior managers who had their own hidden agenda</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Pauline McManigan, Direct Holidays employee</p>
<p>Pauline McManigan, a TSSA member and employee at Thomas Cook subsidiary Direct Holidays' shop in Talbot Street, echoed Cullen's sentiments. "John Kinnane [Thomas Cook's managing director for Direct Holidays] has made things extremely difficult for all staff. He has intimidated staff, bullied staff and used abusive language toward female staff", telling one employee today to "fuck off" in response to a query. Kinnane refused to recognise the TSSA as representing the Direct Holidays staff; without union representation, Direct Holidays staff "were not in any position to consult with senior managers who had their own hidden agenda and proved this when they closed the consultation down when staff said there were other matters that needed to be discussed." Kinnane, she said, made threats similar to Robinson's in order to get employees to vote for the five-week redundancy package.</p>
<figure><caption>Talbot Street, Dublin Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Sebb">Sebb</ref>.</caption></figure><p>McManigan says that Kinnane has demanded Direct Holidays' staff return to work on Tuesday as normal. "That's not gonna happen", she replies, noting that the Direct Holidays staff did not trust Thomas Cook management not to close and strip out the store while the employees were not present. McManigan gave the following statement: </p>
The staff at Direct Holidays based at 17 Talbot Street, Dublin 1 never had any intention to strike, officially or unofficially, on these premises, although we did pledge our support to our colleagues based at the Grafton Street store &amp; our union, the TSSA, who have supported us wholeheartedly all the way through this. Thomas Cook sent their security firm to this building yesterday to intimidate its staff and try to bully them into handing over the keys to this premises. Staff refused to hand over the keys as there was a fear that the Direct Holiday shop based at 17 Talbot Street would be stripped over the bank holiday weekend and when we returned on Tuesday there would be no office here, as was done at North Earl Street Thomas Cook. Thomas Cook/Capital Holdings has provoked all staff based at Direct Holiday into the action. John Kinnane, the managing director of Capital Holdings has never supported staff at Direct Holidays and initiated senior members of human resources from the UK to come to us and bully us. Staff at direct holidays will stand firm united and strong through all of this. We will not stand down.
</text>
