<text id="autogum_interview_doc543" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Jeff Jacobsen, creator of LisaMcPherson.org" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-12" dateModified="2012-12-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Jeff_Jacobsen%2C_creator_of_LisaMcPherson.org" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Do you feel mocking the silliness of the upper level teachings is helpful?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.J.</hi>: No. <hi rend="bold">But</hi>, I think exposing their secret teachings is good.  It's very strange that you have a religion where you can't tell what they believe until you pay them. So it's fine by me to expose their teachings so people can decide if that's what they want to get into or not. I suppose I've helped make fun of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Xenu">Xenu</ref>, though.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : As we understand it, the Church believes their teachings allow you to overcome illness. Does this work? What do they do when it doesn't?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.J.</hi>: Scientology makes abundant medical claims in their writings, yes. But they are not qualified in any way to deal with medical issues. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lisa%20McPherson">Lisa McPherson</ref> was the perfect example of that. They were handling her according to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/L.%20Ron%20Hubbard">Hubbard</ref>'s teachings, and she died as a result. This is one of the ways Scientology hurts people. It should be stopped. Exposing their unscientific gobble-dee gook is hopefully helpful in stopping more harm.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : What is Church of Scientology policy for off-loading its members when they become seriously ill?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.J.</hi>: I'm not sure of the answer to that. I've heard of "off-loading" where there have been reported cases that they've kicked out people who are more a burden than a help and from what I know, they have no retirement plan for long-time employees or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sea%20Org">Sea Orgers</ref>. I'll give one example, Heber Jentzch's wife, Yvonne, got cancer. She died at a young age, they treated it as if she chose to do that. In their obituaries they say "we look forward to X's soon return". They believe in reincarnation.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : What is your key issue with the Church having tax exempt status within the United States?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.J.</hi>: 1) they got it by pressuring the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internal%20Revenue%20Service">IRS</ref> rather than legitimately 2) they aren't qualified 3) they conducted the largest infiltration of the federal government in US history, then that government gives them tax exemption? These are the same people that were there back then. Kendrick Moxon was part of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operation%20Snow%20White">Operation Snow White</ref> and he's still a Scientology attorney. Many reasons. The Sklar case, and the Hernandez Supreme Court ruling also de-legitimizes their tax exemption.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Why mock an organization that has members who believe it has helped them?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.J.</hi>: I hope we don't mock. I hope we inform, expose, and educate. It's easy to make fun of Xenu and that, and I suppose I'm guilty of doing that too. But the goal of critics is to inform, not mock.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Some people claim Scientology has worked for them, why should they be persecuted or hounded, for what after all is free choice of belief?</p>
</text>
