<text id="autogum_academic_doc630" title="Adipose Tissue Quality in Aging: How Structural and Functional Aspects of Adipose Tissue Impact Skeletal Muscle Quality" shortTile="adipose-tissue-quality" author="Flavia  G. De Carvalho, Jamie  N. Justice, Ellen  C. de Freitas, Erin  E. Kershaw, Lauren  M. Sparks" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6643/11/11/2553/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Adipose Tissue Inflammation during Aging</head>
<p>
Adipose tissue plays an essential role in age-related metabolic dysfunction and is linked to systemic, chronic, and low-grade inflammation. Aging is associated with a decline in immune competence referred to as immunosenescence, which leads to chronic, low-grade inflammation named “inflammaging”. Adipose tissue inflammation results in the release of pro-inflammatory cytokines such as TNF-α, IL-1b, IL-6 and monocyte chemoattractant protein (MCP-1/CCL2) from adipose tissue macrophages, and these factors are also associated to the presence of senescent cells (p16INK4A) leading to immunosenescence. </p>

<p>The exposure of macrophages to hormones, cytokines, chemokines, and fatty acids found within dysfunctional adipose tissue stimulates them to adopt a pro-inflammatory phenotype inflammation. Age-associated adipose tissue inflammation is related to the activation of the NFκB signaling pathway, with promotes a pro-inflammatory polarization of adipose tissue macrophages, independent from total adipose tissue mass. The stimulus for age-associated macrophage pro-inflammatory polarization can be associated with endoplasmic reticulum stress, which promotes a pro-inflammatory environment due to the release of IL-6, MCP-1, and TNF-α cytokines within adipose tissue. The decreased vascularization promoted by aging promotes local hypoxia and favors adipose tissue macrophage accumulation. The macrophage infiltration is perpetuated by a reduction in the mitochondrial cytochrome c oxidase subunit 5B (COX5B) component of complex IV within adipocytes, which inhibits lipolytic signaling and free-fatty acid mobilization and increases intracellular lipid storage. Hypertrophic expansion of adipocytes promotes stress signals, thereby contributing to immunometabolic dysfunction both locally and systemically. </p>

<p>Besides macrophages, dysfunctional adipose tissue can exacerbate immunosenescence by promoting activation and differentiation of immune cells such as B cells (B lymphocytes), nautral killer (NK) lymphocytes, regulatory T cells, neutrophils, eosinophils, mast cells, dendritic cells. Immune cell accumulation in AT induces pro-inflammatory cytokine release leads to inflammasome activation and formation of crown-like structure. The function of immune cells have been investigated in obesity, however some studies suggest that the pro-inflammatory microenvironment of aged murine adipose tissue, characterized by TNF-α, IFN-γ, IL-6 and prostaglandin E2 (PGE2) release, could promote NFκB activation consequently modulate dendritic cell function, also can activate neutrophils. Controversially, the pro-inflammatory state can inhibit regulatory T cells and NK lymphocytes, and also impair anti-inflammatory defense. </p>

<p>Taken together, the chronic inflammatory environment promoted by aging can contribute to adipose tissue and skeletal muscle dysfunction and consequently leads to a feedback loop that perpetuates adipose inflammation and redistribution, impairs progenitor cell differentiation and leads to cellular dysfunction and death of adipocytes and neighboring cells such as skeletal muscle cells. The effects of inflammation on skeletal muscle is also related to the effects of inflammatory mediators on muscle protein metabolism (muscle protein breakdown and synthesis); however, way in which the inflammatory factors can induce muscle wasting and the extent to which they do so remains a largely unexplored area of research in aging. </p>
</text>
