<text id="autogum_interview_doc177" title="part1_Wikinews interviews 0 A.D. game development team" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-03-22" dateModified="2011-11-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_0_A.D._game_development_team" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">BD</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why did you choose a free license?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">AS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> People are spending more money, time and attention on playing computer games than ever before, and games are constantly evolving into a more nuanced medium of expression and a greater part of our culture. Just observe how much people play on Facebook and their mobile devices. We think this culture should allow gamers to learn how their games work, change them, share them and redistribute their works. This freedom to tinker is what Free, Open-Source Software (FOSS) is all about and so we hope a lot of people tinker with 0 A.D.</p>
<figure><caption>A city, as shown within the game. Image: Robert Schultz de Plainsboro.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">BD</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How do you coordinate ? What technical and financial resources has 0 A.D.?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">AS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> We mostly coordinate over a forum system we have, as well as a Trac system for task management and technical documentation. We also conduct discussions over IRC (#0ad and #0ad-dev on QuakeNet), that get more concentrated on the weekend, and Saturday afternoon in particular, when we have our weekly meeting.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">BD</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Which type of participants do you need? 'Amateurs' can they participate?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">AS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Amateurs can definitely help with tasks like documentation and spreading the word about 0 A.D. For other tasks, we do require some prior knowledge in fields such as software development, 3d animation etc. 
Our main personnel needs are in three fields: Programmers, artists and sound people. We have many applicants for sound contributors but need a manager to oversee them. For programming we need capable gameplay, AI, sound and graphics programmers, proficient in C++ and/or JavaScript. Finally, in the art department, we could use some more texture artists, 3D artists, animators, and illustrators to draw 2d icons for the game's user interface.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">BD</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">It's been 10 years since 0 A.D. is developing, what obstacles have arisen and how have you resolved?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">AS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> The biggest obstacle we have run into is underestimating the scale and complexity of an RTS game. When embarking upon this journey in 2001, nobody thought that completing this endeavor would take this long. Evidently, making an RTS game requires a great deal of programming features, art assets and more. And, as we discovered the hard way, the first draft of anything is seldom good enough. For example, one of the most important engine components, named "Simulation", was simply planned wrong the first time around. Simulation is in charge of changing the state of each entity in the "world" represented in the game, like handling harvesting resources, doing damage to stuff and handling death. Sadly, over time it got implemented in such a haphazard way it devolved into an unstable, unpredictable ball of mud. Debugging became difficult and attracting new programmers from joining the development effort became impossible. Over time, fewer and fewer developers stayed on with 0 A.D. and it seemed as if the project was in grave danger of ending, the way many initiatives on the internet spontaneously do.</p>
</text>
