<text id="autogum_interview_doc074" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Indiana State Senator Mike Delph" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-03-26" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Indiana_State_Senator_Mike_Delph" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Jones Phillips: Can you tell where you went to school at?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MD</hi>:  I went through the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carmel%20Clay%20School%20District">Carmel school system</ref>. And I’m a graduate of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carmel%20High%20School%20(Carmel,%20Indiana)">Carmel High School</ref> — in 1988. And then I went on to college at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indiana%20University%20Bloomington">Indiana University</ref>. And ultimately received four degrees from Indiana University.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Tew: And those degrees are in ...?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MD</hi>:  I have a Bachelor of Arts degree in speech communications with minors in Spanish, biology, and an emphasis in chemistry. I have a Masters in Public Affairs with an emphasis in international relations — or comparative international relations — and public finance. I have a Masters of Science in Environmental Science, focused on applied ecology. And then I have my law degree at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indiana%20University%20Robert%20H.%20McKinney%20School%20of%20Law">Indiana University School of Law</ref> at Indianapolis.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  And lastly I want to know, how did you become interested in politics?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MD</hi>: I kind of backed my way into politics. I had served as a page for Indiana State Senator <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dan%20Burton">Dan Burton</ref>. And my mom and dad went to high school with Congressman Burton at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shortridge%20High%20School">Shortridge High School</ref>. We had a family friendly connection there. But I really didn't grow up in politics. I didn't serve in student government — except one little stint when I was a graduate student at Indiana University. I served one summer stint as a representative from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indiana%20University%20School%20of%20Public%20and%20Environmental%20Affairs">School of Public and Environmental Affairs</ref>. But I really wasn't involved in politics.</p>
<p>After I was getting ready to graduate from graduate school, I had planned to go to work for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/State%20Farm%20Insurance">State Farm Insurance</ref> as a bond analyst. About that time, I had made contact with Congressman Burton, who was going to become the first Republican chairman, to chair a Congressional committee in over 60[?] years from Indiana. And we got to talking and eventually that led to a job offer for me to come and join him on his personal and professional staff out in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Washington_D.C.">Washington D.C.</ref> working on Capitol Hill. So I worked out of the personal office and then the professional staff of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20House%20Committee%20on%20Oversight%20and%20Government%20Reform">House Committee on Government Reform</ref>, primarily focusing on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War%20on%20Drugs">Drug War policy</ref>. I also did some work with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20House%20Committee%20on%20Foreign%20Affairs">House International Relations Committee</ref>, which at the time was chaired by Congressman <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benjamin%20A.%20Gilman">Ben Gillman</ref> from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York">New York</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Hello Senator Delph, I’m Sara Behnke. We were wanting to know about your family and your work outside of the Indiana Senate.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MD</hi>: My family is: My wife is Beth. She is from Zionsville. She grew up in Zionsville and graduated from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zionsville%20Community%20High%20School">Zionsville High School</ref>. She is the daughter of Russ and Nancy Frankel and has one brother, who is younger, named Matthew. My in-laws are now constituents of mine, which is nice because my mother-in-law could put my yard sign in her yard without confusing her neighbors.</p>
</text>
