<text id="autogum_voyage_doc435" title="Vicenza" shortTile="vicenza" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=37941" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Vicenza</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.comune.vicenza.it/">Vicenza</ref></hi> is a medium-sized city located in <ref target="Veneto">Veneto</ref>, in northeastern <ref target="Italy">Italy</ref>, and the capital of the <ref target="Vicenza%20%28province%29">namesake province</ref>. The city and the surrounding countryside and hills are particularly famous for the many works, and particularly the Villas, by Palladio. Because of the architectonic contributions of Andrea Palladio, it was inscribed in the <ref target="UNESCO%20World%20Heritage%20List">UNESCO World Heritage List</ref> in 1994.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>Vicenza is an ancient city. In 157 b.D. it entered into the roman empire with the name <hi rend="italic">Vicetia</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Vincentia</hi>. In 889 it was destroyed by Hungarians, and in 1001 it became an episcopal stronghold. In 1404 it became part of the Republic of <ref target="Venice">Venice</ref>.</p>

<p>The XVI century was very important for Vicenza because Andrea Palladio built several villas and palaces. During the 19th century, after the fall of Napoleon, the city was taken by Austria, but in 1848 the citizens rebelled against the Austrian government and in 1866 it finally became part of the Kingdom of Italy.</p>

<head>By train</head>

<p>The train station is located on the southern part of the town, at the end of Viale Roma. Piazza Castello and the old town are a mere 5-minute walk from the station. The station is on the line connecting <ref target="Milan">Milan</ref> to <ref target="Venice">Venice</ref>. There are also a number of trains to other major cities and destinations such as <ref target="Bologna">Bologna</ref> to the south, <ref target="Bolzano">Bolzano</ref> to the north, and <ref target="Trieste">Trieste</ref> to the east via connections <ref target="Verona">Verona</ref>, <ref target="Padova">Padova</ref>, Venice, and <ref target="Trento">Trento</ref>.</p>

<p>Trains to the towns and cities around Vicenza depart daily (times provided are for regional trains). The most common are to Verona (1 hour), Padova (25 minutes), Venice (1 hour 15 minutes). Trains also depart for Bassano del Grappa, Treviso, Castelfranco, Rovigo, Sirmione, and Ferrara.</p>

<p>Taking international trains from Vicenza is possible, but it could be slower and/or more expensive since the city is not a major station for train transit. Instead, it is highly recommended to book a train to France, Spain or Switzerland from Milan; Austria and Germany from Verona; and Eastern Europe from Venice. Book a separate (cheap) ticket to these cities and make your connection from there.</p>

<p>More info on <ref target="http://www.trenitalia.com">Trenitalia</ref>. When booking overseas train tickets, make sure to ask for the "Smart" special deal, which provides up to a 50% discount. The deal is especially good for destinations in Eastern Europe such as Budapest or Belgrade, where tickets could be as low as 15 euros one-way (instead of 50 euros and above). Trenitalia requires you to buy the ticket 7–15 days in advance, so make sure you plan your trip ahead of time. The website only accepts Italian credit cards, so your best bet is to buy your ticket at the train station.</p>

<head>By car</head>

<p>Vicenza could be reached via the following highways: A4 - from Torino, Milan, Venice or Trieste; A31 - from Schio, Asiago, and Bassano del Grappa; A22 - From Bolzano, Trento, Garda Lake, Mantova and Modena via Verona; A13 - from Bologna and Florence via Padova</p>

<p>A number of strade statale (SS), strade regionale (SR) and strade provinciale (SP) criss-cross Vicenza, and they are a great way to reach many of the great small towns that surround Vicenza. The roads going south to Colli Euganei through Colli Berici, to the northeast to Recoaro Terme, and to the northwest to Treviso via Bassano del Grappa and Asolo are particularly beautiful and highly recommended for those looking for drives through groves of olive trees, vineyards, hills, hidden valleys, and remote hill towns. However, it is not recommended for going to major towns such as Verona, Padova, or Venice. These roads are almost always backlogged with traffic and marred by seriously ugly industrial areas.</p>

<head>By bus</head>

<p>Vicenza is connected to other cities with a bus service offered by <ref target="http://www.ftv.vi.it/">Ferrovie Tramvie Vicentine</ref> . It is a less comfortable service than train, but it can reach several places that don't have a train station. Some long distance destinations (such as Milan and Venice) are possible, but by and large the buses only serve the province of Vicenza and the immediate towns outside of it. The bus station is located about 100 meters to the left of the train station.</p>

<head>By bicycle</head>

<p>If you are up for it, it is easy to reach Vicenza via the smaller roads listed above via bicycle. Cycling is a very popular activity in Italy, and many are even brave enough to attempt the alpine crossing from countries in the north to Italy. Stay on the secondary roads however, as it is not only illegal but incredibly dangerous to ride your bicycle in the autostrada. Also, do the trip from mid-Spring to late Summer as Northern Italy suffers very heavy fog during Autumn and Winter, and snow and ice conditions could be very dangerous and unpredictable especially in the mountains.</p>

<head>By foot</head>

<p>Vicenza's city center is small enough to be comfortably explored on foot. The main road through the old town is Corso Palladio, which contains the best of the city center's shopping as well as most of Palladio's urban palaces. The hike from the city center to Monte Berico is uphill but still not so strenuous, and the road circles around to Villa Valmarana ai Nani down to the entrance to the Rotonda. Although most recommendations are to take the bus to the Rotonda and back, this walk will get you to some of the best and uncrowded parts of Vicenza.</p>

<head>By bicycle</head>

<p>There are a number of bicycle rental companies in Vicenza as well as surrounding towns and cities that service Vicenza. For a listing of these companies as well as to book a bicycle rental, inquire at the Tourism Offices in Piazza Matteoti next to the Teatro Olimpico or at the Piazza dei Signori right in front of the Basilica Palladiana.</p>

<head>By bus</head>

<p>The city is well-serviced by bus. Times and schedules are posted on their website at <ref target="http://www.aim-mobilita.it/"></ref> (in Italian only). The most important lines are #1 to the shopping malls and #8 to the Rotonda.</p>

<head>By car</head>

<p>Vicenza's city center is small enough that there is no need for a car if you only want to explore the city center, Monte Berico and the Rotonda. In fact, it is also not recommended if you are only staying within these areas as the ZTL (zona trafico limitato—no drive zones) is very strictly enforced, encompasses most if not all of the city center, and changes frequently and without notice.</p>

<p>However, if you are planning on driving around the surrounding country side to see the villas and go wine-tasting, there are really no other realistic option other than to drive a car. Car rental companies Avis and Hertz are both located within a two-minute walk from the train station.</p>
</text>
