<text id="autogum_academic_doc332" title="The Impacts of Nano-Micrometer Pore Structure on the Gas Migration and Accumulation in Tight Sandstone Gas Reservoirs" shortTile="impacts-nanomicrometer" author="Juncheng Qiao, Xianzheng Zhao, Jianhui Zeng, Guomeng Han, Shu Jiang, Sen Feng, Xiao Feng" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/21/4102/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Tight gas has attracted worldwide attention since the exploration of the large Cretaceous Balnco low-permeability gas field in the San Juan Basin in North America. Tight sandstone gas serves as an important alternative to the conventional petroleum resources and shows good resource prospect. Tight sandstone gas has been discovered in more than 70 basins worldwide, which are mainly distributed in North America, Europe, and Asia. The United States and China are two main producers of tight sands gas; the United States has a tight sandstone gas reserve of 42.5 × 1012 m3 with an annual production of 1754 × 108 m3. The exploration of tight sandstone gas has developed rapidly in the past decades in China, and prolific tight gas reservoirs have been discovered in the Ordos Basin, Sichuan Basin, and Songliao Basin. </p>

<p>Tight sandstone gas is generally referred to as the tight sandstone reservoirs with complex gas and water distributions, low gas saturation, and continuous accumulation characteristics. The tight gas sandstone reservoir is defined as gas-bearing sandstone reservoirs with porosity &lt;10%, in situ permeability &lt;0.1 × 10−3 mD or absolute permeability &lt;1.0 × 10−3 mD, gas saturation &lt;60%, and pore-throat radius &lt;1 μm. </p>

<p>Tight sandstone gas reservoirs are characterized by inter-bedded or closely distributed source rock and reservoirs, small pore and throat radii, high water saturation, and non-tectonic controlled gas distributions. The low gas saturation and complex gas and water distributions are the main risks for the exploration and recovery enhancement of tight sandstone gas. The gas saturation varies and has a heterogeneous distribution poorly correlated with reservoir quality. Porosity and permeability are no longer suitable for the prediction of gas enrichment zones in tight sandstone gas reservoirs. Moreover, gas saturation and distribution are determined by the gas migration and accumulation patterns. Due to the nano-micrometer pore system in tight sandstone reservoirs, the capillary pressure increases evidently in tight sandstone. The buoyancy is invalid in driving gas flow and the overpressure becomes the dominant driving force for gas migration. Spencer has emphasized that driving pressure difference decides the degrees of gas migration and accumulation in tight sandstone reservoirs. The ultra-high capillary pressure generated by formation water in the pore space becomes the main resistance for the gas migration in tight sandstone reservoirs. As the resistance is determined by the pore geometries, pore structure becomes an important factor for gas migration and accumulation. The heterogeneity of gas saturation and distribution is attributable to the complex microscopic pore structure of tight sandstone reservoirs. Therefore, pore structure characterization and gas migration characteristics have become the focus of current studies. Pore size, genesis, morphology, and fractal characteristics have been thoroughly investigated by various techniques including mercury intrusion porosimetry (MIP), scanning electron microscopy (SEM), nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR), low temperature N2 absorption (LTNA), and X-ray computed tomography (X-CT). Recent studies tend to characterize the full-range pore size distribution by integration of several techniques, such as NMR and MIP, LTNA and NMR, and MIP and X-CT. These studies provide mature methodology and sufficient information for the pore structure of tight sandstone reservoirs. The gas flow regimes have been clearly stated by experimental and numerical simulations, including the Darcy, high-velocity non-Darcy, and low-velocity non-Darcy flows. However, these results are based on the discussions of single-phase fluid flow and have differences with the gas migration process, which is rarely involved. Zeng firstly proposed the minimum migration pressure gradients by investigating the gas flow in migration in tight sandstone reservoirs and indicated that porosity and permeability influences the gas flow patterns, minimum migration pressure gradients, and gas saturation. Moreover, absent evaluations in the relationships between pore structures and gas flows result in uncertainties in the intrinsic microscopic controlling factors for the gas flow in migration. Therefore, combined pore structure characterization and gas migration simulation appear to be necessary in revealing the impacts of pore structure on the gas migration and accumulation. </p>

<p>The Upper Paleozoic Permian Daniudi gas field in the Ordos Basin was chosen as the study area for the heterogeneous reservoir qualities, complicated gas-water distribution, low gas saturation, and their poor internal relationships, which are similar to the tight gas reservoirs in the sedimentary basins in the North Sea and in North America. In order to reveal the impacts of pore structure on the gas flow in migration and accumulation process in the tight sandstone, physical simulation experiments of gas migration and accumulation combined with X-ray computed tomography (X-CT) and casting thin section (CTS) analyses were conducted on the 13 samples collected from Shanxi and Lower Shihezi formations in the Daniudi gas field. The aims of this paper were as follows: (1) clarifying the gas flow regimes in migration and gas accumulation patterns in the tight sandstone reservoirs, (2) characterizing nano-micrometer scale pore structure of the tight sandstone reservoirs, (3) revealing the intrinsic microscopic controlling factors for gas flow and their impacts on gas migration and accumulation. </p>
</text>
