<text id="autogum_bio_doc031" title="Ingo Ruczinski" shortTile="ingo-ruczinski" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2019-02-04" dateModified="2019-04-23" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ingo_Ruczinski" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ingo Ruczinski</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ingo Ruczinski</hi> is a Polish professor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Biostatistics">biostatistics</ref> at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johns_Hopkins_Bloomberg_School_of_Public_Health">Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health</ref>.</p>
<head>Early life and career</head>
<p>Ingo Ruczinski had obtained an M.A. in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mathematics">mathematics</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Statistics">statistics</ref> at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_at_Albany,_SUNY">University at Albany, SUNY</ref> in 1994. In 1995 he traveled to Germany where he attended the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Würzburg">University of Würzburg</ref> where he got another M.A. degree, this time in mathematics and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer_science">computer science</ref>. After the completion of M.A., he returned to the United States where he attended the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Washington">University of Washington</ref> from which he graduated with Ph.D. in statistics in 2000 at which he also worked as a teaching assistant at its Department of Statistics (until 1996), a consultant at the Department of Statistics (1998-1999) and a research assistant at the Department of Biochemistry (1996-2000).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cv-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In between those positions, Ingo also was a research assistant at the Public Health Sciences of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fred_Hutchinson_Cancer_Research_Center">Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</ref> from 1998 to 2000 and then served as its research associate till 2001. Upon graduating from the University of Washington, Ingo Ruczinski had became a postdoctoral fellow at the Department of Biochemistry of his alma mater and after half a year of doing it was appointed as an assistant professor at the Department of Biostatistics of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johns_Hopkins_University">Johns Hopkins University</ref> at which he served till 2007. A year prior to it, he was a member of the Johns Hopkins Institute for Multiscale Modeling of Biological Interactions but in 2008 quit his membership because he was appointed as an associate professor at the Department of Biostatistics of JHU in 2007. He also was a visiting professor at the Department of Chemistry at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_California,_Santa_Barbara">University of California, Santa Barbara</ref> between 2003 and 2008 and held the same position at the Centre National de Genotypage in Paris-Evry for one year in 2005. Since 2014, Ingo Ruczinski works as a preceptor at the Johns Hopkins Institute of Genetic Medicine and as a professor at the Department of Biostatistics of the Johns Hopkins University and is also an associate Chair at the Department of Biostatistics of JHU since 2018.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cv-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Chairman</head>
<p>As a Chairman, Ingo Ruczinski had been a Session Chair for numerous organizations, including: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Society_of_Human_Genetics">American Society of Human Genetics</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World_Health_Summit">World Health Summit</ref>, International Biometric Conference, Conference on Statistical Methods for Very Large Data Sets, Annual Conference of the International Society for Clininal Biostatistics, Workshop on Statistical and Computational Challenges in Genomics, Symposium on Advances in Genomics, Epidemiology and Statistics. He also was a Session Organizer of the 2006 and 2007 Eastern North Atlantic Region Meetings, the 2002, 2005 and 2006 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joint_Statistical_Meetings">Joint Statistical Meetings</ref>, the International Biometric Conference in 2010 and the Johns Hopkins Biostatistics Centennial Symposium in 2017, which was dedicated to the opening of the Department of the Biostatistics at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johns_Hopkins_University">Johns Hopkins University</ref> in 1877.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cv-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Besides those positions, Ingo Ruczinski is also known for being a Program Chair of the Section on Risk Analysis at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Statistical_Association">American Statistical Association</ref> and had served on a Program Committee of the Joint Statistical Meetings, the Eastern North Atlantic Region, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/European_Conference_on_Computational_Biology">European Conference on Computational Biology</ref>. In 2014 and 2015 he was an organizer and co-organizer of the honor symposiums for Alan Ross and Tom Louis.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cv-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Editorial</head>
<p>Ingo Ruczinski was an associate editor of the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Biometrics_(journal)">Biometrics</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic">BioMed Central Bioinformatics</hi>, and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Biometrical_Journal">Biometrical Journal</ref></hi>s and was serving on an editorial board of the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cancer_Prevention_Research">Cancer Prevention Research</ref></hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cv-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Reviewing</head>
<p>Ingo Ruczinski had also served on numerous reviewing panels, including: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eunice_Kennedy_Shriver_National_Institute_of_Child_Health_and_Human_Development">Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development</ref>, the Special Emphasis Panel of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Cancer_Institute">National Cancer Institute</ref>, Science Unbound Foundation, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Institute_of_Dental_and_Craniofacial_Research">National Institute of Dental and Craniofacial Research</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louisiana_Board_of_Regents">Louisiana Board of Regents</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genome_Canada">Genome Canada</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canadian_Institutes_of_Health_Research">Canadian Institutes of Health Research</ref> as well as being a thesis reader at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yale_School_of_Public_Health">Yale School of Public Health</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cv-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Awards and honors</head>
<p>In 2016 Ingo Ruczinski had became an elected fellow of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Statistical_Association">American Statistical Association</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
</text>
