<text id="autogum_academic_doc114" title="Evaluation of the Criteria for Designating Maintenance Districts in Low-Rise Residential Areas: Urban Renewal Projects in Seoul" shortTile="evaluation-criteria" author="Woongkyoo Bae, UnHyo Kim, Jeongwoo Lee" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5876/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Literature Review</head><head> 2.1. Concepts and Indicators of Residential Environment Quality</head>
<p>
The value of the residential environment refers to the value of the living environment, including the economic, social, and psychological environment, which extends from the daily life of the family unit to that of the entire human settlement. The residential environment refers to the built surroundings of dwelling units that provide the setting for human activities, and it encompasses a range of built environments, from immediate neighbors to large-scale civic environments.  </p>

<p>To develop a REMI based on the global criterion to evaluate the value of the residential environment, we reviewed relevant international standards based on the concept of sustainable development in terms of environmental, social, and economic aspects. The World Health Organization (WHO), Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD), United Nations Human Settlements Programme (UN-Habitat), and Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport and Tourism (MLIT) of Japan, among other international organizations, have implemented many measures to improve urban living conditions. </p>

<p>The WHO drafted guidelines for the basic living requirements of human beings by identifying four dimensions of the residential environment: Safety, health, convenience, and amenity. Further, the WHO suggested that these dimensions are important to the promotion of public hygiene and health. The OECD broadened the concept of quality of life by considering the residential environment’s social impact. Apart from emphasizing quantifiable physical dimensions, the OECD stressed the importance of subjective elements such as “social network support” and “life-satisfaction” in assessing the quality of life and, therefore, included indicators such as happiness, health, social connections, civic engagement and governance, and subjective well-being. Further, UN-Habitat presented urban indicators to monitor urban issues and the progress of individual cities in improving the living conditions of low-income populations. The indicators measure poverty eradication, economic development, diversity, and urban governance in cities as sources of the development problems faced by these cities in terms of economic and social conditions. Similarly, the United Kingdom’s Index of Multiple Deprivation is a governmental assessment tool that monitors the housing environment using indicators related to deprivation levels in terms of income, employment, education, skills, health, and living environment, as well as barriers to the accessibility to housing and services. </p>

<p>Whereas the aforementioned international indicators emphasize basic quality of life and the eradication of poverty at the national or city level, some international organizations indicate that macro-economic indices do not adequately reflect individuals’ quality of life; further, they emphasize neighborhood-level sustainability as an evaluation factor for the judgment criteria of the residential environment. For instance, the United States’ Vital Signs introduced an index focusing on not only housing development but also community activities. Similarly, the Japanese MLIT added the indicators of safety, convenience, comfort, and sustainability to the neighborhood environmental index, which typically assesses microeconomic impacts, with particular emphasis on increasing the community’s sustainability and reducing the load on the environment. The MLIT’s early “housing construction five-year program”, which was based on the mass housing supply plan, focused on improving the residential infrastructure and physical maintenance by considering the indicators of housing quality, including the number of houses available for rent, number of housing units, and spatial size of a house. Over the years, the MLIT has evolved to include qualitative indices of residential stability, such as a living environment level that reflects the different needs and lifestyles of residents. </p>

<p>Overall, these indicators, which were developed by international organizations, are globally applicable, and they focus on residential welfare to maintain public health and on physical and non-physical neighborhood and housing conditions. The indicators are strongly related to the four concepts of the residential environment: (1) The safety of the residential environment, (2) convenience of the residential service, (3) comfort of living, and (4) sense of community (Table 2). Most discussions of the residential environment highlight safety (such as safety from natural disasters and criminal activities) not only as one of the most important aspects of residential satisfaction, but also as a particularly crucial aspect of policies for the management of healthy built environments. Further, greater convenience implies improvements in the accessibility of basic facilities necessary for living or the satisfaction of people’s minimum economic needs, whereas comfort refers to the provision of aesthetic and leisure quality beyond minimum living conditions. The sense of community is a social value that brings together the members of a social system. The higher the sense of community, the stronger the tendency of people to settle in one place. </p>
</text>
