<text id="autogum_voyage_doc98" title="Switzerland" shortTile="switzerland" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=34835" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Switzerland</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://www.myswitzerland.com">Switzerland</ref></hi> (<ref target="German%20phrasebook">German</ref>: <hi rend="italic">Schweiz</hi>, <ref target="French%20phrasebook">French</ref>: <hi rend="italic">Suisse</hi>, <ref target="Italian%20phrasebook">Italian</ref>: <hi rend="italic">Svizzera</hi>, Romansch: <hi rend="italic">Svizra</hi>), officially the <hi rend="bold">Swiss Confederation</hi> (Latin: <hi rend="italic">Confoederatio Helvetica</hi>, hence the abbreviation "CH") is a landlocked country in <ref target="Central%20Europe">Central Europe</ref>. It has borders with <ref target="France">France</ref> to the west, <ref target="Italy">Italy</ref> to the south, <ref target="Austria">Austria</ref> and <ref target="Liechtenstein">Liechtenstein</ref> to the east and <ref target="Germany">Germany</ref> to the north.</p>

<p>Switzerland is known for its mountains (<ref target="Alps">Alps</ref> in the south, <ref target="Jura">Jura</ref> in the northwest) but it also has a central plateau of rolling hills, plains, and large lakes. The highest point is Dufourspitze at 4,634 m (15,203 ft) while <ref target="Lake%20Maggiore">Lake Maggiore</ref> is only 195 m (636 ft) above sea level, and the temperate climate varies greatly with altitude.</p>

<p>Switzerland is intrinsically more culturally diverse than perhaps any other European country. It has four national languages which have historically been dominant in various regions, or <hi rend="italic">cantons</hi>. German, French and Italian are spoken in the regions bordering the respective country, and Romansch - a language of Swiss origin - spoken in the mountainous area of <ref target="Graub%C3%BCnden">Graubünden</ref>. Switzerland also has one of the proportionally largest expat/immigrant populations - literally every fourth resident (25.1% as of 2018) of the almost 8.5 million inhabitants is a foreign national - consisting of almost all of the world's nationalities and ethnic groups. Renowned for tolerance, neutrality and direct democracy, as well as almost-legendary affluence, Switzerland has one of the highest standards of living in the world - and prices to match.</p>

<p>Switzerland can be a glorious whirlwind trip whether you've packed your hiking boots, snowboard, or just a good book and a pair of sunglasses.</p>

<head>Regions</head>
<p>Politically, Switzerland is divided into 26 <hi rend="bold">cantons</hi>, but the traveler will find the following regions more useful:</p>

<p>The <ref target="Swiss%20Alps">Swiss Alps</ref> stretch through the regions of the eastern part of <ref target="Lake%20Geneva">Lake Geneva</ref>, <ref target="Valais">Valais</ref>, <ref target="Bernese%20Highlands">Bernese Highlands</ref>, the southern part of <ref target="Central%20Switzerland">Central Switzerland</ref>, almost the entirety of <ref target="Ticino">Ticino</ref> except for the most southern part, the southern part of <ref target="Northeastern%20Switzerland">Northeastern Switzerland</ref>, and <ref target="Graub%C3%BCnden">Graubünden</ref>.</p>

<head>Cities</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Bern</hi>) — as close as this highly developed nation gets to having a capital with an amazingly well preserved old-town, with arcades along almost every street; great restaurants and bars abound</item>
<item> — the traveller's gateway to the German Rhineland and Black Forest and French Alsace, with an exceptional medieval centre, on the orthogonal bend of the river Rhine arriving from the east and leaving towards the north</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Genève</hi>) — this centre of arts and culture is an international city home to around 200 governmental and non-governmental organisations, birth place of the World-Wide-Web at CERN and the Red Cross organisation (ICRC)</item>
<item> — the outdoor and action sports capital of Switzerland; anything from skydiving, bungee jumping, hiking, white-water rafting, to canyoning</item>
<item> — scenery, dining, dancing, boating and the Swiss wine-country are the draws</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Luzern</hi>) — main city of the central region with direct water links to all of the sites of early Swiss history</item>
<item> — a gorgeous old-town, a pretty lake; much <hi rend="italic">Italianatà</hi> combined with Swiss seriousness</item>
<item> — main city of north-eastern Switzerland, renowned for its <hi rend="italic">Abbey of St. Gall</hi>, a UNESCO World Heritage Site, it also functions as the gate to the very special <hi rend="italic"><ref target="Appenzell">Appenzell</ref></hi> region.</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Zürich</hi>) — Switzerland's largest city on a lake as well and a major centre of banking and culture, numerous restaurants and with a thriving nightlife</item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> — large ski resort where the annual meeting of the World Economic Forum takes place</item>
<item> — the classic resort at the foot of the Eiger</item>
<item> — A region of terraced vineyards on the shore of Lake Geneva and a UNESCO cultural heritage site.</item>
<item> — glitzy ski resort in the <ref target="Engadine">Engadine</ref> valley in south-eastern Switzerland</item>
<item> — A protected area around the largest glaciated area in the Alps. This high alpine park offers stunning views and is also a UNESCO natural heritage site.</item>
<item> — famous mountain resort at the base of the mighty Matterhorn</item>
</list>


<head>History</head>
<p>Switzerland has a history reaching far back into the <ref target="Roman%20Empire">Roman Empire</ref> times, when the tribes inhabiting it were called "Helvetians" by Roman sources - hence the modern-day Latin name "Confoederatio Helvetica", used internally wherever it is not advisable to give preference to any of the country's official languages. You can find many references to "Helvetia" or "Helvetic" in the naming of Swiss organisations and companies, and the International Registration Letter and Swiss top-level Internet domain are CH and .ch, respectively. A quarrel between Caesar and the Helvetians is one of the first things to be described in detail in Julius Caesar's <hi rend="italic">de bello gallico</hi> which is still read by Latin students all over the world.</p>

<p>The Helvetians and their successors have adopted various forms of democracy and devolution to govern their lands, rather than feudalism or autocracy prevalent in the rest of Europe, thus conserving and in a sense modernising Germanic traditions otherwise only found in the Nordic countries. Functioning as a (initially very loose) confederation for centuries, the country has grown to become one of the most diverse in Europe, while also vividly celebrating their national and local identity and the direct democracy employed to make a wide range of civic decisions.</p>

<p>Switzerland's independence and neutrality have long been honored by the major European powers and Switzerland has not been involved in any international war since <ref target="Napoleonic%20Wars">Napoleonic times</ref> and has been at peace internally since the 1850s. The political and economic integration of Europe over the past half century, as well as Switzerland's role in many UN and international organizations has strengthened Switzerland's ties with its neighbours. However, the country did not officially become a UN member until 2002 and maintains a neutral position in foreign relations. Unlike all of its neighbours (bar <ref target="Liechtenstein">Liechtenstein</ref>), Switzerland is not a member of the <ref target="European%20Union">European Union</ref>.</p>

<head>Climate</head>

<p>The <ref target="https://www.meteoswiss.admin.ch/home/climate/past/climate-normals.html">Swiss climate</ref> is temperate, but varies significantly with altitude in the Alps – in average about 6.5° C every 1000m – and among <ref target="https://www.meteoswiss.admin.ch/home/climate/past/climate-of-switzerland.html">the four major climatic regions</ref>: the northeastern and western parts of the Central Plateau, southern Switzerland, and within the Alps.</p>

<p>There are four clearly defined seasons which bring changes mainly in temperature and time of sunshine: rainy or snowy cold winters with short days from December till February, snow-melting and flower-blowing springs from March till May, moderately warm to sometimes hot, but also occasionally quite rainy summers with long days from June till August, and colourful and often quite dry, sometimes still astonishingly warm, but sometimes also already quite cold and foggy Autumns from September till November with days getting shorter and shorter. And <ref target="https://www.meteoswiss.admin.ch/home/climate/present-day/monthly-and-annual-maps.html">each season or month can be quite different year by year</ref>.</p>

<p>Switzerland has cold, on the low Central Plateau often cloudy, rainy or snowy winters, and moderate to warm summers with very changeable weather which can change quite quickly, especially on hot summer days and in the mountains; in extreme cases within minutes. In some years you can experience cloudy, rainy, humid summer days, however on other days or even the next year very sunny, or sometimes even hot summer days with only occasional showers. Approximately every third day throughout the entire year is a rainy day with either a short shower, or constantly drizzling rain throughout the whole day. And a rainy period can endure from less than one hour to three weeks whatever season. <ref target="https://www.meteoswiss.admin.ch/home.html%3Ftab%3Doverview%26amp%3Bdate%3D6days">Weather forecasts</ref> for more than six days ahead are scientifically fundamentally unreliable.</p>

<p>The most convenient and therefore the most visited months are from late May till early October with a particular, often overcrowded high from July to August. You can enjoy its fabulous landscapes either on a hike, a cruise, a train, or a bike ride. You will be able to discover the High Alps, its blacknose sheep, and glaciers. The summer season allows to combine the supposed incompatible, namely beach holidays on the lakes and some, though limited summer skiing. In winter, tourists and locals extensively enjoy many kinds of winter sport, and an enchanting Christmas atmosphere before, and a funny carneval season after the end of the year.</p>
</text>
