<text id="autogum_academic_doc607" title="High-Intensity Interval Circuit Training Versus Moderate-Intensity Continuous Training on Functional Ability and Body Mass Index in Middle-Aged and Older Women: A Randomized Controlled Trial" shortTile="highintensity-interval" author="Ismael Ballesta-García, Ignacio Martínez-González-Moro, Jacobo  Á. Rubio-Arias, María Carrasco-Poyatos" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4205/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The world population aged over 65 years has increased considerably in recent years. Due to hormonal changes (i.e., menopause), the effect of ageing in women is resulting in chronic diseases, functional dependence, the prevalence of sarcopenia and frailty and the risk of falls and injuries, increasing the risk of hospitalization and mortality. This generates significant economic cost for health systems to prevent or treat age-related chronic diseases and dependency situations. </p>

<p>Recently, physical exercise has become relevant for the maintenance of health and functional ability in middle-aged and older women, functional ability being understood as the capacity to carry out activities of daily living. This has been evidenced in recent studies indicating that maintaining high levels of strength, balance, gait and cardiorespiratory fitness are the main objectives for the optimal achievement of the basic and instrumental daily living activities for middle-aged and older women, as well as to delay the onset of sarcopenia and frailty. Similarly, physical exercise also helps maintain healthy body mass index (BMI) values, which is an important factor in their relationship to chronic diseases that cause dependence in older women populations. </p>

<p>For these reasons, governments and the healthcare system are implementing physical exercise programmes for middle-aged and older people at day centres. As the training sessions are usually in groups, circuit training is one of the most common types of training. Circuit training consists of performing a series of exercises for all muscle groups, allowing strength and cardiorespiratory fitness to be influenced simultaneously. Body weight-based circuit training can be considered a functional training method because they are based on the imitation of daily living activities in which only body weight is used (i.e., body weight squats and lunges). </p>

<p>Some research involving the elderly has shown that moderate-intensity circuit training (MICT) has positive effects on strength, cardiorespiratory fitness, balance, body composition and quality of life. Furthermore, during recent years a new type of training called high-intensity interval training (HIIT) has been included as an alternative method of training in healthy people and as part of the treatment of pathologies, especially in cardiac rehabilitation programmes. HIIT consists of intermittent short high-intensity work periods (85–100% of maximal oxygen uptake) and relative rest periods. Some research has shown strong evidence that HIIT is an effective method for improving maximal oxygen uptake, strength, cardiorespiratory fitness, gait and body composition in older people with pathologies. In fact, there is a trend that indicates that health indices and markers are more favourable after HIIT than after MICT. Otherwise, this is still not clear regarding other functional parameters. </p>

<p>However, although the benefits of HIIT are known, there is little evidence on including HIIT methodology in circuit training (HIICT) in healthy middle-aged and older women. In this sense, HIICT is an alternative form of training for improving physical condition and performance in daily living activities due to integrated multiplanar-based movements (squatting, pulling, etc.) performed at maximal speed, which makes it very functional and with high transfer in older adults. </p>

<p>For these reasons, the main objective of the present study was to determine what type of training (HIICT or MICT) induces greater adaptations in the functional ability and BMI of middle-aged and older women. Based on the previous research, our hypothesis was that HIICT would significantly improve the strength, gait, cardiorespiratory fitness, static and dynamic balance and BMI in middle-aged and older women. In addition, it was hypothesized that HIICT would induce greater adaptations in these variables than MICT. </p>
</text>
