<text id="autogum_voyage_doc59" title="Rotterdam-The Hague Metropolitan Region" shortTile="rotterdam-hague-metropolitan" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=127182" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Rotterdam-The Hague Metropolitan Region</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://mrdh.nl/project/european-projects">Rotterdam-The Hague Metropolitan Region</ref></hi> (<hi rend="italic">Metropoolregio Rotterdam Den Haag</hi> or <hi rend="bold">MRDH</hi> in <ref target="Dutch%20phrasebook">Dutch</ref>) is the large metropolitan area around the cities <ref target="Rotterdam">Rotterdam</ref> and <ref target="The%20Hague">The Hague</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Den Haag</hi> in Dutch). It is also a big part of the Southern <ref target="Western%20Netherlands">Randstad</ref> (with other big cities like <ref target="Amsterdam">Amsterdam</ref> and <ref target="Utrecht">Utrecht</ref>) </p>

<p>MRDH was first recognised officially on January 1, 2015, with the merging of the areas <hi rend="bold">Haaglanden</hi> (Greater Hague) and <hi rend="bold">Stadsregio Rotterdam</hi> (Rotterdam Urban Area, more common name <hi rend="bold">Rijnmond</hi>, literally "Rhine Estuary")</p>

<p>This is where all the big waterways flow into the North Sea, which is also the location of one of the biggest sea ports of the world. The Hague is the seat of the Dutch parliament and government, and the future residence of King Willem-Alexander (the Royal Family lives also in the MRDH, but in <ref target="Wassenaar">Wassenaar</ref>). Besides Rotterdam and The Hague, <ref target="Delft">Delft</ref> is a very popular city for tourists. Tourist can discover lots of other interesting places as it comes to culture, nature and recreation. Take the beaches and the dunes which are worthwhile a visit all the year round or discover the beauty of the typical Holland town <ref target="Schiedam">Schiedam</ref>. </p>

<head>Municipalities</head>



<list type="unordered">
<item> — a large economic center with modern architecture. The sea port with impressive large areas like Europoort and the Maasvlakte also belong to Rotterdam.</item>
<item> — Binnenhof, palaces, embassies and several international institutions. Also <ref target="Scheveningen">Scheveningen</ref>, the largest beach resort of the country, forms part of The Hague</item>
<item> </item>
<item> — Delftware pottery and a historic town center</item>
<item> – Seaport and beach resort by the North Sea (part of Rotterdam)</item>
<item> - typical municipality for the region with two little historic centers</item>
<item> </item>
<item> - an open and wide rural area with picturesque villages in between The Hague, Delft, Rotterdam and Europoort</item>
<item> — a rapidly urbanized town near The Hague</item>
<item> — the historic town famous for its jenever and the tallest historic windmills in the world</item>
<item> </item>
<item> — dunes along the sea, home of the rich and the famous including the official residence of the Dutch royal family</item>
<item> — mostly a rural area filled with greenhouses</item>
<item> — Snow World, Dutch Water Dreams, Mormon Temple; a planned city with lots of modern architecture</item>
</list>


<head>By plane</head>
<ref target="Rotterdam%20The%20Hague%20Airport"><hi rend="bold">Rotterdam The Hague Airport</hi></ref> ( RTM ) is the only airport in the region. As <ref target="Amsterdam%20Airport%20Schiphol"><hi rend="bold">Amsterdam Airport Schiphol</hi></ref> which is about north of The Hague receive many more flights, it is the vastly preferable option for many conceivable itineraries even if you final destination is inside this region.

<p><hi rend="bold">From Amsterdam and Schiphol</hi> there are frequent train services to The Hague, Delft and Rotterdam as well as to a few destinations in between like Schiedam. Most of these services are <hi rend="bold">Intercity</hi> trains. <hi rend="italic">Railway station Den Haag Centraal</hi> <hi rend="italic">(the Hague)</hi> is also connected by so called <hi rend="bold">Sprinters,</hi> more little trains who call at every station (and so are slower). Fastest to Rotterdam <hi rend="italic">(Central Station)</hi> is <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.ns.nl/reisinformatie/bijzondere-trajecten/intercity-direct.html">Intercity Direct</ref></hi> or <ref target="https://www.thalys.com/nl/en/"><hi rend="bold">Thalys</hi></ref>. Intercity Direct is more attractive as in general this train is cheaper and travelers do not have to make a reservation. A supplement is required for the line from Schiphol to Rotterdam. </p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Rotterdam The Hague Airport</hi> is connected by a bus service to Rotterdam city which also forms a link to the Rotterdam-Den Haag metro line E. </p>
<head>By train</head>
<p>MRDH has a fast connection with <ref target="Paris"><hi rend="bold">Paris</hi></ref><hi rend="bold">, <ref target="Lille">Lille</ref>, <ref target="Brussels">Brussels</ref></hi> and <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Antwerp">Antwerp</ref></hi> by high-speed train <hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://www.thalys.com/nl/en/">Thalys</ref></hi> which calls at <hi rend="italic">Rotterdam Centraal</hi>. </p>

<p>A slower but often much cheaper option from Antwerp and Brussels is the so called <hi rend="italic">Intercity Brussels,</hi> see <ref target="https://www.b-europe.com/EN/Trains/InterCity"><hi rend="bold">NMBS</hi></ref>, which also stops at <ref target="Mechelen">Mechelen</ref>. This train calls at Rotterdam and The Hague railway station <hi rend="italic">Hollands Spoor.</hi></p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Coming from Germany</hi> travelers always have to make an exchange in the Netherlands. </p>

<p>Traveling on the German high-speed train <ref target="https://www.bahn.com/en/view/trains/long-distance/ice-ice-sprinter.shtml%3Fdbkanal_007%3DL04_S02_D002_KIN0059_FLYOUT-ZUGFLOTTE-ICE_LZ01">ICE</ref> from <ref target="Cologne">Cologne</ref>, <ref target="D%C3%BCsseldorf">Düsseldorf</ref> and <ref target="Oberhausen">Oberhausen</ref>, the exchange will be in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="Utrecht">Utrecht</ref> Centraal</hi> station, and comming from direction <ref target="Berlin">Berlin</ref>, <ref target="Hanover">Hanover</ref>, <ref target="Osnabr%C3%BCck">Osnabrück</ref> (with the <ref target="https://www.bahn.com/en/view/trains/long-distance/intercity-eurocity.shtml%3Fdbkanal_007%3DL04_S02_D002_KIN0059_FLYOUT-ZUGFLOTTE-IC_LZ01">DB-intercity</ref>) it is advisible to exhange in station <ref target="Amersfoort">Amersfoort</ref>. From Utrecht and Amersfoort Intercity-trains depart to The Hague <hi rend="italic">(Centraal)</hi> and to Rotterdam. </p>

<p>Coming from any other city in The Netherlands there are frequent intercity-services to The Hague and Rotterdam (many times direct or with one fast exchange), see for more information the general planner for all kinds of public transport in the Netherlands <ref target="https://9292.nl/en">9292</ref></p>

<head>By ferry boat</head>
<p>Coming from the <ref target="United%20Kingdom">UK</ref> the area is also reachable by several ferry-lines. </p>

<p>Direct connections right to the MRDH are: </p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="http://www.hull-rotterdam.com/uk/"><hi rend="bold">P&amp;O Ferries</hi></ref> - line <ref target="Kingston%20upon%20Hull">Kingston upon Hull</ref> - Rotterdam Europoort</item>
<item> <ref target="https://www.stenaline.nl/en-GB-nl/crossings/hook-of-holland-harwich"><hi rend="bold">Stena Line</hi></ref> - <ref target="Harwich%20%28England%29">Harwich</ref> - Hook of Holland</item>
</list>


<head>By bicycle</head>
<p>Tourists who stay a few days or more time in the area, might like to discover all of the cities, towns and landscapes by (renting a) bicycle. As a part of the Netherlands, MRDH offers a whole infrastructure especially for cyclists.</p>

<p>Especially in city centers, it is strongly advisable to lock your bike, or go to a guarded bicycle parking stations. </p>

<head>Guarded bicycle parking stations</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Many intercity train stations have thier own bicycle parking station. Many time the service is not free.</item>
<item> In and around The Hague (with Scheveningen), Delft and Zoetermeer <ref target="http://www.biesieklette.nl/openbarestallingen/"><hi rend="bold">Biesieklette</hi></ref> offers 55 guarded Bicycle parking station. Parking your bicycle for just a few hours up to one full day is free.</item>
<item> Rotterdam municipality has also <ref target="https://www.rotterdam.nl/zoeken/%3F__url%3D%252Fzoeken%252F%26amp%3Bquery%3Dfietsenstalling">some locations</ref>.</item>
</list>


<p><hi rend="bold">Rent a bike</hi></p>

<p>Bikes can be rented by several different private compagnies. Holland-Cycling.com provides a list of adresses in <ref target="http://www.holland-cycling.com/rotterdam/getting-around-rotterdam/bicycle-rental-in-rotterdam">Rotterdam</ref> and <ref target="http://www.holland-cycling.com/the-hague/getting-around-the-hague/bicycle-rental-the-hague">The Hague</ref>. Another list of bicycle-renting in Rotterdam you will find at <ref target="https://www.rotterdam.nl/vrije-tijd/fiets-huren/">Rotterdam.nl</ref>. Rotterdam also joins <ref target="https://www.o.bike/">oBike</ref> a new kind of bicycle-sharing system (see also <ref target="https://en.rotterdam.info/locations/obike/">city tourist information</ref>). </p>

<p>If you have an <ref target="https://www.ov-chipkaart.nl/home.htm%23/">OV-chipkaart</ref> (see also under <hi rend="italic">"By public transport"</hi>) bicycles can be rented at many train and metro stations and other central locations by the <ref target="http://www.ns.nl/en/door-to-door/ov-fiets">OV-fiets system</ref>. </p>
</text>
