<text id="autogum_fiction_doc260" title="An Outcast of the Islands" shortTile="outcastislands" author="Conrad, Joseph" type="fiction" dateCollected="2019-10-22" sourceURL="http://gutenberg.readingroo.ms/6/3/638/638-0.txt">
<head>CHAPTER TWO</head>

<p>For the next half-hour Almayer, who wanted to give Joanna plenty of time, stumbled amongst the lumber in distant parts of his enclosure, sneaked along the fences; or held his breath, flattened against grass walls behind various outhouses: all this to escape Ali’s inconveniently zealous search for his master. He heard him talk with the head watchman--sometimes quite close to him in the darkness--then moving off, coming back, wondering, and, as the time passed, growing uneasy.</p>

<p>“He did not fall into the river?--say, thou blind watcher!” Ali was growling in a bullying tone, to the other man. “He told me to fetch Mahmat, and when I came back swiftly I found him not in the house. There is that Sirani woman there, so that Mahmat cannot steal anything, but it is in my mind, the night will be half gone before I rest.”</p>

<p>He shouted--</p>

<p>“Master! O master! O mast . . .”</p>

<p>“What are you making that noise for?” said Almayer, with severity, stepping out close to them.</p>

<p>The two Malays leaped away from each other in their surprise.</p>

<p>“You may go. I don’t want you any more tonight, Ali,” went on Almayer. “Is Mahmat there?”</p>

<p>“Unless the ill-behaved savage got tired of waiting. Those men know not politeness. They should not be spoken to by white men,” said Ali, resentfully.</p>

<p>Almayer went towards the house, leaving his servants to wonder where he had sprung from so unexpectedly. The watchman hinted obscurely at powers of invisibility possessed by the master, who often at night . . . Ali interrupted him with great scorn. Not every white man has the power. Now, the Rajah Laut could make himself invisible. Also, he could be in two places at once, as everybody knew; except he--the useless watchman--who knew no more about white men than a wild pig! Ya-wa!</p>

<p>And Ali strolled towards his hut, yawning loudly.</p>

<p>As Almayer ascended the steps he heard the noise of a door flung to, and when he entered the verandah he saw only Mahmat there, close to the doorway of the passage. Mahmat seemed to be caught in the very act of slinking away, and Almayer noticed that with satisfaction. Seeing the white man, the Malay gave up his attempt and leaned against the wall. He was a short, thick, broad-shouldered man with very dark skin and a wide, stained, bright-red mouth that uncovered, when he spoke, a close row of black and glistening teeth. His eyes were big, prominent, dreamy and restless. He said sulkily, looking all over the place from under his eyebrows--</p>

<p>“White Tuan, you are great and strong--and I a poor man. Tell me what is your will, and let me go in the name of God. It is late.”</p>

<p>Almayer examined the man thoughtfully. How could he find out whether . . . He had it! Lately he had employed that man and his two brothers as extra boatmen to carry stores, provisions, and new axes to a camp of rattan cutters some distance up the river. A three days’ expedition. He would test him now in that way. He said negligently--</p>

<p>“I want you to start at once for the camp, with surat for the Kavitan. One dollar a day.”</p>

<p>The man appeared plunged in dull hesitation, but Almayer, who knew his Malays, felt pretty sure from his aspect that nothing would induce the fellow to go. He urged--</p>

<p>“It is important--and if you are swift I shall give two dollars for the last day.”</p>

<p>“No, Tuan. We do not go,” said the man, in a hoarse whisper.</p>

<p>“Why?”</p>

<p>“We start on another journey.”</p>

<p>“Where?”</p>

<p>“To a place we know of,” said Mahmat, a little louder, in a stubborn manner, and looking at the floor.</p>

<p>Almayer experienced a feeling of immense joy. He said, with affected annoyance--</p>

<p>“You men live in my house and it is as if it were your own. I may want my house soon.”</p>

<p>Mahmat looked up.</p>

<p>“We are men of the sea and care not for a roof when we have a canoe that will hold three, and a paddle apiece. The sea is our house. Peace be with you, Tuan.”</p>

<p>He turned and went away rapidly, and Almayer heard him directly afterwards in the courtyard calling to the watchman to open the gate. Mahmat passed through the gate in silence, but before the bar had been put up behind him he had made up his mind that if the white man ever wanted to eject him from his hut, he would burn it and also as many of the white man’s other buildings as he could safely get at. And he began to call his brothers before he was inside the dilapidated dwelling.</p>

<p>“All’s well!” muttered Almayer to himself, taking some loose Java tobacco from a drawer in the table. “Now if anything comes out I am clear. I asked the man to go up the river. I urged him. He will say so himself. Good.”</p>

<p>He began to charge the china bowl of his pipe, a pipe with a long cherry stem and a curved mouthpiece, pressing the tobacco down with his thumb and thinking: No. I sha’n’t see her again. Don’t want to. I will give her a good start, then go in chase--and send an express boat after father. Yes! that’s it.</p>
</text>
