<text id="autogum_academic_doc147" title="Interrelations between the Media and Architecture: Contribution to Sustainable Development and the Conservation of Urban Spaces" shortTile="interrelations-between" author="Juan Monserrat-Gauchi, Manuel Novo-Domínguez, Rosa Torres-Valdés" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5631/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. State of the Question</head><head> 2.1. Literature Review</head>
<p>
There is an abundance of publications on the fields of architecture, communications, sociology, art and urban planning, including numerous studies of the relationships between these fields and how interaction between them can bring about transformations and new creations. Such studies range from academic articles or essays to photography series. </p>

<p>This article constitutes an attempt to go a step further and examine media and advertising interventions as initiatives capable of vesting derelict architectural spaces with value in the interests of promoting sustainability. </p>

<p>One of the pillars of this research is our interpretation of the sociologist Lefebvre’s notion of the right to the city. Lefebvre’s work offers some fascinating insights into urban space, which he understands in terms of the future, the possible, and the alternative, based on the logic of the immediate and the tangible. </p>

<p>Another interesting contribution in this respect has been offered by the architect Tschumi, whose architectural projects are notable for the interrelation he establishes with events. Over the course of the 1970s, in both written texts and drawings, Tschumi highlighted the fact that architecture does not exist without events, actions, or activity. The first projects he developed recognized that buildings respond to and intensify the activities that occur within them, and that events creatively change and extend the structures they contain. In other words, architecture is not defined by its “formal” container but by its combinations of spaces, movements and events. Tschumi’s work has been exhibited in individual exhibitions at the Museum of Modern Art in New York City, the Venice Biennale of Architecture, the Netherlands Architecture Institute in Rotterdam, the Center Pompidou in Paris, and other museums and art galleries in the United States and Europe. </p>

<p>The imaginary dialogues or references that Lefebvre describes so precisely tie in well with the concept of New Babylon, conceived by Constant in 1956 in parallel with his participation in the Situationist International. We therefore refer here to publications on the exhibition of Constant’s work that was held at Museo Reina Sofía in 2016. </p>

<p>With the intention of bringing the ideas of these authors into the contemporary context, we also draw on short essays like <hi rend="italic">La ciudad en Movimiento</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Metrópolis Visionarias</hi>, which help us to understand the current reality of urban planning and sociology, as well as publications in scientific journals and doctoral theses, of which Pinchart-Saavedra’s study titled <hi rend="italic">Rascacielos de Tokio a Babilonia la arquitectura como propaganda</hi> stands out for its role as an anchor for our analysis. </p>

<p>Moreover, bearing in mind the objective of promoting sustainability, this study considers the current scope of the concept of sustainability, i.e., in its environmental, social, economic, and cultural dimensions. This holistic conception of sustainability based on these four pillars represents a redefinition of economic policy and regional development for the reconstruction of urban space and of the social and cultural fabric. In this sense, Hawkes (p. 11) views culture as playing an essential role in public planning, pointing out that sustainability has four objectives: environmental responsibility, represented by ecological balance; economic viability, represented by prosperity; social equity, represented by social justice, engagement, cohesion, and welfare; and cultural vitality, represented by creativity, diversity, and innovation, and also by social well-being. Indeed, art and creativity as elements of expression play an important role in the social appropriation of the concept of sustainability, through the effective production of public campaigns. </p>

<p>The vision of sustainability offered by Hakimi and Firoozabadi is interesting in terms of its way of looking forward to the generations to come: sustainable development is one of the issues that is currently given great importance and is identified by the United Nations as a key part of the 21st century agenda. Sustainable development refers to a kind of development that will meet today’s needs without reducing the ability of the future generations to meet theirs. </p>

<head> 2.2. The Meaning of Urban Space</head>
<p>
Olalquiaga suggests that “history has been replaced by geography, stories by maps, memories by scenarios” (p. 19). </p>

<p>The geo-socio-political, economic, cultural, and technological scenario of the 21st century exhibits tensions between sustainable regional development models and less sustainable models. This process is producing a new scenario of transition, in which sustainability is understood as a fundamental element in the quest for new, responsible forms of production and consumption. Moreover, the concept of sustainable development appears to be associated, on the one hand, with democratic governance with a multidisciplinary perspective, and on the other, with governance that promotes sustainability and social innovation. It also has the power to transform different types of regional vulnerabilities that are social, economic, environmental, and institutional in nature. </p>
</text>
