<text id="autogum_voyage_doc359" title="Pennsylvania" shortTile="pennsylvania" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=27228" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Pennsylvania</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.state.pa.us/">Pennsylvania</ref></hi> is a state in the eastern <ref target="United%20States">United States</ref>. It is known for its Revolutionary War-era historical sites like <ref target="Valley%20Forge">Valley Forge</ref>, its large cities like <ref target="Philadelphia">Philadelphia</ref> and <ref target="Pittsburgh">Pittsburgh</ref>, its farming regions, some occupied by the Amish, and a (once)-strong industrial history. With equally large swaths of cities and towns as fields and mountains, Pennsylvania is a rich and varied state, as well as a worthy travel destination. Pennsylvania is bordered by the states of <ref target="New%20Jersey">New Jersey</ref>, <ref target="New%20York%20%28state%29">New York</ref>, <ref target="Delaware">Delaware</ref>, <ref target="Maryland">Maryland</ref>, <ref target="West%20Virginia">West Virginia</ref>, and <ref target="Ohio">Ohio</ref>. The main cities are Philadelphia and Pittsburgh, and other smaller cities such as <ref target="Allentown">Allentown</ref>, <ref target="Erie">Erie</ref>, <ref target="Reading%20%28Pennsylvania%29">Reading</ref>, <ref target="Bethlehem%20%28Pennsylvania%29">Bethlehem</ref>, and <ref target="Scranton">Scranton</ref>.</p>

<head>Cities</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> — the state capital</item>
<item> — largest city of the <ref target="Lehigh%20Valley">Lehigh Valley</ref>, third largest city in state</item>
<item> — home to Pennsylvania's waterfront on Lake Erie, great for boating and beaches</item>
<item> — Birthplace of Hershey's chocolate, home to Hersheypark.</item>
<item> — a relatively large city right at the heart of Amish country; the birthplace of the battery-powered watch, and a good shopping destination for Amish goods</item>
<item> — "The City of Brotherly Love," with lots of history and cheesesteaks, largest city in Pennsylvania.</item>
<item> — "The Steel City," a scenic, multicultural, major city, 2nd largest in Pennsylvania.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Reading%20%28Pennsylvania%29">Reading</ref></hi> - birthplace of country/pop music artist Taylor Swift.￼</item>
<item> /<hi rend="bold"><ref target="Wilkes-Barre">Wilkes-Barre</ref></hi> — coal region towns perhaps best known for TV's <hi rend="italic">The Office</hi></item>
<item> — host to the annual Little League World Series</item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> — the site of the most famous battlefield on U.S. soil, which saw the bloodiest battle and the turning point of the Civil War</item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> <ref target="Ricketts%20Glen%20State%20Park"><hi rend="bold">Ricketts Glen State Park</hi></ref></item>
<item> </item>
<item> — the third-largest "city" in the state, but only when the Nittany Lions football team is playing</item>
</list>


<head>Understand</head>

<p>The Commonwealth of Pennsylvania is a geographically diverse state with a Great Lake on one shore and a major seaport on the other. The climate of Pennsylvania is pleasant, with cold, often snowy winters, mild to hot, humid summers, and gorgeous green springtimes, and most notably, spectacular displays of colorful autumn foliage.</p>

<p>Pennsylvania hosts a number of vital cities, from Pittsburgh to Philadelphia. The city of Philadelphia houses the Liberty Bell and Independence Hall, two major national historical landmarks. The interior of the state has a number of subcultures worth exploring, including the famous Amish countryside, a religious community.</p>

<p>Pennsylvania is also home to a diverse group of people, with ethnic enclaves of black, Hispanic, and Southeast Asian populations in its major cities.</p>

<p>Pennsylvania is also diverse in that the Eastern and Southeastern parts of the state are urban and densely populated, while much of the rest of the state is rural and/or mountainous.</p>

<head>Talk</head>

<p>Most Pennsylvanians speak American English, although pound-for-pound its variety of regional dialects and accents is richer than any other state in the Union: the Western Pennsylvania ("Pittsburghese"), Central Pennsylvania, Northeastern Pennsylvania, Southeastern Pennsylvania (centered in Pennsylvania Dutch Country and heavily influenced by that language; see below), and Philadelphia dialects are all audibly distinct from each other. People from the Appalachian Mountains speak with a distinctive accent that is similar to a a <ref target="South%20%28United%20States%20of%20America%29">Southern</ref> accent. Travellers may well notice these different speech patterns, but it's highly doubtful they'll present any communication problem for anyone with a workable level of English proficiency. Many of these accents are dying out, and younger people tend to speak with a general American accent.</p>

<p>Reading, Allentown, and Philadelphia all have sizable Spanish-speaking populations, and Philadelphia and Pittsburgh have their share of Asian, European, and other languages too. Again, this should not pose a problem for English-speaking travellers, as most of these people speak English in addition to their native language.</p>

<p>Finally, though there are now smaller clusters in other states too, Pennsylvania remains the home of the large majority of speakers of the famous Pennsylvania Dutch (<hi rend="italic">Pennsilfaanisch Deitsch</hi>) dialect of <ref target="German%20phrasebook">German</ref>. Although widescale non-Amish use of the language faded circa 1950, there are pockets of young people who are learning the language as a way to preserve their heritage.</p>

<head>By car</head>

<p>Pennsylvania is a densely populous state in a densely populous part of the country, with many roads in and out. Interstate highways lead most traffic into the state. Major national interstate highways leading to Pennsylvania include I-95 S from New England, I-95 N from the American South, and I-70 E, I-80 E &amp; I-90 E from the American West and Midwest. Specifically, clockwise from north of Harrisburg:</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> from Montreal &amp; Ottawa to Scranton &amp; Harrisburg: I-81 S.</item>
<item> from Boston to Scranton: I-90 W to I-84 W.</item>
<item> from Boston to the Lehigh Valley &amp; Harrisburg: I-84 W to I-91 S to I-95 S to I-287 W to I-78 W.</item>
<item> from Boston to Philadelphia: I-84 W to I-91 S to I-95 S.</item>
<item> from New York City to Scranton: I-80 W.</item>
<item> from New York City to the Lehigh Valley &amp; Harrisburg: I-78 W.</item>
<item> from New York City to Philadelphia: I-95 S.</item>
<item> from Baltimore to Philadelphia: I-95 N.</item>
<item> from Baltimore to Harrisburg: I-83 N.</item>
<item> from Baltimore to Pittsburgh: I-70 W.</item>
<item> from Washington, DC to Philadelphia: I-95 N.</item>
<item> from Washington, DC to Harrisburg: I-95 N to I-83 N.</item>
<item> from Washington, DC to Pittsburgh: I-270 W to I-70 W.</item>
<item> from West Virginia to Pittsburgh: I-79 N.</item>
<item> from Columbus &amp; Indianapolis to Pittsburgh &amp; Harrisburg: I-70 E.</item>
<item> from Cleveland to Pittsburgh: It's close, but complicated.</item>
<item> from Cleveland &amp; Chicago to Erie: I-90 E.</item>
<item> from Toronto &amp; Buffalo to Erie: I- 90 W.</item>
</list>


<p>Also, U.S. Routes 219, 15, and 220 (soon to be I-99) all enter the state at alternative points from both the north and south.</p>

<p>State-operated Welcome Centers and Comfort Facilities are found just inside the borders at all major crossings into Pennsylvania.</p>

<head>By train</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="Rail%20travel%20in%20the%20United%20States">Amtrak</ref></hi> offers a total of nine different passenger train lines in or across the state of Pennsylvania. A fair amount of these run between New York and Philadelphia, continuing to points south, such as Charlotte, and New Orleans. The Pennsylvanian crosses a large swath of the state during its journey from New York to Pittsburgh, and the Keystone travels from New York to Harrisburg. Pittsburgh and Philadelphia are also each connected to Chicago and Washington D.C.</p>

<p>An inexpensive and quick rail option to the Philadelphia region from New York City as well as its airports, is to take a New Jersey Transit train from Port Authority in lower Manhattan to Trenton Transportation Center in New Jersey. At Trenton, transfer onto a <ref target="http://septa.org/maps/system/index.html">SEPTA (Southeastern Pennsylvania Transit Authority)</ref> train to Center City Philadelphia.</p>
</text>
