<text id="autogum_interview_doc385" title="part6_Wikinews interviews Mark Bunker, producer of anti-Scientology website &amp;apos;XenuTV&amp;apos;" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-05" dateModified="2016-03-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Mark_Bunker%2C_producer_of_anti-Scientology_website_%27XenuTV%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">toresbe</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">By sheer virtue of numbers, we have become very hard to harass, to the point of the personal risk to ourselves being almost negligible. There have been others before us with far more courage who have spoken up against far greater odds. What do you think the effect of our actions have been on these "pioneers"? (yourself included) Do you personally feel that we anons have revitalized the more "serious" efforts of those in the past who have come out with full names - and have probably gotten into problems over this? And do you believe it serves to ease the process for those Scientologists who were already considering leaving?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: To deny Hubbard's connection to OTO is impossible but it also one of the most bizarre aspects of his life and many people would think it impossible and over the top criticism.  That was one of the many flaws of the movie, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Profit">The Profit</ref></hi>. Ultimately Anonymous' rise will be beneficial. It can cause people inside to rethink their beliefs and draw media attention to Scientology's fraud and abuse. All very good. The way they rose however is a double edge sword because when I do interviews, I have to respond to white powder mailings and bomb threats. The anonymous nature and early attacks on Scientology make it easier for Scientology to blame these more serious charges on the group. People in the vast unwashed public aren't looking into it very deep and can believe Scientology's distortions. There is also the fear that we old timers can be lumped in with those abuses. I'm sure Scientology is going to accuse me of being a  leader of terrorists. That is a huge risk I run, but in helping reshape Anonymous to a peaceful league group, I believe I am doing a great service to Scientology. Not that they'll thank me. Especially if their tax exempt status is revoked.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">jennam</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">I was just wondering if you were aware of the many other abuses of other religions such as The Watchtower organization of Jehovah's Witnesses.. They do things strikingly similar to Scientology with regards to killing and abusing members and disconnection policies - now, I'm in no way in favor of the management of Scientology but it does look a little blind to me when these other so-called religions get off scot-free. Have you heard of any such allegations before? My concern is that while a step forward is good against one religion, there are others out there just biding by without no real exposure essentially letting them get away with their abuses. I was also wondering if you knew if The Profit would ever be released for viewing?</hi></p>
</text>
