<text id="autogum_interview_doc056" title="part1_Wikinews interviews painter Pricasso on his art and freedom of expression" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-10-10" dateModified="2019-08-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_painter_Pricasso_on_his_art_and_freedom_of_expression" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> How long can you paint with your penis at one time before it gets too tiring?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Pricasso</hi>: At most Sexpo's and Adult Expos I paint for 13 hours a day in half slots so I paint 20 plus paintings a day. When I am painting I have to concentrate hard and go into a meditative state; I don't notice much going on around me until I have finished.</p>
<figure><caption>Example of Pricasso applying paint before creating a piece of artwork. Image: <ref target="http://www.pricasso.com/">Pricasso</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Other than your penis, what other parts of your body do you use in the painting process?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Pricasso</hi>: I quickly worked out that I could speed it up by using my testicles and butt cheeks to cover large areas in no time at all, but only recently do I paint the edges using my butt-crack, I call it the credit card swipe!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> How did you come up with the name Pricasso?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Pricasso</hi>: That was the heading they christened me with in the Picture Magazine interview in 2006. I realised it was Gold and took out the website and trademark.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> What's the most positive reaction you've had to one of your paintings?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Pricasso</hi>: It is always satisfying to get applause when a painting is finished; at most adult shows this happened all the time; but I do like painting disabled people. I have painted several people with severe <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/cerebral%20palsy">cerebral palsy</ref> and they are over the moon with the result; this gives me the most pleasure, as I do realise that they are still sexually active people and everyone should realise this.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Have any of your paintings been featured in a gallery somewhere?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Pricasso</hi>: I have entered the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bald%20Archy">Bald Archy</ref> Exhibition in Australia every year and sold a few. Also at an exhibition of politicians in Australia, and last November I went to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Miami">Miami</ref> for the <hi rend="italic">Art undressed</hi> exhibition and also painted 15 minute portraits there which was fun.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Do you consider it a form of freedom of expression to create your artwork in the way you do with your penis?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Pricasso</hi>: When I first thought of the idea I was really thinking I could get invited to a few parties as the entertainment which I do regularly, but now I am getting a good style about my work and want to take it to the next level and be accepted as an innovator.</p>
<hi rend="bold">A free society throws up these kinds of people, who exercise their freedom in unusual ways.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Cape Town former-Mayor <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Helen_Zille">Helen Zille</ref></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> In 2008, prior to a Sexpo event in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/South_Africa">South Africa</ref>, you uploaded a video to the Internet of yourself painting a portrait of then-Mayor of Cape Town Helen Zille. Why did you decide to do this?</hi></p>
</text>
