<text id="autogum_reddit_doc061" title="My mom has $0 Savings. I will be ultimately responsible for her retirement. question." shortTile="mom--savings-ultimately" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-04-30" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8fyyz9" speakerList="#HumanBeannn, #teresajs" speakerCount="2">
<head>My mom has $0 Savings. I will be ultimately responsible for her retirement. question.</head>
<sp who="#HumanBeannn">
<p>I graduated college a year ago and am making about $70k/year.  <hi rend="bold"> 6k in 401k </hi>  2k emergency fund  <hi rend="bold"> 20k student loans - most of my extra cash gets dumped into these loans. </hi>  770 credit score My main question is, is it feasible for me to buy my mom an apartment with my financials? She is 50 years old and is currently paying $800 for a studio.. I am looking at an area that has condos from 60k-80k. (1/1). Would this be a smart move? I know she would be able to pay the mortgage on it instead of throwing $800 in rent.. I'm viewing it as a win-win because i'll have an asset in my name and when its payed off that will be a huge stress-reliever for me years down the road without worrying where she'll live.. Are there mortgages for that amount? Or does it have to be cash? Also, how would this change my tax situation? </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#teresajs">
<p>Your mom is 50. That's not at ALL old! Barring illness or infirmity, she could, and should, continue working for another 15 years or so. And if she's been able to pay her bills, so far, she should be able to pay her bills for the next 10-15 years. </p>
<p>Mom doesn't NEED you to buy her a condo. A condo is actually a pretty big liability. On top of the morthage, there are condo fees, homeowners insurance, and property taxes. Plus, as the landlord, you'd be responsible for maintenance. And what if Mom decides to move? Or if she gets ill injured ans has to live in assisted living? You'd be stuck with a condo and need to get rid of it. </p>
<p>What she may need, in the future, is some financial support. Your Mom should qualify for social security payments in her elder years. If you and your brother could each budget a sum of money monthly to help Mom with expenses, she should be mostly okay. </p>
<p>Consider starting an after-tax investment account with the intention that the money could be used to help Mom in the future, when she needs help. My recommendation would be that you pay off your student loans, first. Once you're done with those, put the money you would have paid monthly into student loans into taxable investments (low-fee mutual funds?). </p>
</sp>
</text>
