<text id="autogum_reddit_doc064" title="[Analysis] Here's Some Statcast Metrics to Tell Us What We Should Overreact to from April" shortTile="analysis-heres-statcast" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-04-30" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8g3glw" speakerList="#papermarioguy02" speakerCount="1">
<head>[Analysis] Here's Some Statcast Metrics to Tell Us What We Should Overreact to from April</head>
<sp who="#papermarioguy02">
<p>About a decade ago, you had a decent premise for a baseball blogpost with "<ref target="https://www.fangraphs.com/library/offense/woba/">Player X] has been really bad so far, but his BABIP is only .200, so he probably isn't  <hi rend="bold">that</hi>  bad and will regress with a BABIP closer to .300 in the near future". That was it, and there are quite a few old articles from Fangraphs of that style. But now we have this wonderful thing called Statcast now, if you're reading this you're probably familiar with what it is, it's a tracking system that covers all sorts of player actions on the field and quantifies them. The most famous hitting metrics from this are exit velocity (the speed which with the ball leaves the bat, derived from a lot of math that's above my pay grade here) and launch angle (the angle relative to the ground the ball leaves the bat at). These have been combined into what's probably the most useful hitting metric we have from Statcast, expected wOBA. If you don't know what wOBA (weighted on base average) is, [it's essentially a hitting metric where all your actions as a hitter are given weights by how they on average contribute to run scoring, and then it's given a number scaled to OBP.</ref> Expected wOBA (xwOBA) attempts to calculate this, but based off of exit velocity and launch angle and pretending there's an average defense being hit to, thus attempting to give a more "pure" estimate of a player's hitting ability than the regular hitting metrics that are somewhat left up to the BABIP Gods. It tells us that some players who hit the crap out of the ball can expect their BABIP to be consistently higher than those that don't (looking at you Judge) and a closer look at what a player's performance might actually regress to. xwOBA isn't perfect, it doesn't account for the speed of a player that could give them a higher BABIP, and it doesn't account for the spray angle of hitters, but it's still a better offensive metric for looking at physical tools than we've ever previously had. With that in mind, this is an attempt to essentially re-write that article from a decade ago, but with xwOBA instead of BABIP. #Teams It's probably helpful to look at teams overall this season before looking at individual players. <ref target="https://baseballsavant.mlb.com/expected_statistics?type=batter-team&amp;year=2018&amp;position=&amp;team=&amp;min=1">The top 3 hitting teams in baseball by xwOBA so far are the Red Sox Yankees and Blue Jays (FUCK THIS DIVISION), the worst hitting teams are the Rockies (I should note that AFIAK this isn't adjusted for park effects, making this quite surprising) Padres and Marlins (pretty much as expected for those two).</ref> The luckiest teams so far (best actual wOBA compared to xwOBA) have been the Rays Braves and Twins. With the most unlucky teams have been the Indians Blue Jays and Royals. 28/30 teams currently have a worse actual wOBA than expected wOBA, which I'm assuming is just a product of the shitty weather so far this season, but it might be a concern if that disparity remains consistent throughout the year (either xwOBA is off somehow or the balls got unjuiced a bit). I should probably also note there that the Dodgers offensive woes so far appear to be real, and they really need Justin Turner back. The pitching performances, xwOBA allowed by pitching staffs that is, are also available here. <ref target="https://baseballsavant.mlb.com/expected_statistics?type=pitcher-team&amp;year=2018&amp;position=&amp;team=&amp;min=1">Astros Dodgers and Red Sox have had the best, (with the Phillies being a quite pleasantly surprising 4th place), White Sox Rangers and Royals the worst.</ref> The Twins Orioles and Rockies have been the most unlucky (idk if the Rockies will be consistently unlucky with pitching because of Coors, or if that's taken into account), with the Pirates Royals and Indians being the most lucky. #Players Let's look at the players producing those numbers. <ref target="https://baseballsavant.mlb.com/expected_statistics?type=batter&amp;year=2018&amp;position=&amp;team=&amp;min=50">With a minimum of 50 plate appearances</ref>, the highest xwOBAs in baseball belong to Mookie Betts, Teoscar Hernandez, and Steve Pearce (our old buddy Mike Trout is at number 5). Mookie Betts is well established as one of the best position players in baseball, non-Trout division. But Teoscar and Pearce look pretty out of place there. I actually went to write this because of how pleasantly surprised I was at the Blue Jays' hitting performance. Hernandez is producing more barrels (batted balls with the exit velocity and launch angle typical of hard extra base hits and dingers) per PA than any other player in baseball. Bringing up the rear are Hunter Pence, Jake Marisnick, and Caleb Joseph, all of whom have been absolutely atrocious at hitting this year and didn't need any fancy Statcast metrics to prove it. I should note that Pence has been hurt, which might explain some of his struggles, but it's still a definite concern. The most lucky hitters in baseball are Joey Wendle, Mallex Smith, and Albert Almora Jr. All 3 have been below average hitters by xwOBA but have produced like above average hitters. Didi Gregorius gets special mention as the 4th luckiest hitter, but his xwOBA is still well above average and my guess is that it doesn't account for how perfectly suited Yankee Stadium is for his swing, explaining some of the difference. The unluckiest hitters in baseball have been Matt Carpenter, Steve Pearce, and Randall Grichuk. Pearce has still been doing well but Matt Carpenter and especially Grichuk have probably been given some undue shit for their hitting by their fanbases for their hitting when they really haven't been all that bad looking at these metrics. Shifting over to pitching performances. I'm not gonna spend too much time on relievers here. Josh Hader and Adam Ottavino have been really good, Blaine Boyer has been very bad. Wilmer Font has been bad, but not as bad as you think, and Hunter Strickland has gotten off easy. Starters are where you can draw more meaningful early season conclusions from. Jacob DeGrom, Rick Porcello, and Gerrit Cole have been the best by this metric. Jacob DeGrom is an established ace. Gerrit Cole has always had the stuff, he just needed Houston's coaching to make him truly great. But Rick Porcello is not supposed to be this good, he won a CY in 2016, but that was with a not great competition (and Verlander prolly should've won anyway). He's never been someone to knock your socks off with his stuff, but he's managed it here. <ref target="https://www.fangraphs.com/blogs/the-best-rick-porcello-has-ever-been/">He's increased his control and GB rate without sacrificing swinging strikes by messing with his pitch mix, and it's really paying off.</ref> The worst starters in baseball by this metric have been Mike Leake, Chris Tillman, and Martin Perez, all of which with the possible exception of Leake aren't really worth writing much about (and even then I don't really have much to say other than "lol sog"). The luckiest pitchers so far have been Jarlin Garcia (who I have heard nothing about despite his very good looking raw stats, presumably because he plays for the Marlins and isn't actually that good), Francisco Liriano (brace yourselves for some regression Tigers fans), and Sean Manaea. Manaea Threw a damn no-hitter, so some luck is to be expected there. Unluckiest pitchers have been Jaime Garcia, Vince Velasquez, and Martin Perez. I can breathe a sigh of relief knowing that Jaime hasn't actually been that bad, and lol Martin Perez is still awful after adjusting for his luck. Jays fans should be genuinely worried about Marcus Stroman, who's struggles are very real with the quality of contact he's allowing and his walk problem, I imagine he's still somewhat hurt even if he hasn't said so. Anyway, I hope you enjoyed this post. Please send me all your angry comments about how Statcast unfairly discriminates against your favorite teams or players. And I hope you continue to enjoy watching baseball.</p>
</sp>
</text>
