<text id="autogum_voyage_doc341" title="Dothan" shortTile="dothan" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=9959" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Dothan</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Dothan</hi> is a city in southeastern <ref target="Alabama">Alabama</ref>, serving as the county seat of Houston County, and the chief city of the western Wiregrass region, an area encompassing portions of southeastern Alabama, southwestern <ref target="Georgia%20%28state%29">Georgia</ref>, and the panhandle of <ref target="Florida">Florida</ref>. Its population in 2018 was about 68,000, making it the largest metropolitan area in southeastern Alabama.</p>

<head>History</head>
<p>Dothan began as "Poplar Head", a stop along the main trail that ran through this portion of the state during the early 19th century. It was incorporated in 1885, and renamed after the village mentioned in Genesis 37:17, which reads "let us go to Dothan". The city quickly became a hub for local agriculture and industry, especially the peanut business, and its annual <hi rend="bold">National Peanut Festival</hi> (since 1938) reflects this heritage. Dothan has long proclaimed itself the "Peanut Capital of the World", as approximately one-quarter of the peanuts grown in the U.S. are grown within 75 miles of the city. Movie Gallery, a national movie rental chain, has its national headquarters here.</p>

<head>Climate</head>
<p>Dothan has a humid subtropical climate, with hot, sticky summers and generally mild winters. Snowfall is rare, and when it does come, it seldom accumulates to any great degree or remains for very long. Summer temperatures easily reach or more, while the average winter temperature is .</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>Dothan has one commercial airport, northwest of the city in the tiny village of Napier Field. It is served by ExpressJet, a subsidiary of Delta Air Lines, flying to and from <ref target="Atlanta">Atlanta</ref> International Airport. Dothan Regional Airport offers a full range of airport services and amenities; for further information, visit their website at <ref target="http://www.flydothan.com/">Dothan Regional Airport</ref>.</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>There is no passenger rail service to Dothan. The nearest <ref target="Amtrak">Amtrak</ref> station is in <ref target="Birmingham%20%28Alabama%29">Birmingham</ref>. Chipley, Florida had an Amtrak station prior to the landfall of Hurricane Katrina, but damage to the tracks in northwestern Florida forced its closure. Amtrak has proposed restoring the line, but there is no plan to do so as of March 2019.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>Dothan is served by Greyhound Bus Lines. The station is at 285 S. Foster St., +1 334-792-1191. Further information and hours of operation may be found at Dothan Greyhound Station.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>U.S. Highways 231, 431 and 84 all intersect in Dothan, as do several state highways. There is no interstate service in this part of Alabama, but the three highways named above are all four-laned for several miles beyond the Dothan city limits. U.S. 231 is four-laned all the way north to <ref target="Montgomery">Montgomery</ref>, and all the way south to <ref target="Panama%20City%20%28Florida%29">Panama City</ref>. The city is encircled by a four-lane bypass, known as the "Ross-Clark Circle."</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>There is no public transit system in Dothan, so getting around will require a car or bicycle, or walking. Traffic on the Ross-Clark Circle can be quite heavy, especially during "rush hour" and around lunchtime.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">US Army Aviation Museum</hi>. Located on Ft. Rucker, which lies just north of the town of Daleville about 20 miles north and west of Dothan. Many people do not realize that military aviation existed long before the creation of the Air Force in 1949; all military aircraft used in World War II, for instance, were either Army, Navy or Marine Corps aircraft, with the majority being Army airplanes. This museum pays tribute to the history of Army aviation, with sizable displays of Army aircraft--fixed-wing and rotary--from the earliest twentieth century to today. A variety of life-sized dioramas, films and interpretive material are available. Admission is free. Ft. Rucker is a "closed post"; guards at the post gates will require identification to enter, even for museum visitors.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Dr. George Washington Carver Monument</hi> (at the <ref target="http://www.nationalpeanutfestival.com/">National Peanut Festival Fairgrounds</ref>). This monument honors the African-American genius whose creative work resulted in hundreds of new products created from peanuts, sweet potatoes and other plants native to the South. Most of these were derived from peanuts, which are the principal agricultural product of the Wiregrass region--of which Dothan is the principal city.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Dothan Area Botanical Gardens</hi>. Enjoy the old Southern-style of gardening, and see what works in the Wiregrass. A tranquil, paved nature trail meanders through a beautiful rose garden, through herbs, daylilies, camellias, azaleas, past a peaceful pond, Victorian gazebo and a demonstration garden.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Dothan Opera House</hi>. Built in 1915, represents the elegance of turn-of-the-century southern life. Theatre performances, spectacular concerts, symphonies, ballet performances, and many other cultural events are regularly held in this landmark. Tours are available upon request.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Joseph statue</hi> (in <ref target="http://www.800alabama.com/things-to-do/alabama-attractions/joseph_statue.html">Millennium Park</ref>). The status is a ten-feet tall cast bronze sculpture, located in the historic downtown area. It depicts the Bible verse, "For I heard them say, Let us go to Dothan" (Genesis 37:17), which inspired city founders in 1885 to change the name of the town from Poplar Head to Dothan.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Landmark Park Agricultural Museum and Starlab Planetarium</hi>. The official agriculture museum of the State of Alabama. Visit a 1900s farmstead, complete with farmhouse, outhouses, and farm animals. Stroll the boardwalk and nature trail, see a planetarium show, have a picnic, tour Phase I of the Alabama Agricultural Museum, or catch one of the park's many special events. In the Planetarium, night skies are shown as they appear in season. Constellations are displayed as they relate to mythology. The park also has a new playground. A pavilion near the playground is available for park visitors and children's parties.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Houston-Love Memorial Library</hi>, 212 W. Burdeshaw Street (downtown Dothan across from the main post office).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Maria's Vineyard</hi>. Nestled in a grove of oak and pecan trees, the Vineyard offers a casual place to host an event either outside or inside in the Vineyard House.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Peanut Monument</hi>. At the Visitor Information Center helps to proclaim Dothan as the "Peanut Capital of the World".</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Peanuts Around Town</hi>. A public art project organized by <hi rend="italic">The Downtown Group</hi> consisting of 5-ft-tall peanut sculptures that are decorated in various fashions and displayed around Dothan.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Wiregrass Museum of Art</hi>. Includes five galleries feature changing exhibitions of visual and decorative arts in the historic building. Also features ARTventures, a hands-on exhibit for children and a gift gallery for shopping.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">World's Smallest City Block</hi> (at the intersection of North Appletree, Museum, and Troy streets). This land triangle features a stop sign, a yield sign, a street sign, and a granite marker placed by the Camellia Garden Club on May 1, 1964 stating that the block is the world's smallest city block.</item>
</list>
</text>
