<text id="autogum_interview_doc832" title="part2_ACLU President Strossen on religion, drugs, guns and impeaching George Bush" shortTile="partaclu-president" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-30" dateModified="2019-02-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/ACLU_President_Strossen_on_religion%2C_drugs%2C_guns_and_impeaching_George_Bush" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What would you say the atmosphere was like on campus back then, with all the issues that were being contended with, how would you describe it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  I don’t think it was that different than the atmosphere on law school campuses now, David, which is to say that even at the height—and statistics I have read have verified this—even at the height of the student activist movement, it was still a fairly small percentage of students who were really engaged, especially in law school.  In college there were more involved in the anti-war movement, but in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American%20law%20school">law school</ref> most people were just trying to get good grades and good jobs.  I don’t say that at all disparagingly.  There was a core of people who gravitated toward these extracurricular activities and back in those days you got no course credit at all.  Now most law schools give course credit, so you would have to do all of that on ‘’top’’ of your full time course load.  And if you can believe it, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harvard%20Law%20Review">Harvard Law Review</ref>, which I was also on, you got no course credit for that.  What I’m saying is that I wasn’t <hi rend="italic">really</hi> linked to the law school, per se; my experience was—and I cut a lot of classes, quite frankly—my experience was going to the legal aid bureau, going to the voluntary defenders office, meeting with my clients, doing that kind of work.  Law school classes and exams was just something I had to get through to get my degree.  But I didn’t feel myself so connected to Harvard Law School as an entity.</p>
<head id="Religion_in_schools">Religion in schools</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You had mentioned that one of the things that affected you with your family was seeing points of view not being allowed to be expressed.  Many <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christian%20right">religious conservatives</ref> would say that the ACLU opposes having their points of view in the schools.  How would you respond?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  That is absolutely untrue, but I know that <hi rend="italic">myth</hi> and distortion of what we have advocated and what the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Supreme%20court">Supreme Court</ref> has held, there are so many myths and misrepresentations about that, and the truth is that every individual, whether student or teacher, should be completely free in a nondiscriminatory process, to express whatever ideas or beliefs he or she has as long as it is consistent with the overall educational mission.  So just as it would be inappropriate for a student to stand up in the middle of math class and say, “Join the ACLU!” it would be inappropriate for a student to stand up in the middle of math class and say, “Join the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hare%20Krishna">Hare Krishna</ref> or the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christian%20Coalition">Christian Coalition</ref>!”  But in forums where it is appropriate for individuals to discuss ideas openly, such as extracurricular periods, lunch periods, maybe there are times before or after the school day, then <hi rend="italic">every</hi> viewpoint should be welcome equally, whether it be pro-religion, anti-religion, any religion, any politics, you name it.</p>
</text>
