<text id="autogum_academic_doc494" title="Effects of Detritus on the Mosquito Culex pipiens: Phragmites and Schedonorus (Festuca) Invasion Affect Population Performance" shortTile="effects-detritus" author="Paul  T. Leisnham, Brandon Scott, Andrew  H. Baldwin, Shannon  L. LaDeau" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4118/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
The co-occurrence of exotic species is becoming more common with the increasing spread of organisms worldwide, and a better understanding of their interactions is important to manage biological invasions. Invasive plants that alter the vegetation around ephemeral ground pools may facilitate or resist the spread of the exotic vector mosquito <hi rend="italic">C. pipiens</hi> by altering allochthonous detritus inputs in those pools. In surveys of roadside stormwater ditches, mean <hi rend="italic">C. pipiens</hi> densities did not differ among habitats that varied in litter species, but female <hi rend="italic">C. pipiens</hi> were larger from ditches with <hi rend="italic">S. arundinaceus</hi> and smaller with <hi rend="italic">J. effusus</hi> compared to other plant species (<hi rend="italic">P. australis</hi> and <hi rend="italic">T. latifolia</hi>). In a laboratory microcosm experiment, <hi rend="italic">C. pipiens</hi> per capita rate of population change (λ′) was unaffected when larvae were provisioned with different detritus species, yet larger adults emerged from microcosms with <hi rend="italic">S. arundinaceus</hi> and smaller adults from microcosms with <hi rend="italic">J. effusus</hi>. For adults of numerous mosquito species, larger size is related to survival, and adult survival has been shown to be a critical life-history parameter for pathogen transmission in mathematical models and field studies. The results of this study suggest that the invasion of <hi rend="italic">S. arundinaceus</hi> in stormwater ditches or the displacement of <hi rend="italic">J. effusus</hi> by <hi rend="italic">P. australis</hi> invasion may alter disease transmission of <hi rend="italic">C. pipiens</hi> by producing larger females. Body size is also related to fecundity in mosquitoes. As a part of this study, we developed a fecundity to female body size relationship for <hi rend="italic">C. pipiens</hi> based on data from the wing lengths of 55 females. This allowed us to calculate more accurate λ′ estimates than past studies (e.g.,), which have used a function based on a relationship for four females from an autogenous form of <hi rend="italic">C. pipiens</hi> that almost entirely uses subterranean environments, <hi rend="italic">C. pipiens</hi> f. <hi rend="italic">molestus</hi>. Since egg rafts from autogenous mosquito species’ tend to have fewer eggs than those of anautogenous species, using a size-fecundity relationship based on a small number of <hi rend="italic">C. pipiens</hi> f. <hi rend="italic">molestus</hi> is undesirable for above ground <hi rend="italic">C. pipiens</hi>. Therefore, we recommend future studies that require size-fecundity relationship for above-ground <hi rend="italic">C. pipiens</hi> to refer to the function in this study until an even more robust size-fecundity relationship from a greater number of females over a wider range of wing lengths is calulcated. </p>

<p>Our findings suggest that the litter species within ephemeral ground pools could affect the risk of disease transmission from <hi rend="italic">C. pipiens</hi> in urban areas. Although mosquito size is a consistent factor explaining variability in vector competence, there are conflicting data in the literature as to whether smaller or larger female mosquitoes are more competent disease vectors. Evidence for the efficacy of smaller mosquitoes in transmitting disease was noted in a study on <hi rend="italic">A. albopictus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Aedes aegypti</hi> susceptibility to the Sindbis virus. This study demonstrated that smaller mosquitoes from environments with high density-dependent competition had a higher body titer and higher likelihood of infection than larger mosquitoes from low competition environments. Conversely, other studies have demonstrated that larger females are more efficient disease vectors. Xue et al. found that larger <hi rend="italic">A. aegypti</hi> females live longer and are more likely to seek multiple blood feedings than smaller females, which increased the likelihood that they could become infected with a virus and transmit it to a host within their lifetime. Juliano et al. used both laboratory experiments and field-collected female <hi rend="italic">Ae. aegypti</hi> to demonstrate that intraspecific competition in larval habitats produced smaller females that had reduced survival and were less likely to be infected with dengue. If larger <hi rend="italic">C. pipiens</hi> females are more effective disease vectors, ephemeral pool systems with <hi rend="italic">S. arundinaceus</hi> clippings would produce the most competent disease-transmitting mosquitoes, while pools with <hi rend="italic">J. effusus</hi> detritus with would produce the least competent disease vectors. Changes in vegetation communities surrounding ephemeral pools could then alter the risk of disease transmission from mosquitoes based on which plant species were displaced. For example, if <hi rend="italic">P. australis</hi>, which produces intermediate-sized females, displaced <hi rend="italic">J. effusus</hi> the disease risk in the area could increase, while if <hi rend="italic">P. australis</hi> displaced <hi rend="italic">S. arundinaceus</hi> the risk could decrease. Alternatively, if larger <hi rend="italic">C. pipiens</hi> females are less efficient vectors, scenarios conducive to the establishment of <hi rend="italic">S. arundinaceus</hi> would result in a lower risk of disease transmission. Future research is needed to examine the susceptibility of arboviral infection specifically for <hi rend="italic">C. pipiens</hi> females at different sizes and from different larval environments.  </p>
</text>
