<text id="autogum_interview_doc428" title="part0_Dale Ogden, 2010 California gubernatorial candidate, talks with Wikinews" shortTile="partdale-ogden--california" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-04-27" dateModified="2014-04-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dale_Ogden%2C_2010_California_gubernatorial_candidate%2C_talks_with_Wikinews" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Dale Ogden, 2010 California gubernatorial candidate, talks with Wikinews</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 27, 2010</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Photo of Dale Ogden Image: Dale Ogden.</caption></figure><p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dale%20Ogden">Dale Ogden</ref>, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/California%20gubernatorial%20election,%202010">2010 California gubernatorial candidate</ref>, talks with <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mike_Morales">Mike Morales</ref> about his platform.</p>
<p>Ogden is a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref>' <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Libertarian%20Party%20(United%20States)">Libertarian Party</ref>.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<figure><caption>Logo of the Libertarian Party. Image: Libertarian Party.</caption></figure><p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Morales</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How would you define libertarianism?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Dale Ogden</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Libertarianism is a political philosophy of minimum government espoused by the founders of our nation. People should be free to enjoy the fruits of their labor and government should be limited to protecting the life, liberty and property of its citizens. That includes such things as national defense, a court system to resolve disputes, and the enforcement mechanisms to enforce contracts between consenting adults and legal entities. A key characteristic of the Libertarian Party is that we do not believe that coercion should be used to effect change. When joining the LP, we take the following oath: "I certify that I oppose the initiation of force to achieve political or social goals."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">On one of California's major issues today, how do you propose to fix our failing economy?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DO</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> We need to roll-back spending to the level of 1998, adjusted for inflation and population (does anyone think we didn't have enough government in 1998?); lower taxes significantly (especially income and sales taxes); eliminate harmful, useless, and duplicate regulatory agencies; significantly reduce the number of employees at most state agencies; and permanently limit future spending increases based on population and inflation and limited to the tax receipts available (no more deficit spending).</p>
<p>We need to roll-back excessive salaries and pensions for state employees and increase the retirement age for both current and future state employees to 65 to 70 (from the current 50 or 55). We need to end collusion between politicians, bureaucrats and government employee unions. No elected or appointed official should ever get a pension or post-employment benefits.</p>
<p>The friendly business and low tax environment in California will attract tens of thousands of businesses and millions of jobs to California and, eventually, tax receipts will soar. However, any excess revenue should be used to retire debt or returned to the taxpayers.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What is your stance on gay marriage?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DO</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Why not just get government out of people’s personal lives? Let people choose how to live their lives, choose with whom they share it, and decide for themselves what arrangements (marriage or otherwise) should be made for all of life’s situations. Treat every individual equally. Do not discriminate in favor of or against married couples (or groups). Let them decide what promises to make to one another and embed those promises in contracts. The state can then enforce the contracts, as it should enforce all contracts between consenting adults. If religions want to put their “stamp of approval” on a wedding, let them; let the people involved decide what to do.</p>
</text>
