<text id="autogum_interview_doc554" title="part6_Ingrid Newkirk, co-founder of PETA, on animal rights and the film about her life" shortTile="partingrid-newkirk" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-20" dateModified="2018-02-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ingrid_Newkirk%2C_co-founder_of_PETA%2C_on_animal_rights_and_the_film_about_her_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  In the movie they show PETA making a change in tactics from focusing on exotic animals to focusing on livestock such as turkeys.  Exotic animals are things most people could support, but livestock is more out there for many.  How would you respond to the argument that progress is incremental and by taking a leap from focusing on exotics to focusing on livestock you could be overreaching?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  We work on all of it.  It wasn’t as if we were stopping all investigations into exotics, it’s that we have a string of exposés on these exotic animal farms, from the people who caught these lions cubs for photo shoots with kids and take them to auto shows, and how they are beaten up behind the scenes and bullied.  At one point I thought, ‘Here we are looking into an investigation into another one of these exotic animal places, and yet the biggest problem is that not everyone goes to a game farm, or a roadside zoo for a photo shoot with a bear, but everybody eats.’  I thought we really have to concentrate where <hi rend="italic">everyone</hi> could do something, because three times a day you make that decision.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  A religious argument might be that they were put on Earth <hi rend="italic">for</hi> Man.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  You look at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garden%20of%20Eden">Garden of Eden</ref> and that was a place where the lion lays down with the lamb and there is no slaughter.  The fall comes when somebody kills and blood is shed, and then everything becomes chaos and violence.  If you look at the true Garden of Eden, what were <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adam%20and%20Eve">Adam and Eve</ref> eating?  Fruits, berries.  They weren’t slaughtering the animals but living amongst the animals and everything was peaceful.  So if there’s a biblical sense, I don’t think <hi rend="italic">dominion</hi>—if that’s the scripture you are looking at—I don’t think dominion means exploitation.  It may come with a responsibility to look after and protect, the way the Queen had dominion over Canada.  That didn’t allow for her to put electrodes in its citizens’ heads and test floor polish on Canadians.  It was a protectorate, and isn’t that what we are supposed to be?  Protectors and not big bullies.</p>
<head id="Fashion_and_animals">Fashion and animals</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Did your protest at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean-Paul%20Gaultier">Jean-Paul Gaultier</ref> have any effect?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  It’s hard to tell now because he’s such a bad boy, but recently the Gaultier Company decided they would meet with us and there is a meeting in Paris coming up shortly.  We have been writing to him.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You had mentioned earlier wool clothing in relation to Australian exporters.  Are you against wool clothing or against how it is made and harvested?</hi></p>
</text>
