<text id="autogum_voyage_doc30" title="First and business class flights" shortTile="first-business-class" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=11640" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>First and business class flights</head>

<p>To alleviate the tedium and discomfort of long flights, many passengers investigate the option of flying in <hi rend="bold">first</hi> or <hi rend="bold">business class</hi>. This article discusses whether it's worth the price and how you can reduce the cost.</p>

<head>What you get</head>
<p>Amenities in first and business class (also known as premium classes) vary widely by airline and even plane type, and it's absolutely imperative to research carefully before choosing. </p>

<p>The following overview discusses the amenities you can expect on a <hi rend="bold">long-haul</hi> flight, loosely defined as over six hours. Few airlines offer first class for shorter trips anymore, except in very high-yield Asian routes (e.g. Hong Kong-Singapore) and in the United States, where business class is usually not offered and domestic "first" class approximates short-haul business class elsewhere. Short-haul business class is increasingly converging on offering the same limited in-flight facilities as economy class, the main selling point being flexibility, access to perks (e.g. airline lounges, complimentary in-flight meals), and an empty middle seat.</p>

<p>If you fly within North America, most of the extra features that coach passengers now have to pay for (like food, entertainment and checked luggage) are already included in the ticket price of premium passengers. However, unlike in other countries, flying domestic first class in the United States does not typically include automatic lounge access except for some transcontinental routes; you will need to separately purchase a lounge pass or lounge membership for that.</p>

<head>Premium economy</head>
<p>'Premium Economy' or 'Economy Plus' is offered by some airlines on some aircraft. It provides a larger and more comfortable seat than standard Economy and is cheaper than Business class. On international flights, premium economy seating can amount to what business class used to be, during the 1980s. The extra cost can double the cost of your flight ticket, especially if you're traveling to and from Asia—or just add another 10%, if you upgrade at the last minute on a mostly empty flight—but it is much cheaper than business class. </p>

<p>Extra amenities offered to premium economy passengers vary widely from airline to airline, ranging from nothing more than the extra legroom in United Airlines or American Airlines, to lounge access at the departure airport either for a fee as is the case of Air France or Lufthansa, or as part of the ticket price as is case of All Nippon Airways or Japan Airlines. Check each airline's web-site before you buy.</p>

<p>On U.S. airlines, premium economy usually involves the same seats as economy section, but the rows are spaced a few inches further apart and placed nearer the front of the airplane. The extra cost for this legroom can be as low as US$10 on a short, low-demand domestic flight.</p>

<head>Business class</head>

<p>For a long time, business class was akin to economy with larger seats and more seat pitch (space for your legs), but the continuing drive to strip all frills out of economy and better other airlines' business classes has seen some major changes in the past decade.</p>

<p>At the airport, business class flyers typically have a separate check-in area or at least their own row, and can access a <hi rend="bold">business class lounge</hi> that offers drinks, snacks, newspapers and maybe Internet access. Some of the best lounges offer showers and even nap rooms. Note that you can typically only use a business class lounge at your <hi rend="italic">departure</hi> airport and when waiting for a connection, although some airlines allow long-haul passengers to use them on arrival as well.</p>

<p>Once on board — and you're usually boarded first — <hi rend="bold">seat pitch</hi> in business remains good by any measure: while 91 cm (36 in) is considered unusually generous in economy, few long-haul business seats are under 100 cm (40 in) and 130-153 cm (50-60 in) is considered standard. However, for many travellers the most important consideration is <hi rend="bold">recline</hi>, particularly the holy grail of the <hi rend="bold">flat bed seat</hi> (180° recline, parallel to the floor), which pretty much guarantees a good night's sleep. True flat bed seats are rare and expensive, with British Airways and Virgin Atlantic's Upper Class pioneering the concept, but <hi rend="bold">lie-flat seats,</hi> angled seats like those found in Air France's business class cabin, which recline to an angle of perhaps 170° and are vertically tilted to squeeze in better, are increasingly common. Flat-bed and lie-flat seats are usually found only on long-haul flights in premium carriers (Lufthansa, Singapore Airlines, Cathay Pacific, etc.). That said, these are often also deployed on shorter flights between major financial centres that see very heavy business traffic (eg. Singapore-Hong Kong flights on Singapore Airlines and Cathay Pacific).</p>

<p>Food and drink in business class is much better than the slop usually encountered in economy class. You can expect to be given actual menus with several choices, with courses served one by one from actual porcelain plates and accompanied by free drinks. Some airlines allow you to order from an extensive menu <hi rend="italic">before</hi> you fly, in which case the meal will be loaded especially for you.</p>

<p>Entertainment options in business class are also good, with <hi rend="bold">audio and video on demand</hi> (AVOD) a standard amenity, either via a display built into your seat or portable DVD players passed out by request. Power sockets for laptops are often provided and Internet access may be available too.</p>

<p>The last perk comes at the end, as you'll be the first out of the plane (apart from the first class) and into the immigration and customs lanes. In fact, in some stations such as London's Heathrow Airport, there are dedicated lanes for business class passengers at passport control. In addition, flying business class also provides you with <hi rend="bold">priority baggage</hi> for your checked baggage, meaning that your baggage will be out on the carousel before the economy class passengers' baggage.</p>

<head>First class</head>


<p>Due to the race to improve business class, first class is a slowly dying breed. Some airlines have dropped it entirely and those that still offer it limit it to "premier" or "high-yield" routes with very heavy business traffic and hence enough people willing to pay for the privilege. However in the mid-late 2000s, carriers like Singapore Airlines, Cathay Pacific, Qatar Airways and Emirates have released new first-class products. </p>

<p>The first class experience begins before you board the plane: some airlines like Thai throw in limousine transfers to and from the airport, where you can expect to have your bags carried by a porter, be checked in at a private first-class check-in area and enjoy your first glass of sparkling wine at a first-class lounge. Lufthansa's <ref target="Frankfurt%20Airport">Frankfurt Airport</ref> hub goes a step further, dedicating <hi rend="italic">an entire terminal</hi> to first-class flyers!</p>

<p>Once onboard, first class is perhaps best known for the superlative meal service, and indeed <hi rend="bold">high-quality champagne, lobster tail and caviar</hi> do still feature on some menus. These days, though, the trend is towards a wide selection of entrees served to order and lengthy wine lists. Service is very personal, with first class cabin crew tending to as few as two or three passengers each. In Etihad's "The Residence", which is marketed as a class above first class and perhaps the most luxurious experience on a commercial flight, you will get chauffeur driving you to the airport, a personal lounge, a full-course fine dining meal, a personal butler to attend to your needs until the end of your flight, and an apartment with a double bed on board the flight. It is extremely expensive, with the cheapest tickets starting from US$13,000.</p>

<p>A standard amenity in modern first class is a lie-flat seat, which lies <hi rend="italic">completely</hi> flat (180 degrees) and is increasingly offered in <hi rend="bold">suite</hi> or <hi rend="bold">cradle</hi> configurations where you have a curtain or other privacy divider to separate you from other passengers, and a few airlines even offer these in "double" configurations for two people. When reclined, the seat will actually resemble a bed, made up by crew with comfortable linens, pillows, etc. Pyjamas are usually provided and even the toiletry kit will contain recognizable brand names. When sitting up, seat pitch regularly exceeds 200 cm (80") and there are rarely more than 4 seats in a row.</p>

<p>An exception to the availability of lie-flat seats in first class is on U.S. domestic flights, where first class seats usually the same as those on short-haul business class or long-haul premium economy elsewhere. That said, lie-flat seats are provided on some transcontinental routes or flights between the mainland and Hawaii.</p>

<p>When it comes to frequent flyer miles, first class passengers can accrue up to three times the number of miles flown. For example, those flying round-trip long-haul like Singapore-Los Angeles using SIA's Suite Class have more than enough miles to redeem up to 2 intra-South East Asian flights.</p>

<p>Last but not least, first class gets the <hi rend="bold">best seats in the plane</hi>. This is almost invariably at the front of the plane, where engine noise and turbulence are minimized.</p>
</text>
