<text id="autogum_interview_doc423" title="part2_&amp;quot;Avast ye scurvy file sharers!&amp;quot;: Interview with Swedish Pirate Party leader Rickard Falkvinge" shortTile="partavast-ye-scurvy" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-06-19" dateModified="2015-10-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/%22Avast_ye_scurvy_file_sharers%21%22%3A_Interview_with_Swedish_Pirate_Party_leader_Rickard_Falkvinge" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Besides, it's a way of reclaiming a word. The media conglomerates have been pointing at us and calling us pirates, trying to make us somehow feel shame. It doesn't work. We wear clothes saying "PIRATE" in bright colors out on the streets. Yes, we are pirates, and we're proud of it, too.</p>
<p>Also, the term is not that negative at all in Sweden, much thanks to the awesome footwork of the Pirate Bureau (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Piratbyrån">Piratbyrån</ref>), who have been working since 2003 to educate the public.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">If you are elected, and have the opportunity to become part of the next government of Sweden, do you intend to focus only on the issues in your platform (IP law and privacy)?</hi></p>
<p>Our current plan is to support the government from the parliament, but not be part of it. If we're part of it, that means we get a vested interest to not overthrow it, which puts us in a weaker position if they start going against our interests.</p>
<p>Overall, our strategy is to achieve the balance of power, where both the left and right blocks need our votes to achieve a majority, and then support the issues of whichever government that agrees to drive our issues the strongest. Basically, we sell our votes on other issues to the highest bidder in exchange for them driving ours.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Have you already made any contacts in Swedish politics?</hi></p>
<p>Contacts... I'm not sure what you mean. Several of us have been shaking hands with some of the established politicians, particularly in the youth leagues, if that's what you mean.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">I was thinking along the lines of exploring possible modes of cooperation with established political parties — are you already taken seriously?</hi></p>
<p>We are taken seriously by most of the youth leagues and by at least one of the represented parties. In particular, which is what counts, we are now taken seriously by national media. However, we can't tie contacts that explore modes of cooperation quite yet — since our strategy depends on holding the balance of power, we need to not express a preference for whom we'd like to cooperate with, or we'd put ourselves in a weaker bargaining position.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What is your position on moral rights, as recognized by European Union copyright laws: the right of attribution, the right to have a work published anonymously or pseudonymously, and the right to the integrity of the work. Do you think these rights should be preserved?</hi></p>
<p>We safeguard the right to attribution very strongly. After all, what we are fighting for is the intent of copyright as it is described in the US constitution: the promotion of culture. Many artists are using recognition as their primary driving force to create culture.</p>
</text>
