<text id="autogum_interview_doc766" title="Interview with Curtis Grant, Regional Council candidate for Wards 2 &amp; 6 in Brampton, Canada" shortTile="interview-curtis" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-06" dateModified="2013-05-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Curtis_Grant%2C_Regional_Council_candidate_for_Wards_2_%26_6_in_Brampton%2C_Canada" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Interview with Curtis Grant, Regional Council candidate for Wards 2 &amp; 6 in Brampton, Canada</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, October 6, 2006</hi></p>
<p>The upcoming <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brampton%20municipal%20election,%202006">2006 Brampton municipal election</ref>, to be held November 13, features an array of candidates looking to represent their wards in city council or the council of the Peel Region.</p>
<p>Wikinews contributor Nick Moreau contacted many of the candidates, including <hi rend="bold">Curtis Grant</hi>, asking them to answer common questions sent in an email. This ward's incumbent is Paul Palleschi, also challenging Palleschi is <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Vicky_Colbourne,_Regional_Council_candidate_for_Wards_2_&amp;_6_in_Brampton,_Canada">Vicky Colbourne</ref>, David Esho, Chuck Jeffrey, and Tejinder Singh.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> List the three most important issues in your campaign.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Traffic congestion, community safety, and lack of funding for health and social services.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What one election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Traffic congestion.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What qualities or experiences do you possess, that make you more desirable than the incumbent? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I am passionate and dedicated about building Brampton into a healthier, safer and more prosperous City. I like challenge and I have the ability to work cohesively with all management levels.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent your ward on council?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I love the citizens of Wards 2 &amp; 6 and I believe in putting them front and center of government policies and programs and in a strong and united regional government.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Of the decisions made by council since the last election, which one would you have changed, and why?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I would change the rate of development. This would minimize the negative impacts on our residents and give the city enough time to expand existing infrastructure.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> For the past fourteen years I have dedicated my time and skills to volunteering in different community organizations in the cities of Brampton and Toronto.  I served in the role of Youth Leader, Mentor and Teacher and most recently Ministry Coordinator.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Much of Brampton's existing council is quite seasoned in the civic political process. What could you bring to the table as a "rookie", above and beyond the current roster of councillors?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> As Regional Councillor for Wards 2 &amp; 6, I will put forth a proactive and sustainable plan to build A Stronger Brampton, Stronger Region. I am committed to improving access to government, reducing traffic congestion and enhancing our infrastructure to meet our current and growing demands. I will work to improve the delivery of public health services and I am dedicated to making our City safer. I will strengthen our parks, culture and recreation master plan, build a stronger economy, protect the environment and enhance our social services.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> The Rose Theatre recently launched. What are your thoughts on this facility? Have you had a chance to tour it yet? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> The Rose Theatre is wonderful place to showcase local, national and international talent.  It is an excellent way to boost Brampton's economy. I haven't had a chance to tour it yet.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> The province has strongly encouraged the development of high-density residences near the downtown. Do these buildings fit in with your vision of the downtown? How much say should other levels of government have in urban planning? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I believe in revitalizing the downtown core with high-density residences. I believe urban planning should be a collaborative effort between all levels of government.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How do you feel about Brampton's rate of expansion? Council recently capped the annual amount of new development; do you agree completely with this decision, would you have slowed development even further, or not have imposed a cap at all? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I Support a cap to slow development in Brampton, but a cap alone is not enough.  Council must continue to engage the Provincial government and other municipalities in developing a better population and employment distribution plan for GTA to relieve the development pressure on Brampton.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why should businesses be attracted to locating in Brampton?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> There are several reasons why businesses would want to relocate to Brampton, some of them include: The caring, helpful and hard working people who live here; our skilled workforce; we have stable energy supply; we have a good supply of development land and a beautiful city.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How could Brampton further itself in attracting corporate investment?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Some ways in which Brampton could further itself in attracting corporate investment could include: establishing more competitive municipal tax rate, improving our tourism industry and assisting with relocation costs.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I have a passion to represent the residents of Wards 2 &amp; 6 and the vision to build a stronger Brampton, Stronger Region.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What does Brampton mean to you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Brampton is a wonderful city to call home, a wonderful city to raise my family, a wonderful city the get an education, a wonderful city to operate a business and I'm proud to invite family and friends to visit.</p>
</text>
