<text id="autogum_academic_doc280" title="Capacity Allocation of Game Tickets Using Dynamic Pricing" shortTile="capacity-allocation" author="Aniruddha Dutta" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2306-5729/4/4/141/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Conclusions and Limitations</head>
<p>
The current study uses the mathematical principle of DP combined with empirical data to determine the demand functions for university football game tickets. These estimated demand functions are fundamental for specifying a DP model. Based on the calculated demand functions, it is established that the application of DP strategies would generate more revenues than the optimal fixed price. Therefore, the study contributes to the existing literature by analyzing a pricing approach that is applicable in the field of online ticket sales.  </p>

<p>The other important result of our study is the capacity distribution according to the game intensity. It has been shown that it is not always optimal for a club to sell the entire capacity of tickets by itself. Getting involved with a retailer can be beneficial if the club can earn a commission based on the sales from the retailer. The results depict that for a high intensity game, the demand is generally high and thus the club should sell all the tickets by itself. On the other hand, as the demand fluctuates the capacity allocation is an important factor and a hard mathematical problem for the club to maximize its revenues from ticket sales. As shown in <figure>Figure 6</figure>. when the demand for tickets is relatively low, it is optimal for the club to retain 20–40% of the tickets and the rest of the capacity should be sold to online retailers. In the real world, this pricing technique has been used by football clubs and thus the secondary market online retailers like Ticketmaster and Vivid Seats have become popular in the last decade.  </p>

<p>There are at some limitations to the present study. First, only the ticket prices of games played by the university football team have been studied. An evaluation of other sports clubs for different games in other leagues might reveal different demand functions, which are the core element of a DP model. Thus, it seems advisable to repeat this study in a different context. As mentioned in the introduction, several previous researches have pointed out to the fact that loyal fans are not always deterred by high ticket prices. Due to this fact, several researchers have reported a positive correlation of game attendance with ticket prices. Thus, a more robust data centric study considering all factors is required for further analysis. The present dataset does not contain transactions on season tickets; thus, the present study is limited to only individual transactions. As is evident, teams tend to hold on to their season ticket holders by offering a lower price; a future study involving season ticket transactions and DP is required to find the optimal fixed price for season tickets. Furthermore, the estimated demand functions for five games rely on a small sample data set. Hence, future research could extend the findings from the current study by analyzing a larger data set involving multiple teams and multiple games. Second, the designed DP model is based on only five demand functions, one for each home game played by the university. This study considers the home game as high ranked based on its previous performances. However, if the home game is either medium or low ranked then at least nine different demand functions need to be considered for all game types. This would provide a more detailed analysis of how the capacity distribution of tickets should be allocated by the club to maximize its revenues. However, one reason the DP strategy for pricing sports tickets has been studied extensively is due to interest in different kinds of factors, such as current position in the league standings or weather conditions, in order to price the tickets. These factors have not been considered in the present study. Finally, the present study considers only one type of seats for simplicity for pricing the tickets. Prices for different zones and seat types may yield different result in terms of distribution of the capacity. However, the main result of DP for generating maximum revenues should not change when different seat types are considered. Finally, the study has been done from the perspective of the home team club. The main objective is to maximize the revenue of the club from online ticket sales through third-party retailers. A further scope of research would be to consider sales from both the club and the retailer’s perspective and maximize the revenue of the supply chain. The online retailer might not be able to sell all the tickets, in which case a salvage value can be considered if the ticket is unsold. Thus, the retailer will have a differentiated strategy and the overall supply chain needs to be considered for the benefit of the club and the online retailer.
 </p>
</text>
