<text id="autogum_interview_doc004" title="part0_US study finds correlation between youth suicide, household gun ownership" shortTile="partus-study-finds" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2019-01-18" dateModified="2019-02-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_study_finds_correlation_between_youth_suicide%2C_household_gun_ownership" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>US study finds correlation between youth suicide, household gun ownership</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 26, 2019</hi></p>
<p>Professor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael%20Siegel">Michael Siegel</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Boston_University">Boston University</ref>, co-author of a new study published in the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American%20Journal%20of%20Preventive%20Medicine">American Journal of Preventive Medicine</ref></hi> on January 17, declared household gun ownership rates within the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> to be "the strongest single predictor of a state's youth suicide rate". <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> interviewed Siegel to learn more.</p>
<figure><caption>A suicide prevention sign on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/California">California</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golden%20Gate%20Bridge">Golden Gate Bridge</ref>. Professor Siegel noted guns to be a more lethal method than this famed and high-profile example, and theorised this accounted for household gun ownership being a stronger predictor of successful suicides than the rate of failed suicide attempts.Image: <ref target="https://www.panoramio.com/user/7?with_photo_id=23718">Eduardo Manchon</ref> via <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Panaramio">Panaramio</ref>..</caption></figure>
<p>Siegel and colleagues including predoctoral fellow Anita Knopov, the lead author, compared data from the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Centers_for_Disease_Control_and_Prevention">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</ref> from 2004, when the body last surveyed US gun owners, to corresponding information on suicides by 10–19 year olds from 2005 through 2015. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Youth%20Risk%20Behavior%20Surveillance%20System">Youth Risk Behavior Surveillance System</ref> was used to find data on such variables as <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Education">education</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/depression">depression</ref>, and suicidal planning and ideation.</p>
<p>The study reports "For each 10 percentage-point increase in household gun ownership, the youth suicide rate increased by 26.9 percent". The ten states with highest youth suicide rates had household gun ownership rates above 50%; the ten with the lowest youth suicide rates had household gun ownership around 20%. The data were, the study says, more closely correlated than youth suicide attempts were to actual suicides.</p>
<p>The study notes the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National%20Violent%20Injury%20Statistic%20System">National Violent Injury Statistic System</ref> indicates 82% of youth suicides involving a gun used one from the victim's own household in 2016. Most variables appeared uncorrelated, with only suicide attempts and proportion of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Native%20American">Native American</ref> youth showing correlation. The team wrote that guns "are 2.6 times more lethal than any other means of suicide; thus, access to firearms might be expected to contribute to a higher incidence of suicide." </p>
<p>The highest rate noted by the team was in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Alaska">Alaska</ref>, with fifteen youth suicides per 100,000 individuals. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_Jersey">New Jersey</ref> had the lowest rate, which was three per 100,000 people. There were states that did not match the overall trend: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Alabama">Alabama</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mississippi">Mississippi</ref> had low youth suicide rates of around 4.5 per 100,000 people but high household gun ownership rates of over 50%. Each state has a large proportion of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/African-American">African-American</ref> residents; they were found statistically less likely to commit suicide and to own guns.</p>
<p>Siegel agreed to answer some questions for <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi>‍'s correspondent.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Thank you for taking the time to speak with us. Would you mind telling us a little about yourself, your background, and what led you to look into this subject?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Michael Siegel</hi> I am a professor in the Department of Community Health Sciences at the Boston University School of Public Health. My research has focused on the areas of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tobacco">tobacco</ref>, alcohol, and firearms. We decided to look at this subject because although there have been some studies that reported an association between household gun ownership and youth suicide rates, one could argue that the reason for this association is that gun households differ systematically from non-gun households in that they are more likely to have youth with depression and therefore youth who are more likely to attempt suicide. Our study was designed to control for these factors in order to determine whether differences in suicide attempt rates explain the observed association between household gun ownership and youth suicide rates.</p>
</text>
