<text id="autogum_voyage_doc198" title="West Central Florida" shortTile="west-central-florida" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=38867" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>West Central Florida</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">West Central Florida</hi> is in the state of <ref target="Florida">Florida</ref> in the <ref target="United%20States%20of%20America">United States</ref>. It includes Citrus, Hernando, Hillsborough, Manatee Pasco, Pinellas, Polk and Sumter counties.</p>

<head>Cities</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> - the largest city in West Central Florida.</item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> </item>
</list>


<head>By plane</head>

<p>The largest airport in the region is <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://tampaairport.com">Tampa International Airport</ref></hi> ( TPA ) on the western side of Tampa. TIA serves dozens of destinations, with daily flights to most major cities in the US and almost every major airline hub. The Tampa-<ref target="Atlanta">Atlanta</ref> route carries the most passengers of any route with nearly 3 times as many passengers as the second largest destination <ref target="Charlotte">Charlotte</ref>. The largest airlines in/out of TIA are American, Delta, and Southwest.</p>

<p>Directly across the bay and just 10 miles from TIA is <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.fly2pie.com">St. Petersburg-Clearwater International Airport</ref></hi> ( PIE ), which served mostly by budget airlines and used for private aviation. It is a hub for Allegiant Air which flies to about two dozen small airports throughout the Midwest &amp; Northeast. As of February 2011, it is also served by: Frontier Airlines to Milwaukee &amp; Omaha (both seasonal); Air Transat to Halifax &amp; Toronto (both seasonal); Sunwing Airlines to Toronto; Vision Air to Gulfport-Biloxi; &amp; Locair to Marsh Harbour &amp; Treasure Cay.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://srq-airport.com">Sarasota-Bradenton International Airport</ref></hi> ( SRQ ) is located between Sarasota and Bradenton and is served by American, Delta, JetBlue, and United. About half of the routes are seasonal.</p>

<head>State parks</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Crystal River Archaeological State Park</hi>, 3400 N. Museum Point, ☏ +1 352 795-3817 . 8AM to sundown. A National Historic Landmark. Next to the Crystal River Preserve State Park.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Crystal River Preserve State Park</hi>, 3266 N. Sailboat Avenue, ☏ +1 352 563-0450 . 8AM to sundown. Next to the Crystal River Archaeological State Park</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Dade Battlefield Historic State Park</hi>, 7200 CR 603, Bushnell, ☏ +1 352 793-4781 . 8AM to sundown.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Judah P. Benjamin Confederate Memorial at Gamble Plantation Historic State Park</hi>, 3708 Patten Avenue, Ellenton, ☏ +1 941 723-4536 . 8AM to sunset.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lake Manatee State Park</hi>, 20007 State Road 64 East, Bradenton, ☏ +1 941 741-3028 . 8AM to sunset.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Madira Bickel Mound State Archaeological Site</hi>, 955 Bayshore Drive, Terra Ceia, ☏ +1 941 723-4536 . 8AM to sunset.</item>
</list>


<head>Go next</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="East%20Central%20Florida">East Central Florida</ref></item>
</list>
</text>
