<text id="autogum_academic_doc234" title="Combination of Aerial, Satellite, and UAV Photogrammetry for Mapping the Diachronic Coastline Evolution: The Case of Lefkada Island" shortTile="combination-aerial" author="Konstantinos Nikolakopoulos, Aggeliki Kyriou, Ioannis Koukouvelas, Vasiliki Zygouri, Dionysios Apostolopoulos" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2220-9964/8/11/489/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Coastal areas are defined as those where an interface or a transition between land and sea exists. These areas constitute important and sensitive environments with significant complexity, which are, however, difficult to define due to their diversity in form and dynamics as well as to their spatial boundaries. </p>

<p>Although coastal areas account for 2% of the planet’s surface, they contain almost 10% of the Earth’s population. Coastal erosion is the wasting of land along the shoreline due to diverse natural or human causes, such as wave action, wave and tidal currents, high winds, earthquakes, landslides, dam construction, drainage, and other human-induced causes of erosion. Coastal urbanization pressure, rising sea levels, and the increasing frequency of storms and cyclones are also maximizing coastal erosion and putting people’s lives and properties at risk. Bird (1996) estimated that 70% of sandy shorelines are eroding. However, this research had no robust estimation of shoreline change rates because of the lack of constant and long-term monitoring. Thus, recent studies suggest a lower rate of constant erosion for the world’s sandy beaches, in the order of 24%. </p>

<p>The usefulness of remote sensing imagery has been practically proven in coastal erosion detection and mapping for many decades. Over the years, remote sensing imagery has been transforming as a result of the evolution of aerial platforms from airplanes and satellites to unmanned aerial vehicles (UAVs). The first attempts to map the coastal zone with aerial photography can be traced back to the 1920s, just after the termination of the First World War, during which the method of photogrammetry was first developed. From the outset, the advantages of aerial photos become obvious: they are easily interpreted, they cover large areas, and they offer the possibility to view and map in 3D and to perform very accurate photogrammetric measurements. In one characteristic example, diachronic aerial images, covering a period of forty years, were photogrammetrically processed for monitoring the shoreline evolution at the southern New Jersey coast. Additionally, aerial photographs were used to examine the role of the presence of <hi rend="italic">Posidonia oceanica</hi> on shoreline morphology changes in Sardinia, Italy and Corsica, France. </p>

<p>The next big step was the launch of the first satellites during the early 1970s. The launch of the Landsat series, despite its low spatial resolution, opened new horizons for coastal area mapping due to the existence of multispectral bands, the repeatability of the scenes captured, and the large area coverage. Landsat Thematic Mapper and Enhanced Thematic Mapper images from different years, covering a period of 25 years, were processed in order to map the shoreline changes in Egypt. Landsat imagery covering a 30-year period has been used for the continuous inspection of coastline changes in western Florida. Similar datasets have been interpreted for detecting changes of the shoreline in India, China, and Namibia. Furthermore, Landsat data, along with Google Earth images and aerial photographs, were processed in order to perform a diachronic survey of the evolution of the coastline in Lower Casamance and southern Gambia, Africa. The development of very high resolution (VHR) satellite sensors (i.e., Ikonos and Quickbird) around 2000 rebooted the use of remote sensing data in coastal monitoring. The new sensors present special characteristics, such as four to eight multispectral bands, programmability in image acquisition globally, high repeatability (between 24 to 72 h), and storage of the data in digital format. An automatic procedure for shoreline extraction from Ikonos images using a mean shift segmentation algorithm was proposed by Reference. More recently, Sekovski et al. processed a WorldView-2 multispectal image to portray the coastline by combining supervised and unsupervised image classification methods. In the last five years, the explosion of the commercial UAV market has opened new avenues in coastal monitoring, as described in Reference. UAVs present some obvious advantages for coastal surveying. These advantages include the best spatial resolution among all the other remote sensing surveys, a lower cost compared to all other ground or remote sensing surveys, potential to transmit the acquired photos to the remote controller, the ability to repeat acquisition in case something goes wrong, and very low security risks as the drones are unmanned. </p>

<p>As mentioned in the previous paragraph, different types of remote sensing data have been used in coastal environment applications. High resolution satellite data and air photos were used to monitor the coastline’s changes or to measure volume changes in coastal areas, sea surface temperatures, sea ice coverage, and coastal change processes. A review paper summarizing the remote processing methods performed in shoreline delineation has been presented. Recently, the use of UAVs for coastal monitoring was investigated in many studies. In one of these studies, UAV digital photogrammetry was applied in order to develop point clouds and 3D models of the coastal cliffs in East Sussex, monthly for a one-year period, in order to map their recession. UAV images and structure from motion (SfM) photogrammetry was also tested at Dongshan Island, China to map coastal changes. </p>
</text>
