<text id="autogum_voyage_doc121" title="Finnish national parks" shortTile="finnish-national" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=11620" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Finnish national parks</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.nationalparks.fi/en/nationalparks">Finnish National Parks</ref></hi> are found in most parts of the country. In addition to national parks some other protected areas are presented below, as well as national hiking areas and the wilderness areas of Finnish Lapland.</p>

<ref target="Finland">Finland</ref> has a diverse nature, with forests, fells, mires, bogs, lakes and islands featuring in many of the parks. In a few parks the interaction between Man and nature is a central theme. As Finland is sparsely populated, one can often be alone with nature in the less known parks and in remote areas even of popular parks.

<head>Understand</head>
<p>The parks are open to the public without any entry or hiking fees. Many have services such as marked hiking trails, cottages, goahtis and saunas for rent. The <ref target="right%20to%20access">right to access</ref> is usually somewhat restricted in the parks, but the offered free services should compensate that for most visitors. National parks and strict nature reserves are always on state owned land, but other protected areas may be on ground owned by other entities, even privately owned.</p>

<p>There are nature trails in most of the areas listed below. In nearly all but the smallest areas, there are locations for rest (with campfire sites and pit toilets) and in the bigger ones hiking trails and some lodging facilities (often lean-to shelters, in the north more commonly open wilderness huts, in popular areas also rental cabins).</p>

<p>Berry and mushroom picking is usually allowed, in regard to edible species. Taking anything else from the nature is usually forbidden in national parks and nature reserves. Dogs must be kept on leash with few exceptions; you may see people letting their dog free, but even a friendly dog can wreak havoc, especially among nesting birds.</p>

<p>Information is usually available in English, but some (such as most information boards along nature trails) may be in Finnish only, or Finnish and either Swedish or Sami.</p>

<p>Most of the really large parks are in the far north, in the Sami native region. Regulations of the parks try not to disturb the traditional livelihood of the Sami. Thus e.g. reindeer herding, hunting, fishing, taking wood for own needs and even driving are often allowed for the locals also where forbidden otherwise. The local population is sparse enough that this does not generally threaten the ecology of the areas.</p>

<head>National parks, hiking areas and wilderness areas</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">National parks</hi> are the prime destinations for those wanting to see Finnish nature other than normal countryside. They are always on state owned land where the nature is deemed to be of general interest as a sight or for education. As the national parks are always also nature conservation areas there are restrictions to the <ref target="right%20to%20access">right to access</ref>: collecting stones, plants (other than edible mushrooms and berries) or insects is usually forbidden, wild camping is allowed only in certain areas and entry to some locations may be restricted. Pets may not be kept loose. Services, such as trails, shelters and campfire places more than compensates for this for most visitors. Acquaint yourself to the rules of the park in question, especially if you are not just walking marked trails. The parks are maintained by <hi rend="italic">Mets채hallitus</hi>, the Finnish forestry administration. </p>

<p>The <hi rend="bold">national hiking areas</hi> are specifically for hiking and for acquainting oneself to the nature of the region, offering quite large versatile and at least seemingly unspoiled areas. The nature may not be untouched but at least the forestry should be invisible for the trekker. There is good infrastructure, such as hiking trails, campfire places and lean-to and cooking shelters. Most hiking aseas have also accessible nature trails. The <ref target="right%20to%20access">right to access</ref> also usually applies. The areas are maintained by Mets채hallitus.</p>

<p>The <hi rend="bold">wilderness areas</hi> were established in 1991 to preserve their wilderness character, the Sami culture and the Sami natural form of livelihood. There are twelve such areas, all of which are located in <ref target="Finnish%20Lapland">Lapland</ref>. The wilderness areas are not nature conservation areas and the <ref target="right%20to%20access">right to access</ref> usually applies in full (there may be local restrictions) but on the other hand they are planned to stay wilderness so there's very little infrastructure as well. There are few services in these areas themselves but often tourist businesses nearby may arrange some service on request. The wilderness areas usually lack any marked trails and therefore are of interest especially for experienced hikers who are used to making their own paths. If there are some marked trails, they cover only part of the area. If there are skiing routes in winter, only the markings are maintained, not the tracks themselves. The areas are maintained by Mets채hallitus.</p>

<p>These areas are all listed below.</p>

<head>Nature reserves and other areas</head>
<p>The selection below of nature reserves and other areas is somewhat arbitrary. The ones listed are deemed to be of interest also to the casual visitor, some as a destination in themselves, some worth a visit if you happen to pass by.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Recreation areas</hi> are usually maintained by the municipality. They may have good infrastructure like the national hiking areas, often also facilities for outdoor sports and sometimes camping sites and the like. They are not listed here, but may be mentioned in the city articles.</p>

<p>The <hi rend="bold">strict nature reserves</hi> are primarily for nature protection and research. Visiting a strict nature reserve usually require a written permission from Mets채hallitus, but some have trails inside them though. Hiking is completely restricted to these marked trails at least during the warmer part of the year. Larger reserves may have other infrastructure, such as pit toilets and shelters for rest and overnight stays (often just outside the protected area itself). As the right to access is severely restricted, you always should check the rules of the individual area. Open strict nature reserves are mostly small, some suitable for a trip of a few hours, some for a weekend, but there are also bigger areas, an extreme being the Kevo strict nature reserve with a 64 km trail.</p>

<p>Entry to <hi rend="bold">bird nesting areas</hi> is prohibited in the bird nesting season, but there may be towers for bird watching and trails and other service in the neighbourhood or in less sensitive parts of the area. The <hi rend="bold">seal protection areas</hi> may be closed for public year round.</p>

<p>There are also many areas for protection of specific types of nature or specific features of the nature, such as <hi rend="bold">mire</hi>, <hi rend="bold">old-growth forest</hi> and <hi rend="bold">esker</hi> protection areas. These typically have no restrictions relevant for visitors, other than on any land, but you should probably be careful about not causing erosion or wildfire and not to harm plants and wildlife.</p>
</text>
