<text id="autogum_voyage_doc458" title="Samundri" shortTile="samundri" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=148743" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Samundri</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Samundri</hi> (Urdu, Punjabi: سمندری) is in Faisalabad District of <ref target="Northern%20Punjab">Northern Punjab</ref>, <ref target="Pakistan">Pakistan</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Samundri</hi> is 45 km away from <ref target="Faisalabad">Faisalabad</ref>. Samundri is home to a major grain, whole corn and sugar market.</p>

<p>Samundri is known for its custom truck painting business an for its sugar cane and other agriculture products.</p>
<p>Samundri was on a major trade route during the reign of Sher Shah Suri. The present site of Samundri city was founded in 1887 as Chak No. 533 G.B. Later it was renamed Samundri because of three Hindu mandirs in the area. The word Seh means Three in Persian and a Mandir is Sanskrit word for a temple. In 1887 there were three Hindu shrines in this area but now what remains of them houses the Government Primary School No 4.</p>
<head>Talk</head>
<p>Major language used in Samundri is Punjabi. Some educated people use Urdu &amp; English. Every one can understand Urdu.</p>

<head>By Bus</head>
<p>You can get into <ref target="Samundri">Samundri</ref> city by any of the following three main roads:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Faisalabad">Faisalabad</ref> road</item>
<item> <ref target="Okara">Okara</ref> road</item>
<item> <ref target="Rajana">Rajana</ref> road</item>
</list>


<head>Get around</head>
<p>There are many colonies and villages around the city.</p>

<p>Generally getting around is a pretty experience, you get to see a lot more on foot.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Taxis:</hi> Taxis in Khurrianwala are abundant, popular and generally safe. You can find them at Taxi Stand to travel to nearby village or Faisalabad. Prices will be higher at night. It is always advisable to agree the fare before travelling. The cost may go up for foreigners.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Car hire:</hi> Car hire is also a good way of getting around. Although road signs and directions are only available in Faisalabad, due to Khurrianwala being a town, It is easy to find your way around.</item>
</list>


<head>See</head>
<p>Clock Tower</p>
<p>Parks</p>
<p>Bazaar</p>

<head>Do</head>
<p>Gymnasium</p>
<p>Shopping in <ref target="Almaxi%20center">Almaxi center</ref> and <ref target="City%20Mall%20Plaza">City Mall Plaza</ref>.</p>
<p>Dinner at special hotels.</p>
<p>Sports and different Games.</p>

<head>Buy</head>
<p>There are four main bazaars in Samundri around the clock tower.</p>
<p>Besides this it has many markets related to these main bazaars.</p>
<p>Anarkali Bazaar is the main commercial market of the city, and <ref target="Jinnah%20Market">Jinnah Market</ref> is the oldest.</p>
<p>Other markets in the city include</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Katchery Bazaar,</item>
<item> Mandi Bazaar,</item>
<item> Nehar Bazaar,</item>
<item> Qasim Bazaar,</item>
<item> Kashmiri Bazaar,</item>
<item> Sunny Plaza and Chaki Bazaar.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat and drink</head>
<p>Eateries in Samundri feature Punjabi food, including the staples of biryani, samosas, pakoras, naan and haleem any where from the bazaars and market s.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sweets:</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ice Cream:</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Restaurant:</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Biryani/Pilaow:</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Samosas &amp; Dahi Bale:</hi></item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>
<p>In <ref target="Samundri">Samundri</ref> city many old and modern holels are situated.</p>
<p>Tashqand hotel is on <ref target="Rajana">Rajana</ref> mor.</p>
<p>Bandhan hotel and marriage hall is on <ref target="Faisalabad">Faisalabad</ref> road.</p>

<head>Connect</head>
<p>The area code for Faisalabad is 41. To dial from within Pakistan, dial 041-xxxxxxx. To dial from outside Pakistan 092-42-xxxxxxx.</p>
<head>Stay safe</head>

<p>In the case of an emergency, call police by <hi rend="bold">15</hi> from any landline phone. If you are using a cellphone, dial 911 for police rescue.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ambulance Access</hi> To get an ambulance in case of an emergency, dial 115 from any landline or cellphone.</item>
</list>


<p>If you find yourself in serious trouble and need any type of emergency rescue or help then to dial <hi rend="bold">1122</hi>. The name of the emergency service is "Rescue 1122".</p>

<head>Go next</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Okara">Okara</ref> (اوکاڑہ)</item>
<item> <ref target="Gojra">Gojra</ref> (گوجرہ)</item>
<item> <ref target="Rjana">Rjana</ref> (رجانہ)</item>
</list>
</text>
