<text id="autogum_voyage_doc456" title="Cross country skiing" shortTile="cross-country-skiing" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=8557" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Cross country skiing</head>


<p><hi rend="italic">Cross country skiing</hi> is an efficient way of travelling long distances across snow. The skis are narrower than downhill and slalom skis, and the poles are longer to increase propulsion. Cross country is possible in groomed trails or in untouched snow, the latter often referred to as ski touring or back country skiing. Skis to go outside of the tracks tend to be a bit wider than the skis you use in tracks, to help you to float better in the snow outside of the tracks. Boots for back country skiing are usually made of leather and boots for groomed trails are usually made of synthetic flexible fabric.</p>

<p>Cross country skiing is a good exercise for the whole body and as intense cardio training is an alternative to jogging. Cross country can also be variation at a ski resort or as a means to get to the true wilderness in wintertime.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Cross country skiing is the original form of skiing and was developed as a common mode of transport in Northern Europe. For many people in the <ref target="Nordic%20Countries">Nordic Countries</ref>, "skiing" still means cross country skiing and is widely practiced for exercise or recreation. The word "ski" originates from Old Norwegian and is still used in the wide original meaning - a piece of wood. Unlike in English it is not a verb in Norwegian, only a noun. Instead, in Norwegian and Swedish expressions like "ski hiking" or "ski racing" are used. </p>

<p>There are two different techniques for competitive skiing cross country: "classic" and "freestyle", where the former means mostly gliding forward with the skis in the tracks, while the latter resembles skating. In deep fresh snow classic is the only feasible way, likewise if there is no space besides the tracks on a prepared route. Routes with groomed tracks often offer space for both. If the temperature has varied around the freezing point (0°C, 32°F) there may be hard snow on or near the surface, allowing the skating technique in fields. Frozen lakes and rivers with thin snow cover also invite to this. Competitive skiers use special equipment for freestyle or "skate skiing". Recreational and back country skiing use both techniques depending on the terrain and snow quality. Freestyle or skating is easier with light skis. Skating creates superior speed on hard, even surfaces.</p>

<p>In deep loose snow speeds are low, comparable to slow walking, but in open terrain usually faster than with snowshoes and another world compared to walking in that snow without equipment, if the skis are adequate. In more compact snow, or snow with a frozen layer close to the surface, skiing is usually somewhat faster than when walking on bare ground. With tracks or ideal conditions speeds are comparable to running, sometimes considerably faster; winner times on 50 km classic in the <ref target="https://english.finlandiahiihto.fi">Finlandia race</ref> are 2–2.5 hours.</p>

<p>Classical skiing is based on the principle of traction or friction to allow the backward kick. In groomed tracks, traction is usually achieved with grip wax (a sticky substance applied to the mid part of the ski), while in the back country traction is also achieved with a waxless ski sole or with a removable "skin". The mid part of the ski should touch the track firmly when kicking, but rise when gliding, which means the skis have to be chosen to fit your weight. Some skis are more forgiving, which is an advantage when having a backpack that might be more or less heavy. There are also differences in how carefully the ski has to be prepared (waxed) for the specific kind of snow facing you on a route. </p>

<p>There is a trade-off for length and width of the skis: long and wide skis are good in thick loose snow in open terrain, but long skis are cumbersome in woods, bushes and steep hills and extremely wide skis may not fit in prepared tracks (also some bindings may be problematic).</p>

<p>When getting the equipment, be prepared to choose between several options depending on what you are going to do and what you are prepared to pay (at least in specialist shops, others may offer only one kind). The skis, bindings, boots and poles may be optimized for either classic or skate skiing, for tracks or for true cross-country with deep loose snow, for mostly flat terrain or offering a possibility also to downhill skiing with the telemark technique. Skis, bindings and boots should match and are often sold as a package; consider whether you want to be able to replace some without replacing all of them.</p>

<p>Skiing downhill, in tracks and in untouched snow are very different experiences. Do not expect the thrills of one when performing another. And while some techniques are easy to adopt to another environment, there is much to be learnt for somebody lacking experience in the current one.</p>

<head>Ski types by purpose</head>
<p>There are rough categories of skis for different purposes. The division here may not be universal and there may be compromises, but you should probably decide which types make sense for you. The skis for different purposes and techniques differ in length, width, stiffness and possibly other aspects. If there is a chance you will ski in tracks, in loose snow (other than downhill) or in mountains, try to find a ski that is adequate in all your uses. In wilderness backpacking, the important thing is not to get the best possible performance, but not to have a situation where the ski makes you miserable – avoid the extremes.</p>

<p>Also bindings and poles differ by intended use and skiing boots are usually made to fit one specific model of binding (there are often two big brands with different bindings for any type of ski, and possibly many obsolete designs). Bindings differ, in addition to usability for a specific type of skiing, by how easily frozen snow can stuck the fastening mechanism, to what extent they can be repaired in the field etc. There may be variations in this respect between bindings that fit the same boot.</p>

<p>A traditional all-round ski is about as long as the user with a raised arm. This length allows turning on the spot (after some training). Much longer skis are clumsy in dense wood and going downhill. Somewhat shorter skis are easier to handle for the beginner, in dense wood and in steep terrain. The corresponding poles reach from the ground to the armpit.</p>

<p>The width of old wooden skis was about 5–10 cm (2–4"). Machine made tracks allow up to , which is worth taking into consideration. Wider skis can be made shorter and still carry the user in loose snow (and allow more curvature for going downhill).</p>

<p>The stiffness is usually chosen so that the ski touches the ground under the foot when the user's weight is put on it, but not when the weight is evenly on both skis. This allows effective skiing in tracks as the rougher middle part touches the track only when kicking, but using a gliding-one-way-only structure a less stiff ski can do its job.</p>
</text>
