<text id="autogum_interview_doc901" title="part0_Interview with Reggie Bibbs on his life with neurofibromatosis" shortTile="partinterview-reggie" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-28" dateModified="2010-04-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Reggie_Bibbs_on_his_life_with_neurofibromatosis" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Interview with Reggie Bibbs on his life with neurofibromatosis</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, December 14, 2007</hi></p>
<head id="Infobox:_What_is_neurofibromatosis?"><hi rend="bold">Infobox: What is neurofibromatosis?</hi></head>
<p>Neurofibromatosis (NF) is a genetic condition causing benign tumors (neurofibromas) to grow along certain types of nerves and, in addition, it can affect the development of bones or skin. There are several variants of the disease but type 1 and type 2 NF account for the vast majority of cases.</p>
<p>The disease manifestations can vary from very mild to severe. Major symptoms include growths on and under the skin; skin pigmentations called <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/café%20au%20lait%20spots">café au lait spots</ref> in type 1; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/acoustic%20nerve">acoustic nerve</ref> tumors and consequent hearing loss in type 2. Growths can affect nearly all parts of the body, and pressure on nearby structures can cause a wide variety of complications. There is a small risk that the tumors transform into malignant cancerous lesions.</p>
<p>NF is one of the most common single-gene human diseases; around 1 in 2,500-4,000 live births are affected by NF-1, whereas NF-2 occurs in about 1 in 50,000-120,000. Both type 1 and 2 are <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/autosomal%20dominant">autosomal dominant</ref> conditions, meaning that only one copy of the mutated gene need be inherited to pass the disorder. A child of a parent with neurofibromatosis and an unaffected parent will have a 50% chance of inheriting the disorder. The gene responsible for NF-1 and possibly NF-2 is thought to function as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/tumor%20suppressor">tumor suppressor</ref> gene.</p>
<p>In most cases of neurofibromatosis 1, patients can live normal and productive lives. In about 25-40% of patients there is an associated learning disability with or without <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ADHD">ADHD</ref>. In some cases of neurofibromatosis 2, the damage to nearby vital structures, such as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/cranial%20nerves">cranial nerves</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/brainstem">brainstem</ref>, can be life-threatening. When tumors are causing pain or disfiguration, surgery is thus far the only proven beneficial treatment option.</p>
<p>Reggie Bibbs is a 43-year-old-man living in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Houston">Houston</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Texas">Texas</ref>. Mr Bibbs was born with a genetic disease called <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/neurofibromatosis">neurofibromatosis </ref> (NF), which causes him to develop tumors on his body (see infobox on the right). NF can be a subtle disease, but in Bibbs' case it has left him with a disfigured face and deformed leg. But he is happy with the way he looks, and doesn't want to change his appearance to please other people. He has launched a successful campaign entitled "Just Ask", and that's just what <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> did in a video-interview.</p>
<p>The interview was prepared by <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Stevenfruitsmaak">Michaël Laurent</ref> with the help of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:NCurse">Bertalan Meskó</ref> (who has a popular genetics and web 2.0 blog). Their questions were sent to a close friend of Mr. Bibbs, Lou Congelio, who kindly conducted the interview.</p>
<head id="The_interview">The interview</head>
<head id="On_neurofibromatosis">On neurofibromatosis</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Reggie Bibbs</hi>: My name is Reggie Bibbs, I am 43 years old and I live in Houston, Texas.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wikinews: Can you explain to our readers in simple terms what exactly is neurofibromatosis?</hi></p>
</text>
