<text id="autogum_interview_doc474" title="part1_Interview with Ton Roosendaal about Elephants Dream and free content movies" shortTile="partinterview-ton" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-05-21" dateModified="2014-01-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Ton_Roosendaal_about_Elephants_Dream_and_free_content_movies" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>But, most importantly; the main target of our project was not only to create a 3D movie short, but to experiment with ways to improve the efficiency and quality of open source development. On this aspect only, this project was just a huge success, and the main reason for our  sponsors (the DVD pre-sale) to support it. I know they might have liked a cartoonish funny movie with furry animals better, but for that you get already pretty well served by the bigger 3D animation studios.:)</p>
<p>I'm the first to admit that - looking back especially - certain aspects worked out quite weakly; there's loose ends and questionable decisions,  
especially in story development and continuity. That's just the risk of doing experiments, and nothing I regret really. The five artists from our user community who were invited to make the movie were young people with no professional background in filmmaking. Their personal incentive to participate in this project was also to learn from it, and to create a good portfolio for their future career. I've witnessed them grow in competence in the past year enormously, something I'm incredibly proud of.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">On the technical level, the only major criticism I've seen of "Elephants Dream" is the character animation, especially in the opening scene -- many reviewers felt that the movements seemed a bit unnatural. Do you agree with these criticisms? If so, what do you think can be  done to improve on that level?</hi></p>
<p>Yeah, the challenge the artists set themselves - to use quite realistic personages - is also something that easily works against you. In many  
animation movies they introduce characters in the beginning in a way you get used to their specific characteristic movements, so you accept  
a certain level of non-realism easily. (Check the weird walk cycles in <hi rend="italic">The Incredibles</hi> for example). Another aspect is that we've started work on the first scenes, and ended with the last scenes. I can clearly see the animation quality increase, and that whilst the ending scenes were done in much less time due to time constraints.</p>
<p>We also didn't schedule to do 9.5 minutes of animation either….  Originally it was more like 6. But, it's always easier to look back to define the right decisions, eh?:)</p>
<p>I'm very happy with the reviews we got so far; luckily the movie was perceived as a professional quality product, and reviewed based on comparisons with what the big studios come up with. Even when we couldn't satisfy all these quality demands, it has luckily not been branded as a pathetic presumptuous attempt by amateurs!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Do you think there is hope for a full-length open movie project in the near future? Would the Blender Foundation be interested in such a project, or do you intend to continue focusing mainly on shorts?</hi></p>
</text>
