<text id="autogum_reddit_doc155" title="[No Spoilers] I never thought I’d say this but I hope the CW cancel’s arrow at this point. I can’t believe these showrunners, what the hell has happened to this show!" shortTile="-spoilers-never-thought" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-03-31" dateModified="2018-03-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/88huiu" speakerList="#Demetrius96, #MisterrAlex" speakerCount="2">
<head>[No Spoilers] I never thought I’d say this but I hope the CW cancel’s arrow at this point. I can’t believe these showrunners, what the hell has happened to this show!</head>
<sp who="#Demetrius96">
<p>It really hurts me to say this because Arrow was always one of my favorite shows. The only reason why I still watch it is because I’ve been invested in it since day 1. That’s why I really hope the show goes off the air unless it gets new showrunners because I just want to get put out of my misery. Uncle guggie and co completely destroyed this show beyond repair, and it really breaks my heart that arrow out of all the shows has dropped this low in quality when it was the one that gave us the rest of these CW shows. I’m just really emotionally hurt because this is a show that I invested 6 years into. I remember during the early days of arrow back in 2012 when I was still in high school, and used to get home and be so hyped for arrow to come on. But now, arrow is nothing more than a Batman ripoff and a disrespect to the characters, actors and fans. Moreover, Stephen amell, John Burrowman, Katie Cassidy, Willa Holland, and Manu Bennett were all completely disrespected by Uncle guggie and his team members. Most importantly Stephen amell’s character, Oliver Queen/Green Arrow has been treated very poorly lately. He’s become the side character of the show and he’s running out storylines for the writers to tell which is why we get the same reused storylines every season. For example, GA wanted by the cops, Oliver and diggle fighting, the team separating, Oliver complaining about how he can’t do something, next it’s can we have the room, and finally felicity gives him the prep talk. Felicity- Oliver this is not your fault, you can’t blame yourself Oliver- Felicity, this is my fault Felicity- Oliver everything is going to be fine just relax okay? Oliver with a cringe smile- “Felicity you always make things so easy” I’m pissed because that is not the show I know and love. These writers have literally turned arrow into a high school drama. Hell, the characters on riverdale act more mature than the arrow characters, and the show itself is better which is sad. All of those shitty showrunners need to be fired and replaced by someone who actually respect their fans and casts, and cares about the source material. Lastly, I’m just happy that I have black Lightning as my favorite CW show because it’s miles above arrow in terms of quality. The characters are realistic and relatable, The city of Freeland actually feels alive and not dead like arrow. They also show what life is like on the streets of freeland as an everyday civilian. Most importantly black Lightning is a liberal social justice worrier which is what Green Arrow supposed be on arrow but instead the showrunners would rather have him be a discount Batman because they don’t know how to write anything political even if their life depended on it. But anyways with all of that said, I’m done. Thank you! #RIP-ARROW</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#MisterrAlex">
<p>I used to be the same way about Arrow when it had its resurgence season last year, but this year it has just regressed to the max. It's not even because of Olicity either, that stuff has actually been more subdued surprisingly. I feel like the writers are aimless on what they want to do with Season 6, and it's gonna take a huge turnaround with Richard Dragon to redeem this season. It's not awful like Season 4 but it's rather pointless and there's nothing really to get excited about. </p>
<p>Meanwhile literally in a different department, Legends is killing it every week while Arrow is still stuck with a slow moving plot and conflicts that killed the side characters I actually liked.</p>
</sp>
</text>
