<text id="autogum_interview_doc569" title="part0_Interview with Mathew Njenga, City Council candidate for Wards 2 &amp; 6 in Brampton, Canada" shortTile="partinterview-mathew" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-05" dateModified="2008-10-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Mathew_Njenga%2C_City_Council_candidate_for_Wards_2_%26_6_in_Brampton%2C_Canada" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Interview with Mathew Njenga, City Council candidate for Wards 2 &amp; 6 in Brampton, Canada</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 5, 2006</hi></p>
<p>The upcoming <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brampton%20municipal%20election,%202006">2006 Brampton municipal election</ref>, to be held November 13, features an array of candidates looking to represent their wards in city council or the council of the Peel Region.</p>
<p>Wikinews contributor Nick Moreau contacted many of the candidates, including <hi rend="bold">Mathew Njenga</hi>, asking them to answer common questions sent in an email. This ward's incumbent is John A. Hutton; also challenging Hutton is Derrick Coke, Navdeep Gill, Jim Howell, Joyce Rodriguez, and Doug Whillans.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> List the three most important issues in your campaign.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> The three top issues for my campaign are crime, urban sprawl, and the environment.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What one election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Urban Sprawl – The city has grown so fast especially in Wards 2 and 6 that the infrastructure, recreation centers, libraries and roads are all seriously lagging behind. If we give our kids nothing to do they will end up falling in between the cracks.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What qualities or experiences do you possess, that make you more desirable than the incumbent? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I have worked, traveled and lived in many parts of the world and I have volunteered for the communities that I have lived in and gained a wealth of experience dealing with people from all corners of the world. Brampton represents the world in terms of diversity due to the recent influx of immigrants and my experience dealing with diverse communities make me a more desirable candidate for City Councilor in wards 2 and 6.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent your ward on council?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> The issues that affect Wards 2 and 6 range from the Environment, Urban Sprawl, Business Development, Crime and Fair representation .My understanding of these issues in wards 2 and 6 and associated insights place me at a vantage point to address them for our common good in Brampton.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Of the decisions made by council since the last election, which one would you have changed, and why?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Since the last election, council issued a lot of construction permits for residential construction and that has had a terrible impact on the communities in Wards 2 and 6. In the last five years, the traffic congestion has been unreal, many residence in wards 6 have to travel far to get to a recreational center because non were build to accommodate all the new residents. Our students study in trailers because the schools construction was lagging or the buildings weren't big enough to house all the students. Residential home construction is a good thing but it has to be controlled.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Currently, I volunteer for an after school Basket Ball Program that's put up by Stone Church Community in Wards 6 for free on Tuesday night at Fletchers Meadow. We can only accommodate 50 students and each evening we have to turn away many willing participants because of lack of space. The lack of a recreation center accessible to the youth demonstrates the lack of vision and forethought in community planning by council.</p>
</text>
