<text id="autogum_academic_doc356" title="Control Strategy of BESS for Providing Both Virtual Inertia and Primary Frequency Response in the Korean Power System" shortTile="control-strategy" author="Woo  Yeong Choi, Kyung  Soo Kook, Ga  Ram Yu" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/21/4060/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Application of BESS for Frequency Response Service in the Korean Power System</head><head> 2.1. Frequency Control in the Korean Power System</head>
<p>
As the frequency is a major parameter indicating the balance between generation and demand of a power system, it is controlled in the Korean power system by providing frequency control services. The frequency control services consist of primary and secondary frequency control, which are provided by the resources’ local responses and the automatic generation control (AGC) central response, respectively, as shown in Table 1. </p>

<p>The primary frequency control is the frequency response provided mainly by the generator’s governor, and ESS was permitted to participate in the primary frequency control service in 2015. Table 2 summarizes the requirements for providing the frequency response service defined in the Korean electricity market rule. </p>

<p>In addition, in the Korean power system, the frequency response is evaluated by using two indices, the speed droop and the response quantity. The speed droop is evaluated by calculating the ratio of the responding amount of a generator power to the frequency change in percentage. The responding quantity, which is defined as the governor free response quantity (GFRQ), is evaluated by the difference between outputs before and after the disturbance using the Equation (1):

(1)

where  is the time of a disturbance,  is the time of reaching 59.8 Hz after the disturbance, and  is the power at time . </p>

<p>The secondary frequency control is provided by participating resources’ responses to the AGC frequency control signal, which are determined by the energy management system (EMS). All generators, except for the nuclear generators, participate in the secondary frequency control service. ESS was permitted to participate in the secondary frequency control service in 2016, but it is not yet participating. </p>

<head> 2.2. BESS for Providing Frequency Response in the Korean Power System</head>
<p>
KEPCO announced a plan to install MW-scale BESS to provide a frequency response in 2015. According to the plan, a BESS of 376 MW is being operated commercially to provide the frequency response by KEPCO in 13 substations. <figure>Figure 1</figure> shows each location and the capacity of installed BESS in Korea. </p>

<p>The main purpose of MW-scale BESS is substituting the existing primary frequency response reserves from a thermal generator, which has low generation cost. By doing that, the thermal generator can increase the generation level, and the system marginal price (SMP) will be reduced by excluding high-cost generators in the electricity market. Furthermore, the BESS can provide or absorb the power within 200 ms, considering the communication delay. Therefore, the BESS can provide the needed frequency response by injecting the power into the power system just after the disturbance. </p>

<p>Presently, the proposed control strategy has been implemented in a 376-MW BESS installed at 13 substations to provide both virtual inertia response and primary frequency response. The proposed control strategy is loaded in the individual control unit, where four power conversion systems (PCS) are dispatched, as shown in <figure>Figure 2</figure>. Additionally, there is another control algorithm upstream of the individual control unit. However, this paper focused on the more indicative control strategy-related frequency response. </p>
</text>
