<text id="autogum_interview_doc175" title="part3_Wikinews interviews Andy Martin, U.S. Republican Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-07-28" dateModified="2015-08-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Andy_Martin%2C_U.S._Republican_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : <hi rend="bold">Individually, what is your opinion of some of your fellow candidates for the Republican Party presidential nomination, notably <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mitt_Romney">Mitt Romney</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Michele_Bachmann">Michele Bachmann</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ron_Paul">Ron Paul</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Herman_Cain">Herman Cain</ref>? Why do you feel you would be a better nominee for the party than any of them?</hi></item></list>
<p>Martin: I have occasionally written brief profiles and short commentaries on some of my opponents. Those columns are posted on my blogs. I refer you to those comments and any that appear in the future (as no doubt they will).</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : <hi rend="bold">How often do you campaign, and how has the campaign been received by people you meet?</hi></item></list>
<p>Martin: I campaign every day. I would say I have received an extraordinarily warm and positive response wherever I have campaigned. I place my campaign in the top 10, i.e. among the top 10 Republican presidential candidates nationally. While most of the media attention is focused on the top 5, some of the top 5 are tottering and will not survive.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : <hi rend="bold">Which other candidates would you also place in the top 10?</hi>
<p>Martin: the usual ones, so long as they have actually announced. I don’t count unannounced ones.</p></p></p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : <hi rend="bold">Have you received any notable endorsements?</hi></item></list>
<p>Martin: I receive the “endorsement” of ordinary Americans every day in my campaign. That is the only endorsement that counts.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : <hi rend="bold">Do you feel you can still win the nomination despite not receiving an invitation to any of the presidential debates?</hi></item></list>
<p>Martin: I have a game plan and strategy to try to win, and we are executing that game plan well. I am very satisfied with the progress of the campaign. Actually, by excluding me from some of the debates to date, the media have been the losers. Some of the candidates they are showcasing are imploding, thereby brightening my prospects to move up on the presidential leader board.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : <hi rend="bold">In your estimation approximately how many supporters does your campaign have?</hi>
<p>Martin: I can’t give an exact number, nor would I if we tallied supporters that way. But it clear my campaign is gaining altitude and other candidates are faltering. We are executing our game plan; others rather obviously are not.</p></p></p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : <hi rend="bold">If you do not win the Republican nomination, would you consider running for a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Third%20party%20(United%20States)">third party</ref>'s nomination?</hi></item></list>
<p>Martin: No.</p>
<head id="Political_views">Political views</head>
<p>On his campaign website, Martin describes himself as a supporter of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second%20Amendment%20to%20the%20United%20States%20Constitution">Second Amendment to the United States Constitution</ref> in opposition to stringent <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gun_control">gun control</ref>. He opposes <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American%20Clean%20Energy%20and%20Security%20Act">Cap and Trade legislation</ref> and mandated health care coverage. He identifies himself as a proponent of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First%20Amendment%20to%20the%20United%20States%20Constitution">First Amendment to the United States Constitution</ref> and a "corruption fighter". He writes about his issue positions on his personal blog.</p>
<p>Martin was asked to elaborate his answers on some of the questions, but did not respond. He labeled certain questions as "bizarre".</p>
</text>
