<text id="autogum_interview_doc218" title="part2_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green candidate Martin Hyde, Ottawa West-Nepean" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-24" dateModified="2016-07-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Green_candidate_Martin_Hyde%2C_Ottawa_West-Nepean" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">What are your views on the mixed member proportional representation (MMP) referendum?</hi></p>
<p>My view is that the MMP system is better for everyone.</p>
<p>In the short term it is obviously better for smaller parties such as the Greens. In the 2006 federal election the Green Party of Canada won 4.5% of the vote. Fairness would seem to dictate that out of the 308 seats in the House of Commons, around 14 should be Green MPs. Yet there is not one Green MP in the House. Nearly 700,000 Canadians voted Green. Not one of them is represented by their party in the House of Commons.</p>
<p>In the 2003 Ontario election the Green Party only won 2.8% of the vote. Under the proposed MMP system we would not have been able to appoint an MPP. Yet we would only need an additional 0.2% to be eligible for, presumably, three to four MPPs. Clearly, this would be good for the Green Party of Ontario.</p>
<p>In the longer term it would also be good for the larger parties, and for those who vote for them. It’s true that their power stands to be diluted somewhat by parties that have broad support across the province, which will impair their ability to pass the laws they want today. But we all have to live under those laws, and in a democracy that means we should be represented in their creation. When we’re not, those laws begin to lack legitimacy.</p>
<p>In 2003, 43.2% of eligible voters in Ontario did not show up at the polls. There is something wrong when almost half of the people in our province who can have a say in the rules we live under choose not to. There are likely many reasons why people don’t show up, but one is certainly that many people feel their vote does not really count. It has no influence. This will be a problem for all of us in the long run because, the fewer people who participate in the creation of our laws, the less legitimate those laws will appear to be to an increasing number of people. When we have an opportunity to strengthen the foundations on which our society rests, we should take it.</p>
<p>A concern I’ve heard about MMP is that it could result in a large number of unelected MPPs. To understand this concern, consider this example.</p>
<p>You have a legislature with 100 seats. Party X wins 20% of the provincial vote, but only 15 seats. Under MMP Party X will be allowed to appoint five MPPs from their list to bring them up to 20 seats. The concern is that those five MPPs are not elected, but appointed from a list, and that they will not be responsible for any particular riding.</p>
</text>
