<text id="autogum_interview_doc435" title="part2_Ahmedi of Iran&amp;apos;s PDKI discusses Kurdistan&amp;apos;s general strike and the democratic future of Iran" shortTile="partahmedi-irans" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-07-15" dateModified="2009-11-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ahmedi_of_Iran%27s_PDKI_discusses_Kurdistan%27s_general_strike_and_the_democratic_future_of_Iran" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Loghman Ahmedi</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> The strike was mainly organized to mark the 20th anniversary of the assassination of the Kurdish leader and former General-Secretary of the PDKI, Dr. Abdul Rahman Ghassmlou. Every year, since the assassination of Dr. Ghassemlou 20 years ago by the Islamic Republic of Iran, the PDKI has called on the Kurdish nation in Iranian Kurdistan to commemorate Dr. Ghassemlou and at the same time condemn the Islamic regime’s policies of assassination.</p>
<p>But it is at the same time an expression of solidarity and support for the people of Iran that stands up against the Islamic Republic and fights for freedom, democracy and equality.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What role should the Kurdish exile community take in the Iranian unrest - is it better to return now and join the strike against Ahmedinejad, or to give support from abroad? If the latter, how can the Kurdish diaspora best help the Kurdish people in Iran?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Loghman Ahmedi</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Returning to take part in protests would make them easy targets for the regime; the Kurdish diaspora should instead work to raise awareness about the situation in Kurdistan and Iran by, for example, demonstrating, writing letters to government officials in the countries they live in, and so on.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Given the Iranian leadership's past propensity for assassinations, do you think <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mir-Hossein%20Mousavi">Mousavi</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mehdi%20Karroubi">Karroubi</ref> et al are at personal risk in taking part in protests against Ahmedinejad?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Loghman Ahmedi</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> To my knowledge, both Mousavi and Karroubi have indirectly made clear that they will not urge people to take to the streets if they don’t get permission from the regime, hence the possibility that they would take part in future demonstrations is unlikely.</p>
<p>I do not think that the regime will assassinate Mousavi or Karroubi; it would be strategically unwise. It would demonstrate that the regime’s own figures have turned against the Islamic Republic and assassinating any of them would turn them into martyrs and could be used by the peoples of Iran as a pretext to stage violent protests.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Finally, what's the best strategy for the uprising against the Ahmedinejad? How can the Kurds win?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Loghman Ahmedi</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I firmly believe that the uprising is not only targeting Ahmedinejad but rather the regime as a whole. That is not to say that the protesters are homogeneous; different groups have different approaches to what should be done. However, it is imperative that all the different groups that are opposing the regime reach a consensus on a common strategy to bring about real democracy in Iran. For this to be possible, a multinational federal democracy must be recognized as the future model for Iran. Given this, an alliance could be created that can stage protests and other forms of political activity across the country rather than the major cities. In such a scenario, the regime will have greater difficulty to suppress the organized resistance of the peoples of Iran, as it did recently.</p>
</text>
