<text id="autogum_interview_doc362" title="part8_Creator of website satirizing Glenn Beck on winning domain name case" shortTile="partcreator-website" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-11-09" dateModified="2019-02-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Creator_of_website_satirizing_Glenn_Beck_on_winning_domain_name_case" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>When Beck first filed his WIPO action, I was ready to just give in to make things easier for myself.  Surrender is always the easiest thing, isn't it? But, I started to think about what the case meant.  It did occur to me that if Beck succeeded, that his very predictions that he gives on the air -- about international bodies threatening our free speech rights -- would come true.  I then realized that the case was about much bigger principles.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Are you happy with your decision to turn over the "www.glennbeckrapedandmurderedayounggirlin1990.com" domain name to Beck?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">E-H</hi>: Absolutely yes. For one, the meme is already out there. In one sense, the job of the meme is over and done with - it has gotten people to talk about the issue, and that was one of the primary goals. Another primary goal was to foster that sense of community, and to provide a release valve for the frustration so many have with Glenn Beck, and others like him. Of course, we want to keep the entire thing going, but we can do that without the statement version of the domain.</p>
<p>That domain gets a LOT of traffic.  I could have taken down the domain, put up a pay per click site, and made a heck of a lot of money by harnessing the advertising revenue from the site.  It was in my financial best interest to do that - but this was always about free speech - not about profit.</p>
<p>I absolutely think giving him the domain sends the message that I want to send - this wasn't personal, it was political.  Beck made it about Free Speech principles, and I think I did my part to stand up for those principles.  But, keeping this particular domain wouldn't have advanced that cause any further than it had already been advanced.</p>
<p>I wanted to give him the domain to demonstrate the fact that my interest in fighting the WIPO case was purely a matter of principle.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Do you have any thoughts or advice for other potential creators of satirical parody websites who may undergo a similar legal process in the future?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">E-H</hi>: If you decide to make a political satire site, do it. Be prepared to stick it out. Get a good lawyer who is committed to First Amendment principles, who knows how to handle this kind of thing, but get one who will teach you and make sure that you are able to make informed decisions.</p>
<p>There were a lot of lawyers to choose from, but Mr. Randazza seemed to be the best guy for this kind of case.  His First Amendment credibility is unshakeable, his knowledge of this area of law is fantastic, but he has a reputation for managing his clients' interests really well. He didn't tell me what to do, he taught me what the law was, he gave me options and choices, and let me make informed decisions.  In a process like this, it is easy to feel like things are out of your control.  Make sure your lawyer teaches you about what you can control.  It will make you feel a lot more comfortable.</p>
</text>
