<text id="autogum_academic_doc415" title="Systematic Culturomics Shows that Half of Chicken Caecal Microbiota Members can be Grown in Vitro Except for Two Lineages of Clostridiales and a Single Lineage of Bacteroidetes" shortTile="systematic-culturomics" author="Magdalena Crhanova, Daniela Karasova, Helena Juricova, Jitka Matiasovicova, Eva Jahodarova, Tereza Kubasova, Zuzana Seidlerova, Alois Cizek, Ivan Rychlik" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-2607/7/11/496/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Assessing gut microbiota composition is currently relatively simple due to recent developments in DNA sequencing techniques. Consequently, various studies have associated the composition of gut microbiota with age, disease or behaviour. However, the vast majority of published data are based on epidemiological studies and correlation analyses, which may not necessarily prove the causative link between the tested intervention, microbiota composition and host response. In addition, the correlation analysis cannot distinguish between the cause and the consequence—is the change in gut microbiota composition the cause of the behavioural change or its consequence? </p>

<p>Studies administering defined bacteria, followed by verification of their presence in the intestinal tract and their association with tested characteristics, are much less frequent and most frequently involve the administration of <hi rend="italic">Lactobacillaceae</hi> family members. However, <hi rend="italic">Lactobacillaceae</hi>, though common in the small intestine, form only a small fraction of gut microbiota in the distal parts of the intestinal tract like the caecum, microbiota of which is formed by hundreds of anaerobic bacterial species different from <hi rend="italic">Lactobacilli</hi>. Because of this, we and others have initiated systematic culturing of gut anaerobes to have them available for whole genome sequencing and subsequent experiments. </p>

<p>Soon after we formed an initial laboratory collection of chicken gut anaerobes, we compared the isolates from the collection with those commonly found in chicken intestinal tract. In other words, we were interested whether there were any chicken gut anaerobes which were difficult to culture. Other studies addressed the same question by comparing the bacterial composition in original faecal or caecal samples with those in nutrient broth after culture. These studies concluded that between 50 to 90% of total gut microbiota could be cultured in vitro if the appropriate culture conditions are provided. Unfortunately, these studies did not perform phylogenetic analyses of the OTUs (operational taxonomic units) capable or incapable of in vitro growth. Therefore, it is not known whether the bacterial species resistant to in vitro growth are randomly distributed among known bacterial phyla, classes, orders, families, genera or species, or whether the microbiota members resistant to in vitro growth are clustered in particular lineages, which is exactly what we investigated in this study. Using a larger set of different culture conditions, the primary aim was to determine which bacterial lineages colonising the chicken caecum have not yet been cultured in vitro. Furthermore, the experimental design also enabled us to address secondary aims such as to which extent feed or food additives, therapeutics or drugs influence in vitro bacterial growth in complex microbial populations and what are the most selective culture conditions for particular taxa. Indirectly, such data also points towards possible functions of individual microbiota members in vivo. </p>
</text>
