<text id="autogum_interview_doc442" title="part0_CanadaVOTES: NDP candidate Michael McMahon running in Prince Edward—Hastings" shortTile="partcanadavotes-ndp" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-09-22" dateModified="2013-01-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CanadaVOTES%3A_NDP_candidate_Michael_McMahon_running_in_Prince_Edward%E2%80%94Hastings" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>CanadaVOTES: NDP candidate Michael McMahon running in Prince Edward—Hastings</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, September 26, 2008</hi></p>
<p>On October 14, 2008, Canadians will be heading to the polls for the federal election. <hi rend="bold">New Democratic Party candidate Michael McMahon</hi> is standing for election in <hi rend="bold">the riding of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prince%20Edward—Hastings">Prince Edward—Hastings</ref></hi>. McMahon moved to Windsor in 1951, getting a degree in education, teaching locally and in Papua New Guinea. He served as Branch President of the Ontario Secondary School Teachers' Federation (OSSTF), served on multiple of their major committees, and recently retired from the Hastings and Prince Edward District School Board.</p>
<p>Wikinews contacted Michael McMahon, to talk about the issues facing Canadians, and what they and their party would do to address them. Wikinews is in the process of contacting every candidate, in every riding across the country, no matter their political stripe. All interviews are conducted over e-mail, and interviews are published unedited, allowing candidates to impart their full message to our readers, uninterrupted.</p>
<p>Since being redefined in 2003, the riding includes the County of Prince Edward and the County of Hastings (except the City of Quinte West). Conservative Party member Daryl Kramp currently represents the riding, after beating a Liberal in 2004. Ken Cole of the Liberals and Alan Coxwell of the Greens are also running in the riding.</p>
<p>For more information, visit the campaign's official website, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Main_Page#External_links">listed below</ref>.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why are you running for political office, why at the federal level, why this party, and why in this riding?</hi></p>
<p>My political involvement grew from seeing the disparity between rich and poor in our wealthy country, and concern for our people who are not getting their fair share. I was attracted to the New Democratic Party because of the importance placed on the social issues, such as poverty, health care, education, housing and health of the environment. I joined the NDP when I decided to do something about the way things were going for average Canadians, and the Canada we all share. Our people, our Country, and our environment must always come before the interests of big corporations.</p>
<p>Only the Federal level can address these issues.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Previous to this campaign, have you been politically involved? How will you apply your previous work/volunteer/life experience to serving your constituents?</hi></p>
<p>This is my second campaign for MP. I have been involved with my union, OSSTF, for many years in various roles, including branch president.</p>
<p>I was a high school teacher for 30 years. This has given me a real insight into the people and families in our riding. I taught Science. I am a trained critical thinker with a good understanding of the realities of energy, environment, technology, and the economy. I am well suited to play a part in our shift from fossil fuels to a new sustainable energy currency. And I will be able to explain it.</p>
</text>
