<text id="autogum_reddit_doc001" title="Employer basically asking for free hours. Implies my termination when I question it. Is this how salary positions work?" shortTile="employer-basically" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-05-31" dateModified="2018-05-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8nlbwq" speakerList="#Poopdedooploop" speakerCount="1">
<head>Employer basically asking for free hours. Implies my termination when I question it. Is this how salary positions work?</head>
<sp who="#Poopdedooploop">
<p>I've been working a lower management position for a very large logistics company for about 2 years now. I walked in as a wage earner but showed a lot of skill with systems so was quickly moved into a salary position. My manager was promoted and the area was left in a limbo forcing me to step up and manage the area. I did this to the best of my ability but 3 other team members left shortly after leaving the area drastically under resourced. Despite my constant requests this be rectified to my operations manager (who was my old manager that was promoted) it was not actioned. Now the area is performing very badly and they've hired on a new manager for it who is impeccably lazy (more time on FB than anything in his day). I've been working 12 hour days 6 days a week to keep up with the areas demands as I now have my team backfilled and can start making some headway. However I am working 60+ hours a week and my contract states I am only being compensated for 38 hours of my time. I'm not normally a whinger about this stuff but my current manager does as little as 5 hours a day some days. Keep in mind there are no days in leiu or bonuses given at my company. So in a lunch with my site manager we were speaking pretty freely and he was thanking me for my efforts. Said my area would be lost without me and he knows the stress I'm under and to let him know if he can help at all. I decide to bring up the difficulty I'm having to motivate myself to work the huge hours at no personal benefit. That the lack of extra renumeration for my time makes me wonder if I should just hang the sense of it and spend that time with my family instead. He seemed to take it well and said he understood but then I was pulled into a meeting with the contract manager and asked why I was complaining about hours. I reiterated my statement to the contract manager and just said "I don't understand where my motivation is to work more than my 8 hour day" he tells me it should be my passion for my work. I reply with I am passionate about my work hence my hours and he implies in no uncertain terms that they will terminate my contract if I don't like as "there are hundreds of others out there that want my job". His whole idea seems to be that I'll throw away my time for free chasing the crumb of a managers title or they'll get rid of me. Is this normal in corporate situations? I have never really worked it and honestly it's leaving me feeling very taken advantage of and very much like I'd rather go back to a wage earner to ensure my time is properly compensated. At least I'd get paid all hours worked.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#Poopdedooploop">
<p>Thanks for all the replies guys. So the consensus is salary can be advantageous if the company makes it so but by and large most don't and therefore it means a dismal hourly rate compared to wages. </p>
<p>I think it's a simple fact of salary work isn't for me. I love the work but working 60 hours plus a week for only 38 hours pay is just not worth it for me. </p>
</sp>
</text>
