<text id="autogum_voyage_doc96" title="Tacoma" shortTile="tacoma" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=35031" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Tacoma</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://cityoftacoma.org/">Tacoma</ref></hi> in the <ref target="Washington%20%28state%29">state of Washington</ref>, is the state's second-largest city, with just under 200,000 residents.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Tacoma often gets a negative description reminiscent of the one given to <ref target="Oakland">Oakland</ref>, <ref target="California">California</ref>. These negative vibes are equally unrealistic and often come from those who have never lived in or even visited the city. While it has neither the tourist amenities of its neighbor <ref target="Seattle">Seattle</ref> to the north nor the suburban safety of <ref target="Olympia%20%28Washington%29">Olympia</ref> to the south, you can certainly spend a few pleasant days in Tacoma and see the city's dynamic art scene and its great ballet.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>The ( SEA ) is the nearest airport for commercial flights. It is 25 mi/40km north of Tacoma. <ref target="http://portseattle.org/seatac/">Sea-Tac airport</ref> serves much of the greater Seattle Metropolitan area and the Pacific NW. Options besides taxi/limo or rental car are:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sound Transit Rt #574</hi>. Daily express bus between Lakewood, Tacoma, Federal Way, <ref target="Kent%20%28Washington%29">Kent</ref>, SeaTac light rail station and the airport.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">ShuttleExpress</hi>, ☏ +1 425 981-7000 . Operates shared and private shuttle services between the airport and hotels &amp; residents within the Tacoma-Seattle-<ref target="Bellevue">Bellevue</ref>-<ref target="Everett%20%28Washington%29">Everett</ref> corridor and its vicinity. Catch them at the 3rd level of the parking garage. During the morning commute hours (7-10AM), it may not be best to take this transportation if you go to downtown Seattle unless you have a lot of baggage to take care of; the more spacious Link Light Rail trains will get you there for about the same duration or even quicker. Walk-ins are allowed for trips from the airport (shared vans only), reservations necessary for trips to the airport.</item>
</list>

 Downtown from $18.

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Capital Aeroporter</hi>, toll-free: +1-800-962-3579 . For areas mainly south of the airport (Tacoma, Olympia, <ref target="Auburn%20%28Washington%29">Auburn</ref>, Kent, <ref target="Chehalis">Chehalis</ref>, <ref target="Centralia%20%28Washington%29">Centralia</ref>, <ref target="Shelton%20%28Washington%29">Shelton</ref>).</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bremerton-Kitsap Aeroporter</hi>, (scheduled stop) Dennys Restaurant @ 5924 6th Ave (6th &amp; Pearl), ☏ +1 360 876-1737 . Connects the airport to Tacooma, <ref target="Gig%20Harbor">Gig Harbor</ref> and the <ref target="Kitsap%20Peninsula">Kitsap Peninsula</ref>. They go south on I-5 to Tacoma and over the Narrows Bridge along WA Hwy 16 to get to the Kitsap Peninsula rather than going across on the ferry from Seattle. They also have a separate run between the airport and the Lewis-McChord Joint Military Base. Be sure to have a valid DoD ID card to enter Lewis-McChord.</item>
</list>



<head>By car</head>
<p>Tacoma is along <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Interstate%205">Interstate 5</ref> (I-5),</hi> approximately 35 mi south of Seattle (35 min), 293 mi (5 hr) southwest of <ref target="Spokane">Spokane</ref>, and 143 mi (2.5 hr) north of <ref target="Portland%20%28Oregon%29">Portland</ref>.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> From <hi rend="bold">Interstate 5 (I-5)</hi> Tacoma is accessed from exits #136 ("Port of Tacoma") through #127 ("S Tacoma Way/WA-512 to Puyallup") along I-5. To get to downtown, exit off at the Interstate 705 off ramp at Exit 133, just beyond the Tacoma dome if going south from I-5, or continue along I-705 past downtown to Schuster Pkwy to get to old town, north Tacoma and the Ruston Way waterfront. Continue to the next exit along I-5 to 132B to get to WA-16 going west towards Gig Harbor, <ref target="Bremerton">Bremerton</ref> and for additional access to other parts of town. To get to Joint Base Lewis McChord continue south past WA-512 to exits #125 ("Bridgeport Way/McChord Field"), #123 ("Thorne Ln"), 122 ("Berkely Ave nearest access to Madigan Hospital and Camp Murray"), 120 ("Joint Base Lewis-McChord") which is the location of the main gate &amp; visitors center into the base, or 119 (Dupont-Steilacoom Rd). Access to the military base is controlled and a valid Dept. of Defense (DoD) ID and vehicle decal are required to be allowed through. Otherwise see the visitors center off of exit 120. Exits 119-125 will come first before getting into Tacoma if going north on I-5 from Olympia.</item>
<item> From <hi rend="bold">Interstate 90 (I-90)</hi> coming from eastern Washington exit off at WA-Hwy 18 at Exit # 25. Go south on WA Hwy 18 through Tiger Mountain, Convington, Maple Valley and Auburn to Federal Way where WA-18 merges into I-5. Follow signs to I-5 south to Tacoma.</item>
<item> From <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Kitsap%20Peninsula">Kitsap Peninsula</ref></hi> Go south on Hwy 3 and follow signs for "WA-16 EAST to Port Orchard - Tacoma". Continue south along WA-16 through Gig Harbor and across the Tacoma Narrows Bridge into Tacoma. There's a toll to cross the Narrows Bridge into Tacoma but no toll coming the other way into Gig Harbor. There are 5 exits into town from along WA-16 between the bridge and where the highway ends at I-5. Follows signs for I-5 "To Seattle" and exit at the next exit to I-705 to get downtown otherwise follow signs for I-5 south "To Portland" to get to the south or east part of town.</item>
</list>


<head>By bus</head>
<p>The bus station for Greyhound, Northwestern Trailways, Sound Transit, Intercity Transit, Pierce Transit &amp; Link Light Rail is at the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="http://www.piercetransit.org/transit-centers/">Tacoma Dome Station</ref></hi> Parking Garage Buildings at 510 - 610 E Puyallup Ave (facing E Puyallup Ave), between East E St and East G St, one block north of Freighthouse Square (2501 East D St). Greyhound, NW Trailways and a taxi stand are at the west building while Sound Transit, Intercity &amp; Pierce Transit buses are next door in front of the east building. The Link Light Rail to downtown Tacoma is at the opposite side of the parking buildings along E 25th, between the E Parking Garage Building and the Freighthouse Square building:</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Greyhound</hi>, Tacoma Dome Station, W Parking Bldg @ 510 E Puyallup Ave, ☏ +1 253 383-4621 , toll-free: +1-800-231-2222 . Travels primarily on Interstate 5 (Seattle, Tacoma, Olympia, Centralia, Kelso/Longview and Portland.) Passengers transfer in <ref target="Seattle%23By%20bus">Seattle</ref>, <ref target="Olympia_%28Washington%29%23By%20bus">Olympia</ref> or <ref target="Portland%20%28Oregon%29%23By%20bus">Portland</ref> to get to additional destinations.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Northwestern Trailways</hi>, Tacoma Dome Station, W Parking Bldg 510 E Puyallup Ave, ☏ +1 509 838-4029 , ✉ team@northwesterntrailways.com . Goes north to Seattle and Everett along I-5 and then east to Lake Stevens, <ref target="Leavenworth%20%28Washington%29">Leavenworth</ref>, <ref target="Wenatchee">Wenatchee</ref>, <ref target="Ephrata">Ephrata</ref>, Moses Lake Ritzville &amp; <ref target="Spokane%23by%20bus">Spokane</ref> along US Hwy 2 and I-90. In Tacoma they stop at both the Greyhound station and the Amtrak station down the road.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sound Transit</hi>, Tacoma Dome Station, E Parking Bldg @ 610 E Puyallup Ave, ☏ +1-888-889-6368 . Operates express routes between Lakewood, Tacoma &amp; Seattle.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="https://www.soundtransit.org/schedules/route/40_574">Rt #574</ref> <ref target="Seattle-Tacoma%20International%20Airport">Seattle-Tacoma International Airport</ref>, Kent-Des Moines Hwy (SR-516), S 272nd St, <ref target="Federal%20Way">Federal Way</ref>, Tacoma Dome &amp; Lakewood</item>
<item> <ref target="https://www.soundtransit.org/schedules/route/40_586">Rt#586</ref> Downtown Tacoma//UW Tacoma, Tacoma Dome, <ref target="Seattle/University%20District">University of Washington/U-District</ref>. Northbound only during morning rush hours and southbound only during afternoon rush hours. No stops in downtown Seattle</item>
<item> <ref target="https://www.soundtransit.org/schedules/route/40_594">Rt#590,594</ref> <ref target="Seattle/Downtown">Downtown Seattle</ref>, Tacoma Dome Station, Downtown Tacoma/UW Tacoma &amp; Lakewood. Rt 590 travels only between Downtown Tacoma, Tacoma Dome &amp; Downtown Seattle during weekday rush hours only.</item>
<item> <ref target="https://www.soundtransit.org/schedules/route/40_592">Rt#592</ref> <ref target="Seattle/Downtown">Downtown Seattle</ref>, Lakewood Park &amp; Ride, Lakewood Sounder, Dupont. Northbound only during morning rush hours and southbound only during afternoon rush hours. No stops in downtown Tacoma or Tacoma Dome.</item>
<item> <ref target="https://www.soundtransit.org/schedules/route/40_595">Rt#595</ref> <ref target="Seattle/Downtown">Downtown Seattle</ref>, Tacoma Community College (TCC), Gig Harbor, Purdy. Northbound only during morning rush hours and southbound only during afternoon rush hours. No stops in downtown Tacoma or Tacoma Dome.</item>
<item> <ref target="https://www.soundtransit.org/ride-with-us/stations/tacoma-link-light-rail-stations">Link Light Rail</ref> runs frequent trains from Freighthouse Square to downtown Tacoma (just north of 9th &amp; Commerce). The train goes by UW Tacoma, several museums, several downtown hotels and the downtown convention center. The stop is along E 25th between the parking garage buildings and the Freighthouse Square building.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">King County Metro</hi>, ☏ +1 206 553-3000 . Operates buses in and around Seattle and the surrounding cities and suburbs in King County. Nearest transfer points to King County Metro from Tacoma are in Auburn, Federal Way/NE Tacoma and the Tahlequah ferry terminal (<ref target="http://metro.kingcounty.gov/schedules/118/s0.html">Rt #118, 119</ref>) in the south end of Vashon Island.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Intercity Transit</hi>, Tacoma Dome Station, E Parking Bldg @ 610 E Puyallup Ave, ☏ +1 360 786-1881 , toll-free: +1-800-287-6348 . Operates express buses from downtown Tacoma and the Tacoma Dome Station down to Lacey (Rt #612) and <ref target="Olympia%20%28Washington%29%23By%20bus">Olympia</ref> (Rt #612) via Lakewood Station and Lakewood P&amp;R during the work week only. The #620 bus operates from the Tacoma Mall down to Olympia via Lakewood and Lacey on weekends only with no service to downtown Tacoma or Tacoma Dome Station. They operate local buses in Lacey, Olympia and Tumwater.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pierce Transit</hi>, ☏ +1 253 581-8000 , toll-free: +1-800-562-8109 . Operates local routes on buses that run on natural gas and connect with other regional transit systems. Pierce transit can also be tracked with a free smartphone app from <ref target="http://www.onebusaway.org/">One Bus Away</ref> that provides easy access to real-time transit information for the Puget Sound region and beyond. From the Tacoma Dome Station they go out to the surrounding cities and towns of Federal Way (#500,501,574); Fife (#500); Lakewood (#574, 594 or #3 from downtown); Point Defiance Pk &amp; the Ferry Terminal (#11, The #41 bus going from Tacoma Dome Station to downtown becomes the #11); Puyallup (#400); Gig Harbor (#102 during weekday rush hour or the #1 or #2 from downtown to TCC Transit Center &amp; transfer to Rt #101); downtown Tacoma &amp; UW Tacoma (13, 14, 41, 500, 501, 586, 594 &amp; Link Light Rail) Adult $2, youth $0.75 and is part of the regional Orca payment system.</item>
</list>
</text>
