<text id="autogum_whow_doc224" title="Choose a Fund Manager" shortTile="choose-fund-manager" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2009-02-26" dateModified="2019-05-26" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Choose-a-Fund-Manager" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Choose a Fund Manager</head><p>By choosing the right fund to invest your money in, you can have a team of professionals picking stocks, managing your money and executing trades. Large funds can afford to have a separate person focusing on picking stocks, allocating the assets of the fund into different areas (stocks, bonds, cash, etc) and managing the most efficient tax position. Large funds may also re-invest some of their money into other funds in the pursuit of lower risk and higher gains. The great thing about mutual funds is that you share the cost of these services with thousands of other investors in the same fund.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Research the fund manager's track record.  <figure rend="Choose a Fund Manager Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Not every fund performs well. Just because a fund has performed well in the past doesn’t necessarily tell you how the fund will perform in the future. In picking a fund, it helps to research the fund’s key personnel, their experience and accomplishments, the fees they charge, and  their investment style.</item>
<item>Managing other people’s money requires experience, maturity and a strong sense of responsibility. Check a fund manager’s track record. How well did they do at the last fund they managed? While veteran managers can't guarantee better performance than a fresh face, there is a lot to be said for experience in the markets.</item>
<item>Having a long view of your manager’s history will help you to see how they performed in both bull (strong) and bear (weak) markets. A consistent performer in both good and bad times is more likely to bring you peace of mind with your investments.</item>
<item>How does a manager's track record compare to that of his/her peers? Be careful with comparisons. Different managers employ different investing styles. Some choose growth stocks, ones they expect to grow in value without paying much in dividends. Others may look for income from dividends. Still others may choose stocks they believe the market has undervalued.</item></list></item>
<item>Add “Alpha”: <figure rend="Choose a Fund Manager Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>An important measure of a fund manager’s value is the “alpha” that they can add. “Alpha” is the measure of how much more the manager adds to the value of your investment than if you had simply invested in an index fund. An index fund attempts to mirror the market by investing in every company (or a representative sampling of companies) listed in a particular index. Such a list may reflect a particular industry, economic sector, geographic region, company size, or investing style.</item>
<item>You can discover a fund's "alpha" measurement by researching the fund online at Morningstar.com or various other fund-analysis services.</item></list></item>
<item>Compare with index funds.  <figure rend="Choose a Fund Manager Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Generally index funds charge lower fees, because they face lower research-and-analysis expenses. They may be expected to do as well as the relevant market in general. If, on the other hand, you choose to pay the higher fees associated with a managed fund, be sure that the fund manager is not merely following some index.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>In regulated financial markets like  Europe, UK and Australia, governing bodies publish regular performance figures of the various funds on offer. These bodies will have information about the key personnel running a fund and may also attempt to define their specific styles. In the United States there are a number of online sources of such information, notably Morningstar.</item></list>
</text>
