<text id="autogum_interview_doc431" title="part0_French workers use threats in compensation demand" shortTile="partfrench-workers" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-07-17" dateModified="2019-09-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/French_workers_use_threats_in_compensation_demand" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>French workers use threats in compensation demand</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, July 17, 2009</hi>
Following similar threats by workers at New Fabris and Nortel, workers at  JLG in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tonneins">Tonneins</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">France</ref>, threatened to blow up several platform cranes. The JLG factory announced in April 2009 that it will fire 53 of its 163 workers by the end of 2009, while the remaining 110 jobs will not be secure over the next 2 years.</p>
<p>JLG Tonneins was acquired in 2006 with its parent <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JLG%20Industries">JLG Industries</ref>, a maker of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aerial%20work%20platform">aerial work platforms</ref>, by the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">U.S.</ref>-based <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oshkosh%20Corporation">Oshkosh Corporation</ref>. Despite being hugely profitable in the past, production has been much reduced since 2008 with the contraction of the construction industry and lower demand for its products. Despite excellent past results the new American management demanded sweeping cuts at the company.</p>
<p>In the view of locals, "the company's actions are a disgrace given the expensive perks, such as official cars, for its corporate fat cats, compared to the sacrifice, silence, and dignity demanded by the company of those it has made redundant."</p>
<p>The management offered severance pay of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euro">€</ref> 3,000 (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20State%20dollar">US $</ref>4,200), however the workers demanded a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Severance%20package">severance package</ref> commensurate with "the wealth that their labor has generated." Worker's delegates requested a "supra-legal" payment of € 30,000, on Thursday 16 of July the management responded with a counter offer of € 16,000. On Thursday night the worker's actions secured the € 30,000 settlement initially demanded.</p>
<head id="Interview:">Interview:</head>
<p><hi rend="italic">A JLG Tonneins worker who wished to stay anonymous spoke to </hi>Wikinews.</p>
<figure><caption>Wikinews</caption></figure><p><hi rend="bold">Can you explain what inspired the workers at JLG to make these threats?</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Photograph of the threatened machines, Tonneins, France. (Photo credit:Public domain photograph provided by a Tonniens worker)</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JLG worker</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> After four months of negotiations with very little progress, we saw the need for a media coup in our dispute. Similar threats in recent disputes, reported by the mainstream media, have proven to be productive. We were spurred on by redundancy pay of 3,000 Euro, derisory in view of the wealth that our labour has generated in previous years and the threat that these lay-offs pose to our families. Responsibility must also lie with the refusal by the management, these last four months, to negotiate an appropriate severance package; the movement in our company has therefore resorted to the media with a visually striking example. Machines designed and built at our workshops were therefore surrounded by two and four canisters of gas. The visual effect was created.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">You have demanded a large severance payment. In the context of the crisis in the building industry, can JLG afford it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JLG worker</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> JLG is part of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oshkosh%20Corporation">Oshkosh Corporation</ref>, the group brought JLG in 2007 because of its very good economic health, 2006 was a very good year, and the fiscal year of 2007-2008 was excellent for JLG, our best figures ever. So yes, with regards to the figures for 2007-2008 the results to come 2009, 2010 are very poor. But only in comparison with exceptionally profitable years! The crisis appears to be a belt-tightening one. This is not the optimal solution, almost exclusively the solution chosen is to lay off technicians and employees at the sites, when they are the least expensive [part of the work force]. Yes, JLG France has other ways to better manage this crisis. This would require that all tighten their belts, which does not appear to be the strategy chosen by the management. Hence the accumulation of tension in the company.</p>
</text>
