<text id="autogum_interview_doc275" title="part1_Eurovision &amp;apos;09 competitor Chiara talks about her current song &amp;quot;What If We&amp;quot; and her past accolades" shortTile="parteurovision--competitor" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-03-05" dateModified="2013-09-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eurovision_%2709_competitor_Chiara_talks_about_her_current_song_%22What_If_We%22_and_her_past_accolades" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Chiara</hi>: When I go into a competition, I always go to win, but I was nervous like everyone else...I think [when] you win a festival, [you win] for what you present, not for what your history is.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Growing up, did you always want to become a singer? Who were your musical influences, and what genres do you think are your favorite? Do you think these preferences have molded you into the singer you are today?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chiara</hi>: Definitely. My mum always says I used to sing and dance for them all the time since I was a baby, and I've always loved ballads. In fact, my favourite singer has always been Whitney Houston.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> How did you come to the decision to enter the Eurovision pre-selection for Malta back in 1998? What kinds of feelings did you experience during the path you took to eventual victory in the national final?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chiara</hi>: 1998 was my first time in the festival. I was very young and I felt I could never win it. I wanted just to try and be there with the big names of those times. It was very scary and overwhelming, [and] then I won.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Did you feel overwhelmed performing in front of an international audience in Birmingham? What kind of personal feelings and emotions made you relate to the song you sang, "The One That I Love"? There were remarks afterwards that your performance was great, but your dress had similarities to Barbara Dex's from five years before (and she has become well-known for her "fashion don't"). Looking back on it, what did you think of that dress?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chiara</hi>: Well...looking back I remember that I was completely overwhelmed [singing] in front of so many people. I was very scared but managed to do well. As for the dress, they were different times [back then] and it was beyond my control.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You came very close to winning the Contest for Malta back in 1998. When you didn't, how did it make you feel? Did you feel "robbed"? As an addenda, some Wikipedians I've talked to have hypothesized that tabloid hype before the event helped Dana International win; in other words, she would not have won had she not been a transsexual. Do you feel that's true, and did you like her song?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chiara</hi>: I know a lot of Maltese who voted for Dana because they liked the song and for no other reason. The song was good and we still hear it today. </p>
<p>Obviously when you are so close to winning something and you don't, yes, you feel a bit robbed, but [then there's] the moment [when] you realise you did well and you are happy.</p>
</text>
