<text id="autogum_whow_doc404" title="Create Dot Paintings" shortTile="create-dot-paintings" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2017-08-01" dateModified="2017-08-01" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Create-Dot-Paintings" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Create Dot Paintings</head><p>Dot painting originates from the Australian Indigenous people, who used to hide sacred meanings behind the paintings. This article shows a more modern version of the form of art.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Painting With a Q-tip</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>gather the materials. This will include paints, water, paper and several Q-tips. Watercolor or acrylic paint is best recommended for the paint as you can create lighter or darker hues with the colors and watercolor paper is suggested, thought normal paper will work as well. you will need a Q-tip for each chosen color and remember not mix the Q-tips together. You will also need a small amount of water in a bowl and a Q-tip for each chosen color. You can  keep some tissues in hand to lighten the hues.</item>
<item>You will need to start by wetting the watercolors with a bit of water. To do this, just add about two to three drops of water on the paints and mix it.</item>
<item>Now it's finally time for the fun part, painting. Dip the Q-tip in the paint so it covers up the bottom of it. dab the Q-tip gently on the paper towel and then press the it on the paper. you will see that it forms a dot. The paint on the Q-tip will stay for a short time, so you don't need to dip it in the paint after every dot. Make patterns with the dots, overlap one dot with the another, do anything you want and let your imagination run wild.</item>
<item>If you want to experiment with techniques first, you can use scrap paper.</item>
<item>You can even make little circles. Cut the Q-tip in half and dip the part without the cotton in the paint and quickly press it on the paper. You will need to dip it after every dot, unlike when you're using the soft bit for it.</item>
<item>when you Have finished your painting, let it dry. You can let it dry naturally or, to make things faster, use a hair dryer. You can also dab a clean tissue on the painting to make the colors lighter and also dry faster. don't touch the painting with bare hands in this process!</item>
<item>when the art work is finished, you can keep it on a scrap book or uses it as a decoration. Keep it on a frame or laminate it.</item></list>
<head>Water Drop Painting</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Gather the materials. You will need a lot of water, paints, paper, small bowls and a dropper. Reccomend using tube paints as it will make it easier to mix with paint and try to use watercolor paper. the bowls should be approximately the same size and as small as possible.</item>
<item>Mix the paint with the water. put a small amount of paint in your one of the bowls and fill it half-way with water. Mix the ingredients togather. if the mixture looks a bitt pale keep adding more paint till it's oppaque. Follw this procudure with as many colors as you would like.</item>
<item>Time for the easy part. Fill the dropper with one of the paint mixtures. Put one drop of the liquid onto the paper to create a dot. folow this process to create your art work.</item>
<item>When your art work is complete, let it dry naturaly and don't temper with it. Since the droplets are fragile, try to put it somewhere still, because if even one droplet is ruined, it might ruin the whole piece. When it is dry, your masterpeice will be complete.</item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>see dot painting pictures on the intranet for inspiration.</item>
<item>if you are dot painting on darker paper, consider using lighter colors and less amount of water.</item>
<item>Do not use a hair on the Water drop dot paint as the wind is too harsh.</item>
<item>Instead of a Q-tip, you can also use a stick</item></list>
</text>
