<text id="autogum_interview_doc908" title="part0_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green candidate Bruce Haines, Bramalea-Gore-Malton" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-24" dateModified="2007-11-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Green_candidate_Bruce_Haines%2C_Bramalea-Gore-Malton" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green candidate Bruce Haines, Bramalea-Gore-Malton</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, September 24, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bruce Haines</hi> is running for the Green Party of Ontario in the Ontario provincial election, in the Bramalea-Gore-Malton riding. Wikinews' Nick Moreau interviewed him regarding his values, his experience, and his campaign.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>During the last year I have become very involved in helping my community locally on environmental issues, urban sprawl/greenspace issues and at a local food bank and soup kitchen. A number of people noticed my efforts and suggested that I run for MPP, so I took them up on the challenge. I chose to run in the riding where my family and I live and where my children go to school. With two children now, and another on the way, I wanted to make sure we left behind a better world for the future generations.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>I have followed the political process throughout my life, and on three occasions have helped municipal candidates with their campaigns. I have a tremendous amount of experience working in a community setting, both as a police officer and as a business owner. I have the ability to work well with people from varying cultures, and tend to gain respect from others quickly.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why? What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?</hi></p>
<p>The biggest challenge will be overcoming the status quo parties, rather than the other candidates themselves. The other parties have been around for a long time and people have developed a loyalty that is sometimes hard to overcome.</p>
<p>I believe I am the best candidate for my riding because I have the ability to unite our community and make it stronger. I am a strong, vocal, active person who possesses the right leadership attributes to help the constituents in my riding. Throughout my life I have demonstrated that I am a noticeable leader: during my high school days I was President of the Athletic Association; during my policing career I advanced quickly, and in business I have built up a company that employs more than 125 people and is respected in its market.</p>
</text>
