<text id="autogum_whow_doc104" title="Operate Multiple Computers With One Keyboard and Monitor" shortTile="operate-multiple" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2008-02-13" dateModified="2019-10-03" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Operate-Multiple-Computers-With-One-Keyboard-and-Monitor" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Operate Multiple Computers With One Keyboard and Monitor</head><p>Here's a convenient way to operate two (or more) computers from one location without the need for duplicating a keyboard, mouse and monitor.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Determine which method works best for you. Hardware and software based solutions are available.  Read on to help figure out which is best for your personal situation. <figure rend="Operate Multiple Computers With One Keyboard and Monitor Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>A software based solution will require that each computer under control has a network connection.  The network can be a LAN if it will be controlled locally only, or an internet connection if it will need to be controlled from any computer in the world with an internet connection. <figure rend="Operate Multiple Computers With One Keyboard and Monitor Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Obtain software and service for your computers.  One such provider is <ref target="http://www.logmein.com">LogMeIn</ref>.  They have several levels of service ranging from <hi rend="italic">free</hi> for "simple remote control" (LogMeInFree) to the more robust "full service" offerings (such as LogMeInPro) but has a monthly fee of about US$20 per computer. The LogMeIn service in general works very well, but like any network based solution, is best when connected by high speed LAN or broadband internet between the computers. Select the service level that best meets your needs, create an account and download / install the software. <figure rend="Operate Multiple Computers With One Keyboard and Monitor Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>A second software based option is the open source solution called "synergy" this works across operating systems, when simply trying to control several computers locally with one keyboard and mouse, a "soft" KVM switch if you will. <figure rend="Operate Multiple Computers With One Keyboard and Monitor Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>A hardware based solution can be achieved with a "KVM Switch"  KVM is an acronym for "Keyboard, Video, Mouse".  These devices typically have connections for multiple Video inputs from the computers and a single output to connect to a monitor.  There are also multiple PS/2 Mouse and Keyboard outputs to connect to the computers and two inputs for connecting both a keyboard and a mouse.  Newer KVM switches have transitioned from PS/2 and round Keyboard connectors to the popular USB ports instead.  Be sure to obtain a KVM that supports the style Keyboard and Mouse connectors the computer uses or obtain adapters.  Due to limitations on the length of cable that KVM (and USB for that matter) signals can travel, all the computers will probably have to be located fairly close (within 10 feet or so of the KVM hardware) unless some other repeater or extender hardware is employed. <figure rend="Operate Multiple Computers With One Keyboard and Monitor Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Purchase any additional cables needed to complete connections between the KVM and the computers and I/O devices. <figure rend="Operate Multiple Computers With One Keyboard and Monitor Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select the product that has computer and operating system(s) support for your setup.  Many KVM's install device drivers and use a small program to switch between computers.  This means if multiple OS's are involved, drivers will be required for each in order to work properly. <figure rend="Operate Multiple Computers With One Keyboard and Monitor Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Install the KVM and software as specified in the manufacturer's instructions. <figure rend="Operate Multiple Computers With One Keyboard and Monitor Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
</text>
