<text id="autogum_whow_doc278" title="Make Kataif" shortTile="make-kataif" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-10-11" dateModified="2018-11-17" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-Kataif" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make Kataif</head><p>Kataif, typically eaten during the month of Ramadan, is a Middle Eastern sweet that can be made in a number of ways. Kataif is eaten in many of the countries in the Middle East but mostly in Palestine, Syria, Jordan, and Lebanon. The recipe below provides a few ways to create these tasty sweets. Perfect dessert for those celebrating Ramadan and for those who simply enjoy trying Middle Eastern desserts.
Quantity:12-15
Time to make:30-40 min</p>
<head>Ingredients</head>
<head>Batter</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>1/3 cups of all purpose flour</item>
<item>1 cup of semolina</item>
<item>1/2 teaspoon of yeast</item>
<item>1/3 cup of sugar</item>
<item>1/3 cup of pancake mix (Aunt Jemimah pancake mix compete)</item>
<item>1 cup of water</item>
<item>1/2 teaspoon Mahlab spice</item></list>
<head>Filling</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>1/2 1 Ib. block of sweet cheese</item>
<item>2 cups of toasted almonds</item>
<item>1 tablespoon of sugar</item>
<item>2 teaspoons of cinnamon</item>
<item>1/4 teaspoon of cardamon</item></list>
<head>Syrup</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>2 cups of sugar</item>
<item>1 cups of water</item>
<item>2 tablespoons of lemon water</item>
<item>1 teaspoon of rosewater</item></list>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find a clean surface. Make sure to work in an environment that is clean and spacious so that nothing gets dirty and messy.</item>
<item>Prepare the batter. Get a blender and place the 1/3 cups of flour, 1 cup of semolina, 1/2 teaspoon of ground mahlab, 1/2 teaspoon of yeast, 1/3 cup of sugar, 1/3 cup of pancake mix, and 1 cup of water (may require 1/2 a cup more until the batter becomes smooth) into it. Blend the batter until it gets smooth.</item>
<item>Heat frying pan. pour the mix i a large bowl and allow the it to rest for 10-15 minutes while the pan heats up. Make sure it is on medium to low heat and that the batter is covered. <figure rend="Ingredientsinblender.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pour the mix. Once to batter has rested, use a ladle and pour about 1/4 cup onto the frying pan. Notice that the kataif will start to bubble around the edges and soon will start to cover the entire surface. If it is not covered with bubbles, then that means that the batter is too thick. if that is the case add small quantities of water, whisk and try again.  <figure rend="Ingredientsinbowl.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remove the kataif. When it is no longer shiny and liquidy, then they are ready to be removed from the pan.  <figure rend="Liquidbatter.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>NOTE: cooking them over high heat will cause them to get burnt quickly and will dry them out. That will cause them to split when they are filled or will reopen. you want to color to be a golden brown so check with the first one, if its too dark, lower the heat and try again. if it is too light, brig the heat up a little.  <figure rend="Bubbledbatter.jpg"></figure>,  <figure rend="Colorofkataif.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Cover them with a towel. Take the kataif off the heat and immediately cover them with a kitchen towel or a light blanket. THIS IS VERY IMPORTANT! Covering them allows the kataif to remain soft and easy to stuff and seal without worrying about it splitting.
<list type="unordered"><item>NOTE: if you do not cover the kataif they will dry out and the results will be that it will no longer seal and it will begin to split.  <figure rend="Coveredkataif.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Prepare the fillings. Take 1/2 block of 1 Ib. white sweet cheese and begin shredding it with a shredder into a plate until you feel is enough for the portion. An alternative filling is ricotta:
<list type="unordered"><item>Take 2 cups of toasted almonds/walnuts that are chopped or crushed, 1 tablespoon of sugar, 2 teaspoons of cinnamon, and 1/4 teaspoon of cardamon and place them into a small mixing bowl and mix them.  <figure rend="Shreddedcheese.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Stuff the kataif. To stuff the kataif, place about 1-2 teaspoons of the desired filling into the middle of the kataif and fold it in half. At this point it should look like a half moon. Then begin to seal the edges by pinching them, with your thumb and index,  tightly together. once sealed, place them back under the covers and begin working on the syrup.
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure you don't over stuff them because that may cause them to burst open during cooking. <figure rend="Stuffing1.jpg"></figure>,  <figure rend="Stuffing2.jpg"></figure>,  <figure rend="Stuffing3.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Making the Syrup. Take 1 cup of sugar, 3/4 cup of water, and 1 teaspoon of lemon juice and placed them in a pot to boil. once it has reached its boiling point, lower the heat and let it simmer for 5 minutes After simmering is done, turn off the heat totally and add 1 teaspoon of rosewater.
<list type="unordered"><item>Some people replace the rosewater with cinnamon or orange peel. <figure rend="Syrup.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Frying the Kataifi. Grab a pot and pour about 2-3 cups of vegetable oil in it and turn on the heat, once the oil begins to boil, place the 2 or 3 kataif into the pot  at a time and fry it util the edges become crisp and golden brown.
<list type="unordered"><item>NOTE: Baking the kataif is another method. brush the kataif wit melted butter or vegetable oil and arrange them on a blanket sheet. Bake them in a preheated oven at 200C until golden and crisp. <figure rend="FryingKataif.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Soak with syrup. Once the kataif is finished being fried or bakes, take it and quickly dunk them into the syrup and then arrange them on a serving plate.
<list type="unordered"><item>NOTE: do not dunk them for more than a few seconds of else they will become soggy and soft. <figure rend="Kataifsyrup.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Make tea. In most middle eastern cultures, it is traditionally eaten with tea. Take a tea pot and fill it up with water. When you see that the water has boiled, place two bags of Lipton black tea and either a handful of mint leaves or sage (maramia). Turn off immediately and let it brew for about 5 min. Once it has finished, pour in into a cup with about 2 teaspoons of sugar and enjoy it with kataif. <figure rend="Kataiffinised.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
