<text id="autogum_interview_doc672" title="part15_Gay Talese on the state of journalism, Iraq and his life" shortTile="partgay-talese-state" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-27" dateModified="2019-01-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gay_Talese_on_the_state_of_journalism%2C_Iraq_and_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And a happy society. At least I found a lot of people who were very content. They may not have an easy life, but they were quite content.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  They have their <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Honor">honor</ref>. They have their <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dignity">dignity</ref>. They're not a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/serf">serf</ref> class to the aristocracy.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  People dancing in the streets at night.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  I went out at night and I saw a lot of that. That's true. They have their values.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And friendly.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  And friendly. Much more than those <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cuban%20American">Cubans in Miami</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  My friend I was with was Colombian from Miami, and he made the exact same observation. He had a prejudice against Cubans from his time in Miami and he said, "These people aren't anything like the Cubans in Miami."</hi></p>
<head id="On_Chinese_gay_bars">On Chinese gay bars</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">David Shankbone:  Do you have a favorite country you have visited?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Gay Talese:</hi>  Well I think the city I found most interesting was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beijing">Beijing</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You talk about China a lot.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  I found that really a place that changes every year. And it's what you can do.  That's one city. I spent so much time in Europe when I was young.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is it interesting to you to watch China change?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  Yeah, I read everything that's in the papers about China. I completed a story today about how the Bush administration was being used by China.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you get tired of going to the same region and then you're like, ‘I need to go to Asia for a while?'</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  That's right. That happened to me in 1998. Kind of interesting. I was able to see without being interrupted with interpretation because I couldn't understand anything. I so so enjoyed being places I've never been before like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kuala%20Lumpur">Kuala Lumpur</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Singapore">Singapore</ref>, not <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hong%20Kong">Hong Kong</ref>, but other places. You asked me about Beijing. It's the most interesting city because it's an international city in which there is this history going back hundreds and hundreds of years of turmoil, accommodation. They are such entrepreneurial people on the lowest level to the highest level, the Chinese. And they're so quick in understanding how to survive and there are so many of them. God, there are so many of them. Have you been to Asia?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I haven't been to Asia. It doesn't particularly interest me all that much. There are countries I would like to see, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cambodia">Cambodia</ref> being one. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South%20America">South America</ref> is one of the areas that I am most interested to explore because I speak Spanish.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  You do?  I don't speak anything.  I felt similarly when I first got out of Beijing. I said Beijing is an interesting city because it's international, because it has the press from around the world and the political representation of the whole world in that capitol city. But at night, especially if you have some Chinese friends who speak English so you're able to have them tell you a little bit about what you're seeing as they take you around and you go to clubs. What first impressed me in Beijing was the great number of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gay%20rights%20in%20China">gay men</ref>, and women I guess, but gay men who had clubs, gay bars in Beijing. I don't read this in the paper. But what impressed me was how open it is. One called Club Vogue. I went there.</p>
</text>
