<text id="autogum_whow_doc362" title="Catch a Falling Star" shortTile="catch-falling-star" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-09-26" dateModified="2017-06-26" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Catch-a-Falling-Star" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Catch a Falling Star</head><p>You might ask "What? What in the whole wide world do you mean to "catch" a falling star?" Well, to answer the question, you first have to know how to watch a falling star rise again. Only then will you <hi rend="italic">be able to catch a falling star</hi>. So the real purpose of this article is to try to explain '<hi rend="italic">how to watch a falling star rise again to the level of becoming yet another star.</hi></p>
<p>Stars: They are wondrous things that glow and twinkle in the night sky, silently observing all that we think, say, and do. To catch the falling stars, you may need a little extra equipment and gadgetry, but a lot of these steps can be taken by simply observing the current ways and means we already have to see into the universe, including - your very own eyes.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Dress comfortably and take at least 30 minutes or so out of your evening.<figure><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Special:FilePath/Catch_a_Falling_Star_Step_1.jpg">Image:Catch a Falling Star Step 1.jpg</ref></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are getting ready to rest, take a chair outside and wear your evening clothes.</item>
<item>The exception to this is if you are in a public place. In that case, you will want to still dress comfortably and find a place to sit where you can see the night sky.</item></list></item>
<item>Be aware of the time. You want to be sure to be prepared and do it no sooner than an hour "after sunset time."<figure><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Special:FilePath/Catch_a_Falling_Star_Step_2.jpg">Image:Catch a Falling Star Step 2.jpg</ref></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Listen to your local radio station or TV, or find the information in your newspaper.</item>
<item>If you want very accurate information, a World Clock Time Zone website will help so you can easily find the correct time. <ref target="http://worldtimeserver.com">Here's a link to the WorldClockTimeServer website</ref> out of the many accurate time servers that exist. Check your local time against the World Clock to ensure your watch is set right so you can watch the star.</item></list></item>
<item>Find out what time the sun sets in your area.<figure><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Special:FilePath/Catch_a_Falling_Star_Step_3.jpg">Image:Catch a Falling Star Step 3.jpg</ref></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="http://www.timeanddate.com">Check this website</ref> to find your local sunset and sundown times.</item>
<item>Please note that these are only two websites out of the very many in CyberSpace that you can use to get the same information, but for the purposes of this article, it should only be limited to one for the correct time and one to find the sunset and sunrise information.</item></list></item>
<item>Check the weather outside.<figure><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Special:FilePath/Catch_a_Falling_Star_Step_4.jpg">Image:Catch a Falling Star Step 4.jpg</ref></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Go outside and look up, while panning your eyes across the top of the horizon.</item>
<item>Can you physically see clouds or does it look gray or white? If so, this is not a good night to see or watch the stars without a strong telescope that can peer out past the clouds, such as the Hubble Telescope because the weather is too cloudy if it's not crystal clear.</item>
<item>There are other space telescopes besides Hubble, but it's the most talked about space telescope at this time.</item>
<item>Can you see stars twinkling in the beautiful night sky?</item></list></item>
<item>Wait until it's a really clear night then go outside and find a dark place to view the sky.<figure><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Special:FilePath/Catch_a_Falling_Star_Step_5.jpg">Image:Catch a Falling Star Step 5.jpg</ref></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>It could be your backyard, a park, or even just a quiet place in your mind.</item></list></item>
<item>Tilt your head straight up and stop.<figure><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Special:FilePath/Catch_a_Falling_Star_Step_6.jpg">Image:Catch a Falling Star Step 6.jpg</ref></figure></item>
<item>Close your eyes and <hi rend="italic">count to 10 very slowly</hi>.<figure><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Special:FilePath/Catch_a_Falling_Star_Step_7.jpg">Image:Catch a Falling Star Step 7.jpg</ref></figure></item>
<item>Open your eyes very slowly and gaze into the universe.<figure><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Special:FilePath/Catch_a_Falling_Star_Step_8.jpg">Image:Catch a Falling Star Step 8.jpg</ref></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't you wonder how it got there?</item>
<item>Look at all the constellations and far away stars and planets.</item>
<item>Yes, some planets and stars are so far away that you can't even see them.</item>
<item>The ones you cannot <hi rend="bold">yet see</hi> are the falling stars.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If it's a night and you're in a city, you may need to go to the rooftop of the building so you can get above the lights of the city.</item>
<item>If you know the song "When You Wish Upon a Star," try singing it while you watch and have fun.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Everyone knows that in all practicality you really can't possibly catch a falling star literally, so don't try to do that!</item>
<item>If you're going to a rooftop building, stay away from the edge.</item>
<item>Use a chair to sit down and lean back. It helps you relax and enjoy the view more.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>A dark comfortable place to watch stars</item>
<item>A computer (optional)</item></list>
</text>
