<text id="autogum_news_doc513" title="Football legend Johan Cruyff dies at 68 due to cancer" shortTile="football-legend-johan" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-03-26" dateModified="2017-11-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Football_legend_Johan_Cruyff_dies_at_68_due_to_cancer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Football legend Johan Cruyff dies at 68 due to cancer</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, March 27, 2016</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Netherlands">Netherlands</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/FC_Barcelona">FC Barcelona</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Football_(soccer)">football</ref> legend <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johan%20Cruyff">Johan Cruyff</ref> died in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barcelona">Barcelona</ref> on Thursday at the age of 68. He had lung cancer, announced last October.  Per <hi rend="italic">World of Johan Cruyff</hi> website statement, he died peacefully, his family present.</p>
<figure><caption>April 25, 1947 (Amsterdam)–March 24, 2016 (Barcelona)File photo of Johan Cruyff Image: Mieremet, Rob / Anefo.</caption></figure>
<p>The Dutch maestro won three <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ballon%20d'Or">Ballon d'Or</ref>s in his nineteen-year career, in 1971, 1973, and 1974. Born in the Dutch capital <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Amsterdam">Amsterdam</ref>, Cruyff began his career with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ajax%20AFC">Ajax AFC</ref>. He won three consecutive European titles, eight <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eredivisie">Eredivisie</ref> titles ("Dutch league"), five <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/KNVB%20Cup">KNVB Cups</ref> ("Dutch Cup"), a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UEFA%20Super%20Cup">UEFA Super Cup</ref>, and an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intercontinental%20Cup%20(football)">Intercontinental Cup</ref> with the capital club. Later in his career, he signed for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Feyenoord">Feyenoord</ref> and won the Dutch league Dutch Cup with them as well.</p>
<p>He joined the Catalans in 1973. In his first season at Barça, the Blaugrana won the league after fourteen years without. That season, Barcelona defeated <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Real_Madrid">Real Madrid</ref> 5–0 at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santiago%20Bernabéu%20Stadium">Santiago Bernabéu Stadium</ref>. He managed Barcelona for eight years, from 1988 to 1996. When he signed for the managerial position, he said, "I know the club and I don't want history to repeat itself[...] If we want things to change, we must change history." In his managing career at Barcelona, he won four consecutive <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/La_Liga">La Liga</ref> titles and the club won its very first European Cup in 1992 at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wembly%20Stadium">Wembly</ref>. Before the match, he told the team ""Go out and enjoy yourselves" ((es))Spanish: ‍Salid y disfrutad. He won a total of eleven trophies before he was sacked. Before he became the manager, the Catalonians had only ten Spanish titles but after 1990, they won thirteen trophies in 26 years.</p>
<p>He took the Dutch national team to the 1974 FIFA World Cup final, but lost 2–1 to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">West Germany</ref>. He completed 34 dribbles, the most by any player in the tournament. Cruyff won the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FIFA%20World%20Cup%20awards#Golden_Ball">FIFA World Cup Golden Ball</ref> in that World Cup. The tournament also saw his famous '<ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/Cruyff%20turn">Cruyff turn</ref>' for the first time in a match against <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sweden">Sweden</ref>. He also promoted the idea of 'Total Football', a style of playing the game.</p>
<p>He had a heart bypass surgery in 1991 and stopped smoking. He had been a heavy smoker. Last month, he said that he was he "2–0 up in the first half of a match" against lung cancer.</p>
<p>As a tribute, the Netherlands v <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">France</ref> friendly football match on Friday was paused in the 14th minute, as his jersey featured the number 14. The French side won the match 3–2 with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Antoine_Griezmann">Antoine Griezmann</ref> scoring an early goal in the 6th minute.</p>
<head id="Achievements">Achievements</head>
<head id="AFC_Ajax_(Player)">AFC Ajax (Player)</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>8 Eredivisie titles</item>
<item>5 KNVB Cups</item>
<item>3 European Cups</item>
<item>1 UEFA Super Cup</item>
<item>1 Intercontinental Cup</item></list>
<head id="FC_Barcelona_(Player)">FC Barcelona (Player)</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>1 La Liga</item>
<item>1 Copa del Rey</item></list>
<head id="Feyenoord">Feyenoord</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>1 Eredivisie</item>
<item>1 KNVB Cup</item></list>
<head id="AFC_Ajax_(manager)">AFC Ajax (manager)</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>1 KNVB Cup</item>
<item>1 UEFA Cup Winners' Cup</item></list>
<head id="FC_Barcelona_(Manager)">FC Barcelona (Manager)</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>4 La Liga</item>
<item>3 Supercopa de España</item>
<item>1 European Cup</item>
<item>1 UEFA Super Cup</item>
<item>1 UEFA Cup Winners' Cup</item>
<item>1 Copa del Rey</item></list>
</text>
