<text id="autogum_academic_doc469" title="Role of Hypoxia and Metabolism in the Development of Neointimal Hyperplasia in Arteriovenous Fistulas" shortTile="role-hypoxia-metabolism" author="Nirvana Sadaghianloo, Julie Contenti, Alan Dardik, Nathalie  M. Mazure" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1422-0067/20/21/5387/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 6. HIF and Vascular Diseases</head>
<p>
In vascular pathology, hypoxia is typically the consequence of altered, destroyed or absent blood vessels leading to tissue ischemia. The mechanisms of the HIF response have therefore been studied in ischemic vascular diseases, such as myocardial infarction (consequence of obstruction of coronary arteries) or peripheral vascular disease (PAD, consequence of obstruction of arteries going to the limbs). </p>

<p>Besides tissue ischemia, mechanisms of hypoxia and ischemia can occur within the vascular wall itself, with implications for diseases such as atherosclerosis, arterial aneurysm, chronic venous insufficiency and thromboembolism. There is growing evidence that the HIF pathway is implicated—for better or for worse—in the response of the vascular wall to inadequate oxygenation and/or increased cellular oxygen, a demand secondary to various stresses or injuries. </p>

<head> 6.1. HIF and Atherosclerosis</head>
<p>
Atherosclerosis is a condition in which fatty deposits (plaques) develop in the arterial wall, leading to stenosis and ultimately to thrombosis of the vessel. Atherosclerotic plaques are mainly composed of cholesterol, other lipids, calcium, fibrin and inflammatory cells. Oxygen diffusion through space-occupying atherosclerotic plaques could be limited due to wall thickening. Hypoxia could also originate from the high oxygen demand of metabolically active inflammatory cells, such as macrophage foam cells that play a pivotal role in this disease. Detection of HIF-1α and activation of its target genes occurs in atherosclerotic plaques. During atherogenesis (plaque build-up), hypoxia increases angiogenesis, releases pro-inflammatory mediators, activates MMPs, forms reactive oxygen species, and oxidizes low-density lipoprotein. Necrotic cores within atherosclerotic plaques can lead to plaque instability and thromboembolic complications. The HIF-1α protein is found in tissue surrounding atherosclerotic arteries, inflammatory macrophages and arterial SMCs around these necrotic cores. Proangiogenic HIF-target genes, such as VEGF-A, are responsible for intra-plaque neoangiogenesis, contributing to plaque instability. HIF-1 activity also alters the lipid metabolism of macrophages and vascular SMC. Finally, besides hypoxia, several non-hypoxic stimuli of HIF have also been found in plaques and plaque macrophages, such as inflammation, ROS, vasoactive and thrombotic factors. </p>

<head> 6.2. HIF and NH in Vascular Grafts</head>
<p>
The role of the HIF pathway in the development of NH has also been studied. When atherosclerotic lesions occupy a long segment of the artery, surgeons frequently use a graft to bypass the lesion and provide blood to distal tissues. Either venous or prosthetic, these grafts are prone to NH. Although vein grafts and prosthetic grafts are not identical, because of different hemodynamics and oxygen tension, the characteristics of NH in vein grafts are similar to those of NH that form in AVFs. In studies with animal models, grafts showed increased hypoxia within the vessel wall in regions of neointimal hyperplasia. A study using a porcine model showed an association of HIF-1α expression with the degree of neointimal hyperplasia in grafts, and suggested that reducing hypoxia might inhibit venous NH formation, possibly by reducing the phenotypic switch of fibroblasts to myofibroblasts. Paradoxically, increased activation of the HIF pathway may also protect against NH formation. Nakao et al. studied the role of carbon monoxide, a physiologically important vasodilator that acts via cyclic guanosine monophosphate, in the formation of NH. They showed that a vein graft placed immediately after harvest led to less NH than if the graft was rinsed with lactated Ringer for 2 h prior to surgical placement. However, if the lactated Ringer solution was saturated with carbon monoxide, it significantly inhibited NH compared to the untreated control. The effects of carbon monoxide in inhibiting NH formation seemed to be associated with increased HIF-1α and VEGF expression a few hours after grafting. This effect, including the induction of VEGF, was reversed by treatment with YC-1, a HIF-1α inhibitor, supporting the conclusion that these effects were mediated through the activation of the HIF pathway. These apparently contradictory studies suggest that, at least in the setting of vein graft NH, transient activation of the HIF pathway may protect the wall from hypoxia, whereas chronic activation may maintain the ongoing NH process. Carbon monoxide may also display vasoconstrictor effects depending on oxygen and metabolic homeostasis, including ROS production, highlighting the important role of metabolism in the vascular wall. </p>
</text>
