<text id="autogum_reddit_doc118" title="Gauging interest for new blog topic?" shortTile="gauging-interest" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-04-30" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8g19cl" speakerList="#CarpetPuncher, #floopalaide" speakerCount="2">
<head>Gauging interest for new blog topic?</head>
<sp who="#CarpetPuncher">
<p>Hello, I'm new to blogging. I've bought my domain and installed wordpress. I'm an IT guy, so the tech stuff I've got down, thankfully. I've recently been through a lot of stressful life situations. I have diagnosed major depressive disorder, anxiety and ADHD. I'm also a recent recovering alcoholic; this alone gives me much to say. I've been using the outdoors to overcome and move my life forward. I hike and camp, mostly. I have been searching the web for travel / camping bloggers with my particular slant, and it surprised me to find 2-3 people doing the same thing. From what I can tell, I may have a somewhat unique melting-pot of topics to meld into a cohesive and helpful blog. What I'm not sure of is how much interest there really is for said topics. How do I know if the reason I'm finding little for my particular slant is because of lack of interest, or lack of content? Any helpful tools or data I could use to make an informed decision? Or, do I just wing it and hope I can build a base of readers? My SO and I are working toward our dream of traveling and blogging full-time. We know it's hard work. We've spent the last several month working on moving our sources of income to freelance with mild success. Everything takes work and time! </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#floopalaide">
<p>For the record, I think this is a phenomenal niche and I have no doubt in my mind that you could make it work and transform it into something profitable. </p>
<p>As far as validation is concerned, I wouldn't limit yourself to just looking at other bloggers (it's actually ideal if you're the only blogger in a niche that's vastly popular elsewhere. ) </p>
<p>I'm brought back to shows like Brat Camp which play into this idea a lot. I also know there's a lot of books on using the outdoors to cope with these things. I would, honestly, look to Amazon for validation if you can't find blogs in this niche. </p>
<p>When if you find books in your topic, get a good look at the reviews - figure out what they say is missing. Look for phrases like but I wish or I would have loved if . </p>
<p>As far as I'm concerned, that's free advice on exactly what people may want you to write about. </p>
<p>Small niche blogs are definitely a little harder to validate - but even if you don't have the convenience of getting to look up your niche on Pinterest, it's still possible that your topic is popular in ANOTHER medium. That would mean the audience exists, but now you have to draw them in. </p>
<p>Good luck!</p>
</sp>
</text>
