<text id="autogum_bio_doc475" title="Robert Bennet (bishop)" shortTile="robert-bennet-bishop" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-01-28" dateModified="2019-09-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Bennet_%28bishop%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Robert Bennet (bishop)</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">Robert Bennet</hi> (Bennett) (died 1617) was an English Anglican bishop and the Dean of Windsor.</p>
<p>Bennet was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baldock">Baldock</ref>, Hertfordshire to Leonard Bennet and his wife, Margaret Langley. He matriculated at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trinity_College,_Cambridge">Trinity College, Cambridge</ref> in 1563, graduating B.A. in 1567, and becoming a minor Fellow in the same year.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-White-2">[2]</ref> He became a full Fellow in 1570, in which year he also gained his M.A,. He was incorporated at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oxford">Oxford</ref> in 1572, at which time he opposed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Whitgift">John Whitgift</ref>'s redrafted Cambridge University statutes, and in 1576 he served as university preacher at Cambridge. As a young man he was noted for his good looks and as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_tennis">royal tennis</ref> player. After obtaining his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bachelor_of_Theology">B.Th.</ref> in 1577, he was referred to as Erudito Benedicte because, in the words of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Harington_(writer)">John Harington</ref>, "'he would tosse an Argument in the Schools, better than a Ball in the Tennis-court".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-odnb-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>In 1583, Bennet became master of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hospital_of_St_Cross">Hospital of St Cross</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Winchester">Winchester</ref> and left Cambridge. Together with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Bilson">Thomas Bilson</ref>, the warden of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Winchester_College">Winchester College</ref>, he became active in attempts to end Catholic <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Recusancy">recusancy</ref>. This work brought him to the attention of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Cecil,_1st_Baron_Burghley">William Cecil, Lord Burghley</ref>, who appointed Bennet as one of his personal chaplains and, in March 1596, aided his appointment as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dean_of_Windsor">Dean of Windsor</ref> in succession to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Day_(bishop)">William Day</ref>. He combined his work as dean with that as master of St Cross.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-odnb-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>He offended <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_I_of_England">Elizabeth I</ref> by preaching against her proposed marriage to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/François,_Duke_of_Anjou">François, Duke of Anjou</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-White-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Despite Bennet's opposition to royal demands that he cede property under his control, he was elected as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Hereford">Bishop of Hereford</ref> in January 1603. He had turned down the offer of the bishopric of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salisbury">Salisbury</ref> in 1598 because that had required him to alienate some of his property rights. He determined in his new role to continue his suppression of Catholic recusancy but was unsuccessful in persuading his superiors– such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_I_of_England">James I</ref> – to grant the diocesan commission that he envisaged to be his instrument in achieving this end. His health began to fail, which he blamed on the "cold and rheumatic" climate of the diocese. He failed in his attempt to move to the vacant bishopric at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Worcester">Worcester</ref> in 1610 and subsequently used his position to promote evangelical work and to improve the education of clergymen,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-odnb-3">[3]</ref> notably through the Leintwardin lecture.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>Bennet was married but details of his wife are unknown. He left a substantial sum of money for his burial expenses and detailed instructions regarding what should be done at his death, which occurred in October 1617.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[lower-alpha 1]</ref> He had designed his own white <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alabaster">alabaster</ref> effigy, which still exists in Hereford cathedral, where he was buried close to where his wife sat. His heir was a nephew, also called Robert Bennet,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-odnb-3">[3]</ref> and his successor at Hereford was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_Godwin">Francis Godwin</ref>, the author of numerous books including the remarkable piece of science fiction titled <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Man_in_the_Moone">The Man in the Moone</ref></hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[8]</ref> He left money to the cathedral, Trinity College in Cambridge, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oxford_University">Oxford University</ref> and the poor of various places, including that of his birth, Baldock,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-price-7">[7]</ref></p>
</text>
