<text id="autogum_academic_doc519" title="A Pilot Intervention Using Gamification to Enhance Student Participation in Classroom Activity Breaks" shortTile="pilot-intervention" author="Lexie  R. Beemer, Tiwaloluwa  A. Ajibewa, Gabriel DellaVecchia, Rebecca  E. Hasson" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4082/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
The present study determined the effect of adding game design elements guided by goal-setting theory to an evidence-based intervention, InPACT, to enhance in-class PA participation among elementary school age students. Specifically, goal-setting theory was used to gamify InPACT by setting attainable classroom goals, providing weekly feedback on student progress toward meeting the goal, and establishing an end-of-study reward to motivate behavior change towards increased PA levels. Our findings demonstrated that gamification increased the percentage of students exercising at a moderate-to-vigorous intensity during an activity break by 27%. Additionally, gamification increased student MVPA participation in all grades and in both boys and girls, with greater increases observed over time in fourth- and sixth-grade classrooms and female students. These findings suggest gamification is a tool that can be integrated into classroom-based PA interventions to enable children to accumulate health-enhancing PA in this environment. </p>

<p>Gamification has previously been applied to pediatric PA interventions outside of the classroom. For example, Verstraete et al. provided game equipment during recess and demonstrated a significant increase in MVPA (from 48% to 61%) in the intervention group, while activity levels decreased in the control group. In the Beat the Street intervention, Coombes et al. examined the use of gamification on active transport to school in children aged 8–10 years by providing rewards such as supplying the school with books. Coombes et al. demonstrated that total MVPA increased during active transport by approximately 3.5 min in children who engaged in the intervention at least 15 out of 63 days. While these authors noted a significant increase in MVPA participation through the provision of rewards, it was unclear how their incentive structures were informed by theory. The present study was guided by goal-setting theory and designed to include setting specific and achievable goals as well as receiving weekly feedback and rewards. This theory-based design resulted in a 27% increase in student MVPA participation during the gamified activity breaks compared with standard activity breaks. At the end of the intervention, approximately 55% of students were exercising at the desired intensity, thereby accumulating 20 min of health-enhancing PA per day in the classroom. This 27% increase in student MVPA was similar to that found by Althoff et al., who demonstrated a 26% increase in daily step counts following the use of the Pokémon Go™ app over a period of 30 days. Future research should seek to determine the independent effect of each game design element (goal setting, feedback, and rewards) in motivating behavior change toward increased PA participation at the desired intensity among children.  </p>

<p>While gamification increased MVPA participation during activity breaks across all grades, a smaller improvement was observed in the third- and fifth-grade classrooms. A key tenet of the goal-setting theory is that individuals must accept the goals they are given. Given the higher baseline participation in these classrooms, students may have benefited from a more challenging goal to motivate an increase in MVPA participation. Future studies should consider including student feedback when developing goals. Another possible reason for the smaller improvements noted in third- and fifth-grade classrooms may relate to the type of rewards provided. Cugelman et al. suggests that the type of rewards offered during an intervention is an important motivating factor for behavior change because the reward may or may not be of value to the community or individual participants. Specifically, Cugelman et al. suggest it is important to identify and tailor specific intervention components that will be receptive to the population and setting. As such, the rewards offered during InPACT (i.e., placing a series of stickers on their class trophy in order to win a field day) may not have appealed as motivational factors to students in third- and fifth-grade classrooms. In addition, other factors that may have contributed to a lack of motivation in these classrooms include: potential differences in social connectedness, perceptions of fun, and capacity to overcome challenges, all of which can affect student motivation. Additional research is needed to better understand the grade-level differences in student motivation for MVPA related to goal setting and external rewards given during gamified activity breaks.  </p>
</text>
