<text id="autogum_bio_doc118" title="Annie Ivanova" shortTile="annie-ivanova" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-03-14" dateModified="2019-09-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Annie_Ivanova" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Annie Ivanova</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Antoanetta "Annie" Ivanova</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulgarian_language">Bulgarian</ref>: Антоанета Иванова; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Traditional_Chinese_characters">Chinese Traditional</ref>: 易安妮 <hi rend="italic">Yì Ānnī</hi>) is an international curator and author, cultural <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Entrepreneurship">entrepreneur</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> and one of Australia's leading authorities on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cultural_diplomacy">cultural diplomacy</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> Ivanova has collaborated with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Centre_Pompidou">Centre Pompidou</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ars_Electronica">Ars Electronica</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barbican">Barbican</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smithsonian_Institution">Smithsonian Institution</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Palace_Museum">National Palace Museum</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Australian_Centre_for_the_Moving_Image">Australian Centre for the Moving Image</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queensland_Gallery_of_Modern_Art">Queensland Gallery of Modern Art</ref>, among others.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>Education</head>
<p>Annie Ivanova holds MA qualifications in Foreign Affairs and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Trade">International Trade</ref> from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monash_University_Faculty_of_Business_and_Economics">Monash University, Graduate School of Business and Economics</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Melbourne">Melbourne</ref>. She pursued interests in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Global_Leadership">Global Leadership</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cultural_Diplomacy">Cultural Diplomacy</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Entrepreneurship">Entrepreneurship</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strategic_Management">Strategic Management</ref>.{cn}</p>
<p>Ivanova was a team leader for an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip_C._Jessup_International_Law_Moot_Court_Competition">International Law Moot Court Competition</ref>, debating the issue of terrorism and human rights through a fictional dispute between two states presented to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Court_of_Justice">International Court of Justice</ref>.</p>
<p>Ivanova's first academic degree is from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Tasmania">University of Tasmania</ref>, graduating with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fine_Arts">Bachelor of Fine Arts (BFA Hons.)</ref> in 1998. Her Honours theses discussed the effect of mass media when reporting stories about war atrocities.</p>
<p>In the late 1980s Ivanova studied at the Bulgarian National College of Polygraphs and Photography. The college was one of the then most progressive professional schools in the country, preparing students for careers in film and TV. She majored in photography, specialising in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Photojournalism">photojournalism</ref>.</p>
<head>Career</head>
<p>Professionally active since 1996, Annie Ivanova has initiated and realised over 80 international exhibitions, conferences and public diplomacy projects. She is a Fellow of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Australian_Institute_of_Company_Directors">Australian Institute of Company Directors</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Australian_Institute_of_International_Affairs">Australian Institute of International Affairs</ref>.</p>
<p>Ivanova has chaired and produced three major international conferences,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> and has been a keynote speaker on wide-ranging Culture &amp; Creative Industries topics.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p>Global work scope spans: USA, Canada, UK, France, Germany, Spain, Italy, Austria, Denmark, Finland, Iceland, Eastern Europe, Greece, Turkey, Malaysia, Thailand, Vietnam, China, Korea, Japan, Singapore, Taiwan, and Australia.</p>
<p>Ivanova co-founded and was the executive director of Australia's first media arts agency Novamedia Ltd.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> Between 2001–2011, Novamedia represented some of Australia's most renowned media artists: Jon MacCormack, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stelarc">Stelarc</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drew_Berry">Drew Berry</ref>, Troy Innocent, Justine Cooper, George Khut. It also initiated and produced projects for Australia's overseas diplomatic missions.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref></p>
<p>In 2012 Australia Unlimited, the national branding campaign promoting Australia's most inspiring achievers, featured Ivanova's blockbuster exhibition 'Wonderland: New Contemporary Art from Australia' at MOCATaipei.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref> The piece was narrated by art historian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edmund_Capon">Edmund Capon</ref>.</p>
<p>Ivanova is the first and only foreign curator to travel across <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taiwan">Taiwan</ref> to work with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taiwanese_aborigines">Taiwanese aborigines</ref>, researching artists from every tribe.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref> She has become a passionate advocate for the preservation of local indigenous heritage. In a public statement she says: "Elders are dying out without their knowledge being recorded. This common to all humankind heritage is becoming endangered and it could disappear within two generations. It needs all the international attention it could get. I'm compelled to do my part."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref> Her pioneering work was recognised in the inaugural Australian Arts in Asia Awards.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[16]</ref></p>
<p>In recognition of her cultural work in Taiwan, Ivanova received a scholarship from the Taiwanese government to undertake Chinese Language studies at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mandarin_Training_Center">Mandarin Training Center</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Taiwan_Normal_University">National Taiwan Normal University</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taipei,_Taiwan">Taipei, Taiwan</ref>, which came to fame as the college of Australia's Chinese-speaking Prime Minister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kevin_Rudd">Kevin Rudd</ref>.</p>
<p>Over the course of her career Ivanova has received over 55 awards from national and international institutions, becoming the most successful independent curator in Australia.</p>
<p>In 2016, Annie Ivanova became the first cultural representative to receive the prestigious ANZ Chamber of Commerce Business Award for "outstanding contribution the Australia-Taiwan Relationship".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-17">[17]</ref> She is also the only businesswoman awarded that year. Annie Ivanova is also the Regional President of Asia Designer Communication Platform.</p>
<head>Personal life</head>
<p>Annie Ivanova was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tryavna">Tryavna</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulgaria">Bulgaria</ref> to an artistic family. Her father was an industrial designer and her mother drama teacher. Her grandfather had a professional photographic studio in the 1930s. During the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Revolutions_of_1989">1989 revolution</ref> Ivanova was working as a junior reporter, assisting <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reuters">Reuters</ref> photographer Oleg Popov. She was a front-line witness of the dramatic events leading to the collapse of communism in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sofia">Sofia</ref>. Soon after, with the help of a colleague, she moved to London where she studied design at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London_College_of_Fashion">London College of Fashion</ref>. In 1994 Ivanova immigrated to Australia.</p>
<p>Ivanova identifies herself as an Australian of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulgarian_Australian">Bulgarian heritage</ref>. She has commented that her international work has always been about 'persuading through culture and ideas that reach across borders'.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-18">[18]</ref> She has said the Balkan atrocities of the 1990s have left a very deep mark in her mind, becoming a motivational force to pursue a career in international relations.</p>
<p>Following long term interests in Asian culture, since 2010 she has been living between Melbourne and Taipei. The Chinese name given to her by a friend is 易安妮 (Yì Ānnī). Yì was taken from the character in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/I-Ching">I-Ching</ref> "Book of Changes" as an auspicious match. In Taiwan she is known by her Chinese name.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-19">[19]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-20">[20]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-21">[21]</ref></p>
<head>Taiwan by Design</head>
<p>Annie Ivanova is the acclaimed author of "Taiwan by Design: 88 products for better living"<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-22">[22]</ref> the first comprehensive design book from the Beautiful Island. The project took 2.5 years to complete and run a hugely successful <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crowdfunding">crowdfunding</ref> campaign raising NT 1,500,000.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-23">[23]</ref>
The North American release of the book featured on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CNN">CNN</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-24">[24]</ref> and it was reported as breaking news by all major newspapers<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-25">[25]</ref> in Taiwan.</p>
<head>Significant Exhibitions</head>
<head>International Curator-in-Residence</head>
</text>
