<text id="autogum_academic_doc427" title="Social Life Cycle Assessment of Brine Treatment in the Process Industry: A Consequential Approach Case Study" shortTile="social-life-cycle" author="Georgios  Archimidis Tsalidis, Gijsbert Korevaar" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5945/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The environmental and economic aspects of the process industry have been investigated thoroughly with different methods, such as life cycle assessment (LCA) and techno-economic analysis. However, the societal performance with Social Life Cycle Assessment (SLCA) of the process industry is little discussed in literature. So far, SLCA practitioners have solely focused on modelling within a chosen temporal window. Therefore, the focus of this study is the first use of SLCA for modelling the societal impact change in response to decisions for brine treatment within the process industry in the port of Rotterdam.  </p>

<p>Industrial brine is a high-concentration solution of salt in water and waste produced in large amounts. Its disposal is, on one hand, problematic due to the environmental degradation of water bodies resulting in the increasing salinity level and its content in critical raw materials and, on the other hand, challenging in eliminating the contained metal elements. The European Directive on Waste mandates member countries to address waste and byproduct reuse. Furthermore, industrial brine contains materials that the European Union has identified as critical raw materials, such as magnesium, and has prioritised them in the Circular Economy Package. Magnesium shows both a high supply risk and economic importance as all available processed magnesium is imported to Europe mainly from far eastern Russia or China. Therefore, the need for a solution to environmental and raw material problems led to the development of sophisticated brine disposal methods. One of these methods actually improves water recovery to the highest level while reducing brine. This method is called Zero Liquid Discharge (ZLD) and currently represents state-of-the-art technology. ZLD technology eliminates brine disposal via its conversion to highly pure water (95–99% water recovery) and salt. It typically consists of a preconcentration stage based on membrane-based technologies, evaporation, and crystallization mainly based on thermal-based technologies, which enable the industry to conform to regulations. The preconcentrating stage (for instance, filtration) is easy to use in waste water treatment plants and vital for the following two stages. On the other hand, the cost of thermal-based technologies can become a burden for a system employing ZLD. Therefore, benefits should be achieved in other aspects of the system that employs ZLD, such as environmental, social, regulatory, etc. The Zero Brine project aims at applying the ZLD technology in a demineralized water plant (coded as DW) in the port of Rotterdam, in the Netherlands, to recover clean water, sodium salt, and magnesium. </p>

<p>Mining in Russia has a distinct characteristic. Modern Russian traditions are still influenced by more than 70 years of communist rule and ideology (1917–1991). Among the surviving traditions of that period is an authoritarian type of governance, some weak civil society institutions, and some underdeveloped democratic decision-making procedures. Therefore, companies do not necessarily need to secure social acceptance to make tough decisions with major consequences. In Russian company towns, such as Kuldur where the magnesium mining occurs, negative environmental impacts from mining companies are offset by job creation and social services provided by the same companies.  </p>

<p>The 2005 World Summit on Social Development identified sustainable development goals based on the three aspects of sustainability, i.e., economic development, social development, and environmental protection. The environmental, economic, and social facets can be evaluated with LCA, life cycle costing, and SLCA, respectively. Unlike LCA, SLCA is not yet standardized, and researchers are not consistent in using indicators. As a result, various social indicators have been used in literature, and SLCA is still undergoing evolution. SLCA follows the same framework as the LCA method, from the goal and scope definition phase to the life cycle inventory, the life cycle impact assessment, and interpretation phases. SLCA is described as “a social impact assessment technique that aims to assess the social and socio-economic aspects of products and their potential positive and negative impacts along their life cycle”. Therefore, researchers suggest that decision-making based on the SLCA method leads to more beneficial situations for the society and general sustainability. </p>
</text>
