<text id="autogum_whow_doc226" title="Avoid Dealer Status to Obtain Capital Gains" shortTile="avoid-dealer-status" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-03-29" dateModified="2019-03-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Avoid-Dealer-Status-to-Obtain-Capital-Gains" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Avoid Dealer Status to Obtain Capital Gains</head><p>Two different groups purchase and sell capital assets: dealers and investors. Dealers are generally subject to more stringent financial and tax laws and regulations. If you are considered a dealer, you will not be able to claim capital gains on, for example, the sale of a property; the sale will be considered business income. Capital assets include both securities and real estate. Of the two, real estate transactions are usually more complex.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Decide what you want to do with the property you own. If you own a house, you may want to make improvements or sell the property. <figure rend="Avoid Dealer Status to Obtain Capital Gains Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Obtaining capital gains when you sell the property may be dependent upon whether you live in the house and how long you have owned the house. The process of "flipping" a house, or buying and selling it within a short period of time, may put you in the dealer category.</item>
<item>The method you use to sell a house could also affect dealer status. You might advertise the home as "For Sale By Owner" on a sign that you place on your front lawn to avoid being seen as a dealer. If you advertise in multiple newspapers and on television, you may be seen as a dealer.</item></list></item>
<item>Limit the number of properties you sell. If you own multiple properties and sell and buy properties frequently, the government may view you as a dealer. There is an extensive legal case history that determines the parameters for dealer status. <figure rend="Avoid Dealer Status to Obtain Capital Gains Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Subdividing a property for the purpose profit could propel you to dealer status. Frequency and the extent to which you develop a property to be divided also plays a role. In one case, a person with a non-real-estate job sold several lots of land over a twenty-year period and obtained capital gains.</item></list></item>
<item>Don't set up an office from which you purchase and sell real property. Professional real estate agents have offices. If you open an office, the government may consider you a dealer. <figure rend="Avoid Dealer Status to Obtain Capital Gains Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Avoid hiring someone to sell your property, as in a person over which you have a supervisory role or a person who you have on a payroll. The government may consider this an activity consistent with being a real estate professional, which would put you in the dealer category. <figure rend="Avoid Dealer Status to Obtain Capital Gains Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Devote only a small portion of your time to purchasing and selling property to avoid dealer status. If you avoid devoting a significant amount of time to selling a property, the government may not consider you to be a dealer. <figure rend="Avoid Dealer Status to Obtain Capital Gains Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>The factors that influence dealer status in real estate are evaluated on a case-by-case basis; no single determinant is more important than another.</item>
<item>Avoiding dealer status may help lower your tax rate. In the United States, the 2011 tax rate for dealers who sell a property is 35 percent; those who obtain capital gains are taxed at a rate of 15 percent.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Investors should carefully review the rules that govern transactions involving capital assets to avoid dealer status and associated capital gains issues.</item></list>
</text>
