<text id="autogum_academic_doc681" title="Residential Land Use Change in the Wissahickon Creek Watershed: Profitability and Sustainability?" shortTile="residential-land" author="John Sorrentino, Mahbubur Meenar, Donald Wargo" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5933/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
In 2018, it was estimated by the Population Division of the Department of Economic and Social Affairs of the United Nations that 55% of the world’s inhabitants live in urban areas. This is projected to rise to 68% by 2050. The movement to “major urban agglomerations” involves a choice between the cities and their suburbs and ultimate land use change. To accommodate this increasing population, residential development can take place on infilled or reclaimed land with higher density and existing infrastructure, or on newly-developed land with lower density and little or no infrastructure.  </p>

<p>The work for this paper involved a major metropolitan watershed that encompasses both a segment of the City of Philadelphia, and all or part of 15 suburban municipalities. The main objective was to determine and compare the economic, energy, and environmental impacts of scenarios of placing housing according to profitability criteria on the one hand, and environmental sustainability criteria on the other. The profitability criteria involved the profit generated by the average housing unit sale, as well as neighborhood characteristics (e.g., an income index and a crime index), in each zip code within the municipalities. The sustainability criteria included proximity to infrastructure and institutions already in place. Both scenarios had areas that were restricted from development. The prior expectations were that the scenario based on profitability would have higher profit, and that based on sustainability would have significantly smaller environmental impacts.  </p>

<p>Different aspects of the work in this paper have been investigated by previous authors. Much of the literature on the geographical aspects of housing, as shown in Hasanzadeh et al., deals with the demand side. Using public participation Geographic Information Systems (GIS), the authors investigated whether people inhabited the parts of the urban structure that their classification of urbanists, semi-urbanists, and nature-lovers suggested they would. The majority did not. On the housing supply side, Saiz used US Geological Survey Digital Elevation Model and National Land Cover data in GIS to examine geographical restrictions on supply in US metropolitan statistical areas over 500,000. The author concluded that those areas with greater restrictions (including regulatory) had higher housing prices and a lower price elasticity of housing supply. Hudson contrasted the treatment of sustainable housing development with the traditional approach in the US, of development without much concern for natural capital. Sandberg approached sustainable housing by looking at proposed downsizing of dwellings in Finland. Musse et al. applied a “backcasting” approach to providing low-income housing in a Brazilian city through a vision of a sustainable future. Koshkar et al. studied the impact of urban growth and residential densification on urban–suburban green space and ecosystem services in sections of the Stockholm region. Göçmen, Z. et al. surveyed many county and municipal governments in Wisconsin, USA to ascertain the types of sustainable practices, e.g., New Urbanism, that the agencies implemented with respect to future residential development. Stachuro examined the behavioral implications of creating “eco-districts” with their own sustainable infrastructure within urban areas. Hanlon concentrated on suburban re-development after decades of expansion in Baltimore, MD, USA. Sorrentino et al. and Sorrentino et al. used housing buildout in an urban–suburban watershed to determine the relative impacts of alternative development scenarios. Dunphy et al. proposed a business model that values sustainable retrofit at more than monetary values and involved co-production by sellers and buyers.  </p>

<p>Use of the GREET 2018 model to estimate air pollution and greenhouse gas emissions appeared in Almeida et al.. Using life-cycle analysis, the focus was on how different battery technologies would influence electric automobile emissions over time. Their approach was similar to the work in this paper in that scenarios were evaluated in terms of emissions. However, their scale was national and not related <hi rend="italic">per se</hi> to housing location.  </p>

<p>In the water-related dimension, a recent example of the hydrological modeling approach is Guo et al.. The authors incorporated low impact development (LID) into a Storm Water Management Model (SWMM), and built scenarios showing the effects of green roofs, permeable pavement, and other LID technologies on runoff. Chao et al. reported the results of implementing sustainable residential development on water consumption in two urban regions in Australia. Xian et al. used remote sensing to assess the impacts on water-quality parameters of increased impervious surface and population density in the Tampa Bay, FL, USA watershed. Nesheim and Barkved evaluated the sustainability potential of watersheds altered for hydropower production in Norway, using a process that combined ecosystem services valuation with the value of uses that accrue to beneficiaries from the human intervention itself.  </p>
</text>
