<text id="autogum_whow_doc002" title="Enjoy a Good Book" shortTile="enjoy-good-book" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2007-04-09" dateModified="2018-08-18" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Enjoy-a-Good-Book" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Enjoy a Good Book</head><p>One of life's greatest activities is reading. Not only can you learn a lot by reading, books can take you to far away places that you have never dreamed of. On top of that, enjoying a book can be a pleasurable and memorable experience. There are millions of books out there, and no two are exactly alike! Pick up a book and read!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Learn to read. Hopefully, if you are reading this, you have grasped this step already. If you already know how to read, learn to read better. This can be accomplished by reading more. You can never be too good at reading. <figure rend="Enjoy a Good Book Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try an audiobook.</item></list></item>
<item>Discover a genre you like. Fiction and nonfiction have several genres, and it won't be hard to find something you like. Even magazines and newspapers are great reading material! If you want, find several genres you like. Reading will be more enjoyable if you are reading diverse things. <figure rend="Enjoy a Good Book Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Consider game books.</item></list></item>
<item>Get a book. This can be accomplished by buying one, borrowing one from a friend, or visiting your local lending library. Try not to over look this step. Reading's hard to do if you don't have a book. <figure rend="Enjoy a Good Book Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find some time. You might have the excuse that you don't have time to read. Put aside some time and devote it just to that: reading. Thirty minutes is a good length; however, even twenty, fifteen, or ten minute sessions can be enough. <figure rend="Enjoy a Good Book Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get comfortable. Sitting in a comfortable seat can help you enjoy your book a lot more.Or even just laying back and relaxing. On top of that, being in a comfortable setting will make you want to stay and read. But don't limit your  place to chairs. You can sit on a couch, a bed, or even the floor if you prefer! Make sure your setting is nice and quiet too. <figure rend="Enjoy a Good Book Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Find_an_Old_Friend">Find a friend</ref>. Reading can be more enjoyable when you do it with a friend. Try to read the same book. Although if you read different books then keep each other informed on how good the book is. This will build up and keep you anticipated to read it too. The best part is reading what each of you just read. That way, you can discuss your book in a friendly manner. Also, a friend can encourage you to read. Don't hesitate to encourage your friend also. <figure rend="Enjoy a Good Book Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Read. Just read! You'll find that novel completed in no time at all! <figure rend="Enjoy a Good Book Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You also may want a snack or something to drink. Just don't spill on your reading materials!</item>
<item>Use a bookmark. It is so frustrating to come back and realize that you already read that part of the book. You may also skip over a few chapters and not know what's going on. Use one that is fun and colorful so you won't mind having it with you.</item>
<item>Get a notebook and make notes.</item>
<item>If you are anxious to get to the ending, don't force the words into your head. Relax a little and take a break when you need one.This way you will really enjoy what you're reading.</item>
<item>If it was a very long book or one you didn't think you would like to begin with (but you ended up liking it) reward yourself by getting the movie, or getting some ice cream or just having a good time!</item>
<item>If you get into hard spots to get past, then reread it, slowly. It may help to read it aloud. If it is still tough, then consider getting the audio-book. They are very good, and the fun voices make them enjoyable.</item>
<item>You should not be tired when reading! This will only tempt you you to fall asleep or watch TV.</item>
<item>If you want, you can listen to a CD or your MP3/iPod while reading.  If you especially enjoy a book you can replay the CD when you read it again or read another book.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>you may just enjoy reading yet.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><list type="unordered"><item>books</item></list></item></list>
</text>
