<text id="autogum_interview_doc558" title="part10_Ingrid Newkirk, co-founder of PETA, on animal rights and the film about her life" shortTile="partingrid-newkirk" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-20" dateModified="2018-02-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ingrid_Newkirk%2C_co-founder_of_PETA%2C_on_animal_rights_and_the_film_about_her_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  I don’t know.  In this business I am very easy to cubby hole.  As someone said to me the other day—they had seen the HBO special—and they said, “Are you really a sad obsessed person?”  And I thought, “No, I’m not really a sad person, except when I lie awake at night in winter thinking about all the animals out without shelter, and then I’m sad!”  Who wouldn’t be?  Wouldn’t anybody be sad if they have a heart?  It’s just that I’ve seen so much.  In Taiwan, standing in a slaughterhouse for dogs.  You have to get through it, and to me, having foster-cared chickens; I know if anyone took a chicken in the way they took a dog in they would come to love that chicken and come to see that chicken had personality.  That chicken would wait for you to come home in the evening.  They can’t laugh this off, because it’s actually true!  Chickens develop bonds with people the same way dogs do.  They know you’ve rescued them if you’ve rescued them; they’ll sit on your lap while you’re watching TV.  Having had those relationships it’s just as hard for me to stand in a chicken slaughterhouse.  But if <hi rend="italic">anyone</hi> had had those experiences they would feel the same way.  I think it’s hard to pigeon-hole me as sad.  I’m not.  I’m joyous.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I didn’t see you as sad in that movie.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  Oh really?  Oh, good.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It’s interesting you brought that up, because a thought I had watching the film is that people always find something to criticize with a person.  It’s not, “Okay, Ingrid just really loves animals and wants to help them” but “you’re obsessed and sad.”  If you were taking a $1,000,000 salary every year and driving around in a Mercedes, they would say, “She’s not really in it for the animals, she’s completely stuffing her pockets with her cause.”  But you are not doing that [Newkirk earned $32,000 from PETA in 2005] and the film makes that clear; so instead, the criticism is that you are sad and obsessed.  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  Right.  Thank you.  Thank you.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You’re either milking it for all it is worth—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  Or you are some weird ascetic.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do you think drives people to jump at negative spin?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  It’s human nature.  You see the thing at a silly level with celebrities.  They love them, and then they tear them down.  Or they are just salivating, hoping for somebody to trip and fall.  I think it’s jut another nasty past of human nature.  Especially if you think somebody has done something that makes you a little guilty, it’s very hard to overcome people’s guilt.  I know I was the same way when somebody first suggested to me I should not eat animals.  I was quite defensive about it.  I remember that.  There are many other things along the way that I have had to fight out in my own head and get rid of the defensiveness.  I think people are defensive, and they don’t want someone to tell them what to do.  They know a lot of their life is frivolous.   I had an assistant once who wanted to leave for the evening, and I said, “Could you just finish this before you go home?” and he said, “I’ve got a life!” and I said, “Yeah, me too, but mine doesn’t consist of playing video games for five hours!” [Laughs].  But as you get older I think your perspective might change and whatever drives you it occurs you only have so much time, and you want to accomplish this.</p>
</text>
