<text id="autogum_bio_doc394" title="John Halle" shortTile="john-halle" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-01-17" dateModified="2018-11-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Halle" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>John Halle</head>For other people named Main Page, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page_(disambiguation)">Main Page (disambiguation)</ref>.
<figure><caption>1565 woodcut</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">John Halle</hi>, or <hi rend="bold">John Hall of Maidstone</hi> (c. 1529/1530 – c. 1568)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ODNB-1">[1]</ref> was an English surgeon, known as a medical writer and poet.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Born in 1529 or 1530, Halle became a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Worshipful_Company_of_Chirurgeons">Worshipful Company of Chirurgeons</ref>, and practised as a surgeon at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maidstone">Maidstone</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kent">Kent</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DNB-2">[2]</ref> He is thought to have been a supporter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Wyatt_the_younger">Thomas Wyatt the younger</ref>, and involved in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wyatt's_rebellion">Wyatt's rebellion</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ODNB-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Works</head>
<p>As a poet, Halle was influenced by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Wyatt_the_elder">Thomas Wyatt the elder</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ODNB-1">[1]</ref> His works were:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DNB-2">[2]</ref></p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">Certayne Chapters taken out of the Proverbes of Solomon, with other Chapters of the Holy Scripture, and certayne Psalmes of David, translated into English Metre</hi>, London (Thomas Raynalde), 1549.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">A Poesie in Forme of a Vision, briefly inveying against the most hatefull and prodigious artes of Necromancie, Witchcraft, Sorcerie, Incantations, and divers other detestable and deuilishe practises, dayly used under colour of Judiciall Astrologie</hi>, London, 1563.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">The Court of Vertue, contayning many Holy or Spretuall Songes, Sonnettes, Psalmes, Balletts, and Shorte Sentences, as well of Holy Scripture, as others</hi>, with musical notes, London, 1565. This book seems by the prologue to have been written to contrast with <hi rend="italic">The Court of Venus</hi>, a collection of love songs.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DNB-2">[2]</ref> Dedicated to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Cole_(Archdeacon_of_Essex)">Thomas Cole</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ODNB-1">[1]</ref></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">A most excellent and learned woorke of chirurgerie, called Chirurgia parva Lanfranci, Lanfranke of Mylayne his briefe: reduced from dyvers translations to our vulgar-frase, and now first published in the Englyshe prynte</hi>, black letter, 4 pts., London, 1565. Translation from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lanfranc_of_Milan">Lanfranc of Milan</ref>. It contains a woodcut portrait of the translator, "æt. 35, 1564". Appended were two other works: <hi rend="italic">A very frutefull and necessary briefe worke of Anatomie</hi>; and <hi rend="italic">An Historiall Expostulation: Against the beastlye Abusers, both of Chyrurgerie, and Physyke, in oure tyme: with a goodlye Doctrine and Instruction, necessarye to be marked and folowed, of all true Chirurgiens</hi>, reprinted in volume 11 of the publications of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Percy_Society">Percy Society</ref>, London, 1844, edited by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Joseph_Pettigrew">Thomas Joseph Pettigrew</ref>. Halle denounced in the latter the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quackery">quacks</ref> of the day, and opposed the combination of magic, divination, and physic.</item>
<item>A metrical version of <hi rend="italic">The Prouerbes of Salamon, thre chapters of Ecclesiastes, the sixthe chapter of Sapientia, the ix chapter of Ecclesiasticus, and certayne psalmes of Dauid</hi>, London (Edward Whitchurch), n.d., dedicated to John Bricket, esq., of Eltham. Halle complained that chapters of the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Book_of_Proverbs">Book of Proverbs</ref></hi>, translated by him into English metre, 1550, had been attributed to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Sternhold">Thomas Sternhold</ref>.</item>
<item>English translation of Benedict Victorius Faventinus's and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niccolò_Massa">Niccolò Massa</ref>'s treatises <hi rend="italic">De Morbo Gallico</hi>; <hi rend="italic">Cure of the French Disease</hi>, a manuscript in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bodleian_Library">Bodleian Library</ref>, which also contains letters from Halle to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Cuningham">William Cuningham</ref>.</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Commendatory_verse">Commendatory verses</ref>, in English, prefixed to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Gale_(surgeon)">Thomas Gale</ref>'s <hi rend="italic">Enchiridion of Chirurgerie</hi>, 1563, and to the same author's <hi rend="italic">Institution of a Chirurgian</hi>, 1563.</item></list>
</text>
