<text id="autogum_voyage_doc428" title="Croatia" shortTile="croatia" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=8540" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Croatia</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://croatia.hr/en-GB/Homepage">Croatia</ref></hi> (<ref target="Croatian%20phrasebook">Croatian</ref>: <hi rend="italic">Hrvatska</hi>) is a Mediterranean country that bridges <ref target="Central%20Europe">Central Europe</ref> and the <ref target="Balkans">Balkans</ref>. It is on the eastern side of the Adriatic Sea, across from <ref target="Italy">Italy</ref> on the western side. Croatia is bordered by <ref target="Hungary">Hungary</ref> to the north, <ref target="Slovenia">Slovenia</ref> to the northwest, <ref target="Serbia">Serbia</ref> to the east, <ref target="Bosnia%20and%20Herzegovina">Bosnia and Herzegovina</ref> to the southeast, and <ref target="Montenegro">Montenegro</ref> to the south.</p>

<head>Regions</head>
<p>There are three distinct areas of Croatia: Lowland Croatia (cr: <hi rend="italic">Nizinska Hrvatska</hi>), Littoral Croatia (<hi rend="italic">Primorska Hrvatska</hi>) and Mountainous Croatia (<hi rend="italic">Gorska Hrvatska</hi>) and these can be neatly split into five travel regions:</p>

<head>Cities</head>
 

<list type="unordered">
<item> – the capital and largest city</item>
<item> – historic coastal city and a <ref target="UNESCO%20World%20Heritage%20site">UNESCO World Heritage site</ref></item>
<item> – ancient port city with Roman ruins</item>
<item> – biggest town in <ref target="Istria">Istria</ref> with the Roman amphitheater (commonly called Arena)</item>
<item> – capital of <ref target="Slavonia">Slavonia</ref> and an important city</item>
<item> – Croatia's largest and main port</item>
<item> – biggest city of north-central Dalmatia with rich history</item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Nacionalni park Krka</hi>) – river valley near <ref target="%C5%A0ibenik">Šibenik</ref></item>
<item> Island of </item>
<item> Island of </item>
<item> Island of </item>
<item> Island of </item>
<item> Island of </item>
<item> on the Makarska Riviera</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Nacionalni park Plitvička jezera</hi>) — waterfalls, lakes and botanical assets easily gets it in the top 5 of most beautiful nature attractions of <ref target="Europe">Europe</ref>, it is a <ref target="UNESCO%20World%20Heritage%20site">UNESCO World Heritage site</ref> .</item>
<item> – mountainous region that spans the border between Slovenia and Croatia</item>
</list>


<head>Climate</head>
<p>Northern Croatia has a temperate continental climate, while the central and upland regions have an Alpine climate. The Adriatic coast has a pleasant Mediterranean climate. Spring and autumn are mild along the coast, while winter is cold and snowy in the central and northern regions. The average temperature inland in January ranges from -10°C to 5°C; August 19°C to 39°C. The average temperature at the seaside is higher: January 6°C to 11°C; August 21°C to 39°C.</p>

<head>Terrain</head>
<p>Croatia's geography is diverse with flat agricultural plains along the Hungarian border (Central European area), low mountains and highlands near the Adriatic coastline, and islands. There are 1,246 islands; the largest ones are <ref target="Krk">Krk</ref> and <ref target="Cres">Cres</ref>. The highest point is Dinara at 1,830 m.</p>

<head>History</head>
<p>In ancient times, what is now Croatia was part of the regions of Illyria and Dalmatia. This region came under <ref target="Roman%20Empire">Roman control</ref> and became a province known as Illyricum from 27 BC. In the 5th century, Rome was declining and the Ostrogoths seized an opportunity to rule the area for a short period. The Avars arrived soon after, incorporating the land into the Avar Khaganate. </p>

<p>In the early 7th century the Croats came and defeated the Avars, and formed two duchies: Croatia and Pannonia. The establishment of the Trpimirović Dynasty ca 850 strengthened the Dalmatian Croat Duchy, which together with the Pannonian principality became a kingdom in 925 under King Tomislav. The independent Croatian kingdom lasted until 1102 when Croatia, after a series of dynastic struggles entered into a personal union with Hungary, with a Hungarian king ruling over both countries. In 1526, after the Battle of Mohács, in which Hungary suffered a catastrophic defeat against the Ottoman Turks, Croatia severed its relationship with Hungary and its parliament (Sabor) voted to form a new personal union with the Habsburg Monarchy. Croatia remained an autonomous kingdom within the Hapsburg state (and later <ref target="Austria-Hungary">Austria-Hungary</ref>) until the empire's dissolution following its defeat in World War I.</p>

<p>In 1918, a short-lived State of Slovenes, Croats and Serbs (carved out of south Slavic parts of Austria-Hungary) joined the Kingdom of Serbia to form the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes, later renamed Yugoslavia in 1929. The new state was unitarist in character, erasing all historical borders within its new territorial division, which resulted in a strong movement for more autonomy for Croatia. This was achieved in 1939, only days before the start of World War II, when Croatia was granted broad autonomy within Yugoslavia as Banovina of Croatia. When Germany and Italy attacked Yugoslavia in 1941, the state was dissolved, parts of it annexed to Germany and Italy, and puppet governments installed in Croatia and Serbia. Almost immediately, a strong resistance movement was formed, led by communist leader Josip Broz "Tito" (whose father was a Croat), which gained broad popular support, but by the end of World War II, the Ustashe puppet government and its militia had systematically murdered approximately 30,000 Jews, 29,000 Roma, and at least 300,000 Serbs, mostly at the notorious death camp they built in <ref target="Jasenovac">Jasenovac</ref>. After the end of World War II, a new, communist Yugoslavia was formed with Tito becoming "president for life". Tito ruled with a strong hand, using political repression and secret police to quell any separatist sentiments, with the official motto of the new country being "Brotherhood and Union". Still, because Yugoslavia didn't belong to the Warsaw Pact, having broken off political ties with the USSR in 1948, it was by far the most open socialist country in Europe and its citizens enjoyed more civil liberties and a higher living standard than the rest of the Communist bloc.</p>

<p>After Tito's death in 1980, the weakening of political repression led to a period of political instability. Faced with the rise of nationalist sentiment, a decade-long recession, and the weakening of communist grip on power on the eve of the fall of communism in Eastern Europe, the first free elections were held in Yugoslavia in almost 45 years. In these elections, nationalists won power in all Yugoslav republics, leading to a rise in interethnic tensions, which culminated with Croatia and Slovenia declaring their independence from Yugoslavia in 1991. This led to open war in newly independent Croatia and later in Bosnia and Herzegovina which declared its independence in 1992. The wars ended four years later, in 1995, with a decisive Croatian victory in Operation Storm, bringing peace to both countries. The anniversary of Operation Storm is celebrated as Thanksgiving Day in Croatia every August 5.</p>

<p>After a period of accelerated economic growth in the late 1990s and 2000s Croatia joined NATO in 2009 and the European Union in 2013. Croatia today is a functioning liberal democracy, with a free market system and a robust welfare state.</p>
</text>
