<text id="autogum_interview_doc557" title="part9_Ingrid Newkirk, co-founder of PETA, on animal rights and the film about her life" shortTile="partingrid-newkirk" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-20" dateModified="2018-02-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ingrid_Newkirk%2C_co-founder_of_PETA%2C_on_animal_rights_and_the_film_about_her_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="Ingrid_Newkirk_on_Ingrid_Newkirk">Ingrid Newkirk on Ingrid Newkirk</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Did you and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alex%20Pacheco">Alex Pacheco</ref> have a falling out?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  No—well, we’ve had <hi rend="italic">many</hi> fallings out in our years—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Like a family—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  Yes, yes.  We’ve had many an argument, many a falling out, but he separated a long time ago.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are you still in contact with him?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  Yes, he was in touch with the office a couple of weeks ago.  I was on the road.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is he looking at becoming involved again?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  I’m not sure what he wants to do at the moment and I’m not sure he does, either.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How would Ingrid Newkirk twenty years ago look at Ingrid Newkirk now?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  God, what a horrid question!  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  Do you mean twenty years ago?  Because we’ve had the group twenty-seven years.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Just twenty years ago, the person you were then looking at the person you are now.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  God, less wrinkles!  I don’t know the answer to that.  I really don’t.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think you’ve achieved a lot of the things you had wanted back then?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  I’m never looking ahead.  All I want is to reduce suffering and to get people to think of animals in a different way, and that’s as true then as it is now.  Perhaps I was—I don’t know if I could say if I’m less or more optimistic, I really can’t.  I think I was just me, only younger.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think other people would say that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  I think so…I think so.  I don’t know, really.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you have any regrets?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  Professionally?  Because that’s what we are talking about…</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Or personally.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  I’m not going to talk about personally!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Just in general—in your life.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  These are just terrible questions!  I think you can always look back and in hindsight, knowing the results of what you’ve done, think, ‘Maybe I could have been more strategic then’; or ‘If I had only known…maybe I could have pushed harder then.’  But I think in compromising sometimes, people may find it surprising, but I’m so anxious not to lose ground, but to gain ground so that we can move ahead, that I might take less than if I had known I could have pushed harder what I could have got.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  See.  Sometimes terrible questions birth wonderful answers.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  Oh, pwah!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  The nature of this interview is on a permanent encyclopedia—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  Ah!  God, help me, kill me.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  --so the questions are designed not just around your work, but also around who you are as a person.</hi></p>
</text>
