<text id="autogum_academic_doc734" title="Use of GIS Tools in Sustainable Heritage Management—The Importance of Data Generalization in Spatial Modeling" shortTile="use-gis-tools-sustainable" author="Mateusz Ciski, Krzysztof Rząsa, Marek Ogryzek" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5616/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Sustainable development is nowadays one of the main components used in spatial development. It is considered a Constitutional Principle of the Republic of Poland, as well as in another European countries. The definition of sustainable development can be found in Polish legislation—it is defined in the Environmental Protection Act as the socio-economic development integrating political, economic, and social actions, balanced with environmental protection and a permanence of basic natural processes, in order to ensure the possibility of satisfying the basic needs of communities or individual citizens in both the present and future generations. In The Brundtland Report “Our Common Future” sustainable development is defined as “development that meets the needs of the present without compromising the ability of future generations to meet their own needs”. The report highlighted three fundamental components of sustainable development: environmental protection, economic growth, and social equity. According to Pearce and Turner, sustainable development is associated with maximizing the benefits of economic development, in connection with protecting the quality and usability of natural resources. Such economic development must not only mean an increase in income per capita, but also the comprehensive improvement of other social aspects. Culture, as the basis of social life, is considered to be one of the four pillars of sustainable development. Culture can be both the goal of development of a given society as well as the method of that development, but above all it is the development regulator. Cultural heritage is one of the main elements of such described culture and it is understood much more broadly than just in the field of the protection of monuments, it also consists of: local traditions and customs, cultural affiliation or the sources of non-material values. A greater sense of cultural identity can also contribute to the further development of social capital, because individuals and communities with a stronger sense of place are more actively involved in social matters. People living in places with a higher concentration of significant historical areas tend to have a stronger sense of place and/or increased social capital. Cultural heritage is traditionally regarded as a non-economic factor of spatial development. However, treated as a resource and properly managed, it can be transformed into capital that can play an important role in the sustainable development strategies, both at the local and national level. The term “cultural heritage” covers a broad spectrum of meanings that are not obvious and can be ambiguous. Cultural heritage is important as a source of remembrance and inspiration, and at the same time contributes to national and local identity, which is essential for sense of place and social cohesion. Various studies have shown the influence of cultural heritage as an element of sustainable development on spatial planning, or tourism development. </p>

<p>To properly manage cultural heritage within sustainable development, regardless of the specific goal, knowledge of the location of objects constituting a material element of cultural heritage is necessary. In this article, the starting point for the conducted research and analyses were non-movable monuments in Poland. The legal basis for the protection of monuments in Poland is the Act of 23 July 2003 on the protection of monument and the care of monuments. According to Article 3 of the above-mentioned Act, a non-movable monument is a real estate, its part or a complex of real estate, which is the work of humankind or is related to its activity, and is a testimony to a past era or event; whose protection is in the public interest because of its historical, artistic or scientific value. Article 6 of the Act indicates that non-movable monuments may include: cultural landscapes, urban and rural systems, building units, works of architecture and construction, works of defense construction; technical objects; cemeteries; parks, gardens, and other forms of designed greenery; as well as places commemorating historical events or the activities of remarkable characters or institutions. Non-movable monuments are registered by entry in “the register of objects of cultural heritage” (pol. rejestr zabytków), kept by the Voivodeship Conservators of Monuments. Voivodeship registers of objects of cultural heritage currently contain approx. 85 thousand entries on non-movable monuments, diversified in terms of type. A non-movable monument can be entered into the register on the basis of: an ex-officio decision issued by the Voivodeship Conservator of Monuments, or at the request of the owner of the non-movable monument or perpetual usufructuary of the land on which the non-movable monument is located. In the conducted research, the authors used data obtained from The National Heritage Board of Poland. The National Heritage Board of Poland (NHBP) is a cultural institution established by the Minister of Culture and National Heritage; its present structure was formed in 2007. NHBP is a state agency that gathers and disseminates information on heritage, sets standards for its protection and conservation, and aims to raise the social awareness on cultural heritage of Poland in order to save it for future generations in accordance with the strategy for sustainable development. The generic division of non-movable monuments used by NHBP is shown in the <figure>Figure 1</figure>. </p>
</text>
