<text id="autogum_bio_doc505" title="Baldassare Donato" shortTile="baldassare-donato" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2004-12-28" dateModified="2018-05-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baldassare_Donato" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Baldassare Donato</head><p><hi rend="bold">Baldassare Donato</hi> (also <hi rend="bold">Donati</hi>) (1525-1530 – June 1603) was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Italy">Italian</ref> composer and singer of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Venetian_School_(music)">Venetian school</ref> of the late <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Renaissance_music">Renaissance</ref>.  He was <hi rend="italic">maestro di cappella</hi> of the prestigious <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Marco_di_Venezia">St. Mark's Basilica</ref> at the end of the 16th century, and was an important figure in the development of Italian light secular music, especially the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Villanella">villanella</ref>.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Details of his early life are unavailable; it is not even known where he was born.  The first record of Donato is as a singer at St. Mark's in Venice in 1550, and he was given charge of the musical training of the boys there in 1562.  When <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gioseffo_Zarlino">Gioseffo Zarlino</ref> took over the post of <hi rend="italic">maestro di cappella</hi> from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cipriano_de_Rore">Cipriano de Rore</ref> in 1565, Donato was demoted back to being a singer; conflict between the two men seems to have been a feature of life at St. Mark's, culminating in a climactic fight in 1569, publicly and scandalously, during the Feast of St. Mark.  In 1577 Donato took a position at the Scuola Grande di S Rocco, another Venetian church with an impressive musical tradition and substantial performing ensemble; however he failed to get along with his employers there as well, resigning by 1580.  In 1588 he became assistant <hi rend="italic">maestro di cappella</hi> at St. Mark's, while Zarlino was still alive (whether because of reconcilement or politics is not clear), and in 1590 he took over the post of his former antagonist, holding it until his death in 1603.</p>
<head>Music and influence</head>
<p>Donato represented a progressive trend in the Venetian school, which was already a progressive tradition compared to the other major contemporary Italian musical styles (especially as compared to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_School">Roman School</ref>).  The progressive trend in the Venetian school was represented by composers such as Donato, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giovanni_Croce">Giovanni Croce</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrea_Gabrieli">Andrea</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giovanni_Gabrieli">Giovanni Gabrieli</ref>; the conservative trend involved composers and theorists such as Zarlino, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cipriano_de_Rore">Cipriano de Rore</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Claudio_Merulo">Claudio Merulo</ref>, who tended to follow the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dutch_School_(music)">Franco-Flemish</ref> style which was predominant almost everywhere else in Europe until after mid-century.</p>
<p>Donato's sacred music is the most conservative portion of his output, usually using <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polyphony">polyphony</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giovanni_Pierluigi_da_Palestrina">Palestrina</ref> style, but also using some of the grand <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polychoral">polychoral</ref> effects of the Gabrielis.  In spite of his evident disdain for Zarlino's conservatism, he clearly absorbed some of his style and teaching, as can be seen in his smooth mastery of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Counterpoint">counterpoint</ref> and Zarlinoesque use of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Consonance_and_dissonance">dissonance</ref>, at least when he was deliberately composing in the Franco-Flemish style.</p>
<p>Probably his greatest significance to music history is in the development of a light secular form known as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Villanella">villanella</ref>, a lighter form of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Madrigal_(music)">madrigal</ref>, of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Naples">Neapolitan</ref> origin.  Some of these pieces may have been intended for dancing, and they were evidently popular.  They are similar to the French <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chanson">chanson</ref>, often have a memorable melody in the topmost part, contain vigorous cross-rhythms, and avoid the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polyphony">polyphonic</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chromaticism">chromatic</ref> complexity of the mid-century madrigal.</p>
<p>Donato also wrote madrigals in a more serious style, as well as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psalm">psalm</ref> settings, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Motet">motets</ref>, and ceremonial music.</p>
<head>References and further reading</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Article "Baldassare Donato", in <hi rend="italic">The New Grove Dictionary of Music and Musicians</hi>, ed. Stanley Sadie.  20 vol.  London, Macmillan Publishers Ltd., 1980.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Standard_Book_Number">ISBN</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/1-56159-174-2">1-56159-174-2</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gustave_Reese">Gustave Reese</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Music in the Renaissance</hi>.  New York, W.W. Norton &amp; Co., 1954.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Standard_Book_Number">ISBN</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/0-393-09530-4">0-393-09530-4</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eleanor_Selfridge-Field">Eleanor Selfridge-Field</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Venetian Instrumental Music, from Gabrieli to Vivaldi.</hi>  New York, Dover Publications, 1994.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Standard_Book_Number">ISBN</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/0-486-28151-5">0-486-28151-5</ref> (Note: while this book contains nothing on Donato, it has detailed and readable background on the Venetian school and associated activity at St. Mark's.)</item></list>
</text>
