<text id="autogum_academic_doc370" title="Solute Transport and Transformation in an Intermittent, Headwater Mountain Stream with Diurnal Discharge Fluctuations" shortTile="solute-transport" author="Adam  S. Ward, Marie  J. Kurz, Noah  M. Schmadel, Julia  L.A. Knapp, Phillip  J. Blaen, Ciaran  J. Harman, Jennifer  D. Drummond, David  M. Hannah, Stefan Krause, Angang Li, Eugenia Marti, Alexander Milner, Melinda Miller, Kerry Neil, Stephen Plont, Aaron  I. Packman, Nathan  I. Wisnoski, Steven  M. Wondzell, Jay  P. Zarnetske" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4441/11/11/2208/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Results and Discussion</head><head> 3.1. Conservative Solute Tracer Transport Fluctuates Consistently with Unsteady Discharge</head>
<p>
Observations of conservative tracer (Ura) isolate the role of time-variable discharge on residence times within the study reach. In-stream time series of concentrations (<figure>Figure 2</figure>A) and mass flux (<figure>Figure 2</figure>D) are visually consistent between injections, indicating that diurnal discharge fluctuations are controlling the timing of conservative mass transport and storage. In all four injections (falling, rising, peak, minimum), mass flux is reduced at the daily minimum discharge conditions, and rebounds rapidly when discharge and surface water extent increase. For the injections conducted on the rising and peak discharge conditions, the highest concentrations are advected through the study reach so rapidly that they do not experience minimum discharge conditions (i.e., peaks prior to minimum discharge; <figure>Figure 2</figure>A). As a result, the highest concentration water was preferentially exported from the study reach under higher discharges rather than being stored. Consistent with this preferential export, the late-time tail is no longer visible as the second rising limb of discharge occurs (X = 60 h since 00:00 on day of injection; <figure>Figure 2</figure>A). In contrast, the peak concentration water from the tracer test remained in the study reach during the minimum discharge conditions (<figure>Figure 2</figure>A). Consequently, peak concentration water was stored in the reach rather than rapidly exported during minimum discharge conditions.  </p>

<p>Despite the differences in timing of advection of the highest concentration water relative to the time of minimum discharge, we found few differences between the injections with respect to calculated solute transport metrics. For example, we found no significant trends between discharge and any of the Ura breakthrough curve metrics (Table 2). Similarly, a single SAS function produced reasonable representations of the observed Ura time series for all injections (<hi rend="italic">σerror</hi> = 3.2 μg L−1). Moreover, all SAS model parameters were well constrained by the data. The <hi rend="italic">Smin</hi> was the parameter least sensitive to discharge. Both <hi rend="italic">QU</hi> and <hi rend="italic">SU</hi> were well constrained and sensitive to discharge. The best-fit parameters vary by a factor of 4–6-fold (Table 3). However, the underflow time scale estimated as <hi rend="italic">SU/QU</hi> varied from about 21 h at low flow to about 31 h at high flow. The SAS function varied systematically with discharge (<figure>Figure 3</figure>I–L and <figure>Figure 4</figure>). The long-term mean SAS function has an offset of about 2.5 m3, representing the approximate plug flow volume in the study reach. The SAS function peaks around 15 m3 of storage (the most frequently exported age-ranked storage), and then decays toward the oldest storage.  </p>

<p>During the rising, peak, and falling discharge injections, the tracer age was almost perfectly aligned with the ages being predominantly exported rather than stored. In contrast, tracer was too young to be exported rapidly during the minimum discharge injection. Thus, tracer injected at minimum discharge was predominantly stored in the reach, ultimately labeling older age-ranked storage that is more slowly and consistently exported from the study reach. These differences are attributable to the timing of the study release, as all four injections were well-described by a single SAS function and did not exhibit wide variation in summary metrics such as temporal moments. Indeed, the evolution of SAS functions, and particularly the conditions experienced shortly after each injection, may dominate overall transport and transformation dynamics in the study reach.  </p>

<head> 3.2. Observed Variation in Solute Transport is Primarily Due to Storage Release Timing Relative to an Oscillating Diurnal Cycle in the Underlying Transport Processes</head>
<p>
The best-fit SAS function reveals that high-discharge periods are dominated by the release of younger water, and lower-discharge periods by the release of older water (<figure>Figure 3</figure>). Conceptually, this means periods of higher discharge preferentially shunt younger water through and out of the system, bypassing older storage. In contrast, during periods of low discharge, the water entering the upstream end of the study segment cannot be rapidly transported through and out of the reach. Instead, water entering during low-discharge conditions is almost entirely stored, and older water is displaced and released from the study reach. This means that the general principles of the pulse-shunt model may be operating on a daily basis for a small headwater stream experiencing diurnal fluctuations in discharge. Overall, we found a single parameterization of the SAS function provided a strong fit to observed data, which indicates that the same consistent diurnal cycles of transport processes were present during all four injections and varied systematically with diurnal fluctuations in discharge. However, the observed in-stream time series demonstrate that the timing of the solute tracer release relative to the diurnal cycle is important in determining which age-ranked storage is sampled by the solute tracer, and how the tracer is ultimately stored in and released from the study reach.  </p>
</text>
