<text id="autogum_interview_doc454" title="part8_US presidential candidate Duncan Hunter speaks to Wikinews" shortTile="partus-presidential" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-12-12" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_presidential_candidate_Duncan_Hunter_speaks_to_Wikinews" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="Gay_Marriage">Gay Marriage</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Do you consider yourself States Rights?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  I think so.  I think that's a general philosophy.  Federalism.  I don't think it's absolute; I think there are some issues in which the country as a nation has an interest.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Why would you support the Federal Marriage Amendment if you are for States Rights?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  Because of what I just told you.  I think that states rights are important, but there are some issues in which the nation as a community has an interest, and of course the Marriage Act, one of the fears has been if you end up with one or two states that support homosexual marriage, what you'll end up doing is producing a flow of people going to a particular state, receiving their marriage license in that state, and then due to the Full Faith and Credit Clause of the Constitution, having those marriages recognized in the state where the marriage is banned.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Doesn't DOMA prevent that?  The Defense of Marriage Act?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  Well, if you end up with a federal act that prohibits it--that's what I'm saying, if you prohibit it on a national basis in a Constitutional Amendment or on a federal act, then you eliminate the process of having one or two states generating homosexual marriages and then demanding they be recognized under the Full Faith and Credit Clause.  Do you understand what I'm saying?  If you have one state that allows it, then you have a recognition requirement of the other states.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> But didn't DOMA prevent that?  Massachusetts currently has gay marriage.  So didn't DOMA prevent that from happening?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  Prevent what from happening?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Prevent a swell of people going to Massachusetts and getting married, and then taking their marriage to another state that bans it and forcing them to recognize it?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  What's your point?  I think that's good.  That it does prevent it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> So do you no longer support amending the Constitution is my question.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  No, I think it has still yet to be fully decided as to whether a few states can at some point basically become proliferators, if you will, of non-traditional marriage.  Here's my position:  If it is necessary to amend the Constitution, then I think we will need to do it.  I think you need to have a Defense of Marriage on a uniform basis in all fifty states.  What it takes, in terms of satsifying the federal courts to do that, should be done.  So if it is required that it is necessary to have an amendment to the Constitution to do that, I would support that.  But doing what it takes to have a uniform treatment to defend traditional marriage across all the states.</p>
</text>
