<text id="autogum_interview_doc675" title="part18_Gay Talese on the state of journalism, Iraq and his life" shortTile="partgay-talese-state" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-27" dateModified="2019-01-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gay_Talese_on_the_state_of_journalism%2C_Iraq_and_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Would you agree with the idea that children don't grow up reading much anymore, outside of what's required?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  I think they do. There's always been a number of young people who are in the category of being readers and the majority are not. And that was true when I was a child and when my wife was a child. My wife has now been a professional reader and editor for fifty years. But there were those who were drawn to reading and those who were not, found it boring or were more outward than internalized in their nature. Many of the people I know, who are very successful and read a lot, are people who experienced illness or injury when they were young. They grew up with books because they could not interact at a young age with their contemporaries.  Off the top of my head, Frances Ford Coppollo, people I know, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin%20Scorsese">Scorsese</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lee%20Iacocca">Lee Iacocca</ref>... Or many people who have had to sit when they were eleven or six or five. They had to stay in bed, they were drawn to books and the books became their action. The books became their activity. They vicariously lived through the work of writers or maybe they lived through music, maybe they lived through something else. But that idea of being kept apart from the drive to be popular, the drive to be part of a clique that seemed to be in favor, when you are isolated, then maybe you are drawn out of your isolation by what you read and get a larger sense of the world.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You're saying that there never was really a time when people read more unless they had cause to read a lot based upon their circumstances?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  Well I'll talk about what I really know, which is what I have personally experienced. I grew up in a home with very few books. There was one book, and I had no idea how my father got it. Maybe someone gave it to him. Short stories by the French writer Guy de Maupassant. I read those stories, all of them, twice probably, when I was ten. Later on, when I was in high school, 12, 13, 14, 15, I was reading fiction. The fiction I was reading, and I wrote about this in my last book, was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frank%20Yerby">Frank Yerby</ref>. People have never heard of him; he's not in any canon. Frank Yerby was a black man, who lived in Spain and wrote these romance novels. And there must have been seven or eight or nine of them. They sold very well. A few of them were made into movies I never saw. I loved those stories because they were richly described. The characters were very very detailed. Very precise detail. And that shaped my life. I was a writer who does very much insist on and has affection for detail.</p>
</text>
