<text id="autogum_bio_doc406" title="Nestan-Darejan of Kakheti, Queen of Kartli" shortTile="nestandarejan-kakheti" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-08-12" dateModified="2019-08-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nestan-Darejan_of_Kakheti%2C_Queen_of_Kartli" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Nestan-Darejan of Kakheti, Queen of Kartli</head>"Nestan-Darejan of Kakheti" redirects here. For the 17th-century queen of Imereti, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Darejan_of_Kakheti,_Queen_of_Imereti">Darejan of Kakheti, Queen of Imereti</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Nestan-Darejan</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Georgian_language">Georgian</ref>:ნესტან-დარეჯანი; fl. 1556–1612) was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Georgian_consorts">queen consort</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Kartli_(1484–1762)">Kartli</ref>, a kingdom in eastern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Georgia_(country)">Georgia</ref>, as the wife of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simon_I_of_Kartli">Simon I</ref>, whom she married in 1559. Nestan-Darejan was a daughter of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Levan_of_Kakheti">Levan of Kakheti</ref> and a half-sister of Levan's successor to the throne of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Kakheti">Kingdom of Kakheti</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_II_of_Kakheti">Alexander II</ref>. Her husband spent nearly five decades fighting the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Safavid_dynasty">Safavid Iranian</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman</ref> encroachments on his kingdom, twice losing his throne and personal freedom. Nestan-Darejan suffered further, being humiliated by his half-brother, the king of Kakheti, who capitalized on Simon's difficulties to attack and loot Kartli. After Simon had been sent a prisoner to Iran in 1569, Nestan-Darejan's estates had been pillaged by Prince Bardzim Amilakhori, Alexander's father-in-law; and in 1580, following Simon's return to Kartli and his defeat by Alexander at Dighomi, the latter carried off after the battle his half-sister's drawers on the point of a lance. Nestan-Darejan outlived her husband and died sometime after 1612, having mothered six children, including Simon's successor to the throne of Kartli, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_X_of_Kartli">George X</ref>.</p>
<head>Marriage</head>
<p>Nestan-Darejan was born of Levan of Kakheti's second marriage to a daughter of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shamkhal_of_Tarki">shamkhal of Tarki</ref>, whom the king married in 1529 after he divorced his first wife, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tinatin_Gurieli">Tinatin Gurieli</ref>. Nestan-Darejan married Simon I of Kartli in 1559. This union was one of the first interdynastic marriages between the Kartlian and Kakhetian branches of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bagrationi_dynasty">Bagrationi dynasty</ref>, holding sway over the two breakaway successors of the once united <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Georgia">Kingdom of Georgia</ref>. The union was followed by a pact between the two monarchies, one aim being to evict the Iranian garrison from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tbilisi">Tbilisi</ref>, the capital of Kartli. Levan of Kakheti eventually hung back, but allowed his son and heir, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prince_Giorgi_of_Kakheti_(died_1561)">Prince Giorgi</ref>, to join Simon's army. The Georgians lost the ensuing confrontation and Giorgi was killed on the battlefield.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTERayfield2012171–172-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Persecution</head>
<p>After the Iranian army captured Simon in battle and sent for imprisonment at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alamut">Alamut</ref> in 1569, Queen Nestan-Darejan found herself in a hostile environment in Kartli. Main threats to her security came from her half-brother Alexander II, a disowned son of Levan, on whose death he succeeded as king of Kakheti, having defeated and massacred his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prince_El-Mirza_of_Kakheti">half-brothers</ref>. Out of favor with the Safavid protégé <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_XI_of_Kartli">Daud-Khan</ref>—Simon's Islamized brother and a rival ruler at Tbilisi, who was married to Alexander's relative—the queen became a target of harassment by Prince Bardzim Amilakhori, Alexander II's father-in-law, who, joined by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Ksani">duke of Ksani</ref>, raided and completely looted her estate.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEAllen1970505-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Return to power</head>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lala_Mustafa_Pasha's_Caucasian_campaign">invasion of the Ottoman army</ref> of the Georgian lands led by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lala_Kara_Mustafa_Pasha">Lala Kara Mustafa Pasha</ref> and the quick collapse of Daud-Khan's regime in 1578 compelled the Iranian government to release Simon as the only ruler capable to mount resistance to the Ottoman advance. Back to his homeland, Simon had his domestic adversaries, including Prince Amilakhori, arrested. Amilakhori and the duke of Ksani pleaded for mercy and approached Nestan-Darejan, who persuaded her husband to issue amnesty for them, having reclaimed, in return, what has been lost to these noblemen and, further, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Akhalgori">Akhalgori</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mejuda">Mejuda</ref> from the duke and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kaspi">Kaspi</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karbi,_Georgia">Karbi</ref> from Amilakhori.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBrosset1850155-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Further misfortunes</head>
<p>Alexander of Kakheti's enmity to Simon remained undiminished owing to his hatred of his half-sister. In 1580 the Kakhetian army surprised Simon, staying without troops at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dighomi">Dighomi</ref>, and put him to flight. Alexander could not get at Simon, but he, the Georgian chronicle says, dishonored Nestan-Darejan and, "like a brigand", rode off bearing his half-sister's drawers high upon a lance. Simon vowed revenge and assaulted Alexander's army at Chotori, putting the Kakhetians to rout and Alexander to flight.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEAllen1970505-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEAllen1932157-4">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTERayfield2012178-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>After years of heavy fighting, Simon's turbulent reign ended in 1600, when he was captured by the Ottoman army and sent in prison to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constantinople">Constantinople</ref>. His son, George X, succeeded him. Nestan-Darejan outlived both her son, who died in 1606, and her husband, who died in captivity in 1611. His remains were brought by the Georgian merchant Diakvnishvili from Constantinople to Nestan-Darejan and interred at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Svetitskhoveli">cathedral of Mtskheta</ref>. Nestan-Darejan's subsequent life is obscure. She lived on to see the accession to the throne of her young grandson, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luarsab_II_of_Kartli">Luarsab II</ref>, subsequently a Christian martyr and saint of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Georgian_Orthodox_Church">Georgian Orthodox Church</ref>, and died sometime after 1612.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBrosset1850374-6">[6]</ref></p>
<head>Children</head>
<p>Simon and Nestan-Darejan had six children, four sons and two daughters:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Prince Giorgi (c. 1560 – 1606), King of Kartli as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_X_of_Kartli">George X</ref>;</item>
<item>Prince Luarsab (fl. 1561–1589), taken as a hostage to Iran in 1582;</item>
<item>Prince Aleksandre (fl. 1561–1589);</item>
<item>Prince Vakhtang (fl. 1600), sometime governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Akhaldaba">Akhaldaba</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dirbi">Dirbi</ref>. He had a son, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prince_Luarsab_of_Kartli">Luarsab</ref> (died in 1650), adopted by King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rostom_of_Kartli">Rostom of Kartli</ref> in 1639;</item>
<item>Princess Elene (fl. 1583–1609), wife of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manuchar_II_Jaqeli">Manuchar II Jaqeli</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Principality_of_Samtskhe">Atabag of Samtskhe</ref>;</item>
<item>Princess Fahrijan-Begum (fl. 1582), who married Shahzada Sultan Hamza Mirza (died in 1578 or 1586), son of Shah <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tahmasp_I">Tahmasp I</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mohammed_Khodabanda">Mohammed Khodabanda</ref>.</item></list>
<head>Ancestry</head>
</text>
