<text id="autogum_interview_doc509" title="part3_Wikinews interviews Jeremy Hanke, editor of MicroFilmmaker Magazine" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-11" dateModified="2019-08-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Jeremy_Hanke%2C_editor_of_MicroFilmmaker_Magazine" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>In addition to the software improvements, the 24fps recording of cameras like the DVX100 and the HVX200 when combined with the shallow depth-of-field created by the Redrock Micro M2 and other 35mm lens adapters gives digital filmmakers a way to create an amazing filmic look—even if they can’t do it with the really expensive cameras we mentioned earlier.</p>
<p>Finally, the “absolutely” part.  The most powerful thing that allows low-budget filmmakers to compete with Hollywood films is content.  The fact that so much quality filmmaking gear can be had at such a low prices means that anyone who is willing to put in the work to write a good script and shoot it well can have a film that can gain a following.  Some of the best TV shows I have seen of late could easily have been shot as a low budget film.  (For example, much of CBS’ Jericho, which might have been the most creative show to be introduced in the last twenty years, could easily have been shot on a shoestring budget as a film.)</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">J.F.</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Distributing a movie can be one of the hardest aspects of production. Do you think that today, with the Internet, it's easier to go about doing this and make a profit than it might have been twenty years ago?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mr. Hanke:</hi> Actually, yes I do.   Today, something like 50% of all Indie films turn a profit.  However, considering that many of the films that are made are still extremely esoteric avant garde art films, you can probably estimate that 70-80% of films that deal with any form of readily accessible narrative can turn a profit.  (This is the huge advantage of shooting a $10,000 no-budget film as opposed to a $200 million Hollywood film.  The $200 million Hollywood film has to sell $400 million in tickets to turn a profit, to cover both the production and advertising budgets.  The $10,000 film often only has to sell $15,000 worth of DVDs, Amazon UnBox viewings, and art house shows to turn a profit.)</p>
<p>One of the easiest ways to take advantage of the internet to make your film profitable is to use the CreateSpace service (which used to be CustomFlix and is now owned by Amazon).  They allow you to upload your entire film and high-rez cover art and then they just print a copy whenever someone orders it from Amazon.com or your website, issuing you a percentage without you ever having to buy pre-printed copies to sell.  Additionally, they will let you create a rentable or purchaseable download of your film through the Amazon UnBox service, which further enables you to get your film out there and make it profitable.  (Just remember to make a sexy website with a trailer for your film to encourage people to check it out.  If you want a Flash site but aren’t Flash savvy, the new Adobe Encore CS3 actually has some very powerful abilities to create a professional Flash website with only your DVD menu creation skills required.)</p>
</text>
