<text id="autogum_voyage_doc431" title="Lanzhou" shortTile="lanzhou" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=19080" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Lanzhou</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Lanzhou</hi> (兰州; <hi rend="italic">Lánzhōu</hi>) is the capital of <ref target="Gansu">Gansu province</ref> of <ref target="China">China</ref>.</p>
<head>Understand</head>

<p>Lanzhou is an industrial city of about three million people. It is located on the shores of the <ref target="Along%20the%20Yellow%20river">Yellow River</ref> and was a major stop on the <ref target="Silk%20Road">Silk Road</ref>; in those days, it was known as the Golden City. From the 5th to the 11th century the city was a major seat of Buddhist learning, and it acquired its present name during the Qing Dynasty in 1656. Until the 19th century, Lanzhou was the primary point for crossing the Yellow River via a bridge made by chaining a flotilla of boats together with a road on top to cross on.</p>

<p>Lanzhou used to be one of the most polluted cities in China but the situation has improved.</p>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lanzhou Zhongchuan International Airport</hi> ( LHW ) (is situated 75km from the city centre of Lanzhou). Daily flights to <ref target="Beijing">Beijing</ref>, <ref target="Changsha">Changsha</ref>, <ref target="Chengdu">Chengdu</ref>, <ref target="Chongqing">Chongqing</ref>, <ref target="Dunhuang">Dunhuang</ref>, <ref target="Fuzhou">Fuzhou</ref>, <ref target="Guangzhou">Guangzhou</ref>, <ref target="Haikou">Haikou</ref>, <ref target="Hangzhou">Hangzhou</ref>, <ref target="Jiayuguan">Jiayuguan</ref>, <ref target="Kunming">Kunming</ref>, <ref target="Nanjing">Nanjing</ref>, <ref target="Qingdao">Qingdao</ref>, <ref target="Shanghai">Shanghai</ref>, <ref target="Shenyang">Shenyang</ref>, <ref target="Shenzhen">Shenzhen</ref>, <ref target="%C3%9Cr%C3%BCmqi">Ürümqi</ref>, <ref target="Wenzhou">Wenzhou</ref>, <ref target="Wuhan">Wuhan</ref>, <ref target="Xiamen">Xiamen</ref>, <ref target="Xi%27an">Xi'an</ref> and <ref target="Zhengzhou">Zhengzhou</ref>.</item>
</list>



<head>By train</head>

<p>All long-distance trains nowadays use , a huge modern building that from the street looks like a gigantic Walmart. From here, high-speed trains rush to Xining (1 h 15 min), Jiayuguan (4 h 30 min), <ref target="Urumqi">Urumqi</ref> (12 h), Xian (4 h), Wuhan and Beijing. </p>

<p>Conventional trains still use the old <hi rend="bold">Lanzhou Railway Station</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Lanzhou Huoche Zhan</hi>) at the south end of Pingliang Lu at Tianshui Lu. This is also served by a few high-speed trains, and by the airport train.</p>

<head>By bus</head>

<p>The <hi rend="bold">East Long-Distance Bus Station</hi> is on Pingliang Lu. Destinations include Dunhuang (24 hours), Guyuan (8), Jiayuguan (17), Pingliang (5), Tianshui (4), Urumqi (38), Xi'an (15), Yinchuan (12) and Zhangye (12).</p>

<p>The <hi rend="bold">West Long-Distance Bus Station</hi> is on Xijin Xilu. Destinations include Linxia (3 hours), Liujiaxia (2), Xining (5) and Hezuo (5).</p>

<p>The <hi rend="bold">South Long-Distance Bus Station</hi> serves Xiahe (6 hours).</p>

<head>Get around</head>


<p>The Metro runs east-west across the city, linking downtown with West Railway Station.</p>

<p>The #1 Bus is really useful getting around Lanzhou. It travels from Lanzhou Station to the Lanzhou Hotel, Qingyang Lu, Xihu Gongyuian Park, Qiliheqiao and ending at Lanzhou West Station. It also connects the train station to the starting point of the shuttle bus to the airport, <ref target="http://www.openstreetmap.org/%3Fmlat%3D36.05082%26amp%3Bmlon%3D103.84969%23map%3D18/36.05082/103.84969%26amp%3Blayers%3DTD">here</ref>.</p>

<p>There's a city bike scheme, with pick-up / drop-off stations dotted around.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Gansu Provincial Museum (甘肃省博物馆)</hi>, XiJin Dong Lu (Take bus 1, 18, 31, 50, 53, 58, 59, 71 and get off at Qilihe Qiao Station.). Tu-Su 09:00-17:00. Silk Road history in one place. The museum is divided into two sections, natural resources and historic exhibits. It houses collections of various colour-painted potteries of Neolithic Age and treasures of ancient grottoes. It's also home to precious linen and silk fabrics, books, wooden and bronze vessels, bamboo writing-slips from the Han Dynasty (206 BC-220), frescoes and many other items. The 4-meter high Mammoth is a replica of one excavated from the Yellow River basin in 1973. There are also exhibits of rare modern animals, such as pandas, golden monkeys and red-crowned cranes.The iconic exhibit is the Galloping Horse, excavated in 1969 in Wuwei County, Gansu Province. A horse gallops with long tail waving and head perking; three hooves are in the air, while the right hind hoof has alighted on the back of a small flying swallow. Bird and horse turn in surprise to try to see what's happening. A small replica from the gift shop is Y500. Free, but you need your passport to enter. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Green Corridor along Binhe Road</hi>. (滨河路绿色长廊)</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Five-Spring Mountain</hi> (Wuquanshan Gongyuan). (五泉山) A jumble of a poor amusement park and some renovated temples.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Zhongshan ("Morning") Bridge</hi> (Zhongshan Qiao, 中山桥), Zhongshan Lu (Intersection of Nanbinhe Dong Lu &amp; Zhongshan Lu). Always open. With a name like that, it ought to be a scenic arch on a willow-pattern plate. It's actually a sturdy metal trellis, which it needs to be to withstand the surging, foaming Yellow River, and it's far from pretty. When completed in 1909, it was the first permanent bridge across the river. Pedestrian only nowadays, it's the natural route to and viewpoint for White Pagoda Mountain. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">White Pagoda Mountain</hi> (Baitashan 白塔山). Park ranging over the wooded hillside north of the river, dotted with pagodas and shrines. Enter next to Zhongshan Bridge and wander uphill by any path, eventually to the White Pagoda Temple. (There's also a cable-car from south bank of the river.) Refurbished in 2013 yet the buildings look well-worn, several boarded-up; the "Jade Temple" compound is in the best condition. Free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">White Cloud Temple</hi> (Baiyun Taoist Temple) is on the south river bank, Nanbinhe East Road, one block west of Zhongshan Bridge. It's much less touristy, a peaceful little compound, so the wear-and-tear on the buildings feels venerable rather than run-down. Free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Qiaomen Mosque</hi> (Bridge Gate Mosque, 桥门清真寺) is just south of the bridge.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Xiguan Mosque</hi> is on Cuiyingmen, one block south of the Taoist Temple. Anywhere else, this would be a hard-hat zone, as (in 2018) the mosque compound is being rebuilt. But if you pick your way past blocks of cladding and piles of sand and trailing pipes and cables, the mosque itself remains open. It's quite a simple modern design.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Waterwheel Garden</hi>, Nanbinhe Dong Lu. (水车博览园) Small park along the Yellow River housing impressive traditional waterwheels, originally used to irrigate farmland around Lanzhou. Free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sculptures of the Mother River</hi>. (黄河母亲像)Gansu sculpture by the famous sculptor He E creation,6 meters long,2.2 meters wide,2.6 meters tall, weighing 40 tons, from "mother" and a "baby" of composition.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Gaolan Mountain</hi>. (皋兰山) Cool place to be when the summer heat kicks in.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Qiaomen Mosque</hi>. (桥门清真寺)</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tianfusha Palace</hi>. (天斧沙宫)</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bingling Si</hi>. (炳灵寺石窟) Cave grottoes and a boat ride, all in one trip.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Yantan Park</hi> (雁滩公园). Since founding a state, here has built up to 20 km ring at the dam and 10 km asphalt road, and across the Yellow River tributary, the Yantan and urban integration. Later turned into parks, gardens lush forests, beautiful scenery, has built a pavilion, and the Yellow River scenery mutual authentic, very magnificent.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Solemn Temple</hi> (庄严寺). The great cause of thirteen years (617 years ), Xue Ju in Lanzhou later became the emperor, the solemn temple as the palace. Tang Pingdingxue cited later renamed the temple, by the gate, and QianDian rooms, the main hall, houdian constitute HHS falls. Original gate board, "Chi stately Temple" six characters, is the famous calligrapher Li Puguang the book, font bold. The main hall after a Buddhism godness Guanyin wall murals, dignified and beautiful, wearing white, wanran such as yarn, Panicum Jingping, Cuise such as the new.</item>
</list>
</text>
