<text id="autogum_academic_doc411" title="Biological Adaptations Associated with Dehydration in Mosquitoes" shortTile="biological-adaptations" author="Christopher  J. Holmes, Joshua  B. Benoit" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2075-4450/10/11/375/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Interactions Between Dehydrating Conditions and Vectorial Capacity</head><head> 3.1. Contributions of Behavior to Vectorial Capacity</head>
<p>
Recent publications have explicitly noted a lapse in knowledge on several facets of vector ecology, such as the relationships between environmental factors and disease ecology, vector-host interactions and virus ecology, and a disparity in findings that precipitation positively or negatively correlates to human infection with WNV. It is becoming apparent that the net difference in vectorial capacity must be determined by understanding both the ecological effects and altered biological components of the vector. An improved understanding of how environmental effects, heat, cold, and dehydration directly affect mosquito physiology should be emphasized in future research. Specific attention should be placed on understanding the underlying components that are associated with stress response and compensatory mechanisms that prompt biological responses. </p>

<head> 3.1.1. Blood Feeding and Water Content Regulation Influence Disease Transmission Dynamics</head>
<p>
Blood feeding dynamics are complex, but, simply put, they are driven by reproduction, hunger, nutritional status, and water content regulation. Rapid dehydration prompts similar expression patterns to that of thermal stress, but slower dehydration results in altered trehalose synthesis in other fly systems, which is a major blood sugar in flies, and it is known for its desiccation-resistant properties. Interestingly, dehydration prompts an increase in trehalose breakdown in <hi rend="italic">C. pipiens</hi>, which corresponds to a predicted increase in WNV transmission. Likewise, we see a reduction in the trehalose transporter <hi rend="italic">Ag</hi>TreT1 in <hi rend="italic">An. gambiae</hi> due to desiccation or heat exposure, which results in a decreased infection of the midgut with oocysts of the parasite <hi rend="italic">Plasmodium falciparum</hi>. These findings indicate three themes: (1) desiccation similarly affects gene regulation in prominent representative vectors from both the Culicinae and Anophelinae subfamilies, (2) the outcome of realized infection with arthropod-borne disease is partially dependent upon the metrics by which infectivity is determined, and (3) ecological consequences of the underdeveloped and sometimes confounding interactions between dehydration, disease infection, and heat exposure dynamics must be addressed. </p>

<head> 3.1.2. Mosquito Humidity Sensing is Influenced by Hydration Status and Likely Contributes to altered Pathogen Transmission</head>
<p>
Dry heat has been attributed to the activation of mosquitoes, but moist-heat has been implicated in increased probing behavior. As the time devoid of water increases, mosquitoes discriminate less on the source of a bloodmeal, and, once a host is found, the feeding rates of mosquitoes in higher temperatures likewise increases. Interestingly, dehydration phenotypes may drive sensing that is associated with humidity and perspiring hosts, both of which have been suggested as important host cues. Although humidity sensing in insects, outside of <hi rend="italic">Drosophila</hi>, is under researched, important candidate genes within the mosquito 2La inversion polymorphism have been identified. These genes include an ionotropic glutamate receptor, which is similar to some <hi rend="italic">D. melanogaster</hi> ionotropic receptors that have been implicated in hygro- or thermo-sensation (such as IR25a, IR40a, or IR93a); and, a heat shock protein (Hsp90) that has also been implicated in increased desiccation tolerance in <hi rend="italic">C. pipiens</hi>. As many conserved chemosensory genes exist in insects, hygrosensation receptor candidates may also be conserved. For example, an odorant binding protein (Obp59a) contributed to humidity-sensing in <hi rend="italic">Drosophila</hi> and it was proposed as a candidate for disease control methods as well as a proxy for climate change progress in mosquitoes. Associations between humidity sensing, host-preference, and disease transmission in mosquitoes are severely wanting, but recent studies indicate new focus in the area. </p>

<head> 3.2. Alternative Perspectives: Utilizing Environmental Stressors as a Proxy for Behavioral and Biological Adaptation to Insecticide Resistance</head>
<p>
Stressors, such as dehydration, starvation, temperature, infection status, and insecticide exposure, can contribute to compensatory alterations in factors, such as feeding behavior, survival, vectorial capacity, fecundity, longevity, and activity. Theoretically, these stressors (disregarding insecticide exposure) have acted upon mosquitoes for over 150 million years, in such time, mosquitoes have become exceptionally efficient vectors for a plethora of pathogens. Mosquitoes still possess the ability to establish insecticide resistance and persist although mosquito control methods have existed for less than a millionth of that time. It may be—through inherent susceptibilities, recurrent exposure, and conserved responses to stressors—that mosquitoes have developed an exceptional ability to adapt and overcome stress. These adaptive abilities are of great concern regarding insecticide application, but also provide a unique opportunity to study how mosquitoes respond to a relatively new stressor in reference to preexisting stressors. </p>

<p>Over time, the selective pressures for resistance that are prompted by pesticide administration begin to place the success of control programs at risk, where more than half of the malaria vectors have already developed pyrethroid resistance in less than a single decade. In one such scenario, the LT50 for <hi rend="italic">An. gambiae</hi> that was treated with deltamethrin increased by 2.6-fold in just over four months. By researching both insecticide and conserved stress responses in mosquitoes, novel strategies regarding stressor combinations and underlying genetic components may be elucidated. Regardless of the stressor, be it insecticidal or environmental, responses should be comprehensively researched and directly compared to one another. </p>
</text>
