<text id="autogum_interview_doc642" title="part0_Popular soap opera &amp;apos;The Young and the Restless&amp;apos; celebrates 35 years on the air" shortTile="partpopular-soap" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-25" dateModified="2014-04-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Popular_soap_opera_%27The_Young_and_the_Restless%27_celebrates_35_years_on_the_air" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Popular soap opera 'The Young and the Restless' celebrates 35 years on the air</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 26, 2008</hi></p>
<p>The popular <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">American</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/soap%20opera">soap opera</ref> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Young%20and%20the%20Restless">The Young and the Restless</ref></hi>, currently the reigning <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daytime%20Emmy%20Awards">Emmy Award-winner</ref> for best daytime drama, celebrated 35 years on the air Wednesday. </p>
<p>The 35th anniversary also comes after the series, known colloquially as <hi rend="italic">Y&amp;R</hi>, marked its 1,000th straight week as the highest-rated soap opera in a daytime slot. In addition to keeping the #1 spot every week since December 1988, <hi rend="italic">Y&amp;R</hi> has also been the top-rated soap in the African-American demographic since 1991. </p>
<p>A trend-setter since the beginning, <hi rend="italic">Y&amp;R</hi> relied on character-driven storytelling, accentuated with understated sexuality from its cast, which at that time was mostly young, in order to bring in teenage and twentysomething viewers who were ignored by soap producers and networks up to that time. These traits immediately set <hi rend="italic">Y&amp;R</hi> apart from other soap operas, and other soaps have since mimicked <hi rend="italic">Y&amp;R'</hi>s formulaic approach to offering something for everyone, especially younger viewers. </p>
<p>Since premiering on March 26, 1973, <hi rend="italic">Y&amp;R</hi> has become a worldwide cultural institution in its own right, racking up an impressive 100 Emmy Awards between the writers, producers, cast and crew since 1974. The show has aired in over 100 countries, including Australia, New Zealand, France, Germany, Italy, and Turkey, and reaches a worldwide audience of ten million daily. So far-reaching was <hi rend="italic">Y&amp;R'</hi>s appeal that Romanian gymnast <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nadia%20Comaneci">Nadia Comaneci</ref> chose the serial's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nadia's%20Theme">theme song</ref> as accompanying music to her floor exercises at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1976%20Summer%20Olympics">1976 Summer Olympics</ref>. In Australia, where <hi rend="italic">Y&amp;R</hi> has aired since 1974, the show was canceled by the original network that aired it in 2007, prompting a widespread fan backlash in that country. It was quickly moved to a pay channel.</p>
<p>Over the past 35 years, countless characters, marriages, divorces, births, deaths, and every joy and trauma in between have visited the residents of Genoa City, where <hi rend="italic">Y&amp;R</hi> is set. To commemorate the milestone, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:TheCustomOfLife">Mike Halterman</ref> from <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> interviewed three actresses who have played long-running characters on <hi rend="italic">Y&amp;R</hi>, and asked them to share their memories. All three responded to questions about what being on <hi rend="italic">Y&amp;R</hi> means to them, what their favorite storylines were, what they perhaps would have wanted to do all over again, and what they'd love to tell their fans directly.</p>
<p>Below are portions of all three interviews. </p>
<head id="Wikinews_interviews_Y&amp;R_cast_members">Wikinews interviews <hi rend="italic">Y&amp;R</hi> cast members</head>
<p>Throughout March, Mike Halterman spoke to three <hi rend="italic">Y&amp;R</hi> actresses: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Melody%20Thomas%20Scott">Melody Thomas Scott</ref>, who has portrayed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nikki%20Newman">Nikki Newman</ref> since 1979; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michelle%20Stafford">Michelle Stafford</ref>, who has portrayed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phyllis%20Summers%20Newman">Phyllis Summers Newman</ref> since 1994; and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tricia%20Cast">Tricia Cast</ref>, who portrayed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nina%20Webster">Nina Webster</ref> from 1986 to 2001.</p>
<head id="Questions_asked_to_all_three">Questions asked to all three</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi>: How do you feel about the way the show has evolved from the day you started the show, to what it is now?</p>
</text>
