<text id="autogum_whow_doc103" title="Build a Computer Pricing Site" shortTile="build-computer-pricing" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-06-25" dateModified="2019-03-22" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Build-a-Computer-Pricing-Site" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Build a Computer Pricing Site</head><p>Today you are going to learn to make a computer pricing site. It might sound difficult or boring but it is not that difficult.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Research</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>I believe it is a very important step as you have to know the exact prices of all computers and any sales or deals on them. For this, first note down a framework of all the types of computers whose prices will be on your site.</item>
<item>Then find all models of all good companies that are eligible in your categories that you made. Make sure that the computers have all the essential features, a reasonable price and are popular.</item>
<item>A very very important thing to remember is that your research should be first hand that is, you yourself should go to the markets to get the prices and compare them with the online ones.</item>
<item>See the present sites on this topic and try and find atleast 3 or 4 things in that site that are essential but missing. This will provide your website the edge you need to be successful.</item></list>
<head>Getting a software to make the website</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>In this part I assume you will yourself make the website including the designing and coding part. Do not look shocked as there are softwares available to help you in this process thereby reducing you difficulty and work.The software that I recommend is WordPress. It is an easy to use software and is used by many.</item>
<item>You can also hire a person or firm that will take care of this part for you.</item></list>
<head>Testing</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Make sure you test your website before opening it to the world.</item></list>
<head>Buy a Domain Name</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>For your website to be there on web browsers, the website should have a domain name. This is the official name of your website which will be used by your users to identify your website. For this go to websites like GoDaddy.com and buy the domain name. You have to rent it so you have to pay for it annually.</item>
<item>Make sure that the domain name is catchy and not only related to your website, but also to the keywords people enter to find such websites.</item></list>
<head>Hire a web host and a search engine</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>For those of you wondering what these terms meanL-Web Hosts are companies that present your site to the users.Search Engine are websites such as google that provide links to web sites that have the information the user requires.</item>
<item>Make sure that you know how good they both are and keep paying to keep you website on top in the search engines.</item></list>
<head>Revenue Generation Scheme for your website</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>There are two ways to generate revenue from your website. The first is to get the user to pay to access your website or get advertisers to advertise on your website and pay you for it.</item>
<item>I personally recommend the latter as advertisers pay a lot of money and all you need to do is make sure that your website gets popular so much so that at least a million people visit it. If you want to earn by making the user pay, beware that also requires your website to be successful before you charge them.Also some users feel disappointed or have trust issues and so, do not access your website.</item></list>
<head>Other Help sources</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>If you feel that your website needs something even more then read books on startups. I recommend THE INTELLIGENT INVESTOR or THE LEAN STARTUP to start you website.</item></list>
<head>Marketing</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Though immense investment is required for this you can start using cheap ways first. Make fierce or advertise personally that is up to you.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>make sure that all of the parts of the website mentioned above are taken care of.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>The initial investment might be a big shock.</item></list>
</text>
