<text id="autogum_interview_doc247" title="part5_Dr. Joseph Merlino on sexuality, insanity, Freud, fetishes and apathy" shortTile="partdr-joseph-merlino" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-04" dateModified="2013-09-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dr._Joseph_Merlino_on_sexuality%2C_insanity%2C_Freud%2C_fetishes_and_apathy" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="Sadomasochism"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sadomasochism">Sadomasochism</ref></head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think there are psychological distinctions between sadism and masochism in men?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  Clearly there's a distinction between what those individuals do, but what do you mean by psychological distinctions?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Freud assumed sadism in men resulted from a distortion of an aggressive component of male sexual instinct, whereas masochism in men was seen as an aberration, completely contrary to the nature of male sexuality.  Is that still a function of psychoanalysis?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  For some, it is the psychological need to dominate, for others the need to be dominated.  Others vacillate between both domination and submission.  Part of it is rooted in biology.  We may be born with a tendency towards—let's call it 'problem' for a moment—and let's say someone is sadomasochistic.  It's a problem only if it is getting that individual into difficulties, if he or she is not happy with it, or it's causing problems in their personal or professional lives.  If it's not, I'm not seeing that as a problem.  But assuming that it did, what I would wonder about is what is his or her biology that would cause a tendency toward a problem, and dynamically, what were the experiences this individual had that led him or her toward one of the ends of the spectrum.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What is the motivation behind S&amp;M?  Pain for sexual pleasure?  Gratification from cruelty?  Pleasure from power and the absence thereof?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  It's all of those things.  It's an individual kind of thing.  I think all of us have a little S&amp;M in us.  We don't all go around wearing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leather%20subculture">leather</ref>, but—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  —the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Missionary%20position">missionary</ref> gets boring after awhile—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  —yes.  I think all of us want to explore and do these different things, and that is all perfectly normal within a consensual relationship.  Obviously, if I go out and rape somebody, it's a problem.  But if it's in the confines of a relationship and it is something that stimulates both people, they enjoy it, and it spices up their life, then it's fine.</p>
<p>[<hi rend="italic">A follow-up note from Dr. Merlino:</hi>  The above discussion assumes S&amp;M is a consensual sexual relationship.  The gamut of behavior can run from healthy and normal to disturbed and pathological.  Clearly sadism in the context of the detached inflicting of pain on others based on the belief one has the right to do so and that others are there to be abused (e.g. rapists, batterers, etc) is pathological.  Similarly, masochistic behavior rooted in depression or a self-defeating personality make-up is pathological.]</p>
<head id="Paraphilias,_urges_and_fetishes">Paraphilias, urges and fetishes</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What constitutes a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/paraphiliac">paraphiliac</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  Paraphiliac is a general term for a lot of different <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sexual%20deviancy">sexual deviancies</ref>, for example, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fetishism">fetishism</ref>, or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/pedophilia">pedophilia</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/voyeurism">voyeurism</ref>.  It's the blurring of what I might do that is a turn-on for me, and what might get me into problems with others.  Once you cross that line, it exists as a problem.  If I come up to your apartment and peer in your window while you are getting undressed, it's a problem for you and it will end up a problem for me.  I will be labeled a voyeur, and therefore it's a problem.</p>
</text>
