<text id="autogum_fiction_doc89" title="Uncle Tom's Cabin" shortTile="uncletomscabin" author="Stowe, Harriet Beecher" type="fiction" dateCollected="2019-10-22" sourceURL="http://gutenberg.readingroo.ms/2/0/203/203-0.txt">
<head>Marie was busy, turning over the contents of a drawer, as she answered,</head>

<p>“Well, of course, by and by, Eva, you will have other things to think of besides reading the Bible round to servants. Not but that is very proper; I’ve done it myself, when I had health. But when you come to be dressing and going into company, you won’t have time. See here!” she added, “these jewels I’m going to give you when you come out. I wore them to my first ball. I can tell you, Eva, I made a sensation.”</p>

<p>Eva took the jewel-case, and lifted from it a diamond necklace. Her large, thoughtful eyes rested on them, but it was plain her thoughts were elsewhere.</p>

<p>“How sober you look child!” said Marie.</p>

<p>“Are these worth a great deal of money, mamma?”</p>

<p>“To be sure, they are. Father sent to France for them. They are worth a small fortune.”</p>

<p>“I wish I had them,” said Eva, “to do what I pleased with!”</p>

<p>“What would you do with them?”</p>

<p>“I’d sell them, and buy a place in the free states, and take all our people there, and hire teachers, to teach them to read and write.”</p>

<p>Eva was cut short by her mother’s laughing.</p>

<p>“Set up a boarding-school! Wouldn’t you teach them to play on the piano, and paint on velvet?”</p>

<p>“I’d teach them to read their own Bible, and write their own letters, and read letters that are written to them,” said Eva, steadily. “I know, mamma, it does come very hard on them that they can’t do these things. Tom feels it--Mammy does,--a great many of them do. I think it’s wrong.”</p>

<p>“Come, come, Eva; you are only a child! You don’t know anything about these things,” said Marie; “besides, your talking makes my head ache.”</p>

<p>Marie always had a headache on hand for any conversation that did not exactly suit her.</p>

<p>Eva stole away; but after that, she assiduously gave Mammy reading lessons.</p>

<head>CHAPTER XXIII</head>

<head>Henrique</head>

<p>About this time, St. Clare’s brother Alfred, with his eldest son, a boy of twelve, spent a day or two with the family at the lake.</p>

<p>No sight could be more singular and beautiful than that of these twin brothers. Nature, instead of instituting resemblances between them, had made them opposites on every point; yet a mysterious tie seemed to unite them in a closer friendship than ordinary.</p>

<p>They used to saunter, arm in arm, up and down the alleys and walks of the garden. Augustine, with his blue eyes and golden hair, his ethereally flexible form and vivacious features; and Alfred, dark-eyed, with haughty Roman profile, firmly-knit limbs, and decided bearing. They were always abusing each other’s opinions and practices, and yet never a whit the less absorbed in each other’s society; in fact, the very contrariety seemed to unite them, like the attraction between opposite poles of the magnet.</p>

<p>Henrique, the eldest son of Alfred, was a noble, dark-eyed, princely boy, full of vivacity and spirit; and, from the first moment of introduction, seemed to be perfectly fascinated by the spirituelle graces of his cousin Evangeline.</p>

<p>Eva had a little pet pony, of a snowy whiteness. It was easy as a cradle, and as gentle as its little mistress; and this pony was now brought up to the back verandah by Tom, while a little mulatto boy of about thirteen led along a small black Arabian, which had just been imported, at a great expense, for Henrique.</p>

<p>Henrique had a boy’s pride in his new possession; and, as he advanced and took the reins out of the hands of his little groom, he looked carefully over him, and his brow darkened.</p>

<p>“What’s this, Dodo, you little lazy dog! you haven’t rubbed my horse down, this morning.”</p>

<p>“Yes, Mas’r,” said Dodo, submissively; “he got that dust on his own self.”</p>

<p>“You rascal, shut your mouth!” said Henrique, violently raising his riding-whip. “How dare you speak?”</p>

<p>The boy was a handsome, bright-eyed mulatto, of just Henrique’s size, and his curling hair hung round a high, bold forehead. He had white blood in his veins, as could be seen by the quick flush in his cheek, and the sparkle of his eye, as he eagerly tried to speak.</p>

<p>“Mas’r Henrique!--” he began.</p>

<p>Henrique struck him across the face with his riding-whip, and, seizing one of his arms, forced him on to his knees, and beat him till he was out of breath.</p>

<p>“There, you impudent dog! Now will you learn not to answer back when I speak to you? Take the horse back, and clean him properly. I’ll teach you your place!”</p>

<p>“Young Mas’r,” said Tom, “I specs what he was gwine to say was, that the horse would roll when he was bringing him up from the stable; he’s so full of spirits,--that’s the way he got that dirt on him; I looked to his cleaning.”</p>

<p>“You hold your tongue till you’re asked to speak!” said Henrique, turning on his heel, and walking up the steps to speak to Eva, who stood in her riding-dress.</p>

<p>“Dear Cousin, I’m sorry this stupid fellow has kept you waiting,” he said. “Let’s sit down here, on this seat till they come. What’s the matter, Cousin?--you look sober.”</p>

<p>“How could you be so cruel and wicked to poor Dodo?” asked Eva.</p>
</text>
