<text id="autogum_interview_doc258" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Aurélien Miralles about Sirenoscincus mobydick species discovery" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-01-21" dateModified="2013-04-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Aur%C3%A9lien_Miralles_about_Sirenoscincus_mobydick_species_discovery" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Aurélien Miralles about Sirenoscincus mobydick species discovery</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 24, 2013</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Aurélien Miralles with a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Many-scaled%20Cylindrical%20Skink">Many-scaled Cylindrical Skink</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Morocco">Morocco</ref> in July 2012. Image: Mr Philippe Geniez.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>The <hi rend="italic">Sirenoscincus mobydick</hi>. Image: Aurélien Miralles.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption><hi rend="italic">Sirenoscincus yamagishii</hi>, another species in the same genus. Image: Mr Falk Eckhard.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption><hi rend="italic">Sirenoscincus yamagishii</hi> (edited photo). Image: Mr Falk Eckhard.</caption></figure> <figure><caption>The <hi rend="italic">Sirenoscincus mobydick</hi>, dead specimen on a leaf. Image: Mrs Andolalao Rakotoarison.</caption></figure>
<p>A group of researchers published a paper about their discovery of a new species of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Madagascar">Madagascar</ref> mermaid skink lizards last December. The species is the fourth forelimbs-only terrestrial tetrapods species known to science, and the first one which also has no fingers on the forelimbs.</p>
<p>The species was collected at Marosely, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boriziny">Boriziny</ref> (French: Port-Bergé), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sofia%20Region">Sofia Region</ref>, Madagascar. The <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sirenoscincus%20mobydick">Sirenoscincus mobydick</ref></hi> name is after the existing parent genus, and a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/sperm%20whale">sperm whale</ref> from the 1851 novel <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moby-Dick">Moby-Dick</ref></hi> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herman%20Melville">Herman Melville</ref>.</p>
<p>This week, <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> interviewed one of the researchers, French zoologist Aurélien Miralles, about the research.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What caused your initial interest in Madagascar lizards?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Aurélien Miralles</hi>: Well, I would say that since I am a child I am fascinated by the biodiversity of tropical countries, and more especially by reptiles. I did a PhD on the evolution and systematics of skink lizards from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/South_America">South America</ref>. Then, I get a Humboldt grant to do a postdoc in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">Germany</ref>, at the Miguel Vences Lab, in order to study Malagasy skinks. Madagascar being a fabulous hotspot for reptiles (and not only for reptiles actually), it was a very nice opportunity. Professor Vences proposed me to associate our complementary fields of expertise: he is expert in <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/herpetology">herpetology</ref> for Madagascar, and I am expert in skinks lizards (family Scincidae). It was a very fruitful experience, and many other results have still to [be] published.</p>
<figure><caption>Approximate location of the species discovery. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OpenStreetMap">OpenStreetMap</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How was the new species discovered?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM</hi>: By a very funny coincidence actually. In 2010, I went to Madagascar for a long trip through the south of the island, in the semi-arid bush for collecting lizards and snakes samples. Then, during the last days, just before coming back to Germany, I have visited by coincidence the zoological collection of the University of Antananarivo. In that place, I found an old jar of ethanol with two weird little specimens previously collected by a student who didn't realize it was something new. Being expert on skinks, I immediately recognised it was something very probably new, very different from all the other known species.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What does "Sirenoscincus" stand for?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM</hi>: I am not the author of the genus name <hi rend="italic">Sirenoscincus</hi>. This genus name was already existing. It has been described by Sakata and Hikida (two Japanese herpetologists). "Sireno" means mermaid. "Scincus" means skinks, a group of little lizards on which I am particularly focusing my studies. So, Sirenoscinus means "mermaid skink", in reference to [the] fact it has forelimbs but no hindlimbs.</p>
</text>
