<text id="autogum_whow_doc584" title="Know the Odds in Life" shortTile="know-odds-life" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2009-04-06" dateModified="2018-10-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Know-the-Odds-in-Life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Know the Odds in Life</head><p>Life is not easy. Life does not convey the same meaning to all... To one it may be a book to explore gradually, reading page by page.
To one life may seem as a beautiful gift of God for which one is thankful.
To one life may seem as a boxing champ catching one in the corner of the ring throwing punch after punch till seeing him/her fall down.
To one life may look life a burden, carrying it on one's back...
Each and everyone of us, has seen or will see these phases of life but more importantly, its necessary to know the odds in life and to deal with them in an efficient way. Below, i would like to share a few tips to make you take life as a precious gift of life and to be thankful for it.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Never Ever say Never. Everyone is unique in some way or the other. What's is important for us is to never give up and never give in. Life is as simple as we take it. The more we make it complicated, the more it gets. <figure rend="Develop-Telekinesis-Step-3-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Fight for your right. Its is mandatory for us to know that we have to fight for our rights simply because its our right. No one has the right to take what is meant to be for us. Its is worth it to fight for your happiness, to fight for your job, to fight for your married life and to fight for everything which you think is somehow connected to you. Remember, I do not mean to throw punches onto someone. Fighting spirit is what is of my concern, the confidence that you can handle relations, communicate effectively and prosper with confidence and stability. <figure rend="Choose-a-Recruitment-Agency-Step-11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Never compromise. As long as you know your capacity to deliver your best, never ever give your second best. <figure rend="Live-Happily-Ever-After-Step-12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do not procrastinate. The evil of procrastination, makes you lose everything you have and meanwhile take the future opportunities waiting for you. When you have decided to take a bath, just do it. <figure rend="Calm-Self-Harming-Thoughts-Step-12-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have faith in God. A religious bonding no matter whatever religion you follow, always helps you keep your spirits and morality into a higher level. Always have faith in God and know that God is watching you and will always be there for you no matter what. <figure rend="Be-Kemetic-Step-17.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Love yourself. You need to love yourself if you are to spread love to others. Always think of best things for yourself, best clothing, best shape, best activities and best food. But make sure, in the course of achieving your goals, do not take away the best of others. Always strike for a fair deal. <figure rend="Fight-Against-Eating-Disorders-Step-4-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get rid of your bad habits. Its not easy, but it is not impossible. Bad habits are like mountains, they are pretty huge in built but they are climbable. If you think you have 3 bad habits, neglect the two till you get rid of the first one. and gradually, replace the 1st bad habit with a good one and same goes for the others two. <figure rend="Break-a-Habit-Step-11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Its your life. Know that its your life. Nobody has the right to control your life, to take away your life and to interfere into your life. As long as you know that you are YOURSELF, you are successful. Do not hesitate to say a FIRM NO or an ENCOURAGING YES to yourself and to others. <figure rend="Deal-with-Workplace-Bullying-and-Harassment-Step-6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do regular Exercise. No matter whatever exercise or whatever sports you are in. Make sure you do something in this regard. Badminton, Basketball, Football or Gym, anything will seal the deal. Its really helps to esteem your self-image, and good physique. <figure rend="Motivate-Yourself-to-Work-Out-Step-18-Version-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do not Concentrate on what i have written. My writing is not standard, my suggestions are not the best. Its just some tips, take it or leave but make sure you decide what is best for you. <figure rend="Achieve-Something-in-Life-Step-7-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Following it will help you tackle the odds.</item>
<item>Not following them will not make your life miserable either.</item></list>
</text>
