<text id="autogum_academic_doc209" title="Recent Advances in the Discovery of Novel Antiprotozoal Agents" shortTile="recent-advances-discovery" author="Seong-Min Lee, Min-Sun Kim, Faisal Hayat, Dongyun Shin" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1420-3049/24/21/3886/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Recent Progress of Antiprotozoan Agents</head><head> 2.1. Anti-Giardiasis</head>
<p>
Giardiasis is caused by the protozoan parasite <hi rend="italic">G. intestinalis</hi> (also known as <hi rend="italic">G. lamblia</hi> or <hi rend="italic">G. duodenalis</hi>). It is also known by the common name “beaver fever,” because this infection was reported in campers who drank contaminated water that was inhabited by beavers. Giardiasis is the most common protozoan infection in human beings, and it occurs in both developing and industrialized countries. Its global incidence is believed to range between 20%–60%, with 2%–7% incidence in industrialized nations. <hi rend="italic">Giardia intestinalis</hi> was first described in 1681 after the Dutch microscopist Antonie van Leeuwenhoek observed the protozoan in his own diarrheic stools. This disease is often prevalent in poor countries and communities that have untreated water, inadequate sanitation, and poor dietary status. The infection is caused by fecal–oral transmission and initiated by the ingestion of infectious cysts from contaminated water or through person-to-person contact. After excystation, flagellated trophozoites colonize the upper small intestine, where they attach to the epithelial lining but do not invade the mucosa. The duration of Giardia infection is variable; however, chronic infection and reinfection commonly occur. Approximately 50% of the symptoms classically associated with giardiasis are asymptomatic including diarrhea, abdominal pain, nausea, vomiting, and anorexia. However, infected individuals can also develop extraintestinal and postinfectious complications. Chronic extraintestinal sequelae may affect the joints, skin, eyes, and central nervous system, but the underlying mechanisms are unknown. According to research data, Giardia has eight distinct genetic assemblages labelled as assemblage “A” through “H”, and assemblages “A” and “B” are responsible for infection in humans. </p>

<p>Three classes of drugs are currently used for the treatment of giardiasis: metronidazole, mepacrine analogs, and nitrofurans, such as furazolidone (<figure>Figure 1</figure>). Metronidazole is the most widely used drug for the treatment of giardiasis globally and it is generally effective and well-tolerated. However, the United States Food and Drug Administration (FDA) has not yet approved this drug for the treatment of Giardia infection because of its toxicity and major side effects, such as seizures, ataxia, peripheral neuropathy, transient myopia, gastric mucosal irritation, sperm damage, and hematuria. Tinidazole is an N1-position modified 5-nitro imidazole, which has been approved by the FDA for the treatment of giardiasis. Nitazoxanide (NTZ) belongs to an emerging class of 5-nitrothiazole compounds with potential antigiardial activity. However, although NTZ is generally well tolerated, some adverse effects such as abdominal pain, diarrhea, and nausea limit the safe use for human beings. Mepacrine is no longer available in the United States, and it is being replaced in most of its applications with safer and more specific drugs. Furazolidone also has serious side effects, such as gastrointestinal disturbances, hemolytic anemia, disulfiram-like reactions to alcohol, and hypersensitivity reactions, as well as evidence of tumorigenicity in rodent studies. Furthermore, <hi rend="italic">G. lamblia</hi> resistance to this drug has also been reported. Therefore, research focusing on the development of novel, alternative drugs for the treatment of giardiasis is highly desirable. In view of these considerations, researchers have designed and synthesized some novel molecules for the treatment of giardiasis, their results are summarized in Table 1. </p>
</text>
