<text id="autogum_bio_doc384" title="Bartolomé de Argüelles" shortTile="bartolome-de-arguelles" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-07-11" dateModified="2019-09-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bartolom%C3%A9_de_Arg%C3%BCelles" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Bartolomé de Argüelles</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bartolomé de Argüelles</hi> (?  - ?) was the lieutenant treasurer,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Paar1999-1">[1]</ref> royal <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Accountant">accountant</ref> and co-interim governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spanish_Florida">La Florida</ref> (1595–1597) with Alonso de las Alas and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juan_Menéndez_Márquez">Juan Menéndez Márquez</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FrancisCole2011-2">[2]</ref> He served as lieutenant treasurer during the administration of governor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pedro_Menéndez_de_Márquez">Pedro Menéndez de Márquez</ref> (1577-1594).</p>
<head>Career</head>
<p>In 1586, during the governorship of Pedro Menéndez Márquez, the English <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Privateer">privateer</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_Drake">Francis Drake</ref> attacked and burned <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Augustine,_Florida">St. Augustine</ref> (San Agustín), the capital of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spanish_Florida">Florida</ref> (La Florida), destroying many documents including records of account, so that Argüelles had to make a new inventory of property that remained after the fire.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Paar1999-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>When Governor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domingo_Martínez_de_Avendaño">Domingo Martínez de Avendaño</ref> died in 1595, the three treasury officials, treasurer Juan Menéndez Márquez,  accountant Bartolomé de Argüelles and factor-overseer Alonso de las Alas, became acting co-governors of La Florida.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[Note 1]</ref> At the time of Avendaño's death, Argüelles was in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mexico_City">Mexico City</ref> to retrieve the <hi rend="italic">situado</hi>, the annual subsidy from the treasury of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Spain">New Spain</ref> to support the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Presidio">presidio</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Augustine,_Florida">St. Augustine</ref>. Menéndez Márquez and Las Alas were reported to have quarrelled over the governance of Florida until Argüelles returned from Mexico City.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[3]</ref> Argüelles, who had been in Florida since the 1570s and had become accountant in 1591, aspired to be governor.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[Note 2]</ref></p>
<p>Argüelles sent a petition to be appointed as governor to the King shortly after Avendaño's death. The King turned down Argüelles's request, and appointed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gonzalo_Méndez_de_Canço">Gonzalo Méndez de Cancio y Donlebún</ref>, who had never been to Florida, as governor. Méndez arrived at St. Augustine in 1597.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[5]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[6]</ref> Soon after Méndez reached St. Augustine, he encountered resistance over a payment from the royal treasury to the new garrison priest, Father Ricardo. Argüelles and factor-overseer Las Alas refused to make the payment, saying that there was no authorization for it. Menéndez Márquez sided with governor Méndez on the issue. Shortly afterwards, Méndez charged Las Alas with embezzling funds from the royal treasury, and suspended him from office. Las Alas claimed that Méndez and Menéndez Márquez had conspired against him.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[7]</ref> The king had given governor Méndez authorization to name his own lieutenant and successor, and Méndez chose his nephew, Juan García de Navia. Rather than attack governor Méndez directly, Argüelles conducted a letter-writing campaign against García and other officials appointed by Méndez, and against Méndez's handling of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guale">Guale</ref> rebellion.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[8]</ref></p>
<p>Alarmed at repeated incursions into the province of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guale">Guale</ref> by French sassafras traders, who were coming and going unmolested in the harbors of the coast, Argüelles implored Governor Menéndez Márquez to send <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Timucuan">Timucuan</ref> allies with Spanish troops to seize their canoes and burn their food crops, as well as to seize some of the young men and enslave them. Menéndez Márquez's successor, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gonzalo_Méndez_de_Canço">Méndez de Canço</ref>, employed these tactics, thus reviving Márquez's "war of fire and blood" against the rebel <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guale">Guale</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Bushnell1987-11">[9]</ref></p>
</text>
