<text id="autogum_interview_doc361" title="part7_Creator of website satirizing Glenn Beck on winning domain name case" shortTile="partcreator-website" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-11-09" dateModified="2019-02-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Creator_of_website_satirizing_Glenn_Beck_on_winning_domain_name_case" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>As regards the application of the <hi rend="italic">Hustler v. Falwell</hi> case to this case, I think the overall application was fair: Parody and satire are protected forms of free speech.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> On September 29, 2009, your lawyer Marc Randazza requested that Glenn Beck agree to stipulate to the application of the United States Constitution, and also especially to the First Amendment to the U.S. Constitution. In an October 19 interview with <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi>, Randazza said that Beck had not responded to this request. Why do you think Beck chose not to stipulate to the U.S. Constitution and the First Amendment in this case?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">E-H</hi>: I think Beck knew that doing so would hurt his case. The rights of free speech we enjoy in the United States are broader than in some other countries. WIPO, being an international organization, could well have assigned an arbitrator from a country that doesn't protect speech as strongly as we do. And WIPO, not being bound by the U.S. Constitution, might not choose to consider the strong protections we have in rendering their decision.</p>
<p>We also felt it was ironic that Glenn Beck, who is on record as being against an international body making judgments that might overrule the U.S. Constitution, would himself choose to use an international body to try and stifle speech that would be protected under the U.S. Constitution. So ultimately, you could say we were trying to help him retain the patriotic image he has worked to hard to present.</p>
<p>Ultimately, the arbitrator applied the First Amendment anyhow.  We felt that in sending that letter, we would give Beck a chance to show that his purported support for the constitution was real.  His failure to respond shows everyone that he is full of shit.</p>
<hi rend="bold">We also felt it was ironic that Glenn Beck, who is on record as being against an international body making judgments that might overrule the U.S. Constitution, would himself choose to use an international body to try and stifle speech that would be protected under the U.S. Constitution.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Eiland-Hall</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> An article in <hi rend="italic">Online Media Daily</hi> noted, the decision in your WIPO case, "appears to mark a significant win for digital rights advocates because a ruling in Beck's favor could have encouraged other subjects of online parodies to take their complaints directly to the WIPO rather than U.S. courts, which are bound by the First Amendment." How do you feel about the fact that your case may have set precedent for similar cases in the future?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">E-H</hi>: If this has truly set precedent, I am honored to have the chance to serve the cause of Liberty. I'm nobody special, mind you. Anyone could have set up
a site - it just happened to be me that got thrown in the center of this fight.</p>
</text>
