<text id="autogum_interview_doc302" title="part8_Shimon Peres discusses the future of Israel" shortTile="partshimon-peres" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-01-06" dateModified="2013-08-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Shimon_Peres_discusses_the_future_of_Israel" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="Iran:_will_Israel_strike_first?">Iran: will Israel strike first?</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: With Iran, do you think that Israel would ever need to act unilaterally <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operation%20Opera">again</ref>, to make a strike, in response to their nuclear capabilities?  The U.S. National Intelligence Estimate, which is quite controversial, said that they’ve stopped their nuclear weapons program, yet there are many centrifuges in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Natanz">Natanz</ref> that are still producing material.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: First of all about intelligence.  One must understand the nature of intelligence.  Intelligence is an organization to report and not to prophesize.  They are not prophets and they don’t claim to be.  They are experts on what has happened; you can’t ask them to be expert on what may happen because the best intelligence person in America will never have a Persian mind.  So how can you know how the mind acts?  Don’t expect them.  What will finally bring down the danger of Iran is the Iranians themselves; they are sick and tired.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahmoud%20Ahmadinejad">Ahmadinejad</ref> almost replaced Allah with enriched Uranium.  It becomes a holy profession.  “We are enriching uranium!”  What are you enriching uranium, what for?  If you try to use it, you will be hit.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: Are you saying the Iranian people will be the agents of change?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: Yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: But there was so much hope for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mohammad%20Khatami">Mohammad Khatami</ref> and yet his administration ended up a disappointment--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: Yes.  There are hopes that become disappointments.  It doesn’t mean you don’t have to try again.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: But the Iranian people seem to be rallying around their nuclear program.</hi></p>
<hi rend="bold">With Iran, we shall do what we have to do in our own way. We don’t want to bother anybody because it’s a world problem. Until now, the problem was will the world stand on the side of Israel. Today, the question is will the world stand on the side of the world? Iran is a world danger.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right"><hi rend="bold">—On the possibility of an Israeli strike against Iran.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: You’re only as great as your word, don’t forget.  But the Iranian economy cannot hold it and they are mobilizing the world against them.  Gradually.  Every time more and more.  The world is sick and tired.  Finally, the world will have to decide if we live in a world with nuclear devices that can fall in the hands of terrorists or we are going to organize ourselves against this danger.  So I will be very careful not to describe Iran as an Israeli problem.  It’s a world problem and Israel must be sanguine about it.  Keep cool.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: As part of a coalition?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: If they want us, yes.  But we shall not insist.  We are naturally in the coalition; I don’t know if we shall be formally.</p>
</text>
