<text id="autogum_academic_doc468" title="Nursing Students’ Knowledge and Awareness of Antibiotic Use, Resistance and Stewardship: A Descriptive Cross-Sectional Study" shortTile="nursing-students" author="Andrea Rábano-Blanco, Eva  María Domínguez-Martís, Diego  Gabriel Mosteiro-Miguéns, Manuel Freire-Garabal, Silvia Novío" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2079-6382/8/4/203/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Antibiotics are medicines that fight bacterial infections. They can save lives if they are used correctly, but nowadays antibiotic resistance has become a real problem. Infections by resistant microorganisms do not respond to treatment, so the duration of the disease is prolonged, and the risk of death increases. Moreover, if the treatment fails or if the response to treatment is slow, the patient is contagious for longer, which increases the likelihood of resistant microorganisms being transmitted to other people. </p>

<p>The emergence of antibiotic resistance is a natural biological phenomenon, and even though numerous factors have been identified as the cause of this, such as clustering and overcrowding or increased elderly population, one of the most important factors is the inadequate use of antibiotics, a very worrying situation especially for healthcare professionals with high rate of antibiotic prescription such as primary care dentists. According to the World Health Organization (WHO), inadequate use of antibiotics includes the prescription of inappropriate antibiotics for a brief time, in low or insufficient doses and/or for diseases for which they are not indicated; likewise, excessive therapeutic dosage regimens are also considered inadequate uses of antibiotics. In the specific case of Spain, the consumption of antibiotics for outpatients is above the European average, and in hospitals their prescription is increasing. </p>

<p>The inadequate use of antibiotics can be encouraged by self-medication, by the implementation of permissive policies in terms of regulation of the use of these drugs, by the relationship between the healthcare professional and the patient or by the knowledge and attitudes that one has towards them. Regarding the latter, while it is true that a poor knowledge or negative attitude towards antibiotics leads inevitably to bad clinical practice, practical skills are not always a reflection of knowledge, a situation known as “theory–practice gap”. </p>

<p>To date, the studies which have evaluated the training that healthcare students have about infectious diseases, antimicrobial resistance and safe use of antibiotics have been mainly carried out in students of medicine and pharmacy, besides students from other disciplines such as dentistry. However, taking into account that the control of antibiotic resistance requires a multidisciplinary approach, and that nursing staff play a key role in the rational use of antibiotics, as teachers of patients, and as future drug prescribers in our country, the training of nurses could have an important impact in reducing the incidence of antibiotic resistance. Thus, the objective of this paper has been to determine the nursing students’ knowledge and awareness of antibiotic use, resistance and stewardship. </p>
</text>
