<text id="autogum_interview_doc555" title="part7_Ingrid Newkirk, co-founder of PETA, on animal rights and the film about her life" shortTile="partingrid-newkirk" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-20" dateModified="2018-02-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ingrid_Newkirk%2C_co-founder_of_PETA%2C_on_animal_rights_and_the_film_about_her_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  That’s a great question, because there are two things and they really are in tandem.  If I only could have one thing, it would be to end suffering.  If you could take things from animals and kill animals all day long without causing them suffering, then I would take it.  But I think there’s another question that underlies that.  Everybody should be able to agree that animals should not suffer if you kill them or steal from them by taking the fur off their backs or take their eggs, whatever.  But you shouldn’t put them through torture to do that.  We should all agree on that since we really don’t care at all for suffering.  But I think there’s this other question:  Who are we that we have set ourselves up on this pedestal and we believe that we have a right take from others everything—including their life—simply because we want to do it?  Shouldn’t we stop and think for a second that maybe they are just others like us?  Other nations, other individuals, other cultures.  Just others.  Not sub-human, but just different from being human.</p>
<head id="Newkirk_on_the_worst_corporate_animal_abusers">Newkirk on the worst corporate animal abusers</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When you think of companies—obviously <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Butterball">Butterball</ref> would be one—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smithfield%20Foods">Smithfield Foods</ref>, yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Who are some of the most egregious abusers of animals?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  It’s a long list, but I would say at the moment it is people like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Versace">Versace</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean-Paul%20Gaultier">Jean-Paul Gaultier</ref> if you are talking about fur.  If you are talking about wool clothing, there is Australian Wool Innovation that sticks up for all the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wool">wool</ref> farmers that export all over the world the majority of wool, and they are scurrilous.  They will not stop live export where thousand upon thousands of these sheep die in appalling conditions on the way to the Middle East.  They will not stop <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mulesing">mulesing</ref>, which is cutting the flesh off the backsides of lambs when they are just a few days old without any <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/anesthesia">anesthesia</ref>.  We are fighting them.  They need to change and come into the 21st Century.  KFC; we have been after them for several years now.  All we are asking is that they switch to Controlled Atmosphere Killing.  We know they won’t switch to soy chicken overnight, although I <hi rend="italic">have</hi> given them all kinds of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meat%20analogue">soy chicken</ref> and said, “You know, broaden your market base—live a little!”  I’m sure they throw it in the trash, which is a shame.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  “Oh God, here comes Ingrid Newkirk with her soy chickens again!”</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  There’s great stuff!  There are even soy <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buffalo%20wings">Buffalo wings</ref> on the market that are delicious.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What is Controlled Atmosphere Killing?</hi></p>
</text>
