<text id="autogum_academic_doc414" title="Environmental Criteria for Assessing the Competitiveness of Public Tenders with the Replacement of Large-Scale LEDs in the Outdoor Lighting of Cities as a Key Element for Sustainable Development: Case Study Applied with PROMETHEE Methodology" shortTile="environmental-criteria" author="Manuel  Jesús Hermoso-Orzáez, José  Adolfo Lozano-Miralles, Rafael Lopez-Garcia, Paulo Brito" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5982/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Methodology</head>
<p>
At this point, we will define the objectives, the methodology pursued in this work and the case study that will serve as a methodological proposal. </p>

<head> 2.1. Objetive</head>
<p>
The promulgation of the energy efficiency regulations (hereafter REEIAE) in Spain together with the growth of LED technology and the admission of the contracting of energy services companies (Energetics Services Companies) (ESC) by the public administrations are milestones that have emerged in recent years—the facilities in the EU and their method of management, maintenance and control are changing. The pilot experiences carried out by the IDAE (Institute for Diversification and Energy Saving) in the Town Halls of Alcorcón and Soto del Real (Spain) to adapt their outdoor lighting installations to the requirements of the REEIAE through (ESC) and the lines of financing implemented with the aid programs of the National Energy Efficiency Fund and JESSICA FIDAE have revealed the high potential for savings in electricity consumption of this type of facility. In addition, this potential for savings in economic terms allows, in most cases, investments to be made with a simple return period of less than six years, which is ideal for the business of ESC companies. </p>

<p>The municipalities in the case of Spain propose the reform of a set of more than 700,000 existing light points, and more than 97% of the cases have opted for the replacement of discharge lamps with LED technology. With this, an average saving of 65% per year in electricity consumption has been achieved due to the variation in the power of the new light points, which drops from an average of 164 to 58 W per luminaire. Most of the government, especially the local administrations, are opting for public tenders for the concession of the lighting services for to a minimum of 10 years, including maintenance, management, and investments in the ESC (Services Energetics Business) modality. </p>

<p>However, in some municipalities, perhaps due to the rush generated by carrying out the substitutions in a precipitous manner, regardless of demanding minimum qualities and due to the lack of a detailed study of the facilities or the qualities of the equipment to be replaced, unforeseen situations have arisen, such as massive blackouts associated with surges caused by thunderstorms, problems in the cold ignition of the lighting installation, or distortions in the network generated by the harmonic contamination associated with the electronic equipment of the LED drivers. </p>

<p>The EU Circular Economy Action Plan promotes a longer lifespan of the products to be used as building materials or in facilities; in particular, outdoor lighting. However, encouraging longer lives could also generate compensation between different environmental impacts for some product categories such as LED luminaires. This is why the environmental impact analysis in the different categories obtained in the industrial manufacture of LED luminaires using LCA techniques has become a key and priority aspect to be taken into consideration in the preparation of the technical conditions to address the public bidding of projects, whose purpose is to address the technological changes to LEDs in external lighting, based on efficiency criteria as well as energy, light, economic and, of course, environmental requirements. </p>

<p>This work aims to propose an improved model of technical specifications, complementary to those proposed by the IDAE or the CIE (Spanish Lighting Committee), which allows a municipal technician to guarantee that the replacement of LED luminaires will be carried out, with the maximum guarantees of technical performance, light energy, and a low environmental impact, allowing a municipal technician to face this change and its consequences in the medium and long term with the necessary peace of mind that at least the replaced product meets the standards of quality and sufficient light efficiency and respect for the environment. Finally, this specification model is discussed and analyzed, supported by studies and work carried out by specialists in the field. </p>

<p>A Specification of Technical Conditions type or model is proposed as a case study that will allow the replacement of 1034 luminaires with 100 W HM discharge lamps, with LED luminaires with low environmental impact, greater energy efficiency, and similar lighting performance. Contemplating, as a novelty, the analysis of environmental sensitivity of the LED luminaire using LCA techniques, it is intended that this improved technical specification model with respect to the one defined by the IDEA or the CIE will allows us to consider and improve some technical aspects that we consider determinants to improve the functionality and environmental sustainability of the lighting installation to be replaced. </p>
</text>
