<text id="autogum_reddit_doc144" title="How much should I charge for my first professionally built website?" shortTile="much-charge-first" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-03-31" dateModified="2018-03-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/88mpol" speakerList="#hkd987, #iMakeBaadChoices" speakerCount="2">
<head>How much should I charge for my first professionally built website?</head>
<sp who="#iMakeBaadChoices">

<list type="unordered"><item></item>
<item>Text in bold is the actual functionality of the site if you want to skip to it</item>
<item> I've been doing web dev as a hobby for about three years here and there and I've learned a lot and I think I'm pretty good. I've built things from chat rooms to blogs with a custom CMS to a custom social media site like twitter and also a couple sites for the rec clubs I'm in. A family friend has a business and he accepted a new contract. What they're currently doing on the parent companies website is there's a link to download an order form created in excel with a bunch of fields and stuff. The customer downloads the excel sheet, fills it out, emails it to the person (in this case, my family friend) and he has an invoice created using the info from the excel sheet and he emails it back to them. So this is pretty inefficient in my eyes and he wanted it to be automated and done online so I did just that. I created a website where there isn't really an amazing front end (just slapped materialize onto it) since they will come to this website after visiting the parent companies website which would mean they already intend to order stuff.  <hi rend="bold">So there's just a bunch of fields where you fill out all your info, pick the stuff you wanna order, when you need it by, if you wanna make any changes to each item, how much of each item you need, etc, and finally you click submit and all the data is taken, and parsed through where I put it through to an HTML template I have made which then I convert to a PDF and email to the customer and my family friend. So it just saves all the work of the user having to download and fill a file and send it to my friend and then wait for them to respond with the invoice and etc.</hi>  How much would something like this cost to make? I can't really count the hours because this sort of stuff just intrigues me so throughout the day I'm thinking of how I could do it in my mind, and when I'm on the bus or train I'm googling different packages and trying to learn ways to do what needs to be done. However if I had to guess, from beginning to end I did this in about a week and this was my main focus throughout this whole week. So yeah, how much would be a reasonable amount to charge him if he was just a regular customer asking for a website to be made? (I'm probably going to take off a good % of it since he's a family friend who's helped my family a lot)</item>
</list>
</sp>
<sp who="#hkd987">
<p>Ask your self what you want to make a year, divide by 52. That’s what you charge for one weeks work. </p>
<p>So if I want to make 100k a year then I’d charge 1923 for the job. </p>
</sp>
</text>
