<text id="autogum_academic_doc646" title="Parental Approach to the Management of Childhood Fever: Differences between Health Professional and Non-Health Professional Parents" shortTile="parental-approach" author="María  Gloria Villarejo-Rodríguez, Beatriz Rodríguez-Martín" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/20/4014/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Fever, defined as a rectal temperature above 38 degrees centigrade (°C), is the body’s response to an illness or pathological invasion and is one of the most common symptoms of childhood illnesses (for one-third of all presenting conditions in children). Generally, fever is self-limiting and a symptom of a banal viral infection with no known source. </p>

<p>Despite this, childhood fever constitutes 30% of pediatric consultations in primary care in both Europe and the United States. In Spain, reported rates are as high as 60%. This represents a considerable expense considering the extent of medical consultations and emergency service visits in primary care sectors and hospitals, together with complementary exams and antibiotic treatments, which, at times, could be deemed unnecessary. </p>

<p>Regarding the manner in which parents approach childhood fever, prior studies show that parents fear the secondary effects of fever, such as febrile convulsions or brain injury, or the association between high fever and the severity of the illness. These are factors which are conducive to parents initiating antipyretic therapy as soon as possible, thus increasing the risk of an overdose. In this sense, according to previous studies, approximately 50% of parents administer antipyretics when temperatures are below 38 °C or administer incorrect doses of antipyretics or supratherapeutic doses of paracetamol and ibuprofen. It is therefore worth considering that parent empowerment in the management of fever could be a helpful tool for gaining greater control over the decisions and actions that affect both parents’ health and that of their children. Parent empowerment also enables parents to actively take charge of their children’s care. </p>

<p>Previous studies have highlighted the fact that the educational level or, more specifically, health alphabetization, influences the perceptions related to the process of health-illness in the community. Moreover, parents who are health professionals can encounter difficulties when assuming the role of the patient, frequently resorting to self-diagnosis, self-medication, and prescriptions issued to family members. Despite this, to the best of our knowledge, the influence of health training on parents, regarding the management of childhood fever, has not been analyzed to date. </p>

<p>Although the management of childhood fever is well known based on former quantitative research performed using surveys or questionnaires, little is known of the parents’ perception on the process of seeking care, the therapeutic approach, and the expectations regarding this phenomenon. These aspects can provide health professionals and managers with key information for the design and implementation of educational programs targeted at improving the manner in which parents deal with their episodes of childhood fever and promoting an appropriate use of health resources. </p>

<p>The aim of this study was to explore the parents’ approach to fever in children aged between 0 and 12 years, comparing parents with and without health training. </p>
</text>
