<text id="autogum_voyage_doc13" title="Pärnu" shortTile="prnu" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=27062" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Pärnu</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.visitparnu.com/">Pärnu</ref></hi> is a resort seaside city (and Estonia's summer capital) with a small harbour in south-western <ref target="Estonia">Estonia</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>The city is known for its spas, shallow white sandy beach and beautiful parks. It is also a popular place for conferences, theatre performances and concerts. In 1838 the first spa was opened and nowadays Pärnu is a health resort of international stature.</p>

<p>During the Great Northern War, the University of Tartu was relocated to Pärnu from 1699-1710. Tartu University still has a branch campus there today.</p>

<p>Since 1996 Pärnu has been known as Estonia's Summer Capital. Beach life, dozens of festivals, night clubs, big party crowds, concerts and funfairs - Pärnu has it all.</p>

<p>Pärnu is an ancient Hanseatic town where a medieval festival and an arts and crafts fair are held every summer.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tourist Information Centre</hi>, Uus 4, ☏ +372 447 3000 , ✉ parnu@visitestonia.com .</item>
</list>


<head>Get in</head>
<p>See <ref target="Estonia%23Get%20around">Estonia#Get around</ref> for bus and train schedules.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>Buses arrive at the small <hi rend="bold">bus station</hi> (<hi rend="italic">bussijaam</hi>) on the border of the old town. This bus station feels like a big bus stop because the terminal building is somewhat hidden on the opposite side of the street. Note a fast-food kiosk nearby. It opens early in the morning and caters to morning travellers while the whole city is still sleeping.</p>

<p>Buses from <ref target="Tallinn">Tallinn</ref> depart every hour and reach Pärnu in about two hours. You can also travel from <ref target="Viljandi">Viljandi</ref> (1 h) and <ref target="Tartu">Tartu</ref> (2.5-3 h), <ref target="Kuressaare">Kuressaare</ref> (3 h), and <ref target="Valga">Valga</ref> (2.5 h). There is one daily bus from <ref target="Saint%20Petersburg">Saint Petersburg</ref> in <ref target="Russia">Russia</ref> with a stop in <ref target="Narva">Narva</ref> (5 h). Check the schedules at <ref target="http://www.tpilet.ee/en%3F">here</ref>.</p>

<p>Pärnu is a major stop in the middle of the <ref target="Tallinn">Tallinn</ref>–<ref target="Riga">Riga</ref> route. Buses run every 1-2 hours and connect you to the Latvian capital in 2.5 h. Pärnu can be an excellent stopover on your away between the Baltic capitals.</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>Pärnu has a train connection to <ref target="Tallinn">Tallinn</ref>. Trains depart from Tallinn and from Pärnu twice a day. The journey takes about 3 hours, check the <ref target="http://www.edel.ee">Edelaraudtee website</ref> for the current schedule. The station building has been razed down recently, so the train drops you at some strange place 3 km south of the city center (reachable by city bus, though). In contrast to <ref target="Tartu">Tartu</ref>, train connections to Pärnu are underdeveloped and remain inferior to the abundant bus options.</p>

<head>By car</head>

<p>Pärnu has road connections to <ref target="Tallinn">Tallinn</ref> (128 km), <ref target="Haapsalu">Haapsalu</ref> (108 km), <ref target="Tartu">Tartu</ref> (174 km), as well as to <ref target="Riga">Riga</ref> in <ref target="Latvia">Latvia</ref> (184 km). The major artery of the <ref target="Baltic%20states">Baltic states</ref>, <ref target="Via%20Baltica">Via Baltica</ref>, passes near Pärnu.</p>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pärnu airport</hi> ( EPU ) (is 4 km north-west of the city). It has some regular flights, but you are more likely to use this airport for continuing your journey from Pärnu rather than for traveling to the city. <ref target="http://www.lendame.ee/">Luftverkehr Friesland-Harle</ref> operates flights to the islands of <ref target="Ruhnu">Ruhnu</ref> (regular) and <ref target="Kihnu">Kihnu</ref> (on request only). The Ruhnu flight continues to <ref target="Kuressaare">Kuressaare</ref> and costs about €25 for each flight segment.</item>
</list>

 

<head>By boat</head>
<p>Pärnu has a large port, which is mostly used for cargo traffic. Ferries to the island of <ref target="Kihnu">Kihnu</ref> depart from the Munalaid dock located 35 km west of Pärnu. However, a small <hi rend="italic">passenger harbor</hi> <ref target="http://www.veeteed.com/index.php%3Fmoodul%3D100%26amp%3Bidc%3D1011001100010001000%26amp%3B">exists at Kalda 2</ref>(right at the city center) and may serve occasional weekend ferries to Kihnu and <ref target="Ruhnu">Ruhnu</ref>.</p>

<p>If you are arriving by sail boat (keelyacht), you can dock at the <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://jahtklubi.ee/eng/parnu-yacht-club-marina/">Pärnu Yacht Club</ref></hi>.</p>
<p>To stay with motorboat you can use <ref target="http://www.talvesadam.ee/index.php/general-information">Talvesadam</ref> on Pärnu moat (Pärnu vallikraav). <ref target="http://www.google.com/maps/place/P%C3%A4nu%2Bvallikraav/">Pärnu moat on Google map</ref>.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>The bus network covers the whole city, including the suburbs. There are 26 routes and their schedules can be found at <ref target="http://www.bussipark.ee">Pärnu ATP-s website</ref>.</p>

<head>By foot</head>
<p>Pärnu's old town is pretty small and navigable by foot and it's full of small boutiques. Lots of them are on Rüütli street.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The old town with buildings even from Medieval times</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Beautiful wooden villas</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The beach park and promenade</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Art galleries</hi>. Lydia Koidula and Modern Art Museum and City gallery</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pärnu Town Hall</hi>, Nikolai tn 3. The Town Hall is located in a house built in 1797 by the merchant P.R. Harder. In 1804, the Russian czar Alexander I stayed in this house during his visit to Pärnu. A new art nouveau building with neo-baroque details was completed in 1911 to the north side of the town hall.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Church of Jekaterina</hi>, Vee tn 8. Completed in 1768, the Church of Jekaterina is the most style pure and ample baroque church in Estonia. The church has influenced the development of orthodox church architecture in whole Balticum. To this day Pärnu Russian congregation operates in the church.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Seegi Maja (the Almshouse)</hi>, Hospidali tn 1. Seegi Maja (the Almshouse) is known to be the oldest building in Pärnu. It was built in 1658 on the remains of the old almshouse of the Holy Spirit's Church as a shelter to the sick and the cripples.Based on research on the wooden raft under the basement of the building, the old almshouse dates back to 1250-1350. The building was restored to look the way it did in the 17th century. It houses the St. Peterburg Hotel and the restaurant Seegi Maja.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Statue of Raimond Valgre</hi>, Mere puiestee 22. The musician Raimond Valgre who played in Pärnu in 1930s and brought the town a lot of fame, can today be found sitting in the park near Kuursaal, as a bronze statue. You too can sit down next to the beloved Estonian composer and enjoy his beautiful compositions.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Eliisabet's Church</hi>, Nikolai tn 22. Eliisabet's Church, inaugurated in 1750, is the most outstanding sacral building of the Baroque period in Estonia. One of the best organs in Estonia is in Eliisabet's Church and the place is popular as a concert hall among music lovers.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Pärnu Jetty</hi>, Seedri tn 6, Pärnu. The jetty has gained a romantic aura as a place for lovers to take walks on; however, before taking a walk there, be sure to check the water level! The length of both jetties is a bit over two kilometres.</item>
</list>
</text>
