<text id="autogum_academic_doc166" title="The Synthesis of N-(Pyridin-2-yl)-Benzamides from Aminopyridine and Trans-Beta-Nitrostyrene by Fe2Ni-BDC Bimetallic Metal–Organic Frameworks" shortTile="synthesis-npyridinylbenzamides" author="Trinh  Duy Nguyen, Oanh  Kim Thi Nguyen, Thuan  Van Tran, Vinh  Huu Nguyen, Long  Giang Bach, Nhan  Viet Tran, Dai-Viet  N. Vo, Tuyen  Van Nguyen, Seong-Soo Hong, Sy  Trung Do" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2227-9717/7/11/789/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The amide bonds existing in a large number of structures and forming the backbone of the biologically essential proteins are the most basic building blocks of chemistry in nature. The amide is also essential due to its role in the peptide bonds in pharmaceuticals, proteins, and natural products. Amide bonds are characteristically synthesized by combining carboxylic acids and amines; however, the association of these two functional groups does not occur at room temperature. Over the past decades, many researchers have proposed alternative synthesis methods, such as the Staudinger reaction, direct amidation of aldehydes, transition-metal-catalyzed aminocarbonylation, and hydrating coupling of alkynes with azides, esters, alcohols, and alkynes with amines. Pyridyl benzamides are one of the most critical types of N-heterocyclic amides and play an essential role in the composition of many important medicines (e.g., antiulcer agents, kinetoplastid inhibitors, antifungal agents, and luciferase inhibitors). Lately, the number of methods for the synthesis of pyridyl benzamides has been rising significantly. Typical examples include the Cu-catalyzed oxidation of methyl ketones, Cu-catalyzed oxidative coupling of 2-aminopyridines and terminal alkynes with visible light mediation, and the direct oxidative amidation reaction of aldehydes with amines. Since N-heterocyclic amides are increasingly being used in medicine, the discovery of a more effective approach to synthesize pyridyl benzamides is of great importance in the medical industry and has thus been attempted via numerous routes. Xiao-Lan Xu et al. synthesized N-pyridinyl benzamide from benzoylformic acid and aniline using a transition metal catalyst, AgOTf. Additionally, Leiling Deng et al. also created N-pyridinyl benzamide from 2-aminopyridine and phenylacetic acid in the presence of a Cu salt catalyst. Very recently, Zhengwang Chen et al. performed a reaction to synthesize N-pyridinyl benzamide from 2-aminopyridine and <hi rend="italic">trans</hi>-β-nitrostyrene by utilizing Ce(NO3)3·6H2O catalyst in the absence of any oxidant or additive. </p>

<p>Metal–organic frameworks (MOFs), a class of porous materials with excellent potential, have been increasingly used in gas storage and separation because of their high capacity and selectivity properties. MOF crystals are built through the formation of secondary building units (SBUs) consisting of organic linkers and metal ions/clusters. Numerous MOF structures have been designed to obtain different features such as enlarged surface areas, enhanced catalytic activity and electrical conductivity, better interaction at the open metal sites, and improved adsorption. Notably, the application of MOFs as effective catalysts for organic reactions has received much attention. MOFs with metal nodes (metal ions/clusters) can act as the active catalytic sites for many organic reactions such as oxidation reactions, C–C coupling reactions, and hydrogenation reactions. However, the fabrication of a MOF structure with high activity and selectivity still requires further investigation. </p>

<p>Recently, a new bimetallic metal–organic framework (BMOF) with a synergistic effect between different metal ions was developed. Different from the synthesis of MOFs where only one metal ion is combined with organic ligands, the synthesis process of a BMOF produces the pure phase of the BMOF by combining two different metal ions with organic ligands. The BMOFs are expected to have improved stability, activity, and surface area and could be applicable in catalysis. For example, an Fe/Co mixed Hofmann MOF with coupling effects between Co2+ and Fe2+ ions was found to exhibit enhanced catalytic activity for an oxygen evolution reaction compared to that exhibited by the original single-metal MOFs. Despite this, the catalysis applications of BMOFs have not been investigated so far. </p>

<p>The main aim of this study was to appraise the effect of a new BMOF (Fe2Ni-1,4-Benzenedicarboxylic, Fe2Ni-BDC) as a heterogenous catalyst for organic synthesis reactions. Fe2Ni-BDC was generated by bridging iron (III) cations and nickel (II) cations with 1,4-Benzenedicarboxylic anions (BDC−) to create a porous three-dimensional structure. We also investigated the synthesis of N-pyridinyl benzamide via the amidation process of <hi rend="italic">trans</hi>-β-nitrostyrene and 2-aminopyridine using Fe2Ni-BDC as an effective heterogeneous catalyst, without using added reducing agents or oxidizing agents. This catalyst might be reused for the creation of N-pyridinyl benzamide by the amidation reaction without significant depreciation in its efficiency. Fe2Ni-BDC is also satisfactory from the view of green chemistry, as the solid catalyst used for the reaction can be easily recovered and reused. To the best of our knowledge, C=C double bond cleavage has not previously been performed using heterogeneous catalysis. </p>
</text>
