<text id="autogum_academic_doc347" title="Is the Hyporheic Zone Relevant beyond the Scientific Community?" shortTile="hyporheic-zone-relevant" author="Jörg Lewandowski, Shai Arnon, Eddie Banks, Okke Batelaan, Andrea Betterle, Tabea Broecker, Claudia Coll, Jennifer  D. Drummond, Jaime Gaona Garcia, Jason Galloway, Jesus Gomez-Velez, Robert  C. Grabowski, Skuyler  P. Herzog, Reinhard Hinkelmann, Anja Höhne, Juliane Hollender, Marcus  A. Horn, Anna Jaeger, Stefan Krause, Adrian Löchner Prats, Chiara Magliozzi, Karin Meinikmann, Brian  Babak Mojarrad, Birgit  Maria Mueller, Ignacio Peralta-Maraver, Andrea  L. Popp, Malte Posselt, Anke Putschew, Michael Radke, Muhammad Raza, Joakim Riml, Anne Robertson, Cyrus Rutere, Jonas  L. Schaper, Mario Schirmer, Hanna Schulz, Margaret Shanafield, Tanu Singh, Adam  S. Ward, Philipp Wolke, Anders Wörman, Liwen Wu" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4441/11/11/2230/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Challenges, Research Gaps, and How to Overcome Them</head>
<p>
Despite a great amount of HZ research during the past two decades, there are still major research gaps (<figure>Figure 2</figure>) that need to be addressed to progress our understanding of HZ processes and functioning. Further research closing the gaps is necessary to improve our understanding of HZs, to protect HZs and ecosystem services provided by them, and finally to conduct adequate and efficient management measures to restore ecosystem functions and ecosystem services. </p>

<head> 4.1. System Complexity</head>
<p>
Our knowledge about coupled physical, chemical, and biological processes is still limited. Until now, most studies have focused on 1–3 hyporheic processes, which limits our ability to characterize and understand interactions. Individual studies address, for example, the hyporheos, HEFs, hyporheic biogeochemistry, the fate of pharmaceuticals in streambeds, the geomorphology of streams, subsurface hydrogeology, microplastic abundance in streams, or ecological effects of river management measures and damming. Therefore, the water–sediment interface is also an interface of different scientific disciplines. Each discipline has its own methods, definitions, rules, and standards, and often methods vary even between different research groups. In addition, most research groups work only on specific catchments, making it difficult to synthesize the results and translate them to a bigger picture. Thus, there is a need for large studies bringing together different disciplines and research groups to simultaneously investigate various hypotheses. Examples of such efforts are the joint experiments of the project HypoTRAIN and the field campaigns of the project, “Where Rivers, Groundwater, and Disciplines Meet: A Hyporheic Research Network”, funded by the Leverhulme Trust. </p>

<p>Simplifications are common and necessary in HZ research because of the complexity of this system and the involved processes. Nevertheless, much care is required to assure that common simplifications do not result in a systematic bias. For example, bedforms occurring in many streams are dynamic features that form, change shape, migrate, and erode by the force of flowing water. As long as there is sufficient flow velocity in the overlying water body, these bedforms migrate downstream. However, nearly all flume studies have investigated stagnant bedforms and their impacts on HEF. The researchers only rarely considered bed movement, even though the relevance of bed movement for hyporheic exchange has been long recognized, and can lead, for example, to overestimation of nitrate removal. Another example of simplification of complexity is the representation of redox potentials in HZs. There is little empirical evidence on the spatio-temporal extent of the redox zones, how these zones change in response to dynamic hydrologic conditions, and their impacts on nutrients. Furthermore, in many streams the oxygen concentration of the surface water varies dramatically between day and night due to photosynthesis during daytime and respiration of organic matter during nighttime, as already shown in 1956 by Odum, as well as in studies by Mulholland et al., Roberts et al., and Rajwa-Kuligiewicz et al.. However, impacts of fluctuating surface water oxygen concentrations on the extent of the oxic zone in the streambed have rarely been studied (although one example is Brandt et al.). Fieldwork is typically only conducted during the day, potentially missing important diurnal variations in processes. </p>

<head> 4.2. Scale Transferability</head>
<p>
Most field investigations have scale limitations, meaning they are either very localized point measurements in heterogeneous HZs or lack sufficient resolution to draw conclusions about local conditions. Tracer tests remain the primary method for exploring HZ residence times and even nutrient cycling. However, they typically only give a spatially averaged indication of HZ residence times and other characteristics. An improved process understanding is usually difficult or impossible based on large scale investigations. Few studies combine tracer tests with high resolution sampling within the study area. For example, Zarnetske et al. conducted a δ15NO3 and chloride tracer test in a stream in Oregon, United States, in which they sampled detailed solute and nutrient concentrations at many locations within a gravel bar. Schaper et al. combined plot- and reach-scale investigations to identify the relevance of hyporheic removal of TrOCs for their removal in the whole stream. </p>
</text>
