<text id="autogum_voyage_doc489" title="Denver" shortTile="denver" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=9328" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Denver</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.denver.org/">Denver</ref></hi> is the capital and largest city of <ref target="Colorado">Colorado</ref>, <ref target="USA">USA</ref>. Known as "The Mile-High City", Denver sits at an altitude of 5,280 feet (1,600 m) above sea level and lies where the Great Plains give way to the Rocky Mountains. Denver is a large city and one of the fastest growing in the United States.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Denver is a bustling city of more than 650,000 people supporting a fast-growing metropolitan area of nearly 3 million people. The city embraces its cowboy and mining past but also looks toward the future with a vibrant arts and performing arts scene, dozens of great outdoor festivals, and distinct neighborhoods each offering a unique experience. You'll find everything a cosmopolitan city has to offer including a spectacular view of and easy access to the beautiful Rocky Mountains, which are only 12 miles (19 km) west of town.</p>

<p>Denver does have its growing pains. Urban sprawl is becoming a problem, with the metropolitan area sometimes growing faster than the infrastructure can really handle, especially with public transportation. Denver is generally a driving city, and some problems with pollution and traffic are a part of everyday life. Large mass transportation and freeway expansion projects have been completed, including the popular light rail system. By American standards, Denver is betting big on public transportation.</p>

<head>Climate</head>


<p>Denver residents enjoy a mild climate and the third most sunshine of any US state, with four pronounced seasons.</p>

<p>Heavy snowfalls can occur between October and March, often alternating with days of high temperatures and sunshine. About once a year, a snowfall of over a few feet occurs. Winter is also when the Denver area gets pounded by a phenomenon known as the "Chinook". That's when air flows over the mountains to the west and sinks on the leeward (eastern) slopes of the foothills and warms up. This raises air temperatures dramatically, which can last for several days. If you're planning to visit Denver during the winter, be prepared with full winter gear just in case, but also pack a light sweater and T-shirt; the weather is usually very sunny and mild.</p>

<p>Spring in Denver is pleasant, though generally rather brief. Trees begin budding by late March and are in full leaf by mid April to mid May. March, on average, is Denver's snowiest month.</p>

<p>By June, Denver enters its summer season. Temperatures typically rise in earnest at this time, with most heat waves beginning in mid-June and continuing through July, usually Denver's hottest month with temperatures in the high 80s to mid-90s (°F). By late July, the southwest monsoon kicks in. In August, short spells of thunderstorms occur about three to four days per week. By late August, temperatures begin to drop with a noticeable difference between day time and night time temperatures. As the days get shorter through September and October, daytime temperatures drop to the high 50s to mid-60s. Slather on that sunscreen all summer long; the rays are strong and the air is dry, with temperatures often reaching the upper 90s in July and August.</p>

<p>Autumn is a peaceful time to visit, with mild temperatures, little severe weather and lots of that famous clear blue sky. You'll get to see the trees display their fall colors, which usually peak around mid-September in the mountains and October in the city. October usually brings the first snowfall of the season to Denver, although it's very light. By November, it's clear that winter is on its way, with plenty of clouds, some snow and much cooler temperatures.</p>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Denver%20International%20Airport">Denver International Airport</ref> </hi> ( DEN ). Commonly referred to as <hi rend="italic">DIA</hi>, the airport is about 18 miles (29 km) northeast of Downtown Denver and is one of the busiest airports in the nation, due to it being a hub for <ref target="http://www.frontierairlines.com/">Frontier Airlines</ref>, <ref target="http://www.united.com/">United Airlines</ref>, and <ref target="http://www.southwest.com">Southwest Airlines</ref>, and is a popular destination with other major domestic carriers. Many connecting flights are made in DIA, and this airport is more pleasant than most to kill time, with plenty of public art displays, battery charging stations, and free Wi-Fi, as well as a decent selection of restaurants for an airport. Detailed information on the airport can be found on <ref target="Denver%20International%20Airport">its page</ref>.</item>
</list>

 


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Centennial Airport</hi> ( APA ) (south of town, not far from the Denver Technological Center).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Rocky Mountain Metropolitan Airport</hi> ( BJC ) (northwest of town, near Interlocken Business Park, Broomfield and Boulder and the closest airport to Downtown Denver).</item>
</list>

<p>On warm days, the density altitude may make takeoffs difficult; Centennial and Rocky Mountain Airports thus have relatively long runways, to accommodate volumes of private jet traffic. Flight visibility in the Denver area is often in excess of 100 miles; weather fronts tend to travel quickly N-S along the Front Range. For small planes, any direction but west is a good choice.</p>

<head>By car</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">I-25</hi> (north and south), <hi rend="bold">I-70</hi> (east and west), and <hi rend="bold">I-76</hi> (northeast) are the major interstates leading in and out of the city. I-225 and I-270 cross the Denver area.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">U.S. Highway 40</hi> connects Denver to <ref target="Salt%20Lake%20City">Salt Lake City</ref> to the west.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Interstate 70</hi> connects Denver to Summit County, the location of many major ski areas, to the west.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Interstate 25</hi> connects Denver to <ref target="Colorado%20Springs">Colorado Springs</ref> in the south and <ref target="Cheyenne">Cheyenne</ref>, Wyoming in the north.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">U.S. Highway 36</hi> connects to the northwestern suburbs and on to <ref target="Boulder">Boulder</ref>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">C-470</hi> Connects to the southern end of E-470 (also accessible from I-25) leading to the south, southwest, and western suburbs.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Toll Roads</hi> There are a couple of major toll roads in the Denver area, and they can help you avoid some serious rush hour traffic on I-70 and I-25.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">E-470</hi> connects the airport to the southeast, east, northeast and northwest suburbs, C-470 at its southern terminus, and the Northwest Parkway at its northern terminus, leading to <ref target="Boulder">Boulder</ref>. E-470 is a "cashless" toll road - there are no longer any toll plazas and no way to pay tolls except via an in-car device or a billing service. If renting a car, check to see if the rental car agency provides for proper billing; otherwise, you may be subject to billed tolls and hefty service charges. Tolls are $2–4 and without an in-car device, service charges can run to $25 or more.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Northwest Parkway</hi> connects to the north end of E-470 leading to north, northeast and northwest suburbs, and <ref target="Boulder">Boulder</ref>. Also accessible from I-25. Tolls are up to $3 each, and booths accept only cash. There's no attendant between 10PM and 6AM, so pay attention to the signs; though some booths still accept exact change, others require you to pay <ref target="http://www.nwpky.com">online</ref> or by mail.</item>
</list>
</text>
