<text id="autogum_voyage_doc51" title="Boston/North End" shortTile="bostonnorth-end" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=4392" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Boston/North End</head>

<p>Known as "Little Italy" for over a hundred years, the <hi rend="bold">North End</hi> proudly carries the torch of <ref target="Boston">Boston</ref>'s Italian heritage. Its narrow, dense streets consistently draw hordes of visitors looking to experience old world culture and first class dining. The <hi rend="bold">West End</hi> was a sister neighborhood, until it was almost entirely demolished during the 1950s. Today it's the site of a huge sports arena and massive amounts of new construction.</p>

<head>North End</head>

<p>The draw of the North End was evident even to the first Puritan colonists, when powerful minister Increase Mather made this neighborhood his home. This area shared fortunes with Beacon Hill, and people from all walks of life came together to live and worship. The Old North Church was put up in 1723, the oldest church in Boston still standing. As the years wore on, the English and free Blacks living here would be pushed out by a wave of Irish immigrants who arrived in great numbers. Stately mansions were converted into tenements, and living conditions deteriorated. By the mid 19th century, the North End developed something of an unsavory reputation, a red-light district along what is today North Street being chiefly responsible.</p>

<p>By the 1880s the Irish had decamped, and the North End became dominated by Jewish and especially Italian immigrants. These families would barter trade skills to one another, slowly repairing and replacing the area's dilapidated housing stock with what you will see here today. A poorly considered expressway project constructed in 1950s cut this neighborhood off from the rest of Boston. Although this did have the beneficial effect of strengthening already close community connections, and family owned businesses continued to thrive.</p>

<p>When the ugly expressway was removed in 2007 by the Big Dig, a hulking metal barrier was replaced by a welcoming green garden, and the North End was united with the rest of the city once more. This connective parkland invites visitors from around the globe to explore the narrow brick streets, historical highlights, and unparalleled Italian dining that make the North End such a unique destination.</p>

<head>West End</head>

<p>Once simply a small bay and mill pond to early colonists, the West End is another of Boston's neighborhoods built on reclaimed land. After the American revolution, the pond had turned into something of a convenient—although increasingly stinky—garbage dump. By the dawn of the 19th century it was decided to use the earth from one of Beacon Hill's three original hills to fill the pond in.</p>

<p>The creation of this new neighborhood quickly relieved pressure on the town's overcrowded housing stock. Some of the areas first residents would be African American, joining friends and family living nearby on Beacon Hill's north slope. This was one of the few places in the United States where African Americans had a political voice before the Civil War. In the coming years they would be joined by immigrants arriving from across Europe, Russia, and the Middle East.</p>

<p>By the 1950s the once overcrowded area was in the process of "de-slumming" along with the North End. It wasn't perfect, but small shops were still in business and many families still considered it a fine place to live. A city plan to "redevelop" the area was overwhelmingly opposed by residents during a meeting in late 1957. Their pleas fell on deaf ears, however, and eviction notices were handed out a few months later. The following year, a majority of the West End would be razed to the ground.</p>

<p>Today a vibrancy is slowly returning to the remaining pockets of what once was. It will never again feel like a sister to the North End, but as the tall buildings of glass and steel take the place of 50s era parking lots, the West End stands ready to turn the page and write its next chapter.</p>

<head>By foot</head>
<p>The North and West End are of similar size and can be traversed in around 15-20 minutes, so walking is usually going to be your best option. The easiest way to get to the North End is to follow the Freedom Trail from downtown Boston; follow the crowd across the Greenway and you're there. For the West End, turn left as the Greenway ends and the Charlestown bridge looms.</p>

<head>By public transit</head>
<p>By far the largest station in the area is <hi rend="bold">North Station</hi>. Not only is this a major stop on the Orange and Green lines, four <ref target="Boston%23Commuter_rail">Commuter Rail</ref> lines and the Amtrak train to Maine depart from here as well. See <ref target="Boston%23By_train">Boston by train</ref> for more information. While covered more in depth in the <ref target="Boston/Downtown%23By_subway">downtown</ref> article, <hi rend="bold">Haymarket</hi> on the Orange and Green lines can be a very useful station for the visitor. Accessible by Green line tracks; <hi rend="bold">Science Park</hi> is the station you want if you're visiting the Science Museum. If you're going to be on the Blue line anyway, <hi rend="bold">Aquarium</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Bowdoin</hi> stations may also prove useful to you.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>Here are two more neighborhoods where driving is a terrible idea. The North End in particular has streets so narrow they barely accommodate pedestrians, much less automobiles. When visitors aren't clogging up the thoroughfares in summer, the snow picks up that slack in wintertime. There are a few (expensive) parking garages in the West End and downtown if you're determined to go that route. A few businesses in this area may provide valet parking, but call ahead to ensure a spot and don't expect it to come <hi rend="italic">gratis</hi>.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Old North Church</hi> (Christ Church in the City of Boston), 193 Salem St (T: North Station), ☏ +1 617 523-6676 . Jan-Feb: 10AM-4PM daily, Mar-May: 9AM-5PM daily, Jun-Oct: 9AM-6PM daily, Nov-Dec: 9AM-5PM daily. Old North Church was Boston’s second Anglican church. It is most famous for sending the message from Paul Revere that the British were coming by lighting the steeple with lanterns. <hi rend="italic">"One if by land, two if by sea."</hi> Paul Revere had convinced congregant Robert Newman to alert the American militia in Concord, Massachusetts to British troop movements. Newman placed two lanterns in the church steeple and alerted the militia to the approaching British army as Paul Revere began his ride to warn John Handcock and Samuel Adams. By taking a more in-depth behind-the-scenes tour of the church, its history is revealed while exploring the bell tower, and its crypt. $3 donation; behind-the-scenes tours are $6 adults, $5 students/seniors/military, $4 children under 12. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Paul Revere House</hi>, 19 North Sq (T: Haymarket), ☏ +1 617 523-2338 . Apr 15-Oct 31 9:30AM-5:15PM daily, Nov 1-Apr 14 9:30AM-4:15PM daily. Closed Mondays Jan-Mar. Paul Revere is known for his midnight ride from Boston to Lexington, warning all the people along the way that the British were coming. He owned this home for over three decades and it's downtown Boston’s oldest building, dating from somewhere around the 1680s. The average visit is 30 minutes depending on the time of year. $5, $4.50 seniors/students, $1 children 5-17. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Copp's Hill Burying Ground</hi>, Hull St &amp; Snow Hill St (T: North Station). 9AM-5PM daily. The city's second cemetery founded in 1659, Copp's Hill Burying Ground contains more than 1200 marked graves. The remains of notable early Bostonians are interred here, including much of the Mather family; Samuel, Increase, and Cotton. During the Revolutionary war occupying British forces would use the headstones of particularly hated patriots for target practice. Visitors can still see the impressions made by musket fire in the gravestones today. Free. </item>
</list>
</text>
