<text id="autogum_interview_doc410" title="part0_Canada&amp;apos;s Scarborough East (Ward 44) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-scarborough" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-19" dateModified="2013-09-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Scarborough_East_%28Ward_44%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Canada's Scarborough East (Ward 44) city council candidates speak</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 4, 2006</hi></p>
<p>On November 13, Torontonians will be heading to the polls to vote for their ward's councillor and for mayor. Among Toronto's ridings is Scarborough East (Ward 44). One candidates responded to Wikinews' requests for an interview. This ward's candidates include Donald Blair, <hi rend="bold">Diana Hall</hi>, Mohammed Mirza, Ron Moeser, <hi rend="bold">Kevin Richardson</hi>, Richard Rieger, Richard Ross, and Kevin Wellington.</p>
<p>For more information on the election, read <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toronto%20municipal%20election,%202006">Toronto municipal election, 2006</ref>.</p>
<head id="Diana_Hall">Diana Hall</head>
<p>53-year-old <hi rend="bold">Diana Hall</hi> is the Executive Assistant to a City Councillor.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Describe the three most important issues in your campaign.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I want to deliver a made-in-Toronto waste solution – every year Toronto residents produce 500,000 tonnes of waste.  I would like to look at implementing high-rise recycling; investigate new technologies to convert waste into clean energy, expand our recycling program to include materials such as Styrofoam and polystyrene plastic and improve recycling to e-waste to eliminate the 140,000 tonnes of old computers, cellphones and home electronics that end up in our landfills.</p>
<p>I believe we should expand and integrate our public transit system as Ward 44 is poorly serviced by both the TTC and GO transit systems.  I support finding lasting solutions which include developing seamless transit that would make it easier to transfer from TTC to GO, expanding the Sheppard Subway to Scarborough and plan to push the Province to improve GO service with more trains, more often and longer hours.</p>
<p>I believe that the City must live within its means and we should be spending money on the core services that keep the City functioning.  I believe our priorities should be to Improve the Aging Infrastructure.  We need to make sure our water systems, electrical systems, roads and transit systems are safe and well maintained.  I will work to hold tax increases to no more than inflation and want contracts to be openly tendered so we will achieve the best value for our money.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">one</hi></hi> election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Promoting quality communities.  Ward 44 is a great place to live and we have lots of parkland, lots of green space, a new waterfront trail and community centers.  To keep it that way I will: 
<list type="unordered"><item>Promote open communication so that no planning application will go ahead without the community's involvement.</item>
<item>Support the Highland Creek Community Center.  The first step towards achieving this has already been taken.  It was included in the April 2006 Capital Budget.</item>
<item>Make Property Standards Enforcement a Priority. We all enjoy our well-maintained neighbourhoods.   To achieve this I will support  hiring more enforcement officers for our community</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process?</p>
</text>
