<text id="autogum_news_doc447" title="World leaders react to death of Osama bin Laden" shortTile="world-leaders-react" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-05-02" dateModified="2011-05-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/World_leaders_react_to_death_of_Osama_bin_Laden" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>World leaders react to death of Osama bin Laden</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 3, 2011</hi></p>
<hi rend="bold">Osama bin Laden suggested that he was operating in the name of Islam, but in reality he makes a mockery of the fundamental values of his own and every other religion.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Angela_Merkel">Angela Merkel</ref></p>
<p>Leaders and officals around the world have issued varied reactions to the announcement that <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Osama_bin_Laden">Osama bin Laden</ref> has been killed during a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S.">U.S.</ref> military operation in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Pakistan">Pakistan</ref>. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NATO">NATO</ref> has insisted it will continue fighting against militants in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Afghanistan">Afghanistan</ref>, and the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Nations">United Nations</ref> said the death of bin Laden marked a "watershed moment in our common global fight against terrorism."</p>
<p>Announcing that the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Al-Qaeda">al-Qaeda</ref> leader had been killed by U.S. special forces during a forty-minute raid on a compound in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abbottabad">Abbottabad</ref>, near the capital <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Islamabad">Islamabad</ref>, U.S. President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref> said it was "a good day for America." Speaking at a ceremony to celebrate winners of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Medal%20of%20Honor">Medal of Honor</ref>, Obama praised the "anonymous heroes" who took part in the operation. He said: "We may not always know their names, we may not always know their stories, but they are always there on the front lines of freedom and we are truly blessed. As commander-in-chief, I could not be prouder of our men and women in uniform." </p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anders%20Fogh%20Rasmussen">Anders Fogh Rasmussen</ref>, the chief of NATO, vowed the organization would remain fighting in Afghanistan despite the death of bin Laden. "As terrorism continues to pose a direct threat to our security and international stability, international cooperation remains key and NATO is at the heart of that cooperation," he said in a statement. "NATO allies and partners will continue their mission to ensure that Afghanistan never again becomes a safe haven for extremism, but develops in peace and security." </p>
<p>The U.N. and the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/European_Parliament">European Parliament</ref> also welcomed the news. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ban_Ki-moon">Ban Ki-moon</ref>, the U.N. secretary general, said: "The death of Osama bin Laden, announced by President Obama last night, is a watershed moment in our common global fight against terrorism. The crimes of al-Qaeda touched most continents, bringing tragedy and loss of life to thousands of men, women and children."</p>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref> announces the news that bin Laden had been killed. He said it was "a good day for America." Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/White_House">White House</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/David_Cameron">David Cameron</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Kingdom">British</ref> Prime Minister, said the news "will be welcomed right across our country" and was a "massive step forward," but warned the death of bin Laden "does not mark the end of the threat we face from extremist terror." <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Italy">Italian</ref> Prime Minster <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Silvio_Berlusconi">Silvio Berlusconi</ref> said: "This is a great outcome in the fight against evil, in the fight against terrorism, a great outcome for the United States and for all democracies".</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Angela_Merkel">Angela Merkel</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">German</ref> chancellor, said the killing of bin Laden was a "decisive strike" at al-Qaeda. "At his command and in his name, terror was enforced into many countries against men women and children, Christians as well as Muslims," she said. "Osama bin Laden suggested that he was operating in the name of Islam, but in reality he makes a mockery of the fundamental values of his own and every other religion."</p>
<p>Several Asian countries also said bin Laden's death was a step forward in the war against terrorism. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China">Chinese</ref> spokeswoman <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jiang%20Yu">Jiang Yu</ref> said "China has taken note of the announcement. We believe the death of Osama bin Laden is a milestone and a positive development for the international anti-terrorism efforts." <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Japan">Japan</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Malaysia">Malaysia</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Singapore">Singapore</ref> also welcomed the news.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia">Australia</ref> pledged not to withdraw forces from Afghanistan after the announcement. "Osama bin Laden declared war on innocent people and today he has paid the price for that declaration," <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Julia_Gillard">Julia Gillard</ref>, the Prime Minister, said. "The mission in Afghanistan will continue," she added, saying al-Qaeda "will continue". <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Nicolas_Sarkozy">Nicolas Sarkozy</ref>, the President of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">France</ref>, said bin Laden was a "promoter of the ideology of hatred and was the chief of a terrorist organization responsible for the deaths of thousands of victims, especially in Muslim countries," and "justice has been done" for the victims of al-Qaeda attacks.</p>
</text>
