<text id="autogum_academic_doc256" title="Estimation of Origin-Destination Flows of Passenger Cars in 1925 in Old Tokyo City, Japan" shortTile="estimation-origindestination" author="Kazuki Ishikawa, Daichi Nakayama" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2220-9964/8/11/472/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
In recent years, surveys of personal travel behavior have been carried out around the world, and these surveys have been used for understanding the characteristics of people flow and for urban planning. In addition, the results of these surveys have been compiled and disclosed to the public and it is possible to acquire and use them easily. For example, the “National Travel Survey” (NTS) in the UK, the “National Household Travel Survey” (NHTS) in the US, and the “Mobility in Germany” survey have been conducted, and many studies using the data from these surveys have been carried out. In Japan, the Person Trip (PT) survey and the Road Traffic Census (RTC) have been carried out since after World War II. The first extensive PT survey was done in 1967 in the urban areas of Hiroshima City, and PT surveys have been conducted for more than 30 years in the urban areas of Japan. In these surveys, many items, including personal properties, travel objects, travel times, type of mobility, and so on, have been investigated to understand the detailed behavior of people. Many studies have been carried out using such data. Sekimoto et al. (2011) calculated highly detailed people flows for every 1 minute from PT survey data, and some secondary studies have been carried out based on this flow data. The Road Traffic Census (RTC) is a traffic survey which covers the whole of Japan and includes investigations, such as origin-destination (OD) flows, using questionnaires about daily travel, road state investigating surveys, the traffic census, and travel speed investigations. Since the first OD survey in 1958, it has been conducted approximately every 5 years. Kohira et al. (2014) and Fujita et al. (2016) examined traffic flows based on the results of these OD surveys. Recently, obtaining various data concerning human mobility has become easy due to the rapid development of location information techniques. For example, phone call data, smartcard use, and other data like global positioning system (GPS) log data and social networking service data have been used for human mobility studies. Studies using such data were reviewed by Yue et al. (2014). Studies concerning vehicle counts from inductive loop sensors are also carried out. However, these surveys have been conducted mostly after World War II, when these information technologies became available, and it is impossible to acquire people and traffic flows for the modern era. </p>

<p>Engineering studies on human movement have been actively reported. However, these movements have been studied from the perspective of urban planning and the development of the transportation infrastructure, and people and traffic flows in the past have not been considered in these studies. The studies, which take into account the relationships between urban structure and traffic flow, examined them from the point of view of urban transport geography; however, quantitative studies about the estimation of old traffic flows have also not been addressed in this field. There are some quantitative studies that have been carried out, including analyzing historical demography, the changes of urban structure, and land use from the past to the present age. On the other hand, the number of studies on historical geography using the geographic information system (GIS) has risen in recent years. However, these studies did not focus on human mobility. </p>
</text>
