<text id="autogum_fiction_doc150" title="Miss Billy's Decision" shortTile="missbillysdecision" author="Porter, Eleanor H. (Eleanor Hodgman)" type="fiction" dateCollected="2019-10-22" sourceURL="http://gutenberg.readingroo.ms/3/6/362/362-0.txt">
<head>CHAPTER XXIX. KATE WRITES A LETTER</head>

<p>Bertram feared that he knew, before the portrait was hung, that it was a failure. He was sure that he knew it on the evening of the twentieth when he encountered the swiftly averted eyes of some of his artist friends, and saw the perplexed frown on the faces of others. But he knew, afterwards, that he did not really know it--till he read the newspapers during the next few days.</p>

<p>There was praise--oh, yes; the faint praise that kills. There was some adverse criticism, too; but it was of the light, insincere variety that is given to mediocre work by unimportant artists. Then, here and there, appeared the signed critiques of the men whose opinion counted--and Bertram knew that he had failed. Neither as a work of art, nor as a likeness, was the portrait the success that Henshaw's former work would seem to indicate that it should have been. Indeed, as one caustic pen put it, if this were to be taken as a sample of what was to follow--then the famous originator of “The Face of a Girl” had “a most distinguished future behind him.”</p>

<p>Seldom, if ever before, had an exhibited portrait attracted so much attention. As Bertram had said, uncounted eyes were watching for it before it was hung, because it was a portrait of the noted beauty, Marguerite Winthrop, and because two other well-known artists had failed where he, Bertram Henshaw, was hoping to succeed. After it was hung, and the uncounted eyes had seen it--either literally, or through the eyes of the critics--interest seemed rather to grow than to lessen, for other uncounted eyes wanted to see what all the fuss was about, anyway. And when these eyes had seen, their owners talked. Nor did they, by any means, all talk against the portrait. Some were as loud in its praise as were others in its condemnation; all of which, of course, but helped to attract more eyes to the cause of it all.</p>

<p>For Bertram and his friends these days were, naturally, trying ones. William finally dreaded to open his newspaper. (It had become the fashion, when murders and divorces were scarce, occasionally to “feature” somebody's opinion of the Henshaw portrait, on the first page--something that had almost never been known to happen before.) Cyril, according to Marie, played “perfectly awful things on his piano every day, now.” Aunt Hannah had said “Oh, my grief and conscience!” so many times that it melted now into a wordless groan whenever a new unfriendly criticism of the portrait met her indignant eyes.</p>

<p>Of all Bertram's friends, Billy, perhaps not unnaturally, was the angriest. Not only did she, after a time, refuse to read the papers, but she refused even to allow certain ones to be brought into the house, foolish and unreasonable as she knew this to be.</p>

<p>As to the artist himself, Bertram's face showed drawn lines and his eyes sombre shadows, but his words and manner carried a stolid indifference that to Billy was at once heartbreaking and maddening.</p>

<p>“But, Bertram, why don't you do something? Why don't you say something? Why don't you act something?” she burst out one day.</p>

<p>The artist shrugged his shoulders.</p>

<p>“But, my dear, what can I say, or do, or act?” he asked.</p>

<p>“I don't know, of course,” sighed Billy. “But I know what I'd like to do. I should like to go out and--fight somebody!”</p>

<p>So fierce were words and manner, coupled as they were with a pair of gentle eyes ablaze and two soft little hands doubled into menacing fists, that Bertram laughed.</p>

<p>“What a fiery little champion it is, to be sure,” he said tenderly. “But as if fighting could do any good--in this case!”</p>

<p>Billy's tense muscles relaxed. Her eyes filled with tears.</p>

<p>“No, I don't suppose it would,” she choked, beginning to cry, so that Bertram had to turn comforter.</p>

<p>“Come, come, dear,” he begged; “don't take it so to heart. It's not so bad, after all. I've still my good right hand left, and we'll hope there's something in it yet--that'll be worth while.”</p>

<p>“But <hi rend="italic">this</hi> one isn't bad,” stormed Billy. “It's splendid! I'm sure, I think it's a b-beautiful portrait, and I don't see <hi rend="italic">what</hi> people mean by talking so about it!”</p>

<p>Bertram shook his head. His eyes grew sombre again.</p>

<p>“Thank you, dear. But I know--and you know, really--that it isn't a splendid portrait. I've done lots better work than that.”</p>

<p>“Then why don't they look at those, and let this alone?” wailed Billy, with indignation.</p>

<p>“Because I deliberately put up this for them to see,” smiled the artist, wearily.</p>

<p>Billy sighed, and twisted in her chair.</p>

<p>“What does--Mr. Winthrop say?” she asked at last, in a faint voice.</p>

<p>Bertram lifted his head.</p>

<p>“Mr. Winthrop's been a trump all through, dear. He's already insisted on paying for this--and he's ordered another.”</p>

<p>“Another!”</p>

<p>“Yes. The old fellow never minces his words, as you may know. He came to me one day, put his hand on my shoulder, and said tersely: 'Will you give me another, same terms? Go in, boy, and win. Show 'em! I lost the first ten thousand I made. I didn't the next!' That's all he said. Before I could even choke out an answer he was gone. Gorry! talk about his having a 'heart of stone'! I don't believe another man in the country would have done that--and done it in the way he did--in the face of all this talk,” finished Bertram, his eyes luminous with feeling.</p>
</text>
