<text id="autogum_interview_doc071" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Australian wheelchair basketball coach Tom Kyle" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-06-30" dateModified="2015-11-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_wheelchair_basketball_coach_Tom_Kyle" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I know the ones.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tom Kyle:</hi> You know the ones?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tom Kyle:</hi> And they gave me that, and they said, "Oh, you got no software." One of the guys at council said "we've got an old copy of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DataEase">DataEase</ref>. We might give you that," which old an old database programming tool. So I took that and I wrote a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/point%20of%20sale">point of sale</ref> system for the centre. And then we upgraded from DataEase, we went to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/dBase%20III">dBase III</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/dBase%20IV">dBase IV</ref>. Didn't like dBase IV, it had all these bugs in it, so my system started to crash. So I'd go home at night and write the program, and then come back and put it into the centre during the day so they could collect the statistics I wanted. It was a simple point of sale system, but it was effective, and then we upgraded that to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clipper%20(programming%20language)">Clipper</ref> and I started programming object orientated while I was there, and wrote the whole booking system, we had bookings for the pools, learn-to-swim bookings, point of sale. We actually connected it to an automatic turnstyle with the coin entry so it gave me a whole heap of new skills in IT that I never had before, self-taught, because I'd never done any IT courses, when I went to Brisbane City Council and that didn't work out then I started my own computer company. I took what I'd written in Clipper and decided to rewrite that in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Powerbuilder">Powerbuilder</ref>. You've probably heard of it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Yes.  </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tom Kyle:</hi>   So that's when I started my own company. Walked out of the Brisbane City Council. I had an ethical disagreement with my boss, who spent some council money going to a convention at one place and doing some private consultancy, which I didn't agree with Council funds being done like that, so I resigned. Probably the best move of my business life. It then allowed me then to become an entrepreneur of my own, so I wrote my own software, and started selling a leisure package which basically managed leisure centres around the country. And I had the AIS [<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australian_Institute_of_Sport">Australian Institute of Sport</ref>]  as one of my clients.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Oh!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tom Kyle:</hi>    Yes, they have a turnstyle entry system and learn-to-swim booking system and they were using it for many years. Had people all over the country. I ended up employing ten people in my company, which was quite good, right through to, I suppose, 1997?, somewhere in there. And I was still coaching full time, well, not full time, but, voluntary, for about 35 hours a week at Ashgrove at the time, as well as doing, I did the Brisbane under-14 rep side as well, so that gave me a good appreciation of rep basketball. So I'd been coaching a lot of school basketball in that time. And then in 2000 I decided to give that away and went to work for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jupiters%20Hotel%20and%20Casino">Jupiters Casino</ref>.  Bit of a change. I started as a business analyst and ended up as a product development manager. I was doing that, I was going through a divorce, still coaching at Ashgrove, I had been at Ashgrove now from 1992 through to 2003.  I had been coaching full time as the head coach, coordinator of all the coaches and convener of the sport for the school. We won our competitions a number of times. We went to the state schools competition as a team there one year. Which we did quite well. Didn't win it but, did quite well. In 2003 my boys had finished at school and I'd got a divorce at that stage. Been offered another opportunity to go to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Villanova%20College">Villanova College</ref>, which was a competing school across the other side of the river. So I started head coaching there for five years. It was there where I started to get into <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wheelchair_basketball">wheelchair basketball</ref>. It is an interesting story, because at that stage I'd moved on from Jupiters Casino. I'd actually started working for various companies, and I ended up with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suncorp%20group">Suncorp Metway</ref> as a project manager. Got out of my own company and decided to earn more money as a consultant. [evil laugh]</p>
</text>
