<text id="autogum_reddit_doc043" title="A simple fix to the Obj 277" shortTile="simple-fix-obj-" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-05-31" dateModified="2018-05-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8nlfna" speakerList="#V_Epsilon, #WoT_Slave" speakerCount="2">
<head>A simple fix to the Obj 277</head>
<sp who="#WoT_Slave">
<p>People have a lot of complaints about this tank being too good, and it's definitely 'the next best thing' people will want to free exp. It (in it's current form) makes strong tanks like the 5a, 113, and OBJ 430 seem redundant in CW as it can do most of their roles (armor, alpha, speed) but better. To slow the bullshit power creep cycle WG perpetuates, and to keep this tank in-line with the T-10, why not keep everything the same about the 277 but **change the alpha from 490 -> 440.** The base DPM would drop to an acceptable base ~2400, and this tank would feel more like the T-10 which precedes it (but better since it's a tier 10). The 5a would still be more useful because of the higher alpha/dpm, and the 113 would still have DPM. The 430u would also have higher DPM than it, but is slower and worse accuracy. (Frankly the 430u is due for a nerf too). Let there be trade offs for tanks. I'm hating world of Obj 268v4 in the current campaign, and I'd rather not see World of Obj 277 in the next year of CW. (Or that Obj 726 bullshit). #TL;DR: Nerf the Obj 277's alpha from 490 -> 440</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#V_Epsilon">
<p>It won't flat out powercreep the 5A, it lacks the gun depression to do so. HEAT also gives a notable advantage at tier 10 due to the 85 degree ricochet angle (not to say 350 pen APCR means nothing), and its mobility is still arguably better. Slightly lower top speed and hp t ratio, but significantly better terrain resistance stats and effective traverse. </p>
<p>430U isn't being powercrept either, it'll still likely have the armour advantage, and the mobility advantage is undeniable -- the medium tank effective traverse is what sets the 430U apart from other fast 'heavies'. Don't forget the camo, which is easy to get over 30% when stationary and like 25% when moving (iirc, don't have my client open) unlike every heavy ever. </p>
<p>It'll be strong, but I think it's about on par with the 5A and 430U. The only thing I would advocate nerfing for now, before it goes through the live server stages of testing, is the APCR pen and shell speed. 330-335 pen APCR with 1300 m s or so would suffice, not 350 pen with 1800 m s.</p>
</sp>
</text>
