<text id="autogum_voyage_doc86" title="Fort Worth" shortTile="fort-worth" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=11911" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Fort Worth</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Fort Worth</hi> is a city in the <ref target="Prairies%20and%20Lakes">Prairies and Lakes</ref> region of <ref target="Texas">Texas</ref>. With a population of approximately 661,000, it is Texas' 5th largest city. It is part of the <ref target="Dallas-Fort%20Worth%20Metroplex">Dallas-Fort Worth Metroplex</ref>, which has a population exceeding 6 million. Sometimes referred to as Cowtown, it is by far closer to its cowboy roots than neighboring <ref target="Dallas">Dallas</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Fort Worth grew from a military camp established at the close of the Mexican War by Gen. Winfield Scott, and named for Gen. William Jenkins Worth who fought in the war. Forty-two men of Company F, 2nd Dragoons, established the camp on June 6, 1849. The Fort Worth to Yuma, Arizona, stage line was established in 1850. The city became the seat of Tarrant County 1860, and after the Civil War, it became a major shipping and supply depot for cattlemen.</p>

<head>Climate</head>
<p>Fort Worth is located in the American South, and has a subtropical climate with mild winters, hot summers, and a wet spring and fall in between. In winter and summer it can also be a very dry place, as it receives warmer, drier weather from the Mojave Desert in the west and the Great Plains in the north.</p>

<p>Winters are generally mild, with average highs in the mid to upper 50s (10-15 °C) and average lows around the freezing mark (0-5 °C). It is not uncommon for Winter days with highs in the upper 60s (~20°C) with the following days high temperature 20-30 degrees cooler. It may snow in Fort Worth a couple times a year, and occasionally winter temperatures will not get above freezing (32°F, 0 °C), but for the most part winter is just relatively dry and cool. There is, however, the danger of freezing rain and ice storms.</p>

<p>Spring and fall bring very pleasant temperatures, but spring is also known for its storms. Fort Worth is at the Southern tip of Tornado Alley, and springtime weather can be quite volatile and severe storms often occur. Summers are hot and dry - but often humid - with temperatures frequently surpassing 100 °F (38 °C).</p>

<p>Average precipitation in Fort Worth is 33 inches (830 mm) per year.</p>

<head>Neighborhoods</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">TCU</hi> (Texas Christian University), 2900 S University Dr,= 76109. The TCU area is dominated by the campus. Some unique restaurants and boutiques are mixed with standard college fare, but the campus is beautiful and shows up in force (and in Purple) for gamedays</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sundance Square</hi> (Downtown Fort Worth), 400 Main St,= 76102. Sundance Square is a city park in downtown that plays host to multiple events year round. Night and weekend parking is free and additional security patrols not only keep the area safe, but also can help you find your next destination.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Stockyards</hi>. A national historic district, the Stockyards is the iconic background for which Fort Worth is known. The backdrop is all things western from cattle drives and BBQ to country music and belt buckles. No trip to Fort Worth is complete without a quick stop here.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Cultural District</hi>. Home to world class museum, the stock show &amp; rodeo as well as numerous restaurants and merchants, this area hosts many of Fort Worth's main attractions. Located across the Trinity River, 2 miles west of downtown, this area could be though of as uptown. The area is also known as West 7th.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Near Southside</hi>. Also called South Main and Magnolia, this is the area where artists and more liberal mindsets are welcome. The area hosts multiple of the cities micro breweries, bars and restaurants. The area is undergoing a renaissance with new building and merchants, but the growth is keeping with the vibe of the current culture.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Southwest Fort Worth</hi> (Camp Bowie, Hulen, Clearfork). While not a single neighborhood, Southwest Fort Worth has a collection of different shopping areas and neighborhood restaurant clusters.</item>
</list>


<head>By plane</head>
<p>All the major American carriers and many international ones provide scheduled passenger service into the ( DFW ), located from downtown Fort Worth. This airport is one of three major hubs for American Airlines. American Airlines is also headquartered in Fort Worth.</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>The at 1001 Jones St is the central hub for Amtrak inter-city trains and <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.trinityrailwayexpress.org/">Trinity Railway Express</ref></hi> (TRE) commuter trains to Dallas, along with Greyhound inter-city bus service and local bus service provided by the T. TRE trains can provide a stress-free way to travel between the two cities during rush hour and also serve the more historic at 1600 Throckmorton St on the south side of downtown.</p>

<ref target="Amtrak">Amtrak</ref>'s Texas Eagle provides daily service between <ref target="Chicago">Chicago</ref>, <ref target="Illinois">Illinois</ref> and <ref target="San%20Antonio">San Antonio</ref>, Texas with stops in Fort Worth and Dallas. Also, Amtrak's <ref target="http://www.heartlandflyer.com/">Heartland Flyer</ref> provides daily service between Fort Worth and <ref target="Oklahoma%20City">Oklahoma City</ref>, and points in between. Woefully underfunded, passenger train service in the United States is a slow but scenic way to travel, if you aren't too concerned about arriving on time.

<p>Alternatively, arrive from DFW Airport on <hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://ridetrinitymetro.org/texrail/">TEXRail</ref></hi>, another commuter train that provides direct rail service from the airport to downtown Fort Worth.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>Fort Worth may be easily reached via I-20 or I-30 from the east or west, or by I-35W from the north or south. I-35 splits into two branches north of the Dallas/Fort Worth metropolitan area, the west branch going to Fort Worth and the east branch (I-35E) to Dallas. The branches rejoin to the south.</p>

<p>Car rental companies include:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.alamo.com/">Alamo Rent A Car</ref></hi>, Toll free: +1-800-462-5266.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.avis.com/">Avis Rent A Car</ref></hi>, Toll free: +1-800-331-1212.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.budget.com">Budget Rent A Car</ref></hi>, Toll free: +1-800-527-0700.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.dollar.com/">Dollar Rent A Car</ref></hi>, Toll free: +1-800-800-3665.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.e-zrentacar.com">E-Z Rent-A-Car</ref></hi>, Toll free: +1-800-277-5171.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.enterprise.com">Enterprise Rent-A-Car</ref></hi>, Toll free: +1-800-261-7331.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.hertz.com">Hertz Car Rental</ref></hi>, Toll free: +1-800-654-3131.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.thrifty.com">Thrifty</ref></hi>, Toll free: +1-800-847-4389.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://dfweliteautorental.com">DFW Elite Auto Rental</ref></hi>, +1 817-838-7368.</item>
</list>


<head>By bus</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.greyhound.com">Greyhound</ref></hi>. Bus stop is at the Fort Worth Intermodal Transportation Center. Also, subsidiaries of Greyhound, such as TNM&amp;O serve as the regional carrier.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://us.megabus.com">Megabus</ref></hi>. Service from <ref target="Houston">Houston</ref>, <ref target="San%20Antonio">San Antonio</ref>, <ref target="Austin">Austin</ref>, <ref target="Memphis">Memphis</ref>, <ref target="Little%20Rock">Little Rock</ref>, <ref target="Oklahoma%20City">Oklahoma City</ref>, and <ref target="Norman%20%28Oklahoma%29">Norman</ref>. Bus stop is located at 710 Davis St in <ref target="Grand%20Prairie">Grand Prairie</ref>. Fares $1 and up.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.autobusesamericanos.us/EN/Home.shtml">Autobus Americanos</ref></hi>. Mexican trans-border bus line with services to various points in Mexico. Bus stop is located at 5215 McCart in Fort Worth.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://ticket.gruposenda.com/">Turimex Internacional</ref></hi>. Mexican trans-border bus line with services to various points in Mexico. Bus stop is located at 3620 Hemphill St.</item>
</list>
</text>
