<text id="autogum_interview_doc488" title="part4_ACLU, EFF challenging US &amp;apos;secret&amp;apos; court orders seeking Twitter data" shortTile="partaclu-eff-challenging" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-04-06" dateModified="2019-09-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/ACLU%2C_EFF_challenging_US_%27secret%27_court_orders_seeking_Twitter_data" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>My research indicates that this is the case for other Internet services but I cannot tell whether it is the case for Twitter.</p>
<p>Note that even though IP logging, as done by Twitter, is similar to the logging done by GSM [mobile phone] operators, the major difference seems to be that Twitter is subject to US regulation, no matter the citizenship of its users. I find this rather disturbing.</p>
<p>Using 3), one could search for Birgitta on other Internet services, such as social networks, to find more information on her (e.g., hidden accounts). Recent research on privacy shows that people tend to use the same e-mail address to register an account on different social networks (even when they don't want these accounts to be linked together). Obviously, one could then issue subpoenas for these accounts as well.</p>
<p>I do not have the expertise to comment on what could be done with 4).</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  As I believe Jonsdottir to be involved in the Icelandic Modern Media Initiative (IMMI), what are the wider implications beyond the "WikiLeaks witchhunt"?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Le Blond:</hi> Personal data can be used to discredit, especially if the data is not public.</item></list>
<head id="Liberty,_and_the_Electronic_Frontier">Liberty, and the Electronic Frontier</head>
<p>Having been alerted to the ongoing case through a joint press release by the ACLU and EFF, <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> sought clarification on the primary issues which the two non-profits saw as particularly important in challenging the U.S. Government over the 'secret' court orders. Rebecca Jeschke, Media Relations Director for the EFF, explained in more detail the points crucial to them, responding to a few questions from <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> on the case:</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  As a worse-case, what precedents would be considered if this went to the Supreme Court?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold"> Rebecca Jeschke:</hi> It's extremely hard to know at this stage if this would go to the Supreme Court, and if it did, what would be at issue. However, some of the interesting questions about this case center on the rights of people around the world when they use US Internet services. This case questions the limits of US law enforcement, which may turn out to be very different from the limits in other countries.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Since this is clearly a politicised attack on free speech with most chilling potential repercussions for the press, whistleblowers, and by-and-large anyone the relevant U.S. Government departments objects to the actions of, what action do you believe should be taken to protect free speech rights?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Jeschke:</hi> We believe that, except in very rare circumstances, the government should not be permitted to obtain information about individuals' private Internet communications in secret. We also believe that Internet companies should, whenever possible, take steps to ensure their customers are notified about requests for information and have the opportunity to respond.</item></list>
</text>
