<text id="autogum_fiction_doc456" title="Tom Swift Among the Diamond Makers; Or, The Secret of Phantom Mountain" shortTile="tomswiftdiamondmakers" author="Appleton, Victor" type="fiction" dateCollected="2019-10-22" sourceURL="http://gutenberg.readingroo.ms/1/2/8/1282/1282-0.txt">
<head>CHAPTER XVII--THE PHANTOM CAPTURED</head>

<p>Surprise held Tom and his friends almost spellbound for the moment. The young inventor's hand went toward the pocket where he carried his revolver. Mr. Jenks, who had the only other weapon, sought to draw it, but he was stopped by a gesture of one of the two men with guns.</p>

<p>“Hold on, strangers!” the man cried. “I know what you're up to! Better not try to draw anything--it might not be healthy. Now, then, who are you, and what do you want?”</p>

<p>The question came rather as a surprise, at least to Tom and Mr. Jenks. They had taken it for granted that these men--if they were the diamond makers--would know Mr. Jenks, and guess at his errand in coming back to Phantom Mountain. But, it seemed, that they took them all for casual strangers.</p>

<p>No one answered for a moment. Tom caught the eye of Mr. Jenks, and there was a look of hope in it. If ever there was a time for strategy, it was now. Evidently Munson, the stowaway on the airship, had not yet been able to send a warning to his confederates. And neither of the two men recognized Mr. Jenks as the man who had been defrauded of his rights. It might be possible to conceal the real object of the adventurers until they had time to formulate a plan of action.</p>

<p>“Well,” exclaimed the man with the gun, impatiently, “I ask you folks a question. What do you want?”</p>

<p>Fortunately, neither Mr. Damon nor Mr. Parker replied. The former because he deferred to Tom and Mr. Jenks, and the scientist because he was busy inspecting some curious rocks he picked up. As it turned out this was the luckiest thing he could have done. It lent color to what Mr. Jenks said a moment later.</p>

<p>“What are you doing up here?” demanded the man again. “Don't you know this is private property?”</p>

<p>“We--we were just looking around,” answered Mr. Jenks, which was true enough; as far as it went.</p>

<p>“Prospecting,” added Tom.</p>

<p>“After gold?” demanded the second man, suspiciously.</p>

<p>“We'd be glad to find some,” retorted the lad. At that moment Mr. Parker began breaking off bits of rock with a small geologist's hammer which he carried. The men with the guns looked at him.</p>

<p>“So you think you'll find gold up here?” asked the one who had first spoken.</p>

<p>“Is there any?” inquired Tom, trying to make his voice sound eager.</p>

<p>“Nary a bit, strangers,” was the answer, and the two men laughed heartily. “Now, we don't want to seem harsh,” went on the man who seemed to be the spokesman, “but you'd better get away from here. This is private ground, and dangerous too--how'd you ever get up the trail--we heard it was destroyed.”</p>

<p>“There is still a narrow path,” said Mr. Jenks. “We came up that--the lightning and landslide haven't left much of it, though.”</p>

<p>Mr. Parker looked quickly up from the rocks at which he was tapping with his small hammer. “You have terrific lightning up here,” he said. “I am much interested in it, from a scientific standpoint. I predict that some day the entire mountain will be destroyed by a blast from the sky.”</p>

<p>“I hope it won't be right away,” spoke one of the men. “Now I guess you folks had better be leaving while there's a path left to go down by.”</p>

<p>“Might I ask,” broke in Mr. Parker, as calmly as though he was lecturing to a class of students, “might I ask if you have noticed any peculiar effect of the lightning up here on the summit of the mountain? Does it fuse and melt rocks, so to speak?”</p>

<p>“What's that?” cried the spokesman, with a sudden flash of anger. The two men looked at each other.</p>

<p>“I wanted to know, merely for scientific reasons, whether the lightning up here ever melted rocks?” repeated Mr. Jenks.</p>

<p>“Well, whether it's for scientific reasons or for any other, I'm not going to answer you!” snapped the man. “It's none of your affair what the lightning does up here. Now you'd all better 'vamoose'--clear out!”</p>

<p>“All right--we'll go,” said Tom, quickly, at the same time motioning to Mr. Jenks to agree with him. The eyes of the young inventor were roving about. He saw what looked like a second trail, leading down the mountain, from the far side of the cave. He was convinced now that there was another way to get to it. Possibly they might find it. At any rate nothing more could be done now. They must go back, for the cavern was too well guarded to attempt to enter it by force--at least just yet.</p>

<p>“Yes, we'll go back,” assented Mr. Jenks.</p>

<p>Mr. Parker was tapping away at the rocks. He looked toward the black mouth of the big cave. On what corresponded to the roof of it, some distance back from the entrance, he saw a slender metal rod sticking up into the air.</p>

<p>“May I ask if that's a lightning rod?” he inquired innocently. “If it is, I should like to ask about its action in a mountain that is so impregnated with iron ore.</p>

<p>“You may ask until you get tired!” cried the spokesman, again showing unreasoning anger, “but you'll get no answer from us. Now get away from here before we do something desperate. You're on private ground and you're not wanted. Clear out while you have the chance.”</p>
</text>
