<text id="autogum_interview_doc506" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Jeremy Hanke, editor of MicroFilmmaker Magazine" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-11" dateModified="2019-08-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Jeremy_Hanke%2C_editor_of_MicroFilmmaker_Magazine" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Jeremy Hanke, editor of MicroFilmmaker Magazine</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, April 11, 2008</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> held an exclusive interview with Jeremy Hanke, editor of <hi rend="italic">MicroFilmmaker Magazine</hi>. The magazine, which is free to read online, was started as a resource for the low budget moviemaker and features book, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/independent%20film">independent film</ref>, equipment and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Software">software</ref> reviews as well as articles on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/film%20distribution">film distribution</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/special%20effects">special effects</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/lighting">lighting</ref>.</p>
<p>He says that one of the goals of the magazine is to "connect low-budget filmmakers via a feeling of community, as many.....often compete so viciously against one another in film festivals for coveted "shots" with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cinema%20of%20the%20United%20States">Hollywood</ref>, that they can quickly forget their similarities."</p>
<p>When asked if films made on a shoestring budget can really compete with those made for millions of dollars, he replied, "no…yes…and absolutely.  Allow me to explain." And so he does in the interview below.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews (Joseph Ford)</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why was <hi rend="italic">MicroFilmmaker Magazine</hi> started? How does it help the thousands of independent filmmakers out there with big ideas and little cash?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mr. Hanke:</hi>  As a budding low-budget filmmaker at the beginning of the new millenia, I found that it was very hard to find anyone who had practical articles on making films as professional as possible with little money.  Most of the video and film magazines would talk about equipment that could range from $10,000 - $30,000 apiece, which clearly was out of the $7K budget for my first film, which had come from scrimping and saving while working as a commissioned computer salesman.  As I did more research, I discovered that statistically, as many as 70%-80% of all Indie films were being made for less than $30,000, which, obviously, my first film’s budget definitely fell into.  Hollywood considers anything below $100,000 to have such a low budget that it’s considered a no-budget film.  Because of that low regard, no one was wasting their time making magazines or websites designed to help these less-than-no-budget filmmakers, despite the fact that they were (and are becoming even more) the majority of filmmakers in the world.</p>
<p>With no publicized help, I made my first two feature films over the course of four years with XL-1s and other equipment borrowed from local colleges, utilizing helpers that were of extremely varied experiences and drive.  In the process, I learned a pile of things through hard knocks.</p>
<p>After these films were mostly completed, I remember looking online for any new sites that might have cropped up devoted to low-budget filmmaking.  That’s when I found some devoted to microcinema—a boutique-style of video-making that’s largely composed of home videos and short parodies that are meant to be shared with friends and neighbors.  The term originated in San Francisco and was designed to be similar to the micro-brewery movement, which encouraged home brews that were shared in communities.   The concepts of a community of sharing and the emphasis on low-budgets were an encouragement for us, but most microcinema never tried to look professional or strove for high standards, so it fell short of the sort of help I was looking for.</p>
</text>
