<text id="autogum_interview_doc202" title="part3_BDSM as business: Interviews with Dominatrixes" shortTile="partbdsm-business" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-28" dateModified="2008-01-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BDSM_as_business%3A_Interviews_with_Dominatrixes" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Like if you were a stripper or something like that.  You can’t be a forty year old stripper; whereas a 40 year old Dom is like a Godsend!</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  I don’t know if people really know that.  And there’s people like The Baroness, who is older, and she is very much involved in the scene.  Although I don’t know if she’d consider herself professional.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How long do you see yourself doing this, Jada?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  I honestly couldn’t say.  It’s the same thing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It’s open-ended, but you do see it coming to an end at some point?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Well, yeah, all things come to an end at some point no matter what’s going to happen.  It’s always going to be something I enjoy; I took a break for a couple of months and then found myself coming back because I missed it.  It could be the same thing.  At any given time I could suddenly be like, “You know, I’m not sure.”</p>
<head id="What_they_get_asked_to_do">What they get asked to do</head>
<figure><caption>Alex in The Blue Room with a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St.%20Andrew's%20Cross%20(BDSM)">St. Andrew's Cross</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What would be a typical request?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  I don’t know if I can really say that, because everyone is <hi rend="italic">so</hi> specific.  I mean, there are things you get requested for much more often, like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foot%20worship">foot worship</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boot%20worship">boot worship</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  That’s something that comes up a lot…</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  And even if it’s not, you tend to incorporate it. [Giggles]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What happens in a foot worship session?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  It’s again, even though it sounds straight-forward, and I could see where people would think foot worship is one thing, but it manifests itself in so many different ways.  Some people like to be <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trample">stepped on with feet</ref>, some people just like to look at them, others like to lick boots, some like to kiss toes, some like to rub feet—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Some like to give <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pedicure">pedicures</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  It’s kind of endless.  As many individuals as there are, they have a different approach to it.  And that’s what I find fascinating.  I always wonder, and sometimes ask them.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are your reactions scripted by them, such as whether you act disgusted or happy?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  Definitely.  Some people make requests and say things like, “I like it when my Mistress is very strict with me”; others say, “I like it when it is just more conversational and when you are just being real.”  Jada and I have sessioned together, and I think we are both pretty <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intuition">intuitive</ref> and even if they don’t say, we sort of pick up on it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Certain vibes that you get from</p>
</text>
