<text id="autogum_interview_doc896" title="part2_Eurovision &amp;apos;04 winner Ruslana discusses her paths as singer, spokesmodel, stateswoman and source of inspiration" shortTile="parteurovision--winner" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-03-30" dateModified="2015-05-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eurovision_%2704_winner_Ruslana_discusses_her_paths_as_singer%2C_spokesmodel%2C_stateswoman_and_source_of_inspiration" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Ruslana</hi>: My father is from the West Ukrainian area [populated by] the Hutsuls, the dwellers of the Ukrainian Carpathian Mountains. So I was born in it. I saw it all in my childhood. Hutsuls have a unique culture with an ancient and rich history which inspired me to create my concept album <hi rend="italic">Wild Dances</hi>. It combines powerful and permeating ethnic drums, trumpet sounds of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/trembita">trembita</ref>, an ancient Hutsul music instrument, with modern dance beats.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You were chosen by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National%20Television%20Company%20of%20Ukraine">National Television Company of Ukraine</ref> to represent them at Eurovision in 2004. How were you approached by them? Was it a hard decision for you to decide whether or not to accept their offer? Obviously it was very successful for you, but before the fact, did you ever consider not performing?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ruslana</hi>: I can say that before I went to Eurovision there were a lot of talks – [people saying it's] good or bad. I just did not listen to anyone; [I] just trusted my instincts.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Your performance is one of the best-remembered in history. Did it ever tire you to hear yourself compared to "Xena" from the television show "Xena: Warrior Princess"? Are you okay with that being your primary aesthetic attribute to foreign audiences?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ruslana</hi>: For me [a] real Amazon is not [a] "Warrior Princess." It's [a] beautiful, smart, independent woman. She knows what she definitely wants and she gets it. Lana [<hi rend="italic">Editor's note: Ruslana's alter-ego, an "Amazon," in her album Wild Energy</hi>] dreams about love. Magic feelings that give us inspiration and wings.                         </p>
<p>The main idea of [the] <hi rend="italic">Wild Energy</hi> show is to show the character of [an] Amazon. She can be [a] girl [with] wind, girl [with] fire, girl [with] water, girl [with] rock. She's [a] girl [made of the] elements, but she fell in love and became vulnerable. She doesn't know what to do, how to live with those feelings.</p>
<figure><caption>Ruslana performing on Germany's national public TV channel <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Das%20Erste">Das Erste</ref>. German viewers voted her song "Wild Dances" the best song in Eurovision history.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> German public television held a contest a few years ago and the public voted "Wild Dances" the best Eurovision song in history, ahead of well-established standards like "Waterloo" and "Ein bißchen Frieden". Do you feel your song is the best in the history of the entire Contest? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ruslana</hi>: It was a great honor for me. I was so happy to hear it. [There were] a lot of beautiful talented singers and great songs [in all the] years [the competition has been in existence]. I like original songs with deep meaning and of course interesting shows.</p>
<head id="Wild_Energy"><hi rend="italic">Wild Energy</hi></head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> The <hi rend="italic">Wild Energy</hi> concept is tied to a science fiction novel. How did the idea come about that you would take the sentiment expressed in that novel and make music with it? How do you personally relate with the messages conveyed in the novel and in your music? What does "the energy for living" mean to you?</hi></p>
</text>
