<text id="autogum_interview_doc091" title="part18_Wikinews interviews Indiana State Senator Mike Delph" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-03-26" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Indiana_State_Senator_Mike_Delph" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>And I, you know, am concerned about that because I love my five daughters and I want them to grow up with opportunity. I want them to grow up in economic freedom and to be able to compete and do things and love and live and enjoy life and not have a country on the brink of collapse — of economic collapse. So I'm very outspoken on issues like that and on national security issues and also on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Supreme%20Court">Supreme Court</ref> nomination issues, and that sort of thing. And because of that, that's led to speculation.</p>
<p>When the speculation took place regarding Senator <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard%20Lugar">Lugar</ref> and also Congressman <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dan%20Burton">Burton</ref>, we did have brief discussions with my family, with my daughters, around our kitchen table. Some of my daughters have been character actors, or youth interpreters I should say, at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conner%20Prairie">Conner Prairie</ref>, a live museum here in central Indiana, others have served as members of the Indianapolis Children's Choir. They're all very involved in the home school community and their friends are here. So I told them that if I ran and got elected to federal office, they would either have to move out to Washington D.C., or they wouldn't get to see their dad three nights, at least three nights out of the week. And once I gave them that information, they were unanimous in their opposition to me running for Congress or the United States Senate. Until I get to a point where my family balance can be taken into consideration, I don't anticipate seeking higher office. But I'm always humble and grateful that people consider my record and my views worthy of consideration for such purpose.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Tew: Just briefly, senator. Your passage of the local government initiative that would allow governments to merge was very successful in your district, but not successful elsewhere around Indiana. What was it about your district that made it unique in that it decided to merge?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MD</hi>: Well the reform that came from House Bill 1362, which at the time was the most dramatic reform in Title 36, in probably 25 years or more. It allowed for the creation of a government of the people, by the people, for the people subject to the imagination. Whatever the mind could come up with, you could do up to the county boundary. And so in the case of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eagle%20Township,%20Boone%20County,%20Indiana">Eagle</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Union%20Township,%20Boone%20County,%20Indiana">Union Townships</ref> deciding to dissolve themselves and then enter into a pact with the town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zionsville,%20Indiana">Zionsville</ref> and create the new town of Zionsville, it took vision. It took selfless service because you had two township trustees that had to agree to dissolve their reason for being. Not many elected officials will do something like that. It was a very courageous move by the trustee of Eagle and the trustee of Union Townships to do that. I think part of the problem that we've had in other parts of the state, including <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Evansville,_Indiana">Evansville</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fort%20Wayne,%20Indiana">Fort Wayne</ref>, is that the process and the law has not been adequately marketed and explained to the public and to elected officials. But right now in Indiana Code, you could reform local government up to the county boundary in just about any way imaginable to the mind. The only thing that really is the constraint is the imagination.</p>
</text>
