<text id="autogum_bio_doc206" title="Kalema of Buganda" shortTile="kalema-buganda" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-01-28" dateModified="2017-08-23" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kalema_of_Buganda" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Kalema of Buganda</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Rashid Kalema Muguluma</hi> was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kabaka_of_Buganda">Kabaka</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buganda">Kingdom of Buganda</ref>, from 21 October 1888 until 5 October 1889. He was the 33rd Kabaka of Buganda.</p>
<head>Claim to the throne</head>
<p>Kalema Muguluma was the son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muteesa_I_of_Buganda">Kabaka Mukaabya Walugembe Muteesa I Kayiira</ref>, Kabaka of Buganda, who reigned between 1856 and 1884. His mother was Ndibuwakanyi, of the Mamba clan. He was declared Kabaka by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muslim">Muslim</ref> forces that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deposition_(politics)">deposed</ref> his elder brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kiweewa_of_Buganda">Kabaka Kiweewa Mutebi Nnyonyintono</ref> on 21 October 1888. He maintained his capital at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mengo,_Uganda">Mengo Hill</ref>.</p>
<head>Married life</head>
<p>He is recorded to have married the following wives:</p>
<list type="ordered"><item>Nabikukuzi, daughter of Jjumba, of the Nkima clan</item>
<item>Sofia Kabakalongoosa, daughter of Kinyolo, of the Nkima clan</item>
<item>Nakibuuka, daughter of Mugema, of the Nkima clan</item>
<item>Zefiria Nnampa Nakibuuka, daughter of Bakkabulindi of the Ngeye clan</item>
<item>Nabibooge, daughter of Kibaya, of the Nsenene clan</item>
<item>Veneneka Nabiwemba, daughter of Wakooli, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Musoga">Musoga</ref>, of the Ngabi clan</item>
<item>Njera Saabaddu, daughter of Gabunga, of the Mamba clan</item></list>
<head>Issue</head>
<p>His recorded children include:</p>
<list type="ordered"><item>Prince (Omulangira) Kiweewa Zzimbe, whose mother was Nabikukuzi</item>
<item>Prince (Omulangira) Edmond Alamanzaani Ndawula, whose mother was Zefiria Nnampa. He died on July 1, 1916</item>
<item>Prince (Omulangira) Yozefu Musanje Walugembe, MBE. He was born on 31 August 1889. His mother was Nabibooge. He was educated at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Namilyango_College">Namilyango College</ref>. In October 1914, he was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Commissioned_officer">commissioned</ref> as a 2nd Lieutenant in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/African_Native_Medical_Corps">African Native Medical Corps</ref>. In 1915, he was promoted to lieutenant. He served in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First_World_War">First World War</ref> from 1915 until 1919. He was decorated with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Member_of_the_Most_Excellent_Order_of_the_British_Empire">Member of the Order of the British Empire</ref> (MBE), the 1915 Star and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/British_War_and_Allied_Victory">British War and Allied Victory</ref> medals. On 18 November 1907, he married Sala Kiire, daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chevalier_Stanislas_Mugwaanya">Chevalier Stanislas Mugwaanya</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OBE">OBE</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GCSG">GCSG</ref>, at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White_Fathers">White Fathers</ref>' Mission, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nsambya">Nsambya</ref>. Prince Musanje fathered two sons and one daughter: (a) Prince (Omulangira) Joseph Mukaabya (b) Prince (Omulangira) Daudi Kimera and (c) Princess (Omumbejja) Tereza Namukaabya.</item>
<item>Princess (Omumbejja) Yuniya Maliamu Kamuwanda, whose mother was Veneneka Nabiwemba. Princess Kamuwanda was installed as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Naalinnya">Naalinnya</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daudi_Chwa_II_of_Buganda">Kabaka Daudi Chwa II</ref> on August 14, 1897. She received the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Silver_Jubilee">Silver Jubilee</ref> medal in 1935, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King_George_VI_Coronation_Medal">Coronation Medal</ref> in 1937 and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Papal">Papal</ref> medal "Pro Ecclesia et Pontifice" in 1951. She died on May 30, 1951.</item>
<item>Princess (Omumbejja) Besemerese Hana Dimbwe. She was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kampala">Kampala</ref> in 1887. Her mother was Sofia Kabak'alongoosa. In September 1905, she married, at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mbale">Mbale</ref>, as his third wife, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Semei_Lwakirenzi_Kakungulu">Semei Lwakirenzi Kakungulu</ref>, then Kabaka of Bukedi.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></item></list>
<head>His reign</head>
<p>The period from 1884 through 1897 witnessed tremendous strife in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buganda">Buganda</ref>. Sufficient <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baganda">Baganda</ref> had converted to one of the three major religions in the kingdom; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catholicism">Catholicism</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protestantism">Protestantism</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Islam">Islam</ref>. As the ruling class in the kingdom attempted to adjust to the loss of absolute authority over their subjects' lives to these new religions; the kingdom was thrown into turmoil, rebellion, counter-rebellion and religious persecution.</p>
<p>Within a period of thirteen years from 1884 until 1897, Buganda witnessed the change of leadership at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mengo,_Uganda">Mengo</ref>, six times, which was unprecedented in the kingdom. Various Kabaka's took sides with one religion or the other, only to be <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deposition_(politics)">deposed</ref> by the supporters of the religions they did not choose. And the cycle repeated itself.</p>
<p>In October 1888, the Muslim faction was dominant in Buganda. All Christian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Missionaries">missionaries</ref> were expelled, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kiweewa_of_Buganda">Kabaka Kiweewa Mutebi Nnyonyintono</ref> was deposed. Kabaka Kalema Muguluma, who had converted to Islam and taken on the name Rashid, was installed on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Throne">throne</ref>. However, only one year later, he was forced to step down by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_Kingdom">British</ref> imperial forces. He was offered an ultimatum by the British: either convert to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christianity">Christianity</ref> and retain the throne, or remain <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muslim">Muslim</ref> and lose the throne. He evidently chose Islam and was deposed.</p>
<head>The final years</head>
<p>After his removal from the throne by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_Kingdom">British</ref>, Kabaka Kalema went into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exile">exile</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bunyoro">Bunyoro</ref>. He died in exile from complications of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smallpox">smallpox</ref> in January 1891. At the time of his death, his age is estimated to have been in the mid-twenties. His remains were repatriated and buried at Mmende in Busiro.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Succession table</head>
</text>
