<text id="autogum_whow_doc281" title="Cook Humba Pata" shortTile="cook-humba-pata" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-07-10" dateModified="2019-10-24" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Cook-Humba-Pata" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Cook Humba Pata</head><p>Humba pata is a classic Filipino stew. To make this comforting dish, boil ham hocks until they soften a little. Stir them into a pot with sautéed onions and garlic. Then add bay leaves, pepper, pineapple juice, and soy sauce. Simmer the mixture until the meat finishes cooking and the liquids become a flavorful sauce. Stir in a little brown sugar and vinegar before you serve the humba pata with rice.</p>
<head>Ingredients</head>
<list type="unordered"><item> of ham hocks (pata)</item>
<item>½ cup (about 50 g) of dried banana blossoms</item>
<item>1 pork bouillon cube</item>
<item>¼ cup (15 g) of fermented, salted black beans (tausi)</item>
<item>¼ cup (50 g) of dark brown sugar</item>
<item>1 yellow onion</item>
<item>4 cloves garlic, crushed</item>
<item>3 dried bay leaves</item>
<item>½ teaspoon (1 g) of crushed peppercorn</item>
<item> of pineapple juice</item>
<item> of soy sauce</item>
<item> of vinegar</item>
<item> of water</item>
<item> of cooking oil such as vegetable, coconut, or canola oil</item></list>
<p><hi rend="italic">Makes 4 servings</hi></p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Assembling the Humba Pata</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Bring water to a boil over high heat. Pour  of water into a large pot and turn the burner to high heat. The water should come to a vigorous boil. <figure rend="Cook Humba Pata Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Put a lid on the pot to make the water boil faster.</item></list></item>
<item>Boil  of ham hocks (pata) for 40 to 60 minutes. Once the water boils, lower the sliced ham hocks into the pot. Turn the burner down to medium heat and cover the pot. <figure rend="Cook Humba Pata Step 2.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If it looks like too much water is evaporating as the ham hocks boil, add more water to the pot.</item>
<item>The ham hocks should become slightly tender, but it will finish cooking when you fry it.</item></list></item>
<item>Transfer the ham hocks to a plate. Turn off the burner and use a large slotted spoon to scoop the boiled ham hocks out of the water. Set the ham hocks on a plate or bowl and set them aside. <figure rend="Cook Humba Pata Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can discard the water in the pot.</item></list></item>
<item>Sauté the onion and garlic over medium heat for 3 to 5 minutes. Pour  of cooking oil into another pot and turn the burner to medium heat. Once the oil shimmers, stir in 1 <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Chop_an_Onion">chopped onion</ref> and 4 cloves of <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Crush_Garlic">crushed garlic</ref>. <figure rend="Cook Humba Pata Step 4.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Stir the onion and garlic frequently to prevent them from sticking to the bottom of the pot.</item></list></item>
<item>Add the ham hocks and cook them for 1 minute. Put the boiled ham hocks into the pot with the onion and garlic. Stir and cook the ham hocks over medium heat for 1 minute. <figure rend="Cook Humba Pata Step 5.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The ham hocks should brown a little as they sauté.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Simmering and Finishing the Humba Pata</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Add the soy sauce, pineapple juice, and pork bouillon cube. Pour  of pineapple juice and  of soy sauce into the pot. Stir in 1 pork bouillon cube when the liquids begin to boil. <figure rend="Cook Humba Pata Step 6.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Keep stirring until the bouillon cube dissolves.</item></list></item>
<item>Stir in the bay, pepper, banana blossoms, and salted black beans. Add 3 dried bay leaves, ½ teaspoon (1 g) of crushed peppercorn, ½ cup (about 50 g) of dried banana blossoms, and ¼ cup (15 g) of fermented, salted black beans. <figure rend="Cook Humba Pata Step 7.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Stir to incorporate the seasonings into the liquid.</item></list></item>
<item>Cover and simmer it for 20 minutes or until until the pork is cooked through. Put the lid on the pot and reduce the burner to medium heat. Let the liquid bubble gently so it reduces by half. <figure rend="Cook Humba Pata Step 8.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The pork should reach  with a meat thermometer once it's finished cooking.</item></list></item>
<item>Stir in the vinegar and brown sugar and cook it for 5 minutes. Add ¼ cup (50 g) of dark brown sugar and  of vinegar to the pot. Stir until the sugar dissolves and let the humba pata simmer for 5 more minutes. <figure rend="Cook Humba Pata Step 9.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Simmering the humba pata will help the flavors develop.</item></list></item>
<item>Serve the humba pata immediately. Turn off the burner and scoop the humba pata into serving bowls. Serve it with steamed white rice or flatbread. <figure rend="Cook Humba Pata Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Refrigerate the leftover humba pata in an airtight container for up to 3 or 4 days.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Humba pata becomes more flavorful when it's made ahead and reheated.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Measuring cups and spoons</item>
<item>Large pot with lid</item>
<item>Slotted spoon</item>
<item>Knife and cutting board</item>
<item>Spoon</item>
<item>Serving bowl or plate</item>
<item>Meat thermometer</item></list>
</text>
