<text id="autogum_voyage_doc420" title="Ayubia National Park" shortTile="ayubia-national-park" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=140413" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ayubia National Park</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Ayubia National Park</hi> is a well-developed resort complex and a popular picnic spot in <ref target="Abbottabad">Abbottabad</ref> District, Khyber Pakhtunkhwa province.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>It is protected area of 3,312 hectares (8,184 acres). The area supports temperate coniferous forest and temperate broadleaf and mixed forest ecoregion habitats, with an average elevation of 8,000 feet (2,400 m) above the sea level.</p>

<p>Ayubia National Park is surrounded by seven major villages and three small towns: <ref target="Thandiani">Thandiani</ref>, <ref target="Nathiagali">Nathiagali</ref> and <ref target="Khanspur">Khanspur</ref>. </p>

<p>The park has been developed as a resort complex from a combination of four mini resorts of Khaira Gali, Changla Gali, Khanspur and Ghora Dhaka in Galyat. It is managed by the Wildlife and Parks Department of Government of Khyber Pakhtunkhwa.</p>

<head>History</head>

<p>It was declared a national park in 1984. Ayubia was named after Muhammad Ayub Khan (1958–1969), second President of Pakistan. </p>

<head>Flora and fauna</head>
<p>The park holds 104 species of plants. The main floral species are Cedrus deodara, blue pine, yew, silver fir, horse chestnut and oak. Around 21 plants belonging to 19 families are known for their medicinal properties. </p>

<p>The park harbors up to 203 species of birds. Many species of birds, including the golden eagle, the vulture, Eurasian sparrowhawk and the hill pigeon among others can be found here. It is also home to some of the rarer Himalayan pheasant species like the kalij and koklass pheasants. </p>

<p>Ayubia National Park supports 31 species of mammals. Animals such as the Asiatic leopard, hill fox and flying squirrel can be found here.</p>

<head>Climate</head>

<p>The park is cold in the summers, but harsh in the winters. While it remains only placidly hot in May and June, the cold sets in when the monsoons come to lash in late July and early August. In the winters cold increases in severity gradually until the west winds bring rains, which eventually turn into snow. The park remains snow-capped through the later part of winters.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Rainfall: 1,244 cm</item>
<item> Temperature: 3 °C - 11 °C</item>
</list>


<head>Get in</head>

<p>It is about 40 km from <ref target="Abbottabad">Abbottabad</ref> along Murree Road and Nathia Galia Road (about 1 hr 20 min).</p>

<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> riding trails</item>
<item> hiking places</item>
<item> picnic spots</item>
<item> a chairlift in the centre of Ayubia takes the tourists to a nearby summit for a view of the forested hills</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>
<p>At the chairlift, shops offer cultural shawls, caps and necklaces.</p>

<head>Eat</head>
<p>There are restaurants in the 7 villages and 4 major towns around the park.</p>

<head>Sleep</head>
<p>There are lodgings in the 7 villages and 4 major towns around the park.</p>

<p>There is a PTDC motel at the chairlift.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Retreat Hotel</hi>, Nathia Gali (off Nathia Gali Rd), ☏ +92 334-8111445 , ✉ info@retreathotels.pk .</item>
</list>
</text>
