<text id="autogum_whow_doc282" title="Cook Dinuguan" shortTile="cook-dinuguan" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-06-21" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Cook-Dinuguan" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Cook Dinuguan</head><p>If you'd like to replicate blood pork stew at home, make classic Filipino dinuguan. Keep in mind that you can use any combination of pork belly, shoulder, loin, or intestines. Just marinate strips of the pork in fish sauce and sauté them along with onion, garlic, and ginger. Stir pig's blood and vinegar into the mixture. Then let the pork stew simmer until it thickens and the meat becomes tender. Enjoy dinuguan with rice or steamed rice cakes.</p>
<head>Ingredients</head>
<list type="unordered"><item> pork belly</item>
<item> fish sauce</item>
<item>2 in (5 cm) piece of fresh ginger root</item>
<item> pig's blood</item>
<item> vinegar, divided</item>
<item> vegetable oil</item>
<item>1 onion, chopped</item>
<item>4 cloves garlic, minced</item>
<item> water</item>
<item>1 tablespoon (12.5 g) brown sugar</item>
<item>2 Anaheim peppers</item>
<item>Salt and pepper to taste</item>
<item> pork intestines, cleaned, optional</item></list>
<p><hi rend="italic">Makes 4 to 6 servings</hi></p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Marinating the Pork</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Cut the pork belly into strips. Take out  of pork belly and use a sharp knife to slice it into 1/2 in to 1 in (1.3 to 2.5 cm) strips. Place the pork into an airtight container. <figure rend="Cook Dinuguan Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you don't have pork belly, you can use pork loin or shoulder.</item></list></item>
<item>Pour fish sauce over the pork and chill it for 1 hour. Toss the pork with  of fish sauce in the airtight container. Then cover the container and put it in the refrigerator. Marinate the pork for 1 hour. <figure rend="Cook Dinuguan Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Marinating the pork will intensify the flavor of the dinuguan.</item></list></item>
<item>Clean and boil  of pork intestines (optional). Thoroughly rub and rinse the intestines under running water. Then place them in a large pot and pour enough water to cover the intestines. Bring the water to boil over high heat and add 1 1/2 in (3.8 cm) of the fresh ginger root. Boil the intestines for 45 minutes. <figure rend="Cook Dinuguan Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The intestines should become soft. Let them cool before you slice and add them to the dinuguan.</item>
<item>Ensure that you sanitize your work space after handling the intestines because they contain bacteria that can cause disease.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Cooking the Pork with Aromatics</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Combine the pig's blood and  of the vinegar. Pour  of pig's blood into a bowl and stir in  of the vinegar until it's incorporated. Set the blood mixture aside. <figure rend="Cook Dinuguan Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If the blood is coagulated, put it in the blender and pulse the blood until it liquefies.</item></list></item>
<item>Sauté the onion, garlic, and ginger for about 5 minutes. Heat  of vegetable oil in a large pot over medium heat. When the oil shimmers, stir in 1 <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Chop_an_Onion">chopped onion</ref>, 4 cloves of <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Mince_Garlic">minced garlic</ref>, and 1 teaspoon (2 g) of <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Grate_Ginger">grated fresh ginger</ref>. <figure rend="Cook Dinuguan Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Stir the aromatics occasionally until they soften and become fragrant.</item></list></item>
<item>Add the pork and cook it for 3 to 5 minutes. Keep the burner at medium heat and stir in the marinated pork strips. If you're using the intestines, you can also add them. Stir and cook the pork until it becomes light brown. <figure rend="Cook Dinuguan Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Stir in the vinegar and boil it for 5 minutes. Pour  of vinegar into the pot and turn the burner to medium-high. Bring the vinegar to a boil and then continue to boil the mixture with the lid off. Avoid stirring the dinuguan while it boils. <figure rend="Cook Dinuguan Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>About half of the vinegar should evaporate as it boils.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Simmering and Serving the Dinuguan</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Add the water and simmer the dinuguan for 15 to 20 minutes. Pour  of water into the pot and bring the mixture to a boil. Turn the burner down to medium or medium-low so it bubbles gently. Put the lid on the pot and simmer the dinuguan until the pork is tender enough to cut with a fork. <figure rend="Cook Dinuguan Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Stir in the pig's blood mixture and sugar. Add the reserved pig's blood and vinegar mixture along with 1 tablespoon (12.5 g) of brown sugar. Stir until the pig's blood and sugar have dissolved. <figure rend="Cook Dinuguan Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Keep stirring until you don't see lumps of blood or sugar.</item></list></item>
<item>Add 2 Anaheim peppers and season the dinuguan to taste. Stir in the whole peppers and taste the dinuguan. Add salt and pepper according to your taste. <figure rend="Cook Dinuguan Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Simmer the dinuguan for 10 minutes before serving. Let the dinuguan bubble gently over medium heat with the lid off. The sauce should thicken as it cooks. Then turn off the burner and serve the dinuguan with rice or <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_Puto_(Steamed_Rice_Cake)">puto</ref> (steamed rice cakes). <figure rend="Cook Dinuguan Step 11.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Store the leftover dinuguan in an airtight container in the refrigerator for up to 2 days.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Measuring cups and spoons</item>
<item>Knife and cutting board</item>
<item>Airtight container</item>
<item>Bowl</item>
<item>Spoon</item>
<item>Large pot with a lid</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
