<text id="autogum_whow_doc321" title="Eat Soup Politely" shortTile="eat-soup-politely" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2008-12-23" dateModified="2017-06-26" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Eat-Soup-Politely" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Eat Soup Politely</head><p>Eating soup politely is dependent on the company you keep to some extent but there are some key elements to make it a pleasant experience for both the soup consumer and those seated around. Slurping and spilling of soup are not pleasant to hear or see, so do your best to avoid these mistakes and you'll be practicing great dining etiquette.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be seated at the table. If you are eating soup on the couch or somewhere else, be sure to use a Stable Table™ or a tray, to prevent it from slopping around and making a mess, or from burning you. <figure rend="Eat Soup Politely Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Place your serviette or napkin on your lap in case you spill anything. <figure rend="Eat Soup Politely Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Break up any bread or bread roll on the side plate next to you and eat it intermittently with the soup. See "Tips" for what <hi rend="italic">not</hi> to do with bread and soup. <figure rend="Eat Soup Politely Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pull the dish close to you to make sure you don't spill the soup while eating. <figure rend="Eat Soup Politely Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have the correct spoon. A soup spoon is the best spoon to eat soup. Failing that, use a spoon larger than a teaspoon but smaller than a serving dish spoon. <figure rend="Eat Soup Politely Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Fill the spoon about three-quarter the way full. Do not overfill a soup spoon or it will spill as you lift it. Lift your spoon carefully and slowly from the bowl to your mouth. <figure rend="Eat Soup Politely Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Continue eating soup in this manner, methodically, slowly and with care. Always place the entire spoon into your mouth to prevent the need to slurp. Be careful not to clank it on your teeth. <figure rend="Eat Soup Politely Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>As you near the end of the soup, tilt the bowl <hi rend="italic">away</hi> from you and not towards you. This is considered the polite way to finish soup as there is much less risk of spilling the soup into your lap. <figure rend="Eat Soup Politely Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Rest the spoon in your bowl at the end and push the bowl away from you gently. <figure rend="Eat Soup Politely Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>The etiquette applies not to some countries. For example, traditional Japanese intend to have soup loudly to show their chef that the soup is delicious.</item>
<item>Avoid "feeding the ducks" in public. This is the habit of breaking up pieces of bread and dispersing this throughout your soup. Although tasty and a great way to mop up boiling hot soup, this really should only be a family ritual and should never be a part of dinner party or restaurant table meals.</item>
<item>Do not slurp soup; it sounds awful, and it is considered very bad manners. It will also make people think that you haven't taken any time to care about how you present yourselves to others at the dinner table.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If soup is hot, blow a little on it first. Do this carefully and discreetly.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Soup</item>
<item>Soup bowl</item>
<item>Soup spoon</item>
<item>Serviette/napkin</item></list>
</text>
