<text id="autogum_interview_doc475" title="part2_Interview with Ton Roosendaal about Elephants Dream and free content movies" shortTile="partinterview-ton" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-05-21" dateModified="2014-01-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Ton_Roosendaal_about_Elephants_Dream_and_free_content_movies" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>I'd like to wait a little while with defining what a next project would look like. Given the constraints of "organizing projects to improve  
open source development", we might have not much choice either. It would probably mean to work with a new team each time, so most likely  
be based on shorts only. On the other hand, there's also clear signals that this approach works well, and creates excitement and involvement of a lot of people, also from producers and sponsors. That might enable us to set up a next project based on larger targets. For a full-length feature film however, we should involve a sufficient amount of experienced film makers as well, and/or invite the first team to participate again. That would put a lot of pressure on the required  budget…. You can't do that based on a 1000 DVD pre-sale target. Would more be like 20,000 or so….:)</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How did the process of making the movie feed back into the development of Blender? Are there major technical changes that were  made only or primarily because of the film?</hi></p>
<p>Already during the pre-production phase the artists have defined the key targets for Blender development. This then was coordinated with the  
online development community too. I've done the most crucial (re-)development mostly myself, though. Especially on the character animation tools, on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/rendering%20pipeline">rendering pipeline</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/compositing">compositing</ref> tools.</p>
<p>It is especially the latter I'm most satisfied with. In 3D movie production the compositing stage creates a giant content bottleneck. By   transparently integrating this in our render-pipeline, a very efficient workflow has been achieved. And, not to forget, Blender now also offers the first production-level open source compositor on the market!</p>
<p>The current summary you can find in our <ref target="http://www.blender.org/cms/Changes_since_last_ver.727.0.html">work-in-progress release notes</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What are the key technical features in Blender you want to add or improve for future movie projects?</hi></p>
<p>Depends on what the movie is about! There's always hundreds of features you can work on. However, we'll have to work on that anyway, movie project or not. There's a lot of professionals using Blender <hi rend="italic">now</hi>, and they can't wait for the Blender Foundation to do movies! Look at this studio for example:
<ref target="http://www.plumiferos.com/">http://www.plumiferos.com/</ref></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">I read that at least one proprietary software package, Reaktor, was used for the sound effects. Is this because no equivalent free software solution exists yet? Will future projects have a "free software only" policy?</hi></p>
<p>We've limited the "Open Source tools" requirement to our own Studio Orange only. That was what we could keep in control at least, and I can tell you it was not always easy even...:)</p>
<p>For sound and music we've decided from the beginning to seek an external sponsor. We have chosen to work with the best quality studio and composer we could find, preferably using open source, but not as a prerequisite.</p>
</text>
