<text id="autogum_interview_doc625" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Mike Lebowitz, chairman of the U.S. Modern Whig Party" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-07-16" dateModified="2009-08-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Mike_Lebowitz%2C_chairman_of_the_U.S._Modern_Whig_Party" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Over the past few months, the Modern Whig Party has been steadily increasing in membership. Around this time last year, the MWP had under 5,000 members. Today, that number has grown to nearly 30,000. In your opinion, what is the reason for the MWP's sudden and rapid increase and popularity? Do you expect it to continue growing at this pace?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">CL</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> As the word continues to get out about our organization, we do expect the Modern Whig Party to maintain its steady growth. A number of print and broadcast media outlets have even gone so far as to proclaim that the Modern Whig Party is "potentially viable," and "makes sense." Another outlet stated that this organization is the "fastest growing political movement in the nation." Perhaps the main reason we continue to gain traction is that these media outlets are recognizing that the Modern Whig Party is attractive to moderate Democrats, independents and disenchanted Republicans. At the same time, we are building this organization realistically, methodically and gradually in an effort to get this right.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How exactly does the Modern Whig Party differ from America's two largest political parties; the Republican and Democratic?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">CL</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> One important difference between the Modern Whig Party and the other two parties is that we look beyond partisan rivalry and will absolutely support a candidate or elected official from a different party if that person subscribes to a doctrine of common sense and rational solutions rather than ideology. We realize that most people are not limited to one distinct ideology and instead pick and choose based on specific issues.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Is your party running any candidates for federal or statewide office in the 2010 midterm elections?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">CL</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Our strategy is to refrain from trotting out as many candidates as possible just to lose. Instead, we are diverting our resources and focus to a relatively small group of initial candidates who bring quality and viability to the table. We are continuing the vetting process for our potential candidates. So far, we have two announced candidates running for office. A well-qualified candidate named Gene Baldassari is running for the New Jersey State Assembly in the 14th District. That election is November 2009. In addition, Paul McKain is running for Congress in Florida's 2nd Congressional District. Paul McKain is a prominent entrepreneur, retired firefighter and recognized child-safety advocate who brings a wealth of down-to-earth experience and qualifications.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Currently, are there any elected officials in the United States that are members of the Modern Whig Party?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">CL</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> We have some prominent members who have signed onto this organization to include military generals, former GOP county/state officials and current/former elected officials on the local level. However, we do not have any elected officials on the Whig ticket as we still are a newly constituted political organization. In fact, many of our members remain on the GOP and Democratic rolls, which again, is something that we have no problems with as we continue to build.</p>
</text>
