<text id="autogum_interview_doc050" title="part2_Wikinews interviews three figures from Donald Trump&amp;apos;s political past" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-03-12" dateModified="2016-05-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_three_figures_from_Donald_Trump%27s_political_past" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">I've been writing an article on Wikipedia about Trump's 2000 presidential campaign. You were director of his presidential exploratory committee.  Do you recall when Trump first mentioned to you that he wanted to run?</hi></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Stone</hi>: I have wanted Donald to run since 1988 when I arranged for him to speak to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portsmouth,%20New%20Hampshire">Portsmouth</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_Hampshire">New Hampshire</ref> Chamber of Commerce. I wanted him to run in 2000 — probably more than he did. The leaders of the Reform Party begged him to run but the time was not right in his business. I wanted him to run in 2012 and told him <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mitt_Romney">Mitt Romney</ref> was a stone-cold loser. All those who said he would never run, like that turkey <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/McKay%20Coppins">McKay Coppins</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BuzzFeed">BuzzFeed</ref>, look like assholes now.</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why were you willing to join Trump's 2016 presidential campaign after he was quoted in 2008 by <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20New%20Yorker">The New Yorker</ref></hi> describing you as a "stone cold loser" who "always tries taking credit for things he never did"?</hi></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Stone</hi>: I probably said some awful things about him too. We had a brief falling out over my outspoken opposition to [former New York governor] <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eliot_Spitzer">Eliot Spitzer</ref> who was/is a criminal. Trump was friends with Spitzer's father from the New York real estate world. We were subsequently reconciled and remain friends.</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What are your thoughts on the 2016 presidential race thus far?  Can Trump pull off a victory?</hi></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Stone</hi>: I strongly support Donald Trump for President. I think only Trump has the financial independence to take on the special interests. Trump doesn't need the lobbyists or the special interest money with the strings attached. He is the only one who can fix a broken system. Trump's pro-growth tax reform plan will supercharge the economy. Trump can actually cut waste because he is not beholden to the special pleaders. Trump will get in Hillary's face and confront her with her lies. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jeb_Bush">Jeb [Bush]</ref> gave Hillary [Clinton] a medal. The Bush and Clinton families profiteer off public service together. Is it civility or shared criminality? Only Trump can make America great again! It will be #yuge!</item></list></p>
<p>Stone refused to answer additional questions on his recent activities including his potential run for the Libertarian Party's 2016 nomination for U.S. Senate in Florida and his October 2015 book <hi rend="italic">The Clintons' War on Women</hi>.  Stone also did not address the conspiracy theory espoused by 1996 Reform Party vice presidential nominee <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pat%20Choate">Pat Choate</ref> that Trump's 2000 presidential exploration was a "dirty trick" to sabotage the Pat Buchanan campaign and eliminate the Reform Party as an electoral threat to the Republican Party.  Russ Verney addresses the theory further below.</p>
<head id="Dave_Shiflett">Dave Shiflett</head>
<figure><caption>Cover of <hi rend="italic">The America We Deserve</hi> Image: Renaissance Books.</caption></figure>
<p>Last December, <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> reached out to writer Dave Shiflett to talk about his experience with Trump in co-writing <hi rend="italic">The America We Deserve</hi>.  According to Shiflett in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20American%20Spectator">The American Spectator</ref></hi>, Shiflett was approached by Roger Stone who was on assignment from Trump to find the "most eminent <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/hack%20writer">hack writer</ref> in America" to write a book about a potential presidential campaign. Shiflett met with Trump for the first time in Spring 1999 to work on the book.  It was released in January 2000, a month before Trump announced he would not run.  Though not as well known as Trump's first book <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Art%20of%20the%20Deal">The Art of the Deal</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic">The America We Deserve</hi> has had more relevance to his current run. In November, Trump pointed to the book to claim he recognized the threat of terrorism before the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/September_11_attacks">attacks of 9/11</ref>; the book does warn of attacks by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/suitcase%20nuclear%20device">suitcase nuclear device</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/anthrax">anthrax</ref>. Some of Trump's political positions and policy proposals outlined in the book have led to attacks from his Republican primary opponents as being at odds with his 2016 platform including a pro-choice position on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Abortion">abortion</ref> (while noting his opposition to partial birth abortion), a ban on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gun_politics">assault weapon ownership</ref> (as was the law at the time under the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal%20Assault%20Weapons%20Ban">Federal Assault Weapons Ban</ref>), and the implementation of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/single-payer%20health%20care">single-payer health care</ref>.  Other positions in the book match his current platform including increased pressure on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China">China</ref>, fair trade, and border control.  Shiflett says he is not closely following Trump's 2016 campaign and no longer has any interest in politics.  Instead, he is focused on making music, which he posts on his website www.daveshiflett.com.  He discusses what he remembers about working with Trump.</p>
</text>
