<text id="autogum_interview_doc268" title="part1_US free speech lawyer Marc Randazza discusses Glenn Beck parody" shortTile="partus-free-speech" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-10-19" dateModified="2019-02-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_free_speech_lawyer_Marc_Randazza_discusses_Glenn_Beck_parody" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>"We are here because Mr. Beck wants [the] Respondent's [web site owner] website shut down. He wants it shut down because Respondent's website makes a poignant and accurate satirical critique of Mr. Beck by parodying Beck's very rhetorical style," Randazza states in the brief. Additional points in the brief comment on Beck's style of reporting, and highlight a controversial statement made by him when interviewing a Muslim US <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Congress">Congressman</ref>. Beck said to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20House%20of%20Representatives">Representative</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keith%20Ellison">Keith Ellison</ref>, "I like Muslims, I've been to mosques. ... And I have to tell you, I have been nervous about this interview because what I feel like saying is, sir, prove to me that you are not working with our enemies." According to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Citizen%20Media%20Law%20Project">Citizen Media Law Project</ref>, the website's joke premise takes advantage of "a perceived similarity between Beck's rhetorical style and the Gottfried routine".</p>
<p>Randazza argues in the response filed on behalf of Eiland-Hall that Beck is using the process of the WIPO court to infringe the free speech rights of his client; "Beck is attempting to use this transnational body to circumvent and subvert the Respondent's constitutional rights [to freedom of speech]," he wrote. Randazza cites the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Supreme%20Court%20of%20the%20United%20States">U.S. Supreme Court</ref> case, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hustler%20Magazine%20v.%20Falwell">Hustler Magazine v. Falwell</ref></hi>, in arguing that Beck's attorneys advised him against filing legal action in a U.S. court because the website would likely be seen as a form of parody and due to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First%20Amendment%20to%20the%20United%20States%20Constitution">First Amendment to the U.S. Constitution</ref>, such legal action would not be successful.</p>
<p>On September 29, Randazza sent a request to Beck's representatives, asking that their client agree to stipulate to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Constitution">United States Constitution</ref>, and especially to the First Amendment, during the case before the WIPO. In the request, Randazza quotes a statement from Beck himself about the usage of international law by United States citizens, Beck said, "[o]nce we sign our rights over to international law, the Constitution is officially dead." Randazza wrote in the request, "I am certain that neither party wishes to see First Amendment rights subordinated to international trademark principles, thus unwittingly proving Mr. Beck's point. Lest this case become an example of international law causing damage to the constitutional rights that both of our clients hold dear, I respectfully request that your client agree to stipulate to the application of American constitutional law to this case."</p>
<p>Commentators likened the legal conflict between Beck and the site to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Streisand%20effect">Streisand effect</ref>, a phenomenon where an individual's attempt to censor material on the Internet in turn proves to make the material itself more public. <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Techdirt">Techdirt</ref></hi> remarked Beck should have ignored the website, and instead his attempts to take it down served to legitimize it. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gawker.com">Gawker.com</ref> noted that media have written about the website because Beck attempted to shut it down, and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Politics%20Daily">Politics Daily</ref></hi> observed that Beck's legal action served to increase publicity for the site.</p>
</text>
