<text id="autogum_interview_doc115" title="part1_Wikinews interviews specialists on China, Iran, Russia support for al-Assad" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-09-15" dateModified="2015-10-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_specialists_on_China%2C_Iran%2C_Russia_support_for_al-Assad" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Do you think China is talking from experience when it says that foreign countries shouldn't get involved with Syria's internal affairs?</p><figure><caption>File photo of interviewee Sam Roggeveen. Image: Sam Roggeveen.</caption></figure>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Roggeveen</hi>: That stance reflects China’s history as a weak, developing country with a host of territorial disputes with its neighbours. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Beijing">Beijing</ref> does not want to set international precedents that will allow third parties to interfere with, for example, the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Taiwan">Taiwan</ref> issue, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tibet">Tibet</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/East%20China%20Sea">East China Sea</ref> or the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/South_China_Sea">South China Sea</ref>.</item></list>
<p>But increasingly, China’s stance will conflict with its growing strength and growing responsibilities on the world stage. China is already the world’s second biggest economy and a major strategic power in the Asia Pacific [<hi rend="italic">region</hi>]; and, it will increasingly be expected to take up responsibilities that come with such power. Also, as we saw in the case of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Libya">Libya</ref> — where China sent a fleet of ships and aircraft to evacuate its nationals — China has interests and citizens all over the world, both of which need to be protected.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Brown</hi>: It [<hi rend="italic">China</hi>] has always stood by non interference of other counties in the internal affairs of sovereign states; though, this position has changed over time since it was formulated on the back of China's experience of colonisation in the early part of the twentieth-century. Its main priority now is to not see the escalation of issues, as was seen in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iraq">Iraq</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Afghanistan">Afghanistan</ref>; where it runs the risk of being sucked into lengthy conflicts with no real gameplan, and no clear outcome that is relevant to it. It does not see the Syria[<hi rend="italic">n</hi>] conflict [<hi rend="italic">as</hi>] one where there is a an easy, viable, alternative option waiting to govern the country. And, it is very sceptical about US and others' claims that they can control this problem.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Farhi</hi>: Yes, rejection of interference in the internal affairs of other countries — particularly of a military kind — is a principled Chinese position in areas where China doesn't have an over-riding interest.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Mitter</hi>: China has been a hardline advocate of strong territorial sovereignty for decades.  This is, in part, a product of its own history of being invaded and occupied by other countries.</item></list></p>
<figure><caption>File photo of interviewee Rana Mitter. Image: Rana Mitter.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  China abstained from a UN Security Council resolution on Libya — do you think they are trying to reprise what happened in Libya in terms of regime change?</p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Roggeveen</hi>: China and Russia suspect the 'responsibility to protect' doctrine, which was used by Western powers to justify the Libya intervention, was a smokescreen for regime change. So, they are wary of seeing something similar happen in Syria. China also prefers not to be on its own in the Security Council; so, if the Russians come down against a Libya-like resolution, [<hi rend="italic">the</hi>] chances are that China will join them.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Brown</hi>: They felt there was clear mission-creep with Libya. What, however, has most emboldened them in opposing action in Syria is the position of Russia; which they have been able to stand behind. Diplomatically they dislike isolation, so this has proved the issue they have taken cover from.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Farhi</hi>: Libya has set a bad precedent for many countries who supported, or did not object to, NATO action. So, yes, the Libya example is a precedent; but, in any case, the Syrian dynamics are much more complex than Libya and both Russia and China — as well as Iran — genuinely  see the attempt to resolve the imbroglio in Syria through military means as truly dangerous. In other words, they see the conduct of Western powers in the past two years as spawning policies that are tactically geared to weaken the Assad regime without a clear sense or strategy regarding what the end game should be. Particularly since at least part of the opposition to Assad has also elicited support from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Islam">Islamic</ref> radicals.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Mitter</hi>: In general China is reluctant to take decisive action in international society, and [<hi rend="italic">at</hi>] the UN. It prefers its partners, such as Russia, to take on confrontational roles while it tries to remain more neutral and passive.</item></list></p>
</text>
