<text id="autogum_interview_doc033" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Paúl M. Velazco about new yellow-shouldered bat species" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-04-20" dateModified="2017-06-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Pa%C3%BAl_M._Velazco_about_new_yellow-shouldered_bat_species" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  The genus is called <hi rend="italic">Sturnira</hi> Gray in the paper. I've not seen extra adjectives in genus names, before. What is the context for such name?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PMV</hi>: Usually in papers that deal with taxonomy and nomenclature, the first time that a genus or species is mentioned in text is accompanied by the authority that describes that taxon. In the case of <hi rend="italic">Sturnira</hi>, it was Gray in 1842 that named the genus.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What caused your initial interest in the question in the genus? When did you become interested?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PMV</hi>: I have been studying bats for the past eighteen years and I am especially interested in the family Phyllostomidae that is endemic to the Neotropics. This family includes more than 160 species. It is the most diverse family of bats in the Neotropics, which together exhibits more variation in morphological features and feeding ecology than any other family-level group of mammals. Phyllostomid bats exploit an unusually diverse array of feeding habits including <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/sanguivorous">sanguivory</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/insectivorous">insectivory</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/carnivory">carnivory</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/omnivorous">omnivory</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/nectarivorous">nectarivory</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/pollenivorous">pollennivory</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/frugivorous">frugivory</ref>. Because of all mentioned before, phyllostomids are a really interesting group to work with. <hi rend="italic">Sturnira</hi> and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Platyrrhinus">Platyrrhinus</ref></hi> are members of this family.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  The paper mentions that the genus is now the most <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/speciose">speciose</ref> genus in the Neotropical family Phyllostomidae. What genus did it beat? How many species does it include?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PMV</hi>: The other genus with the most species in the family is <hi rend="italic">Platyrrhinus</hi>. Currently, it has 20 species, but soon it will increase to 21. Along with another colleague, Burton Lim, we have a paper in press describing a new species based on molecular and morphological data from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guianan%20Shield">Guianan Shield</ref>.</p>
<figure><caption>Dorsolateral views of the left mandibular toothrows in Sturnira bakeri (A, QCAZ 14635 ♀) and S. burtonlimi (B, ROM 104294 ♂), illustrating taxonomic differences in the shape of the metaconid and entoconid of m1 and m2. Image: Paúl M. Velazco.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What equipment did you use?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PMV</hi>: For the ZooKeys paper, we examined several specimens under the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/stereoscope">stereoscope</ref>. The molecular phylogeny gave us the separation between species, from there our job was to focus on finding morphological differences between these groups.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Did you conduct field study to identify the species' habits? If so, where and how did you do that?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PMV</hi>: I have done fieldwork in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Belize">Belize</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Peru">Peru</ref>, and my coauthor did field work in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brazil">Brazil</ref>, Ecuador, and Peru, where we collected several specimens of <hi rend="italic">Sturnira</hi> (including the third species that has not been described yet). But the two species that were described in the ZooKeys paper are based on specimens collected by our colleagues Dr. Robert Baker from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Texas%20Tech%20University">Texas Tech University</ref> and Dr. Burton Lim from the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Royal_Ontario_Museum">Royal Ontario Museum</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How do you isolate of the living area of the new species from the living area of the old species?</p>
</text>
