<text id="autogum_news_doc167" title="Time magazine names Ahmed Mohamed to &apos;Most Influential Teens of 2015&apos;" shortTile="time-magazine-names" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-10-28" dateModified="2019-08-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Time_magazine_names_Ahmed_Mohamed_to_%27Most_Influential_Teens_of_2015%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Time magazine names Ahmed Mohamed to 'Most Influential Teens of 2015'</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 28, 2015</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Time_(magazine)">Time</ref></hi> magazine named 14-year-old <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ahmed%20Mohamed%20clock%20incident">Ahmed Mohamed</ref> yesterday to its list of "30 Most Influential Teens of 2015". He was made famous after being taken into custody by police when a teacher thought a clock he brought to his <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Texas">Texas</ref> school looked like a bomb. Mohamed joins the ranks of influential teens including <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US">US</ref> President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref>'s daughter Malia Obama, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Nobel_Peace_Prize">Nobel Peace Prize</ref> winner <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Malala_Yousafzai">Malala Yousafzai</ref>.</p>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ahmed%20Mohamed%20clock%20incident">Ahmed Mohamed</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ames%20Research%20Center">Ames Research Center</ref> in 2015 Image: <ref target="http://honda.house.gov/">Courtesy of the Office of Congressman Mike Honda</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="italic">Time</hi> said of Mohamed in announcing the news: "Not many people make national news by bringing a homemade clock to school. But the ninth-grader's arrest, after teachers and authorities mistook said clock for a bomb, kicked off a national debate over racial profiling".</p>
<hi rend="bold">The ninth-grader's arrest [...] kicked off a national debate over racial profiling</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Time_(magazine)">Time</ref></hi> magazine</p>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ahmed%20Mohamed%20clock%20incident">Texas student Ahmed Mohamed</ref> and NASA Astronaut <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alvin%20Drew">Alvin Drew</ref> at the 2015 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White%20House%20Astronomy%20Night">White House Astronomy Night</ref>.Image: <ref target="https://www.flickr.com/photos/132868538@N03/">Harrison Jones, hjonesphotography</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>Mohamed traveled to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/White_House">White House</ref> last week where he met with US President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref>. His family said last week that they would move from Texas to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Qatar">Qatar</ref>, where Mohamed was offered a full-scholarship to a well-respected school in the country.</p>
<p>The September 14 incident in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irving,%20Texas">Irving</ref>, Texas triggered a wider discussion about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Islamophobia">Islamophobia</ref> within the community. The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Twitter">Twitter</ref> hashtag #IStandWithAhmed became part of a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/social%20movement">social movement</ref> in support of the youth. After news of the police response was reported, Mohamed received support online ranging from US President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Facebook">Facebook</ref> creator <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mark_Zuckerberg">Mark Zuckerberg</ref>.</p>
<p>Mohamed brought the digital clock he made to school on September 14, and a teacher mistakenly thought it resembled a bomb. Police arrested and questioned the student. Images of the boy wearing a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NASA">NASA</ref> T-shirt and handcuffed by the police were quickly posted and reposted online.</p>
<hi rend="bold">Cool clock, Ahmed. Want to bring it to the White House?</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—US President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref></p>
<p>The Twitter attention led to outreach from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Google">Google</ref> and Mohamed was invited to their Google Science Fair. Mohamed was a VIP guest at the Google Science Fair, and met finalists at the event held at Google's headquarters located in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mountain%20View,%20California">Mountain View</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/California">California</ref>. Co-founder of Google, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sergey%20Brin">Sergey Brin</ref>, personally met with Mohamed during his visit to Google.</p>
<p>US President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref> tweeted using his @POTUS account: "Cool clock, Ahmed. Want to bring it to the White House? We should inspire more kids like you to like science. It's what makes America great." <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Twitter">Twitter</ref> gave Mohamed the option to come to their company for an internship. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Facebook">Facebook</ref> co-founder <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mark_Zuckerberg">Mark Zuckerberg</ref> tweeted to Mohamed and said the boy was welcome to come and tour the company.</p>
<p>Both the Irving Independent School District and the Irving Police Department have asserted that the boy's religion and name were not a factor in the manner in which they approached the situation.</p>
</text>
