<text id="autogum_reddit_doc128" title="Alternative play styles, players who don't raid." shortTile="alternative-play" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-04-30" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8g2inf" speakerList="#Ayarane, #Kosmos992k" speakerCount="2">
<head>Alternative play styles, players who don't raid.</head>
<sp who="#Kosmos992k">
<p>Monday is a time for trying to escape work. At least escape in our head. So I was thinking about FFXIV and how people play it. One of the more dominant (and prominent) styles of play seems to be all about a very structured approach. Like having a list of things to do on the first and second days after a patch, or logging on after the reset to cap tomes and run the weekly raid. I've known many players with this style of play and sadly, some have burned out and left the game. On the flip side there are totally casual player who seem to have no aims or goals in the game, and just meander through the game driven only by that which is right in front of them at the moment. Unfortunately, these players also seem to suffer a kind of burn out, though it might more aptly called a flame-out since it's as if the flame of interest dies slowly before it really takes hold. I see lots of posts on forums about FFXIV talking about serving mid-core players, but I'm not entirely sure who these mid-core players are. How are they defined? Are they raiders who either don't have the time or are simply not skilled enough to beat the raids within the first month of a patch? And so people want more content that suits those with less structured schedules and/or less skill? But, what about others? FFXIV supports a lot of ways of playing. You can be an omni crafter, you can fish, mine and gather your heart out, you can spend your time playing the mini games, you can spend your time running and re-running the various dungeons, or running whatever FATE you come across, Glamour, Housing, PoTD/Treasure Maps/Eureka/things to come. You can set goals like breeding a race chocobo of your desired color with maxed out stats and highest pedigree, or craft every recipe in the game, or even just indulge in market speculation. Is the game rich enough to sustain players who don't raid outside of the 'normal' versions? Are you such a player? If so, why? I've played the game since the phase 3 ARR bet and been subscribed since ARR Early Access. I generally speaking do not raid. I've done end game content in this and other games and I've raided a bit in this game, but due to factors beyond my control, there are weeks, and sometimes months when my playing partner is not able to play, and so I wait for her, I don't even run the new content until she's able to play again. That's the why of me not raiding. Though I would also add that I don't like the very driven nature that seems to be an advantage when raiding. I play to relax, so I seek to avoid stress, which occurs in abundance in raid content. So, I do spend a lot of my time on other aspects of the game, and I find it quite a relaxing, enjoyable game with some multiplayer action running things with my friends and chatting while I do some of the less intense activities. Some might question whether this is really worth the price of the subscription. Given how much play time I happily give it, I'd say it was a bargain compared to most games I have purchased in the last 5 years. What is your approach to FFXIV, how do you play, and do you find you are feeling burnout, or are you just chilling and enjoying the world? </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#Ayarane">
<p>I probably COULD do Savage and such. It's just that I'm also a Heroic-level raider in WoW and I feel like I would wear myself doing both that and Savage. So I'm happy to just do my Expert roulettes and sometimes poke at an EX primal. </p>
<p>I also really don't want to have to fish around for a static. Doing the equivalent of cold-calling and auditioning for statics just jacks up my anxiety super-bad and gives me awful flashbacks of being bad at job-hunting in RL. In WoW my raid team is a group of friends that is open to nurturing new raiders, which was how I got started and I doubt finding something similar in XIV would be a Thing except maaaaaybe at the start of an expansion.</p>
</sp>
</text>
