<text id="autogum_whow_doc384" title="Make a Wrist Roller Out of PVC" shortTile="make-wrist-roller" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-06-20" dateModified="2018-07-11" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-a-Wrist-Roller-Out-of-PVC" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make a Wrist Roller Out of PVC</head><p>A wrist roller works well for exercise. You can use PVC to make one through a fairly intermediate, yet worthy process. It takes a lot of care and concentration and will be rewarding.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Cut the PVC pipe. Take the pipe and cut it to a desirable length with a hacksaw. This will be your bar and should be long enough to complete the exercise. <figure rend="IMG 3574.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Cut straight across, perpendicular to the pipe.  You can sand the ends if you'd like, but this is not necessary.</item>
<item>Don't panic if you don't have a hacksaw. PVC is a very soft material, so you could get away with many other options.</item></list></item>
<item>Drill the hole for the rope. Insert the drill bit into the drill slightly larger than the rope in order to thread the rope through. Drill the hole through one side of the PVC pipe only in the center of the pipe. <figure rend="IMG 3571.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Thread the rope through the hole. Push your rope through until it comes out one of the ends of the PVC. <figure rend="IMG 3575.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tie the knot once the end of the rope is out. Knot the rope to create a loop at the end and thread the end back through, then pull the rope tight.  Cut the excess rope off if you'd like. <figure rend="IMG 3577.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pull the knot back until it reaches the hole you drilled. The knot should be big enough that it does not come out this hole.</item>
<item>Attach weights. Take the other end of the rope and loop it through the hole in the center of the weights. Then tie a knot in order to hold the weights. A double knot will do fine; this is the same as the knot before but you'll have to go through the loop twice this time. <figure rend="IMG 3579.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Test your knots. Now that everything is together, lift your weights off the ground by lifting the bar up to see if the knots hold.
<list type="unordered"><item>If the rope snaps, you need a thicker rope.  If the knot slips, you have too much weight and you will need a different knot (doubling up knots will make them stronger)</item>
<item>It is unlikely that the PVC will bend, but you could use galvanized iron pipe if it does. It will just take more effort to drill and cut, but still doable with the same tools and method.</item>
<item>If everything holds, you've just made your very own wrist roller! Be proud and enjoy it.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You could substitute the weights with anything you want as long as you can tie it to the end of the rope.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Use caution working with drills and hacksaws.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>PVC pipe ( 1" diameter is a good size)</item>
<item>Rope (should be strong enough to support weights)</item>
<item>Free weights ( circular kind with hole in center)</item>
<item>Drill with drill bits</item>
<item>Hacksaw</item></list>
</text>
