<text id="autogum_academic_doc214" title="Temperature and Microstructure Evolution in Gas Tungsten Arc Welding Wire Feed Additive Manufacturing of Ti-6Al-4V" shortTile="temperature-microstructure" author="Corinne Charles Murgau, Andreas Lundbäck, Pia Åkerfeldt, Robert Pederson" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1944/12/21/3534/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The Gas Tungsten Arc Welding (GTAW) wire feed additive manufacturing (AM) process involves the deposition of metal material using a tungsten arc as an energy source. GTAW belongs to the group of Direct Energy Deposit (DED) methods in the family of AM processes. A solid metal wire is fed through a conventional wire feeder and deposited layer-by-layer onto a substrate. The energy source is electrical heating, which melts the metal wire as well as the base material. The addition of multiple layers produces a dense near-net-shape part. GTAW wire feed additive manufacturing has a high deposition rate. Flexibility and cost savings in manufacturing are important driving forces in the development of such techniques. </p>

<p>The titanium alloy, Ti-6Al-4V, is extensively used in aerospace applications because of its high strength to weight ratio. With an appropriate protective environment to minimize the oxygen content, this alloy shows good weldability and has also been shown to be suitable for additive manufacturing.  </p>

<p>In additive manufacturing, multiple layers are melted on top of each other in a layer-by-layer manner, inducing a number of heating-up/cooling-down cycles in the manufactured material. Since Ti-6Al-4V is a two-phase alloy consisting of 90–95% of hcp-α phase and 5–10% bcc-β phase at room temperature, the final microstructure of the material after being additive manufactured can exhibit a variety of microstructures, depending on the conditions of the thermal cycles. For the industry to fully adopt additive manufacturing, and to be able to qualify titanium parts for aerospace applications, a complete understanding of the mechanical behavior and control of the resulting properties are prerequisites. </p>

<p>Process simulations provide information on how to manufacture components in order to achieve the required properties and support the development and understanding of the manufacturing process itself. Finite Element (FE) simulations, a conventional method used in the modeling of welding processes, particularly for larger components, are applied on the macro scale. In the present work, a validated FE model presented by Lundbäck and Lindgren is used to predict the thermal field that, in turn, determines the microstructural evolution. A number of different strategies exist regarding how to include detailed and explicit modeling on a microscopic scale in a macroscopic simulation. One such strategy is to use submeshes located at the nodes of the FE model, while another is to use dual-mesh methods that place microstructural domains at the nodes of a macroscopic FE calculation. However, with these strategies, the calculations become very cumbersome if a large component is to be simulated. Therefore, for industrial needs, it is more pragmatic to use a density type of model, also called the internal state variable approach by Grong and Shercliff. In this work, a density-type approach is used in order to model the microstructure on a larger scale. Moreover, it facilitates the future combination of the microstructural model with a mechanical model to compute material properties. </p>

<p>The aim of the present study has been to, for the first time, couple the process simulation model, developed by the authors, with a microstructural model, which has also been developed by the authors, to predict the alpha lath size in the GTAW wire feed AM process. The results were validated by building a well-defined, 10-layer-high weld sequence, in which, at specific positions, its microstructural features have been characterized and compared to the predicted results. </p>
</text>
