<text id="autogum_news_doc209" title="UN report says 80 per cent of world&apos;s refugees live in poor countries" shortTile="un-report--per-cent" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-06-20" dateModified="2018-05-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UN_report_says_80_per_cent_of_world%27s_refugees_live_in_poor_countries" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>UN report says 80 per cent of world's refugees live in poor countries</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 22, 2011</hi></p>
<figure><caption>UNHCR aid delivered to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kenya">Kenya</ref>. Image: DoD photo by: TSgt Steve Staedler.</caption></figure>
<p>Reflecting an  "overwhelming imbalance", the  majority  of the  world's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Displaced%20person">forcibly displaced refugees</ref> have been taken in by poor, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/developing%20countries">developing countries</ref>, not  industrialized countries, according to the  2010 Global Trends report by the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Nations">United Nations</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20Nations%20High%20Commissioner%20for%20Refugees">High Commissioner for Refugees</ref> (UNHCR) released on Monday. The report states that many of the poorest countries in the world have accommodated the largest numbers of refugees in absolute terms and also in proportion to their economies.</p>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nyanzale">Nyanzale</ref>, in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Masisi">Masisi</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Congo">Congo</ref> refugee camp. Image: Julien Harneis.</caption></figure>
<p>There were 43.7 million people  displaced worldwide at the end of 2010, according to the report, more than half children.  UNHCR works in over 120 countries and includes both refugees forced to flee a country  as well as those forced out of areas in their own country. The global total is broken down into the following categories: 15.4 million <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Refugee">refugees</ref>, 27.5 million internally displaced people, and another 840,000 people awaiting to be assigned to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Convention%20Relating%20to%20the%20Status%20of%20Refugees">refugee status</ref>. </p>
<p>In addition, there are an  estimated 12 million <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Statelessness">stateless people</ref> around the world; people who lack even the basic identity  of a nationality. Since 2004, the  reported numbers of  stateless populations has steadily increased.</p>
<p>According to the report, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Pakistan">Pakistan</ref>'s 1.9 million refugee population is the largest, followed by  <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iran">Iran</ref> with 1.1 million and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Syria">Syria</ref> with 1 million. The neighboring nations of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Afghanistan">Afghanistan</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iraq">Iraq</ref> accounted for the largest number of people fleeing.</p>
<p>The report states: "Pakistan also has the biggest economic impact with 710 refugees for each US dollar of its per capita <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gross%20Domestic%20Product">Gross Domestic Product</ref> (GDP), followed by <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Democratic_Republic_of_the_Congo">Democratic Republic of the Congo</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kenya">Kenya</ref> with 475 and 247 refugees respectively. By comparison, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">Germany</ref>, the industrialized country with the largest refugee population (594,000 people), has 17 refugees for each dollar of per capita GDP."</p>
<figure><caption>Refugees arriving at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Travnik">Travnik</ref>, central <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bosnia">Bosnia</ref>, during the war in 1993. Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Evstafiev">Evstafiev</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>The new report depicts a very different situation than  when the UN refugee agency was founded in 1950 to deal with the  2.1 million Europeans displaced by <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/World_War_Two">World War Two</ref>. And it comes at a time when anti-refugee feelings are increasing in many industrialized countries.</p>
<hi rend="bold">Fears about supposed floods of refugees in industrialized countries are being vastly overblown or mistakenly conflated with issues of migration. Meanwhile, it's poorer countries that are left having to pick up the burden.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—António Guterres, UN High Commissioner for Refugees</p>
<p>"Fears about supposed floods of refugees in industrialized countries are being vastly overblown or mistakenly conflated with issues of migration. Meanwhile, it's poorer countries that are left having to pick up the burden", said <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/António_Guterres">António Guterres</ref>, UN High Commissioner for Refugees.</p>
<p>UNHCR UK spokesman Mans Nyberg called for greater urgency in conflict resolution: "We are also concerned with the 7m people in protracted situations who are living in camps for more than 10 years, sometimes even 30 years. We are really appealing to the international community to put more efforts into conflict resolution so that these situations can be resolved."</p>
<p>The report notes that in  2010 <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Japan">Japan</ref> resettled 18 families from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Myanmar">Myanmar</ref>, becoming the first <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Asia">Asian</ref> country to accept refugees.</p>
<p>The large number of people that fled <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Libya">Libya</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Côte_d'Ivoire">Côte d'Ivoire</ref> and Syria in 2011, were not tallied in the report.</p>
</text>
