<text id="autogum_interview_doc007" title="part1_Male Magellanic penguins pine for pairings: Wikinews interviews biologist Natasha Gownaris" shortTile="partmale-magellanic" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2019-01-03" dateModified="2019-07-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Male_Magellanic_penguins_pine_for_pairings%3A_Wikinews_interviews_biologist_Natasha_Gownaris" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How did you approach putting together such a large-scale study?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NG</hi>: This study started in 1982, long before my joining the lab in March of 2016. Dr. Dee Boersma began this study as a response to a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Japan">Japanese</ref> company's interest in harvesting penguins for their skin, meat, and oil. Although the project has evolved over time, Dr. Boersma had the foresight to start banding chicks in 1983 and to set up a standard protocol that we follow each year. Since then, over 44,000 chicks have been banded at Punta Tombo. We’ve been able to follow some individuals for 30+ years, collecting detailed information on things like how often they breed and how many mates they've had. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How much time did you end up spending in Argentina? What was it like at the breeding site?</p>
<figure><caption>The two males continue their battle over the female.Image: Natasha Gownaris.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">NG</hi>: Members of the Boersma lab and volunteers spend approximately six months each year at Punta Tombo. I was fortunate enough to spend nearly four months at the colony between 2015 and 2017. It's an incredible, otherworldly place. Magellanic penguins nest in burrows or bushes, and some areas of the colony are so dense with burrows that you feel like you're on a different planet. The colony has declined by over 40% since the study started...so I can't even imagine what it was like in the 1980s. My favorite time of the day is around 8PM, when (hopefully fat) penguins are returning to the colony <hi rend="italic">en masse</hi> after a foraging trip. They are also most vocal in the morning and evening, making their characteristic braying sound— the related African penguin earned the name "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/jackass%20penguin">jackass penguin</ref>" because they sound a bit like donkeys. The colony is also full of other beautiful and interesting creatures, including a llama-like species called the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/guanaco">guanaco</ref> and an <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ostrich">ostrich</ref>-like species called the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/rhea">rhea</ref>.</p>
<hi rend="bold">I was fortunate enough to spend nearly four months at the colony between 2015 and 2017. It's an incredible, otherworldly place.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—Natasha Gownaris</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Do you have any theories on why more female juveniles die at sea? You mention starvation; what might be the causes of that, and are there other possible explanations you can think of?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NG</hi>: We are not yet certain why females are more likely to die, but we think it must be related to their smaller body size. Because the mortality is most uneven in juveniles, higher mortality doesn’t seem to be related to greater costs of breeding for females than for males. Female Magellanic penguins are about 17% lighter than males and have smaller bills. We think that, because of this size difference, females have a lower storage capacity, can't dive as deep, and can't take as wide a range of prey as males — all disadvantages when faced with limited and unpredictable food resources. These disadvantages hit juvenile females even harder, as juveniles are still learning how to forage and often travel further than adults do in the non-breeding season. Counts of carcasses in the species' migration range support starvation as the main cause of female-biased mortality; while oiled carcasses have a sex ratio of 1:1, females outnumber males in carcasses of starved birds. The only other possibility is that females are moving to other colonies at higher rates than are males, but this species is known to almost always return to its natal colony to breed.</p>
</text>
