<text id="autogum_whow_doc347" title="Choose a Hospital for Surgery" shortTile="choose-hospital-surgery" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2017-02-02" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Choose-a-Hospital-for-Surgery" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Choose a Hospital for Surgery</head><p>Finding the right hospital for surgery can be a complicated task. You should first consult with your primary care doctor and your insurance provider to determine which surgeons and facilities will meet your needs. Then you should review the different hospitals, looking at patient reviews and examining data on things like success and complication rates. Finally, you should consult with different surgeons and talk with them about the procedure and if there are any alternative treatments. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Getting the Basics</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Talk with your doctor. The first step in finding a surgeon and location for your operation is talking with your primary care provider. You may need your primary care doctor to write you a referral to a surgeon. They will likely recommend surgeons and hospitals that they have worked with in the past. Often, your choice of surgeon will determine your choice of hospital. <figure rend="Get-a-Clean,-Acne-Free-Face-Step-26.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>When you are talking to your doctor, ask things like “Who would you recommend as a surgeon?” and “What hospital do you recommend?”</item></list></item>
<item>Check with your insurer. After you consult your doctor, you should contact your insurer. Unless you are willing to pay out-of-pocket for the surgery, you will need to make sure that any surgeon and you go to is in-network. Depending on the surgery, an out-of-network operation may end up costing you thousands of dollars. <figure rend="Have a Good Job Interview Step 9 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>When you talk to your insurer, ask questions like “What specialists are covered by my insurance?” and “Is this surgeon in-network?”</item></list></item>
<item>Look for hospitals that have expertise in treating your condition. To get the best care, you will want to go to a hospital that has a reputation for treating your condition. General hospitals are great for routine operations like hernias or gallbladder surgery. However, you may need a specialty hospital if you need something like heart bypass or reconstructive surgery. Talk with your primary care provider and your insurer to find the facility that meets your needs and is affordable. <figure rend="Cure Nausea Step 10 Version 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure that your surgeon has the ability to admit patients at the hospital you are considering.</item>
<item>Hospitals that perform many of the same types of procedures tend to have higher success rates.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Finding the Right Hospital</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Review hospital ratings. There are a number of nonprofit and government organizations that collect and publish hospital reviews and ratings. You can look up reviews of specific hospitals through groups like Consumer Reports and Hospital Compare. Try to find facilities that received good reviews and have a high success rate for the procedure you need. <figure rend="Write a Blog Post Step 17.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Many states and consumer groups give health care facilities report cards that highlight their strengths and weaknesses.</item>
<item>Try checking out <ref target="http://www.leapfroggroup.org/">http://www.leapfroggroup.org/</ref> for data on quality and safety of procedures in hospitals throughout the U.S.</item></list></item>
<item>Examine the data. When you are reviewing hospital information, be sure to look at data about infection rates, readmission, and death. Avoid hospitals where there are high rates of infection or where patients are readmitted soon after the are discharged. In addition, you should check the mortality rate of each hospital. These numbers are good indicators of the quality of care that you might expect in that facility. <figure rend="Apply-for-an-Entrepreneurial-Grant-Step-2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Look for the “outcome studies” published by the different facilities. These studies will let you know how well patients do after having certain types of procedures. You can often find these published by nonprofit or government groups.</item></list></item>
<item>Visit the hospitals. Take some time to visit each facility that you are considering. Check out the hospital and make sure that it looks and smells clean. If a hospital seems run down, you might want to look into other facilities. <figure rend="Become-a-Physician-Assistant-Step-8-Version-3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>It’s also important for the staff to be friendly and approachable. Pay attention to how hospital employees respond to you when you visit.</item>
<item>Many facilities allow you to schedule a tour. To save some time, you should schedule a tour after your surgical consults.</item></list></item>
<item>Think about location. Depending on where you live, you might need to travel for your surgery. This could be because where you live does not have the facilities or the staff to perform your procedure. You might also travel in order to have your surgery done by a renowned surgeon at a particular facility. However, you might also choose to stay local in order to have your family and friends near. Think about what your expectations are for the surgery and whether or not you are willing to travel for it. <figure rend="Get-a-Job-in-Another-State-Step-2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Choosing the Right Surgeon</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Review their credentials. Look for a surgeon that has the necessary training to perform the operation you need. You want a specialist certified by the American Board of Medical Specialties. This tells you that they received a degree from a qualified medical school, completed their residency, is licensed by a state medical board, and passed at least on ABMS exam. You can check the qualifications of your doctor by going to certificationmatters.org. <figure rend="Become-a-Petite-Model-Step-5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Look for red flags. Check with your state medical board to see if your surgeon has had any malpractice claims or disciplinary actions. Although most surgeons are sued once or twice, a specialist who has been sued multiple times may be problematic. In addition, multiple disciplinary actions may be an indication of substance abuse or a behavioral issue. <figure rend="Do-a-Criminal-Background-Check-Step-9-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Meet with the surgeon. Once you have narrowed down your options, you should schedule some consultations with various surgeons. Talk with them about their success and complication rates when performing your operation, and ask them how many of this type of procedure they have performed. You should also talk with them about their attitudes on an alternative to surgery. Finally, it is important to get a feel for whether you trust this person. Listen to your gut and determine if you are comfortable with this person potentially having your life in their hands. <figure rend="Get-a-Clean,-Acne-Free-Face-Step-25.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>A doctor who is confident in their ability and has a solid track record will be willing to discuss their success rate with you.</item>
<item>You should ask your surgeon things like “What is your success rate with this procedure?” and “Do you recommend any alternatives to surgery?”</item></list></item></list>
</text>
