<text id="autogum_academic_doc606" title="Effects of Periodic Fasting on Fatty Liver Index—A Prospective Observational Study" shortTile="effects-periodic" author="Stefan Drinda, Franziska Grundler, Thomas Neumann, Thomas Lehmann, Nico Steckhan, Andreas Michalsen, Francoise Wilhelmi de Toledo" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6643/11/11/2601/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
Diet interventions are well-established strategies to reduce body weight and improve glucose metabolism, however no evidence exists about the effects of periodic fasting on NAFLD. This study is the first to show the beneficial effects of periodic fasting on fatty liver. The results of our study supported the hypothesis that FLI, a surrogate parameter of fatty liver, significantly decreases in individuals with and without T2DM after a fasting intervention of at least 6 days. The prospective study design according to a standardized protocol with a well-established fasting technique and a close clinical monitoring was a strength of this study. </p>

<p>Weight reduction and improvement of fatty liver indicators are known to be interrelated. Our results indicate that even a modest reduction of BMI improved surrogate markers of fatty liver. Indeed, in nearly half of the subjects in the highest risk category (FLI &gt; 60), a BMI reduction of less than 5% was sufficient to induce a shift to a lower risk category. </p>

<p>In most patients, NAFLD is associated with features of metabolic syndrome, central obesity, elevated blood pressure, dyslipidemia, hyperglycemia, and insulin resistance. Although these pathologies can be addressed by lifestyle interventions, in daily life the adherence to the necessary lifestyle changes is poor, resulting in suboptimal outcomes. In contrast, in pragmatic programs there is a greater benefit in a more substantial weight loss, particularly at early stages of the intervention period. Hence, periodic fasting can significantly reduce weight, and this effect can be maintained over time.  </p>

<p>There are several concerns about the adverse effects of fasting. Several non-fatal (e.g., headache) and rarely fatal (e.g., ventricular arrhythmia) events have been reported. In contrast, no severe adverse events were found in a cohort of 1422 subjects treated with a periodic fasting lasting 4–21 days,. Michalsen et al. evaluated the acceptance, safety, effects on health-related outcomes, and lifestyle adherence of fasting therapy in different chronic internal diseases. They found no serious adverse events throughout their study. Our study supports the hypothesis that fasting therapy provided in a controlled clinical setting is a safe intervention. </p>

<p>There is a large body of evidence on the beneficial effects of carbohydrate restriction and hypocaloric diets on NAFLD. It has also been shown that-at equal levels of weight reduction-a carbohydrate-restricted diet leads to a significantly greater intrahepatic triglyceride reduction than low-calorie diet alone. The metabolic advantage of carbohydrate restriction appears to be related to a more pronounced lipid oxidation and enhanced ketogenesis. In recent years, intermittent and periodic fasting has gained popularity as an alternative to continuous caloric restriction. In addition to the weight loss effects, periodic fasting is associated with several metabolic benefits, including the improvement of lipid profiles. This has been also shown for intermittent fasting, e.g., Ramadan fasting. The key mechanism responsible for many of these beneficial effects is the metabolic switch from the utilization of glycogenolysis-derived glucose to fatty acids and fatty acid-derived ketones, i.e., a fundamental switch from lipid synthesis and fat storage to mobilization of fat in the form of free fatty acids and fatty acid-derived ketones. This occurs between 12 and 36 hours after cessation of food consumption. Hyperinsulinemia suppresses ketogenesis and therefore prolongs the time to switch in cases of obesity, insulin resistance, and T2DM. Although there is some evidence of impaired ketogenesis during the progression of liver disease to steatohepatitis, therapies that increase hepatic ketogenesis are expected nonetheless to ameliorate NAFLD.  </p>

<p>Our data provided first evidence that periodic fasting leads to a clearance of liver fat: fasting significantly reduced FLI and increased the proportion of patients without NAFLD (FLI &lt; 30 units; <figure>Figure 2</figure>). The effects of fasting therapy were stronger in males and in individuals with higher baseline FLI, higher GOT, and higher cholesterol levels. Each additional fasting day further decreased the FLI. The binary logistic regression showed that every day of fasting increase by 40% the chance to improve a manifest fatty liver (FLI &gt; 60) and switch to a lower category of risk. This implies that the duration of fasting must be sufficient to influence fatty liver positively. This should be taken into account when periodic fasting is considered as treatment for NAFLD. </p>

<p>As already mentioned, insulin resistance, T2DM, and the development of NAFLD are closely associated conditions. Taylor et al. have shown that remission of T2DM requires a decrease of liver fat. Patients with T2DM tend to have higher FLI scores, but in this study, we could demonstrate that the fasting intervention was equally effective in T2DM patients and in non-diabetic subjects in terms of FLI, although the improvement of other parameters (e.g., HDL, LDL, and AP) was not as complete. These results are in line with a previous study on periodic fasting in T2DM. </p>

<p>Liver enzymes, insulin resistance, and cholesterol levels are related in NAFLD. Our results supported a correlation between changes in FLI and changes in liver enzymes (GGT, and GOT) and lipid parameters (TG) after fasting intervention, although this was limited to subjects without T2DM. </p>
</text>
