<text id="autogum_interview_doc640" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Flame about special effects at New Zealand&amp;apos;s Rock2Wgtn festival" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-22" dateModified="2014-04-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Flame_about_special_effects_at_New_Zealand%27s_Rock2Wgtn_festival" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>In total Flame travelled 6 fire dancers, including Flames choreographer, producer and creative directors, along with 2 safety crew from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queenstown">Queenstown</ref>, where we are based, to Wellington.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews (Blood Red Sandman)</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">This was a very unique event. How did it differ from your previous experience?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Milly Bea:</hi> It was a great event to be involved in because the bands were such big names and legends, one way or another!!! And of course the thousands of people to perform to over 2 nights… to Rock music!!</p>
<p>In these ways it was a unique experience, definitely performing to original kiwi rock music…we often fire dance to the likes of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fat%20Boy%20Slim">Fat Boy Slim</ref> &amp; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/prodigy">prodigy</ref>…</p>
<p>We have performed throughout New Zealand with our biggest audience probably being the Qtn Winter Fest openings in 2005 &amp; 2006 but I think the Rock2Wgtn was bigger than that.... And it was different to feel part of a whole production, with the stunt guys and zombie girls and the NZ bands and the big time bands and the dragon!!?… Often we’ve been a stand alone performance so it felt good to have a role, alongside others, in  creating a rocking experience for the rock enthusiasts.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews (Blood Red Sandman)</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Was it hard to choreograph a show around the rock music that was on offer?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Milly Bea:</hi> Our fire dance performances are usually fully choreographed routines, from start to finish of one track, with an assortment of fire spinning devices… for this gig we requested the bands set list, in order of their play. We familiarised ourselves with their music and used combinations of toys that would work best with each song, according to rhythms, tempo and feel. For example, the up beat rock songs were great for the fire hula hoop or staff or poi, where as the more tragic rock ballads leaned towards a slow seductive fire whip. We skipped the songs that didn’t inspire us and went for it, having heaps of fun, with those songs that did.</p>
<p>The combining improvised fire dance with tight choreography on the chorus seemed to work best for us. It flowed naturally and looked effective in performance.  We discovered rock music, at times, had quite complex beats, making some songs harder to choreograph than others, in such instances we avoided choreography and let the improvised fire dance roll!! Our aim was to use toys that had the biggest fire for the hottest most blazing effect. We had well over a month of rehersing two nights a week, to get to know the songs, the choreography and practise improvised rock dance moves.</p>
<p>So while still being flexible for any last minute changes we were ready to rock with prepared toys, routines and dancers specifically for each song.</p>
</text>
