<text id="autogum_academic_doc173" title="Diagonally Implicit Block Backward Differentiation Formula with Optimal Stability Properties for Stiff Ordinary Differential Equations" shortTile="diagonally-implicit" author="Hazizah Mohd Ijam, Zarina  Bibi Ibrahim" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-8994/11/11/1342/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Numerical Results</head>
<p>In the interest of validating the numerical results of our method, the -DIBBDF algorithm was written in C programming language on the Microsoft Visual C++ platform to obtain the approximate values. BBDF in and DI2BBDF in are chosen as the methods of comparison because they are of the same order as our derived method. For our method, we choose  to compare with . Due to space limitation, only some  values will be examined. A detailed description of the selection of , was discussed in. For the four selected test problems, the numerical results of the maximum error and execution time are given in Table 3, Table 4, Table 5 and Table 6, with

where <hi rend="italic">T</hi> is the total number of steps, <hi rend="italic">N</hi> is the number of equations,  and  are the approximated and exact solutions, respectively. </p>

<p><b>Test Problem 1:</b></p>

<p>Exact solution:</p>

<p>Source: </p>

<p><b>Test Problem 2:</b></p>

<p>Exact solution:</p>

<p>Source: </p>

<p><b>Test Problem 3:</b></p>

<p>Exact solution:</p>

<p>Source: </p>

<p><b>Test Problem 4:</b></p>

<p>Exact solution:</p>

<p>Source: </p>

<p>The notations used in Table 3, Table 4, Table 5 and Table 6 are described as follows:<table class="html-array_table"><tbody><tr><td align="right" class="html-align-right" valign="middle">H :</td><td align="left" class="html-align-left" valign="middle">Step size</td></tr><tr><td align="right" class="html-align-right" valign="middle">MAXE :</td><td align="left" class="html-align-left" valign="middle">Maximum error</td></tr><tr><td align="right" class="html-align-right" valign="middle">TIME :</td><td align="left" class="html-align-left" valign="middle">Execution time (seconds)</td></tr><tr><td align="right" class="html-align-right" valign="middle"><hi rend="italic">ρ</hi>-DIBBDF(<hi rend="italic">ρi</hi>) :</td><td align="left" class="html-align-left" valign="middle"><hi rend="italic">ρ</hi>-Diagonally Implicit Block Backward Differentiation Formula (<hi rend="italic">ρ</hi> value)</td></tr><tr><td align="right" class="html-align-right" valign="middle">BBDF :</td><td align="left" class="html-align-left" valign="middle">Block Backward Differentiation Formula of order 3 in</td></tr><tr><td align="right" class="html-align-right" valign="middle">DI2BBDF :</td><td align="left" class="html-align-left" valign="middle">Diagonally Implicit 2-point BBDF of order 3 in</td></tr></tbody></table></p>

<p>Table 3, Table 4, Table 5 and Table 6 display the numerical results of -DIBBDF, BBDF and DI2BBDF using different step sizes of  and . Based on the results, we observe that our method with  obtains a smaller MAXE than  for all the test problems. This is due to the stability properties discussed in Section 3, whereby a good choice of the parameter , we can produce a method that has better accuracy. For MAXE, we observe that for all the  values, the -DIBBDF outperforms the BBDF method. This is due to the nature of the BBDF method, which has more interpolating points in the fully implicit form, thus increasing the cumulative errors during the computation process (refer to). Compared to DI2BBDF, our method obtains comparable accuracy for all the tested problems. For TIME, our method with  manages to solve the test problems in less execution time compared to BBDF and DI2BBDF. </p>

<p>To illustrate the performances of the suggested method and other compared methods, graphical presentations of the numerical results are shown in <figure>Figure 4</figure>, <figure>Figure 5</figure>, <figure>Figure 6</figure> and <figure>Figure 7</figure>. For a particular abscissa, the lowest value of the coordinate is considered to be more efficient at the abscissa considered. It follows that the graphs of  against  demonstrate the advantage of the -DIBBDF(−0.75) method over the other , BBDF and DI2BBDF methods in terms of efficiency. Overall, we observe that the -DIBBDF(−0.75) method performs better than the other , BBDF and DI2BBDF methods. </p>
</text>
