<text id="autogum_interview_doc549" title="part1_Ingrid Newkirk, co-founder of PETA, on animal rights and the film about her life" shortTile="partingrid-newkirk" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-20" dateModified="2018-02-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ingrid_Newkirk%2C_co-founder_of_PETA%2C_on_animal_rights_and_the_film_about_her_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>The group's tactics have been criticized. Co-founder Pacheco, who is no longer with PETA, called them "stupid human tricks."  Some feminists criticize their campaigns featuring the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lettuce%20ladies">Lettuce Ladies</ref> and "I'd Rather Go Naked Than Wear Fur" ads as objectifying women.  Of their Holocaust on a Plate campaign, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anti-Defamation%20League">Anti-Defamation League</ref> Chairman <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abraham%20Foxman">Abraham Foxman</ref> said "The effort by PETA to compare the deliberate systematic murder of millions of Jews to the issue of animal rights is abhorrent." (Newkirk later issued an apology for any hurt it caused).  Perhaps most controversial amongst politicians, the public and even other animal rights organizations is PETA's refusal to condemn the actions of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Animal%20Liberation%20Front">Animal Liberation Front</ref>, which in January 2005 was named as a terrorist threat by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Department%20of%20Homeland%20Security">United States Department of Homeland Security</ref>. </p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref> attended the pre-release screening of <hi rend="italic">I Am An Animal</hi> at HBO's offices in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20York%20City">New York City</ref> on November 12, and the following day he sat down with Ingrid Newkirk to discuss her perspectives on PETA, animal rights, her responses to criticism lodged against her and to discuss her on-going life's work to raise human awareness of animal suffering.  Below is her interview. </p>
<head id="The_HBO_film_about_her_life">The HBO film about her life</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">David Shankbone:  How did you feel about the film?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ingrid Newkirk:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>] Oh…um…I didn’t know what it was going to be.  I had expectations because I <hi rend="italic">did</hi> trust <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matthew%20Galkin">Matthew</ref>, but I realize there has to be a certain more interesting bent to it.  Like my hate mail and my will.  Getting naked for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Times%20Square">Times Square</ref>.  Trying to draw me out so that I will cry.  Those are the kinds of things I think HBO wants to have because those are the things that will hold an audience better than just the facts.  So much was left out, and I didn’t know what was going to be left out, so that was interesting.</p>
<figure><caption>Newkirk and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matthew%20Galkin">Matthew Galkin</ref>, who directed <hi rend="italic">I Am an Animal</hi>, the story of Newkirk's life.Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You are pretty media savvy; was that okay with you that they crafted the film the way they did?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  You have to make allowances, because you know you will not be directing and producing it yourself, so there is some give and take.  I hoped what would be shown is the good of the behind-the-scenes PETA, and the footage, and giving a glimpse to people of why we do what we do.  You have to take the bits that you wouldn’t necessarily put in your own film.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Many people when they hear about PETA think they are an organization that is more concerned with the well-being of chickens than they are with the well-being of humans.  How would you respond to that?</hi></p>
</text>
