<text id="autogum_voyage_doc218" title="Loch Ness" shortTile="loch-ness" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=19983" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Loch Ness</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.visitlochness.com/">Loch Ness</ref></hi> is a lake or <hi rend="italic">loch</hi> which runs for 23 miles (37 km) along the fault line of the Great Glen in the <ref target="Scottish%20Highlands">Scottish Highlands</ref>. It's about a mile wide, very deep (740 ft / 226 m), and dark with peat. It contains more fresh water than all the lakes, reservoirs and rivers of England and Wales combined, and is the supposed home of the <hi rend="bold">Loch Ness Monster</hi>.</p>

<p>The <hi rend="bold">Great Glen</hi> is the deep diagonal fault line that runs across Scotland from Fort William in the south-west to Inverness in the north-east. The fault continues out to sea on both sides, as far as Shetland to the north and Clew Bay in Ireland to the west. It formed some 430 million years ago as the Caledonian mountains were thrust up, and remains active to this day. The fault movement shattered the granite, so that glaciers in later ice ages carved out a deep valley, which filled with rivers and lakes when the ice melted. Loch Ness is the longest and deepest of these, with Loch Oich and Loch Lochy further south. At its north end, Loch Ness is pinched into a narrow channel then widens again: this last section is called Loch Dochfour but it's the same body of water. </p>

<p>The Glen has long been a transport route through the Highlands. The first paved road was built by General Wade in the 1720s as a military route to keep the rebellious Highlanders in check. Nowadays this is the B862 &amp; B852 running along the unpopulated east bank of Loch Ness. The modern main road is the A82, which runs along the west bank. The two roads combined make for a 70 mile (110 km) circuit of the loch.</p>

<p>The <hi rend="bold">Caledonian Canal</hi> is a coast-to-coast channel, built by Thomas Telford in the early 19th C, that makes use of the string of lochs and rivers along the glen. Commercially and strategically it was obsolete as soon as it was completed in 1822, as shipping had outgrown it, and round-the-coast navigation was much safer since the end of the Napoleonic wars. It fell into disrepair but was rehabilitated for pleasure craft. Loch Ness, its centrepiece, is the magnificent natural channel that doesn't need maintenance, but there are ladders of lock-gates at each end that very much do. At the south end the canal and River Oich feed in from Loch Oich, the highest part of the system; at the north end, canal and River Ness flow down from Dochgarroch Weir towards the sea at Inverness. </p>

<head>Cities, Towns and Villages</head>

<p>See the entries below for details of transport, accommodation, eating &amp; drinking, and sights &amp; activities. This page is just about the loch itself.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> is six miles north of the loch. It's by far the largest town in the region, with the most visitor amenities, so it's the obvious base for touring the loch and Great Glen. It's also close to other sights such as <ref target="Culloden">Culloden</ref>, the Black Isle, <ref target="Aviemore">Aviemore</ref>, Spey Valley and <ref target="Cairngorms%20National%20Park">Cairngorms National Park</ref>.</item>
<item> Along the east bank, via B852 &amp; B862 the old military road, <hi rend="bold">Dores</hi> is close enough to town to be commuterland, and has a couple of B&amp;Bs and a pub, described under <ref target="Inverness">Inverness</ref>. There's basically nothing but scenery along the rest of the route, south through Inverfarigaig, Foyers and Whitebridge.</item>
<item> is a small village on the A82 (west bank) but with hotels and facilities out of proportion to its size, thanks to "monster" tourism. The ruins of Urquhart Castle are two miles south at Strone point. The A831 branches west here into wild lonely hills towards Glen Affric and Cannich village, eventually looping north back towards Inverness.</item>
<item> is an even smaller west-bank village where the River Moriston flows out into Loch Ness over a series of rapids. There's a couple of B&amp;Bs and a camping &amp; caravan site just south, and Alltsigh youth hostel two miles north, described under Fort Augustus. The A887 branches west up scenic Glenmoriston, eventually joining A87 to Kyle of Lochalsh and <ref target="Skye">Skye</ref>.</item>
<item> is the village at the south end of the loch, where the canal begins its final climb up to Loch Oich. The fort, built in the 1730s, has variously been an abbey, a school, and a heritage centre, but is now an upmarket hotel.</item>
<item> is 20 miles south of the loch, where the Great Glen enters the sea. So it's not the standard base for visitors but it has good transport and amenities, and is close to Ben Nevis, Glencoe, and routes to the Hebrides. With a car you can easily day-trip around Loch Ness from here.</item>
</list>


<head>By plane</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://www.invernessairport.co.uk/">Inverness Airport</ref></hi> ( INV ) is 9 miles east of <ref target="Inverness">Inverness</ref>, off the A96 towards Nairn and Aberdeen. It has flights to Amsterdam, London (LHR, LGW and LTN), Bristol, Birmingham, Manchester, Kirkwall (Orkney), Sumburgh (Shetland), Benbecula (for N &amp; S Uist) and Stornoway (Lewis). </p>

<p>Glasgow GLA and Edinburgh EDI have a better choice of flights across Europe, then it's a 3-hour drive north to reach the loch.</p>

<head>By train</head>

<ref target="Inverness">Inverness</ref> has trains from Edinburgh, Glasgow, Perth, Aberdeen, London (Kings Cross daytime, Euston for the Caledonian Sleeper), Kyle of Lochalsh for Skye, Ullapool for Stornoway on Lewis, and Thurso for Orkney.

<ref target="Fort%20William">Fort William</ref> has trains from Glasgow, and another portion of the Caledonian Sleeper from London Euston. These trains also stop at Spean Bridge in the Great Glen, and various middle-of-nowhere places up the Spean valley and across desolate Rannoch Moor. (You half-expect to see a Victorian ghillie in horse &amp; trap awaiting, and the station for Brigadoon.) Fort William also has trains to Glenfinnan and Mallaig, for Skye and the Small Isles.

<p>There is no railway along Loch Ness.</p>

<head>By bus</head>

<p>Inverness has buses every hour or so from Edinburgh and Glasgow via Perth and Aviemore. The main operators are Citylink, Parks of Hamilton and Megabus. There's an occasional through-bus from London Victoria.</p>

<p>Fort William has buses from Glasgow, Oban and Skye, plus summer services from Edinburgh, Perth, Kingussie and Aviemore.</p>

<p>Fort William and Inverness are linked by Citylink / Stagecoach Bus 919, four times M-Sat and two on Sundays. This runs along A82 via Spean Bridge, Laggan, Fort Augustus, Invermoriston and Drumnadrochit. It's a shared service, but each company only lists its own services, and there's no combined ticketing. This is no barrier to corporate guff about community transport partnerships.</p>
</text>
