<text id="autogum_interview_doc794" title="part1_CanadaVOTES: Liberal Dr. Eric Hoskins running in Haldimand—Norfolk" shortTile="partcanadavotes-liberal" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-09-18" dateModified="2019-07-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CanadaVOTES%3A_Liberal_Dr._Eric_Hoskins_running_in_Haldimand%E2%80%94Norfolk" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>In Haldimand-Norfolk, the three hottest topics in this election are the impasse over land claims in Caledonia, the state of agriculture and food policy, and health care.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Land Claims</hi></p>
<p>I will make the impasse in Caledonia a cabinet priority. This dispute is a federal problem that requires a federal response. Negotiations must happen with frequency, and I will ensure that interim targets are established and met within a timeline. I will do more to ensure this dispute is resolved, and ensure that the Federal, Provincial and local governments work together with Police Services to resolve this impasse in a timely manner.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Agriculture and Food Policy</hi></p>
<p>We need a food policy that puts Canadian farmers first. I will fight for a national food strategy that prioritizes Canadian farming by promoting local agriculture, food safety and food security. Canadians should be encouraged to buy local food stuffs, however, we have to ensure they are protected from food-born illnesses. The government must do more to support farmers and to keep our food supply safe.</p>
<p>I believe in the wheat board and support supply management. Farm programs should be simplified and made transparent. The Conservative government has marginalized the farming communities it claims to represent. We need concrete support for our farmers and a real solution for tobacco producers, not more politics and posturing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Health Care</hi></p>
<p>Families in Haldimand-Norfolk deserve quality health care. As a medical doctor, I understand the challenges facing our communities, including a lack of physicians, long wait times and spiraling drug costs. The size of your bank account should not be the determinant of the quality of care you receive. We will continue to fight to ensure that the future of health care does not follow this course. Our health care system should remain publicly-funded and properly funded.</p>
<p>All patients have a fundamental right to receive access to timely care for necessary medical services. It is unacceptable that too many Canadians are without a family physician. Wait times in emergency rooms or for important diagnoses are too long because there aren't enough nurses or other medical professionals to keep up with the increasing needs. With an aging population we need a plan to ensure greater access to health care professionals. I will work hard to attract new doctors and bring better health services to our communities. I will support the Liberal Doctors and Nurses Fund, which will invest $420 million to ensure all Canadians have access to a medical professional. I will also work to ensure that the goals of the National Pharmaceuticals Strategy are achieved, namely catastrophic drug coverage.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Are there any misconceptions about you, your leader, or your party and platform?</hi></p>
<p>I think there are several misconceptions about Stéphane Dion. He is a strong, thoughtful leader who is genuine in his desire to serve the best interests of Canadians. Throughout the Liberal leadership campaign, his integrity was never questioned.</p>
</text>
