<text id="autogum_whow_doc041" title="How To Make Admirable Art" shortTile="make-admirable-art" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2016-05-15" dateModified="2017-12-05" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/How-To-Make-Admirable-Art" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>How To Make Admirable Art</head><p>Everyone has a talent, which is part of what makes everyone special. Maybe your talent is to be an artist who makes admirable art. Wether its to paint, draw, sculpt, or other things, this article would be great for you. Read on to find out how to make admirable art!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Buy art supplies. You can't make art without the art supplies you need! So you can go to any art store that you know and buy all the things that you need to make the art that you want! Or if you already have all the things you need at home, you don't have to worry about getting anything!</item>
<item>Think of what you want to make. It is best for you to plan ahead of time for what you want to make before you start or even buy anything.</item>
<item>Make what you see. True artists create artwork based on what they see, not what just everyone else sees, if you know what I mean. But if you want, you can always just make what you feel like making.</item>
<item>Frame it. If you would like, you could frame your artwork or just leave it how it is. But a frame is always a great compliment to artwork. And in my opinion, it make things look better, prettier, and would definitely make your art stand out.</item>
<item>Add your signature. You should always put your name on your artwork so other people know who made it. Artists usually write their signatures on the bottom right of their masterpieces, but you can write you're signature wherever you want.</item>
<item>Add the date. Writing the date is completely optional. I just like to put the date on all my artwork so I know when I made the it. If you are going to put the date on your's, I would suggest you put it on the back. But, if you must, you may put it on the front.</item>
<item>Practice. Did you ever hear the saying: "practice makes perfect"? Well its true. Well, practice makes things better, anyway. Especially with art. If you want to be a great artist, you should practice as much as you can. And I promise you, the more you practice, the better and better you'll become at art.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you don't want to or you just can't find an art store, but if you still want to make art, you can always go order art supplies online. You will just have to wait the amount of time that it take for it to get delivered.</item>
<item>If you want to get an inspiration of what you should make, you can look online or even go explore and see what you think you should make</item>
<item>I would strongly suggest, if you ever want to post your artwork on social media or on the internet or something, you should always put your signature on it. If not, someone can steal the picture of your artwork and claim it as their own.</item></list>
</text>
