<text id="autogum_interview_doc680" title="part3_Sam Brownback on running for President, gay rights, the Middle East and religion" shortTile="partsam-brownback" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-12" dateModified="2014-12-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sam_Brownback_on_running_for_President%2C_gay_rights%2C_the_Middle_East_and_religion" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="On_the_role_of_religion_in_the_Presidential_race">On the role of religion in the Presidential race</head>
<figure><caption>Brownback reading to children at the Via Christi Family Practice Clinic.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evangelical">Evangelical</ref> candidates haven't fared particularly well in this primary season.  What do you think is the reason for that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  I don't know.  I'm baffled by that myself.  We haven't been able to raise money.  But you would think we should be able to do that.  If you look at both <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mike_Huckabee">Mike Huckabee</ref> and myself in particular.  I've had some difficulty based on the immigration issue, because I've supported a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/guest%20worker%20program">guest worker program</ref>.  I think it's part of looking at every human as having dignity.  We should try to enforce the laws, and we should enforce the laws and build a fence on the border, but at the same time see every person as a beautiful person created in the image of God, and that's been a very tough topic on our side of the aisle.  Why we haven't gotten more traction, I don't know.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  The Democrats often have concerns about the electability of their candidates; <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hillary_Clinton">Hillary Clinton</ref>, for example. Do you think that it might scare some people that in this point in time that Evangelicals aren't particularly electable?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  Oh, I suppose it could be.  I suppose it actually applies in reverse more, in that the reason why <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Rudy_Giuliani">Rudy Giuliani</ref> is getting support is because of 9/11 and he is seen as the most likely person able to beat Hillary.  I think it probably applies to that setting more than not seeing an Evangelical as electable, because <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/George_W._Bush">George Bush</ref> I think would generally be seen in that category and was elected twice.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mitt_Romney">Mitt Romney</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mormon">Mormonism</ref> is an issue that people should take into consideration?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  I don’t.  There's no religious test for public office in this country.  There shouldn't be.  I think people should run on who they are and their record, and there I think he has a challenge, based on his record.  But his faith should not be an issue.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What if someone was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zoroastrian">Zoroastrian</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  Well, let's see what their policies are.  Uhh--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Or a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Satanism">Satanist</ref>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  Let's see what their policies are.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Really?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  There's not a religious test in this country, and let's see what their policies are.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Even though religious beliefs are so fundamental to a person?  It's more of a policy issue than it is a faith issue?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  I think you'll see a person by what they produce, in their fruit, if you'll let me use that religious phrase.  I think you'll know a person by their fruit.  And that's what I think you'll see more coming through in people, and that that's what you should look for, and that's, I think, an observable--about how they live their own life, about what policies they advocate, about what are their priorities.</p>
</text>
