<text id="autogum_voyage_doc510" title="County Donegal" shortTile="county-donegal" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=8396" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>County Donegal</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.donegaldirect.ie">County Donegal</ref></hi>, is in <ref target="Northwest%20Ireland%20and%20Lakelands">Northwest Ireland and Lakelands</ref> and is the northernmost county in Ireland, stretching further to the north than any part of <ref target="Northern%20Ireland">Northern Ireland</ref>.</p>

<head>Towns and villages</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> </item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Béal Atha Seanaidh</hi>) — is on the road into the county from <ref target="Enniskillen">Enniskillen</ref> in <ref target="Northern%20Ireland">Northern Ireland</ref> and from <ref target="Sligo">Sligo</ref></item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Bun Crana</hi>) — is the largest town in the <ref target="Inishowen%20Peninsula">Inishowen Peninsula</ref></item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Bun Dobhrain</hi>) — is the first major town you meet when travelling into County Donegal from Sligo</item>
<item> is an ancient fort site</item>
<item> </item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Dún na nGall</hi>) — is a major tourist center in the county and draws many visitors</item>
<item> - is a village offering coastal scenery, beaches and a golf course nearby</item>
<item> </item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">An Fhál Charrach</hi>) — is a market town in the parish of Cloughaneely on the N56 route, between Dunfanaghy and Gweedore</item>
<item> -  is a small town on the NW coast and has associations to St. Columba</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Na Gleanntaí</hi>) — is renowned as one of Ireland's tidiest towns</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Gort a'Choirce</hi>) — is a small village in the parish of Cloughaneely</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Leitir Ceanainn</hi>) — is the largest town in the county</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Leifir</hi>) — is the administrative capital of the county, uniquely linked to <ref target="Strabane">Strabane</ref>, <ref target="County%20Tyrone">County Tyrone</ref> in <ref target="Northern%20Ireland">Northern Ireland</ref> by a bridge</item>
<item> — is a village on the road between <ref target="Killybegs">Killybegs</ref> and <ref target="Donegal%20Town">Donegal Town</ref></item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> </item>
<item> — boasts a world-class beach at <ref target="Portsalon">Portsalon</ref>, which can be almost deserted at times, even in high season</item>
<item> Finn Valley — is the area around the River Finn and includes the towns of <ref target="Ballybofey">Ballybofey</ref> and <ref target="Stranorlar">Stranorlar</ref></item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Gaoth Dobhair</hi>) — is a heavily populated area in <ref target="The%20Rosses">The Rosses</ref>, with a fine beach and some hotels</item>
<item> — has <ref target="Buncrana">Buncrana</ref> as its main town, the Inishowen 100 is a day-long, one hundred kilometre trip around the coastline of the eponymous peninsula</item>
<item> — is the area around the River Laggan, lying east of <ref target="Letterkenny">Letterkenny</ref></item>
<item> Slieve League (<hi rend="italic">Sliabh Liath</hi>) — is a popular tourist destination in the county, with the second highest seacliffs in Europe</item>
<item> — is probably the best defined region, encompassing much of the Irish speaking areas of the county to the north west, including Gweedore, <ref target="Arranmore%20Island">Arranmore Island</ref> and <ref target="Cruit%20Island">Cruit Island</ref></item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Oileán Toraigh</hi>) — is an island off the northern coast</item>
</list>


<head>Understand</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Donegal</hi> is the English translation of "Dún na nGall", literally "Fort of the Foreigners", the county taking its official name from the town of Donegal, where this fort was located. It was also known as <hi rend="bold">Tír Conaill</hi>, which translates to "Land of Conal", a more ancient name, referring to its links with the Uí Neill and Ó Domhnaill clans who ruled the region. Irish language speakers tend to refer to the county by its older name of Tír Chonaill.</p>

<p>There are very deep connections between the people of <hi rend="bold">Donegal</hi> and <ref target="Scotland">Scotland</ref>, <ref target="Glasgow">Glasgow</ref> in particular, due to the economic need for emigration in the past and the strong ties forged over the generations as a result.</p>

<head>Geography</head>
<p>The Donegal mainland coastline is the longest in the country at 1,134km and constitutes over 17% of the total national coastline. The main inlet is <hi rend="bold">Lough Swilly</hi> which extends 30km inland from the north coast to <ref target="Letterkenny">Letterkenny</ref>.</p>

<p>The county consists chiefly of low mountains, with a deeply indented coastline forming natural loughs. The mountains (more famously known as the "Hills of Donegal") consist of two main ranges, the <hi rend="bold">Derryveagh Mountains</hi> in the north and the <hi rend="bold">Bluestack Mountains</hi> in the south. <hi rend="bold">Mount Errigal</hi>, at some 750 metres, is the highest peak. The <hi rend="bold">Slieve League</hi> cliffs are among the highest sea cliffs in Europe and <hi rend="bold">Malin Head</hi>, in the <ref target="Inishowen%20Peninsula">Inishowen Peninsula</ref>, is the most northernly point on the island of Ireland.</p>

<head>Climate</head>
<p>The climate is temperate and dominated by the Gulf Stream, with cool damp summers and mild wet winters. Average air temperatures are between 4°C and 6°C in winter and are between 14°C and 16°C in the summer. Temperatures in winter can be as low as minus 5°C and as high as 30 deg C in summer. The average annual rainfall in Donegal is between 1,000 and 2,000mm and rain is common even during the summer months.</p>

<head>Tourism</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Donegal</hi> natives often say that Donegal is the <hi rend="italic">forgotten county of Ireland</hi> as they feel that it is cut off from the rest of the Republic of Ireland, both economically and geographically. Its proximity to <ref target="Northern%20Ireland">Northern Ireland</ref> means that it suffered from a lack of tourist numbers during the recent troubles there and has been heavily influenced by that province's economic fortunes. Much of its border is shared with <ref target="Northern%20Ireland">Northern Ireland</ref>, with only about 20 km of land connecting it to the Republic, on the <ref target="Bundoran">Bundoran</ref> to <ref target="Sligo">Sligo</ref> road.</p>

<p>Thus, <hi rend="bold">Donegal</hi> is not as accessible as other tourist-oriented places in the Republic of Ireland, such as <ref target="County%20Galway">County Galway</ref> or <ref target="County%20Kerry">County Kerry</ref> and this means it is not as commercialised in the tourist sense. This can be a good thing or a bad thing, depending on your expectations. If you are looking to get away from over-commercialised tourism, Donegal can offer unspoilt scenery (apart from over-building of holiday homes and chalets in areas like <ref target="Dunfanaghy">Dunfanaghy</ref> and <ref target="Downings">Downings</ref>) and cheaper prices. To combat the overdevelopment of holiday homes, Donegal county council has adapted a plan whereas only one in five houses will be developed as holiday homes in the future.</p>

<p>The downside of not being as commercialised as other Irish counties is that facilities and amenities are not as readily available in Donegal and travelling out-of season will restrict your options. On the other hand, if you are into <hi rend="bold">fishing</hi>, <hi rend="bold">walking</hi>, <hi rend="bold">rock-climbing</hi>,<hi rend="bold">water sports</hi> or <hi rend="bold">golfing</hi>, and you are prepared to "rough it" at times in the less developed and populated areas of the county, then Donegal has a lot to offer the more adventurous visitor. Donegal's rugged landscape lends itself to active sports like climbing, hillwalking and surfing. Many people travel to Donegal for the superb golf courses - long sandy beaches and extensive dune systems are a feature of the county, and many links courses have been developed.</p>

<p>The pastime of rock climbing is of very high quality and still under-developed in the county. The complete Donegal climbing guidebook <ref target="http://www.uniqueascent.ie/undiscovered_donegal"></ref> is available at the Unique Ascent <ref target="http://www.uniqueascent.ie"></ref> website. There is a wealth of good quality climbing locations in the county from granite rocks in the south to the quartzite and dolerite-based landscape in the north. There is more climbable rock in Donegal than the rest of Ireland combined from the world class sea stacks, <ref target="http://www.uniqueascent.ie/sea_stack_guide">Free Donegal Sea Stack Guide</ref>to the off shore islands of Cruit <ref target="http://www.uniqueascent.ie/cruit_island_guide">Free Cruit Island Guide</ref> and Gola <ref target="http://www.uniqueascent.ie/gola_island_guide">Free Gola Island Guide</ref>.</p>

<p>Surfing on Donegal's Atlantic coast <ref target="http://www.beachwizard.com/beach.asp%3Fcountry%3DIreland%26amp%3Bbeachid%3D2090"></ref> is considered to be as good as any in Ireland. Donegal has hotel facilities as good as any other in Ireland in its major towns, as well as top class restaurants.</p>
</text>
