<text id="autogum_interview_doc396" title="part9_The Raveonettes on love, death, desire and war" shortTile="partthe-raveonettes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-16" dateModified="2010-12-23" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Raveonettes_on_love%2C_death%2C_desire_and_war" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are you late a lot?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Nods head</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  All the time.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do you most value in your friends?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  Don't say the obvious one!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  Humor!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  Oh, okay.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  What's the obvious one?  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loyalty">Loyalty</ref>?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  Yeah...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  Love, loyalty.  I like people who are driven, passionate, ambitious, but very witty and knowledgeable, but good people.  Good to the world and themselves.  Healthy.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you keep a large circle of friends or do you tend to keep it close?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  I would say close.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How many friends do you have that if you were to self-destruct, they would be there for you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  Five.  How many friends do you have?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Close friends like I asked you about?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  Yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I keep it pretty close or I find it too overwhelming because I am always working on projects and I need to concentrate.  But in terms of self destruct?  If I was to self destruct I would say four people that would be there.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  Yeah, I mean I didn't count in my mom and my dad...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  No, I didn't, either.  How about you?  If you self-destructed how many people could you count on to stay by you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  Is that including all the girl? [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  No...really close friends?  I would say not that many.  Well, hopefully Sharin would be there...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Did you include Sune in your count?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  Noooo!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  Yeah, I did!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  You did?!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  Yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  Within the band, our drummer in Denmark is my really good friend, because we have been living such a crazy life together for so long that we just became so close.  And over here I might have maybe five, six people, maybe.</p>
<figure></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  As your fame has increased, have you found it more difficult to trust people?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  Not at all.  I haven't experienced anything like that.  I have found it easier to meet people.  But I haven't found too many phonies, and I haven't had a problem with that.  I don't go out much, and when I go out I just usually go out with my friends and I'll occasionally go out to see a show.  So, I really don't meet that many people.  And the people I meet on the road are fans and stuff, and I always try to be polite and accommodate them as best I can.</p>
<head id="On_touring">On touring</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you guys see an end to the band, a day when you can see yourselves feeling done with it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  I don't know...I guess sometimes we think about if we want to start a family or something like that.  Or maybe there will be other priorities at a certain point...we joke about it a lot, actually...</p>
</text>
