<text id="autogum_bio_doc482" title="Tanzio da Varallo" shortTile="tanzio-da-varallo" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-01-17" dateModified="2018-11-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tanzio_da_Varallo" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Tanzio da Varallo</head>
<p>Antonio d'Enrico, called <hi rend="bold">Tanzio da Varallo</hi>, or simply <hi rend="bold">il Tanzio</hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> (c. 1575/1580 – c. 1632/1633) was an Italian painter of the late-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mannerism">Mannerist</ref> or early <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baroque_painting">Baroque</ref> period.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>He was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Riale_d’Alagna">Riale d’Alagna</ref>, and was active mainly in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lombardy">Lombardy</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Piedmont">Piedmont</ref>, including the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sacro_Monte_di_Varallo">Sacro Monte</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Varallo_Sesia">Varallo Sesia</ref>, where he worked contemporaneously with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pier_Francesco_Mazzucchelli">Pier Francesco Mazzucchelli (il Morazzone)</ref>. He painted a <hi rend="italic">Circumcision</hi> for <hi rend="italic">Fara San Martino</hi>, and a <hi rend="italic">Virgin with saints</hi> for the Collegiate at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pescocostanzo">Pescocostanzo</ref>. Some of his paintings acquire the influence of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tenebrism">Tenebrist</ref> styles and morbid thematic characteristic of the followers of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caravaggio">Caravaggio</ref> and also of many <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lombardy">Lombard</ref> painters, including his somewhat gruesome <hi rend="italic">David with Goliath</hi> (1620). His animated and crowded <hi rend="italic">Battle of Sennacherib</hi> (1627–28) for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basilica_of_San_Gaudenzio">Basilica of San Gaudenzio</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> reflects the influence of his work in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sacri_Monti_of_Piedmont_and_Lombardy">Sacri Monti of Piedmont and Lombardy</ref>, painting scenographic diorama scenes.</p>
<p>His brother Melchiorre was also a painter, studied in Milan, and painted a last judgement for the parish of Riva.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Works</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">Madonna col Bambino, San Francesco e donatore</hi>, oil on canvas, c. 1610, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colledimezzo">Colledimezzo</ref> (CH), parish church of San Giovanni Evangelista.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Circumcision</hi>, oil on canvas, c. 1610, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fara_San_Martino">Fara San Martino</ref> (CH), church of San Remigio.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Pentecost</hi> (5 fragments), oil on canvas, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Naples">Naples</ref>, previously in church of Santa Restituta, now in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Museo_di_Capodimonte">Museo di Capodimonte</ref>.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Madonna dell'incendio sedato</hi>, oil on canvas, 1614, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pescocostanzo">Pescocostanzo</ref> (AQ), collegiate church of Santa Maria in Colle.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">San Carlo attends those afflicted with plague</hi>, oil on canvas, 1615–16, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domodossola">Domodossola</ref> (VB), collegiate church of Santi Gervasio e Protasio.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Sant'Antonio da Padova</hi>, oil on canvas, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Varallo_Sesia">Varallo Sesia</ref>, Pinacoteca Civica.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">San Sebastiano curato da Sant'Irene e un angelo</hi>, oil on canvas, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Gallery_of_Art">National Gallery of Art</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Washington,_D.C.">Washington</ref>, Samuel H. Kress Collection.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Christ taken to court of Pilate for first time</hi>, fresco, 1617–18, Varallo Sesia, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sacro_Monte_di_Varallo">Sacro Monte</ref>, Cappella XXVII.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Pilate washes his hands</hi>, fresco, 1619–20, Varallo Sesia, Sacro Monte, Cappella XXXIV.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">San Giovanni Evangelista, Santa Caterina d’Alessandria, San Teodoro e Santa Apollonia</hi>, oil on canvas, 1618, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Verbania">Verbania – Pallanza</ref>, Museo del Paesaggio.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Davide con la testa di Golia</hi>, oil on canvas, Varallo Sesia, Pinacoteca Civica.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Gentiluomo</hi>, oil on canvas, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milan">Milan</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pinacoteca_di_Brera">Pinacoteca di Brera</ref>.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Gentildonna</hi>, oil on canvas, Milan, Pinacoteca di Brera.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Testa di gentiluomo</hi>, oil on copper, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gallarate">Gallarate</ref>, Museo Gallaratese di Studi Patri.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">San Gerolamo</hi>, oil on canvas, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kansas_City,_Missouri">Kansas City</ref>, The Nelson-Atkins Museum of Art.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Adorazione dei pastori</hi>, 1605-1610, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palais_des_beaux-arts_de_Lille">Palais des beaux-arts de Lille</ref>.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">La Vergine col Bambino adorata dai santi Domenico e Francesco</hi>, oil on canvas, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lumellogno">Lumellogno</ref> (NO), church of Santi Ippolito e Cassiano.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Due angeli che reggono la corona della Vergine</hi>, oil on canvas, Varallo Sesia, Pinacoteca.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Jacob and Rachel</hi>, oil on canvas, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turin">Turin</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Galleria_Sabauda">Galleria Sabauda</ref>.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Visitation</hi>, oil on canvas, Vagna, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frazione">frazione</ref> of Domodossola, church of San Brizio.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Gentiluomo</hi>, oil on canvas, c.1625, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cleveland_(Ohio)">Cleveland (Ohio)</ref>, The Cleveland Museum of Art.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Adoration of shepherds with San Carlo Borromeo</hi>, oil on canvas, Turin, Museo Civico di Arte Antica.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Adoration dei pastori con San Francesco e San Carlo Borromeo</hi>, oil on canvas, Los Angeles, Los Angeles Country Museum of Art.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">La fuga in Egitto</hi>, oil on canvas, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Houston">Houston</ref>, The Museum of Fine Arts, Samuel H. Kress Collection.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">San Giovanni Battista nel deserto</hi>, oil on canvas, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tulsa,_Oklahoma">Tulsa, Oklahoma</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philbrook_Museum_of_Art">Philbrook Museum of Art</ref>.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Gesù davanti ad Erode</hi>, fresco, 1628, Varallo Sesia, Sacro Monte, 1628, Cappella XXVIII.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">San Carlo porta in processione il Sacro Chiodo</hi>, oil on canvas, c. 1629, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cellio">Cellio</ref> (VC), parish church of San Lorenzo.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Santi in adorazione della Trinità</hi>, Fontaneto d’Agogna (NO), oil on canvas, parish church of Beata Vergine Assunta.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">I Santi Pietro e Marco</hi>, oil on canvas, Turin, Galleria Sabauda.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Crucifixion</hi>, oil on canvas, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gerenzano">Gerenzano</ref>, parish church of Santi Pietro e Paolo.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Decorazione della cappella dell'Angelo Custode</hi>, fresco, and <hi rend="italic">Sennacherib sconfitto dall'Angelo</hi>, oil on canvas, 1617–19, Novara, Basilica di San Gaudenzio.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Sennacherib sconfitto dall'Angelo</hi>, oil on canvas, c. 1618, Novara, Museo Civico.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Annuncio dei pastori</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Adorazione dei pastori</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Gloria angelica</hi>, 1631–32, fresco, Milan, Santa Maria della Pace.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Il Redentore in gloria</hi>, <hi rend="italic">I profeti Daniele e Isaia</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Angeli musicanti</hi>, fresco, 1631–32, Milan, church of Sant’Antonio Abate.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">St Roch</hi>, oil on canvas, Varallo Sesia, Pinacoteca (previously in the parish church of Camasco, frazione of Varallo Sesia).</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">La Madonna col Bambino e i santi Carlo e Francesco</hi>, oil on canvas, Varallo Sesia, Pinacoteca.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Martyrdom of Franciscans in Nagasaki</hi>, oil on canvas, Milan, Pinacoteca di Brera.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Beato Giovanni Tavelli da Tossignano</hi>, oil on canvas, Varallo Sesia, Pinacoteca.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Decorazione a fresco della cappella Gibellini</hi>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Borgosesia">Borgosesia</ref> (VC), collegiate church of Santi Pietro e Paolo.</item></list>
<head>Footnotes</head>
</text>
