<text id="autogum_academic_doc358" title="Cropland Classification Using Sentinel-1 Time Series: Methodological Performance and Prediction Uncertainty Assessment" shortTile="cropland-classification" author="Erkki Tomppo, Oleg Antropov, Jaan Praks" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-4292/11/21/2480/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussions</head>
<p>
Each study concerning crop species prediction with multi-temporal SAR data has some unique features, including the classification approach, number, and specificity of crop species used, as well as the SAR data used. This generally complicates comparison, as no baseline mapping approach is established, often requiring testing with several approaches within each study, e.g.,. Other factors affecting the possible accuracy levels in mapping are the structure of the crop species, that is, whether only crop species are predicted or also root vegetables. </p>

<p>In this study, different types of species groups were predicted with high accuracy. Uncertainty levels of the prediction were also assessed. Achieved accuracy levels compare favourably to prior recent studies particularly with multitemporal Sentinel-1 data. Here, OA was either at same level or higher, especially when using the parcel size threshold of four hectares. Importantly, the number of crops was considerably higher, indicating a potential for further development of an operational crop mapping method. </p>

<p>The overall accuracy (OA) with the ik-NN method varied depending on the number of species included in the classification, and whether all field parcels were included, or an area threshold for the field parcels was employed. The later one exhibits the dependence of OA on the size of the area threshold. The OAs have been calculated here using the observation as the weight, that is, each field parcel had the same weight. The area weighted OAs had been larger because the crop species were predicted more accurately for the larger field parcels than for the small field parcels. </p>

<p>Some tests with a very high number of the species groups showed also a great OA. The OA was at a level of 82% with 41 species and with an area threshold of 0.5 hectares. However, the results with 41 species groups are dominated by a few species with large areas explaining an unexpected large OA. </p>

<p>The uncertainty assessments of the predicted crop species also gave promising results. The certainty was over 90% in most cases when using 95% confidence intervals (Table 7 and Table 8, see also <figure>Figure 7</figure>). The prediction uncertainty is largest in the rare species groups, such as 2, 4, and 7 (Broad bean Vicia faba, Spring Oilseed Rape and 7 = Winter wheat, Winter barley) as can be expected. Overall, the species can be predicted relatively accurately in most cases, even compared to the earlier studies. </p>

<p>Importantly, while SAR time series have been used recently, the analyses of the effect of the precise acquisition time of the SAR data in crop species predictions has been studied less. The scenes from the late growing season had the greatest explanatory power in predicting the crop species (<figure>Figure 4</figure> and <figure>Figure 5</figure>). The analyses separately with the VV and VH polarizations and with one Sentinel-1 scene only revealed the same thing; in addition to that, the VV polarization gave greater OAs than VH polarization in the later part of the growing season (<figure>Figure 8</figure>). </p>

<p>Establishing the number of Sentinel-1 scenes and the timing of SAR data that it takes to achieve acceptable overall accuracy can have important effects on operational LPIS. The time period from which the Sentinel-1 scenes or other SAR data are needed depends naturally on the progress of the growing season and thus the latitude and other growing factors. The data acquisition period must be adapted to the local conditions. The proposed method to estimate the confidence intervals of the probabilities of the predicted species group is also new to the best of our knowledge. </p>
</text>
