<text id="autogum_reddit_doc127" title="What is the policy for granting a Replacement Unit for MacBook Pro (under 1-year warranty) given repeated, back-to-back hardware issues? Can an exception for purchasing AppleCare+ be made under the same scenario?" shortTile="policy-granting-replacement" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-04-30" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8g3kgu" speakerList="#DreamHQ" speakerCount="1">
<head>What is the policy for granting a Replacement Unit for MacBook Pro (under 1-year warranty) given repeated, back-to-back hardware issues? Can an exception for purchasing AppleCare+ be made under the same scenario?</head>
<sp who="#DreamHQ">
<p>Hello everyone, I'm looking for some advice for my particular situation. Last year, in August 2017, I purchased an new old stock 15-inch 2016 MacBook Pro from B&amp;H (was a new computer, unopened; they just never sold it so they were discounting it to make room for new shipments). I had opted out on purchasing AppleCare\+, as I did not think I would ever use the accidental service (I work at home and only use my laptop while working, rarely take it out of my house). However, just two weeks ago, I started having an issue with the new keyboard mechanism (never had any issues with the laptop prior to this); my "A" key was malfunctioning and would either print out "aa" (repeating the keystroke) or nothing at all when pressed. With my 1-year original warranty running out in a few months, I made an appointment with the Genius Bar to get the issue fixed. Took it in 4/18, and got a call 4/20 after stating that it was ready for pickup. I go to pick it up, and when I close the laptop, I see a 1-inch scratch on the lid that wasn't there when I dropped it off. Talked to the employee helping me, and after checking the notes to confirm that the scratch wasn't on the laptop when I dropped it off, he offered to remedy the issue by replacing the display, which was the only option. I agreed, and they told me they would call when it was ready for pickup in "24-48 hours". On 4/25 (over 96 hours later) I call them, as I never got a call or email that it was ready. They have some issues finding me in their system, but after 10 mins on hold, they tell me that it is ready for pickup. I drive over, and when I go to pick it up, the display has some lines running across the screen, but it came off when I wiped it with a microfiber cloth. There was also some left over adhesive strips on the bottom of the display. No worries I thought, as long as everything works fine. Booted up the laptop and saw that the CAPSLOCK button function was inverted; it would light up when not pressed, and when I pressed it to activate CAPSLOCK, the light would go off. Tried logging into my computer and it went to a black screen with the cursor turning into the spinning pinwheel. Restarted it, and the CAPSLOCKS button issue was remedied, but I still couldn't log into my account; still kept getting the black screen with spinning pinwheel. Genius Bar Employee told me to log into the other accounts on my laptop (to see if it was a hardware of software issue), but all of them would lead to the black screen with spinning pinwheel. They run a diagnostic test, but everything hardware related checks out and seems to be working fine. The Employee tries running an OS that they have on hand using a dongle, but when he tries to log in, the black screen with the spinning pinwheel persists (although this time, occasionally the top left portion of the display would flicker), leading him to believe that it is a hardware issue. He has no idea what may be causing the issue, so he gets his Manager. Manager states that it could possibly be a graphics card failure, although he is not certain. He tells me that they can replace the logic board/motherboard (and transfer over my SSD to retain data) as that is the only part left they have not replaced, and it should most likely solve the issue. I ask if I can just get a replacement unit (as this point, they would have replaced everything on my laptop) since I have a backup of my data, but he states that unfortunately, Apple's policy is that they must perform 3 major repairs before exploring the possibility of a replacement unit. If after the logic board replacement my laptop is still acting up, they will allow for a replacement unit. But for now, my only option is to wait another 5-7 days to pick it up. Currently borrowing a friend's laptop for work in the meantime (which is what I am typing this post on), while I wait until 4/30-5/2 to pick up the MacBook once they have replaced the motherboard. Also, note that both times I went to pick up my MacBook Pro, I didn't leave the store. Ever since I first brought it into the store on 4/18 (for the keyboard issue), it has never left the store. My MacBook is also currently updated to the latest version of OSX. My question to you all is: 1) Have you ever encountered someone who went through a similar situation, and if so, how was their situation handled? 2) Is what the manager said regarding the 3 major repairs not remedying the issue before replacing the laptop unit true? It seems a tad unreasonable as it's taking them more work and time to fix the issues in the long run. 3) As I said earlier, I did not purchase AppleCare\+ when buying the MacBook. However, now that my warranty is running out and all these issues are starting to occur, I regret that decision. I'm worried that given this track record, another issue will arise once my warranty expires, and I will be stuck paying the repair costs out of pocket. Also (no offense), but I am paranoid of the quality of the repairs done as well, as only one key on my keyboard was not functioning properly when I visited the Genius Bar the first time, and now all these issues are arising back-to-back AFTER they "repaired" it (never saw any signs of these issues before). That and the fact that didn't bother testing to make sure everything worked and forgot to call me for pickup the second time, scratched the lid without telling me the first time, and didn't clean the replacement display (and left the adhesive strips on it) before handing back my laptop leads me to question their craftsmanship and quality control at this particular location. I don't want to end up holding the short end of the stick when my 1-year warranty expires due to an oversight when they made the repair. My question is, is it possible for an exception to be made and purchase AppleCare\+ for my Macbook Pro (even though it has been more than 60 days since the purchase date)? Especially given all the repairs, everything on my laptop that can be replaced has been replaced (and it technically is a new machine). Asked the manager on 4/25 and he said he didn't have the authority to make that exception, although he has never dealt with a scenario like mine.</p>
</sp>
</text>
