<text id="autogum_academic_doc290" title="A Cloud Information Monitoring and Recommendation Multi-Agent System with Friendly Interfaces for Tourism" shortTile="cloud-information" author="Kune-Yao Chen, Sheng-Yuan Yang" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/9/20/4385/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Conclusions and Discussion</head>
<p>On the basis of wearable devices, web services, and linked open data, this study’s intelligent travel cloud information monitor and recommendation multi-agent system explored LOD access technologies for [email protected] by integrating the aforementioned UAI technology links for increasing the accuracy, authenticity, and integrity of intelligent tourism information, effectively adding value to the quality of cloud information monitoring and recommendation through the support of three-stage intelligent decision-making with CEOonoIAS. This paper extends the application scope of Dr. What-Info and reached the ultimate goal of the research—the construction of an intelligent mobile information monitoring and recommendation multi-agent system with friendly interfaces for autonomously providing corresponding cloud information. The results and conclusions of the system’s practical exploration are listed as follows: </p>

<p>
<list>
<item>(1) This study established three-tier address-based, UAI-based LOD access technology by actively developing the proposed system with friendly interfaces that assist users in quickly, accurately, and effectively obtaining relevant and timely useful links and open information.</item>
<item>(2) With the operational support of CEOntoIAS, this study established a cloud interactive paradigm supported by web services through the corresponding query semantic content with the CURRL in JSON format. With the support of three-stage intelligent decision-making, such as OntoDMA, OntoCBRA, and OntoIAS, the proposed system APPs autonomously and effectively added value to the quality of the monitoring and to the recommendation of intelligent tourism information. Therefore, this study is unique and different from other information agents found in the literature.</item>
</list>
</p>

<p>Furthermore, regarding the evaluation results mentioned above, the mobile APP, as proposed in this system, can be easily solved, which is completely in line with the original intention of the research—timely, appropriate, and free, as well as providing the latest and complete mobile information services. In addition, based on Tu’s comparison table for LBSs, the proposed system receives an overall function up-to-standard rate of 87.5%, and such recommendations provide users with high information correctness and user satisfaction. The proposed system architecture not only uses the back-end database more efficiently; it also provides users with more all-inclusive LBS. The satisfaction score of the usability of the proposed system and the ease of using the interface design was 84 points in terms of Quesenbery’s 5Es and Nielsen ratings, which indicated that this system APP must be improved in two aspects: error tolerance and help documents. The verification results of the interface design showed that the human–machine interface of our proposed system can meet important design preferences and provide approximate optimal balance with average <hi rend="italic">BI</hi> = 0.008430. Finally, although the interface appearance is more convenient, the operation and fluency are somewhat insufficient, and should be enhanced. Information correctness was graded as being high, and the graphical menu design of the system APP was easy for users to use, which were obvious outcomes. Although there is plenty of room for improvement in experience and in more travel-related agents, such as instant traffic assistance agents and trip planning agents, the feasibility of the proposed service architecture has been proven.</p>
</text>
