<text id="autogum_voyage_doc467" title="Stockholm Arlanda Airport" shortTile="stockholm-arlanda" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=140354" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Stockholm Arlanda Airport</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://www.swedavia.com/arlanda/%3F_ga%3D2.180474087.1731738644.1503395940-529487520.1503395940">Stockholm Arlanda Airport</ref></hi> ( ARN ), commonly known as <hi rend="bold">Arlanda</hi>, is an international airport in the <ref target="Stockholm%20County">Stockholm County</ref> region of <ref target="Sweden">Sweden</ref>, some 35 km north of central <ref target="Stockholm">Stockholm</ref>. It is by far the busiest airport in Sweden, a close third in the Nordic countries after Oslo-Gardermoen and Copenhagen Airport, and the major gateway to international air travel for most of the country.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>In the late 1950s it became obvious that <hi rend="italic"><ref target="Stockholm%20Bromma%20Airport">Stockholm Bromma Airport</ref></hi> was too small to serve international flight traffic to Stockholm, so a new airport was constructed and Arlanda was inaugurated in 1962. The name is derived from "Arland", an old name for the parish "Ärlinghundra" where the airport is, and also makes as a pun on the <ref target="Swedish">Swedish</ref> verb "landa" (landing). It is in the small town of <ref target="Sigtuna">Sigtuna</ref>, about half-way between Stockholm, by far the largest city in Sweden, and <ref target="Uppsala">Uppsala</ref>, the fourth largest city in the country.</p>

<p>The airport has four terminals called 2, 3, 4 and 5. Terminals 2 and 5 serve international flights and Terminals 3 and 4 serve domestic ones. One of the main shopping and cafe areas is "SkyCity" is outside of the transit and security zones, between Terminals 4 &amp; 5. Arlanda is the busiest airport in Sweden and the third largest in the <ref target="Nordic%20countries">Nordic countries</ref>, serving some 25 million passengers in 2016.</p>

<head>Flights</head>
<p>All terminals have self-service check-in and baggage drop. Check-in automats can also be found at Stockholm central station, by the Arlanda Express trains, and at Cityterminalen in downtown Stockholm. Of course, all terminals also have staffed check-in desks.</p>

<head>Rail</head>
 is located in "Sky City" between terminals 4 &amp; 5.

<p>The fastest way to the airport from Stockholm Central Station is the Arlanda Express high-speed train service, making the trip in 20 minutes. The ticket price is fairly high at 280 kr for an adult (26 or older) as of 2018. If you buy tickets on the train, it's even more expensive as a 100 kr printing fee is applied. However, various combo, student/child and advance deals are avalable to the point that four children under 18 can travel free on each adult ticket and said ticket can cost only 154 kr if bought 90 days early - see <ref target="https://www.arlandaexpress.com/fares.aspx">here</ref> for more details.</p>

<p>It is possible to use the Stockholm commuter rail service (Pendeltåg) between Uppsala C and central and southern Stockholm. This route takes 38 minutes between Arlanda C station and Stockholm C. The fare is higher from Arlanda compared to other journeys on the commuter rail network, but less than the Arlanda Express.</p>

<head>Bus</head>
<p>Flygbussarna, Swebus and SL operate coaches to and from the airport which stop at some locations in northern Stockholm County and at Stockholm City Centre and Stockholm Central Station. There is also a local bus line no 583 to Märsta, from where there are commuter trains to Stockholm and surroundings, the cheapest way of getting to/from Stockholm (a bus ticket which includes commuter train to stockholm cost 44 kr as of April 2018). Bus 801 takes around 40 minutes to Uppsala and departs every 15 to 30 minutes.</p>

<head>Road</head>
<p>The motorway E4 goes past the airport and connects Arlanda with central Stockholm as well as Uppsala and other cities further north. Terminal parking, short-term and long-term parking is available at the airport. The low price long-term parking requires a free shuttle bus ride. The bus departs every 8–15 minutes. There are rental car facilities at the airport.</p>

<head>Taxi</head>
<p>All taxi companies are required to offer fixed prices when going from the airport, which takes away the guesswork of how much the fare will cost (you can still request use of the taxi meter). Most major companies also offer fixed prices to the airport.</p>

<p>Taxi fares are unregulated in Sweden, meaning taxis can claim any price as long as they follow the price list shown in the taxi and stuck on the side window. But taxis at the Arlanda taxi stations are not allowed to charge more than 675 kr for at single trip to Uppsala or the northern parts of Stockholm.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<p>Despite being the largest airport in Sweden, Arlanda is not huge but rather walkable. You can take a free one minute train ride between terminals 2/3 and 5.</p>

<head>Wait</head>
<p>There are two playgrounds run by <hi rend="bold">Junibacken</hi>, an <ref target="Astrid%20Lindgren%20tourism">Astrid Lindgren-themed</ref> theme park in <ref target="Stockholm/Djurg%C3%A5rden">Djurgården</ref> in Stocksholm. The playgrounds can be found at terminals 4 &amp; 5 after passing security.</p>
<head>Lounges</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Menzies</hi> has one lounge at terminal 2 and two lounges at terminal 5.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">SAS lounge</hi> has two longes, one at terminal 4 an one at terminal 5.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Stockholm Arlanda Lounge</hi>, End of Terminal 5, at the Gate F26-F69 wing (Right at SkyCity and at the end having passed two other Terminal 5 concourses). For Emirates First Class and Business class, Qatar Airways (Platinum, Gold, Silver Members, Oneworld Emerald, Sapphire, Ruby Members), Ukrainian International Airlines Business class, Novair, Thomas Cook Airlines, Air Serbia, IranAir and Rossiya Business Class. Coffee, tea, cold beverages and a cold buffet is served. Free access to Wi-Fi and newspapers.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat and drink</head>
<p>A lot of restaurants, cafés and bars can be found at terminals 2, 4, 5 and at "Sky City", outside the transit zone between terminals 4 &amp; 5. Terminal 3 only has a café which serves hot drinks and pastry.</p>

<p>Bottled <ref target="water">water</ref> is expensive at Arlanda; 20 kr or more for a 50 cL bottle (similar to the price at gas stations throughout Sweden). Since Swedish tap water is of excellent quality, a workaround is to bring a refillable bottle to the airport, and fill it up from the toilet tap (after security). Some terminals have drinking fountains.</p>

<head>Sky City</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Alfredo's</hi> (Sky City), ☏ +46 8593 607 80 . Daily 09:00-22:00. Serve pizzas, kebabs and Swedish meatballs, among other things.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Indochine</hi> (Sky city), ☏ +46 8593 612 23 . M-F 10:00-19:00. Soups 140 kr, salads 130 kr.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Itamae Sushi</hi> (Sky City), ☏ +46 830 03 31 . Daily 10:00-21:00. Sushi from 100 kr, hot dishes from 110 kr.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kitchen &amp; Table</hi> (Clarion Hotel in Sky City), ☏ +46 8 444 18 00 . M-F 11:30-14:00 17:00-22:00, Sa Su 17:00-22:30. Hotel restaurant of Clarion Hotel Prices start at 185 kr.</item>
</list>
</text>
