<text id="autogum_interview_doc098" title="part2_Wikinews interviews specialists on Russian intervention in Ukraine" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-03-02" dateModified="2016-11-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_specialists_on_Russian_intervention_in_Ukraine" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Blank</hi>: It is unlikely that Ukraine could prevail in such a conflict but I think it would unhinge Russian calculations, create the basis for protracted conflict, including guerrilla war for which Russia is not prepared, and thus force the West to act and begin the process of imposing costs on Russia that Putin did not foresee. Indeed that is one reason why this is an incredibly reckless action on Putin's part.</item></list></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Kotsonis</hi>: No one thinks Ukraine can stand up to Russia. It's partly because Russia is bigger and better equipped, partly because Russia has bases in Ukraine, and partly because Russia is relatively united. One will have to see whether Ukraine will unite when so many of its citizens identify with Russia. We do not know the answer to this, only anecdote.</item></list></p>
<figure><caption> File photo of interviewee Jeremy Morris. Image: Jeremy Morris.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Would penalties imposed on Russia by the 'Western nations' being the United States, UK and France have severe consequences for the Russian economy?</p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Morris</hi>: Not really, so much depends on oil price for Russia, but fall in [the] <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russian%20ruble">rouble</ref> due to lack of confidence may affect ordinary Russians' ability to buy imported goods.</item></list></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Brandist</hi>: Clearly such measures would have negative effects, and the business community in Russia is clearly worried. That said, however, the likelihood of any coherent action against Russia is not great, not least because much of Europe is reliant of Russian gas. Moreover, it is European states that would face any potential flood of refugees and so European states will not be keen on too much pressure that could lead Russia to press Ukraine even more. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">Germany</ref> effectively vetoed Georgia's attempt to be part of NATO, and it would have even more interests in trying to stabilize the situation now. In this situation the 'Western nations' mentioned have limited leverage, though it clearly would have an impact.</item></list></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Blank</hi>: Ejecting Russia from the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/G8">G8</ref> is meaningless. Sanctions that would register are sanctions on Putin et al so they cannot access their money, action in the WTO [<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/World_Trade_Organization">World Trade Organization</ref>] to arraign Russia for violating its  statutes, legislation  placing sanctions on Russia equivalent to those on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iran">Iran</ref> that have crippled it, staging a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/bank%20run">run</ref> on the rouble, and if necessary  blockading the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Baltic_Sea">Baltic</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Black_Sea">Black Seas</ref> to prevent maritime commerce.  Most importantly but this is over time, Europe must reorient its gas and oil purchases away from Russia on a long-term basis.  All these moves must be taken together and in tandem with  military-political moves to uphold Ukraine's integrity and sovereignty  and  thus preserve peace by deterring Russia and imposing excessive costs upon it.</item></list></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Kotsonis</hi>: It will probably make matters worse for Russia but it won't be a causal factor. Russia is overly dependent on commodities exports and is at the mercy of world prices. The world wants those resources and will probably not renounce them, but they may not be enough to keep the economy growing in Russia. Any penalties would only accelerate the secular trend.</item></list></p>
</text>
