<text id="autogum_whow_doc324" title="Follow Singaporean Food Etiquette" shortTile="follow-singaporean" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2007-11-22" dateModified="2016-12-26" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Follow-Singaporean-Food-Etiquette" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Follow Singaporean Food Etiquette</head><p>Singapore is dubbed the "Food Paradise" by people all over the world. Many delicacies and good food from all over the world can be found in Singapore. Here we will show two common yet unique ways of eating non-local food and more conventional foods in Singapore, using your hand and chopsticks.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Indian and Muslim food (hand)</head>
<p>Indian and Muslim food like nasi briyani, roti prata, nasi lemak and nasi padang are usually consumed using the hand by the locals. They are taught to use their right hand only when taking the food.</p>
<list type="ordered"><item>Use only your right hand. <figure rend="Follow Singaporean Food Etiquette Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use your thumb, index finger and middle finger to grasp the food. Only your fingers should come in contact with the food. <figure rend="Follow Singaporean Food Etiquette Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep hand contact to the food to the minimal. <figure rend="Follow Singaporean Food Etiquette Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The thumb of the hand is used to "push" or "guide" the food into your mouth.</item></list></item>
<item>When consuming roti prata, you should tear the prata with one hand only. Using your thumb and index finger, tear a piece of the prata off, and then scoop the curry or the vegetables, with the bread and then eat. <figure rend="Follow Singaporean Food Etiquette Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>It is incorrect, and inelegant to eat the curry and the bread separately. <figure rend="Follow Singaporean Food Etiquette Step 4Bullet1.jpg"></figure></item></list></item></list>
<head>Chinese food (chopsticks)</head>
<p>Chopsticks are naturally believed to have originated in the olden days of China. The traditional eating tools are a pair of small identical, even-length tapered sticks.</p>
<list type="ordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Put one chopstick between the palm and the base of the thumb</hi>, using the ring finger (the fourth finger) to support the lower part of the stick. With the thumb, grip the stick down while the ring finger pushes it up. The stick should be steady and very stable. <figure rend="Follow Singaporean Food Etiquette Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Use the edge of the thumb</hi>, index and middle fingers to sustain the other stick like a pen. Make sure the tips of the two sticks line up. <figure rend="Follow Singaporean Food Etiquette Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Balance the upper stick up and down</hi> towards the stationary lower stick. With this oscillation one can pick up food of any amazing sizes! <figure rend="Follow Singaporean Food Etiquette Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>With plenty of <hi rend="bold">practice</hi>, the two sticks will serve like a pair of tongs. <figure rend="Follow Singaporean Food Etiquette Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Chopsticks generally should be held at the thicker end about one-third along their length for balance and accuracy. For greater touch to pick up food further away, hold the chopsticks at the upper ends.</item>
<item>If the tips fail to its position, it will be difficult to hold things. Hold the chopsticks upright with one of the tips lightly touching the table, and gently push the chopsticks down or gently loosen your grip for a moment to let both tips become equal in length. You can also alter your grip or holding position this way.</item>
<item>With practice, it is likely to perform step one and two according on lifting up the chopsticks with one hand. Adjust your grip if possible.</item></list>
</text>
