<text id="autogum_interview_doc204" title="part5_BDSM as business: Interviews with Dominatrixes" shortTile="partbdsm-business" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-28" dateModified="2008-01-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BDSM_as_business%3A_Interviews_with_Dominatrixes" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  It’s really rare you get people saying that.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  I’m still high from the session, because of that conversation we had and he thinks this is going to make him a better person.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That you are going to help him.  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  Yeah, because <hi rend="italic">he</hi> feels that way.  I don’t know if this type of thing…it definitely wouldn’t help everybody out there, but it helps some people.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  The people who see you, it does help them.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  Well, yeah, you know, for some people it is just a means to an end—it’s the only way they can get off, or whatever.  I don’t judge anyone.  But I find it really fascinating, all the different types.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are they typically embarrassed when they first start coming in here?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  Some are, and some aren’t.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Yeah, some are and some aren’t.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Depending on their experience or their comfort level?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  I think it depends on how people have reacted to them in the past, as you can imagine.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Like the guy I was seeing.  He was originally very nervous.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  Yeah, he was probably embarrassed.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  We’ve had a few people come in, get nervous, and are like, “I…I…I don’t know what I should say, or what I can tell you.”</p>
<head id="Psychological_challenges">Psychological challenges</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How do you make them feel comfortable?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Anything they have to say, you’ve heard it before! [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  Yeah, sometimes they are like, “Oh, this might sound weird…” and I’m like, “Trust me, it doesn’t sound weird!” Not to make them feel like they are one of a thousand.  I try to let them know that I appreciate their being honest with me, and I find it interesting.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do you think in your own histories has made you so non-judgmental?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  Well, that would be getting into personal information I wouldn’t want to talk about.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Yeah.  You can’t be judgmental in this industry.  You have to be open-minded.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Alex, do people ever come in with fantasies that are <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraq%20War">Iraq War</ref>-related.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  I haven’t.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  I’ve had some like that.  There have been a few fetishes that are racial play, or war related.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nazi%20chic">Nazis</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  People come here with things to work out.  Maybe they’ve been traumatized or maybe they have some issue.  They come here with things.  I haven’t run into anyone, but I wouldn’t be surprised.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Like veterans?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  Yeah.  I have <hi rend="italic">definitely</hi> seen vets before, I know I have.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So you were saying you have war-related?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  I’m not sure how it develops with an individual.  But usually the request is a specific type of role play, like I am the German Nazi and this is the Jew and I have to punish him in some sense.</p>
</text>
