<text id="autogum_whow_doc608" title="Know Yourself when You Don&apos;t Have a Mother" shortTile="know-yourself-dont" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-07-01" dateModified="2018-09-27" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Know-Yourself-when-You-Don%27t-Have-a-Mother" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Know Yourself when You Don't Have a Mother</head><p>Understanding yourself is often a little easier if you know where you came from. But if you do not have a mother in your life, this can be a part of your life story that you will never know quite the same way as other people. And that can leave an emptiness in a person's heart. It can make simple questions of connection a mystery. </p>
<p>But whether your mother is dead, or you were adopted by another family as a child, or for some other reason your mother is not present in your life -- it helps to know that there are ways to make connections that can help you understand yourself. This article will teach you how to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Get_to_Know_Yourself">know yourself</ref>, despite losing your mother or never knowing her.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Remember your childhood memories of your mother, if you have any. Recall what you can about the time you spent with your mother. All memories are precious, even those that make us sad or angry, even those that seem pointless. You may only recall vague details about your mother, her smell, the way she sang to you, the books she read to you, the things she told you off for even. All of these have influenced you, and, they are still in your head, so something in your brain hung onto those memories, what you remember is part of what makes you unique, part of what makes you <hi rend="bold">you</hi>, a way for you to know yourself. <figure rend="Know Yourself when You Don't Have a Mother Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Ask others to tell you their memories of your mother, whether you have any memories of your own or not, you can ask others what they know of her. If you lost your mother when you were older, you might like to find out about what your mother was like at your age, be that twelve, twenty, thirty-six, forty or any other age. You may be told you are like your mother was. You might hear stories that you identify with or a tale that makes you think, "that's just what I would of done in that situation". You can know yourself by identifying with others in this way, and if you identify with your mother, you can feel a connection with her even though she is no longer around. You may be nothing like your mother, that's okay, you are yourself, not your mother. Knowing if you are not like her or if you are just like her, or even a bit like her, all help you to know yourself and how alike or not you are to your mother. <figure rend="Know Yourself when You Don't Have a Mother Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Recognize that what you experience and how you get through things, good and bad, are what make you "you". You may have turned out a completely different person if your mother had been around for your whole life. Her passing has had a huge influence on your life, however old or young you were when you lost her, whether you feel it or not, even if you had another supportive care giver who took great care of you, your mother may have done things differently and raised a different you, only different of course, not a better you, and not a worse one either. You are the person you are because of your mother's passing, and that in and of itself is a piece of yourself. <figure rend="Know Yourself when You Don't Have a Mother Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>In some case some your mother's information will be available when you reach adulthood. <figure rend="Know Yourself when You Don't Have a Mother Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For instance, if you were adopted, you may be able to find out your birth information if your family chooses to withhold that information.</item>
<item>If there was a family tragedy such as a death, you may be able to gain information such as court records if you choose to research it.</item></list></item>
<item>You may not be able to find out anything. In some circumstances, you may not be able to find out anything about your mother. For instance, if you were abandoned as an infant, and no one knows your birth mother. Or you were part of a closed adoption. <figure rend="Know Yourself when You Don't Have a Mother Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>You are you, whoever your mother is or was. Whatever you remember, find out, or otherwise know about your mother, remember that you are a unique, separate individual -- just like everyone else gets to discover. While it often helps to know your biological or family history, in the end, your story is your own. <figure rend="Know Yourself when You Don't Have a Mother Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Other people who were close to your mother may get upset remembering things about her. It could be because of the pain of missing her, anger about hurtful things she did, or confusion about choices she made--and perhaps all of these at the same time. Remember that this has no reflection on you, that it may be hard for others to talk about these things, and you likely had no responsibility for your mother.</item>
<item>Be careful in dealing with mothers that have had issues of responsibility, criminal activity, abuse towards others and so on. Sometimes children are so eager to establish a relationship they become blind to the fact that such a relationship may have been broken for a reason. Be careful.</item>
<item>If family members are reluctant to give out sensitive information about your mother, be respectful of their judgement. Some information may not really be useful to you and cause you or others unnecessary hurt. Often information may be revealed to you when you are judged mature enough to process the facts.</item>
<item>You may get hurt depending on how it turns out.</item></list>
</text>
