<text id="autogum_interview_doc168" title="part1_Canada&amp;apos;s Don Valley West (Ward 25) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-don-valley" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-16" dateModified="2007-06-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Don_Valley_West_%28Ward_25%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent this particular ward on council?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Since I was five years old, I have spent a lot of my time in places such as Wilket Creek Park, Edwards Gardens, the Don Mills Centre, the Yonge and Lawrence area and many others. Ward 25 is where I grew up. I feel I know this ward and its varied neighbourhoods as well as anyone.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Practically all the services I make use of (entertainment and numerous other amenities) are located in Ward 25. My breakfast club and many other friends live in Ward 25. If elected I will make the short move to Ward 25.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What does Toronto mean to you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Toronto is a culturally diverse and lively place to live in. Compared to other major North American cities, it is relatively safe and clean. We need to work hard to make it continue to be regarded as such. The city must resist the current trend to intensify development without taking into consideration the "existing character" of any given neighbourhood. Our past is as important as our future. Hopefully, we can be a model to the world of what a progressive and environmentally conscious city can and should be.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Which council decision (since the 2003 election) do you feel the city/your ward should be most proud of, and which was least desirable?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> A very recent council decision (the vote against condominiums at the intersection of Fairlawn and Avenue Road) was a good one -- of course the developer has appealed this ruling to the OMB. The city should be least proud of its decision to increase their salaries by 8.9%.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> If you were elected as a "rookie" councillor, what would you bring to the table beyond the incumbent?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I am not a "business" person. I bring to council a fresh new perspective on things. I'm very serious about transparency and moral and ethical conduct. The public has a right to know many things that are apparently hidden from it at present. I really want to "open things up." After all, we are supposed to be the representatives of the people. We should strive to earn the respect of those who have elected us.</p>
<head id="Robertson_Boyle">Robertson Boyle</head>
<p>46-year-old <ref target="http://www.RobertsonBoyle.com">Robertson Boyle</ref> is a management consultant (marketing/business development for businesses in the professional services)</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Describe the three most important issues in your campaign.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Managing the City's phenomenal growth with a focus on those areas that impact on Ward 25.</p>
<p>•  Urban development pressure and its impact on the neighbourhood, infrastructure, and environment.</p>
<p>•  Accountability, transparency and responsible fiscal management at City Hall with a focus on increasing efficiency and reducing spending to alleviate upward pressures on property taxes.</p>
</text>
