<text id="autogum_interview_doc905" title="part4_Interview with Reggie Bibbs on his life with neurofibromatosis" shortTile="partinterview-reggie" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-28" dateModified="2010-04-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Reggie_Bibbs_on_his_life_with_neurofibromatosis" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: Yes, mainly the left side.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: Any reason for that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: No, there's no reason. We just never know how NF is gonna affect anyone. Everything on the left side accept the arm. The arm has a lot of strength and is not disfigured in any way.</p>
<head id="The_daily_life_of_Reggie_Bibbs">The daily life of Reggie Bibbs</head>
<figure><caption>Reggie having fun with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beyoncé%20Knowles">Beyoncé Knowles</ref> in April 2007.Image: Greg Gorman.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: What's a regular day in your life like?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: A regular day for me starts off with waking up in the morning and taking care of my leg. There are a few areas that really need treatment, special dressings for it, and after I, you know, wash and dress that area and then I go through the difficult task of putting the sock on. So I have to really work hard with this sock with a net on and after that everything else goes on. And I have to work on my eyes, I have to wash it when I wash and put my eye ointment in. And then after that it's basically doing what everyone else does with the exception of... I do a lot for my family so I'm doing a lot for them which I don't mind. I'm happy to help. That's basically how it starts. And I usually go to the grocery stores and things like that in my area, where people know me. They are nice there.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: Is it hard for you going outside your area?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: It's really hard for me to go to a store that's not in my area. It's like there's a boundary to where I stay inside of that boundary. There's only certain stores in the area that I would go to and if I'm on the other side of town if I need something I won't go to a store where people are not used to seeing me. I just don't want to create problems, I don't want to shock anyone or hurt anyone or I don't want to be hurt. So I just don't feel comfortable into going into stores that I'm not accustomed to be going to.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: What kind of bad experiences have you had?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: Well, there are some bad experiences where I walk up to a door, some people will lock the door and won't let me in. Some people will just turn and go the other way or cover their face or just shy away from me.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: How does that make you feel?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: It makes me feel angry because it makes me feel like I know they know better but they're doing it to be mean.</p>
</text>
