<text id="autogum_interview_doc752" title="part1_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green candidate Jim Reeves, York-Simcoe" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-01" dateModified="2007-11-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Green_candidate_Jim_Reeves%2C_York-Simcoe" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>These are also issues about which I have great concern. We must stop all development on the Lake Simcoe watershed until a comprehensive study can be completed to identify where development can take place with minimal impact on the watershed. This will have to be done through legislation like the proposed Lake Simcoe Act.</p>
<p>“Smart” planning techniques should be adopted, where the developments are along existing corridors of infrastructure. They should include mixed density housing, affordable housing, seniors housing, shopping and cafes. Facilities for doctors, lawyers, dentists etc all with walking or biking distances. This type of planning promotes a community spirit. People meet and talk and know each other. There tends to be less crime. This approach to planning is in use all over the world.</p>
<p>Developers should also be required to build facilities to encourage business to locate nearby. People can travel short distances to work.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business for the 39th legislative Assembly?</hi></p>
<p>Climate change is a fact and we see it in many of the everyday events. Eg. this summer we have had the same amount of rainfall as usual but it fell in several very heavy showers as opposed to the longer more ground penetrating kind we usually have. Considering this I think the first order of business should be to look at the many small changes that can considerably reduce our carbon footprint. The technology is available; other countries and cities are using it; Lets. Act now and get that leadership from the government of Ontario.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are property taxes in your riding at a fair level for the amount of services received in the municipality?</hi></p>
<p>The whole issue of property tax needs to be revisited. The Green Party proposes to place a moratorium on any increases in the assess market value of all residential properties and to establish a Royal Commission to study alternatives such as a location value tax system. Also consider a system which does not penalize property owners for making improvements.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How can the province lead the way in stimulating job creation?</hi></p>
<p>We need to become the leader in “green” jobs in sustainable industries. Recent trends show that the public is willing to pay more for “greener” products. Small business and co-ops are important engines of a vibrant green economy and should be encouraged, and money should be diverted to the form of loans to help them get started</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What are your views on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mixed%20member%20proportional%20representation">mixed member proportional representation</ref> (MMP) referendum?</hi></p>
<p>I am in support of changing the electoral system to MMP. It will give the people of the province a greater influence on the legislature. Each person can now vote for the candidate whom they feel best represents their riding, irrespective of party and then party of their choice. Many people have commented on the extra number of seats, however looking at the mathematics this was the smallest number that could be used to allow a seat for a party that gets over 3% of the vote. Also people now will have two representatives to advocate for them in the legislature.</p>
</text>
