<text id="autogum_academic_doc362" title="A Magnetically Tunable Check Valve Applied to a Lab-on-Chip Nitrite Sensor" shortTile="magnetically-tunable" author="Sean  C. Morgan, Andre  D. Hendricks, Mae  L. Seto, Vincent  J. Sieben" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1424-8220/19/21/4619/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Microfluidic devices have obtained global relevance since their initial application in miniaturized separation and chromatographic instrumentation. More recently, micro-total-analysis systems (µTAS), have been applied to chemical analysis and environmental monitoring. The small, low-cost, power efficient nature of microfluidic analysis platforms have even been used for in situ ocean nutrient sensors in recent years. Their potential to do automated and low-volume measurements at high pressures makes them amenable for sensor deployment in deep ocean environments. However, reliable fluid handling remains a core development area in establishing higher levels of integration on microfluidic devices. This is typically accomplished with specialized micro-valves and micro-pumps. </p>

<p>Microfabricated valves fall into one of two categories: Active or passive. Active valves require external actuation and often rely on off-chip support systems. A typical active membrane valve uses induced fluid pressure to actuate a movable diaphragm to seal a channel. Generating and controlling pressure for these on-chip active valves require a substantial amount of energy and external equipment that limit the ability to miniaturize. Complex in situ lab-on-chip systems employ multiple pneumatic or hydraulic actuators driven by off-chip solenoids. In the works by Ogilvie et al. and Beaton et al., completely automated lab-on-chip nutrient sensors contained 10–15 actuators. The solenoids contributed to a significant power draw during operation for fluid routing and handling, over 10 Watts, equating to 100 s if not 1000 s of Joules of energy per sample measurement. Using this much energy per sample limits the number of measurements possible per deployment with current battery capacities on small autonomous underwater vehicles and drifting floats. Incorporating rugged passive valves can reduce the energy demand for fluid handling on microfluidic devices. </p>

<p>Passive valves require no external power or interface and most often use simple mechanical biases, like an elastomeric membrane, or some other physical property to restrict fluid flow in one direction. The Tesla valve, for example, uses an in-channel geometric pattern to increase fluidic resistance in one direction and not the other. Passive valves can also be made by exploiting capillary pressure differences in microchannels, or by using an air bladder to create a capillary stop-valve. Other types of valves include using comb-like structures or centrifugal elastic valves. Flap valves are perhaps the most common and use a thin membrane that seals against a rigid body in one direction, and have freedom to deflect in the other. Although flap valves generally seal well against reverse flow, they are still subject to leakage at low flow rates and do not have a strong seal in an unbiased state. Furthermore, such membrane valves are usually made up of at least two distinct materials, requiring unique bonding procedures between layers. This introduces extra manufacturing equipment and methods, such as UV exposure/oxygen plasma/chemical surface modifications and are prone to sealing failures if stringent quality controls are not implemented. Alternatively, a few researchers have implemented ball and cage valves based on the Starr–Edwards valve used in heart surgery. When forward flow is applied, the ball is dislodged from a seat and retained by the cage. In reverse flow, the ball is pushed into the seat, creating a seal. However, like flap valves, ball valves show appreciable leakage, on the order of 100 µL min−1 when a reverse pressure of 25 kPa is applied. Backflow is unacceptable and must me be minimized on any in situ marine sensor, as reagent cross-contamination reduces the integrity and accuracy of the measurements. </p>

<p>Many microfluidic applications use magnetic fields to implement on-chip actuation without direct physical coupling. Micro-magnetofluids, for example, can be manipulated with an external magnetic field to perform on-chip mixing, pumping, or even droplet formation. Yamahata et al. and Shen et al. have explored the use of permanent magnets encased in a deformable membrane to act as a piston for a solenoid-based micropump. The reported systems use oscillating magnetic fields to drive an on-chip piston with two ball-style check valves to pump fluid. Other groups in the biomedical field have researched magnetic hydrogels to create magnetically actuated microvalves. These systems, however, are intended for use in benchtop applications and are not likely to withstand extreme pressure environments. Furthermore, the valves require more than 3 s to fully seal, which exceeds the activation time requirement for many applications. Single use drug delivery systems have used permanent magnets as external valve actuators but are targeted for limited and disposable applications. Magnetorheological fluids can be actuated using a permanent magnet to seal a microchannel. These innovative valves, however, are made with an intermediary PDMS layer, and partially seal 80–90% of the channel at extremely low flow rates (&lt;0.1 µL min−1). Other common valve designs use magnetized polymers to create magnetically actuated membrane valves. Valves of this sort, however, require the fabrication and bonding of specialized polymers. Many of the reported magnetic valves in the literature, as listed above, are activated with external linear translation stages or with energy intensive electronic systems. Passively biased magnetic valves are much less common but have potential for use in power restricted applications. </p>
</text>
