<text id="autogum_bio_doc441" title="Bartholomew Gilbert" shortTile="bartholomew-gilbert" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-07-09" dateModified="2019-09-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bartholomew_Gilbert" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Bartholomew Gilbert</head><p>
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Captain_(nautical)">Captain</ref> <hi rend="bold">Bartholomew Gilbert</hi> was an English <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sailor">mariner</ref> who in 1602 served as co-captain on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Age_of_Exploration">first recorded European expedition</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cape_Cod">Cape Cod</ref>.  His decisions resulted in that expedition's failure to establish a colony there.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Voyage to Cape Cod</head>
<p>Gilbert served aboard <hi rend="italic">The Concord</hi>, a small <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barque">bark</ref> which sailed out of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dartmouth,_Devon">Dartmouth, Devon</ref>, to establish a colony in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_England">New England</ref> (which was then known as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virginia">Northern Virginia</ref> and was considered a part of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colony_of_Virginia">Colony of Virginia</ref>).  The ship's captain was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bartholomew_Gosnold">Bartholomew Gosnold</ref>, an experienced seaman who had sailed with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_Raleigh">Walter Raleigh</ref> and who was related to Gilbert on Gosnold's father's side.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The Concord</hi> had thirty-two men on board and sailed due west from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Azores">Azores</ref> to New England, arriving in May 1602 at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cape_Elizabeth">Cape Elizabeth</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maine">Maine</ref> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/43rd_parallel_north">latitude 43 degrees</ref>) and skirted the coastline for several days before anchoring in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/York_Harbor">York Harbor</ref>, Maine, on 14 May 1602.  The next day, they sailed into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Provincetown_Harbor">Provincetown Harbor</ref> and named Cape Cod.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Gabriel_Archer's_diary-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Following the coastline for several days, they discovered and touched at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martha's_Vineyard">Martha's Vineyard</ref>, entered <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buzzard's_Bay">Buzzard's Bay</ref> (which they called Gosnold's Hope), and established a small post on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth's_Island">Elizabeth's Island</ref>, which is now called <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cuttyhunk">Cuttyhunk Island</ref> and is part of the town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gosnold,_Massachusetts">Gosnold</ref>.  In nineteen days they built a fort and storehouse on an islet and began to trade with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Massachusett">Massachusett</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fur">furs</ref>, skins, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sassafras">sassafras</ref> plant.  They sowed wheat, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barley">barley</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peas">peas</ref>, and in fourteen days the young plants had sprung nine inches and more.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-humilitypress.org-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>They planned to leave Gosnold and some of the crew to start a colony while Gilbert returned to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Devon">Devon</ref> for more supplies. However, when it became known that Gilbert had provided insufficient provisions to overwinter (their provisions, after division, would have lasted only six weeks), all hands decided to return to England with him.  They made a very short voyage of five weeks and landed at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exmouth,_Devon">Exmouth</ref> on 23 July. Their freight realised a great profit, the sassafras alone selling for £336 a ton.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-humilitypress.org-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>A notable account of the voyage, written by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Brereton">John Brereton</ref>, one of the gentlemen adventurers, was published in 1602,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> and this helped in popularising subsequent voyages of exploration and colonisation of the northeast seaboard of North America. A second account by Gabriel Archer was not published until over 20 years later.  Although the mission failed to establish a colony, the attempt is commemorated by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_World_Tapestry">New World Tapestry</ref> and Gilbert is one of the people represented thereon.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Parsons-6">[6]</ref></p>
<head>Voyage to Virginia</head>
<p>In July 1603, Gilbert returned to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Americas">the Americas</ref>. Setting anchor in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chesapeake_Bay">Chesapeake Bay</ref>, Gilbert and four crewmen went ashore to search for the missing members of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roanoke_Colony">Roanoke Colony</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-HudsonTesser1994-7">[7]</ref> They subsequently ran afoul of and were killed by a group of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Algonquian_peoples">Algonquians</ref> on 29 July.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Zandt2008-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>The date of this historic landing is represented in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seal_of_Northampton_County,_Virginia">Seal of Northampton County, Virginia</ref>.  Not until 1607 did the English successfully establish <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jamestown,_Virginia">Jamestown, Virginia</ref>, their first colony in what is now the United States.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref></p>
</text>
