<text id="autogum_voyage_doc439" title="Chiba" shortTile="chiba" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=7097" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Chiba</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.city.chiba.jp/somu/shichokoshitsu/kokusai/portal-en.html">Chiba</ref></hi> (千葉) is the largest city in <ref target="Chiba%20%28prefecture%29">Chiba</ref> prefecture, <ref target="Japan">Japan</ref>. Practically speaking, it can be considered a large suburb of <ref target="Tokyo">Tokyo</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Oyumino</hi> is not so big and is more a suburb surrounded by a lot of nature. There are many beautiful parks and nature trails. By contrast, development of Oyumino has been proceeded at the same time. Every year, the number of new housings and shopping centres increases rapidly.</p>

<p>Chiba is where the anime Ore no Imouto ga Konna ni Kawaii Wake ga Nai (俺の妹がこんなに可愛いわけがない, lit. My Little Sister Can't Be This Cute) takes place, and you can see the Chiba Urban Monorail in the opening of the anime.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>The JR Narita Line links Chiba directly to <ref target="Tokyo%20Narita%20Airport">Narita</ref>'s international airport. A few N'EX limited expresses stop at Chiba on their way to <ref target="Tokyo">Tokyo</ref>, but usually the ordinary rapid service trains are a better bet.</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>Train is the obvious means of arrival, as a dense web of routes links Chiba to Tokyo and points in the vicinity.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> The <hi rend="bold">JR Sōbu Rapid Line</hi> (総武快速線) runs from <ref target="Tokyo%20Station">Tokyo Station</ref>'s underground platforms to Chiba station via Kinshichō and Tsudanuma. Rapid trains reach Chiba in approximately 40 minutes at a cost of ¥620; you have the option, especially during the evening rush, of shelling out an additional ¥810 for a reserved seat on a limited express train, which make the run to Chiba in as little as 25 minutes.</item>
<item> The <hi rend="bold">JR Chuō-Sōbu Local Line</hi> (中央・総武線「各駅停車」) runs directly across the Yamanote Line loop, via <ref target="Tokyo/Shinjuku">Shinjuku</ref> and <ref target="Tokyo/Akihabara">Akihabara</ref>. Local trains take about 70 minutes to reach Chiba from Shinjuku on a regular service; this is shaved a little if you change to a Sobu Rapid train at Kinshicho. In either case the fare is ¥780.</item>
<item> The <hi rend="bold">JR Keiyō Line</hi> (京葉線) runs from <ref target="Tokyo%20Station">Tokyo Station</ref> to Chiba Minato and Soga stations along the coast (45 minutes, ¥740), via Maihama (<ref target="Tokyo%20Disneyland">Tokyo Disneyland</ref>), Nishi-Funabashi and Kaihin-Makuhari.</item>
<item> The private <hi rend="bold">Keisei Chiba Line</hi> (京成千葉線) runs into Chiba-Chuō (千葉中央) station from Tsudanuma station on the Keisei Main Line (from <ref target="Tokyo/Ueno">Ueno</ref> and Nippori).</item>
</list>


<head>By bus</head>
<p>Airport Limousine buses link Chiba to <ref target="Haneda">Haneda</ref> and <ref target="Tokyo%20Narita%20Airport">Narita</ref> Airports.</p>

<head>By monorail</head>
<p>The two lines of the suspended <hi rend="bold">Chiba Urban Monorail</hi> (千葉都市モノレール) <ref target="http://www.chiba-monorail.co.jp/"></ref>, the world's longest suspended monorail, are an attraction in themselves, connecting the port (千葉みなと <hi rend="italic">Chiba Minato</hi>) to Chiba station and then branching out to the northwest and northeast.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Chiba Port Tower</hi> (千葉ポートタワー). 10 minutes on foot from monorail and Keiyo line Chiba Minato station. Towers like this are a fixture of any self-respecting Japanese city, and here the observation deck (112m) offers views of the surrounding industrial wastelands and container docks, at least for a kilometer or two until they fade off in the smog. There is also a curious display of stuffed fish mounted on sticks in a simulated ocean environment downstairs; the simulation is needed since heavily polluted Chiba Bay hasn't sustained anything above seaweed for quite a while. Entry ¥410, open daily from 9AM to 7PM (or 9PM in summer).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Chiba Castle</hi> (千葉城 chiba-jō ; 亥鼻城 inohana-jō) (about 5–10 minutes walk from the Kenchomae Chiba Urban Monorail station). A reconstruction, but it does look quite cool- just try to ignore the fluorescent tubes inside! It hosts the city Folk Museum. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Aoba no Mori Koen</hi> (青葉の森公園) (10mins walk from the Keisei Chiba line station Chibadera). (<hi rend="bold">Blue Leaf Forest Park</hi>). Nothing too spectacular, but during the Sakura (Cherry blossom) season a nice place to get away from the concrete jungle.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Comic markets</hi>. Very great place for anime likers and otaku! There are many anime events held and also there are anime shops. Foreigners would surely love this place. Just stop by and see many kinds of Japanese animes.</item>
</list>


<head>Kaihin-Makuhari</head>
<p>On the western outskirts of the city in Mihama Ward and accessible on the JR Keiyo line (Kaihin-Makuhari Station, 海浜幕張駅), this is a showcase "city of the future", similar to Tokyo's <ref target="Tokyo/Odaiba">Odaiba</ref> but grander and more artificial in scope.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Makuhari Messe</hi> (幕張メッセ). Also known as the <hi rend="bold">Nippon Convention Center</hi>, this is the largest convention center in the Tokyo region. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Makuhari Techno Garden</hi> (幕張テクノガーデン). An impressive complex of shopping malls, restaurants and office towers; white tile, glass and polished steel with atmospheric lighting and realistic plastic plants, with footsteps echoing in the quiet walkways and aerial bridges.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Chiba Marine Stadium</hi> (千葉マリンスタジアム). Home to the <hi rend="bold">Chiba Lotte Marines</hi> baseball team. Its 30,000 seats also host events and converts, including the annual <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.summersonic.com/">Summer Sonic Festival</ref></hi> in August, drawing big-name musical acts from around the globe. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mitsui Outlet Park Makuhari</hi> (三井アウトレットパーク 幕張) (close to the Kaihin-makuhari Station). There are lots of shops including such major brands as Coach, Edwin, Nike, and so on. During special events or holiday seasons like Christmas the sales draw large crowds. For people who want to enjoy shopping with their pets, some shops have special areas that pets can enjoy.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Costco(コストコ幕張倉庫店)</hi>In Japan, there are few Costcos, and one of them is in Makuhari. This way of displaying items is uncommon in Japan, so many people are interested in it and go there. Entering the building can be done without a membership card if entering at a busy time; the only time memberships are absolutely checked for is at the cash register. For some Japanese, the items are too big or too much, so people like to divide the items with others. To get there, you can take bus from Kaihin-makuhari or Shin-Narashino Station. It costs ¥100 and takes 5 minutes.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bay Town</hi> (幕張ベイタウン) (Heiwa Koutsu Bus or Keisei Bus from Kaihin-Makuhari, ¥150). The view of town is very modern and constructions are very colorful. It's not so common in this area, so some TV shows in Japan use this town as a location. You can buy houses or rent them.</item>
</list>


<head>Oyumino</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Four seasons roads</hi> (四季の道) There are four nature trails named Spring Road, Summer Road, Autumn Road and Winter Road. If you go to Spring Road in spring, you can enjoy beautiful flowers and plants bloom in spring. Some people just walk through and some people jog in these roads.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sakura Park</hi> (さくら公園) is a park which has many beautiful cherry blossom trees.When spring comes,a lot of people come to enjoy seeing them.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Izumiya park</hi> (泉谷公園) has fireflies in this park, but you cannot see them often because they have been protected carefully.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Oyumino fireworks festival</hi> (おゆみ池花火大会) is one of the biggest festivals in Oyumino and is held in August every year. About 3500 fireworks are launched, and countless viewers enjoy dancing and having traditional foods there.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Rokutsu Temple</hi> (六通神社) was built in 1677 (the Edo era). At that time, many farmers tried to develop this area and building the temple was one of their activities. It is not so huge but has been loved by local people. In September 2007, Chiba was hit by a typhoon, and the temple was destroyed, but people living in the area decided to use the community chest for its restoration. Finally, it was repaired and reborn by local people. It has been a symbol of Oyumino and is still cherished.</item>
</list>
</text>
