<text id="autogum_whow_doc094" title="Prevent a Computer from Waking Up from External Devices" shortTile="prevent-computer" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-09-09" dateModified="2019-03-27" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Prevent-a-Computer-from-Waking-Up-from-External-Devices" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Prevent a Computer from Waking Up from External Devices</head><p>If you've experienced your computer suddenly turning itself on after you've put it to sleep or you've just shut it down, you may need to investigate what’s causing it to wake up. The common causes that wake up your computer are hardware devices and scheduled tasks set to wake up the computer. You might not even know that this has been happening especially if you have closed the lid of your laptop and didn't notice the lights blinking again.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Determining the Possible Causes for the Wake Up</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Access the Command Prompt. Click on the Start menu and look for the Command Prompt application. This is usually found under the Accessories folder. Click on it to launch it, and a window with a DOS-like environment will be opened. <figure rend="Prevent a Computer from Waking Up from External Devices Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Check the last wake trigger. On the Command Prompt, type in “powercfg –lastwake” and then press the Enter key. The Wake History details will be displayed. <figure rend="Prevent a Computer from Waking Up from External Devices Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If the Wake History Count is more than 0, that means your computer was woken up by something.</item></list></item>
<item>Note the wake source. If the Wake History Count is not 0, the Wake Source details will also be displayed. The Wake Source will state what caused your computer to wake up. <figure rend="Prevent a Computer from Waking Up from External Devices Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, if a device attached to a USB port was the source, USB Root Hub will be displayed.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Preventing Devices from Waking Up the Computer</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Access the Command Prompt. <figure rend="Prevent a Computer from Waking Up from External Devices Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Check devices. To see the list of hardware devices that can wake up your computer, type in “powercfg -devicequery wake_armed” on the Command Prompt and then press the Enter key. The list of hardware devices will be displayed. <figure rend="Prevent a Computer from Waking Up from External Devices Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Some possible devices that can wake your computer include, but is not limited to, your keyboard and your mouse.</item></list></item>
<item>Note the devices. Take note of the list of hardware devices that can wake up your computer. You will need to configure them properly in the Device Manager. <figure rend="Prevent a Computer from Waking Up from External Devices Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Open the Control Panel. Click on the Start menu and click on “Control Panel.” The Control Panel applets will be displayed. <figure rend="Prevent a Computer from Waking Up from External Devices Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Open the Device Manager. Browse through the items under the Control Panel and look for “Device Manager.” Click on it. The Device Manager will be opened and the list of hardware devices for your computer will be displayed. <figure rend="Prevent a Computer from Waking Up from External Devices Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Look for the devices. Navigate through the Device Manager until you find the possible devices that may cause your computer to wake up. Click on the triangle icon beside each device to expand the category. <figure rend="Prevent a Computer from Waking Up from External Devices Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Open the Device Properties. Right-click on the device you want. Select “Properties” from the menu to bring out the device’s properties. <figure rend="Prevent a Computer from Waking Up from External Devices Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Disable Wake Up property. From the Device Properties window, select the Power Management tab. Untick “Allow this device to wake up the computer” option. <figure rend="Prevent a Computer from Waking Up from External Devices Step 11 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Click “OK” to save your changes and exit. The selected device will no longer wake up the computer.</item></list></item>
<item>Disable all other devices’ wake up properties. Repeat Steps 6 to 8 to disable all possible devices that can wake up your computer. If left enabled, sudden or accidental movements that affect these devices can wake up your computer.  <figure rend="Prevent a Computer from Waking Up from External Devices Step 12 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Preventing Tasks from Waking Up the Computer</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open Command Prompt. <figure rend="Prevent a Computer from Waking Up from External Devices Step 13 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Check wake timers from tasks. To see the list of scheduled tasks that have set wake timers, type in “powercfg –wake timers” on the Command Prompt and then press the Enter key. The list of scheduled tasks will be displayed. <figure rend="Prevent a Computer from Waking Up from External Devices Step 14 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Wake timers wake up your computer at the defined time for it to run the scheduled tasks. This can be useful if you want to run certain tasks on schedule, even without you monitoring them.</item></list></item>
<item>Note the tasks. Take note of the list of scheduled tasks that can wake up your computer. <figure rend="Prevent a Computer from Waking Up from External Devices Step 15 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Uninstall programs or adjust schedules. From the list of scheduled tasks, check which ones you really need. Uninstall or remove the ones you don’t need, and adjust the schedules for the ones you do. <figure rend="Prevent a Computer from Waking Up from External Devices Step 16 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Set a schedule that’s good for you and your computer. Adjusting the scheduled tasks can be done from the Windows task scheduler or directly from each of the programs.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Disabling Wake Timers</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open Control Panel. Click on the Start menu and click on “Control Panel.” The Control Panel applets will be displayed. <figure rend="Prevent a Computer from Waking Up from External Devices Step 17 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Open “Power Options.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> Browse through the items under the Control Panel and look for “Power Options.” Click on it. The Power Options will be opened. <figure rend="Prevent a Computer from Waking Up from External Devices Step 18 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Change the plan settings. Your computer’s power plans will be displayed. Click on the “Change plan settings” link beside the power plan you’d like to modify. <figure rend="Prevent a Computer from Waking Up from External Devices Step 19 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Change advanced power settings. Look for the “Change advanced power settings” link and click on it. The Advanced settings for the Power Options will be displayed. <figure rend="Prevent a Computer from Waking Up from External Devices Step 20 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Disable wake timers. Navigate through the list of settings until you find “Sleep.” Click on it to expand its properties. <figure rend="Prevent a Computer from Waking Up from External Devices Step 21.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Under Sleep, click on “Allow wake timers” to expand it further. Set both properties under it to Disable.</item>
<item>No wake timers will now be able to wake up your computer.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
