<text id="autogum_news_doc034" title="2007 FIFA U-17 World Cup: Ghana vs. Germany" shortTile="-fifa-u-world-cup" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-08-23" dateModified="2018-04-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2007_FIFA_U-17_World_Cup%3A_Ghana_vs._Germany" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>2007 FIFA U-17 World Cup: Ghana vs. Germany</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 23, 2007</hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cheonan">Cheonan</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South%20Korea">South Korea</ref></p>
<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ghana">Ghana</ref>
<hi rend="bold">2</hi>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi>
<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">Germany</ref>
<caption><hi rend="italic">Match Stats</hi></caption>
<hi rend="bold">Attendance</hi>
7,516
<hi rend="bold">Goalscorers for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ghana">Ghana</ref></hi>
Osei (52') &amp; Adams (53')
<hi rend="bold">Goalscorers for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Germany">Germany</ref></hi>
Bigalke (5') &amp; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toni%20Kroos">Kroos</ref> (12' &amp; 27')
<hi rend="bold">Bookings (Ghana)</hi>
Boampong, Adu &amp; Nortey (Yellow (3))
<hi rend="bold">Bookings (Germany)</hi>
Erb, Rausch, Dowidat &amp; Sauerbier (Yellow (4)), Rausch (Yellow-Red (1))
<p>Germany have qualified for a place in the Round of 16 at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2007%20FIFA%20U-17%20World%20Cup">2007 FIFA U-17 World Cup</ref> by defeating Ghana 3-2 in their 2nd Group F match at the Cheonan Sports Complex today.</p>
<p>The Germans put the Africans under pressure from the first whistle and were rewarded for their positive attitude by a 5th minute goal from Sascha Bigalke. The outstanding playmaker <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bayern%20Munich">Bayern Munich</ref>'s Toni Kroos increased Germany's lead in the 12th minute when his free-kick from 20 yards out 1st hit the post before bouncing in off Ghana keeper Joseph Addo. Kroos made it 3-0 for Germany in the 27th minute after a through ball from Bigalke.</p>
<p>Ransford Osei and Sadick Adams got a goal a piece in the 52nd minute and 53rd minute respectively to make it 3-2..</p>
<p>Germany's Konstantin Rausch was shown a red card in the 2nd half, but they held on for the win.</p>
<head id="Quotes">Quotes</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Heiko Herrlich (GER)</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Germany coach:</hi>
"We were magnificent in the first half. We could have scored five or six against a team of the calibre of Ghana. We just had that little bit of luck in the end, but even when we were down to ten men, the boys fought for each other. When you look at the game as a whole, I think it was a more than deserved win, despite the tight finish. Toni Kroos led the team superbly and took on more responsibility when we went down to ten men. He is a true captain."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sellas Tetteh Teivi (GHA)</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Ghana coach:</hi>
"Of course we are disappointed. In the second half, we showed the form we were aiming for in the first half. We definitely need to talk about that and change it for the future. We have to win our last game against Colombia now. If we get a second win we'll definitely reach the Round of 16."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Toni Kroos (GER)</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Germany midfielder:</hi>
"We played fantastic football in the first 20 minutes and created a lot of chances. After getting into such a good position, we were then focusing on not conceding a goal. The two goals right at the start of the second half threw us off our game, but we'd got back on track again by the end."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sadick Adams (GHA)</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Ghana forward:</hi>
"We are very disappointed. We were determined to win this game, but we couldn't find our form in the first half. It was a great comeback in the second half, but it just wasn't enough. We really need to win our last game now. We have certainly learned a lot from this match."</p>
<head id="Standings">Standings</head>
<head id="Group_F">Group F</head>
<p><hi rend="italic">Standings after Thursday's games</hi></p>
Pos
Team
GP
W
D
L
F
A
GD
Pts
1Colombia2110835<hi rend="bold">4</hi>
2Germany2110651<hi rend="bold">4</hi>
3Ghana2101642<hi rend="bold">3</hi>
4Trinidad &amp; Tobago200219-8<hi rend="bold">0</hi>
<head id="Standings_for_Top_4_3rd_place_teams">Standings for Top 4 3rd place teams</head>
<p><hi rend="italic">Standings after Thursday's games</hi></p>
Teams
GP
W
D
L
GF
GA
GD
Pts
Ghana
2101642<hi rend="bold">3</hi>
Belgium
210134-1<hi rend="bold">3</hi>
Togo
2020110<hi rend="bold">2</hi>
France
201123-1<hi rend="bold">1</hi>
Syria
201112-1<hi rend="bold">1</hi>
North Korea
201127-5<hi rend="bold">1</hi>
</text>
