<text id="autogum_bio_doc489" title="Thomas Pope (actor)" shortTile="thomas-pope-actor" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-20" dateModified="2018-08-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Pope_%28actor%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Thomas Pope (actor)</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">Thomas Pope</hi> (died 1603) was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English_Renaissance_theatre">Elizabethan</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Actor">actor</ref>, a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Chamberlain's_Men">Lord Chamberlain's Men</ref> and a colleague of  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Shakespeare">William Shakespeare</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> Pope was a "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comedian">comedian</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Acrobatics">acrobat</ref>."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Beginnings</head>
<p>Nothing is known of Pope's early life. He was one of the English players who toured Denmark and Saxony in 1586–87, along with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Bryan_(16th-century_actor)">George Bryan</ref>, another future Chamberlain's man. He was in the production of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Seven_Deadly_Sins_(play)"><hi rend="italic">The Seven Deadly Sins</hi></ref> c. 1591, which was performed by a combination of personnel from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Strange's_Men">Lord Strange's Men</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Admiral's_Men">Admiral's Men</ref>, and which starred <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Alleyn">Edward Alleyn</ref> and included Bryan, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Burbage">Richard Burbage</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Augustine_Phillips">Augustine Phillips</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Cowley">Richard Cowley</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Sinklo">John Sinklo</ref>, all soon-to-be Lord Chamberlain's Men. Pope toured with Lord Strange's Men under Edward Alleyn in 1593, with most of the same personnel.</p>
<head>Chamberlain's</head>
<p>Pope was most likely an original member of the Lord Chamberlain's Men at their re-constitution in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1594_in_literature">1594</ref>, along with Shakespeare, Burbage, and the others. He was a figure of some significance in the early phase of the company's history, in that he and Heminges were the payees for their Court performances — a responsibility that would have been given only to trusted members. Though no information has survived on his specific roles, it is thought that his physique and style most suited the comic character of stout, braggartly cowards, such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Falstaff">Falstaff</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sir_Toby_Belch">Sir Toby Belch</ref>, although he is also conjectured to have performed in dramatic roles, such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mercutio">Mercutio</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shylock">Shylock</ref>. He was also cast in the two <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ben_Jonson">Ben Jonson</ref> plays acted by the company in the late 1590s, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Every_Man_in_His_Humour">Every Man in His Humour</ref></hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1598_in_literature">1598</ref>) and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Every_Man_Out_of_His_Humour">Every Man Out of His Humour</ref></hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1599_in_literature">1599</ref>). In 1599 he also became one of the original sharers in the new <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Globe_Theatre">Globe Theatre</ref>. He was no longer part of the company when they became the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King's_Men_(playing_company)">King's Men</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1603_in_literature">1603</ref>; he might have been retired by then, and in fact died in that year. Like some other actors and members of his troupe (Shakespeare; Phillips), Pope lived in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Southwark">Southwark</ref>, near the theatres; he is thought to have remained unmarried.</p>
<head>Post mortem</head>
<p>Pope's last will and testament was dated 22 July 1603 (and probated on 13 February 1604). He left legacies to two other actors, one of whom was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Gough_(actor)">Robert Gough</ref>, an actor with the Lord Chamberlain's Men who continued with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King's_Men_(playing_company)">King's Men</ref> after 1603. The other was a John Edmans, or Edmonds. Pope left Gough and Edmans "all my wearing apparel, and all my arms, to be equally divided between them."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> Pope also left his share in the Globe, and a share in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Curtain_Theatre">Curtain Theatre</ref>, to a Mary Clark; in 1612 the Globe share was owned by a John and Mary Edmans — she, presumably, being the former Mary Clark.</p>
<p>The fact that Pope owned a share in the Curtain Theatre, where the Lord Chamberlain's Men had acted in the 1597–99 era, is significant for an understanding of an important facet of the development of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English_Renaissance_theatre">English Renaissance theatre</ref>. [For the importance of the Curtain shares, see: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Underwood_(actor)">John Underwood</ref>.]</p>
</text>
