<text id="autogum_interview_doc278" title="part0_2008-09 Wikipedia for Schools goes online" shortTile="part-wikipedia-schools" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-10-22" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2008-09_Wikipedia_for_Schools_goes_online" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>2008-09 Wikipedia for Schools goes online</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 22, 2008</hi></p>
 This article mentions the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Foundation">Wikimedia Foundation</ref>, one of its projects, or people related to it. <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> is a project of the Wikimedia Foundation.
<p>Monday saw the latest edition of the vetted version of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia">Wikipedia</ref></hi>, which is aimed at educational use, go quietly online. The extensively revised version covers over five thousand topics, targeting the eight to seventeen years age group. Partnerships with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shuttleworth%20Foundation">Shuttleworth Foundation</ref> and the Hole in the Wall project will see it distributed in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/South_Africa">South Africa</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/India">India</ref> as well as copies being available globally via the offices of SOS Children UK's umbrella organisation, SOS Kinderdorf worldwide.</p>
<p>First launched in 2006 as a 4,000 article edition, the extract of <hi rend="italic">Wikipedia</hi> has employed hi-tech distribution methods, as well as offering a website version which has steadily climbed up in ranking to above other reviewed <hi rend="italic">Wikipedia</hi> rivals and copies; the 2007 version was available on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BitTorrent">BitTorrent</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/peer%20to%20peer">peer to peer</ref> network to keep distribution costs down and was equivalent to a fifteen-volume printed encyclopedia. Monday's release is compared to a twenty-volume print edition.</p>
<hi rend="bold">Our goal is to make Wikipedia accessible to as many people as possible around the world, and SOS Children is a great partner that helps us make that happen.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—Sue Gardner, Wikimedia Executive Director</p>
<p>Key to the process for selecting articles is the English National Curriculum and similar educational standards around the world. The initial vision was to bring this wealth of knowledge to schools where access to the Internet was poor or unavailable, but copies of <hi rend="italic">Wikipedia for Schools</hi> can be found on many first world school intranets and web servers. Among the compelling reasons to adopt the project are the vetting and additional study materials which overcome the oft-publicised concerns many educators have with the million article plus <hi rend="italic">Wikipedia</hi> that anyone can edit.</p>
<p>In today's press release announcing the launch, Wikimedia Foundation Executive Director <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sue%20Gardner">Sue Gardner</ref> expressed delight at seeing the project bring out a new version, "Our goal is to make Wikipedia accessible to as many people as possible around the world, and SOS Children is a great partner that helps us make that happen. Wikipedia is released under a free content license so that individuals and institutions can easily adapt, reuse and customize its content: we encourage others, like SOS Children, to do exactly that."</p>
<p>Running 192 schools in the developing world, SOS Children sees <hi rend="italic">Wikipedia for Schools</hi> as a key piece in fulfilling the educational aspect of their mission. SOS Children's Chairwoman, Mary Cockcroft gave us an introduction and, a <hi rend="italic">Wikipedia</hi> administrator himself, the charity's CEO Andrew Cates spoke to <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> at length about the project.</p>
<figure><caption>Wikinews</caption></figure><p> You are part of SOS-Kinderdorf International, can you explain a little about how this works in terms of distributing funds raised in the UK and involving UK citizens in work outside the country?</p>
</text>
