<text id="autogum_voyage_doc529" title="West Lombok" shortTile="west-lombok" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=39066" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>West Lombok</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">West Lombok</hi> is a region of <ref target="Lombok">Lombok</ref>, <ref target="Indonesia">Indonesia</ref>.</p>

<head>Cities</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> - the largest city in Lombok and the provincial capital of West Nusa Tenggara</item>
<item> - historic port city and site of the previous international airport serving Lombok, however those airport facilities have now been moved to Bandara Internasional Lombok near Praya, and the airport has been closed to airline operations.</item>
<item> Cakranegara - the main commercial area on the eastern flank of Mataram</item>
<item> - the main tourist strip, including the neighboring beaches of <hi rend="bold">Mangsit</hi>, Klui and Batu Bolong</item>
<item> - on the north west coast including the newly developing areas of Medana and Sire beach, administrative capital of the North Lombok Regency</item>
<item> - little harbor servicing the Gili Islands</item>
<item> Pemenang - a local service centre and northern gateway to the Pusak pass and Monkey forest, support township for Bangsal and Gili islands</item>
<item> Gerung - administrative capital of the West Lombok Regency, to the south of the provincial capital of Mataram</item>
<item> - non-descript harbour town for the larger vehicular and passenger carrying ferries to and from <ref target="Bali">Bali</ref></item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> — <ref target="Gili%20Air">Gili Air</ref>, <ref target="Gili%20Meno">Gili Meno</ref>, <ref target="Gili%20Trawangan">Gili Trawangan</ref>, these tiny islands of the west coast are popular with divers, backpackers, heodonists and those looking for a relaxing island holiday. Each island has a different flavour and tempo, research well for a good fit and if you get it wrong just change islands, they are very close to each other and to the mainland for day trips or further exploration</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sire beach</hi> at Tanjung — developing into a location for palacious fully serviced rental villas and intimate 5-star resorts.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kosaido Golf Club</hi> on the Sire Peninsula in Tanjung</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Medana Bay Marina</hi> — in Tanjung, 18 holes on gentle undulating greens surrounded by rustic villages and coconut groves</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Monkey forest</hi> — at Pusuk pass on the road between Gunung Sari and Pemenang, an alternative route northward from Mataram</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Old town and port of <ref target="Ampenan">Ampenan</ref></hi>, the inlet is still in use for fishing boats and Lombok's maritime oil and fuel terminal and storage tanks are sited on the foreshore. Has a forlorn but interesting seaside esplanade that has seen better days</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Gunung Sari</hi> — the mountain overlooks the northern flanks of the city, it has a traditional market and is the gateway to the Pusuk pass</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Batu Bolong</hi> — means 'rock with a hole in it', one of many wave eroded rocks with holes in them along the west coast but this one is an important Hindu site</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kerandangan beach</hi> — popular spot for satays and beach activities on Sundays, has a strring of traditional thatched warungs along the beach. Far back in the long valley behind the beach there are a few rental villas and as a gateway to the forest there is a lineal conservation park</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mangsit beach</hi> — the quieter and more civilised end of Senggigi, a lovely beach and good range of hotels from budget to boutique resort and has the full scale 4-star Lombok Holiday Resort and the popular Qunci boutique resort right on the beach</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Klui beach</hi> — even quieter again and site to a new small boutique resort hotel, has a lovely beach popular on Sundays with local people eating satay and playing on the beach</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lendang Guar</hi> — quiet scenic beach immediately north of Klui beach and Mangsit beach, 3 hotels, one on the beach and 2 on the main road</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Malimbu beach</hi> — has spectacular views from the headlands at either end, popular with sunset photographers</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Nipah beach</hi> — a lovely clean bay with traditional fishing activities and a stunning mountain backdrop</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The scenic west coast highway</hi> — with beautiful bays, headlands and mountain framed rice fields to the north, a must for a motorbike enthusiast</item>
</list>


<head>Understand</head>

<p>West Lombok is the principal area of tourist activity and endeavour in Lombok. It has the most facilities including hotels, restaurants, tour companies, car and motorbike rental operators, western and locally oriented bars, clubs and restaurants.</p>
<p>The focus of this activity is upon the township Senggigi including it's lineal satellites along the coast north to the quieter and pretty Mangsit beach and Klui beach, and south to Batu Bolong, Batu Layar and Monton</p>

<p>The Senggigi area and in particular the township itself serves as the principal gateway to the other attractions of Lombok northward up the west coast including the Gili Islands and to Tanjung with it's upmarket resorts and rental villas at Sire Beach and Medana beach. Tanjung in the north of the district is the gateway to the North Lombok region including Senaru, Mount Rinjani and further on to the historic villages of Bayan and Sembalun in adjoining North Lombok.</p>

<head>Talk</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Bahasa Sasak</hi> is the language of the Sasak peoples of Lombok.</p>
<p>In western Lombok the local people speak in varying dialects of the indigenous language of Lombok. Informal versions of Bahasa Indonesian are also spoken by many people especially amongst the younger generations who may also introduce elements of Javanese or Jakarta slang into their conversations. In the hotels, larger shops and offices of the district people will normally speak in more formal versions of <ref target="Bahasa%20Indonesia">Bahasa Indonesia</ref>. In the tourism areas along the west coast some people may speak English, especially those associated in some way with tourism activities. In tourist venues such as hotels and restaurants catering to overseas tourists there is more likelihood of English speakers being available most especially in the major hotels, restaurants and other establishments.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>Lombok International Airport ( LOP ) is located near the city of Praya on in <ref target="South%20Lombok">South Lombok</ref>, and is approximately 10-60 km from the various parts of West Lombok (40 km southeast of Mataram). The airport is covered in the <ref target="Lombok%23By%20plane">main Lombok article</ref>.</p>

<ref target="Lombok%23Get%20from%20the%20airport"><hi rend="bold">Airport taxis</hi></ref> travel into West Lombok and are available to arriving passengers at Lombok International Airport (<hi rend="italic">Bandara Internasional Lombok</hi>). The taxis providing services to and from the airport use a taxi meter. Payment of an <hi rend="italic">Airport Taxi Service Charge</hi> is required for taxis departing the airport. The fee for West Lombok destinations is Rp 17,000, payable at a dedicated Airport Taksi desk at both the domestic and the international terminals.

<p><hi rend="bold">Airport pick-up</hi>, the established hotels and resorts of the West Lombok area may offer pick ups and transfers to and from the airport or other locations in Lombok. You will need to enquire at the hotels for this service and ensure you book ahead.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">DAMRI</hi> public airport bus service provides a scheduled air-conditioned service in late model buses operating between the airport and Mandalika central bus terminal on the eastern outskirts of Mataram (Rp 15,000/person) and to Senggigi on the west coast (Rp 25,000/person).</p>
</text>
