<text id="autogum_interview_doc530" title="part3_Billy West, voice of Ren and Stimpy, Futurama, on the rough start that shaped his life" shortTile="partbilly-west-voice" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-13" dateModified="2013-06-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Billy_West%2C_voice_of_Ren_and_Stimpy%2C_Futurama%2C_on_the_rough_start_that_shaped_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  They pander. Slowly they take away the aspects of what made those characters who and what they were. In other words, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cartoon">cartoons</ref> contained sometimes gratuitous violence with the squash and stretch animation. Sometimes it was gratuitous. But that was only an aspect of the cartoon. When you start stripping away those things that made it a full dimension character, you’re going to have Xeroxes of it in every way including creativity. The worst mistake Warner Brothers ever did was make all these characters friends, because then you took away the dynamic. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elmer%20Fudd">Elmer</ref> wanted to kill <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bugs%20Bunny">Bugs Bunny</ref>. There was no question in anybody’s mind. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sylvester%20(Looney%20Tunes)">Sylvester</ref> wanted to kill <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tweetie">Tweetie</ref>. There was no question in anyone’s mind, unless you wanted to say, “He just wanted to eat him. He didn’t want to kill him.” Go figure that out. There was danger involved, and some life truths involved. When you’re telling the truth, you’re really dealing with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Comedy">comedy</ref>. If you don’t have the truth on your side, then comedy can’t spring from it, unless you have some weird hydroponic garden that doesn’t need any of the standard things that it takes to grow something.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How do you choose a project, or does the project choose you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  It works both ways. I get offers for stuff. If it looks like a good offer, I’ll take it. I’m not a snob. I love working, and every now and then somebody will say, “Why did you do that?” You know what? It’s none of your business. All I owe you is a good performance.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Where do you think voice acting is going? It doesn’t seem like it’s ever an art that’s going to lose its place, but do you see it diminishing? Is it on a downturn? Is it on an upturn? Is it idling?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  What they’re doing slowly is they’re going to have to turn the celebrities and actors into cartoons, slowly but surely, because it’s the look that people are seduced by. It’s almost as if they like watching animation more than they do live action because of all the farms of kids being fostered to love computer-generated images. If you don’t do this, if you don’t start turning all of the celebrities into cartoons, we’ll lose our star system. It’s better to have their likenesses with their voices rather than trying to act out something that sprung from someone’s imagination that needed a concerted effort to give it a voice, a look. These characters are actors, they look like themselves, but they’re doing it with cartoon and computer processing. This is where it’s going.</p>
</text>
