<text id="autogum_academic_doc106" title="Regional Heterogeneity of Migrant Rent Affordability Stress in Urban China: A Comparison between Skilled and Unskilled Migrants at Prefecture Level and Above" shortTile="regional-heterogeneity" author="Tingzhu Li, Ran Liu, Wei Qi" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5920/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Richard Florida’s creative class theory has exerted an increasingly significant impact in today’s regional sciences and urban geography studies. Compared with the overwhelming role of capital in attracting talent, talent itself is also a more and more effective and attractive factor to attract capital. Florida pointed out that the great metropolises with high shares of skills, creativity, and knowledge would inevitably have high wages and housing costs borne by high-skill and low-skill occupations across the American metropolises. Empirically and theoretically, the most creative people prefer living in places that provide better housing security, greater freedom, and more cultural opportunities. With the deepening marketization of housing system and the increasing housing demands in the developed and developing countries, the crisis of the real estate bubble has generally occurred. China has experienced the largest massive rural to urban migration in human history, of around 250 million internal migrants on the move in 2015. Housing is an important aspect of the basic needs of urban migrants, but a person with a rural <hi rend="italic">hukou</hi> status is still not fully eligible for state-sponsored housing assistance in urban areas. Many studies have revealed that the most important decision for migrants is rental housing. The housing problem is quite challenging among the unskilled migrants, who are limited to certain lower-level sections of the urban job market and thus have lower capacities to afford the urban housing market. Furthermore, the flow of talent has effectively affected the development of the knowledge economy, and the amenity-driven mobility of talent has become the new geographical phenomenon in recent years in China. </p>

<p>The announcement of the National New Urbanization Plan (2014–2020) by the Chinese government in 2014 has marked a huge change of Chinese urbanization policy towards a more inclusive growth pattern. The regional differences of urbanization patterns in the more and less advanced areas in China will persist, and such areal heterogeneity is expected to bring with them many problems with housing, employment, medical care, social security and education provisions for the migrant workers. The great variance between cohorts has attracted much attention, too, as the old rural workers (<hi rend="italic">nongmingong</hi>, known as migrant labors from rural areas) and the new-generation migrant workers (those born in the 1980s and afterwards) coexist together in the huge labor market in the Chinese metropolises. The Chinese internal migration pattern has changed remarkably due to the inflow of a new generation of migrants as the main force of internal migration. The new-generation migrants who are motivated by the superior urban lifestyle and prosperous career development in the big cities are generally better educated and skilled, and are more likely to work in the advanced manufacturing industries and the well-paid service industries than in the traditional construction industry, based on Richard Florida’s study and an empirical observation on China’s industrial upgrading. At the same time, as Chinese higher education is undergoing the process of universalization, the young generation has gotten better trained and they are more capable of engaging in skilled jobs. For this reason, the skilled migrant population has grown and is better equipped for the great economic restructuring in Chinese cities. It is apparent that the skills of highly-educated migrants have contributed to their superior positions in the labor and housing markets compared with their unskilled peers, which results in a different residential distribution in cities. The housing affordability capacities, the consumption preference and behaviors in the housing market of skilled migrants are therefore distinct from the unskilled ones. But the divide of migrant rent affordability stress between skilled and unskilled migrant workers and the regional heterogeneity of this stress in urban China have rarely been reported in the existing literature. </p>

<p>At the same time, another profound institutional reform on the <hi rend="italic">hukou</hi> system is proceeding, but cities of different administrative ranks in China have taken different actions as to how to better attract, serve, and manage the migrant workers in the destination cities. The releasing of <hi rend="italic">hukou</hi> constraints and the “talent war” between second tired cities are believed to be the reactions of local governments towards population aging and an impending drop in China’s demographic dividend in recent years in urban China. It is reported that the decline of demographic dividend has prompted some cities to introduce a young and high-skilled labor force to improve the demographic structure in the aging regions, rust belts, and those experiencing industrial upgrading. Interestingly, despite the very strict <hi rend="italic">hukou</hi> regulation and housing purchase limits on migrants in first-tier cities such as Beijing and Shanghai, second-tier cities including provincial capital cities like Wuhan and Zhengzhou have provided very generous housing subsidies in order to attract the young high-skilled migrants who have a bachelor’s degree and above. The regional variance in terms of housing policy towards migrant workers has been a new policy incentive explaining the new trends of internal migration in China now. </p>
</text>
