<text id="autogum_academic_doc142" title="Estimating the Young Generation’s Willingness to Pay (WTP) for PM2.5 Control in Daegu, Korea, and Beijing, China" shortTile="estimating-young" author="Peng Ning, Sang-Ho Lee" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5704/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Methodology </head><head> 2.1. Evaluating Willingness to Pay for Air Pollution Control Using the Contingent Valuation Method (CVM)</head>
<p>
Defined as the maximum price at or below which a consumer will definitely buy one unit of a product, the concept of willingness to pay (WTP) was originally developed for establishing prices for public goods and services or valuing subjects that are not usually given monetary terms such as human life. There are a wide range of methods to evaluate WTP, which can be broadly classified into either the category of revealed preference method or that of stated preference method. Revealed preference approaches are based on actual observable choices from which the value of environment or resources can be directly inferred. In contrast, with regard to values that are usually not directly observable, stated preference methods are applied, which use survey techniques to induce WTP for either enabling a marginal improvement or preventing a marginal loss. There are a number of approaches known as stated preference methods, including contingent valuation, conjoint analysis, choice experiments, contingent ranking, attribute-based models, etc.. </p>

<p>The contingent valuation method (CVM), the most direct approach among all stated preference methods towards WTP, is widely accepted by academic and political circles. The CVM presents hypothetical opportunities for the consumers to buy public goods and services and then asks people’s WTP for these goods and services, which enables individuals to consider all factors (e.g., income level, other key socio-economic characteristics) that are important to them in the supply of the goods and services. The CVM is regarded as the single method that can interpret both user values and non-user values (e.g., bequest value and existence value). </p>

<p>As the CVM is a survey-based tool for assessing non-market goods and services like environmental preservation or pollution impacts, questionnaire design is critical because all estimated values are contingent on the information collected from the survey. There are generally three available approaches for WTP elicitation, namely, (1) via open-ended questions for the respondents to directly state their WTP; (2) via payment cards for the respondents to select the amount closest to their valuation from a range of possible payments; and (3) via dichotomous choice questions (including the single-bounded model and the double-bounded one) for the respondents to give Yes or No answers. At present, the double-bounded dichotomous choice model is believed to have a higher efficiency in assessing WTP and is more frequently used in practice. </p>

<p>WTP has been extensively applied by researchers to evaluate environmental benefits or losses to address the challenges arising from the lack of a competitive market for environmental goods and benefits. Researchers have also identified a special strength of using the CVM on the environment, that is, the CVM can be applied to a wide spectrum of situations to gauge the benefits of environmental changes, and at the same time contribute to a better knowledge of the good and/or service being valued and the corresponding public preference to facilitate decision-making. The CVM has proven to be the most popular method among all available ways for directly evaluating the environment in monetary terms. A substantial number of CVM practices are used in determining WTP in many environment-related areas, ranging from areas related to outdoor recreation (such as national park or nature reserve management) to the reduction of risks from drinking water and ground water pollution, and from improving air and water quality to protecting wilderness areas and endangered species, indicating a constantly broadening application scope of the CVM in the environmental sector. </p>

<p>Researchers have been using the CVM to estimate the welfare impact of air pollution at high frequency. A number of research studies were conducted to assess people’s WTP for air pollution control and air quality improvement both in developed countries and the developing world. These studies not only established a benchmark of monetary values for air quality improvements in different localities, but also identified a series of analysis models and major factors which may affect the amount of WTP. Existing CVM literature positively confirmed that level of income (both at the individual and household levels, including household assets such as ownership of house and car), education, knowledge of air pollution and PM2.5, and risks of respiratory disease from air pollution are the most common and strong factors that significantly affect people’s WTP for improved air quality. </p>
</text>
