<text id="autogum_voyage_doc490" title="Plymouth (England)" shortTile="plymouth-england" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=27879" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Plymouth (England)</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.visitplymouth.co.uk">Plymouth</ref></hi> is a city in <ref target="Devon">Devon</ref>, and the largest city on <ref target="England">England</ref>'s south coast, with a population of 250,000. It is located approximately 190 miles (310 km) south-west of London, where the River Plym and the River Tamar (pronounced "TAY-mar") flow into the large bay of Plymouth Sound, creating a perfect natural harbour. The sea has been at the heart of Plymouth since it was founded in the middle-ages as a trading post and the source of its prosperity. Plymouth was the point from which <ref target="Early%20United%20States%20history">the Pilgrim Fathers left England</ref> in 1620 for <ref target="Massachusetts">Massachusetts</ref> - commemorated today in the Mayflower Steps.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>Plymouth is one of England's classic ocean cities, and for centuries has been a centre for shipping; first for trade and commercial shipping, and today as a base for the Royal Navy. Indeed, the city's Devonport Dockyard is the most extensive naval base in western Europe. The water, with its leisure activities, brings many tourists to Plymouth, as well as its various museums and other tourist attractions. In addition its location close to <ref target="Dartmoor">Dartmoor</ref> and other sights of south Devon to the east and <ref target="Cornwall">Cornwall</ref> to the west make it an excellent base for a trip to the south-west of England.</p>

<p>The city was heavily bombed in World War II and much of the city-centre was destroyed. After the war, a comprehensive reconstruction plan at first produced the carefully-planned urban spaces and elegant buildings of the shopping streets in the city centre, constructed in the 1950s. However, due to budget restrictions many of the buildings erected in the 1960s and 70s were of poor architectural quality, and these are now being torn down and replaced across the city by modern ones (with exceptions of some quality, such as the listed tower of the Civic Centre on the Royal Parade). As a result, there are many modern buildings with others under construction.</p>

<p>Plymouth is a friendly city with an egalitarian feel and a sense of openness among its people, and there is less evidence of a sharp divide between rich and poor that is found in much of the southern half of England. Wonderful Devon and Cornwall scenery surrounds the city and famous city locations, such as the Hoe, the Barbican, and Plymouth Sound draw thousands every year yet Plymouth doesn't have the "tourist trap" feel that hangs over many other English cities. For those who love the sea, or the coast, or the brooding landscapes of <ref target="Dartmoor">Dartmoor</ref>, or just want a break in a welcoming and interesting city, Plymouth is an enticing and friendly destination.</p>

<p>A resident of Plymouth is called a <hi rend="bold">Plymothian</hi>. You may also hear the more derogatory term "Janner" being used - but don't call anyone this if you are a visitor! There is a large military presence in the city, with the Royal Navy's main base at Devonport, a commando regiment of the British Army at the Royal Citadel, and a Royal Marines base at Stonehouse. In addition, you'll likely find a lot of tourists and students.</p>

<head>Orientation</head>

<p>The city is located at the south-west corner of Devon, with Cornwall beginning immediately to the west of the city. It lies between two river mouths - the estuary of the River Tamar ("TAY-mar") to the west (the estuary is called the <hi rend="bold">Hamoaze</hi>) and the estuary of the River Plym to the east (called the <hi rend="bold">Cattewater</hi>). To the south is <hi rend="bold">Plymouth Sound</hi> (everyone just calls it "the Sound"), a large bay bounded to the west by the Rame Peninsula which is now part of Cornwall, and to the east by the Mount Batten Peninsula. This produces one of the world's most impressive natural harbours, in which you'll see innumerable yachts, sailing ships, kayaks, other pleasure craft, and even small fishing vessels (of which there are a reasonable number in Plymouth). The Sound is protected from the sea by a huge breakwater at its southern end, easily seen from the shore. You'll often see naval vessels around it.</p>

<p>Immediately above the water is a grassy area called <hi rend="bold">Plymouth Hoe</hi> (always just called "the Hoe"), whose names comes from a Saxon word for "grassy slope". You can spot the Hoe easily because of the lighthouse (Smeaton's Tower) that sits on it, and its wide grassy area. From here, planned as part of the grand reconstruction of the 1950s, runs north the "spine" of the city - from Smeaton's Tower on the Hoe, to the railway station north of the city-centre (which you can identify from its 1970s tower, InterCity House). This "spine" is <hi rend="bold">Armada Way</hi>, a wide street, mostly pedestrianised, with council offices at its southern end, and shops and banks and cafés as you head north. Running east-west across Armada Way are other important city-centre streets with their elegant yet now-faded buildings; Royal Parade, New George Street, Cornwall Street, and Mayflower Street. These city-centre streets are bounded by busy main roads. To the east of the Hoe is the <hi rend="bold">Barbican</hi> area (with its historic streets and large harbour/marina), and the University of Plymouth's large and impressive campus is just across the main road at the north-east of the city-centre. Other major streets can be found off these.</p>

<p>The <hi rend="bold">Tourist Information Centre</hi> is in the Barbican area, at the quayside just opposite the Mayflower Steps, at 3-5 The Barbican (that's the street address). It is open 9AM-5PM on weekdays and 10AM-4PM on Saturdays, all year.</p>

<head>Background</head>

<p>Plymouth City is within the historic county of Devon. The area was first recorded in the Domesday book as "Sudtone" (1086; later Sutton), which was located where the Barbican area of the city is today. Around this time also existed the trading port of Plymstock, further up the river (it still exists today as a suburb). However, the River Plym at Plymstock silted up in the 11th century and the area gradually came to be known as "Plymouth". <hi rend="bold">The sea</hi> has always been at the heart of Plymouth's story and it has a long and historic seafaring tradition. Its growth from a small fishing village and then trading port has been based on its position on one of the world's largest natural harbours and the enterprise of its seafarers - fishermen, merchants, privateers and later the Royal Navy.</p>

<p>Plymouth was the home of Elizabethan privateer and hero/villain <hi rend="bold">Sir Francis Drake</hi> (though he was born at Tavistock a few miles north), and from here he planned his raids and other maritime adventures. In 1588, the English Navy, which was led in part by Drake, set sail from Plymouth to defeat the <hi rend="bold">Spanish Armada</hi>. It is said that Drake refused to leave port until he had finished his game of bowls on the Hoe. While this is probably more legend than history, there is still a bowls club on the Hoe today. In 1620 the Pilgrim Fathers sailed to the New World after setting into Plymouth for repairs, escaping from religious persecution to eventually set up Plymouth Colony, Massachusetts. Plymouth was a stronghold of Parliamentarian forces in the English Civil War, written across its history in areas such as Freedom Fields park. After the restoration, the new king, Charles II, ordered the construction of a massive fort (the <hi rend="bold">Royal Citadel</hi>) to protect the town from invaders - such was its strategic importance. But the fort's guns also faced inland, it is said as a signal to the people of the city about where their loyalties should lie! The Royal Citadel is still home to a unit of the Army. The <hi rend="bold">Royal Dockyard</hi> was built in the area, on the banks of the River Tamar, in 1690. Plymouth was amalgamated in 1914 with the towns of Devonport and Stonehouse to form the modern city which was granted city status in 1928. It includes the historic areas of Plymstock and Plympton.</p>

<p>The city was seriously damaged by bombing during the <hi rend="bold">Second World War</hi> (1939–45) and the city-centre was extensively redeveloped afterwards. At Charles Cross, the ruined Charles Church was left as a memorial to the many dead. Behind it, the Drake Circus shopping centre was constructed to frame it in dramatic fashion, as an impressive entrance to the city from the south-east. The shopping streets of the city-centre were first to be reconstructed, according to the grand plan of Sir Patrick Abercrombie. This resulted in the elegant large buildings from the 1950s that can be seen on streets such as Armada Way, New George Street, and Cornwall Street. However, these are now in need of restoration. Much of the rest of the reconstruction involved cheap buildings in the Brutalist style fashionable in the 1960s and 1970s, most of which had no architectural merit. However, exceptions included the Civic Centre which is Grade II-listed. Many historic buildings remain, particularly in the Barbican area, isolated city-centre examples such as the City Museum, and also outside the city-centre which escaped the worst of the bombing (e.g. the Royal William Yard).</p>

<p>With its dramatic coastal setting, the surrounding landscape is quite striking. Plymouth is by turns rugged and hilly, or green and rolling. Famous Dartmoor was designated a National Park in 1951. Popular sites include Smeaton's Tower (a lighthouse rebuilt on the Hoe from its original location at Eddystone Rock when it was replaced with a new one), the Mount Batten Peninsula, the National Marine Aquarium, and Buckland Abbey, which was Drake's former home. Tourism is an important aspect of Plymouth's economy. Nearly 12 million people visit Plymouth every year. As well as all the attractions of a modern city, Plymouth is a popular launch pad to other notable areas including the beaches and footpaths of the Devon and Cornwall coastline and the brooding landscape of nearby Dartmoor.</p>
</text>
