<text id="autogum_voyage_doc400" title="Finnmark" shortTile="finnmark" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=11623" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Finnmark</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.nordnorge.com/en">Finnmark</ref></hi> (Sami: <hi rend="italic">Finnmárkku fylka</hi>) is <ref target="Norway">Norway</ref>'s northernmost county, well within the <ref target="Arctic">Arctic</ref> circle. It is the largest county in Norway by area (48,637 km) but the smallest by inhabitants (74,000 in 2012). Finnmark is the northernmost part of mainland Europe, as well as the easternmost part of Norway.</p>

<head>Towns</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> </item>
</list>


<head>Understand</head>
<p>Finnmark covers an area about the size of countries like Slovakia, Switzerland or Denmark. From west to east it is almost 1000 km, comparable to the distance from London to Edinburgh. A large part of the county consists of the <hi rend="italic">Finnmarksvidda</hi> plateau at about 300 to 500 meters above sea level. Finnmark's rugged coastline totals about 6800 km if islands are included (more than the coastline of Spain or Chile). The municipality of Kautokeino is about 10,000 square kilometers (4 times the size of Luxembourg) with a population of less than 3,000. Almost 10 % of Kautokeino's area is lake surface. In total there are well over 100,000 lakes in Finnmark.</p>

<p>In Eastern Finnmark the borders of Finland, Norway and Russia coincide, with no less than three different time zones within a few steps. Finnmark is the northernmost as well as the easternmost part of Scandinavia. <ref target="Kirkenes">Kirkenes</ref> sits at about 30°E, corresponding to St. Petersburg or Istanbul.</p>

<head>Climate and daylight</head>
<p>Finnmark is Norway's coldest area, but temperatures varies over the county. The interior has a continental climate with winter temperatures down to -40°C/F (record -50°C), while summers can be warm. Karasjok for instance has an <hi rend="italic">annual</hi> average at . The coast has chilly summers, and winters that are not so cold but windy (the open sea is ice free in winter). The town of Vardø has an Arctic climate, as even July has a monthly average at 9°C, like most of the outer coastline of Finnmark.</p>

<p>During summer there is a long period of <ref target="midnight%20sun">midnight sun</ref> (24 hour sun) and vice versa there is a long period in winter during which the sun is below the horizon (polar night, <hi rend="italic">skábma</hi> or <hi rend="italic">mørketid</hi>, "dark period"). In <ref target="Alta">Alta</ref> the polar night lasts from November 25 to January 17.</p>

<head>History</head>
<p>Finnmark was largely destroyed during <ref target="World%20War%20II%20in%20Europe">World War II</ref>. The eastern part of Finnmark was on the front between Soviet Union and Germany; fierce fighting took place east of the small town of Kirkenes, which was subjected to more than 300 bombing raids. When the occupying forces retreated to Troms, they applied a scorched earth strategy, where virtually every home, church, factory, bridge and telegraph pole was destroyed. The population was relocated by force to Tromsø and further south. The result was a vast no-man's land about twice the size of Belgium (similar tactics was applied across the border in Northern Finland). Kirkenes and eastern Finnmark was liberated by the Soviet army 1944, the Soviets retreated in 1945. Some 20,000 residents refused to relocate and endured the winter in tunnels, caves and makeshift lodgings. The county was quickly rebuilt after the war, virtually no building older than 1945 exist.</p>

<p>Finnmark was for centuries Norway's frontier. The very northern regions of Norway, Sweden, Finland and Russia was largely a common area without clear boundaries until 1826. Along with the Sami people and Norwegians there are also Kven people of Finnish origin in Finnmark. There have been close connections across the border to Finland and Russia. Trade with the Pomors of Russia even resulted in a local pidgin language that mixed elements of Russian and Norwegian, as well as words from English, French, Sami and other languages.</p>

<head>Talk</head>

<ref target="Norwegian%20phrasebook">Norwegian</ref> is spoken by all, but in parts of Finnmark <ref target="Sami%20phrasebook">Nortern Sami</ref> is the majority language and there is a Kven/<ref target="Finnish%20phrasebook">Finnish</ref> speaking minority as well. Sami is a family of languages and the northern variant spoken in Finnmark and Troms is the most common. Sami languages are also spoken in Finland, Russia and Sweden. As in rest of Norway, English proficiency is good. Signs are often with Sami names in addition to Norwegian names, for instance <ref target="Kautokeino">Kautokeino</ref> is spelled Guovdageaidnu in Sami. In Eastern Finnmark around Kirkenes, Russian is used on signs and also spoken. Well over 10 % of the population in Kirkenes are Russians.

<head>Get in</head>
<p>Finnmark is located on the very north of the Fenno-Scandinavian landmass, just north of Finland. Mode of transport and route is therefore important. Overland transport is very time consuming from most places, including South Scandinavia. For a brief visit air transport is usually the only realistic option. Overland transport from South Scandinavia and the European mainland is fastest and easiest – but less scenic – through Sweden and Finland. The shortest road from for instance Hamburg to North Cape is about 2800 km (1700 miles), more than 30 hours non-stop driving. There is a single border crossing from Russia near Kirkenes (note that this is an outer border of Schengen). There is no rail network this far north (you get to <ref target="Bod%C3%B8">Bodø</ref>, <ref target="Narvik">Narvik</ref>, <ref target="Lule%C3%A5">Luleå</ref>, <ref target="Kolari">Kolari</ref>, <ref target="Rovaniemi">Rovaniemi</ref> or <ref target="Murmansk">Murmansk</ref>, you can take your car on some trains or continue by bus).</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>There are direct flights from Oslo to Alta ( ALF ) and Kirkenes ( KKN ) and in summertime also to Lakselv ( LKL ), served by <ref target="http://www.flysas.com/">SAS</ref> or <ref target="http://www.norwegian.com/">Norwegian</ref>.</p>

<p>Other airports are Båtsfjord ( BJF ), Berlevåg, Hammerfest, Hasvik, Honningsvåg, Lakselv, Mehamn, Vadsø, Vardø. They are served by local flights from either Alta, Kirkenes or Tromsø ( TOS ), operated by <ref target="http://www.wideroe.no/">Widerøe</ref>.</p>

<p>There are (per 2015) no international flights.</p>

<head>By bus</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.eskelisen-lapinlinjat.com/en/">Eskelisen Lapin Linjat</ref></hi> offers bus rides from Finland to <ref target="Vads%C3%B8">Vadsø</ref>, <ref target="Alta">Alta</ref>, and <ref target="Nordkapp">Nordkapp</ref>.</item>
<item> Regional express buses from Tromsø to Alta, about 7 hours.</item>
</list>


<head>By boat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Hurtigruten">Hurtigruten</ref> coastal ships, daily departures</item>
</list>


<head>By car</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> From Norway: The <ref target="E6%20through%20Sweden%20and%20Norway">E6</ref>, from South Norway this is longer but more scenic road than E4.</item>
<item> From South Norway through Sweden and Finland</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="E4%20through%20Sweden">E4</ref> is fastest also from Oslo. A suggestion is to drive E6, 3, 25, 311 past Trysil and Särna, then 314, 83 and E14 past Sveg and Ånge to Sundsvall and the E4. A longer but better road is E16 to Gävle.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> From Sweden and through Finland</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Fastest from south Sweden to Alta: <ref target="E4%20through%20Sweden">E4</ref> to Luleå, then <ref target="E10%20through%20Sweden%20and%20Norway">E10</ref> and 392 and 403 past Pajala to the border to Finland, then E8 and road 93.</item>
<item> Fastest from south Sweden to Kirkenes: E4 to Kemi (in Finland), then <ref target="highway%204%20%28Finland%29">E75</ref> and road 971.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Finnish <ref target="highway%204%20%28Finland%29">highway 4</ref> (E75) stretches from Helsinki up to the "head" of Finland from where you can continue to west to Lakselv, north to Tana or east to Kirkenes. Helsinki itself is connected by ferry from <ref target="Tallinn">Tallinn</ref>, <ref target="Travem%C3%BCnde">Travemünde</ref> and <ref target="Stockholm">Stockholm</ref>.</item>
<item> European route 105 (E105) enters from <ref target="Russia">Russia</ref> at Storskog border crossing 15 km east of <ref target="Kirkenes">Kirkenes</ref>. This is the only overland crossing between Norway and Russia. Crossing by vehicle only, no pedestrians nor cyclists (as of January 2016). <hi rend="italic">Note</hi>: This is an outer border of <ref target="Europe%23Schengen_Agreement">Schengen</ref>.</item>
</list>
</text>
