<text id="autogum_news_doc373" title="Australian men, women win 2013 Asia-Oceania Wheelchair Basketball Championships" shortTile="australian-men-women" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-11-25" dateModified="2015-02-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australian_men%2C_women_win_2013_Asia-Oceania_Wheelchair_Basketball_Championships" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Australian men, women win 2013 Asia-Oceania Wheelchair Basketball Championships</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, December 1, 2013</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thai-Japanese%20Bangkok%20Youth%20Center">Thai-Japanese Bangkok Youth Center</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bangkok">Bangkok</ref> —
The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia_men's_national_wheelchair_basketball_team">Australia men's national wheelchair basketball team</ref>, known as the Rollers, and the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia_women's_national_wheelchair_basketball_team">Australia women's national wheelchair basketball team</ref>, known as the Gliders, won gold medals on Friday, the final day of the Asia–Oceania Zone Wheelchair Basketball Championships in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bangkok">Bangkok</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Thailand">Thailand</ref>.  The eight day championship was opened on November 22. </p>
<figure><caption>Asia–Oceania Zone Wheelchair Basketball Championships, Bangkok, 2013. IWBF President Maureen Orchard presents silver medals to the Chinese women's team Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Hawkeye7">Hawkeye7</ref>.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>Australian Gliders are addressed by their head coach, Tom Kyle Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Hawkeye7">Hawkeye7</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>Maureen Orchard. President and Secretary General of the International Wheelchair Basketball Federation Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Hawkeye7">Hawkeye7</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>Asia–Oceania Zone Wheelchair Basketball Championships — Australia's Amber Merritt Image: Matthew Wells.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>Asia–Oceania Zone Wheelchair Basketball Championships — Japan's Mari Animoto Image: Matthew Wells.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>Asia–Oceania Zone Wheelchair Basketball Championships — Australia's Tristan Knowles Image: Matthew Wells.</caption></figure>
<p>Ten countries competed for places at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International%20Wheelchair%20Basketball%20Federation">International Wheelchair Basketball Federation</ref> (IWBF) World Championships next year — ten in the men's: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Japan">Japan</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iran">Iran</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China">China</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Malaysia">Malaysia</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Taiwan">Taipei</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia">Australia</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/South_Korea">Korea</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kuwait">Kuwait</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_Zealand">New Zealand</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Thailand">Thailand</ref>; and four in the women's: Australia, Japan, China and Thailand. For the Australians, it was a rare opportunity to play teams from neighboring countries. Their efforts to help other teams were appreciated; after one game the Kuwait men led a cheer of "Aussie! Aussie! Aussie!" To which the Thai women replied: "Oi! Oi! Oi!" </p>
<p>Both the Australian teams went through the tournament undefeated. The Gliders defeated China in the gold medal game 57–35. The Rollers then took to the court and defeated Korea 63–46. Iran and Japan won the men's and women's bronze medal matches.</p>
<p>This was one of four zone championships. The zones correspond to those of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IPC">IPC</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FIBA">FIBA</ref>: Americas, Europe, Asia–Oceania and Africa. Each zone is guaranteed one place at the World Championships. Under recently-introduced rules, performance at the Paralympic games gains additional spots for the zone, not for the country. Only the home team is guaranteed a place.</p>
<p>The new zone system has already proved controversial, with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Algeria">Algeria</ref>  defeating <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/South_Africa">South Africa</ref> in the recent Africa Zone Championships in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Angola">Angola</ref> to grab the sole spot allocated to Africa, and Canada missing out on one of the four men's spots for the Americas zone. In a shock result, these places went to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Argentina">Argentina</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mexico">Mexico</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Colombia">Colombia</ref>. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UK">Great Britain</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Turkey">Turkey</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Spain">Spain</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sweden">Sweden</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Italy">Italy</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">Germany</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Netherlands">Netherlands</ref> are to round out the championships as the men's teams from the European Zone.</p>
<p>The men's World Championship are to be held in July next year in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Incheon">Incheon</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/South_Korea">South Korea</ref>, while the women's are to be in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Toronto">Toronto</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada">Canada</ref>. Maureen Orchard. President and Secretary General of the IWBF told <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> the women's competition will in no way be inferior to the men's. The women are to be put up in a five-star hotel, and play at Toronto's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Air%20Canada%20Centre">Maple Leaf Gardens</ref>. Without their men's team competing, the women's competition is expected to generate considerable interest in Canada. The home team is to be joined by teams from the Netherlands, Germany, Great Britain, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">France</ref>, the United States, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brazil">Brazil</ref>, Mexico, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Peru">Peru</ref> to compete against the winners from the Asia–Oceania Zone.</p>
<p>The sport of wheelchair basketball has great popularity. In London, additional seats at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North%20Greenwich%20Arena">North Greenwich Arena</ref> sold out online within minutes.</p>
</text>
