<text id="autogum_voyage_doc274" title="Fort Wayne" shortTile="fort-wayne" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=11908" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Fort Wayne</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.cityoffortwayne.org">Fort Wayne</ref></hi> is a city in the northeastern part of <ref target="Northern%20Indiana">Indiana</ref> a state of the <ref target="United%20States%20of%20America">United States of America</ref>. It is 30 minutes from the western Ohio border and 70 minutes from the southern border of Michigan. With a population of around 260,00 in the city and 615,000 in the metropolitan area, it's Indiana's second largest city.</p>

<p>Fort Wayne is a metropolitan city with a small community feel. It provides the rush of urban activity while never losing an intimate personal connection with those who live or visit here. Fort Wayne is the second largest city in the state of Indiana, located in Allen County, the largest county in the state by geography. It is the regional commerce and industry center for Northeast Indiana and also impacts the economies of Southwestern Michigan and Western Ohio. Fort Wayne has been and is a breeding ground for entrepreneurs and high tech industries.</p>

<p>The city has many historical buildings that usually offer regular tours. The city itself has a long history going back to the 1700s, but has lately succumbed to the urban sprawl so widespread in the Midwest. It is nicknamed the "Summit City" because, even though the surrounding area seems completely flat, it is on the high point of the old Wabash-Erie canal.</p>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fort Wayne International Airport</hi> ( FWA ). Recommended to passengers looking for the convenient and friendly way to travel. Recognized as "the nation's friendliest airport" by USA Today. FWA's airlines offer daily direct flights to/from Atlanta, Chicago, Cincinnati, Cleveland, Detroit, and Dallas-Fort Worth. With free wireless internet throughout the terminal, ample parking, short security lines and access to hundreds of destinations worldwide.Fort Wayne International Airport operates 24 hours a day, 7 days a week.It's served by commuter and regional jets from most of the major hubs in the country. The airport has free internet (wireless or in carrels upstairs on the secure side). </item>
</list>


<p>There is a cookie factory right across the street from the airport, and you can tell what they're baking that day by smell. Volunteers meet you when you arrive and give away free cookies as you come through security.</p>

<p>For flights to Chicago, expect to pack your hand luggage into a small cargo hull. It is recommended that you avoid packing anything fragile in your carry-ons. The smaller lines operate tiny planes in between FW and Chicago and there is little room for even ladies' purses.</p>

<p>There is a shuttle bus service between Indianapolis and Fort Wayne run by Hoosier Shuttle.</p>

<head>By car</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Interstates 69</hi> makes Fort Wayne easily accessible by car from the north and south. It connects to <ref target="Indianapolis">Indianapolis</ref>, in the south and <ref target="Lansing%20%28Michigan%29">Lansing</ref>, to the north.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">I-469</hi> is an southern and eastern interstate by-pass of Fort Wayne that connects with I-69 at both ends.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">U.S. 24</hi> is an important expressway and connects to <ref target="Toledo%20%28Ohio%29">Toledo</ref>, Ohio in the northeast and <ref target="Lafayette%20%28Indiana%29">Lafayette</ref>, Indiana, to the southwest.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">U.S. 27</hi> is an important highway, providing access primarily from places to the south and is the main north-south highway through downtown.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">U.S. 30</hi> is an important expressway, providing access primarily from places to the west and east. It connects to <ref target="Lima%20%28Ohio%29">Lima</ref>, Ohio in the east and <ref target="Valparaiso%20%28Indiana%29">Valparaiso</ref>, to the west.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">U.S. 33</hi> is an important highway, providing access primarily from places to the northwest and south. It connects to <ref target="Columbus%20%28Ohio%29">Columbus</ref>, Ohio in the south and <ref target="Goshen">Goshen</ref> and <ref target="Elkhart">Elkhart</ref>, to the northwest.</item>
</list>


<head>By bus</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.greyhound.com">Greyhound</ref></hi> has multiple long-haul services to Fort Wayne from most nearby cities. The is located downtown at 121 W Baker St.</p>

<head>By train</head>

<p>Fort Wayne is not directly served by passenger rail, but <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.amtrak.com">Amtrak</ref></hi> has several daily services to nearby Waterloo, half an hour north of Fort Wayne. Be prepared to phone for a cab or have someone meet you because transportation from the station to the city is limited. The station is served by <ref target="https://www.amtrak.com/routes/capitol-limited-train.html"><hi rend="italic">Capitol Limited</hi></ref> between <ref target="Washington%20D.C.">Washington D.C.</ref> and <ref target="Chicago">Chicago</ref> as well at the <ref target="https://www.amtrak.com/routes/lake-shore-limited-train.html"><hi rend="italic">Lare Shore Limited</hi></ref> between <ref target="New%20York">New York</ref>, <ref target="Boston">Boston</ref> and Chicago.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>There is a municipal bus system that can get you around called <ref target="http://www.fwcitilink.com"><hi rend="bold">Citilink</hi></ref>. The system has limited routes and hours of operation.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>To get into downtown US 27 would be the main route from north or south and Jefferson Boulevard from the west. From the east the route to downtown Fort Wayne Washington Boulevard and would pass through New Haven.</p>
<p>All major Rental Car Companies have franchises are at the airport, but don't rent here. The airport branches are much more expensive. Call the Enterprise Car Rental location on the SW or NE side and have them pick you up. They have a weekend rate for $9.95 a day, from Friday morning through Monday morning. Reserve other rates online for the best rates.</p>

<p>If you get into the airport on a late flight, don't assume there will be taxis waiting. Call ahead and arrange one on A-1 taxi at 260-478-9910 or 800-871-0518.</p>

<head>Museums and History</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Allen County Public Library Genealogical Collection</hi>. It is the largest public genealogical collection in the United States. The library offers special classes and has librarians there to assist you in your search. One night a year, they keep the room open until midnight. It is usually around Halloween.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Fort Wayne History Center</hi>, 302 E Berry St, ☏ +1 260-426-2882 . Is a museum with many interesting displays about the area, from the days before Europeans came, to modern times. Even the castle-like building is worth a careful look. Among the stories to be read there are the afternoon that hi fidelity sound (from separating the frequencies and routing them through different speakers) was invented at the local Magnavox plant. They had settled on the term "tweeter" for the small speaker, but rejected a number of other suggestions before settling on "woofer" for the big ones. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fort Wayne Firefighters Museum</hi> (Engine House No. 3), 226 W Washington Blvd, ☏ +1 260-426-0051 . </item>
</list>
</text>
