<text id="autogum_interview_doc791" title="part6_Eurovision &amp;apos;73 winner Anne Marie David discusses her four-decade career and the Contest, past and present" shortTile="parteurovision--winner" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-02-15" dateModified="2012-02-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eurovision_%2773_winner_Anne_Marie_David_discusses_her_four-decade_career_and_the_Contest%2C_past_and_present" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>For "Federico" it's Jean Renard who had the idea. [It was] a task which was totally unlike [anything in] my experience, but he trusted me and I trusted him. I don't regret it. There is a little bit of me in "Federico." I have Iberian origins from my mother, and furthermore this allowed me to write two songs in Spanish. Nothing but happiness!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> What new projects will you be doing in 2009? Are you doing any concerts?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AMD</hi>: Yes, I will be in some concerts but this time as an artisan. I will co-produce a large portion of them; I'm preparing an album of twelve new songs for 2010... and after if God wills it I'll celebrate my 40 years in [music] at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paris%20Olympia">Olympia</ref> if it's possible. I also continue [on] as a coach and the artistic director of the group "Caprice" ([who are] three of my students), who had hoped to represent France at Eurovision 2009, but whom France 3 discarded from the game in a pretty dishonest way (along with all the others, for that matter). They will record other songs this year and I'm sure they'll do great. I like talent and they have it. I already partially explained my point of view on the subject in my response to  [an earlier question regarding the representative at Eurovision 2009].</p>
<head id="Views_about_Eurovision_today">Views about Eurovision today</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> In the past ten years or so, public interest in Eurovision has dwindled somewhat in France, a trend that has already been seen in countries like the Netherlands and Germany. Why do you feel that is? Is there anything France, or perhaps France Télévisions, can do to get French people watching the Contest again, especially in a television landscape populated by reality television?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AMD</hi>: The only solution would be to stop changing a game rule that has proven itself for years, not [to] mix the genres, [to] return to the fundamentals. Eurovision is a contest of songs, not of stars, or [a] dance floor, or <hi rend="italic">Top Model</hi>... If this type of manifestation, which pleases the [current viewing] base had not been derived, all those who loved Eurovision would watch it still. </p>
<p>But the system of votes by SMS developed the youths' votes, against whom I bear no ill but few adults play that game (my grandmother or mother will never vote that way). To put the spotlight favourably on the operators who that night will swipe the wealth [<hi rend="italic">Editor's note: A reference to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pactolus">Pactolus</ref>, in which King Midas washed his hands of the golden touch in the river there</hi>], they prefer to take from it an evening which was an international family party... And tell yourself that any economic power who wants to make his candidate win can afford the luxury of buying millions of portable cell phones, distribute them with unlimited plans for a night to kids who could not afford them and win! Anyway, when I say "win", [it nowadays] implies not really winning! </p>
</text>
