<text id="autogum_news_doc464" title="Football: Chelsea beats Manchester United 1-0 to win English FA Cup" shortTile="football-chelsea" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2018-05-21" dateModified="2018-06-19" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Football%3A_Chelsea_beats_Manchester_United_1-0_to_win_English_FA_Cup" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Football: Chelsea beats Manchester United 1-0 to win English FA Cup</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 22, 2018</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/London">London</ref>-based <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Soccer">football</ref> club <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Chelsea_FC">Chelsea</ref> defeated <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Manchester_United">Manchester United</ref> 1–0 at the Wembley stadium on Monday to win the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/England">English</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FA%20Cup">FA Cup</ref>. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Belgium">Belgian</ref> winger <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eden_Hazard">Eden Hazard</ref>, who was brought down by Manchester's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phil%20Jones%20(footballer,%20born%201992)">Phil Jones</ref> in the penalty area, scored the only goal — a 22nd minute penalty — to win the match for <hi rend="italic">The Blues</hi> as they won their eight FA Cup trophy, their first since 2012.</p>
<p>United had greater ball possession — 67%, twice Chelsea's. Manchester had eighteen shots, managing five on target; while the Londoners had just six shots, three on target. Early, in the first ten minutes, Hazard attempted to score a left-footed shot in the left corner, assisted by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tiemoué%20Bakayoko">Tiemoué Bakayoko</ref>. Soon after 20 minutes on the clock, United defender Jones committed a foul on Hazard in the penalty area and was shown a yellow card. Match official Martin Oliver referred to video assistant referee and awarded Chelsea a penalty kick. Taking a short run, Hazard converted the spot-kick into a goal, sending United's goalkeeper <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20De%20Gea">David De Gea</ref> in the wrong direction. The first half ended in a 1–0 lead for <hi rend="italic">The Blues</hi>, with Phil Jones the only one booked in that half.</p>
<p>In the 56th minute, United came close to equalising, but Chelsea's goalkeeper <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Thibaut_Courtois">Thibaut Courtois</ref> denied <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcus%20Rashford">Marcus Rashford</ref> the chance to level up. A couple of minutes later, Manchester United's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antonio%20Valencia">Antonio Valencia</ref> was shown yellow. In the 63rd minute, Alexis Sanchez almost equalised for United, from Jones's assist, but was caught offside. Manchester made a double-substitution in the 73rd minute as Belgian forward <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Romelu_Lukaku">Romelu Lukaku</ref> came on for Rashford and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anthony%20Martial">Anthony Martial</ref> replaced injured <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesse%20Lingard">Jesse Lingard</ref>.</p>
<p>Spanish midfielder <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juan%20Mata">Juan Mata</ref> replaced Jones in the 87th minute, and Chelsea made their first substitution in the 89th minute when <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Álvaro%20Morata">Álvaro Morata</ref> came on for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Olivier_Giroud">Olivier Giroud</ref>. Hazard was replaced by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Willian%20Borges">Willian</ref> in the injury time, and Chelsea's Belgian goalkeeper Courtois got booked minutes before the final whistle.</p>
<p>This was the first domestic cup victory for the Italian manager Antonio Conte, who lost last year's FA Cup against <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Arsenal_FC">Arsenal FC</ref>. Conte's Chelsea won the Premier League last season but finished fifth this time, missing out the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UEFA_Champions_League">UEFA Champions League</ref> qualification for next season.</p>
<p>After the victory, Conte said, "I'm very satisfied because today was very difficult [...] To win the FA Cup against a really strong team — a really great team like Manchester United — we must be pleased. It wasn't easy, but I'm very happy for our fans, for my players."</p>
<p>United's manager and former Chelsea boss <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/José_Mourinho">José Mourinho</ref> said, "I congratulate them but I don't think they deserved to win". The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Portugal">Portuguese</ref> added, "Every defeat hurts, but for me personally the ones that hurt less are when you give everything and you go without any regrets. [...] I knew the opponent I was going to play against. I knew they have a compact low block with lots of physicality where they try to close everything." Manchester United finished second in the league this season, nineteen points behind their city rivals <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Manchester_City">Manchester City</ref>.</p>
<p>FA Cup winners Chelsea earned 1.8 million <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/pound%20sterling">British pounds</ref> prize money.</p>
May 19, 2018
<hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Chelsea_FC">Chelsea</ref></hi>
<hi rend="bold">1–0</hi>
<hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Manchester_United">Manchester United</ref></hi>
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wembley%20Stadium">Wembley Stadium</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/London">London</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/England">England</ref> Attendance: 87,647 Referee:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael%20Oliver%20(referee)">Michael Oliver</ref> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Football%20Association">England</ref>)
<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eden_Hazard">Eden Hazard</ref>  22'(pen.)<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Thibaut_Courtois">Thibaut Courtois</ref>  90+3'
(1–0) <hi rend="bold">HT</hi>
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phil%20Jones%20(footballer,%20born%201992)">Phil Jones</ref>  21'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antonio%20Valencia">Antonio Valencia</ref>  58'
</text>
