<text id="autogum_interview_doc341" title="part1_Wikinews interviews former Congressman Virgil Goode, Constitution Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-02-27" dateModified="2017-02-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_former_Congressman_Virgil_Goode%2C_Constitution_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>One of my main points is to achieve a balanced budget, sooner not later, not five years down the road, not ten years down the road. We need to do that now.</p>
<p>I also understand the need for secure borders. And I am the only candidate that is in favor of totally stopping illegal immigration, and reducing legal immigration. Immigration costs this country billions of dollars. We should not be bringing in more green card holders while our unemployment rate is between eight and nine percent. We need jobs in America, and U.S. citizens first, and not bring in so many from other countries that take jobs from U.S. citizens.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why did you decide to join the Constitution Party and seek its nomination?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Goode</hi>: I have been going to the National Committee meetings. I am a member of the National Committee of the Constitution Party, and I've attended about ten meetings.  The Constitution National Committee, unlike the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republican%20National%20Committee">Republican National Committee</ref> and unlike the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Democratic%20National%20Committee">Democratic National Committee</ref>, was willing to take a stand and support the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arizona%20SB%201070">Arizona legislation</ref> to counteract illegal immigration. I think the federal government should be supportive of the efforts of states to deal with the problems, and of course the current administration does not.  And the Republican National Committee did not do a resolution supporting Arizona like the Constitution Party National Committee.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">If you win the nomination, are you concerned you will take votes away from the Republicans and help re-elect <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Goode</hi>: No. I think I’ll take votes from Obama.  I just talked to the guy that filled my tanks with gas. I’ve known him for many years. He’s gonna vote for Obama — he was — but he says now, he’s gonna vote for me. So I think I’ll take as many votes from Obama as I will from the Republican.</p>
<p>I think when people focus on our campaign, we’re gonna get a lot of votes from both Democrats and Republicans.  My campaign is only taking donations of $200 and less. That’s a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/grassroots">grassroots</ref> campaign. Running a grassroots campaign should be very appealing to Democrats who do not favor the big money that’s backing President Obama.  He’s lowering the ethics with big <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Political%20Action%20Committee">PAC</ref> donations , and he has maximum limit donations, which I believe is about $10,000 per couple now.  Our limit is $200, so I think we’ll take votes from President Obama and with those who really want to balance the budget right away will vote with us too.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">If you were elected in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_presidential_election,_2008">2008</ref>, what would you have done differently than Obama?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Goode</hi>: I would not have pushed for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Patient_Protection_and_Affordable_Care_Act">Obamacare</ref>. I would have secured the borders, stopped illegal immigration, reduced legal immigration, done away with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diversity%20Immigrant%20Visa">diversity visas</ref>, supported legislation to stop <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Birthright%20citizenship%20in%20the%20United%20States">automatic birthright citizenship</ref> for those born of illegals that come into this country. And I would not have adopted the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American%20Recovery%20and%20Reinvestment%20Act%20of%202009">stimulus bill</ref> that he approved with all <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deficit%20spending">deficit spending</ref>. There are many areas that need to be cut. When I was in Congress, I was often among the lowest spenders of the Congressional expense money. We need to do that across all levels of the federal government.  Instead of expanding government, we need to have less regulation, and encourage the private sector.</p>
</text>
