<text id="autogum_whow_doc181" title="Strategize" shortTile="strategize" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-06-06" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Strategize" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Strategize</head><p>A strategy is a well-designed plan of attack for a personal or professional goal. The success of a strategy depends upon how realistic it is, how detailed it is and how organized the action steps are. Create your strategic planning team, organize five to 10 action steps and set up review deadlines to strategize effectively.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Choosing an Issue to Address</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Start with an issue you want to address. This is your starting point. <figure rend="Strategize Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Strategize one issue at a time. If you have several issues that need to be addressed, you will need several strategies. Strategy is a custom process, not a one-size-fits-all solution. <figure rend="Strategize Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pick a goal or desired outcome. Choose the scope of what you want to achieve. You have created your ending point, and the strategy will fill out all your actions from start to end. <figure rend="Strategize Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Decide whether the goal is feasible. Perhaps you want to ask others with more experience if they think it can be done. For example, if you want to get a promotion in one year, ask a colleague in a higher position how long it took them to get into a management role. <figure rend="Strategize Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If the goal is not a feasible one, try to go for a more feasible solution, such as getting a 5 percent raise or more responsibility. Later, strategize how to get a promotion in two or five years.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Making a Planning Team</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Invite others to join your strategic planning session that have a stake in the outcome. At work this may be all the members of management or a department. For personal goals, this may be your partner, parents or friends. <figure rend="Strategize Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Explain the goal to your team. Give them a period time to think about the issues. <figure rend="Strategize Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Specialize. If someone is a human resources representative, they should strategize how best to ask for a raise. If someone else is a financial planning expert, they can strategize how the raise could improve your quality of life and motivation. <figure rend="Strategize Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Brainstorm some ideas about how to address the issue. Write any potentially useful ideas. <figure rend="Strategize Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Picking Your Tools</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Get organized. The most important tools are a pen and pencil while you bring up ideas. However, other tools can help you collect information along the way and chart progress. <figure rend="Strategize Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Decide how you will keep track of your process. You will need to quantify your success on a weekly or monthly basis. <figure rend="Strategize Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, if you want to gain 500 more Facebook followers, you should report on the number of total and new followers each month, in addition to the posts you have used. Facebook itself has several valuable reporting tools.</item></list></item>
<item>Get high tech. At the very least, you should have an Excel spreadsheet, but you may also want to sign up for a Google Analytics account, a CRM management software or a financial tracker like Mint.com. <figure rend="Strategize Step 11 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Setting Goals and Timelines</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Decide when your final deadline to achieve a strategy will be. <figure rend="Strategize Step 12 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Break down the strategy into 5 to 10 action steps between now and the final deadline. Date those steps to indicate when they should be put into motion. <figure rend="Strategize Step 13 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Mark those dates in your calendar, with extra reminders for projects that will take several weeks to complete. <figure rend="Strategize Step 14 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Break each step into sub-steps if necessary. Organize them into bulleted points with as much information as necessary. <figure rend="Strategize Step 15 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Delegate tasks to others if it is a team strategy. Make them accountable to you or other people, by asking them to submit a progress report on a specific day. <figure rend="Strategize Step 16 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Review the data every month. Adjust your steps accordingly to account for adjustments in deadline or approach. <figure rend="Strategize Step 17 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Share all strategy plans with people who are involved with the strategy. Update the documents and share them whenever they change. <figure rend="Strategize Step 18 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Consider starting a Google Drive spreadsheet or document if you don’t have a common platform to use with other people in the strategic planning committee.</item></list></item>
<item>Make a date for the strategy to be complete. Review it at that time. If it has been successful, consider using similar strategies in the future. <figure rend="Strategize Step 19 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If it hasn’t been successful, learn from your mistakes and try new steps each time.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
