<text id="autogum_academic_doc140" title="Application of the Soil Security Concept to Two Contrasting Soil Landscape Systems—Implications for Soil Capability and Sustainable Land Management" shortTile="application-soil" author="Brian Murphy, Peter Fogarty" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5706/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Soil Capability and Soil Condition</head><head> 2.1. Basic Definitions</head>
<p>
In the soil security concept, soil capability currently refers to “…the ability of the soil to function, and in particular answers the question ‘what can the soil do?’” (p. 17). McBratney et al. further suggest that soil capability can be thought of “… as a reference state that defines an optimal capacity of the soil to which the current condition of the soil can be compared”. This is the genoform. The difference between the baseline condition of the soil in the reference state and the current soil condition, the phenoform can be used as a quantified measure of the soil capability. There is a recognition that soil capability has a link to soil management, and that soil should be managed within its capability. McBratney et al. also recognise that the response of the soil condition to land management is included within the soil capability dimension, “…the management of soil over longer periods of time may result in changes to the soil which needs to be accounted for” (p. 206). In fact, soil capability can define how the soil condition responds to stresses, pressures, influences or forcings imposed on the soil by the environment and land management. One interpretation is that the soil capability defines or predicts what are the mechanisms or “forcings” that change the soil condition from the reference state to the current condition. It predicts the changes in soil condition between the genoform and phenoform. An important implication is that while soil condition indicates the actual state of the soil at the time of measurement, soil capability, while making assessment of the potential capacity of the soil to perform various functions, it also makes predictions about how soil condition changes with time. Hence, its assessment ideally should include information about land management and how this can change soil properties and about environmental variables such as climate and landform. This was the approach common in land capability schemes such as Klingebiel and Montgomery, Emery and Helms, or the land and soil capability schemes of the Office of Environment and Heritage (OEH) and Levin et al..  </p>

<p>As it is intended to be used, the scale at which soil capability can be applied is specific soil type or to an area defined by a soil mapping unit. Frequently, and possibly mostly in its application, the soil capability of a soil mapping unit, or group of soil mapping units will be the object of assessment. A soil mapping unit represents a parcel or tract of land and this will be characterised by series of land features as well as soil properties (Table in Reference). Both the soil properties and land features can be used to assess the soil and land capability. Dominati et al. and McBratney et al. acknowledge that soils are part of the landscape and that land features or land qualities have a bearing on land evaluation and soil capability. In the latest use of the term capability for land evaluation, it has been defined as “land and soil” capability, in which both land features and specific soil properties are used in the evaluation. In this paper, soil capability is applied to tracts of land that are defined by sets of similar soil mapping units or soil landscapes. </p>

<p>At the field scale, it is possible that assessment of the soil capability can be dominated by soil properties alone because the climate and landform features are approximately constant. However, once the extent of the land to be assessed expands beyond a field, the landform is no longer constant, and at the catchment/regional scales, the climate is no longer constant. A reasonable approach is that at the broader scales, it is not possible to separate the assessment of land and soil capability. </p>
</text>
