<text id="autogum_academic_doc601" title="Daily Physical Activity Among Toddlers: Hip and Wrist Accelerometer Assessments" shortTile="daily-physical-activity" author="Soyang Kwon, Kyle Honegger, Maryann Mason" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4244/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Despite the recognized health benefits of physical activity (PA), a majority of children do not meet the recommended physical activity (PA) level. Children who are inactive at age 5 years tend to remain inactive throughout childhood and adolescence. Recent longitudinal studies have reported that PA behavior tracks at a moderate level from age 1 to 3 years, or age 1 to 5 years. Collectively, these findings suggest that PA behaviors could be established at a very young age and sustained over time. Recognizing the emerging need to assess PA behavior among very young children, studies have begun to investigate wearable sensor-measured PA levels among toddlers aged 1 and 2 years. </p>

<p>Accelerometers are widely accepted as the best practice for objectively measuring regular PA among children. In particular, ActiGraph accelerometers (Pensacola, FL, USA) are the most commonly used research-grade accelerometers. The ActiGraph accelerometers are relatively small and light devices (e.g., 4.6 cm × 3.3 cm × 1.5 cm and 19 g for the wGT3X-BT model). Several aspects of the device have been shown to be acceptable, such as its size, weight, and its ability to be worn on a hip and a wrist, by attaching it to a waist belt, a waist clip, or a wrist band, for several days, among preschoolers and older children. However, this same level of feasibility cannot be assumed for toddlers, given that their bodies are significantly smaller and their daily life activity patterns are uniquely different (e.g., naps and frequent clothes/diaper changes) from older children. Only a few studies have examined the feasibility of using ActiGraph accelerometers among toddlers. These studies reported that the use of a hip-worn accelerometer is feasible among toddlers. A paper by Johansson et al. reported the successful completion (89% of the sample) of a wrist-worn accelerometer assessment among toddlers, although it did not explicitly assess feasibility. The placement of the accelerometer (e.g., hip or wrist) is a key methodological issue that has important implications not only for data processing algorithms, but also for adherence to the monitoring protocol. Although hip- and wrist-worn accelerometers are both feasible for use in older children, wrist placement has shown higher compliance than hip-placement, while hip-worn accelerometer data have shown higher accuracy in estimating PA than wrist-worn accelerometer data. However, to our knowledge, no studies have yet reported on a comparison of the feasibility between hip and wrist placement among toddlers. The aims of this study were to examine the feasibility of using hip vs. wrist-worn ActiGraph accelerometers and to report accelerometer-derived PA metrics among toddlers. </p>
</text>
