<text id="autogum_whow_doc013" title="Enjoy a Book" shortTile="enjoy-book" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2009-08-16" dateModified="2019-04-20" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Enjoy-a-Book" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Enjoy a Book</head><p>Do you want to become an avid reader but don't know how to enjoy a book? Do you find reading tedious? Do all the words make your head hurt? It's time for you to start reading and enjoying it.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Pick out a good book</hi> that you are interested in reading. If you like mystery, head over to the mystery section. If you like fantasy, go to the fantasy section, etc. Remember to read the back of the book to see if the plot looks interesting, and most importantly,<hi rend="bold">don't judge a book by it's cover</hi>. <figure rend="Enjoy a Book Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find a quiet or calming place. This will help you become the character and focus more on the book. When you find the calm place, make sure you have a comfortable spot, for this will help you relax. <figure rend="Enjoy a Book Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Put yourself in the character's shoes. Focus on what they say. What they hear, smell, see, feel, taste. Once you put yourself where the character is, you will feel as if you are really there. <figure rend="Enjoy a Book Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Understand. Look up the meaning of all the words you don't understand or haven't heard. In case of classic literature, you could also look up some background for the story to put it into historical context. This will allow you to see the book from the authors view and understand why they wrote that or why the story progressed the way it did. <figure rend="Enjoy a Book Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Go deeper. Think outside the box. Maybe instead of what did happen, think about what would happen if the character did something different. Allow yourself to enter your book and stretch all the possibilities and limits the author has set before you and make up your own events.</item>
<item>Take notes as you read. This would allow you to think about what your read.</item>
<item>Take breaks from the book to help you picture things better. When you take these breaks that they really help you see the book more clearly. <figure rend="Enjoy a Book Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Enjoy the book. <figure rend="Enjoy a Book Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Don't skim.</hi> Read the book slowly and calmly picking up as much information as you can in order to understand the book more.</item>
<item>Remember, <hi rend="bold">reading is for enjoyment</hi>. It's not a race so take your time.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Go to your local library or book store for books</hi>. Ask for help if you don't know what to get; the people who work there will have great recommendations. If you aren't a serious reader, I would suggest starting out at the library so you can return the book if you don't like it.</item>
<item>It always helps to read books before you go to bed because it gives you something pleasant to dream about.</item>
<item>While you are reading your book, just find out the conclusion of that particular topic. You don't need to remember all the story. Just find the conclusion by yourself and write down.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Do not over-read</hi>. This could cause headaches and you would miss the thrill of guessing what's next in the book.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Books</item>
<item>Notebook</item>
<item>Pen</item></list>
</text>
