<text id="autogum_academic_doc432" title="The Potential of Open Space for Enhancing Urban Seismic Resilience: A literature Review" shortTile="potential-open-space" author="David Koren, Katarina Rus" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5942/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Conclusions</head>
<p>
In the presented research, it was found that most studies on urban resilience consider buildings, infrastructure and social community, while there is a significant lack of research on the impact of urban open space on urban resilience. Among the latter there was observed a dominant focus on the climate change issue. On the contrary, a topic on the importance of open space for urban seismic resilience is rare in the existing scientific literature. The interest in this issue has only appeared in the last decade, which offers an opportunity for further research. </p>

<p>There are some important differences considering resilience to a climate change or an earthquake. While climate change is a long-lasting and slowly progressive process, an earthquake strikes suddenly and unannounced. Therefore, coping with climate change requires constant adaptation, while seismic impact reduction addresses a quick response and effective recovery strategies. Green open spaces contribute to climate resilience enhancement. On the other hand, not only green space, but also built-up and undeveloped open space have an important role for urban seismic resilience. </p>

<p>Resilient open spaces are distinguished by their specific characteristics which depend on specific types of disaster and particular site conditions. These characteristics are the qualitative and quantitative properties of resilient open spaces which should be evaluated for the holistic resilience assessment of an urban system. In the performed literature reviews, a lack of quantitative studies on open space for urban seismic resilience has been recognized. To address this issue, the authors’ conceptual proposal for the quantitative assessment of an open space, including interactions with other urban components, is presented. The proposed draft concept applies a complex network approach for the seismic resilience assessment of the urban system as a whole. The urban system modelled as a mathematical graph, contains all urban components, including open space. Beside the general resilience, the conceptual evaluation model allows the identification of critical points and bottlenecks in the system. Therefore, it can serve as a basis for the actions of urban resilience enhancement.  </p>

<p>The strategy of urban resilience enhancement has an important impact on urban landscape configuration, city layout, engineering, hydro-engineering, urban economy, agriculture, mobility, and especially emergency management of urban systems. To achieve the goal of a resilient system, the qualitative and well-distributed open space can make a significant contribution to emergency response and city recovery. Considering this, for further research it is planned to work on the realization of the proposed draft model, which would allow seismic resilience assessment by applying algorithms of the graph theory. Moreover, to contribute to resilience enhancement different simulations of the urban system recovery scenarios based on the potential of open space would be performed.
 </p>
</text>
