<text id="autogum_voyage_doc412" title="Lanzarote" shortTile="lanzarote" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=19079" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Lanzarote</head>



<p><hi rend="bold">Lanzarote</hi> is in the <ref target="Canary%20Islands">Canary Islands</ref>, part of <ref target="Spain">Spain</ref>.</p>

<head>Regions and cities</head>

<p>The resorts of Lanzarote are in the south and southeast of the island, most of them are only a few decades old. The traditional municipalities are in the middle of the island, and agriculture is still present. The north-west of the island is sparsely populated and is characterized by bizarre volcanic structures. To the north is the Chinijo Archipelago. It includes the smaller island of La Graciosa and four other islands, including Alegranza and Montana Clare, both uninhabited.</p>

<p>The island is divided into several regions around the biggest cities:</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Arrecife">Arrecife</ref></hi>. Greatest area, the island's capital. It's the nerve center of the island and almost obligatory entrance point of Lanzarote (unless you come via Playa Blanca). The city has no great attraction except for its coastal area: <hi rend="italic">Playa del Reducto</hi>, a pretty calm beach, Fort San Gabriel on an islet accessible by La puente de los Bolas, and the Charco of San Gines, lagoon of sea water surrounded by a beautiful walk. The other center of interest of the city hides towards the merchandise port. It is the International Museum of Contemporary Art which took its quarters in the fort San José. Designed by Cesar Manrique, the museum also houses a gourmet restaurant at reasonable prices.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Haria</hi>. In the north, with famous volcanic caves and the most green area. After crossing a pass from Teguise, Haria appears like an oasis at the bottom of a valley. With a nickname "Ten thousand palm trees valley", Haria contains palms than a classic city. The major attraction of Haria is the house of César Manrique. Excentric, the artist's last home is an unfinished work. The center is quite small but nice. At the <hi rend="italic">Leon y Castilla</hi> square, it is possible to take a break on the terrace of a café, in the shade of eucalyptus. On the same square, a craft market happens every Saturday morning, selling local products.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">San Bartolomé</hi>. Central city of the island. San Bartolomé is above all a large crossroads between the North (Tinajo), South (Arrecife,East (Geria Valley) and west (Teguise). A gigantic sculpture by Cesar Manrique <hi rend="italic">The monument to the peasant</hi> is visible at the intersection of these roads. Beyond this symbolic work, Casa Museu, in the same place, allows to appreciate the local culture and its (peasant) history. Half way between a museum and a the craft shop, the creation "manriquienne" also houses a restaurant.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Teguise</hi>. Former capital, with the holiday resort Costa Teguise. It naturally presents the most representative face of the traditional aristocratic architecture. Walking through ancient cobbled streets or around the church square, the visitor can admire numbers of facades, massive doors or other wooden balconies. The Spinola Palace, home to the Timple Museum (local musical instrument) and the piracy museum hosted at Santa Barbara Fort (outside the city, placed on a volcano) are the two unavoidable attractions of the city. Also here, a large weekly market occurs on Sunday, attracting crowds of tourists - though it's rather uninteresting, since mostly overpriced rubbish is sold here.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tías</hi>. The city is not very interesting, the municipality is primarily known for Puerto del Carmen seaside resort - which is even bigger than the city. The vineyards of the Garia valley are also here.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tinajo</hi>. At the north of the island and the edge of the Parque Natural de Los Volcanes, it's the most authentic and secluded. The flow of tourists from the south and east of the island stops mostly in the Geria Valley or Timanfaya National Park. Two points are worth a visit: Mancha Blanca on one side (hermitage of Los Dolores and Sunday morning market) and the agricultural museum El Patio on the other. The <hi rend="italic">Lanzaroteño</hi> identity is undoubtedly most present here.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Yazia</hi>. A tourist center and ferry port Playa Blanca. The most spectacular scenery on the island. If the north of the island has been valued by the artistic work of Cesar Manrique, the landscapes of the south (and thus the municipality of Yaiza) are sufficient for themselves. Yaiza resides between Timanfaya, Papayago and el Golfo - a charming little sleepy village. There is little to see except maybe in the neighboring village of Uga, a smoked salmon smokehouse (you can buy one, too) and a dromedary (camel) breeding center. The latter organizes daily round trips to Timanfaya, performing a promenade for the coming tourists.</item>
</list>


<p>Lanzarote is in the same time zone as rest of the Canary Islands - Western European Time (<ref target="w:Western%20European%20Time">WET</ref>). This means the time is synchronized e.g. with <ref target="Portugal">Portugal</ref> and <ref target="United%20Kingdom">United Kingdom</ref>.</p>

<head>Other destinations</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Costa%20Teguise">Costa Teguise</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Puerto%20del%20Carmen">Puerto del Carmen</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Playa%20Blanca">Playa Blanca</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Monta%C3%B1a%20Clara">Montaña Clara</ref> - The smallest island of the Canary Islands.</item>
<item> <ref target="Alegranza">Alegranza</ref> - In the most northern part of the Canary Islands, Alegranza is another one of the smaller scaled islands. Its name comes from the Spanish word for 'Joy'. The terrain is mostly flat, home to only one small volcano. The island is part of a conservation act with (Chinijo Archipelago) Natural Park, so it has no active or documented inhabitants. The historic lighthouse of (Punta Delgada) can be found on the eastern part of the island. Built in 1865, it was declared a historical monument in December 2002.</item>
<item> <ref target="Graciosa%20%28Canary%20Islands%29">La Graciosa</ref> - Derived from the Spanish word for 'graceful', this volcanic island was formed by the Canary hot spot.The entire island is composed of volcanic rock and sand. It is also apart of the Islands conservation groups Parque Natural del Archipiélago Chinijo, Reserve of the Biosphere, and "Marine Reserve of La Graciosa". Having only a population of approximately 700, there are only two inhabited areas on the Island. those areas are Caleta del Sebo and summer-friendly Casas de Pedro Barba. The island has a school, lyceum, post office, supermarkets, a bank, port, beaches, and — except bar-restaurants — a square where bicycles can be hired (plaza). The main industry of the island is tourism and fishing. The climate of the island is one of the most commonly reported pull factors for travelers. Streets and roads on La Graciosa are unpaved sand. The Gracioseras can often be seen early each morning sweeping the streets smooth of the previous night's footprints. Motor vehicles are strictly prohibited and limited to a handful of licensed vehicles for special purposes. Since the roads are bad, and cars have to be shipped to Lanzarote for repair, about 70% of the motor vehicles on the island are old Land Rovers which often can be repaired by a local serviceman. There are no natural water sources on the island. Desalinated water has to be piped directly from Lanzarote since 2001.</item>
<item> The North - The North of Lanzarote is rural, and unusually green when compared to the rest of the island. The main town is Haria, and there are three fishing villages, Punta Mujeres, Arrieta and Orzola. The area is also home to two attraction Jameos del Agua, and Cueva de los Verdes</item>
</list>
</text>
