<text id="autogum_whow_doc432" title="Make an Elevator an Express Elevator" shortTile="make-elevator-express" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2007-08-01" dateModified="2019-10-01" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-an-Elevator-an-Express-Elevator" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make an Elevator an Express Elevator</head><p>Say you're on the first floor and your meeting is on the tenth. You get in the elevator, but you don't want it to stop because you'll be late. Here are some hacks to help get you to floor faster.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Using Button Codes and Other Methods</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Press and hold your floor. In some elevators, simply pressing your floor and holding it will do the trick. You have to hold the button all the way to your floor. <figure rend="Make an Elevator an Express Elevator Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use the "Close Door" button. When you get on the elevator, press the "Close Door" button. Often, this button will be two triangles pointing in towards each other. Continue holding the "Close Door" button as you push your floor. In some elevators, this combination will give you an express ride. <figure rend="Make an Elevator an Express Elevator Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This combination often works on Otis, Desert, and Dover elevators.</item>
<item>Note that sometimes the "Close Door" button is just a placebo for impatient riders, so this trick may not work.</item></list></item>
<item>Cancel other highlighted floors. In some elevators, you can cancel floors that have already been pressed. Of course, if people see you do so, they will probably not be very happy. Or, they may press their floor button again.  <figure rend="Make an Elevator an Express Elevator Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The simplest method is to double press the button, which works in Mitsubishi Electric. In other brands, such as Fujitec, pressing it five times works. Another method is to hold the "Open Door" button while pressing the floor button twice.</item></list></item>
<item>Use your foot. Some people suggest that you can use your foot to keep the door from opening. Simply put your foot on the middle of the elevator door, covering the edges of the door. In theory, the sole of your shoe will keep the door from opening on floors. <figure rend="Make an Elevator an Express Elevator Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Ask your building manager. If you're cozy with your building manager, you may be able to get the secret elevator code from him or her. However, you may need to promise to use it only for good. <figure rend="Make an Elevator an Express Elevator Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Using the Master Key</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Ask for a copy of the master key. The master key will give you an express ride if you have one. Your building's manager should have a key, and if you have enough clout, you may be able to just ask for a copy of the key. <figure rend="Make an Elevator an Express Elevator Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Ask your firefighter friends. Firefighters have master keys that work on most elevators, as they need them in case of emergency. If you know someone in the profession, you may be be able to convince him or her to give you a copy of the elevator's key. <figure rend="Make an Elevator an Express Elevator Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>However, understand that your firefighter friend is likely to be reluctant. Putting master keys in the hands of the public can be dangerous and possibly even illegal. Check the legality of having such a key in your area.</item></list></item>
<item>Check eBay. If you fail in your quest, you can also check eBay for master keys. You can look for all-access keys that should work in a variety of elevators. Most of these have four sides to work in multiple types of elevators. <figure rend="Make an Elevator an Express Elevator Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Buying keys is somewhat of a legal gray area. Check to see if it's legal in your state before purchasing one.</item>
<item>However, to make sure the key you buy works on your elevator, you may need to do a little research. Look at the make and model of your elevator, which is usually listed inside the elevator. Use that information to find out what kind of key it takes.</item></list></item>
<item>Use the key. To use the key, insert it in the keyhole when you get in the elevator. You may need to try more than one if it's four-sided. Leave the key in. Push the button of your floor to get an express ride. <figure rend="Make an Elevator an Express Elevator Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Realize that these hacks will not work on every elevator. In fact, some people contend that the code hacks do not work at all.</item>
<item>Use these hacks sparingly, especially in large office buildings, where there are busy people with places to be.</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
