<text id="autogum_academic_doc309" title="Measurement of Heat Dissipation and Thermal-Stability of Power Modules on DBC Substrates with Various Ceramics by SiC Micro-Heater Chip System and Ag Sinter Joining" shortTile="measurement-heat" author="Dongjin Kim, Yasuyuki Yamamoto, Shijo Nagao, Naoki Wakasugi, Chuantong Chen, Katsuaki Suganuma" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-666X/10/11/745/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Silicon carbide (SiC) and gallium nitride (GaN), are wide band-gap (WBG) semiconductors, are strongly recognized as the best materials for the power electronics applications demanding higher power and higher temperature. Since these WBG semiconductors have superior properties, kind of a wide band gap (&gt;3 eV), a high critical electric field (&gt;3 MV/cm) and a high saturation velocity (&gt;2 × 107 cm/s), SiC and GaN can enable to overcome the ultimate performances reached by silicon (Si) based devices, in terms of power conversion efficiency. In addition, WBG semiconductor devices can be operating much higher temperatures (&gt;250 °C) than Si based devices (&lt;150 °C), this means massive, complex and heavy cooling systems can be eliminated from power conversion systems. Inverters and converters automotive components can be change to smaller by the simply heat dissipation design of in the high temperature environments. In general, the structure of the power module has multi-layer structures of a semiconductor chip and a heat dissipation/insulation plate. All the layers have different material properties like a coefficient of thermal expansion (CTE), which causes thermos-mechanical stress during repetitive operating. </p>

<p>Besides, to withstand higher power and higher thermal density, how to insulate electricity and dissipate heat is one of the key issues of WBG power conversion systems. Therefore, there have been some issues, for instance how to interconnect these multi-layers to implement in high temperature and have a thermal-stable reliability. In addition, power electronic substrate plays an important role in dissipating heat to prevent power electronic module failure. Heat dissipation/insulation substrate, which is a direct bonded copper (DBC) and a direct bonded aluminum (DBA), are existed between power semiconductor device and heat sink. Heat is transferred from surface of the power semiconductor device to the heat sink. The DBC and DBA were metallized both side of ceramic plate, to improve the thermal conductivity of ceramic substrates and form circuits, and were considered as the most promising substrates for power modules due to their excellent thermal conductivity, low thermal resistance, and high insulation voltage. </p>

<p>However, the sandwich structure of the DBC and DBA substrate will cause thermo-mechanical stresses due to the CTE mismatch. It has been reported that heat resistance of the substrate depending on the type of ceramics and metals. In this regard, our group carried out to evaluate thermo-mechanical stability of various ceramic applied active metal brazed (AMB) DBC substrates with the Ni plating layer during a harsh thermal shock cycling test at the temperature range of from −50 °C to 250 °C. The DBC substrate with silicon nitride (Si3N4-DBC) ceramics middle layer indicate no serious damage within 1,000 cycles of thermal shock cycles, while those of an aluminum nitride (AlN) and alumina (Al2O3) caused by Cu layer severe delamination after the same cycles. </p>

<p>The results indicated that the failures may impress that the AlN and Al2O3 have critical disadvantage of higher CTE value and lower toughness than Si3N4. Since this previous study just investigated the DBC substrate itself, the failures must be induced by the mismatch between Cu and ceramic, meaning that the stress occurred from the DBC. Such thermal cycles give only homogeneous temperature change in the substrate specimens as shown in <figure>Figure 1</figure>a. However, the realistic thermal distributions in a ceramic substrate must have a large temperature gradient to transfer the generated heat from surface of the device chips to the cooling system as shown in <figure>Figure 1</figure>b. The stress induced by the CTE mismatch during the thermal conduction from chips to cooling system was more complexed than single DBC substrate. Therefore, the evaluation of such a practical temperature distribution is urgently needed for designing power module. In this context, power cycling test is the strongly useful evaluation methods to evaluate the reliability of a device packaging used in a condition similar to those in actual operations. In this process, the heat transfer performance of such a substrate mainly depends on the thermal properties of employed ceramic materials, e.g., Al2O3, AlN, and Si3N4. Power modules was required with a comprehensive combination of conductive Cu and insulation ceramics, involving the layer thicknesses and circuit patterns to achieve both thermal management and the least power loss at the same time. Usually, to measure the thermal resistance of devices after a power cycling test, it needs an equipment of power cycling system and also a T3ster system which means the Thermal Transient Tester system. It is a technology to monitor the thermal transport through the devices. However, both of the power cycling system and the T3ster system are very expensive and need to take up a lot of space. A simple, fast and miniaturized thermal measurement system is actually necessary. </p>
</text>
