<text id="autogum_interview_doc657" title="part0_Gay Talese on the state of journalism, Iraq and his life" shortTile="partgay-talese-state" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-27" dateModified="2019-01-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gay_Talese_on_the_state_of_journalism%2C_Iraq_and_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Gay Talese on the state of journalism, Iraq and his life</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 27, 2007</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gay%20Talese">Gay Talese</ref> wants to go to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Green%20Zone,%20Iraq">Iraq</ref>.  "It so happens there is someone that's working on such a thing right now for me," the 75-year-old legendary journalist and author told <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref>.  "Even if I was on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al-Jazeera">Al-Jazeera</ref> with a gun to my head, I wouldn't be pleading with those bastards! I'd say, 'Go ahead. Make my day.'"</p>
<p>Few reporters will ever reach the stature of Talese.  His 1966 profile of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frank%20Sinatra">Frank Sinatra</ref>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frank%20Sinatra%20Has%20a%20Cold">Frank Sinatra Has a Cold</ref></hi>, was not only cited by <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Economist%20(magazine)">The Economist</ref></hi> as the greatest profile of Sinatra ever written, but is considered the greatest of any celebrity profile ever written.  In the 70th anniversary issue of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Esquire%20Magazine">Esquire</ref></hi> in October 2003, the editors declared the piece the "Best Story Esquire Ever Published."</p>
<p>Talese helped create and define a new style of literary reporting called <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20Journalism">New Journalism</ref>.  Talese himself told <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National%20Public%20Radio">National Public Radio</ref> he rejects this label ("The term new journalism became very fashionable on college campuses in the 1970s and some of its practitioners tended to be a little loose with the facts. And that's where I wanted to part company.")  </p>
<p>He is not bothered by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bancroft%20family">Bancrofts</ref> selling <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Wall%20Street%20Journal">The Wall Street Journal</ref></hi>—"It's not like we should lament the passing of some noble dynasty!"—to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rupert%20Murdoch">Rupert Murdoch</ref>, but he is bothered by how the press supported and sold the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraq%20War">Iraq War</ref> to the American people.  "The press in Washington got us into this war as much as the people that are controlling it," said Talese.  "They took information that was second-hand information, and they went along with it."  He wants to see the Washington press corp disbanded and sent around the country to get back in touch with the people it covers; that the press should not be so focused on--and in bed with--the federal government.  </p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Augusten_Burroughs_on_addiction,_writing,_his_family_and_his_new_book">Augusten Burroughs once said</ref> that writers are experience junkies, and Talese fits the bill.  Talese--who has been married to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nan%20Talese">Nan Talese</ref> (she edited <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James%20Frey">James Frey</ref>'s <hi rend="italic">Million Little Piece</hi>) for fifty years--can be found at baseball games in Cuba or the gay bars of Beijing, wanting to see humanity in all its experience.</p>
<p>Below is <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> reporter David Shankbone's interview with Gay Talese.  </p>
<head id="On_Gay_Talese">On Gay Talese</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">David Shankbone:  Does it bother you that your name has come to mean 'homosexual'?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Gay Talese:</hi>  No, it doesn't bother me at all!  I've always been called that, I had bylines in high school.  I started getting bylines when I was in high school and I wrote for the <hi rend="italic">Ocean City Sentinel</hi>.  I was Gay Talese.  I even had a column when I went to college in Alabama, it was called <hi rend="italic">Sports Gay-zing</hi> - I was the sports editor for the college paper.</p>
</text>
