<text id="autogum_interview_doc857" title="part2_Q and A with New Zealand Prime Minister hopeful" shortTile="partq-new-zealand" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-05-17" dateModified="2019-09-19" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Q_and_A_with_New_Zealand_Prime_Minister_hopeful" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What parties would you consider as possible coalition partners? Specifically the Maori Party, the Greens and NZ First?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.K.</hi>: National remains focussed on its own policies to lift after-tax incomes and provide the social safety nets that we have all come to expect and deserve.  MMP means that we may have to speak with other parties after the election, and we will do that.  But it would be an insult to the people of New Zealand to start talking about those things before they’ve even had their say.  Frankly, National will work with the cards we are dealt by the public, that is what MMP is all about. I have not ruled ‘out’ any party, nor have I ruled ‘in’ any party.  These are matters that the public must have a say in.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What kind of tax-cuts package are looking at implementing if you win the election?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.K.</hi>: National will be announcing an ongoing programme of personal tax cuts closer to the election.  We have been consistent with our view that reducing personal taxation should be a routine part of Government business in a growing economy. At its heart taxation is an argument about trust.  National thinks New Zealanders should be trusted with more of their own money, Labour does not.  National understands that taxpayers are the generators of the income that provides the social safety nets we deserve and expect.  We will recognise that with a programme that gives people more incentive to work hard and get ahead under their own steam.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Will it require any cuts to any public services?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.K.</hi>: No, in fact the fallacy of that argument is being laid in front of New Zealanders by the current Finance Minister, who, faced with embarrassingly large surpluses and growing resentment among those paying his bills, now says he accepts he was wrong and that National was right. Frankly, I do not think he can be trusted to do as he says on taxation.  The only personal tax cut he has ever offered to New Zealanders was cancelled to pay for his other spending promises – but only after he’d been re-elected.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How are you looking at closing the gap between Australia and New Zealand in terms of the economy?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.K.</hi>: Starting to close the gap between Australian and New Zealand after-tax incomes is something I take very seriously because I want New Zealand and New Zealanders to be optimistic about their futures. I don’t want them forced to move to Australia to make ends meet. The wage gap that has been allowed to widen in recent years will not be closed overnight – but we must start trying.  Michael Cullen once said New Zealand was ‘probably better off’ without those who left New Zealand to live in Australia, but I strongly disagree.</p>
</text>
