<text id="autogum_news_doc653" title="Anti-abortion March for Life draws thousands in Washington, D.C." shortTile="antiabortion-march" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-01-27" dateModified="2017-02-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Anti-abortion_March_for_Life_draws_thousands_in_Washington%2C_D.C." speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Anti-abortion March for Life draws thousands in Washington, D.C.</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 28, 2017</hi></p>
<p>Yesterday,  thousands of anti-abortion protesters rallied in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Washington,_D.C.">Washington, D.C.</ref> Unlike the half a million who walked to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/the%20White%20House">the White House</ref> waving signs last Saturday, these came to support one of the policies espoused by the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> president <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Donald_Trump">Donald Trump</ref> and Vice President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mike_Pence">Mike Pence</ref>: making <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Abortion">abortion</ref> harder to come by.</p>
<p>This event, called the March for Life, has taken place every year since 1973, the year abortion was ruled legal in the U.S. by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roe%20v%20Wade">Roe v Wade</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_Supreme_Court">Supreme Court</ref> decision. "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pro-life">Pro-life</ref>" is the umbrella term of choice of the U.S. political movement that favors rendering abortion illegal and less accessible and "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/pro-choice">pro-choice</ref>" is the corresponding term for the movement that favors keeping it legal and accessible.</p>
<p>Donald Trump has recently reversed <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref>'s repeal of a global funding ban, which prohibits the use of U.S. funds for any organization that provides or counsels for abortions abroad.</p>
<p>Trump specifically asked Vice President Mike Pence to attend the march. "Life is winning in America!" he told the crowd, noting that he serves under "a president who I proudly say stands for the right to life." A Pew Research Institute poll taken this year shows that 69% of Americans support the Roe v Wade decision, up from 60% in 1992.</p>
<p>One reason why many opponents of abortion say the procedure should be illegal is the belief, often religious, that life begins at <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/conception">conception</ref>. Correspondingly, the event was accompanied by religious music and speeches, including one by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catholic">Catholic</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishop%20Timothy%20Dolan">Archbishop Timothy Dolan</ref>. One reporter for the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BBC">BBC</ref></hi> noted a large number of young women in the crowd, especially college students. Signs included "Women DO Regret Abortion" and "I am the Pro-Life Generation," many held up by young women. Others showed pictures of <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/fetuses">fetuses</ref>, quoted <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bible">Bible</ref> verses, or called for the defunding of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Planned_Parenthood">Planned Parenthood</ref> by name. There is already a law in place, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyde%20Amendment">Hyde Amendment</ref>, which bans the use of federal funds for abortions, though this money can go to organizations that also perform abortions so long as the funds are kept separate.</p>
<p>As governor of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Indiana">Indiana</ref>, Mike Pence established some of the country's strictest abortion laws. Years ago, Donald Trump said publicly that he was "very pro-choice" but has since changed his stance. Trump commented, as is his custom, via <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Twitter">Tweet</ref>, "To all of you marching — you have my full support!"</p>
<p>The crowds in Washington, D.C. yesterday numbered in the tens of thousands, in contrast to the roughly 500,000 in last week's Women's March, though some organizations did attend both events. March for Life President Jeanne Mancini told <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/National_Public_Radio">National Public Radio</ref></hi>, "I think we're a pretty different march — we're a one-issue march."</p>
<p>The abortion rate in the United States hit a record low in 2013, but the pro- and anti-abortion rights movements are at odds about why. Both sides credit increased availability of contraceptives, but anti-abortion organizations tend to give more credit to state-level laws that have made it harder to keep abortion clinics open and limit abortions to only the early stages of pregnancy. As <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NARAL%20Pro-Choice%20America">NARAL Pro-Choice America</ref> President <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ilyse%20Hogue">Ilyse Hogue</ref> pointed out, the anti-abortion movement now has the opportunity to work at the federal level; "We're living at the apex of a 40-year, state-by-state effort by the anti-choice people [...] We have to be prepared for the fact that they've got all the pieces in place to do real damage."</p>
</text>
