<text id="autogum_bio_doc185" title="Little Bear (Native American leader)" shortTile="little-bear-native" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-04-02" dateModified="2019-11-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Little_Bear_%28Native_American_leader%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Little Bear (Native American leader)</head><figure><caption>Native American Cree leader Little Bear <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cabinet_card">cabinet portrait</ref> from 1906</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Little Bear</hi> (<hi rend="italic">born </hi>Ayimâsis<hi rend="italic"> or Macquettoquet</hi>) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cree">Cree</ref> leader who lived in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alberta">Alberta</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Idaho">Idaho</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Montana">Montana</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saskatchewan">Saskatchewan</ref> regions of Canada and the United States, in the 19th and early 20th centuries. He is known for his participation in the 1885 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North-West_Rebellion">North-West Rebellion</ref>, which was fought in Alberta and Saskatchewan.</p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>Son of tribal leader <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Bear">Big Bear</ref>, his exact date of birth is unknown, but some assume it to be in the mid-1800s. One account has him being 43 years old in 1897,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> while another said Little Bear was already in his 70s in 1915.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> He may have been born in the early or mid-1840s. He was probably living in the Idaho, Montana, and Wyoming region in the 1850s.</p>
<p>Little Bear said in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Butte,_Montana">Butte, Montana</ref> in either 1912 or 1913, that his father lived along the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Snake_River">Snake River</ref> in Idaho but relocated to the Butte, Montana region to hunt for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_bison">buffalo</ref> and other wild game.</p>
<head>The Black Hills War</head>
<p>Little Bear was said to have participated in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Sioux_War_of_1876">Great Sioux War of 1876</ref> or Black Hills War. However, nearly all the battles of that war were fought in Montana and northeastern Wyoming. After the War, many Cree fled north to Canada and west into British Columbia, Idaho, Oregon, and Washington, but Little Bear and his family continued to live in extreme northern Montana.</p>
<head>Treaty of Fort Industry</head>
<p>Apparently, a different native of the name Little Bear was at the 1805 signing of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treaty_of_Fort_Industry">Treaty of Fort Industry</ref>, but this could not have been the Little Bear discussed here as he was not born yet at that time.
In July 4, 1805 Little Bear along with leaders from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wyandot_people">Wyandot</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottawa_(tribe)">Ottawa</ref>, Chipawa, Munsee and Delaware, Shawanee, and Pottawatima nations signed the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treaty_of_Fort_Industry">Treaty of Fort Industry</ref> with the United States government at Fort Industry in Ohio. This treaty ceded their lands to the US government but allowed for the tribes to continue to hunt and fish in the lands that they formerly owned.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>The North-West Rebellion and aftermath</head>
<p>In early 1885, the Cree living in central Alberta and central Saskatchewan fought and lost in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North-West_Rebellion">North-West Rebellion</ref> against Canada.</p>
<head>Frog Lake Massacre</head>
<p>During the Rebellion, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wandering_Spirit_(Cree_leader)">Wandering Spirit</ref> led a group of  soldiers—including Little Bear—into attacking the tiny settlement of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frog_Lake,_Alberta">Frog Lake, Alberta</ref>. They killed nine Whites in what became known as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frog_Lake_Massacre">Frog Lake Massacre</ref>.</p>
<head>Return to Montana</head>
<p>After the Rebellion ended, Little Bear and Lucky Man, knowing the Canadian Whites were after them, fled. The two gathered many of their people and journeyed back to Montana. They slipped through the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Babb,_Montana">Babb, Montana</ref> region in 1885 and hid out in that region, and then roamed about their original Montana homeland. They frequented the land on and around the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flathead_Indian_Reservation">Flathead Reservation</ref> which the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Confederated_Salish_and_Kootenai_Tribes_of_the_Flathead_Nation">Flathead Indians'</ref> agent did not like. Little Bear was considered the leader of the Ojibwas of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basin,_Montana">Basin, Montana</ref> region (southwest Montana).</p>
<head>Deportation</head>
<p>Montana native and non-native peoples did not welcome Little Bear and his group, saying he had not been born in the United States.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> They called for Little Bear and the Ojibwas he led to be deported to Canada. </p>
<p>For the first couple of years after returning to their original Montana homeland, many of Little Bear's people roamed throughout the vast <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blackfeet_Indian_Reservation">Blackfeet reservation</ref> on the U.S. side of the line. In 1888, the United States reduced the size of the Blackfeet reservation and divided it into three small reservations - the Blackfeet reservation, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fort_Belknap_Indian_Reservation">Fort Belknap reservation</ref>, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fort_Peck_Indian_Reservation">Fort Peck reservation</ref>. Life got harder for Little Bear and his people, and they often went hungry. </p>
<p>In 1895, the United States deported Little Bear, Lucky Man and hundreds of other landless Cree and Ojibwas of Montana back to Canada. Little Bear and Lucky Man feared the death penalty for their participation in the attacks at Frog Lake. When they arrived in Canada, they were apprehended. One account has it they stood trial for their part in the Massacre and were acquitted of the charges, while another says no charges were laid against Little Bear as the magistrate said the evidence did not deem charges. (It is noticeable that Little Bear is listed among the eight Natives hanged on Nov. 27, 1885 at Battleford, so perhaps the government did not want the confusion, or mistaken identity to come out in public.)  </p>
<p>Little Bear settled in Canada perhaps at Onion Lake<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> and in 1898 travelled, with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Chantler_McDougall">Rev. John McDougall</ref>, to Ottawa to complain of the treatment of his people by the government.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>He soon returned to Montana.</p>
<head>Efforts to gain a reservation</head>
<p>Little Bear knew he had to follow the Chippewa leader <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chief_Rocky_Boy">Rocky Boy</ref> if the landless nations of Montana were to gain reservations. In 1902, Rocky Boy and Little Bear attempted to gain either a reservation or tribal recognition on the Flathead reservation. The bill to make the Flathead reservation for other landless tribes failed in 1904. In 1905, 1906, 1908, and around 1911 Little Bear contacted Canadian leaders to request land for some of the Cree of Montana. At least five <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First_Nations">First Nations</ref> were set aside for the Chippewa of Montana. They are the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Onion_Lake_Cree_Nation">Onion Lake</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samson_First_Nation">Samson</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ermineskin_Cree_Nation">Ermineskin</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_Bull_138b">Louis Bull</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Montana_First_Nation">Montana First Nations</ref>. In 1910 Little Bear and his tribe joined the Rocky Boy Reservation.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<head>The Babb Chippewa reservation</head>
<p>In 1909, the United States set aside a new Chippewa reservation within the Blackfeet reservation, in Montana, between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint_Mary_Lake">Saint Mary Lake</ref>, Babb, and the Canada–US border. Chief Rocky Boy was the first to settle there, followed by Little Bear and the people he led. In all, around 200 Chippewa and Cree people settled there.</p>
<head>Rocky Boy reservation</head>
<p>Since hundreds of Chippewas and Cree continued to remain landless, Rocky Boy and Little Bear stepped up their efforts to get another reservation set aside in Montana. Rocky Boy's brother, Pennahto, told Little Bear to request the old Fort Assiniboine Military Reservation be set aside as a new reservation. Neither Pennahto nor Rocky Boy lived to see the establishment of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rocky_Boy_Indian_Reservation">Rocky Boy Reservation</ref>. After Rocky Boy Reservation was officially established in 1916, Little Bear became its first Chairman. He was already an old man at the time. Little Bear died in 1921, at or nearly eighty years of age.</p>
</text>
