<text id="autogum_interview_doc389" title="part2_The Raveonettes on love, death, desire and war" shortTile="partthe-raveonettes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-16" dateModified="2010-12-23" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Raveonettes_on_love%2C_death%2C_desire_and_war" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  I don't care about it at all because if people compared us to bands that are really shitty then I would probably mind.  But if they compare us to Buddy Holly and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Everly%20Brothers">The Everly Brothers</ref>, then I think it's fine.  You always need names for bands so you can tell people what they sound like.  That's fine.  Those are good names...I really don't care about it one bit.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Did you guys follow the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phil%20Spector">Phil Spector</ref> trial?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  A little bit.  I didn't have any thoughts on it.  It's 50/50</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Knowing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ronnie%20Spector">Ronnie Spector</ref> it must have been an interesting perspective to see it from.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  Well, Sune knows her.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  I'm good friends with his daughter, and that was another weird perspective, really.  Because that was more a sad perspective because obviously she was very saddened by her dad being on trial for murder.  That was a whole different way of looking at it all of a sudden.  She's coming tonight, actually.  I don't know....I know he has been throwing around guns for ages, so if a gun went off I wouldn't be surprised.  On the other hand, why would he kill someone?  I don't know.  I have no idea.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Dogme influenced you guys early on, does it still?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  It's still there, a lot actually.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  But I think it's more of a subconscious, integrated thing.  It has become an integrated part of how The Raveonettes sound.  Initially it's what created the sound and being more aware of the tools and the creative process as a Dogmeist, and the rules.  But now it's just what happens automatically.  We tend to gravitate more towards the minimal sound and very simple things.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  We don't' think about it.  It's like if I write a song at home I don't think it has to be in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/B%20flat">B flat</ref>, I just play in B flat.  That's just a starting point, and I don't think about it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are you more inspired by things in nature or man made things?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  Probably more man made things than nature...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  Yeah</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  People are sort of man made things too, I guess.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Sure; made by man.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  Don't you think Sune?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  Yeah, I probably prefer man made.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  Are you talking musically or aesthetically?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It's an open question.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  I don't know.  I think with the Raveonettes there's a lot of inspiration from man made things...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Like cities vs. mountains.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  They are all good in certain ways.  I use them all in different ways.  Nature doesn't really inspire me to be creative, it just inspires me to relax and feel good about myself, which is a good thing, too.  I need the city and that kind of life.</p>
</text>
