<text id="autogum_voyage_doc152" title="Ireland" shortTile="ireland" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=15723" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ireland</head>


<ref target="http://www.ireland.com"><hi rend="bold">Ireland</hi></ref> (<ref target="Irish%20phrasebook">Irish</ref>: <hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Éire</hi></hi>), also known as the <hi rend="bold">Republic of Ireland</hi> (Irish: <hi rend="italic">Poblacht na hÉireann</hi>), has a rich culture that, along with its people, has been exported around the world.

<p>Ireland, in fact, has two cultures: the historical Gaelic culture (including one of the oldest literatures in Western Europe) and the more recent English-speaking culture which largely replaced it. It can be worth your while to dig a little deeper before visiting Ireland to discover something about the older world that lies beneath. It is a world still living, though not always visible.</p>

<p>Some Irish history has been very dark indeed, but it remains a land of poets, story-tellers, and musicians, with marvellous scenery, an advanced knowledge economy, first-rate infrastructures, and leading industries, with a high gross domestic product and standard of living.</p>

<head>Regions</head>

<ref target="Northern%20Ireland">Northern Ireland</ref>, a home nation of the <ref target="United%20Kingdom">United Kingdom</ref>, is covered in its own separate article.
<head>Cities and towns</head>


<p><hi rend="italic">For cities in <ref target="Northern%20Ireland">Northern Ireland</ref>, see the separate article.</hi></p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Baile Átha Cliath</hi>) — the capital and largest city in Ireland. With excellent pubs, fine architecture and good shopping, Dublin is a very popular tourist destination and is the fourth most visited European capital.</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Corcaigh</hi>) — the country's second biggest city — on the banks of the River Lee. Founded c.600 by St Finbarre and known for great food (especially seafood), pubs, shopping and festivals. If you venture outside of the city along the coastline which borders the Atlantic Ocean, you will find long windy beaches, beautiful villages with history, castles and an array of outdoor activities to enjoy.</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Gaillimh</hi>) — a city on the river Corrib on the west coast of Ireland. Famous for its festivals and its location on Galway Bay. Known as the City of Tribes, Galway's summer is filled with festivals of music, food, Irish language and culture. Galway hosts over fifty festivals a year, including the Galway Oyster Festival. The locals seem to give off a positive Bohemian vibe. Galway is split between two types of beautiful landscape: the gorgeous mountains to the west, and the east's farming valleys.</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Cill Áirne</hi>)— Possibly, the most popular tourist destination in Ireland. A pleasant town in its own right, it is also the start of most <ref target="Ring%20of%20Kerry">Ring of Kerry</ref> trips.</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Cill Chainnigh</hi>) — attractive medieval town, known as the Marble City — home to the Cat Laughs Comedy Festival, held annually in early June.</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Leitir Ceanainn</hi>) — Main town in <ref target="County%20Donegal">County Donegal</ref>, designated gateway status and reputed to be the fastest growing town in Europe. Good base for travelling in Donegal.</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Luimneach</hi>) — a city strategically sited where the river Shannon broadens into its mighty estuary in the south-west of the country. First city to receive the designation of National City of Culture (2014).</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Sligeach</hi>) — Home to W.B. Yeats, internationally renowned poet. Mountains and beaches, scenery in general are the best points of Sligo.</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Port Láirge</hi>) — Ireland's oldest city. In the south-east and close to the ferry port at <ref target="Rosslare">Rosslare</ref>. Waterford is a popular visit for those who want to learn more about the most ancient history of Ireland. It is quite possibly one of the best cities in the country as it is not too large and is full of history. Many festivals take place throughout the year including Spraoi. The food is good and the Granary Museum is the best for ancient Irish history in the country. Don't forget to try a blaa before you leave (a floury bread bun peculiar to this area of Ireland).</item>
</list>
<head>Other destinations</head>

<p><hi rend="italic">For other destinations in <ref target="Northern%20Ireland">Northern Ireland</ref> such as the <ref target="Giant%27s%20Causeway">Giant's Causeway</ref>, see the separate article.</hi></p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Oileáin Árann</hi>) — in Galway Bay</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Brú Na Bóinne</hi> — in Co. Meath are some of the finest neolithic monuments in the world, the oldest of which is <ref target="http://www.heritageireland.ie/en/midlands-eastcoast/brunaboinnevisitorcentre/">Newgrange</ref>, dating back to 3100 BC.</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Boirinn</hi>) and the (<hi rend="italic">Aillte an Mhothair</hi>) — both in the County Clare</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Conamara</hi>) — an Irish speaking region in Western County Galway</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Contae Dhún na nGall</hi>) — the coastal regions of this county have spectacular scenery and excellent beaches</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Corca Dhuibhne</hi>) — a Gaeltecht region (Irish-speaking district) in the very South West corner of Ireland</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Gleann Dá Loch</hi>) — fine ruins and hiking trails in Co. Wicklow</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Cionn tSáile</hi>) — gastronomic excellence in Ireland's oldest town</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Ring of Kerry</hi>) and — (<hi rend="italic">Sceilg Mhichíl</hi>) in County Kerry</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Iarthar Chorcaí</hi>) — mountains, coves, islands and beaches at the very south of the country</item>
</list>


<head>History</head>
<p>The earliest evidence of human presence in Ireland goes back to 10,500 BCE, when the country was inhabited by a handful of hunter gatherers. Some time before 4000 BCE they were followed by Neolithic settlers, who had migrated northwards along the European coastline from Spain. They brought farming with them and a liking for large stone monuments. They established some of the earliest field systems known in Europe, preserved until the 20 century under layers of peat. </p>

<p>The Bronze Age – marked by skilful metalworking – began in Ireland around 2500 BCE. During the Iron Age (beginning c. 800 BCE) a Celtic language and culture emerged in Ireland, possibly as a result of cultural diffusion from Britain, since there is no archaeological evidence of a Celtic "invasion". </p>

<p>Ireland was Christianised from the 5th century onward, and this brought with it literacy and a knowledge of Latin culture. Monastic towns were established, becoming centres of learning and literature. The monks were the first to commit Ireland’s legends to writing, and composed exquisite nature poetry. The monasteries were a prime target for the <ref target="Vikings%20and%20the%20Old%20Norse">Norsemen</ref> who invaded in the late 8th century and eventually established important settlements in Dublin, Wexford, Waterford, Cork and Limerick. Local military alliances shifted and melded frequently but monastic Christian culture endured and sent successful missionaries to Scotland, England and as far afield as Switzerland.</p>

<p>The Normans invaded in the early 12th century and set in place Ireland's uneasy position within England's sphere of influence. The Gaelic Ireland they entered had a distinctive society which tended to assimilate newcomers linguistically and culturally. An intensively cultivated classical tradition had developed in the Irish language, producing a unique literature which was matched by a rich folk culture. The Normans had brought English-speaking followers with them, but English for a long time remained marginal. </p>

<p>Irish lords retained a great deal of practical independence until the end of the Elizabethan period. The English Crown, in the person of Elizabeth I, made a determined attempt to impose its own power towards the end of the 16th century, with resistance being led by powerful northern lords, especially Red Hugh O'Neill. Their defeat meant the gradually replacement of the native elite by English landlords.</p>

<p>Irish society and culture were most severely disrupted during the Cromwellian period in the 17 century, when native leaders tried to re-establish Irish independence but were weakened by internal dissension. Despite this, Irish language and culture remained strong, with the 18th century seeing a literary flowering. General adoption of the English language did not occur until the second half of the 19 century, largely as a consequence of bilingualism. </p>

<p>The Act of Union that came into force on 1 January 1801 — in which Catholics, 90% of the Irish population, were excluded from Parliament — saw Ireland joining the United Kingdom. While Great Britain was the <ref target="Industrial%20Britain">cradle of the Industrial Revolution</ref> in the 18th and 19th centuries, Ireland remained a farming country; millions of Irish emigrated to Britain, North America and Australia, where the men often worked as labourers and the women as domestic servants. Initially, they often spoke little English.</p>

<p>Irish nationalism remained strong in the 19th century, often expressed through English. Much attention was drawn to the evils of landlordism, exacerbated by the Great Famine of the 1840s, which left many dead and caused a wave of emigration. At the end of the century there occurred the Gaelic Revival, with influential urban intellectuals insisting on the need to modernise and extend Gaelic culture as a basic principle of Irish nationality. Some of them were later at the fore of armed resistance to British rule. The Catholic Church, which had suffered various degrees of persecution from the 16th century on, had now been reorganised and strengthened. It became a potent element in Irish nationalism and a symbol for many of Irish identity, though its influence was to wane in the later 20th century. </p>

<p>By 1900 institutions of British origin were firmly established in Ireland. English was the language of the vast majority but had a strongly native flavour; this made itself felt in a literature which was to become world famous. Irish was still cultivated by a small minority and produced a distinguished modern literature of its own.</p>

<p>Some bars to non-Anglican civic participation had been removed in the 1820s, but in the latter half of the 19th century and early 20th century the subject of Irish home rule was a major debate within the British parliament. After several failed attempts, a Home Rule bill finally passed through parliament in 1914 although the start of the first world war saw its indefinite postponement. A failed rebellion on Easter Monday in 1916 showed a hint of things to come with years of war to follow, beginning with the Irish War of Independence (1919-1921) and continuing with the Irish Civil War (1922-1923).</p>

<p>Eventually a somewhat stable situation emerged with the independence of 26 of Ireland's counties known as the Irish Free State; the remaining six, in the north-east of the country and comprising two-thirds of the ancient province of Ulster, remained part of the United Kingdom — a status that has continued to the present day. In 1949 the Irish Free State became "Ireland" (also known as the Republic of Ireland) and withdrew from the British Commonwealth.</p>

<p>Ireland's history post-partition has been marked to some extent by violence. A a period known as "The Troubles", generally regarded as beginning in the late 1960s, saw large scale confrontation between opposing paramilitary groups seeking to either keep Northern Ireland as part of the United Kingdom or bring it into the Republic. The Troubles saw many ups and downs in intensity of fighting and on occasion were even responsible for terrorist attacks in Britain and continental Europe. The governments of both the UK and the Republic were opposed to all terrorist groups. A peace settlement known as the Good Friday Agreement was finally approved in 1998 and is being implemented. All signs point to this agreement holding steady.</p>

<p>Though a relatively poor country for much of the 20th century, Ireland joined the European Community in 1973 (at the same time as the United Kingdom). Between the mid 1990s and 2008, Ireland had a massive economic boom (and was called "The Celtic Tiger"), becoming one of the richest countries in Europe. However, the global banking crisis and subsequent recession hit Ireland hard, with high levels of unemployment and emigration. The economy is now recovering and many emigrants are returning.</p>
</text>
