<text id="autogum_academic_doc678" title="People with Learning Disabilities and Smartphones: Testing the Usability of a Touch-Screen Interface" shortTile="people-learning-disabilities" author="Peter Williams, Sidharth Shekhar" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2227-7102/9/4/263/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
This section explores the general lessons that can be elicited from the disparate results outlined above. One way to attempt a global interpretation of results of this experiment is to differentiate between a user’s general beliefs and attitudes regarding technology, and a specific perception to a particular application. In the case of our participants, how they approached the system-specific tasks—especially in the face of difficulty or negative feedback, for example, at the hands of the error message in the map, or the unexpected navigation screen—might be indicative of their a priori attitude towards digital or mobile use in general. Only with encouragement from the researcher and with successful iterations were the participants enabled to develop an application-specific opinion and comfort level that allowed for greater ease of use. Due to the fact that universally accepted mobile-native affordances were used throughout this app, such as the text and appearance of the buttons, the map functionality, and user interface touch/swipe movement patterns, one can infer that either the specific participant group may have not had as much exposure to standardised mobile digital experiences as others, and/or that their intrinsic motivation levels for interacting with mobile applications was predisposed to waning in the face of negative feedback.  </p>

<p>Despite differences in layout, design and input mechanisms, one result was similar to prior work undertaken on web interfaces. The propensity to choose the top two photos when deciding on which attraction to locate, reflects work undertaken by the author on web site design and usability on static devices, where he developed the idea of ‘serial access’. This can be defined as the practice of linearly absorbing each unit of information, without skipping any phrases or words that may be irrelevant and without looking beyond the immediate content encountered. Such behaviour leads to content being so absorbed from left to right and top to bottom. Interestingly, in the mobile environment, the easiest content with which to interact for people using their thumb to interact may not be at the top, but on the right of the screen (for right-handed people). Nevertheless, results showed that the top two photos were by far the most chosen, representing 10 out of 18 iterations. Indeed, the photo on the right (The London Eye) was chosen 6 times—30% of all iterations. At the other end of the scale, those photos only visible (or fully visible) on swiping were only chosen twice, and then only in third iterations, tentative indications that the reluctance to scroll identified in the author’s prior work is in evidence in a mobile environment, despite the fact that the swipe action required may be easier than using either a mouse or arrow keys. We classified this as an affordance difficulty due to the fact that there was no visible indicator (such as an arrow pointing down) to indicate a downward swipe. However, the photos themselves were not strictly controlled variables and may have played a part in the selection (for example the natural visual attractiveness of the London Eye).  </p>

<p>There were also other limitations to the study. First, the lack of prior research on which to build is a constant limitation where innovative technology is an area of interest. By the time the research cycle of finding a topic, obtaining funding, carrying out the study, writing up, and publishing has been undertaken, the technology will have moved on and other areas appearing for study. For example, the author’s PhD on website design for people with learning disabilities, completed only five years ago, is unlikely to be replicated or built upon, as the world of IT is now mobile and dominated by apps rather than by web pages on large screens. This is, indeed, one reason we decided to create an app which tested interactions likely to be used over a long period of time (tap, swipe, etc.). </p>

<p>Second, as with the studies by McKenzie et al. and Ho et al. cited earlier, the study relied on gatekeepers to interpret a given participant profile. Archibald and Munce describe how gatekeepers may limit access to potential participants to those of their choice, such as those likely to have ‘an above average understanding of the [research] instead of participants with a more typical profile’ (p. 35). Participants had varied experience with technology, although in a way this could be seen as a strength, permitting a wider spectrum of user behaviour to be observed.  </p>

<p>A longer time-lapse between app demonstration and the usability test may have elicited more usability issues, as the participants would not have been able to rely on memory so much. However, this heightened possibility for errors may not have been justified purely in terms of participant wellbeing. </p>
</text>
