<text id="autogum_interview_doc600" title="part5_Wikinews interviews John Wolfe, Democratic Party presidential challenger to Barack Obama" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-05-19" dateModified="2013-09-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_John_Wolfe%2C_Democratic_Party_presidential_challenger_to_Barack_Obama" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>I would go in there and do just the opposite.  I would make sure that was separated. People set their own index. Make it open. Right now these things are traded secretly. Put it out there just like any other stock exchange, and make sure that when people bet money that they got the resources to cover it one way or the other. I mean, you don't let people go to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Las_Vegas">Las Vegas</ref> with two dollars and make a ten dollar bet.  We shouldn't let these people do it either, especially when where we're guaranteeing it. But Obama is and the man is weakening for Wall Street.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Do you believe Obama has done any good things as president?</hi></p>
<hi rend="bold">If [Obama] would just educate the people like I could, he would get people on his side and he would win an election based on a populist economic view</hi>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wolfe</hi>: Well, I think it was good doing away with don't ask, don't tell. I think the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American%20Recovery%20and%20Reinvestment%20Act%20of%202009">stimulus</ref> was a good start but it wasn't very effective because it wasn't enough.  He's been too cautious about a lot of things. He tried to increase the taxes on the very well-to-do. The top one fifth own 94 percent of financial wealth in this country. They were saved by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Troubled%20Asset%20Relief%20Program">bailouts</ref>. They made money when the stock market went down to six thousand so they could invest low... People like that who were saved and benefited by these trillion dollar bailouts should be the ones paying higher tax rates now, but Obama hasn't emphasized that point. He has not instructed people. He isn't going out there and telling people the stuff I'm telling you.  If he would just educate the people like I could, he would get people on his side and he would win an election based on a populist economic view. People get back to work and people make money and people are empowered then businesses make more money too.</p>
<p>It's not like we want to nationalize resources and take away private capital. We just want to work with feet. The end of the economy is the betterment of the people and not just the accumulation of capital and casino capitalism. It's not that. You know it's the betterment of people. Capitalism is a means to an end. It's not the ends itself. Human needs are not cyclical. Economic cycles of the economy can be cyclical, but that's why you have to have fair taxes, an interventionist government to make sure that society works for the people and Obama's not doing that. The man has failed.</p>
</text>
