<text id="autogum_voyage_doc195" title="Bayham (Ontario)" shortTile="bayham-ontario" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=127198" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Bayham (Ontario)</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://www.bayham.on.ca">Bayham</ref></hi> is a municipality in <ref target="Elgin%20County">Elgin County</ref>, Ontario.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Bayham is made up of several communities near Lake Erie, including Corinth, Eden, Froggetts Corners, North Hall, Port Burwell, Richmond, Springer's Hill, Straffordville, Vienna and Wadger.</p>

<p>Bayham was named in 1810 for Viscount Bayham Charles Pratt, a friend of land grant recipient Colonel Talbot.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> The nearest <hi rend="bold">bus</hi> and <hi rend="bold">train</hi> stations are 50 km away in <ref target="Ingersoll%20%28Ontario%29">Ingersoll</ref>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">By car</hi>, from Toronto, it's about 200 km away: take Highway 401 west, then turn south on Culloden Line (County Road 10), and east on County Road 30 to Staffordville. You can take County Road 19 south to Port Burwell.</item>
</list>


<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Museum of Naval History — HMCS Ojibwa</hi>, 3 Pitt Street, Port Burwell, ☏ +1 519-633-7641 , ✉ curator@elginmilitarymuseum.ca . Daily 10AM-5PM. The HMCS Ojibwa is a Canadian Navy submarine brought to Port Burwell in 2013. Tours of the sub are offered daily. Tourists can go on an external tour, where the guide will point out various features of the submarine's external components, an interior tour, where a guide will take the tourists through all of the rooms on the submarine, or both. Cameras are allowed outside of the submarine but not inside due to the sensitive nature of the equipment still on board. Interior tour: adults $25, children 6-13 $15, children under 6 not permitted; exterior tour adults $12.50, children 6-13 $6, children under 6 free (taxes included); both tours: adults $33, children 6-13 $17.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Port Burwell Marine Museum &amp; Historic Lighthouse</hi>, Museum: 20 Pitt Street; lighthouse: 17 Robinson Street, Port Burwell, ☏ +1 519-874-4807 . 12 &amp; under free; adults (13+) $3 one site; adults (13+) $5 for both sites; family $8 for one site; family $12 for both sites.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Periscope Playhouse Cultural Centre</hi>, 42 Wellington Street, Port Burwell, ☏ +1 226-271-3815 . Theatre for concerts &amp; shows.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Port Burwell Provincial Park</hi>, 9 Wilson Lane, Port Burwell, ☏ +1 519-874-4691 . Mid-May to mid-Oct. A 232-ha park. The 2.5-km sandy beach is one of most beautiful on the northern shore of Lake Erie. A family friendly campground with large, well-treed, level sites as well as an outstanding play area for kids. Family-friendly Discovery Drop-ins from July 1st to Labour Day. Annual autumn hawk-watching program. A birder’s paradise. The park’s three campgrounds are a short distance away from the lake in a mature forest and campsites are well-planned, easily accessible, large, private and many are grass-covered. A recreation area features an amphitheater, children’s playground, volleyball and badminton courts, horseshoe pits, ball diamond, Frisbee golf and a basketball foul shooting court.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Izzy's Schooners</hi>, 35 Robinson Street, Port Burwell, ☏ +1 519-874-4363 . Su-Th 7AM-8PM, F Sa 7AM-9PM. Fish and chips, burgers, pasta.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sunshine Restaurant</hi>, 8237 Plank Rd, Straffordville, ☏ +1 519-866-3770 . Su 8AM-7PM, Tu-Th 7AM-7PM, F 7AM-8PM, Sa 8AM-8PM. Diner. All-day breakfast, sandwiches, burgers, wraps, seniors' dinners.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bayham's Family Table and Bake Shop</hi>, 6209 Plank Road, Port Rowan, ☏ +1 519-874-4085 . Daily 6AM-3PM. Diner.</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Lighthouse Restaurant &amp; Pub</hi>, 36 Robinson St, Port Burwell, ☏ +1 519-874-4112 , ✉ info@lighthouserestaurant.ca . F noon-8PM, Sa 11:30AM-8PM, Su 11:30AM-7:30PM. Serving fresh caught Lake Erie perch, burgers, sandwiches, ribs, pickerel.</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Nans Nook B&amp;B</hi>, 13 Victoria St, Port Burwell, ☏ +1 226-271-3815 , ✉ notmanconsulting@eastlink.ca . A 100-year-old home in the village of Port Burwell on Lake Erie. Two bedrooms for rent. Swimming pool. It's a five minute walk to the lake and the local restauants.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Grey Gables Bed and Breakfast</hi>, 22 Erieus St., ☏ +1 519-874-4644 . from $125.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Big Otter Marina &amp; Campgrounds</hi>, Bridge Street, Port Burwell, ☏ +1 519-874-4034 . Tenting, full-hookup sites. Dockage. Lake Erie access, walleye fishing on lake; cat fishing from the banks. Restaurants, beaches nearby.</item>
</list>
</text>
