<text id="autogum_interview_doc296" title="part2_Shimon Peres discusses the future of Israel" shortTile="partshimon-peres" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-01-06" dateModified="2013-08-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Shimon_Peres_discusses_the_future_of_Israel" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: To miniaturize?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: Yes.  And from the beginning you can create invisible sensors that will inform you about every movement in armies all over the world.  Then you can hand over the soldier, a new uniform made of nano which is immune against cartridges, against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Biological%20warfare">biology</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chemical%20warfare">chemical warfare</ref>.  It’s a strong material because the nano material is 100 times stronger than steel and it weighs only 1/6 of it.  It can warm up the soldier in cold weather; cool him in the warm weather.  It enhances his strength 3 times; he can lift 120 kilos with one hand.  And then you can go on and say not only to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nanomedicine">protect the protector</ref> but as well to create robots as in planes without pilots and military units without soldiers.  You don’t need a soldier; you can run it by proxy.  Small weapons, small robots that can penetrate or perform in conditions that a human being cannot.  He is too large, too inflexible.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: That’s amazing.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: Then take the nano in medicine.  You can produce the smallest instruments that you don’t have to invade the body.  You can do it from the outside control, with such tiny little instruments.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: Are you satisfied with the progress in the nanotechnology sector here in Israel?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: Look, I started it 5 or 6 years ago to explain to the people the importance of it, then I was instrumental in collecting several hundred million dollars that was given to the universities and the research institutes.  As a result, we have a very good group of nano experts, you see, all of the best, and now they are working with me voluntarily.  I have 30 top scientists in Israel who have developed different ideas in the domain.  This type of research can be applied to whatever you want:  Alternative energy, because if you want to have solar energy, you need very large equipment.  With nano you can condense it.  The same is true about desalinization.  It can replace the uniform of humankind.  In the future ladies will have a dress.  You can press a button and it will change the color.  The nano has what has been called the lotus effect.  Lotus is a flower that keeps cleaning itself.  And so is a nano so it doesn’t shrink, doesn’t get dirty.</p>
<head id="The_future_of_the_peace_process_in_Israel">The future of the peace process in Israel</head>
<figure><caption>"<hi rend="bold">The future is only peace.  The problem is how long will it take and how many victims will it call for.</hi>" <hi rend="italic">Shimon Peres</hi>Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: Mr. President, as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nobel%20Peace%20Prize">Nobel Peace Prize</ref> recipient and as one of the fathers of the modern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peace%20process%20in%20the%20Israeli-Palestinian%20conflict">peace process in Israel</ref>, do you still think that there is a future to the peace process?</hi></p>
</text>
