<text id="autogum_voyage_doc256" title="Chișinău" shortTile="chiinu" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=7103" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Chișinău</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.chisinau.md/">Chişinău</ref></hi> (Russian <hi rend="bold">Kishinyov</hi>, Ukrainian <hi rend="bold">Kishiniv</hi>, pronounced "Kishinau" with "nau" as in the English word "know") is the capital of <ref target="Moldova">Moldova</ref> with a population of around 790,000 plus 250,000 people coming each day for work and entertainment from all over the country and abroad. The city's territory with nearest suburbs cover the area of 635 km.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Chişinău is very wealthy compared to the rest of the country, as Moldova is not a very rich country, and the countryside especially is poor. As is common in developing countries, you are likely to see great disparities in wealth. It's also very much a post-Soviet city, with both the good and bad qualities associated with it. By other side you'll see many modern and great buildings of steel, concrete and glass.</p>

<p>The majority of the middle and working class population lives in blocks of flats. These look standard, maybe not too nice but are not "dangerous" as similar areas may be considered to be in Western Europe. Do not expect Western standards everywhere, but the situation is improving every year. There are 4- and 5-star hotels, good restaurants and cafes, coffee houses and bars. Many restaurants and almost all the hotels in the city accept the credit cards. There are hundreds of ATMs throughout the city.</p>

<head>By plane</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Chişinău International Airport</hi> ( KIV ). Served by many airlines like <ref target="http://airbaltic.com/">AirBaltic</ref>, <ref target="http://airmoldova.md/home-en/">Air Moldova</ref>, <ref target="http://aua.com">Austrian</ref>, <ref target="http://www.lufthansa.com">Lufthansa</ref>, <ref target="http://mdv.md/">Moldavian Airlines</ref>, <ref target="http://tarom.ro/en/">Tarom</ref>, <ref target="http://thy.com/">Turkish Airlines</ref>, S7 Aircompany, <ref target="http://www.wizzair.com">Wizz Air</ref> with flights around the Europe and Asia, notably to <ref target="Athens">Athens</ref>, <ref target="Bucharest">Bucharest</ref>, <ref target="Budapest">Budapest</ref>, <ref target="Frankfurt">Frankfurt</ref>, <ref target="Istanbul">Istanbul</ref>, <ref target="Madrid">Madrid</ref>, Milan-<ref target="Bergamo">Bergamo</ref>, <ref target="Moscow">Moscow</ref>, <ref target="Munich">Munich</ref>, <ref target="Riga">Riga</ref>, <ref target="Rome">Rome</ref>, <ref target="Timisoara">Timisoara</ref>, <ref target="Vienna">Vienna</ref>, <ref target="Vilnius">Vilnius</ref>, <ref target="Saint%20Petersburg">Saint Petersburg</ref>, <ref target="Varna">Varna</ref>, <ref target="Paris">Paris</ref>, <ref target="London">London</ref>, <ref target="Bologna">Bologna</ref> and <ref target="Surgut">Surgut</ref>.</item>
</list>




<list type="unordered">
<item> N. 165 takes you through Botanica to the center, Izmail street. Tickets cost 3 lei; luggage will cost you another ticket. The minibuses are white vans leaving from the airport parking lot. If you leave the airport building from the arrivals area, turn right and walk towards the end of the building. The buses are marked with the number 165 on a sign behind the windshield and you can flag one down passing you, or walk up to the ones still parking. Don't open the sliding door even though you have luggage; for some reason they always use the co-drivers door to get on and off.</item>
<item> N. 30 leaves just out of the arrivals door and is marked by a sign with the times. Pay the girl with an apron 2 lei (July 2018) once the bus is running. It takes you to Botanical Gardens, Ismail Street and Bulevardul Stefan cel Mare si Sfint (main street).</item>
</list>


<head>By train</head>
<p>See <hi rend="bold">Calea Ferata Moldova</hi> (CFM) - <ref target="http://www.railway.md/">Moldovan Railways</ref>.</p>

<p>There is one Central Railway Station and a few suburban stations at the city's ends. The trains depart to Europe through Romania and to the Community of Independent States, especially to Russia, Ukraine and Belarus.</p>

<p>From Western Europe, the train is much cheaper than a flight. The downside is that they are slow, particularly when crossing the borders into the former Soviet Union, where they need to stop to have their wheels changed due to different rail gauge.</p>

<p>The most popular route is from <ref target="Bucharest">Bucharest</ref>, daily overnight trains leave <hi rend="bold">Gara de Nord</hi> station at 19:15 and arrive at 09:30. The 'couchette' - shared sleeper cabin, cost approximately 136 <ref target="Romania%23Money">Romanian lei</ref> purchased the day of in Bucharest.</p>

<p>Another useful route is from <ref target="Warsaw">Warsaw</ref>, departing every second day taking two nights (38 hr). Chişinău is served by three routes from Russia, one from <ref target="Moscow">Moscow</ref> via <ref target="Kiev">Kiev</ref>, one from <ref target="Saint%20Petersburg">Saint Petersburg</ref> and one from <ref target="Rostov-on-Don">Rostov-on-Don</ref>. Several cities in Ukraine also have daily connections.</p>

<p>A direct train from <ref target="Odessa">Odessa</ref> leaves Odessa at 16:00 and arrives at ~22:00 the same evening, running only on Saturdays and Sundays. This train crosses the unrecognised breakaway state of <ref target="Transnistria">Transnistria</ref> and makes a quick stop-over in its capital, <ref target="Tiraspol">Tiraspol</ref>. A single journey costs 244 <ref target="Ukraine%23Money">грн</ref> as of May 2015.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>Roads in Moldova are quite bad. The road leading from Chişinău to Leuseni is pretty nice. You are likely to be sharing the road with trucks, cars, and livestock, all moving at various speeds without a lot of regard for safety.</p>

<p>Because the driving and quality of the roads in Moldova is different from what a Westerner would probably be used to, it is thus better to rely on public transport, which is very cheap and (mostly) reliable.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>Chişinău has three bus stations:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Gara Centrală</hi> (Autogara Chișinău Centru), Strada Mitropolitul Varlaam 58, ☏ +373 22 542185 . Serving mainly in-country destinations including Transnistria. Buy your ticket at the Kassa. Tickets for international trips have to be bought inside the bus station instead of directly from the driver. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Gara de Nord</hi> (Chisinau North Bus Station), Strada Calea Moșilor 2/1. For in-country destinations on the northern part of the country like Sorocca, Rezina, Ocnita, for travel to Odessa, Kyiv and elsewhere in Ukraine. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Gara de Sud</hi> (Южный автовокзал), ☏ +373 22 723983 . For in-country destinations in the southern part of the country like Comrat, Cahul and for journeys to Romania. <hi rend="bold">Getting there/away</hi>: from central Chişinău on rutiera (microbus) number 120, 124, 180 or 192 for 3 lei. Gara Nord is served by rutiera 163 and trolleybus #9, along with a bunch of others. </item>
</list>


<p>You can check bus timetables (for in-country, and international destinations) at <ref target="http://www.autogara.md">this website</ref>.</p>

<p>From specific destinations:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Transnistria">Transnistria</ref> – From <ref target="Tiraspol">Tiraspol</ref> (leaving from the train/bus station: <hi rend="italic">gara</hi>) and <ref target="Bendery">Bendery</ref> there are semi-hourly marshrutkas taking 90 min and 40 <ref target="Transnistria%23Money">rubles</ref>. You can also pay in Moldavan lei, about 37 lei.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Bucharest">Bucharest</ref> – Many companies operate 'rutieras' during the day and larger coaches during the night heading to Bucharest. The journey is 8-9 hr journey with hourly departures in the evening. There often is no toilet on the bus but several stops were made by the bus driver. Most companies run to/from the central bus station behind the Central Market.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Ia%C8%99i">Iași</ref> – Coach services are operated to/from Gara de Sud. There are nine services a day. The trip takes around 3½–5 hr.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Odessa">Odessa</ref> – The journey from Odessa takes around 5 hr and costs around US$10. Most buses from Odessa go through southern Moldova, avoiding the Transnistrian region—these will be marked as going through Palanka or <ref target="Causeni">Causeni</ref>.</item>
</list>


<p>There are also several buses throughout the day from <ref target="Chernivtsi">Chernivtsi</ref>, and <ref target="Lviv">Lviv</ref>. </p>
</text>
