<text id="autogum_interview_doc351" title="part3_Wikinews discusses H1N1 with the WHO" shortTile="partwikinews-discusses" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-01-29" dateModified="2019-09-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_discusses_H1N1_with_the_WHO" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Rarely, such influenza vaccines can cause allergic reactions such as hives, rapid swelling of deeper skin layers and tissues, asthma or a severe multisystem allergic reaction due to hypersensitivity to certain vaccine components.</p>
<p>Live vaccines are given via a nasal spray, and can commonly cause runny nose, nasal congestion, cough, and can less frequently cause sore throat, low grade fever, irritability and head- and muscle- aches. Wheezing and vomiting episodes have been described in children receiving live influenza vaccines.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What action has the WHO taken, if any, to insure vaccines are available?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">KM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> During the first stages of the pandemic in 2009, the Director-General highlighted the need to make vaccine and medicines available to countries who would be unable to access them on their own.  As the WHO pandemic vaccine donation programme was first established, all countries were surveyed by WHO, and 95 identified as having no access to pandemic vaccines, and therefore eligible for donations.</p>
<p>Based on the pledges of donated vaccine, a plan was prepared for a two phase approach to supply sufficient vaccines for 10% of the population in these countries; an initial supply to cover health workers and other essential workers, equivalent to 2% of the population, and a second supply of 8% for other priority groups. The sequencing of supply was based on assessments of vulnerability to the pandemic, and readiness to utilize vaccines.</p>
<p>To date, 25 countries have received donated H1N1 vaccine totaling more than 10 million doses, along with ancillary supplies.   Another 15 to 20 countries will be receiving their vaccine shipments in the upcoming few weeks. </p>
<p>The 25 countries who have received shipments are: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Azerbaijan">Azerbaijan</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Afghanistan">Afghanistan</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Cambodia">Cambodia</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Fiji">Fiji</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kiribati">Kiribati</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kosovo">Kosovo</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Laos">Laos PDR</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Maldives">Maldives</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mongolia">Mongolia</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Nauru">Nauru</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Nicaragua">Nicaragua</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Papua_New_Guinea">Papua New Guinea</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Solomon_Islands">Solomon Islands</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Togo">Togo</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tonga">Tonga</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Vanuatu">Vanuatu</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Cuba">Cuba</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Honduras">Honduras</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/El_Salvador">El Salvador</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kenya">Kenya</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Samoa">Samoa</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tokelau">Tokelau</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Cook_Islands">Cook Islands</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Pakistan">Pakistan</ref>, [and] <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Philippines">Philippines</ref></p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Last November, the WHO <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/WHO_states_H1N1_swine_flu_world's_most_dominant_virus">stated the H1N1 virus is world's most dominant virus</ref>. Is this still true?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">KM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> On February 18th, WHO concluded a four-day meeting to look at vaccine strains for seasonal influenza vaccine for the 2010 and 2011 season.  This is part of the routine work that WHO does twice yearly to determine vaccine strains to be included in upcoming northern and southern hemisphere seasonal influenza vaccines.</p>
<p>During the scientific discussions which ended on the 18th of February, it was confirmed that the overwhelming number of influenza viruses that were isolated around the world were the pandemic H1N1 virus.  The experts believe that based on this information that this virus will continue to be one of the dominant viruses in wide circulation in the coming fall and winter season.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Is there anything that the WHO believes to be very important for the public to know about the H1N1?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">KM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> </p>
<list type="unordered"><item>The overall impact of the pandemic has been moderate and most people experienced mild symptoms or illness. However, some groups are more vulnerable and have a higher risk of complications or severe illness, for example pregnant women, infants, young children and people with chronic diseases.</item>
<item>Many of the severe cases have been due to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/pneumonia">viral pneumonia</ref>, which is harder to treat than the bacterial pneumonia normally associated with seasonal influenza. Many of these patients have required intensive care, which has led to intensive care units being frequently overwhelmed at the peak of the outbreak.</item>
<item>Most of the deaths caused by the pandemic influenza disease occurred among younger people than is the case during seasonal influenza outbreaks, including among those who were previously healthy.</item>
<item>To protect people from infection and avoid related severe outcomes, the H1N1 vaccine is an important public health tool as long as the pandemic H1N1 virus is circulating and causing illness.</item>
<item>Since September 2009, more than 75 Member States and territories have implemented immunization programmes, and 290 million doses of the pandemic (H1N1) 2009 vaccine have been administered.</item></list>
</text>
