<text id="autogum_voyage_doc196" title="Dortmund" shortTile="dortmund" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=9957" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Dortmund</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.dortmund.de">Dortmund</ref></hi>(Low German: Düörpm; Latin: Tremonia) is a city with a population of about 600,000 in the North Rhine-Westphalia region in Germany. It is in the middle part of the state and is considered to be the administrative, commercial and cultural centre of the Ruhr area with some 5.21 million inhabitants (2017). The city is famous for its beer, football, events and for shopping. </p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>The city pops up first when people think of the <ref target="Ruhr">Ruhr</ref> valley, and that's no surprise. It is the largest Ruhr city, the third largest by population after <ref target="Cologne">Cologne</ref> and <ref target="D%C3%BCsseldorf">Düsseldorf</ref>, and the geographical center of the <ref target="North%20Rhine-Westphalia">North Rhine-Westphalia</ref> state. Worldwide, the city is foremost know for <ref target="Beer%20%28beverage%29">beer</ref> (pale export/lager beer called Dortmunder) and the famous sports club <hi rend="bold">Ballspielverein Borussia 09</hi>, Borussia Dortmund or BVB for short. But therein another, altogether gentler, side to this former industrial powerhouse. Modern Dortmund is vibrant and cultural, well-known for excellent shopping, a range of fascinating museums and theaters, one of Germany's most surprising startup scenes (not quite on the same level as Berlin, but ahead of the Rhine-Ruhr area and even Munich), and with half the city given over to parks and gardens, enough green areas to sooth the sense.</p>

<p>And yes, the city is no classy beauty, and rough at first glance, though pretty honest, adorable and cordial at the second. </p>

<head>History</head>

<p>Founded around the year 882, Dortmund became an Imperial Free City. Throughout the 13th and 14th centuries, it was the "chief city" of the Rhine, Westphalia, and of the Netherlandish Circle of the <ref target="Hanseatic%20League">Hanseatic League</ref>. After the <ref target="Thirty%20Years%27%20War">Thirty Years' War</ref>, the city was destroyed, and decreased in significance until the onset of industrialization; then, it became one of Germany's most important coal, steel and beer centres. Dortmund acquired the nickname <hi rend="italic">Stahlstadt</hi> (Steel City) in the 19th century, when it became the world center of steel production. Consequently, the city was one of the most heavily bombed cities in Germany during <ref target="World%20War%20II%20in%20Europe">World War II</ref>. The devastating bombing raids of 12 March 1945, with more than 1,110 aircraft, destroyed 98% of buildings in the inner city center, a record to a single target in this war. Much of what you see in the city center was built in the last 50 years. The region has adapted since the collapse of its steel and coal industries, and shifted to high technology, biomedical technology, micro systems technology and also services. </p>

<p>In November 2017, according to a study by data of German National Statistics Office, the National Employment Agency, Mercer, Handelsblatt, Numbeo and Immowelt, Dortmund was ranked as the seventh most livable city in Germany for expats. In September 2017, <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi> praised the city of Dortmund, which has adapted since the collapse of its century long steel and coal industries and shifted to high technology biomedical technology, micro systems technology and services, as the hidden star of structural change with a good quality of life for employers. According to the 2017 Global Least &amp; Most Stressful Cities Ranking, Dortmund is one of the least stressful cities in the world. It's ranked 27th out of 150 between <ref target="Copenhagen">Copenhagen</ref> and <ref target="Vancouver">Vancouver</ref> and highly ranked in the category Traffic &amp; Public Transport, Gender equality and debt per capital.</p>

<head>When to visit</head>
<p>The best times for Dortmund are late spring to early autumn, its peak season for tourist. The summers tend to be sunny and warm around 25°C (77°F), during the November and December 5°C you can find several Christmas markets in the city, in combination with the festive mood, its a nice time to visit.</p>

<head>Tourist office</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Dortmund Tourist and Information Office</hi>, Kampstraße 80, ☏ +49 231-18999222 , fax: +49 231-18999333 , ✉ info@dortmund-tourismus.de . M-F 10:00-18:00, Sa Su holidays 10:00-16:00; New Year and New Year's Eve 10:00-23:00; closed on December 25 and 26.</item>
</list>


<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Dortmund airport</hi> ( DTM ). Home of several low-cost airlines (easyJet, Wizzair), it serves mainly national and European travellers, with a particularly heavy focus on Eastern Europe. Unusually for a German airport, there is no direct train or tram connection to the airport, but there are shuttle buses between the airport and Dortmund Central Station or Holzwickede Station. </item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">From and to Central Station:</hi> A non-stop shuttle-bus can be found opposite the main railway station. The journey lasts 25 - 30 min and costs €6.5 per passenger (6-14 children €2; younger children free). This bus service is not covered by a travelcard.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Via Aplerbeck</hi> The 440 bus travels past Aplerbeck where passengers can change to the Stadtbahn U47 which will go to the Hbf via the major Stadtbahn hub, Stadtgarten. The journey is approximately 45 min. Tickets cost €2.50 or a travelcard can be used. This service runs more frequently than the shuttle bus.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">From Holzwickede Station:</hi> A bus service (€3/passenger), runs regularly about every 15 minutes between 05:00 and 23:00. The trip to the terminal building takes approx. 5 minutes.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">By taxi:</hi> The trip costs around €25 to the City Centre. Drivers operate on the meter; if they don't, get a different taxi!</item>
</list>



<p><hi rend="bold">Duesseldorf Airport</hi> ( DUS ) can also be used and may be a better option, especially for passengers who prefer major carriers. It is a 45-60 minute drive away from Dortmund. Direct train services also run between Dortmund Central Station and Düsseldorf Airport operated by Deutsche Bahn. <ref target="D%C3%BCsseldorf">Düsseldorf</ref> Airport serves a variety of long haul destinations in North America and Asia, as well as short haul services throughout Europe.</p>

<head>By train</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Dortmund central station</hi> (Dortmund Hauptbahnhof), Königswall 15, 44137. This is a major stop for Deutsche Bahn (German state railway) and has over 600 departing trains on a typical weekday. There are different types of trains such as S-Bahn, Regionalbahn, and Regionalexpress. The station is a terminus for some Thalys trains (usually 3 per day). </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Dortmund Hörde Bahnhof</hi> (Hörde Hauptbahnhof), Hörder Bahnhofstraße, 44263. This is the second biggest stop in Dortmund and it is classified by Deutsche Bahn as a category 4 station. Trains run hourly, except for the RB 59 (Hellweg-Bahn) service, which runs every 30 minutes on weekdays. There are additional services on weekdays during the peak hour </item>
</list>

<p>All tickets will have to be validated before departure. For the trains like Regionalbahn or Regionalexpress there's an orange machine before you go up the stairs to the platform, where you have to stamp your ticket. The Stadtbahn Dortmund (DSW21) tickets for the local Stadtbahn (light rail) and Straßenbahn (tram) service must be validated on the actual trains although you will find stamp boxes at the entrance to the platform as well.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="http://www.bahn.de">Deutsche Bahn </ref></item>
</list>
</text>
