<text id="autogum_bio_doc452" title="John Wingfield" shortTile="john-wingfield" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-07-19" dateModified="2019-10-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Wingfield" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>John Wingfield</head>For others, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Wingfield_(disambiguation)">John Wingfield (disambiguation)</ref>.
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Sir John Wingfield</hi> (before 1582–1596) was an English soldier.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>He was the third son of Richard Wingfield of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wantisden">Wantisden</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suffolk">Suffolk</ref>, and Mary, daughter and coheiress of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Hardwick_of_Derby">John Hardwick of Derby</ref>, and the sister of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bess_of_Hardwick">Bess of Hardwick</ref>. His brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anthony_Wingfield_(MP_for_Ripon)">Anthony Wingfield</ref> was reader in Greek to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_I_of_England">Elizabeth I of England</ref>.</p>
<p>He was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Member_of_Parliament">Member</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parliament_of_England">Parliament of England</ref> for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lichfield_(UK_Parliament_constituency)">Lichfield</ref> in 1593.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>A volunteer against the Spanish in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holland">Holland</ref>, he was appointed captain of foot in the expedition there of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Dudley,_1st_Earl_of_Leicester">Robert Dudley, 1st Earl of Leicester</ref> in December 1585. Wounded action before <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zutphen">Zutphen</ref> on 22 September 1586, he was knighted by Leicester. He was one of the twelve knights, friends and relations, who walked at the funeral of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sir_Philip_Sidney">Sir Philip Sidney</ref> on 16 February 1587.</p>
<p>Returning to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Netherlands">Netherlands</ref>, he was appointed governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geertruidenberg">Geertruidenberg</ref>. With the assistance furnished him by his brother-in-law, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peregrine_Bertie,_13th_Baron_Willoughby_de_Eresby">Peregrine Bertie, 13th Baron Willoughby de Eresby</ref>, he managed to hold out successfully during 1588, and to assist materially in forcing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_Farnese,_Duke_of_Parma">Alexander Farnese, Duke of Parma</ref> to raise the siege of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bergen,_North_Holland">Bergen</ref> in November. His position, though, suffered from tension between the English auxiliaries and the States-General. The garrison lacked pay, and was mutinous. A rumour arose that he intended to hand over the place to the Spanish, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maurice_of_Nassau">Maurice of Nassau</ref> came with a demand for its surrender. Wingfield denied the imputed treason; but Geertruidenberg was on 10 April 1589, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capture_of_Geertruidenberg_(1589)">delivered to the Spanish</ref>.</p>
<p>Returning to England with his wife and newly born child, Wingfield served as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Master_of_the_ordnance">master of the ordnance</ref> under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Norreys">Sir John Norris</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brittany">Brittany</ref> against the forces of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catholic_League_(French)">Catholic League</ref> in 1591, and the following year he is mentioned as being in charge of the storehouse at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dieppe,_Seine-Maritime">Dieppe</ref>.</p>
<p>In June 1596 he sailed on board the <hi rend="italic">Vanguard</hi>, as camp-master with the rank of colonel, in the expedition under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Devereux,_2nd_Earl_of_Essex">Robert Devereux, 2nd Earl of Essex</ref> against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cadiz">Cadiz</ref>. After an attack on the Spanish fleet led by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_Ralegh">Walter Ralegh</ref>, in which he took part, he was one of the first to enter the town. Ordered on 21 June to bait an ambush, Wingfield led 200 men along the isthmus leading to the city gates which were defended by 500 Spanish cavalry. He then feigned a panic-stricken retreat and drew the Spanish back into the arms of a larger hidden English force. In the rout that followed the English broke through the city gates and Wingfield was wounded in the thigh, while Essex and a small band fought through to the plaza. Unable to walk, Wingfield captured a horse to follow Essex, and—now an obvious target—was killed instantly by a bullet to the head just as the city surrendered. He was buried five days later with <hi rend="italic">all the funerall solemnities of warre</hi> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cadiz_Cathedral">cathedral at Cadiz</ref>, while <hi rend="italic">the generalls threw their handkerchiefs wet from their eyes into the grave</hi> (Stow). John Donne, a member of the expedition, composed the well-known epigram (<hi rend="italic">Farther then Wingefield, no man dares to go</hi>) in tribute.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Green-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> In the following year the queen granted his widow an annuity of £100 a year.</p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>Wingfield married, about 1582, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Susan_Bertie,_countess_of_Kent">Susan Bertie, countess of Kent</ref>, sister of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peregrine_Bertie,_Lord_Willoughby_de_Eresby">Peregrine Bertie, Lord Willoughby de Eresby</ref>, and widow of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reginald_Grey,_5th_Earl_of_Kent">Reginald Grey, 5th Earl of Kent</ref>, by whom he had two sons, Peregrine, born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holland">Holland</ref>, presumably named after her brother, and Robert Wingfield.</p>
</text>
