<text id="autogum_whow_doc456" title="Find a Contractor" shortTile="find-contractor" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-03-27" dateModified="2018-02-24" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Find-a-Contractor" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Find a Contractor</head><p>Even the handiest of homeowners need assistance with renovations occasionally.  From new construction to tear downs, help from an expert may be needed to ensure the job gets completed correctly.  Before calling the first name you come across in your phone book or on the Internet, consider the following advice when trying to find a contractor.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Seek advice from family and friends.  Ask people you know and trust for a recommendation if they have had similar work done in their homes.  You will feel more confident in calling a contractor who has made your best friend or brother happy with the renovation. <figure rend="Find a Contractor Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Consult with professionals you already know.  If you have a great electrician or plumber, he has experience with reliable contractors and will not hesitate to provide you with names and numbers.  Your professional will not recommend someone he wouldn't use. <figure rend="Find a Contractor Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Collect more than one contractor estimate. Make sure that you have at least 3 contractors bid on your home renovation project rather than hiring the first one that walks through your front door. When you sit down to compare, the work that was quoted by each contractor should be similar in its specifications. <figure rend="Find a Contractor Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Examine business cards.  A contractor should provide a business card when meeting you, and that card needs to have a physical address, telephone number and a license number.  Once she leaves, verify the information and the status of her license. <figure rend="Find a Contractor Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Check references. A decent contractor will not hesitate to provide a written list of references, and the longer the list, the more likely he is reputable. Call as many on the list until you have the information you need. A tip to ensure quality is to skip around the list instead of going in the order provided. <figure rend="Find a Contractor Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Verify insurance information.  When you are meeting with a prospective contractor, ask her to show you an insurance certificate.  In the alternative, you can request the contractor's insurance carrier and telephone number so that you can be sure the policy is in good standing. <figure rend="Find a Contractor Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Beware of cash.  When you find a contractor that you like, ask how he expects to be paid.  The one who wants all cash may be cutting corners that will also cut the quality of the job done in your home.</item>
<item>Drop a contractor without a cell phone.  Almost every professional has a cell phone, so if you find a contractor without one, do not hire her.  A contractor should provide you with means to reach her easily.</item>
<item>Question the contractor who eliminates the permit. If your renovation project is substantial, you will most likely need a construction permit. If the contractor suggests skipping this paperwork, it could mean that he isn't licensed or doesn't want to be monitored.</item></list>
</text>
