<text id="autogum_interview_doc681" title="part4_Sam Brownback on running for President, gay rights, the Middle East and religion" shortTile="partsam-brownback" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-12" dateModified="2014-12-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sam_Brownback_on_running_for_President%2C_gay_rights%2C_the_Middle_East_and_religion" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  If someone told you that they were scared to vote for someone who doesn't believe in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/evolution">evolution</ref>, what would you say to that person?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  Well, I'd say to them that, for my part, I think most people agree that Man is not an accident, and that evolution is something that's taught in science class by state standards, they're not set by the Federal government, really shouldn't be something that would enter into their mind, not a Federal issue, it's one that's set by the states.  I think most people that are concerned about evolution from a faith side want to see more taught about the science of how we got here, both at the very start--how did we get the initial cells, the initial biological entities, how did we get this incredible physics set up of this planet, universe that could have a carbon-based system here, all based on science.  Just teaching science.  And to teach more science, not less, on it.  For me personally, I just have no doubt that God created us.  How he did it, what mechanisms he used, I don't know.  The fact that he did it, I have no doubt.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You don’t think that evolution is incompatible with an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/intelligent%20design">intelligent design</ref> theory?  That we could have evolved based upon the evolution idea, but that it could have still been the work of God?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  There's some people that look at it that way.  I think there's some--I think that's kind of an interesting way of looking at it.  I don't--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What's your personal belief on that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  I don't know.  Just what I said--that I don't know how God did it.  A number of people would in what you're describing a kind of, I don't know what you'd term it, a faith-based evolution or--that's not the term that some would call it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It works.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  A guy at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Human%20Genome%20Project">Human Genome Project</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis%20Collins">Francis Collins</ref>, I've met with several times, I've read his book <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Language%20of%20God:%20A%20Scientist%20Presents%20Evidence%20for%20Belief">The Language of God</ref></hi>, is in that category. And I find that very interesting.  I think there's some rationality, too, when you look at the consistency of the genetic code between species, the different lengths, the different pieces that are in it, but there's a lot of the same genetic language that's there.  Where I think we're really lost is we're segregating science and faith.  And they ask and answer different questions.  Science asks how, and faith asks why.  And I think we'd be so much richer, and in societies in the past in Western civilization they did this a lot more, if you had the interaction of the two, of faith and science.  Because these don't conflict.  If they do, you need to either check your science or check your faith.  But they conflict, and for most people's lives in the United States, they want somebody to strongly support science. And whatever we can do to understand better the cosmos and how we work and improve our lives.  And yet it's a faith-based country.  You have ninety percent of the country that believes in God.  Most people, they don't see conflicts in this, and we would be so much richer if we had the discussion, rather than really trying to pit one against the other.</p>
</text>
