<text id="autogum_interview_doc393" title="part6_The Raveonettes on love, death, desire and war" shortTile="partthe-raveonettes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-16" dateModified="2010-12-23" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Raveonettes_on_love%2C_death%2C_desire_and_war" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How about as people?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  Yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How so?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  Well, it affected me in the sense that I feel like it has changed where I have come from very much; Denmark participated in it and sent soldiers to support the U.S.  And I think that definitely made me aware of what a decision like that does to a country.  Now I think the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Danish%20people">Danish</ref> people are really confronted with having to redefine this strong sense of a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socialism">Socialist</ref> heart that doesn't seem as strong as it was.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  Mmmm, well, not really.  I mean, I knew what America was in it for, and I disagreed with it.  It's about money and oil and stuff like that.  And, they are just using the terrorist thing when it started as just a front, you know?  I get much more affected not so much by war itself but when I hear about civilians involved in war.  But I was much more affected by stuff that happens in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chechnya">Chechnya</ref>, for instance.  I used to read a lot about that, and that is a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chechen%20War">forgotten war</ref> that <hi rend="italic">really</hi> people don't give a shit about.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why do you have such a particular interest in Chechnya?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  Not particularly, I guess it was just after the school shooting and people were getting down on the Chechen rebels, and I'm like, "Yeah, that was such a <hi rend="italic">horrible</hi> thing to happen, all those innocent children, that was probably the worst..."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beslan">Beslan</ref> was it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  Yeah.  The thing is there was a reason for it, know what I mean?  I'm not justifying it any way because I know it is absolutely atrocious...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But it was ideology and not oil...</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  Yeah!  The reason for it was to show the world that there is a huge problem going on where we live and people don't pay attention to it.  We are going to have to do something for you to take notice.  And what they did was just a very wrong way of doing it, but at least they grabbed a little attention for themselves.  But the only attention they got out of it was basically that Chechen rebels were murderers and child killers.  But the Russian soldiers rape and kill innocent Chechens every single day, and <hi rend="italic">no one</hi> gives a damn about it.  Every single day!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why do you think it's not talked about?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  I actually don't know, to be honest with you.  And I actually don't know the world that well, and I'm sure there are <hi rend="italic">a lot</hi> of forgotten wars still raging in the world, so I don't know, to be honest with you.</p>
</text>
