<text id="autogum_interview_doc170" title="part3_Canada&amp;apos;s Don Valley West (Ward 25) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-don-valley" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-16" dateModified="2007-06-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Don_Valley_West_%28Ward_25%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="Cliff_Jenkins_(incumbent)">Cliff Jenkins (incumbent)</head>
<p>60-year-old <hi rend="bold">Cliff Jenkins</hi> is the incumbent for Ward 25, Don Valley West. Previous to that, Jenkins was a client executive for IBM Canada, leading a team of information technology professionals to meet the business needs of a large client.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Describe the three most important issues in your campaign. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Managing Toronto's density explosion:</hi>  The population of Toronto is increasing at about 15,000 people per year.  New residents require additional infrastructure – increased sewer capacity, more TTC buses, increased solid waste capacity, extension of our subway service to York University and beyond, increased policing capability.  Just about every municipal service has to be ramped up to meet the increased demands - and ramping up generates significant complexity and increases costs.  The best estimate of the amount new capital infrastructure required by each new person is $20,000.  Unfortunately, we receive only about $4,000 per person in development charges.  As a result, we've had about a $240,000,000 capital shortfall every year – which we've "solved" by increasing debt and seeking handouts from other orders of government. This is unsustainable and unacceptable.  Increasing development charges is the first step towards solving the infrastructure shortfall.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Protection and preservation of neighbourhoods:</hi> The density explosion puts great pressure on our stable residential neighbourhoods.  The City's Official Plan directs growth to specific places in the City – particularly those serviced by rapid transit.  But the development industry continues to seek growth in those areas of the City which are NOT targeted for intensification, as well as over-intensification in those areas identified for growth.  This has immediate negative impacts on neighbouring single-family homes.  While we have made gains in improving policies of the Official Plan to protect these neighbourhoods, it will be the job of the next Council to ensure that Planning Staff interpret and enforce these policies to really protect them.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Election Finance Reform:</hi> While Council has indicated its intent to reform how candidates raise money for election campaigns, it does remain a serious problem that must be fixed.  VoteToronto, an independent organization, has documented the problems at www.votetoronto.ca of the influence that can result from election contributions of special interest groups.  The new City Council must finish the job of election finance reform.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What one election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> In Ward 25, the key issue is protection of neighbourhoods.  For most people, their investment in their homes is their single biggest investment.  Intrusive nearby development can have major negative effects.  For example, at 1000 Mt. Pleasant Road, an application for a 13-storey apartment building which would tower over and impact neighbouring single-family homes was deemed, by City planners, to be contrary to the City's Official Plan and should be refused.  City Council did refuse the application.  But, on appeal, the Ontario Municipal Board (OMB) overturned the City's decision.   City Council must re-enforce policies and processes which protect our stable residential neighbourhoods and must demand OMB reform from the provincial government.</p>
</text>
