<text id="autogum_fiction_doc32" title="The Son of Tarzan" shortTile="sontarzan" author="Burroughs, Edgar Rice" type="fiction" dateCollected="2019-10-22" sourceURL="http://gutenberg.readingroo.ms/9/90/90.txt">
<head>Chapter 24</head>

<p>Sometimes lolling upon Tantor's back, sometimes roaming the jungle in solitude, Korak made his way slowly toward the West and South. He made but a few miles a day, for he had a whole lifetime before him and no place in particular to go. Possibly he would have moved more rapidly but for the thought which continually haunted him that each mile he traversed carried him further and further away from Meriem--no longer his Meriem, as of yore, it is true! but still as dear to him as ever.</p>

<p>Thus he came upon the trail of The Sheik's band as it traveled down river from the point where The Sheik had captured Meriem to his own stockaded village. Korak pretty well knew who it was that had passed, for there were few in the great jungle with whom he was not familiar, though it had been years since he had come this far north. He had no particular business, however, with the old Sheik and so he did not propose following him--the further from men he could stay the better pleased he would be--he wished that he might never see a human face again. Men always brought him sorrow and misery.</p>

<p>The river suggested fishing and so he dawdled upon its shores, catching fish after a fashion of his own devising and eating them raw. When night came he curled up in a great tree beside the stream--the one from which he had been fishing during the afternoon--and was soon asleep. Numa, roaring beneath him, awoke him. He was about to call out in anger to his noisy neighbor when something else caught his attention. He listened. Was there something in the tree beside himself? Yes, he heard the noise of something below him trying to clamber upward. Presently he heard the click of a crocodile's jaws in the waters beneath, and then, low but distinct: "By George! The beggar nearly got me." The voice was familiar.</p>

<p>Korak glanced downward toward the speaker. Outlined against the faint luminosity of the water he saw the figure of a man clinging to a lower branch of the tree. Silently and swiftly the ape-man clambered downward. He felt a hand beneath his foot. He reached down and clutched the figure beneath him and dragged it up among the branches. It struggled weakly and struck at him; but Korak paid no more attention than Tantor to an ant. He lugged his burden to the higher safety and greater comfort of a broad crotch, and there he propped it in a sitting position against the bole of the tree. Numa still was roaring beneath them, doubtless in anger that he had been robbed of his prey. Korak shouted down at him, calling him, in the language of the great apes, "Old green-eyed eater of carrion," "Brother of Dango," the hyena, and other choice appellations of jungle opprobrium.</p>

<p>The Hon. Morison Baynes, listening, felt assured that a gorilla had seized upon him. He felt for his revolver, and as he was drawing it stealthily from its holster a voice asked in perfectly good English, "Who are you?"</p>

<p>Baynes started so that he nearly fell from the branch.</p>

<p>"My God!" he exclaimed. "Are you a man?"</p>

<p>"What did you think I was?" asked Korak.</p>

<p>"A gorilla," replied Baynes, honestly.</p>

<p>Korak laughed.</p>

<p>"Who are you?" he repeated.</p>

<p>"I'm an Englishman by the name of Baynes; but who the devil are you?" asked the Hon. Morison.</p>

<p>"They call me The Killer," replied Korak, giving the English translation of the name that Akut had given him. And then after a pause during which the Hon. Morison attempted to pierce the darkness and catch a glimpse of the features of the strange being into whose hands he had fallen, "You are the same whom I saw kissing the girl at the edge of the great plain to the East, that time that the lion charged you?"</p>

<p>"Yes," replied Baynes.</p>

<p>"What are you doing here?"</p>

<p>"The girl was stolen--I am trying to rescue her."</p>

<p>"Stolen!" The word was shot out like a bullet from a gun. "Who stole her?"</p>

<p>"The Swede trader, Hanson," replied Baynes.</p>

<p>"Where is he?"</p>

<p>Baynes related to Korak all that had transpired since he had come upon Hanson's camp. Before he was done the first gray dawn had relieved the darkness. Korak made the Englishman comfortable in the tree. He filled his canteen from the river and fetched him fruits to eat. Then he bid him good-bye.</p>

<p>"I am going to the Swede's camp," he announced. "I will bring the girl back to you here."</p>

<p>"I shall go, too, then," insisted Baynes. "It is my right and my duty, for she was to have become my wife."</p>

<p>Korak winced. "You are wounded. You could not make the trip," he said. "I can go much faster alone."</p>

<p>"Go, then," replied Baynes; "but I shall follow. It is my right and duty."</p>

<p>"As you will," replied Korak, with a shrug. If the man wanted to be killed it was none of his affair. He wanted to kill him himself, but for Meriem's sake he would not. If she loved him then he must do what he could to preserve him, but he could not prevent his following him, more than to advise him against it, and this he did, earnestly.</p>
</text>
