<text id="autogum_whow_doc277" title="Make South African White Pap" shortTile="make-south-african" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-11-06" dateModified="2019-01-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-South-African-White-Pap" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make South African White Pap</head><p>Maize Meal is a relatively coarse flour (much coarser than corn flour or cornstarch).. he Portuguese had originally brought corn or maize as it is  known in Southern Africa from the Americas to Africa. In the USA grits is the closets equivalent.
This food was originally eaten by the Voortrekkers during The Great Trek has become the diet staple of South Africa. Because of its ability to be stored without refrigeration, it is cheap and abundant in all shops and markets. It is also a food staple in Mozambique, Lesotho, Swaziland, Zambia, Zimbabwe, Malawi, Botswana and many other parts of Southern Africa. Traditionally maize meal is made into uphuthu, sour-milk porridge, pap, and also Umqombothi (a type of beer).
The raw ingredient of Maize meal is added to boiling water, the ratio of which produces either porridge or the firmer pap. For a creamier dish, milk is added to produce porridge with a thick texture and is commonly eaten for breakfast in southern Africa. The firmer pap is eaten with meat and gravy dishes as well as vegetables.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Begin with water in the pot. The ingredients are: 4 cups Water; 1 tsp Salt; 1 cup Maize meal. *Please note that you can use the same ingredients for making pap and porridge. <figure rend="Salt.jpeg"></figure> <figure rend="Star.jpeg"></figure> <figure rend="Mabela.jpeg"></figure></item>
<item>Bring the water to a boil for Pap. Set the temperature of your stove to 25 degrees C. Add salt to taste. Add  3 cups of maize meal and stir with a wooden spoon/fork until thick and smooth. Reduce the heat and simmer 30 minutes  stirring occasionally (3 to 4 times), until the pap is thick, stiff and cooked through.</item>
<item>Serve the cooked Pap. When cooked pap can be served with almost anything. South Africans love it with different kinds of side dishes: Meat, Salads, Stews and with Milk. <figure rend="Pap.jpeg"></figure></item>
<item>Bring the water to a boil for Porridge. Set the temperature of your stove to 25 degrees C. Add salt to taste. In a bowl, mix maize meal with cold water. Make sure it is smooth before pouring into the hot pot. Pour and stir the maize meal into the boiling water. Keep on on stirring until iti s well mixed. Let it simmer for at 30 minutes with the lid on. Add a spoon of butter and mix it up.</item>
<item>Serve the porridge with milk and sugar /honey.</item>
</list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Pap is an amazing staple food for the African people. Most African homes serve pap on a daily basis. It can be served with side dishes like meat, salads, different kinds of soups. You can even serve it with famatted milk (fermented milk i.e. yoghurt?) and sugar! It has even modified it to cook in less time. There are a lot of brands, but White Star is recommended.</item>
<item>Porridge is mostly for mornings. Make sure when making, it is smooth. You can either have white or brown porridge. For flavor, you can add sugar and milk. It is easy for kids to eat.</item>
<item>When cooking, kids should not be near the pot. The maize meal pops while it is being poured into the pot. So be careful.</item></list>
</text>
