<text id="autogum_academic_doc654" title="Positive Impact of Expert Reference Center Validation on Performance of Next-Generation Sequencing for Genetic Diagnosis of Autoinflammatory Diseases" shortTile="positive-impact-expert" author="Guilaine Boursier, Cécile Rittore, Sophie Georgin-Lavialle, Alexandre Belot, Caroline Galeotti, Eric Hachulla, Véronique Hentgen, Linda Rossi-Semerano, Guillaume Sarrabay, and Isabelle Touitou" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2077-0383/8/10/1729/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
Recognizing patients with monogenic AIDs is difficult because their clinical spectrum may range from very mild inflammatory episodes to severe chronic disease. Moreover, the disease features significantly overlap. Our targeted NGS approach resulted in genetic confirmation in a relatively small proportion (7%) of patients. This finding is consistent with two 2019 reports by Karacan et al. and Papa et al., who used recent guidelines for the definition of positive diagnosis as we did. Three previous studies using a broader definition claimed 19%, 20%, and 22% diagnostic yield. In those reports, for example, frequent variants, such as p.(Glu148Gln) (<hi rend="italic">MEFV</hi>), p.(Arg121Gln) (<hi rend="italic">TNFRSF1A</hi>), or p.(Val198Met) (<hi rend="italic">NLRP3</hi>), and all known susceptibility factors for inflammation were considered consistent with the diagnosis. Moreover, our definition was more stringent than these four previous studies because we considered that we could not conclude on the diagnosis when the parent’s DNA was lacking segregation analyses of heterozygous rare VOUS. </p>

<p>The low performance of the AIDs panel might also be explained by our study design that did not include most of the patients with features of FMF, MKD, and DADA2 because they were screened by Sanger sequencing. Still, the genes <hi rend="italic">MEFV</hi>, <hi rend="italic">MVK,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ADA2</hi> remained among the four most frequently involved in the conclusive diagnoses of our study. This observation possibly stems from a better detection by NGS of the new molecular mechanisms involved in AIDs (mosaicism, CNVs) and better information on these three diseases because they are among the best-described AIDs. In addition, FMF is now recognized as a disease caused by gain-of-function variants with a dosage effect rather than a purely recessive condition. For one-third of the patients with one heterozygous pathogenic variant in a recessive condition, the gene was <hi rend="italic">MEFV</hi>. If we had included heterozygous carriers of a <hi rend="italic">MEFV</hi> pathogenic variant, the genetic diagnosis yield would have improved up to 10% (<figure>Figure 2</figure>). </p>

<p>In an attempt to find a cause that could explain the low rate of genetic confirmation using panels in the patients referred to us, we wondered whether validation of the request by a specialized reference center could improve this performance. The success of the NGS approach was suggested to rely on its use in the context of a highly specialized clinical service for patients with AIDs. National reference centers and networks cover all the expertise necessary for patient care and operational management and efficiency. We established a pre-requisite for a systematic evaluation of undifferentiated AIDs patients by clinicians from reference centers. It is possible that many doctors from non-reference centers could not find the time to present their patients to MSM. This certainly accounts for the decrease in the proportion of patients referred by the non-reference centers. However, our study showed that this strategy resulted in a better clinical filter for ordering genetic tests and almost doubled the performance of our NGS strategy. Also, our reference center recently offered a diagnostic checklist to guide practitioners who may suspect an AID for ordering genetic tests. In our patients with a conclusive diagnosis of AID, the main features identified were mucocutaneous, articular, and gastro-intestinal. This result reflects daily practice because the cutaneous/mucosal, digestive tract, and musculoskeletal systems are the three most common systems involved in AIDs. </p>

<p>We cannot rule out a relative underestimation of the potential of NGS panels for AIDs in general. Indeed, because of our study design, some of the patients or their relatives were not available for NGS or segregation analysis. However, our aim was not to evaluate the exact performance of NGS but to find ways to improve it. In addition to the successful clinical option we demonstrated here, it is easy to predict the upcoming discovery of new genes or molecular mechanisms involved in AIDs that will continue to revolutionize our routine genetic diagnosis. Recent inputs of the literature advocate closer interactions between clinicians and geneticists in the era of whole-genome sequencing. Among them are the identification of genetic modifiers, affecting the penetrance of homozygous pathogenic <hi rend="italic">MVK</hi>:p.(Val377Ile) variant; the lack of detection of pathogenic variants in patients with a clear given phenotype, such as pathogenic canonical splice site variants not covered by Sanger and panel approaches (e.g., <hi rend="italic">ADA2</hi>:c.-47+2T&gt;C); or large chromosomal rearrangements, encompassing several genes in patients with complex phenotypes. In those circumstances, an MSM could help find the best appropriate strategy in accordance with the patient’s phenotype. </p>

<p>The role of the reference centers is to determine whether or not the clinical/anamnesis/genealogical tree is compatible with a known AID. If compatibility does not seem to be the case, the role is to evaluate the potential added value to perform the NGS. If this value appears to be low, the reference center recommends that no NGS be conducted in discussion with geneticists. Thus, this discussion decreases the number of individuals whose phenotype is not typically enough. </p>
</text>
