<text id="autogum_interview_doc867" title="part7_Wikinews interviews World Wide Web co-inventor Robert Cailliau" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-07-22" dateModified="2014-09-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_World_Wide_Web_co-inventor_Robert_Cailliau" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>The principle of an information market with micropayments is simple and it is not new (the French <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minitel">Minitel</ref> has had it since the early 80s).</p>
<p>There are currently three ways to put info on the web:</p>
<list type="ordered"><item>for free (but who pays my time?)</item>
<item>by subscription with a name and password valid for a certain length of time</item>
<item>by soliciting advertisers to put their ads on the site</item></list>
<p>Manner 1 can only if I have other sources of income.</p>
<p>Manner 2 is used often but puts off people because of the high level of the subscription.
That bars the reader from using many different sites, e.g. to browse many newspapers.  The sum of the subscriptions is too high.</p>
<p>For example:  I sometimes want to look up a word in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oxford%20English%20Dictionary">Oxford English Dictionary</ref>, but not so often that I find it worth my while to pay for the subscription.  Therefore I can't use it at all.</p>
<p>Manner 3 is the most used even if that is not pleasant for the user.  For example, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ViaMichelin">Via Michelin</ref>, an excellent service, has recently become very irritating because it carries so much advertising, in addition animated as well so that it is difficult to concentrate on what I want to do there for all the moving stuff.  Adverts, especially the animated variety, is a pest on useful sites.</p>
<p>With micropayments and digital money I would be able to pay Oxford a tiny sum for each time I consult the dictionary, but without having to pay a full subscription.</p>
<p>A good implementation of micropayments must also provide comfort:  I should not have to log in or agree, my computer automatically pays behind the scenes.  We are talking here of sums of less than a eurocent.</p>
<p>And I could of course set limits by telling the browser to warn me if I spend more than 10 Euros a day or when a site charges more than a cent for a page, etc.</p>
<p>In this way I could read the news in several papers without having to pay a complete subscription to each and having to log in.  If they want, sites can of course also distinguish between a paying entrance after which there are no more adverts and things work faster, and an entrance that is free but full of adverts.</p>
<p>In short, there is then a true market for information, directly between the seller and the customer. Nothing is obligatory, but a lot more is possible. With the Euro it is now perhaps time to try an experiment with micropayments.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi>: The web was invented in Europe, but it grew exponentially and to some extent the invention has exploded in your face; at any point did you feel that the WWW had been hijacked by the United States?</p>
</text>
