<text id="autogum_bio_doc191" title="Terence MacManus" shortTile="terence-macmanus" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-02-17" dateModified="2019-02-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terence_MacManus" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Terence MacManus</head>
<figure><caption>Trial of the Irish patriots at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clonmel">Clonmel</ref>. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Francis_Meagher">Thomas Francis Meagher</ref>, MacManus, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patrick_O'Donoghue_(Young_Irelander)">Patrick O'Donoghue</ref> receiving their sentences of death.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>Grave of Terence Bellew MacManus in the Fenian Plot, Glasnevin, Dublin.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Terence Bellew MacManus</hi> (born 1811 or 1823 – 15 January 1861) was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irish_people">Irish</ref> rebel who participated in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Young_Irelander_Rebellion_of_1848">Young Irelander Rebellion of 1848</ref>.  Sentenced to death for treason, he and several other participants were given commuted sentences in 1849 and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transported">transported</ref> for life to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Van_Diemen's_Land">Van Diemen's Land</ref> in Australia. Three years later in 1852, MacManus escaped and emigrated to the United States. </p>
<p>He lived in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Francisco,_California">San Francisco, California</ref> until his death in 1861.  There he was unable to re-establish his career.  His body was returned to Dublin for burial, where the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fenians">Fenians</ref> gave him a large funeral in honor of his part in the rebellion. </p>
<p>MacManus was notable for his statement in court in 1848; he explained his actions by saying: "...[I]t was not because I loved England less, but because I loved Ireland more."</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Terence MacManus was born about 1811 (or 1823)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-libraryireland-1">[1]</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tempo,_County_Fermanagh">Tempo</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/County_Fermanagh">County Fermanagh</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ireland">Ireland</ref>. He was educated in parochial schools.</p>
<p>As a young man he moved to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liverpool">Liverpool</ref>, a major port, where he became a successful shipping agent.  In 1848 he returned to Ireland, where he became active in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Repeal_Association">Repeal Association</ref>, which sought to overturn the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Act_of_Union_1800">Act of Union</ref> between Great Britain and Ireland.  After joining the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irish_Confederation">Irish Confederation</ref>, he was among those who took part with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Smith_O'Brien">William Smith O'Brien</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Blake_Dillon">John Blake Dillon</ref> in the July 1848 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Young_Irelander_Rebellion_of_1848">Young Irelander Rebellion</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ballingarry,_South_Tipperary">Ballingarry</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/County_Tipperary">County Tipperary</ref>.  MacManus and the other leaders were charged and convicted of treason, and sentenced to death for their actions.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-libraryireland-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Due to public support for clemency, the men's sentences were commuted to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deportation">deportation</ref> for life.  MacManus was transported to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Van_Diemen's_Land">Van Diemen's Land</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tasmania,_Australia">Tasmania, Australia</ref> in 1849 on the <hi rend="italic">Swift</hi>, together with O'Brien, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Francis_Meagher">Thomas Francis Meagher</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patrick_O'Donoghue(Young_Irelander)">Patrick O'Donoghue</ref>.  They were assigned to different settlements to reduce their collaboration in the new land. However, the Irish men continued to meet secretly. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>In 1852 MacManus and Meagher escaped from Australia and made their way to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Francisco,_California">San Francisco, California</ref>, where MacManus settled.  (Meagher went on to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_York_City">New York City</ref>.) Like other immigrants, the Irish revolutionaries carried their issues to the United States.  Ellis, captain of a ship that was supposed to carry O'Brien to freedom, also emigrated to San Francisco.  MacManus held a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lynching">lynch</ref> court of Ellis among Irish emigrants for his betrayal of O'Brien in his escape attempt from Van Diemen's Land.  The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Court_martial">court martial</ref> acquitted Ellis for lack of evidence.</p>
<p>Failing to re-establish his career as a shipping agent, MacManus died in poverty around the age of 50.  His body was returned to Ireland, here he was buried in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glasnevin_Cemetery">Glasnevin Cemetery</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dublin">Dublin</ref>, on 10 November 1861. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fenians">Fenians</ref> organized a huge funeral and nationalist demonstration to honor MacManus.</p>
<head>Quotes</head>
<p>From the dock before sentencing, 24 October 1848:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>... "I say, whatever part I may have taken in the struggle for my country's independence, whatever part I may have acted in my short career, I stand before you, my lords, with a free heart and a light conscience, to abide the issue of your sentence. And now, my lords, this is, perhaps, the fittest time to put a sentence upon record, which is this - that standing in this dock, and called to ascend the scaffold - it may be to-morrow - it may be now - it may be never - whatever the result may be, I wish to put this on record, that in the part I have taken I was not actuated by enmity towards Englishmen - for among them I have passed some of the happiest days of my life, and the most prosperous; and in no part which I have taken was I actuated by enmity towards Englishmen individually, whatever I may have felt of the injustice of English rule in this island; I therefore say, that it is not because I loved England less, but because I loved Ireland more, that I now stand before you".</p>
</text>
