<text id="autogum_interview_doc586" title="part4_Wikinews interviews Australian Paralympic skiers Toby Kane, Cameron Rahles Rahbula, and Mitchell Gourley" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-12-10" dateModified="2014-05-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_Paralympic_skiers_Toby_Kane%2C_Cameron_Rahles_Rahbula%2C_and_Mitchell_Gourley" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Cameron Rahles-Rahbula:</hi> This week I think Australia has a pretty good, strong team from a standing perspective, so we're probably racing against each other.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  So you do not care about the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Chile">Chileans</ref>, or whoever, hanging around?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Cameron Rahles-Rahbula:</hi> The Canadian and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US">American</ref> teams are here, and they've got some developing athletes. Probably more the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Europe">Europeans</ref> who are developing who've got the highest others skiing in our particular division, and the Americans are very strong with their sit skiers. So this week being just a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/North_America">North American</ref>-based race we'll probably be looking at the other two in terms of racing, but yeah, when we get over to the world cups over in Europe in January, that's when the whole field's together, and gives us some idea of what we're racing against.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I feel like we're almost coming to a close. What do you do outside of skiing? You had some life you said.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Cameron Rahles-Rahbula:</hi> I work as a physiotherapist, and I am a family man. Since Vancouver I haven't skied a huge amount since then. I've got a little boy, and so other priorities definitely start to take effect. I think as a skier, it's a challenge from the travelling perspective when you do have family. I think that's unlike a lot of summer athletes who have their training base next door. For us, we need to be always on the move, so that's always one of the challenges with alpine skiing.  You get the privilege of travelling but you're away from your family, so for me, my last year I have focused more on family life and sort of getting back into the skiing this year.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What do you do Mitchell?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mitchell Gourley:</hi> I'm still studying. I'm a bit younger than these guys so I'm...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Which university?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mitchell Gourley:</hi> I'm at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Melbourne_University">Melbourne University</ref> studying. So I've got pretty much a year to go now, but that'll take me two years to do just because of where Sochi is, in March 2014 I'll cut back this year coming, 2013, and I'll only do probably about half — I'll do five subjects as opposed to eight, just because when you're out travelling during the year and prepping, using your weekend to ski will it getting to you like that. With the schedule, from June to the end September will be pretty much flat skiing. Last time I did that leading into Vancouver, I mean I do that every year but probably a bigger load in the games lead that kind of thing. And I did that in the middle of Year 12 last time, and that was interesting, but now I can actually...</p>
</text>
