<text id="autogum_voyage_doc130" title="Nipigon" shortTile="nipigon" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=24647" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Nipigon</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://nipigon.net/visitors/">Nipigon</ref></hi> is a township of 1,600 people (2011) on the north shore of Lake Superior in <ref target="Northern%20Ontario">Northern Ontario</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>Nipigon is a small village on an isolated section of <ref target="Trans-Canada%20Highway">Trans-Canada Highway</ref> which follows the sparsely-populated north shore of Lake Superior between <ref target="Thunder%20Bay">Thunder Bay</ref> and <ref target="Sault%20Sainte%20Marie%20%28Ontario%29">Sault Sainte Marie (Ontario)</ref>. There is little population and few services outside the few villages on this lengthy stretch of highway. The local economy of Nipigon Township depends primarily on forest products, fishing, and tourism. Multiply Forest Products, a hundred-worker sawmill which was the largest employer in Nipigon, burned to the ground on February 6, 2007.</p>

<p>Nipigon's population declined by over 25% between 1991 and 2011.</p>

<p>Nipigon is a departure point for fishing excursions onto Lake Superior, the Nipigon River system and Lake Nipigon. Common fish varieties include Atlantic salmon, lake trout, speckled trout, rainbow trout, walleye, northern pike, bass, and perch.</p>

<p>In Jan 2016, the Nipigon River Bridge, the first cable-stayed bridge in Ontario, failed weeks after it opened. Traffic was rerouted through the United States, and road transportation between eastern and western Canada was not possible for a period of 17 hours. A pair of two-lane cable-stayed bridges opened in Nov 2018. </p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Nipigon Tourist Information Centre</hi>, 453 Trans-Canada Hwy, ☏ +1 807 887-3188 . Late May to mid-Oct: M–F 8:30AM–4:30PM, in the summer open M-F until 8PM and Sa Su 10AM-8PM. Interactive historical displays about the area, clean washrooms.</item>
</list>


<head>Get in</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Nipigon is on the <ref target="Trans-Canada%20Highway">Trans-Canada Highway</ref> where Ontario Highways 11 and 17 run concurrently. This means that there is only one road connecting eastern and western Canada. The stretch between Nipigon and <ref target="Thunder%20Bay">Thunder Bay</ref> is designated the <hi rend="italic">Terry Fox Courage Highway</hi>.</item>
<item> There is no passenger rail service in Nipigon-Thunder Bay.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="http://www.gokasper.com"><hi rend="bold">Kasper Bus</hi></ref> bus service connects to White River and Thunder Bay.</item>
</list>


<head>Get around</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Spirit Taxi</hi>, ☏ +1 807 372-0013 .</item>
</list>


<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Nipigon Historical Museum</hi>, 40 Front St, ☏ +1 807 887-0356 . Summer: daily 11AM-8PM. History of Nipigon from the fur trade to development of the forest industry, displayed through literature and artefacts: tools that were used, products that were made, pictures of people there at that time. By donation.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Nipigon River Recreational Trail</hi>. 8-km (5-mi) all-season riverside trail connecting the Nipigon and <ref target="Red%20Rock%20%28Ontario%29">Red Rock</ref> Marinas. Several lookout points (the most dramatic of which is Eagle's Ridge); leaves and foliage take on their fall colours from mid August through October.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Northshore Golf and Country Club</hi>, Golf Course Rd (off Trans-Canada 11/17 between Nipigon and Red Rock), ☏ +1 807 887-2006 . Nine-hole golf course with licensed dining room and restaurant, open 7 days a week.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ouimet Canyon Provincial Park</hi>, ☏ +1 807 977-2526 . Victoria Day weekend to Thanksgiving. Seasonal day-use park and nature reserve.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Paddle to the Sea Park</hi>, 52 Front Street (beside the shops and restaurants). A water park and interactive playground based on the book <hi rend="italic">Paddle to the Sea</hi>, which was made into a film by the National Film Board of Canada.</item>
</list>


<head>Guides, charters and adventures</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bowman Island Lodge and Charters</hi>, RR#1 Nipigon, ☏ +1 807 886-2504 . Bowman Island is off the south shore of St Ignace Island in the Lake Superior Marine Conservation Area. A 30-ft water taxi and 45-ft trawler carry 8-10 passengers. Outfitter supplies fishing packages (fly rod, spin cast or troll), transportation for canoes or kayaks, outdoor adventure packages.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">By the Bay Adventures</hi>, Nipigon Marina, 3 Brennen Drive, ☏ +1 807 887-4614 . Charter a boat+captain for $700-900/day or $350/half day.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Epic Adventures</hi>, ☏ +1 807 887-1008 . Mountain bike festival, hiking, geocaching.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hardcore Fishing and Adventures</hi>, RR#1 Nipigon, ☏ +1 807 886-2792 . Guided fishing trips, $300-500/day.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">McGuire Farm and Greenhouse</hi>, 600 Hwy 17 (RR#1), ☏ +1 807 886-1151 , fax: +1 807 886-9909 . May 1-Oct 31: M-F noon-8PM. Eco guiding tours and moose hunt guide, fresh blueberries and vegetables in season.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Nighthawk Charters</hi>, ☏ +1 807 885-3171 , fax: +1 807 885-3387 . mid-May to mid-Sept. Fishing and hunting packages, day excursions, dinner cruises, kayaking and sightseeing.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Nipigon River Bear Hunts</hi>, Hwy 17, ☏ +1 807 887-2813 , toll-free: +1-877-825-7417 , fax: +1 807 887-3801 . Local guide Bob Bearman leads (typically) six-day all-inclusive hunting expeditions for bear, wolf and moose. US$2000-5000.</item>
</list>


<head>Events</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Blueberry Blast Festival</hi>. First weekend in August. Guided berry picking, local craft and food sales, live music, Active Circus Zone, juggling show, youth talent show, active-play children’s games, minnow races, crafts for kids, cards for seniors, face-painting and Teddy Bear’s Picnic.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Canyon Country Birding Festival</hi>, Dorion, ☏ +1 807 857-2265 . last weekend in May. Ouimet Canyon Provincial Park, Eagle Canyon Adventures and the Dorion Fish Culture Station are on Trans-Canada 11/17 west of Nipigon/Red Rock.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Nipigon Ice Fest</hi>, 52 Front St.. One weekend, mid-March. Winter camping and ice climbing, Beginners, Intermediate and Advanced/Mixed levels.</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>
<p>A limited selection is available in the village, including a grocer (Zechner's), hardware (Home Hardware and Canadian Tire), auto towing and repair; there is a discount store (the Bargain Shop) and a second-hand store for clothing and general merchandise.</p>

<head>Eat</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">La Luna Café</hi>, 46 Front St, ☏ +1 807 889-1537 . Tu-F 8:30AM-5:30PM, Sa 9AM-6PM. Freshly baked goods, homemade soups &amp; sandwiches, pizza. Across the street from Paddle to the Sea Park. Breakfasts $6-9; individual pizzas, sandwiches and wraps $10.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Edgeview at Sunnyside</hi>, 133 Railway St, ☏ +1 807 887-5739 . Daily 11AM-8PM. Home cooked meals, and Pub foods, patio and licensed dining room.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sue Chef</hi>, 522 Highway 11/17, ☏ +1 807 887-3915 . Daily 8AM-10PM. Burgers, sandwiches, Indian dishes.</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>
<p>Beer and spirits are available for takeaway from the Beer Store and the LCBO.</p>

<head>Motels</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Beaver Motor Motel</hi>, 412 Hwy 11/17, ☏ +1 807 887-3132 . Single/double rooms and 2-bed/1-bath apartment-house suites with LCD TVs, full kitchenette in some rooms.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Birchville Motel</hi>, 386 Highway 11/17, ☏ +1 807 887-3141 , toll-free: +1-866-282-4843 . Wi-Fi, 32" flat screen TV with movie channels, fridges, microwaves, phones, coffee, bottled water and ice. Smoke-free, kitchenettes in some rooms.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Locking Horns Motel</hi>, 461 Hwy 11/17, ☏ +1 807 887-1750 , fax: +1 807 887-1752 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Northland Motel</hi>, Hwy 17, ☏ +1 807 887-2032 , fax: +1 807 887-1188 . In-room coffee and fridges, fax and copy service, automated wakeup calls, movie and VCR rentals.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pinecrest Motel</hi>, 536 Hwy 11/17, ☏ +1 807 887-2813 , toll-free: +1-877-802-3803 , fax: +1 807 887-3801 . 14 rooms, coffee, refrigerators, BBQ.</item>
</list>
</text>
