<text id="autogum_news_doc498" title="President Trump fires FBI Director James Comey, raising questions about Russia investigation" shortTile="president-trump-fires" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-05-10" dateModified="2019-07-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/President_Trump_fires_FBI_Director_James_Comey%2C_raising_questions_about_Russia_investigation" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>President Trump fires FBI Director James Comey, raising questions about Russia investigation</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 11, 2017</hi></p>
<p>On Tuesday, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">U.S.</ref> President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Donald_Trump">Donald Trump</ref> dismissed <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/James_Comey">James Comey</ref> from his position as head of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Federal_Bureau_of_Investigation">Federal Bureau of Investigation</ref> (FBI).  Officially, Comey was fired for mishandling the issue with former presidential candidate <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hillary_Clinton">Hillary Clinton</ref>'s alleged <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clinton%20email%20scandal">misuse of private email servers</ref>, but <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_Senate">Senate</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S._Democratic_party">Democrats</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/American_Civil_Liberties_Union">American Civil Liberties Union</ref> (ACLU) have raised concerns over whether the real reason may have been that Comey was leading the investigation into the Trump campaign's alleged ties to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Russia">Russia</ref> and possible <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Russian_interference_in_the_2016_United_States_elections">tampering with the election</ref> that placed Trump in high office.</p>
<figure><caption>James Comey with predecessor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert%20S.%20Mueller">Robert S. Mueller</ref> and then-President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref>.Image: US Federal Government.</caption></figure>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CNN">CNN</ref> reports a source within the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/White_House">White House</ref> told CNN reporter <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dana%20Bash">Dana Bash</ref> the President's office gave this reason intending to avoid controversy because many Democrats have also criticized Comey for mishandling the Clinton case, and some have blamed him for Clinton losing the election. Specifically, recently confirmed Deputy U.S. Attorney General <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rod%20Rosenstein">Rod Rosenstein</ref> released a memo criticizing Comey's statements in a July 2016 press conference, in which he called Hillary Clinton "extremely careless" for using private email servers to transmit government information but said she would not be charged with a crime. "The director was wrong to usurp the attorney general's authority on 5 July 2016, and announce his conclusion that the [Clinton] case should be closed without prosecution. [...] Compounding the error, the director ignored another longstanding principle: we do not hold press conferences to release derogatory information about the subject of a declined criminal investigation," wrote Rosenstein.</p>
<p>"It simply defies logic that President Trump, who made the FBI investigation of Hillary Clinton's emails a centerpiece of his campaign, would all of the sudden convert to the view that Clinton was treated unfairly," said Democratic Senator <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher%20S.%20Murphy">Christopher S. Murphy</ref>. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CNN">CNN</ref> legal analyst Jeffrey Toobin rejected it as "absurd." He went on to compare it to the dismissal of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archibald%20Cox">Archibald Cox</ref> during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Watergate%20scandal">Watergate scandal</ref>.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anthony%20Romero">Anthony Romero</ref> of the ACLU also expressed concern: "The independence of the FBI director is meant to ensure that the president does not operate above the law. For President Trump to fire the man responsible for investigating his own campaign's ties to the Russians imperils that fundamental principle."</p>
<p>Most <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S._Republican_party">Republicans</ref> agreed with Trump's decision. Senator <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Chuck_Grassley">Chuck Grassley</ref> said, "The handling of the Clinton email investigation is a clear example of how Comey's decisions have called into question the trust and political independence of the FBI." However, Republican <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S._House_of_Representatives">Representative</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Justin%20Amash">Justin Amash</ref> referred to the rationale behind the dismissal as "bizarre" and said that he and his staff would look into laws that might allow the establishment of an independent commission to continue the Russia investigation. Such a commission has also been called for by Republican Senator <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_McCain">John McCain</ref> and Democratic Senator <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bob%20Casey">Bob Casey</ref>.</p>
<p>Minority leader <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Chuck_Schumer">Chuck Schumer</ref> said, "If deputy attorney general Rosenstein does not appoint an independent special prosecutor, every American will rightly suspect that the decision to fire director Comey was part of a cover-up."</p>
<p>Schumer was one of several Senate Democrats to ask for a special prosecutor or special counsel. Others, expressing themselves both by <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Twitter">Tweet</ref> and traditional television interviews, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tim%20Kaine">Tim Kaine</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Virginia">Virginia</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeff%20Merkley">Jeff Merkley</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Oregon">Oregon</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cory%20Booker">Cory Booker</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_Jersey">New Jersey</ref>.  However, special prosecutors are appointed by the U.S. Attorney General, in this case <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jeff_Sessions">Jeff Sessions</ref> who recused himself from any further involvement in the investigation into the Trump campaign's ties to Russia.  According to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/ABC_News_(US)">ABC News</ref> chief legal analyst <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dan%20Abrams">Dan Abrams</ref>, the responsibility would then fall to a deputy, who would be unlikey to act except in response to pressure from Congress.</p>
<p>President Trump responded, as is his custom, via tweet: "Cryin' Chuck Schumer stated recently, 'I do not have confidence in him (James Comey) any longer.' Then acts so indignant. #draintheswamp" and "The Democrats have said some of the worst things about James Comey, including the fact that he should be fired, but now they play so sad!" </p>
<p>Deputy Director <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrew%20McCabe">Andrew McCabe</ref> is to serve as acting head of the FBI until a replacement is confirmed.</p>
This story has updates
See <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Changing_position,_President_Trump_says_FBI_Director_Comey_was_fired_over_Russia_investigation,_showboating">Changing position, President Trump says FBI Director Comey was fired over Russia investigation, showboating</ref>, May 13, 2017
</text>
