<text id="autogum_whow_doc383" title="Create an Upcycled Planter and a Wooden Pallet Planter" shortTile="create-upcycled-planter" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-06-21" dateModified="2019-08-10" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Create-an-Upcycled-Planter-and-a-Wooden-Pallet-Planter" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Create an Upcycled Planter and a Wooden Pallet Planter</head><p>A great start to a healthier life is to grow your own fruits and vegetables. You don’t need a big space to have a garden, as you can grow your own produce with small planters. In this article, you will learn how to make an upcycled planter where you can start to grow your plant and a Wooden Pallet Planter where you can then transfer your plant into later so it can start to grow crops. </p>
<head>Things You’ll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>1 Empty 2L plastic bottle with cap</item>
<item>10-12 inches of cotton wick</item>
<item>10-20 liters of potting soil</item>
<item>Clean pallet</item>
<item>Sandpaper</item>
<item>Nails</item>
<item>Hammer</item>
<item>Drill</item>
<item>Hand saw or table saw</item>
<item>Utility scissors</item>
<item>Work gloves</item>
<item>Safety glasses</item></list>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Creating an Upcycled Planter</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Cut the 2L plastic bottle. Make the cut about 1/4 of the way down, where the bottle flares out to the largest width.</item>
<item>Unscrew the bottle cap and drill a hole through it. Place the plastic cap on a hard work surface and carefully drill a hole through the middle of the cap. Screw the cap back on the top of the bottle.
<list type="unordered"><item>Ensure the hole is wide enough to fit your wick through.</item></list></item>
<item>Add water to the bottom of the bottle. Fill it up about six inches up.</item>
<item>Take the top half of the bottle and insert into the bottom half, cap down.
<list type="unordered"><item>Ensure a snug fit.</item>
<item>Make sure that the water in the bottom doesn't overflow when the top is in place.</item></list></item>
<item>Cut 10-12 inches of the wick and thread it through the cap.
<list type="unordered"><item>Ensure the wick is in the water and hold it at the top of the bottle.</item></list></item>
<item>Add soil to the top half of the bottle. While holding the wick at the top, add in the soil. The top half of the wick should now be buried in the soil.
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure that the soil is not overflowing at the top.</item></list></item>
<item>Make a small hole to plant your seeds.
<list type="unordered"><item>After planting your seeds, water them and place planter somewhere where they can get enough sunlight.</item></list></item>
<item>Take care of your plant and watch it grow.</item></list>
<head>Creating a Wooden Pallet Planter</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Break down your pallet. Remove all the nails from the pallet and separate the panels from the blocks.
<list type="unordered"><item>An easier way to do this is by cutting off the two shorter ends just inside of the blocks, then use a crowbar or hammer to remove the nails from the remaining wood.</item></list></item>
<item>Cut your wood panels to size. Depending on how large you want your planter and how many pallets you have available, measure then cut your wood to size.</item>
<item>Create the foundation. Cut two long pieces of wood, then nail shorter planks across forming the base.
<list type="unordered"><item>You can leave a bit of space between the planks to allow for drainage.</item></list></item>
<item>Form the walls to your box. Create a box around the base and in each corner nail in a support post.
<list type="unordered"><item>The support posts will determine how tall your box will be.</item></list></item>
<item>Continue to build up the walls. Build up the walls by nailing your side planks to support posts in each corner.</item>
<item>Sand away rough edges. When you have built up the walls to your desired height, use sandpaper to sand down the rough edges surfaces.</item>
<item>Fill with soil. After you have completed your box, fill with soil and transfer your mature plants.
<list type="unordered"><item>Always water your plants after transfer.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Safety first. Always wear eye protection when cutting or sawing wood.</item>
<item>Using household compost in your planters is a great way to give your plants nutrition and keep a green footprint.</item></list>
</text>
