<text id="autogum_academic_doc157" title="Preparation and Evaluation of Carbamazepine Solid Lipid Nanoparticle for Alleviating Seizure Activity in Pentylenetetrazole-Kindled Mice" shortTile="preparation-evaluation" author="Mona Qushawy, Kousalya Prabahar, Mohammed Abd-Alhaseeb, Shady Swidan, Ali Nasr" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1420-3049/24/21/3971/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Epilepsy is a disorder in the central nervous system (CNS) that is characterized by an increase in the number of electrical impulses that occurs in one focal locus of the brain and/or the entire brain, resulting in partial or generalized seizures. </p>

<p>The administration of antiepileptic drugs is mostly done via the oral or intravenous routes. Drug resistance at the late stage of therapy develops in about 40% of patients. Drug resistance leads to uncontrolled seizures, a higher risk of brain damage, and increased mortality rates. Patients with epilepsy suffer from emotional and behavioral changes, seizures, convulsions, muscular spasms, depression and, in some cases, unconsciousness. Drugs used for the treatment of epilepsy have poor bioavailability and eventually become ineffective over the course of treatment due to drug resistance. </p>

<p>Epilepsy treatment is often complicated due to the poor release of the drug through the adjunctive blood–brain barrier, which may be overcome by the preparation of the drug as solid lipid nanoparticles. The ideal delivery systems of antiepileptic drugs are the ones which provide localized and controlled drug release to targeted sites in the brain, which helps to reduce drug-associated toxicities and enhances the efficacy of the drug. </p>

<p>Carbamazepine (CBZ) is an antiepileptic drug with a narrow therapeutic index, and it is poorly absorbed when taken by the oral route. Its oral bioavailability is 75%, and its maximum achieved plasma concentration is about 4–8 h after administration. Carbamazepine acts through the inactivation of sodium channels, making brain cells less excitable. </p>

<p>Solid lipid nanoparticles (SLNs) are considered an alternative to colloidal systems like liposome, noisome and polymeric nanoparticles. SLNs consist of solid lipids, which act as a stabilizer when dispersed in water in the presence of a surfactant. </p>

<p>SLN is characterized by its small size (nano range), large surface area, and high drug loading capacity. In addition, it improves drug stability and has the ability to improve the oral bioavailability of poorly water-soluble drugs. Gangurde and Kumar prepared lamotrigine solid lipid nanoparticles with a high efficacy for treatment of epilepsy. Nair et al. prepared carbamazepine solid lipid nanoparticles to improve its therapeutic effect. Kumar et al. prepared solid lipid nanoparticles of methylthioadenosine for the management of neurological conditions via oral delivery. </p>

<p>The objective of the current study was to prepare carbamazepine solid lipid nanoparticles (CBZ-SLNs) as a novel and alternative method for other colloidal dispersion carriers. The study aimed to prepare CBZ-SLNs with high entrapment efficiency%, small particle size, and high anticonvulsant activity compared to free CBZ. </p>
</text>
