<text id="autogum_interview_doc242" title="part0_Dr. Joseph Merlino on sexuality, insanity, Freud, fetishes and apathy" shortTile="partdr-joseph-merlino" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-04" dateModified="2013-09-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dr._Joseph_Merlino_on_sexuality%2C_insanity%2C_Freud%2C_fetishes_and_apathy" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Dr. Joseph Merlino on sexuality, insanity, Freud, fetishes and apathy</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, October 5, 2007</hi></p>
<figure rend="Joseph Merlino by David Shankbone.jpg"></figure>You may not know <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joseph%20Merlino%20(doctor)">Joseph Merlino</ref>, but he knows about you and what makes you function.  He knows what turns you on and he knows whether it is a problem for you.  Merlino, who is the psychiatry adviser to the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20York%20Daily%20News">New York Daily News</ref></hi>, is one of the more accomplished psychiatrists in his field and he is the Senior Editor of the forthcoming book, <hi rend="italic">Freud at 150: 21st Century Essays on a Man of Genius</hi>.  The battle over interpreting Freud's legacy still rages, a testament to the father of psychoanalysis and his continuing impact today.  
<p>On the eve of the book's publication, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref> went to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Upper%20East%20Side">Upper East Side</ref> of Manhattan to discuss the past and future of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sigmund%20Freud">Freud</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/psychoanalysis">psychoanalysis</ref> with Dr. Merlino, one of the preeminent modern psychoanalysts.  Shankbone took the opportunity to ask about what <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Insanity">insanity</ref> is, discuss <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/paraphilias">aberrant urges</ref>, reflect upon <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/sadomasochism">sadomasochism</ref> ("I'm not considered an expert in that field," laughed Dr. Merlino),  and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/heteronormativity">hegemony of heterosexuality</ref>.  </p>
<p>Dr. Merlino posits that absent structural, biochemical or physiological defects, insanity and pathology are relative and in flux with the changing culture of which you are a part.  So it is possible to be sane and insane all in one day if, for instance, you are gay and fly from the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Kingdom">United Kingdom</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Saudi_Arabia">Saudi Arabia</ref>.</p>
<head id="What_is_normal_and_what_is_insane?">What is normal and what is insane?</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How do we know what is normal and what is insane?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi> That is part of what moved psychiatry and the psychoanalytic field to where it is currently, and that is the value and appreciation for societal values.  It's not like definitions of normality and pathology were handed down on some tablet that spelled out what those things are.  It is largely defined by society and culture.  We, as a profession, have to incorporate that as practitioners in that society and culture.  For example, something in our society might not be a problem, but it might be in another culture or society.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And that would be considered insanity?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  In some societies homosexuality is still considered pathology, where here it is mostly not.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So insanity is always relative to a society?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  To some degree, I think it is.  Not where there are underlying physiological problems; for example, severe depressions have biochemical changes, such as in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/serotonin">serotonin</ref> levels, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/schizophrenia">schizophrenics</ref> have differences in the way their brains processes information along with blood flow and other changes in various brain areas.  These are where it is more black and white.  Most societies would see those as mental illnesses.</p>
<p>The question is when does it come to the attention of practitioners and when does it become a problem, and that varies greatly by society.  For example, if you are on a farming society in an area that is not very populated, an individual might not be considered schizophrenic, but just odd.  They may be accepted within a family structure and tolerated within the community.  In our culture and society it is more difficult for an individual like that to survive without coming to the attention of an authority where they are put into treatment.</p>
</text>
