<text id="autogum_interview_doc798" title="part1_Antje Duvekot on life as a folk singer, her family and her music" shortTile="partantje-duvekot" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-11" dateModified="2014-03-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Antje_Duvekot_on_life_as_a_folk_singer%2C_her_family_and_her_music" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Does the idea that our lives on Earth may be all that there is unsettle you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  Yes, sure.  I think there’s more.  I’m always seeking things of beauty, and my art reflects the search for that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You had said in an interview that your family wasn’t particularly supportive of your career path, but you are also saying they were atheists who weren’t curious about the things you are curious about.  It sounds like you were a hothouse flower.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  Yes.  I think what went with my parents' atheism was a distrust of the arts as frivolous and extraneous.  They were very <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pragmatic">pragmatic</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  They almost sound <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soviet%20Communism">Soviet Communist</ref>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  Yeah, a little bit [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>].  They had an austere way of living, and my wanting to pursue music as a career was the last straw.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What’s your relationship with them now?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  I don’t actually speak to my mother and stepfather.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  A lot of reasons, but when I was about 21 I was fairly certain I wanted to go the music path and they said, “Fine, then go!”</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That’s the reason you don’t speak with them?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  That’s the main.  “Go ahead, do what you want, and have a nice life.”   So the music thing cost the relationship with my parents, although I think there may have been some other things that have done it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That must be a difficult thing to contend with, that a career would be the basis for a relationship.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>Yes, it’s strange, but my love of music is perhaps stronger for it because of the sacrifices I have made for it early on.  I had to fight.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Would you say in your previous work some of your conflict of dating would have been birthed from how your relationship with your family?  How do you see the arc of your work?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  My songs are sort of therapy for me, so you <hi rend="italic">can</hi> trace my personal progress through them [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>].  I think there is some improvement.  I wrote my first <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Love%20song">love song</ref> the other day, so I think I’m getting the hang of what relationships are all about.  I’m ever grateful for music for being there for me when things weren’t going so well.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Has the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraq%20War">Iraq War</ref> affected you as an artist?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  Not directly, but I do have a few songs that are political.  One about George Bush and the hypocrisy, but it’s very indirect; you wouldn’t know it was about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George%20W.%20Bush">George Bush</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How has it affected you personally?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  I feel sad about it.  People say my music is sad, but it’s a therapeutic thing so the war affects me.</p>
</text>
