<text id="autogum_interview_doc299" title="part5_Shimon Peres discusses the future of Israel" shortTile="partshimon-peres" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-01-06" dateModified="2013-08-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Shimon_Peres_discusses_the_future_of_Israel" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: A criticism of the Arab states is that back in the 1990s they had squandered the wealth that they were making on the high oil price because they had not invested it wisely.  It seems that that has changed, that the Arabs are creating these <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sovereign%20wealth%20funds">new wealth funds</ref> and that much of the money that is generated in the Middle East is now coming from Arab states.  Are you worried that Israel will become increasingly marginalized in the Middle East?  Right now it’s very <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraq%20War">Iraq War</ref> focused or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foreign%20relations%20of%20Iran">Iran</ref>-focused or the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arab%20states%20of%20the%20Persian%20Gulf">Emirates around the Gulf with their money</ref>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: Look, if you’ll ask me “What is the real wealth, money or brains?”  I say brains is the greater producer of wealth, not oil.  It’s limitless, and you’ll see that the GNP of Israel is very close to the Saudis’.  So they are 3 times larger than us and they have all the oil in the world.  We have brains.  We have to develop it.  And for that reason I say that whoever dwells in the past is ignoring the future.  Modern society is not based on the experience of the past but on risk-taking for the future.</p>
<head id="Is_Israel_a_united_society?">Is Israel a united society?</head>
<figure><caption>In 2006 the northern town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kiryat%20Shmona">Kiryat Shmona</ref> came under heavy shelling during the Lebanese War.  Norman Sandberg, (<hi rend="italic">above, left</hi>), who is a Vice President at Meytav, Israel's largest technology incubator, said it has become difficult to find people willing to leave the bustle of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tel%20Aviv">Tel Aviv</ref>, the heart of Israel's business and technology sectors, to work in Kiryat Shmona, where Meytav is based.Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: As you know, I’m part of a group from a technology mission over here of journalists.  We went to Meytav, your largest technology incubator, and spoke with their Vice President Norman Sandberg.  One of the things that he raised as an issue is that Israeli society is becoming dichotomized between Tel Aviv and the rest of the country.  How do you develop the brainpower without Israel becoming a city-state with Tel Aviv?  Mr. Sandberg told us nobody wants to go to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%20North%20District%20(Israel)">North</ref>.  They want to stay in Tel Aviv.  They don’t want to actually spread out and work on developing the rest of the country and invest outside of there.  Is that a problem that you foresee that this bubble is forming around Tel Aviv in terms of brainpower?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: The whole world is moving from rural to urban life.  Now everybody is made up of city-states; they are not a state of cities but cities that are states on their own.  First of all, Tel Aviv is becoming noisy like all cities.  It has all the flaws of a city, the crime and drugs, and the pollution.  Like in America, you see people and companies are leaving the cities.  It will happen here, too.  Secondly, it’s a matter of transportation.  If we shall speed up transportation, it’s a small country, then people will move.  In the United States, if you go half an hour, an hour, to work, it’s normal.  Here, an hour is the other side of the moon.  It’s nonsense.  They’ll get used to it.  And then, more and more people today are not working in the same building, but using the same computers.  So you computerize from home, which is again a difference.  Today, a young boy is attending three schools: the formal school in the morning,; the informal school—television—in the afternoon; and the new language, which is Internet.  We talk all the time that education is in the school; the school is just a third of the education of the children.  What keeps them up-to-date is more the television and now more the internet.  They look upon their teachers as old-age and a little bit boring, because they already know more than the teachers do.  They have a new language, they have a new mind, they have a new sensitivity.  In my judgment, the greatest thing is to bring over people from the old past that was slow--the cultivation of land--to a new future, which is as quick as an Internet.</p>
</text>
