<text id="autogum_interview_doc437" title="part0_Psychiatrist Dr. Jerald Block tells Wikinews about addiction to the Internet" shortTile="partpsychiatrist" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-10-21" dateModified="2017-05-30" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Psychiatrist_Dr._Jerald_Block_tells_Wikinews_about_addiction_to_the_Internet" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Psychiatrist Dr. Jerald Block tells Wikinews about addiction to the Internet</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 22, 2008</hi></p>
<p>Dr. Jerald Block is a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/psychiatrist">psychiatrist</ref> based in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portland">Portland</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oregon">Oregon</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref>. Dr. Block has attracted some media attention due to one theory of his - the idea that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet">Internet</ref> addiction can be viewed as a distinct mental condition.</p>
<p>In an interview with <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi>, Dr. Block discusses this theory, including what needs to be done about it, and the alleged violent response that can arise from an addict's withdrawal. Below is the full exclusive interview.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<figure><caption>Wikinews</caption></figure> <p><hi rend="bold">When and how did you first come up with the idea that it is possible to become addicted to the Internet?</hi></p>
<p>I have been working in this area since 1993.  Earlier, really.  I was initially trained as an Industrial Engineer before becoming a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doctor%20of%20Medicine">MD</ref>.  I remember reading and writing about the impact of technology on people for an ergonomics class in college, way back in 1985.  Even then, I found the topic fascinating.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Do you have any ideas for how Internet addiction could be treated?</hi></p>
<p>Harshly vs. gently.  The hardball approach is to punish for excessive use and restrict/limit access.  Perhaps send the individual to a computer-free outdoor camp for several weeks.  Some practitioners do this and think highly of the method.  My concern with it is (1) it generates tremendous anger; (2) there is a high relapse rate, since the restriction is to something enormously common in society, enjoyable, and the limits are imposed rather than self-endorsed; (3) what behavior will take the place of the computer?  Is it any better?</p>
<p>The gentle approach is to talk about the issue, come to some agreement about whether it truly is a problem, and then try to negotiate some sort of mutually-agreed on treatment plan.  This method also has its difficulties: it is time consuming, expensive, and does not guarantee the target behavior, the computer use, will ever be adequately addressed (at least from society's viewpoint).</p>
<p>Finally, both these methods can be helped along with the conservative use of meds, all of which would be "off-label" and targeted at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Obsessive%20Compulsive%20Disorder">OCD</ref>/Depressive sxs.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Activities such as gaming and viewing pornography predate the Internet, as does the potential to be addicted to them. What is different about it when it is online?</hi></p>
<p>Well, with regards to porn, there are the three As -- Anonymous, Affordable, and Accessible.  One has the illusion of anonymity so, when looking at porn or researching one's own paraphilia, individuals may no longer feel the shame that they might have in the past.  And, the porn is cheap and readily available.</p>
<p>With gaming, I'd modify the list somewhat but it remains mostly true.  I'd also add that games (and porn, sometimes) provide an effective outlet for aggression that is (1) time consuming, (2) socially acceptable, (3) entertaining, (4) empowering, and (5) engaging.  In moderation, the preoccupation can prevent people from acting on angry impulses.  However, over time, it may exacerbate such issues and make things worse.</p>
</text>
