<text id="autogum_voyage_doc39" title="Tehran (province)" shortTile="tehran-province" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=35509" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Tehran (province)</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Tehran Province</hi> (persian: استان تهران, transliteration: ostān-e Tehrān) is a province in <ref target="Central%20Iran">Central Iran</ref>. It covers on area of 18,909 km² and is located to the north of the central plateau of Iran. This province has common borders with the Mazandaran province from north, Qom province from south, Semnan province from east and Qazvin province from west.</p>

<head>Geography</head>
<p>The province of Tehran has over 12 million inhabitants and is Iran's most densely populated region. Approximately 84.15% reside in urban areas and 15.85% in rural areas of the province.</p>

<p>The highest point of the province is Mount Damavand at an elevation of 5,678 m, and the lowest point of the province being the plains of Varamin, 790 m above sea level.</p>

<p>The largest Lakes of this province are Karaj River and Jajrud River.</p>

<p>Mountain ranges such as the Alborz span the north; Savad Kooh and Firooz Kooh are located in the north east; Lavasanat, Qarah Daq, Shemiranat, Hassan Abad and Namak Mountains are in the southern areas; Bibi Shahr Banoo and Alqadr are situated in the south east and the heights of Qasr-e-Firoozeh being located to the east of the province.</p>

<p>Environmentally speaking, the climate of Tehran province in the southern areas is moderately warm, but in the mountain vicinity it is cold, and in the higher regions it is even colder with long winters and fairly large amounts of snow. The hottest months of the year are from mid-July to mid-September when temperatures range from 28°C to 30°C, and the coldest months experience -10°C around December–January. Tehran city has cold winters and hot summers. Average annual rainfall is approximately 500 mm, the maximum being during the winter season.</p>

<head>Cities</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> - the capital of Iran</item>
<item> - a small town outside of Tehran</item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> - the oldest existing city in Tehran province</item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
</list>


<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Palaces, museums, mosques, shrines, mausoleums and churches.</item>
<item> Golestan Palace, a <ref target="UNESCO%20World%20Heritage%20List">UNESCO World Heritage site</ref> where the Peacock Throne of the Persian Shahs can be found.</item>
<item> National Museum of Iran</item>
<item> Sa'dabad Palaces Complex</item>
<item> Glassware and Ceramics Museum of Iran</item>
<item> The Carpet Museum of Iran</item>
<item> Tehran's Underglass Painting Museum</item>
<item> Niavaran Palace Complex</item>
<item> The Tehran Museum of Contemporary Art features the works of great artists such as Van Gogh, Pablo Picasso and Andy Warhol.</item>
<item> Soltani Mosque, built by Fath Ali Shah</item>
<item> Atiq Mosque, built in 1663</item>
<item> Mo'ezz o-dowleh mosque, built by Fath Ali Shah</item>
<item> Haj Seyd Azizollah mosque, built by Fath Ali Shah</item>
<item> Al-javad mosque, Iran's first modernist design mosque.</item>
<item> The Old Sepahsalar mosque, another prominent Qajar-era mosque.</item>
<item> The new Sepahsalar mosque (Madreseh e Motahari)</item>
<item> Filsuf o-dowleh Mosque, Qajar era</item>
<item> Moshir ol-Saltaneh Mosque, Qajar era</item>
<item> Mo'ayyer ol-Mamalik Mosque, Qajar era</item>
<item> Shahr Banu Mausoleum</item>
<item> Javan-mard Qassab Mausoleum, a pre-Islamic semi-mythical hero</item>
<item> Dozens of Imam-zadeh shrines, hundreds of years old, including that of Imam Zadeh Saleh.</item>
<item> Ibn Babviyeh cemetery, where many Iranian giants such as Takhti and Ali Akbar Dehkhoda are buried.</item>
<item> Zahir o-dowleh cemetery, where many Iranian giants of art and culture such as Iraj Mirza, Mohammad Taghi Bahar, Forough Farrokhzad, Abolhasan Saba, Ruhollah Khaleghi, and Darvish-khan are buried.</item>
<item> Kordan Tomb, Seljuqi era, Karaj.</item>
<item> Maydanak Tomb, 13th century, Karaj</item>
<item> The Polish cemetery north of Tehran, where World War II Allied soldiers are buried.</item>
</list>


<p>Churches:</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Surep Georg Church, 1790</item>
<item> Thaddeus Bartoqimus Church, 1808</item>
<item> Tatavus Church, from the Qajar era</item>
<item> Enjili Church, 1867</item>
<item> Assyrian Church</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>
<p>Parks and recreation are among the greatest things to do while you are in Tehran Province. Here are things that might amuse you while you are in Tehran Province:</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Lavizan Forest</item>
<item> The Niavaran Public Library</item>
<item> Tochal Skiing resort: is one of the best ski resorts around the world.</item>
</list>


<p>The French (Poma) built gondolas that carry tourists and skiers to Tochal mountain.Within 10 minutes of driving distance from Tehran lies a ski resort. Tochal is the world's 4th highest ski resort at over 3,730 m (12,240 ft) at its highest 7th station. The resort was completed in 1976 shortly before the overthrow of the Shah.</p>

<p>Here, one must first ride the eight kilometres (five mile) long gondola lift which covers a huge vertical. The 7th station has three slopes. The resort's longest slope is the south side U shaped slope which goes from the 7th station to 5th station. The other two slopes are located on the north side of the 7th station. Here, there are two parallel chair ski lifts that go up to 3,900 m (12,795 ft) near Tochal's peak (at 4,000 m/13,125 ft), rising higher than the gondola 7th station. This altitude is higher than any of the European resorts.</p>

<p>From the Tochal peak, one has a spectacular view of the Alborz range, including the 5,671-m (18,606 ft) high Mt. Damavand, a dormant volcano.</p>

<p>At the bottom of the lifts in a valley behind the Tochal peak is Tochal hotel, located at 3,500 m (11,483 ft) altitude. From there a T lift takes skiers up the 3,800 m (12,500 ft) of Shahneshin peak, where the third slope of Tochal is.</p>

<p>Tochal 7th station has skiing eight months of the year. But there are also some glaciers and year-round snow fields near Tehran where skiing began in 1938, thanks to the efforts of two German railway engineers. Today, 12 ski resorts operate in Iran, but the most famous are Tochal, Dizin, and Shemshak, all within one to three hours of Tehran.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Darband hiking trail</item>
<item> Chitgar Park</item>
<item> Mellat Park</item>
<item> Laleh Park</item>
<item> Jamshidieh Park</item>
<item> Niavaran Park</item>
<item> Sa'ei Park</item>
<item> Shatranj Park</item>
<item> Tangeh Savashi</item>
<item> Darabad hiking trail</item>
<item> Darakeh hiking trail</item>
<item> Jahan-e Kudak Park</item>
<item> Azadi Sports complex</item>
<item> Enghelab Sports Complex and Golf course</item>
<item> Several caves, springs, and waterfalls outside Tehran.</item>
<item> Latyan Lake</item>
<item> Lavizan Forest Park</item>
<item> Vard-Avard Forest Park</item>
<item> Khajeer National Park</item>
<item> Kaveer National Park</item>
<item> Tar Lake</item>
<item> Amir Kabir Lake</item>
<item> Lar Protected Natural Habitat</item>
<item> Varjeen Protected Natural Habitat</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>
<p>Kebab shops are scattered all over the province. If you are sick or not into kebab, there are lots of international restaurants in the city which range from Persian to Italian.</p>

<head>Drink</head>
<p>There are a lot of tea houses in the province, especially the capital. Soft drinks such as cola, Fanta and Pepsi are also available. The ZamZam Cola is the local Iranian cola. Although alcohol is not allowed, it is drunk in some underground parties and weddings.</p>
</text>
