<text id="autogum_interview_doc422" title="part1_&amp;quot;Avast ye scurvy file sharers!&amp;quot;: Interview with Swedish Pirate Party leader Rickard Falkvinge" shortTile="partavast-ye-scurvy" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-06-19" dateModified="2015-10-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/%22Avast_ye_scurvy_file_sharers%21%22%3A_Interview_with_Swedish_Pirate_Party_leader_Rickard_Falkvinge" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Do you think you will be able to cover future expenses such as radio and television ads?</hi></p>
<p>Following the raid on the Pirate Bay, and our tripling of the member roster, we don't need advertising. We've been mentioned almost every news hour across all channels on national television in the last week.</p>
<p>Also, the established parties have now started to turn, following our success. Parties representing almost half of the elected parliament are now describing today's copyright situation as not working. They still don't understand why, though, they are just echoing what we say without understanding what the words mean. We'll get around to teaching them — them and the voters alike.</p>
<p>This might be hard for people not following the Swedish media to grasp, but we have made a <hi rend="italic">big</hi> splash. Today, our Minister of Justice was quoted as saying that he's open to changes to copyright laws that would make file-sharing legal, with the headline "Bodström (his name) flip-flops about file sharing." Immediately underneath were the Pirate Party's comments to his suggestions. Let's take that again: when a minister makes a statement about file sharing, media calls us for comments, and publishes them next to that statement. That's how big we have become since the raid on the Pirate Bay.</p>
<p>The Minister of Justice later denied having made that statement to the press that reported it.</p>
<p>We will never be able to pay for television ads, the way I see it. Unless a very wealthy donor comes on stage. (If any such person is reading this, we have planned how to spend up to $375,000 in a cost-efficient way up until the elections, on the chance that donations appear. That spending does still not include any TV ads.)</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are you aware of similar initiatives in other countries?</hi></p>
<p>Some are trying, but none have achieved the necessary momentum and critical mass that we have. We expect that momentum to happen once we get into Swedish Parliament and show that it can be done.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">[Ed.: A <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Pirate%20Party">United States variant</ref> of the party was recently launched. See also: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Category:Intellectual%20property%20activism">Intellectual property activism category</ref> on Wikipedia]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">The name "Pirate Party" seems to identify the party with what is currently defined as a crime: piracy of software, movies, music, and so on. Will a name like "Pirate Party" not antagonize voters, given that the label is so negatively used? How about potential allies abroad who argue for a more balanced copyright regime, such as the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Electronic_Frontier_Foundation">Electronic Frontier Foundation</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Creative_Commons">Creative Commons</ref>?</hi></p>
<p>Oh, it <hi rend="italic">is</hi> a crime. That's the heart of the problem! The very problem is that something that 20% of the voters are doing is illegal by punishment of jail time. That's what we want to change. Where the established parties are saying that the voters are broken, we are saying it's the law that is broken.</p>
</text>
