<text id="autogum_interview_doc624" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Mike Lebowitz, chairman of the U.S. Modern Whig Party" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-07-16" dateModified="2009-08-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Mike_Lebowitz%2C_chairman_of_the_U.S._Modern_Whig_Party" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Mike Lebowitz, chairman of the U.S. Modern Whig Party</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, July 17, 2009</hi></p>
<p>According to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pew%20Research%20Center">Pew Research Center</ref>, a non-advocacy organization that evaluates issues, attitudes and trends shaping the political landscape of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/centrism">centrism</ref> is on the rise in America. According to Pew, the number of Americans identifying themselves as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/political%20independent">independents</ref> has reached the highest level in 70 years.</p>
<p>Recently 36% of Americans say they are independents, 35% identify as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Democratic%20Party%20(United%20States)">Democrats</ref>, while 23% see themselves as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republican%20Party%20(United%20States)">Republicans</ref>. Some people are abandoning the major parties, re-registering as independent or joining <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/third%20party%20(politics)">third parties</ref>.</p>
<p>One of these third parties are the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Modern%20Whig%20Party">Modern Whig Party</ref> (MWP), who have enjoyed phenomenal growth over the past year; from just 3,000 members last summer to 30,000 now. With the Party's commitment to "fiscal responsibility" and "bold social progression", several <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conservative%20Democrats">conservative Democrats</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rockefeller%20Republican">centrist Republicans</ref> have been attracted to it.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> reporter Joseph Ford recently spoke with the Modern Whig Party's chairman, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mike%20Lebowitz">Mike Lebowitz</ref>, about the MWP's history, present state and future prospects. "Our membership is comprised of people from all parts of the mainstream political spectrum," Lebowitz explains. He says that the MWP has "pragmatic, realistic, and mainstream" approaches to the numerous issues facing America today.</p>
<p>"A number of print and broadcast media outlets have even gone so far as to proclaim that the Modern Whig Party is "potentially viable," and "makes sense"," Lebowitz points out. "We are building this organization realistically, methodically and gradually in an effort to get this right."</p>
<p>He went on to say much more — including why he thinks you should consider leaving the GOP or the Dems for the MWP — in the interview below. </p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<figure><caption>Wikinews</caption></figure><p><hi rend="bold">In a nutshell, what does the Modern Whig Party stand for?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Chairman Lebowitz</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Founded by <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iraq">Iraq</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Afghanistan">Afghanistan</ref> veterans, the Modern Whig Party represents a movement toward common sense, rational solutions ahead of partisan bickering and ideology.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Is the MWP on the left or right end of the political spectrum?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">CL</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> The general principles of the Modern Whig Party relate to fiscal responsibility, strong national defense and bold social progression. Looking a bit deeper into our detailed vision, the organization takes pragmatic, realistic, and mainstream approaches to areas such as energy independence and tax disbursement that take into account the needs of corporate America along with everybody else. To this end, our membership is comprised of people from all parts of the mainstream political spectrum. This tells us that we may be on the right track for developing that elusive formula where voters of all political stripes can find common ground with one political movement.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How old is your party? Who founded it and why?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">CL</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> The historic Whig Party was a dominant political force that included such luminaries as Abraham Lincoln. So in that regard, the Whigs are one of the oldest political movements in the nation. The modern revival was conceived by American soldiers serving in Iraq, who in turn communicated via the Internet such ideas with fellow soldiers in Afghanistan. In Iraq and Afghanistan, soldiers have a lot of time to reflect. We watched how common sense rationality was being abandoned in favor of partisan bickering and decisions based solely on ideology. We noticed how the partisan fighting and ideological focus trumped common sense on not just military issues, but most other issues as well. This included traffic, education, trade, scientific development, fiscal soundness, energy independence, etc. Upon our return in 2006, we initially revived the Whig Party as a military advocacy organization on behalf of soldiers, veterans and military families. By 2008, we had attracted a group of military and non-military supporters to the point where we became a mainstream political organization. The historic Whigs represented a moderate, common sense movement focused on improving US infrastructure and education. In this regard, we found the Whigs to be an excellent fit in our modern context.</p>
</text>
