<text id="autogum_interview_doc473" title="part0_Interview with Ton Roosendaal about Elephants Dream and free content movies" shortTile="partinterview-ton" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-05-21" dateModified="2014-01-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Ton_Roosendaal_about_Elephants_Dream_and_free_content_movies" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Interview with Ton Roosendaal about Elephants Dream and free content movies</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, May 21, 2006</hi></p>
<p>Three days after the Internet release of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/free%20content">free content</ref> 3D short <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elephants%20Dream">Elephants Dream</ref></hi> (see <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Elephants_Dream:_Free_content_3D_film_released_to_the_Internet">Wikinews coverage</ref>), we exchanged e-mails with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ton%20Roosendaal">Ton Roosendaal</ref> about the reaction to the film, open source filmmaking, and the changes to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blender%20(software)">Blender</ref> that resulted from the production. Ton Roosendaal is the lead developer of  the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blender%20(software)">Blender</ref> 3D rendering and modelling software that was used for the movie. He is also the chairman of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blender%20Foundation">Blender Foundation</ref>, a non-profit organization which was formed in support of the software and projects like <hi rend="italic">Elephants Dream</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How much money did the Blender Foundation spend on producing the movie? Has the money been fully recouped by DVD orders and donations?</hi></p>
<p>We still have to finish the final bookkeeping for this project. It has been executed in co-production with the Netherlands Media Art  
Institute, and we each had our own internal budgeting for the project. When you exclude expenses of pre-production and producer personnel, the  
total budget was about 120,000 €, of which we covered half. Our contribution was roughly covered half by the DVD sales, and half by European Union support (<ref target="http://www.uni-verse.org">http://www.uni-verse.org</ref> consortium).</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">One of the most common criticisms of CGI films is focus on  technology over content. For instance, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Final%20Fantasy:%20The%20Spirits%20Within">Final Fantasy: The Spirits Within</ref></hi> flopped with audiences, in spite of being an undisputed technical milestone. I've seen many reviews that criticized the plot of "Elephants Dream" as too bizarre or confusing. In retrospect, are you happy with the story development process?</hi></p>
<p>Haha, I knew the story and plot would get a mixed acclaim. There's a couple of reasons I'd like to mention for it.</p>
<p>First of all; the criticism resembles how people witness Blender itself, too. Many people expect that Free Software is an easy accessible  mass audience product. We get a lot of complaints by non-artists that they can't get into the software easily, whilst the complexity of commercial products like Maya or Houdini is perceived as a confirmation of its "quality". Apparently an Open Movie created similar expectations with the audience.</p>
<p>Luckily we also got many positive reviews of the artistic result of the movie. It is quite abstract, but definitely has many layers of information, inspiring many of the viewers to see relevant real life messages hidden here.</p>
<p>For this project we've teamed up with the Netherlands Media Art Institute, internationally renowned as a resource for video art. So for <hi rend="italic">Elephants Dream</hi>, we've had the luxury to challenge ourselves to create real independent artistic content as well. The artists had a lot of freedom from the start; they were responsible for the concept, story and creative development of the entire movie. This has resulted in a lot of quite personal choices, based on what the artists liked to do themselves. I really cherish such an approach, it has resulted in a very motivated team working crazy hours the last months to get it all realized.</p>
</text>
