<text id="autogum_interview_doc337" title="part2_Wikinews interviews DuckDuckGo, Opera, Mozilla, Wikimedia about DoNotTrack feature" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-12-23" dateModified="2019-01-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_DuckDuckGo%2C_Opera%2C_Mozilla%2C_Wikimedia_about_DoNotTrack_feature" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">HFB</hi>: There are obvious limitations to a pure self regulatory approach, but our hope is that self regulation will provide a sufficient good outcome in this case.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What do you see as an ideal solution to resolve the misleading situation with DoNotTrack that you acknowledged in your response to the second question?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">HFB</hi>: First of all, I personally do not think the name of DoNotTrack is misleading. However, the challenge is to have a meaningful standard that users can still be aware of the risks of that may be involved without giving a false sense of security. For example "private mode" in your browser does not prevent that your internet access provider can still keep track of what websites you visit, websites can collect information about you and so on. It only removes the trace of the sites you visited in your "browser".  Similarly, the websites can by accident or intention to be set up in a way so they do not comply with the DNT signal. There is always a risk of rouge agents.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How do you envision the "self regulatory" approach? How would it work?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">HFB</hi>: Self regulation basically means that the different stakeholders without having a legal obligation to do so, comply with a set of rules, for example an industry technical specification as W3C tracking protection standards. My take is that DNT would be a success if all major stakeholders involved in the process would comply with the standards. It is more an open question to what extent compliance to the technical standard is sufficient to comply with applicable laws in its respective country, for instance, in EU, or in the USA.</p>
<head id="Mozilla">Mozilla</head>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> contacted the Mozilla press office and got replies on behalf of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mozilla%20Corporation">Mozilla Corporation</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  When and why did you decide to start supporting the Do Not Track feature?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mozilla</hi>: Mozilla introduced Do Not Track in the desktop Firefox browser in January 2011, and in June 2011 Firefox for Android became the first mobile browser to support Do Not Track.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M</hi>: We support Do Not Track because we believe it is crucial to put users in control of their online experience.  Do Not Track is intended to give users choice and control in a persistent, accessible way without preventing the customization and valuable advertising that powers the Web economy.  We are seeking ways to give users better insight and control into the ways their personal information is collected, used, stored and shared.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Do you think that all websites should respect DNT users' preferences in the long run?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M</hi>: Mozilla is actively working with companies that have started to implement Do Not Track and with others who have committed to doing so.  Ultimately, the goal is for all industry stakeholders to trust and respect the signal in the long run.</p>
</text>
