<text id="autogum_interview_doc190" title="&amp;apos;The Regime&amp;apos; hacks 711chan.org in response to &amp;apos;Anonymous&amp;apos; attack on Scientology; takes web site off line" shortTile="-regime-hacks-chanorg" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-01-26" dateModified="2013-08-19" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/%27The_Regime%27_hacks_711chan.org_in_response_to_%27Anonymous%27_attack_on_Scientology%3B_takes_web_site_off_line" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>'The Regime' hacks 711chan.org in response to 'Anonymous' attack on Scientology; takes web site off line</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, January 27, 2008</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> has learned that a new entity calling itself <hi rend="italic">The Regime</hi> used <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/keylogging">keylogging</ref> to gain an administrator password to 711chan.org, a site popular with the open vigilante group "Anonymous" that has recently been attacking Scientology online.</p>
<hi rend="bold">This website has been deleted due to copyright claims from the Church of Scientology.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Message at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/711chan">711chan.org</ref> as of 9:57 p.m. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eastern%20Time%20Zone">EST</ref> on Saturday.</p>
<p>At 9:57 p.m. (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eastern%20Time%20Zone">eastern time</ref>) the site 711chan.org, was replaced, allegedly by <hi rend="italic">The Regime</hi> by the title <hi rend="italic">Church of Scientology</hi> along with a statement on the home page stating "This website has been deleted due to copyright claims from the Church of Scientology." A search performed using <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Google">Google</ref>, on 711chan has returned the number one result of the apparent hack. All that remains of 711chan.org is an apparent message to the members of the site to "run" and "hide."</p>
<p>"711chan is full of fucking fail for siding with Gaia. I'm out of here, faggots. Enjoy your Gaia," said the message, which currently is only available in a cached version.</p>
<p>At 1:45 a.m. on January 27, the site was replaced with "And now a message from our sponsors. YOU SUCK
711chan will be back online shortly. I love you guys for helping me out. &lt;3 plasma," acknowledging the possibility 711chan was back in control of their site. The site's name has been changed to "Church of 711."</p>
<p>The Regime's first attack went along with a message posted to 711chan's website (quoted below) saying that "This site has not been blessed by The Regime and is deemed lame", believing Anonymous to be self-proclaimed hackers (although this title was primarily used by the media). It also refers to Anonymous' attempt to bring down the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church%20of%20Scientology">Church of Scientology</ref> (named '<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Project%20Chanology">Operation Chanology</ref>'), saying that "chanology is lame, scientology is lame". It thereafter declared that the message board where Anonymous had been discussing Operation Chanology had been removed. Minutes later, 711chan stopped responding to queries.</p>
<p>The legitimate administrators of 711chan regained control after only three minutes, but it took nearly six hours to restore the site with recent additions missing. However, The Regime took the site down again twelve hours later, claiming to have removed the backups and stating, "all your db are belong to us" (an allusion to the phrase "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/all%20your%20base%20are%20belong%20to%20us">all your base are belong to us</ref>").</p>
<p>A new video posted to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/YouTube">YouTube</ref> by someone who claimed to be <hi rend="italic">The Regime</hi> shows a logo and uses a computer animated voice to threaten 711chan.org and their affiliates. <hi rend="italic">The Regime</hi>, however, denies making the video saying "we are in no way responsible for making, nor are we tied to that video in any way."</p>
<p>The video declares, "Dear 'Anonymous'. We are The Regime. Your attacks on Scientology have not gone unnoticed." The video's text description states that "Your attacks on Scientology have not gone unnoticed, we have the money, resources and tools to put an end to your SP behaviour and so called hacking activities. You have soiled the good name of LRH and now it is you that have *our* attention." </p>
<hi rend="bold">You have soiled the good name of LRH and now it is you that have *our* attention.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—"Re: Message to Scientology", video posted to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/YouTube">YouTube</ref>.</p>
<p>The acronyms in the text description are <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scientology%20terminology">Scientology jargon</ref> "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/suppressive%20person">suppressive person</ref>" (a person who criticizes Scientology) and Scientology founder <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/L.%20Ron%20Hubbard">L. Ron Hubbard</ref>. Both terms were also used recently in a leaked internal Church of Scientology video featuring <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tom%20Cruise">Tom Cruise</ref> promoting his beliefs. The video goes on to state that "Anonymous" has been declared "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fair%20Game%20(Scientology)">Fair Game</ref>" (another Scientology term).</p>
<p>The title of <hi rend="italic">The Regime</hi> video, "Re: Message to Scientology", is a reference to the video "Message to Scientology", which was posted by "Anonymous" to YouTube on Monday. The original "Message to Scientology" video has been viewed over 1,000,000 times since it was posted.</p>
<p>"We have your IP addresses, your documents and secret plans. We own your 711chan, your IRC, and we are taking care of your raid forums. Call off your attacks on our religion immediately, or 4chan YTMND, something awful and your other bases will be brought to ruin. Do not underestimate us. You are out of your league. You have been warned," added the video.</p>
<p>In an exclusive interview with <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi>, the group is only called <hi rend="italic">The Regime.</hi> When asked what their mission was, they stated "we have none."</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> also asked who or what was in charge of their group and they replied, "At one point, this would have been a complicated question as there were many tiers and positions of authority, however now leadership is confined to a single council." They are also not affiliated with any other group and act alone with "no contacts with groups or individuals outside of itself." They also refused to describe their group as a whole. They also stated to "define affiliated" when <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> asked if they were part of the Church of Scientology.</p>
<p>Their motivations are still not clear. When asked what motivates their group to do what they do, they replied, "What motivates any human to do anything? Money, Power, Respect? Choose one," but also state that they will continue their attacks "if necessary."</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> also asked if <hi rend="italic">The Regime</hi> was in any way affiliated with the Church of Scientology, including working for or against their beliefs or being a 'branch of The Church' <hi rend="italic">The Regime</hi> simply replied, "We are not Scientologists, this is all we have to say on the subject."</p>
<p>Sources within the "Anonymous" group have played down the actions of The Regime who - when announced on the IRC channel the group utilizes for communications - were said to be "... a bunch of gloryhunters ridin [sic] on our tails". Another user of the IRC channel, calling himself "Anonz", was quoted as telling other members of the group "... It's funny how they call us scriptbunnies yet use scripts themselves." The general consensus was that "Anonymous is not impressed."</p>
</text>
