<text id="autogum_interview_doc189" title="part1_Interview with recent Wikimedia Foundation board appointee Domas Mituzas" shortTile="partinterview-recent" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-03" dateModified="2010-09-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_recent_Wikimedia_Foundation_board_appointee_Domas_Mituzas" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why do you think you were chosen for this position, and what do you think you can contribute?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DM</hi>: One of reasons was both my long-term presence in site operations and communicating about our work, spreading our ideology, providing opinions. I try to be able to explain difficult topics in human language, and that is quite well appreciated. Additionally, I was being a bit of outsider - more of a reader than writer, so I feel that my views are slightly less community centric, more of value centric. My experience in a technology team is quite similar to what I expect to see in the board - wide array of issues to work on, and maintaining consensus is incredibly important to keep the productivity high. So even though I have deep roots in the project, I feel that I can bring in lots of fresh ways to the board. Of course, I will try to provide best possible technology advise, if the board needs it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Will you continue doing your previous technical work at the same time? If you do, how will you find a balance?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DM</hi>: I would really avoid to do all previous work - but it is not needed any more. Years ago we were monitoring the site 24/7, shortage of resources was causing all sorts of difficult problems. Now everything is way more steady and reliable, so I have way much more free time. I used to do lots of other activities too, so I think I can scale my time just fine. And still, of course, I'll provide as much work to technical part as needed, it just isn't as demanding as it used to be, and we're really happy about that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What major actions do you expect to come your way during your term in office?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DM</hi>: Though my term is quite short for now (until June elections), the biggest work will be done in understanding how the foundation should function to establish a really long-term presence, to support the projects far into the future. It may need changes in how we get external experience, how we interact with other organizations, how we do interact with office staff and each other. Foundation did lots of work to get to stable and reliable state, now it is time to think more about the future sustainability and expansion.</p>
<p>I have operations experience, so of course I will want to maintain high efficiency of overall operation, but on the other hand I want to work on scaling other parts of the foundation - especially reach out, evangelism, and of course - fundraising. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Do you expect any major upgrades to be needed to hardware or software anytime soon, and if so what?</hi></p>
</text>
