<text id="autogum_interview_doc073" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Indiana State Senator Mike Delph" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-03-26" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Indiana_State_Senator_Mike_Delph" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Indiana State Senator Mike Delph</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 29, 2014</hi></p>
<hi rend="italic">This is an edited transcript of a </hi>Wikinews<hi rend="italic"> exclusive audio interview.</hi>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Special:FilePath/Senator_Mike_Delph_2014.jpg">File:Senator Mike Delph 2014.jpg</ref></p><figure><caption>Indiana State Senator Mike Delph, S-29<hi rend="italic">(Image <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Template:Missing_image/message">missing</ref> from commons: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/File:Senator_Mike_Delph_2014.jpg">image</ref>; <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Special:Log?page=File%3ASenator+Mike+Delph+2014.jpg">log</ref>)</hi></caption></figure>
<p>On <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi>, we have an exclusive audio interview with Indiana State Senator <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mike%20Delph">Mike Delph</ref>.</p>
<p>Today is Thursday, March 27, 2014. I am Chad Tew and we are here in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WSWI">The Edge</ref> radio studios with my journalism students and recording from the campus of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/University_of_Southern_Indiana">University of Southern Indiana</ref>.</p>
<p>This is <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi>.</p>
<head id="Introduction">Introduction</head>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Indiana">Indiana</ref> State Senator Mike Delph is a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(US)">Republican</ref> who represents the northwest side of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indianapolis">Indianapolis</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carmel,%20Indiana">Carmel</ref>, as well as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zionsville,%20Indiana">Zionsville</ref>, Indiana.</p>
<p>After being selected to finish former State Senator J. Murray Clark's final term in 2005, Mike Delph has served two full terms for District 29 in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indiana%20Senate">Indiana State Senate</ref>. He is currently facing re-election this fall. His opponent is likely to be <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Democratic_Party_(US)">Democrat</ref> JD Ford, who is running as an openly gay candidate. </p>
<p>Senator Delph has also been considered in the past for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_House_of_Representatives">US Congress</ref> but he declined to run, and he has already been mentioned in the Indiana media as a possible candidate for any potential opening in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_Senate">US Senate</ref> in 2016. He is widely known across the state of Indiana for both his <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_state_of_Arizona_signs_into_law_controversial_immigration_bill">Arizona-style</ref> legislation on immigration and his support of traditional marriage.</p>
<p>During the legislative session this year, Senator Delph made what is known in Indiana as the "tweet heard around the world". The tweet announced the defeat of a proposed amendment to the Indiana State Constitution in a form that would have banned civil unions. Senate leader <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20C.%20Long">David Long</ref> punished Delph because of this tweet on the grounds that it concerned confidential caucus information. What exactly took place in that Republican caucus and between Senator Delph and Senator Long is currently unknown to the public.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Tew: State Senator Delph good morning and welcome to <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Delph</hi>: Thanks for having me professor.</p>
<head id="Interview_(part_I):_A_biographical_portrait">Interview (part I): A biographical portrait</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Chad Tew: Here with our first question is Ashely Jones Phillips. Jones Phillips: Hi! Good morning, Senator Mike Delph. My name Is Ashley Jones-Phillips. The first question that I have is, I wanted to know if you can tell me a little bit about your parents, where are you from, and where were you were raised and born?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Delph</hi>: Sure, I  grew up here in Carmel, Indiana. I was raised by my mother. My parents were divorced for most of my upbringing. While my father was on leave from his business — or actually helping his dad, my grandfather, with one of their plants out east — I was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South%20Weymouth,%20Massachusetts">South Weymouth</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Massachusetts">Massachusetts</ref>, just outside of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Boston">Boston</ref>. So I was actually born in Boston or just outside of Boston but raised in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Indiana">Indiana</ref> by my mother. I have three brothers. I shared a bedroom with my little brother John. And my two older brothers Jamie and Stephen were with us as well.</p>
</text>
