<text id="autogum_bio_doc386" title="Rowland York" shortTile="rowland-york" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-01-30" dateModified="2017-07-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rowland_York" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Rowland York</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">Rowland York</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Yorke</hi> (died 1588) was an English <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soldier">soldier</ref> of fortune and defector to Spain.</p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>Rowland York was the ninth of eleven sons of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_York_(Master_of_the_Mint)">Sir John York</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref>  He volunteered for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Netherlands">Netherlands</ref> under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Morgan_of_Llantarnam">Thomas Morgan of Llantarnam</ref> in 1572. He embarked at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gravesend,_Kent">Gravesend</ref> on 19 March that year with his two companions, the poet <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Gascoigne">George Gascoigne</ref> and William Herle, but the ship in which they sailed was nearly lost on the coast of Holland owing to the incompetence of the Dutch pilot.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> Reaching the English camp in safety, he took part in August that year in the attack on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goes">Goes</ref> under Captain (afterwards Sir) <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Humphrey_Gilbert">Humphrey Gilbert</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_the_Silent">the Prince of Orange</ref>'s agent Jerome Tseraerts.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Plots and equivocal reputation</head>
<p>Opinions differed about York. By some he was held "bolde of courage, provident in direction, industrious in labour, and quick in execution".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> But his profligacy and the fact that he was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_Catholic">Roman Catholic</ref> caused him from the first to be distrusted by the states.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Meteren-6">[6]</ref> In October 1580 he was reported by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Herle_(spy)">William Herle</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_Walsingham">Francis Walsingham</ref> to have been arrested on a charge of felony.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>Four years later York was detected in a plot with John Van Imbyss to betray <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ghent">Ghent</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_Farnese,_Duke_of_Parma">the Duke of Parma</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> Against the advice of the Prince of Orange, who would have preferred a more summary punishment, he was clapped in prison in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brussels">Brussels</ref>, whence he was released when the city fell into Parma's hands in 1585. He served at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siege_of_Antwerp_(1584-1585)">siege of Antwerp</ref>, but by the intercession of his friends he was allowed to return to England.</p>
<p>Joining the expedition under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Dudley,_1st_Earl_of_Leicester">the Earl of Leicester</ref> that year, he succeeded in ingratiating himself with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sir_Philip_Sidney">Sir Philip Sidney</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Meteren-6">[6]</ref> Appointed by Leicester  to the command of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zutphen">Zutphen</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sconce_(fortification)">sconce</ref>, he, according to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Camden">William Camden</ref>, took the opportunity thus offered him of paying back a grudge he had against the earl by surrendering the sconce to the Spaniards and inducing Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Stanley_(Elizabethan)">William Stanley</ref> to do the same for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deventer">Deventer</ref>.</p>
<p>He was appointed captain of a troop of lancers in the Spanish service; but was not, as he thought, sufficiently rewarded. Since he was known to be a bold and determined villain,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> it is said the Spaniards took precaution to prevent any double treachery by causing him to be poisoned.</p>
<head>Death</head>
<p>He died on a Sunday in February 1588, having first ‘received sacraments, unction, and all’.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> Three years later his body was exhumed and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gibbeting">gibbeted</ref> by order of the states. His heir was Edmund Yorke, who was executed at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tyburn">Tyburn</ref> in 1595 for attempting to assassinate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen_Elizabeth_I">Queen Elizabeth</ref>. Edmund had been persuaded by his uncle's associate Sir William Stanley, and Stanley's rather mysterious lieutenant Jacques de Francesci (Captain Jacques), that the assassination would be a meritorious act. On returning to England he quickly fell under suspicion, due perhaps to his association with the Irish fencing master <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patrick_O'Collun">Patrick O'Collun</ref>.  They were both arrested, along with Richard Williams, and all three were convicted of treason and executed.</p>
</text>
