<text id="autogum_interview_doc096" title="part0_Wikinews interviews specialists on Russian intervention in Ukraine" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-03-02" dateModified="2016-11-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_specialists_on_Russian_intervention_in_Ukraine" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews specialists on Russian intervention in Ukraine</head>
<figure><caption>Map of the Autonomous Republic of Crimea and of Sevastopol, Ukraine. Image: PANONIAN.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>People in Ukraine protesting against Russia's intervention "Crimea is Ukraine". Image: ВО Свобода.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption> A Crimean self-defense group with shields painted as the flag of the autonomous republic. Image: E. Arrott.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 5, 2014</hi>
In the past few days, tension has been increasing due to conflict between <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ukraine">Ukraine</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Russia">Russian Federation</ref> which has led to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Kingdom">United Kingdom</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">France</ref> increasing pressure on Russia to remove their troops from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Crimea">Crimea</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> interviewed specialists in Russian foreign policy and specialists in international law about the legality of Russia's actions and the consequences of any sanctions imposed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G7">G7</ref> nation economies.</p>
<head id="Interviewees">Interviewees</head>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> interviewed:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Jane Burbank</hi></hi>, Professor of History and Russian and Slavic Studies at the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York_University">New York University</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York">New York</ref></item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Jeremy Morris</hi></hi>, Senior Lecturer in Russian Studies at the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/University_of_Birmingham">University of Birmingham</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Birmingham">Birmingham</ref></item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Craig Brandist</hi></hi>, Professor of Cultural Theory and Intellectual History in the Department of Russian and Slavonic Studies at the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/University_of_Sheffield">University of Sheffield</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sheffield">Sheffield</ref></item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Stephen Blank</hi></hi>, Senior Fellow for Russia at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American%20Foreign%20Policy%20Council">American Foreign Policy Council</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Washington,_D.C.">Washington, D.C.</ref></item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Yanni Kotsonis</hi></hi>, Director, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York_University">New York University</ref> Jordan Center for the Advanced Study of Russia in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York">New York</ref>.</item></list>
<head id="Wikinews_Q&amp;A"><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> Q&amp;A</head>
<figure><caption> File photo of interviewee Craig Brandist. Image: Craig Brandist.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Are Russian troop deployments into Ukrainian territory a clear violation of sovereignty?</p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Morris</hi>: Yes.</item></list></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Burbank</hi>: Yes, the borders of the Ukrainian state were drawn up in 1991 and reinforced by the 1994 Budapest accords.  See the article by Paul Goble on these accords.</item></list></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Brandist</hi>: It would be hard to describe it otherwise. That said, however, it is quite extraordinary hypocrisy for the US and UK to strike moral poses about this, especially after <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iraq">Iraq</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Afghanistan">Afghanistan</ref>. Russia clearly has strategic interests in the region, and there is a large Russian-speaking population in much of Ukraine, a majority in Crimea and an important part of the east of the country, and the arrangement after the collapse of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/USSR">USSR</ref> was clearly fragile, especially when <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NATO">NATO</ref> expansion took place. None of this is to excuse Russian actions, but they cannot be understood without focus on the 'great game' of which it is part.</item></list></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Blank</hi>: By any standard Russia's actions represent a violation of Ukrainian sovereignty and integrity, a premeditated break with numerous treaties signed by Russia guaranteeing Ukraine's security, integrity, and sovereignty, and thus <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arseniy%20Yatsenyuk">Premier Yatsenyuk</ref> is right these are acts of war.</item></list></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Kotsonis</hi>: On the surface it seems so. Mind you, it is complicated because Russia has been given rights to the bases on the Crimea and this may give Russia the pretext for a larger intervention. But it does not seem to be a clear-cut legal case for intervention and everyone understands that this is Russia smarting over the loss of an ally in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Viktor_Yanukovich">Yanukovich</ref> and guarding its own back yard interests.</item></list></p>
</text>
