<text id="autogum_interview_doc648" title="part6_Popular soap opera &amp;apos;The Young and the Restless&amp;apos; celebrates 35 years on the air" shortTile="partpopular-soap" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-25" dateModified="2014-04-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Popular_soap_opera_%27The_Young_and_the_Restless%27_celebrates_35_years_on_the_air" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi>: You've been working at Y&amp;R eleven years across two separate stints. That kind of tenure in any job is a long time. What made you stick with it as long as you have?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Michelle Stafford</hi>: Because it's fun!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi>: Do you think Phyllis and Nicholas have a fighting chance, or will Phyllis be doomed to losing the men she loves, like with Danny and Jack?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Michelle Stafford</hi>: I think that it's a soap opera and nobody ever stays happy for a long long time.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi>: Phyllis had a lot of foils and enemies in the series, like Christine, Drucilla, and Diane. Which one of those women do you think is Phyllis's epic foil? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Michelle Stafford</hi>: Christine by far.  She really really really gets under Phyllis' skin. The other two women are bad themselves, so they don't get under her skin.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi>: You've won two Emmy Awards, both from separate and distinct parts in your story. Out of the work which got you both Emmy Awards, which do you feel was your strongest body of work, the one you received on your first stint, or the one you got for your current stint?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Michelle Stafford</hi>: Because the Emmys are judged by submitting two shows, I can't honestly answer that question. The way Emmys are judged are on two shows from that year. And you win if you have two strong shows, which is really luck. A lot of luck, some talent, but a lot of luck. You hope those two shows mix well together. That's luck too.  I had other years where I had more of a storyline written for me and didn't win.  So it's really based on if you're lucky enough to get two shows that really stand out.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi>: Do you think Y&amp;R should make more use of umbrella storylines, like the recent "Out of the Ashes" event?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Michelle Stafford</hi>: I'm a big fan of character driven storylines. That's why I was a big fan of the Nick/Phyllis affair; that was very much a character driven storyline and ratings really peaked at that time because everyone was interested in seeing the fallout. I think that any actor on daytime is going to answer that question the same way.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi>: Some of your fans are new to the show, and others have watched since you first appeared in 1994, and others have watched since the show first started. What would you like to say as an end note to all of your fans?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Michelle Stafford</hi>: Thank you for watching! I hope we've entertained you all.  When I watched the daytime shows when I was younger I used to be highly entertained.  I hope you're as entertained as I was.</p>
</text>
