<text id="autogum_voyage_doc483" title="Lansing" shortTile="lansing" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=19076" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Lansing</head>


<ref target="http://www.lansing.org/"><hi rend="bold">Lansing</hi></ref> is an aesthetically pleasing city, and as <ref target="Michigan">Michigan</ref>'s state capital, it is home to many government offices. Downtown Lansing has a historic shopping district amidst the campus of Thomas M. Cooley Law School. Its suburb—<ref target="East%20Lansing">East Lansing</ref>—is the home of Michigan State University, a Big Ten school and one of the <ref target="United%20States%20of%20America">United States'</ref> largest and most distinguished public universities with three medical schools and a law school. General Motors has a major presence in the area. The Lansing metro area has a population of about 464,000 (2010).

<head>By car</head>
<p>Lansing is easily accessible from <ref target="Detroit">Detroit</ref> and <ref target="Chicago">Chicago</ref>. Interstate 96 directly connects Lansing and East Lansing to Detroit and <ref target="Grand%20Rapids">Grand Rapids</ref>. US-127 to Interstate 94 connects Lansing and East Lansing to Chicago, <ref target="Ann%20Arbor">Ann Arbor</ref>, and Detroit. Interstate 69 connects Lansing and East Lansing to <ref target="Flint">Flint</ref> and <ref target="Fort%20Wayne">Fort Wayne</ref>.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<ref target="http://www.cata.org/">Capital Area Transportation Authority (CATA)</ref> provides local bus service.


<list type="unordered">
<item> Greyhound Lines service Lansing and East Lansing, with direct connections to Detroit, Grand Rapids, and <ref target="Kalamazoo">Kalamazoo</ref> (with transfers to Chicago).</item>
<item> Owosso, Michigan-based Indian Trails Bus Lines provides daily service to Chicago.</item>
<item> Michigan Flyer Motorcoach service provides multiple daily connections to Detroit Metropolitan Airport with stops in Jackson and Ann Arbor.</item>
</list>


<head>By train</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="Amtrak">Amtrak</ref></hi> provides one daily train service via the <hi rend="italic">Blue Water Service</hi>, which connects to <ref target="Flint">Flint</ref> and <ref target="Port%20Huron">Port Huron</ref> to the east and <ref target="Battle%20Creek">Battle Creek</ref>, <ref target="Kalamazoo">Kalamazoo</ref>, and <ref target="Chicago">Chicago</ref> to the west. There's also Amtrak Thruway Buses to the <hi rend="italic">Wolverine</hi> line between Chicago and <ref target="Detroit">Detroit</ref> as well as the <hi rend="italic">Capitol</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Lake Shore Limited</hi> services via <ref target="Toledo%20%28Ohio%29">Toledo</ref>.</p>

<p>All trains depart from (+1 800-872-7245), located on 1240 S Harrison Rd next to the Michigan State University in East Lansing. CATA's route 20 provides service to the station for both departures and arrivals on weekdays, and for arrivals to East Lansing on Saturday. Connections to downtown Lansing are provided by route 1.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
 ( LAN ) is in DeWitt Township, 3 miles (5 km) northwest of downtown Lansing on Grand River Avenue (Business Route 96). Capital Region International Airport offers non-stop domestic flights to Detroit, Chicago, <ref target="Minneapolis">Minneapolis</ref>, <ref target="Atlanta">Atlanta</ref>, <ref target="Washington%20D.C.">Washington D.C.</ref>, and <ref target="Orlando">Orlando</ref>. Non-stop international flights are available seasonally to <ref target="Canc%C3%BAn">Cancún</ref> and <ref target="Puerto%20Vallarta">Puerto Vallarta</ref>, <ref target="Mexico">Mexico</ref>; and <ref target="Punta%20Cana">Punta Cana</ref>, <ref target="Dominican%20Republic">Dominican Republic</ref>. A concierge travel center in the airport terminal offers the ability to book airline tickets, cruises, tours, car rentals, and hotel rooms. The airport is served by Capital Area Transit Authority (CATA) bus line 14, which provides direct service to downtown Lansing.

<ref target="Detroit%20Metropolitan%20Airport">Detroit Metropolitan Airport</ref>, Flint Bishop International Airport, and Grand Rapids Gerald R. Ford International Airport are other nearby airports which serve the region.

<head>By taxi</head>
<p>A large number of taxi companies provide around the clock service to the Lansing-area. It is not necessary to call ahead for evening taxi service near downtown East Lansing, but riders should allow at least 30 minutes for taxi service to arrive elsewhere. This is especially true on weekends. A service in the Meridian Township area is Meridian Transportation LLC. They can be reached at 517-339-TAXI (8294)</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>Lansing is served by a number of highways. Travel by car to any part of the city normally takes very little time. Traffic is generally light in the region. While there is some rush hour traffic, visitors driving in the region should not anticipate heavy congestion. The heaviest traffic is concentrated on the east and west sides of the city.</p>

<p>The Lansing-area is served by the Capital Area Transportation Authority (CATA) bus system. Visitors should find bus service to downtown Lansing, downtown East Lansing, and Michigan State University a convenient and affordable alternative to driving. Buses along the Michigan/Grand River Ave corridor (Route 1), which travel between downtown Lansing and East Lansing, run until 3AM on Thursday, Friday, and Saturday, making it easy to avoid driving and parking fees. CATA recommends using the smartphone app Transit to plan trips, track buses in real time, and see up-to-date departure information.</p>

<p>Many companies provide taxi service throughout the area. Taxi service is heavily concentrated in the downtown East Lansing-area, especially during evenings and weekends. There is no need to call ahead for taxis in downtown East Lansing, as an available taxi can always be found on Albert Street behind downtown East Lansing. In downtown Lansing, taxi service is not as frequent. Taxi service usually arrives in under 30 minutes. Visitors should expect longer delays on the weekends and during Michigan State University football games.</p>

<p>The City of Lansing provides an extensive river walk trail along the Red Cedar River and Grand River. Visitors will enjoy strolling along the Red Cedar as it meanders through the beautiful Michigan State University campus, through dense forest, past the City of Lansing's Potter Park Zoo, where the Red Cedar joins the Grand River (Michigan's largest river) and continues through downtown Lansing, Cooley Law School Stadium (formerly Oldsmobile Park), home of the Lansing Lugnuts minor league baseball team, the downtown Farmer's Market, and to the River Walk terminus near the historic Old Town on Lansing's north side.</p>

<p>The area offers many bike lanes, especially in East Lansing near the Michigan State University. Whether on foot or by bike, the area offers plenty of sidewalks, bike lanes, and trails to connect pedestrians to all the local attractions.</p>

<p>For visitors arriving or leaving, Lansing is well-connected to the major regional transportation hubs of Chicago and Detroit. The Capital Region International Airport, Amtrak, CATA, Greyhound Bus Lines, Indian Trails, and Michigan Flyer provide transportation services to and from Lansing. Freeways I-96, I-496, I-69, and US-127 provide fast and convenient connections throughout the Lansing area.</p>

<head>See</head>
<p>Lansing is the state capital of Michigan and the regional center of Mid-Michigan. The city's population is under 115,000 and the metropolitan is under 500,000. Do not expect the big city lights and action of a metropolitan of millions. But there are still many great things to do in and around Lansing. Yes, it snows in Michigan. So embrace the beauty of the seasons, and plan your activities accordingly.</p>
</text>
