<text id="autogum_interview_doc111" title="part2_Wikinews interviews specialists on South Korea military parade" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-10-02" dateModified="2015-01-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_specialists_on_South_Korea_military_parade" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">You</hi>: Not direct response. However, this parade has not been done for many years and resumed this year indicating [the] Park government would not tolerate any hostile action by North Korea.</p>
<figure><caption> File photo of interviewee Young-hae Chi. Image: Young-hae Chi.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  South Korea's President, Park Geun-hye, has warned of a "very grave" threat posed by North Korea. Would a military parade like this be more likely to encourage hostile behaviour?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Kelly</hi>: Not really, because NK already engages in so much hostile behavior it is hard to know how much more restraint SK show. My own sense is that SK demonstrates remarkable forbearance in the face of NK threats. If one thinks of how, e.g., the US or <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Israel">Israel</ref> would respond to such threats, SK looks downright gentle. So SK needs to signal both that it does not seek escalation, but also that it cannot be bullied. It's a tough balancing act, and this parade is to send that second message.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Kosal</hi>: Not necessarily. North Korean behavior is difficult to predict with any fidelity. The military parade, while it shows potential capacity, is a fundamentally passive (rather than active or reactive) form of behavior. Reinforces a consistent posture by the South Koreans and the US.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ledyard</hi>: There is a sixty-year history of such back-and-forth with an impressive absence of active military conflict. It's tit for tat, and both sides either maintain the balance or one or the other loses face. It would take much more than a parade for actual conflict to erupt.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Terry</hi>: No, not in the long run although this kind of a military parade might provoke temporary, short-term hostile behavior by the North.  The North has never been ideological or suicidal.  Its chief goal always has been regime survival.  It knows if a war were to break out, it will definitively lose to South Korea.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chi</hi>: The South Korean government has been implementing military parades since 1956, and as such it is unlikely to encourage or discourage hostile behaviour.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">You</hi>: Could be. North Korea already criticized [the] Park government about the recent parade and very bold move by the Park Government in negotiating family reunion and resuming of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mount%20Kumgang">Diamond Mountains</ref>. However, I do not believe that North Korea will take any hostile action since the US Secretary of State, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Kerry">Kerry</ref>, is proposing North Korea a peaceful dialogue.</p>
<figure><caption> File photo of interviewee Margaret Kosal. Image: Margaret Kosal.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Does the presence of US Defence Secretary <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Chuck_Hagel">Chuck Hagel</ref> to this military parade show a further strengthening in the US–South Korea alliance?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Kelly</hi>: It does, but the Secretary's presence is more for the optics than substance. The US–Korean alliance was substantially strengthened about 4 years ago by the previous SK president. This is just a refresher that looks good on TV.</p>
</text>
