<text id="autogum_interview_doc289" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Frank McEnulty, independent candidate for US President" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-15" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Frank_McEnulty%2C_independent_candidate_for_US_President" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Frank McEnulty, independent candidate for US President</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, February 16, 2008</hi></p>
<p>While nearly all cover of the 2008 Presidential election has focused on the Democratic and Republican candidates, there are small political parties offering candidates, and those who choose to run without a party behind them, independents.</p>
<p>Wikinews is interviewing some of these citizens who are looking to become the 43rd person elected to serve their nation from 1600 Pennsylvania Avenue NW.</p>
<p>First off is Long Beach, California's <hi rend="bold">Frank McEnulty</hi> (b. 1956), a married father of two with an MBA (Venture Management) and BS (Accounting/Finance).</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why do you want to be President?</hi></p>
<p>My name is Frank McEnulty and I am running as an independent candidate for President of the United States in 2008.  Crazy right?  Well maybe, but I am just way too fed up with how the two major parties are running (or should I say ruining) politics in this country and I feel the need to try and do something about it.</p>
<p>I've noticed over the past several years that most of the political ads are pushing a party, rather than ideas or an individual.  "Vote for me, I'm a Republican" or "Vote for me, I'm a Democrat" is all one seems to hear any more.  What do these people stand for?  Nothing until the party tells them to or else they get cut off from the fountain of money.</p>
<p>Do these candidates have independent thoughts?  Maybe, but they never voice them in public because it might not be in line with party doctrine.</p>
<p>Do they ever vote for a bill, law or policy because it is the right thing to do for the country?  Only if the party tells them it is okay to do so.</p>
<p>Usually, if a Republican introduces a piece of legislation it must be wrong per the Democrats because the Democrats didn’t come up with it.</p>
<p>Usually, if a Democrat introduces a piece of legislation it must be wrong per the Republicans because the Republicans didn’t come up with it.</p>
<p>What’s wrong with just working together to do what is right for the country regardless of what party you are affiliated with?</p>
<p>If you’re as disillusioned with how the political process seems to be working as I am let’s get together and make them see how upset we are.  None of us can do it by ourselves, but if enough of us band together we can and will make them sit up and take notice.</p>
<p>Please visit my website at www.frankforpresident.org  to see where I stand on a lot of today’s important issues and pass this email along to all your family members and friends, co-workers and everyone else you know.</p>
</text>
