<text id="autogum_interview_doc834" title="part4_ACLU President Strossen on religion, drugs, guns and impeaching George Bush" shortTile="partaclu-president" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-30" dateModified="2019-02-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/ACLU_President_Strossen_on_religion%2C_drugs%2C_guns_and_impeaching_George_Bush" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Can you give an example of a religious symbology case where the ACLU supported religious freedom?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  We’ve had a number of cases around the country where city governments had government-run cemeteries.  They would not allow families to put their religious symbols on top of their graves, and the ACLU has consistently come to the support of the religious freedom right to do that.  In fact, one of my favorite cases in this general vein is just because of what the lady calls herself.  In Virginia we have a client who calls herself “The Lone Ranger of the Manger”.  She goes around at Christmastime to every park where people are allowed to put up whatever symbols they want, and she wants to have her own nativity scene to put up.  A number of city governments have told her she can’t do that because they say it violates the separation of church and state; they misunderstand.</p>
<head id="How_the_ACLU_is_misrepresented_by_politicians_and_televangelists">How the ACLU is misrepresented by politicians and televangelists</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do people misconstrue or misunderstand your work and what you have argued for or against?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  Not only our work, but they misconstrue what the Supreme Court has said.  It’s hard for people to tell, because those who <hi rend="italic">want</hi> to say the ACLU is hostile to religion distort what we have done, distort what the Supreme Court has done, and then they are surprised that government officials believe them and say, “Oh no, no religious display is allowed at all, or no student is allowed to make a religious statement,” which is <hi rend="italic">not</hi> the case.  It’s <hi rend="italic">so</hi> ironic.  I’ve debated <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pat%20Robertson">Pat Robertson</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jerry%20Falwell">Jerry Falwell</ref> before he died, and they would constantly say, “Little children are not allowed to pray in school; you’re not allowed to talk about religious subjects in school.”  Teachers are listening to them, and so somebody says, “I want to have a student prayer group” and teachers say, “Oh no, you can’t, the Supreme Court has said you can’t—“</p>
<figure></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  —and the ACLU said—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  That’s right!  Right!  But it’s <hi rend="italic">actually</hi> Jerry Falwell who told them that the ACLU is doing that, and it couldn’t be <hi rend="italic">further</hi> from the truth!  In fairness, I have to say, if what you are talking about is a <hi rend="italic">government</hi>-sponsored or promoted display, those were the cases where we <hi rend="italic">do</hi> oppose it and with the support of the Supreme Court.  To take a well-known recent example, the state judiciary building of Alabama, and the Chief Justice brings in this ten ton <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/10%20Commandments">10 Commandments</ref>—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  —<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roy%20Moore">Roy Moore</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  —Yes, Roy Moore, and says that it’s because <hi rend="italic">God</hi> is the ultimate law-giver.  He’s not saying it’s because this is the foundation of American law. He’s <hi rend="italic">endorsing</hi> a religious message, and that’s a different thing.  In his own chambers, we would <hi rend="italic">totally</hi> defend his right to do it.  If there’s a public park where people are allowed to put their own displays, we would totally defend his right to do it.   I don’t think it’s that complicated, you just have to look at the context:  who, where, why, what message are they promoting?  It really comes down to crystallizing the whole topic into a key question that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sandra%20Day%20O’Connor">Sandra Day O’Connor</ref>—hardly a flaming radical—formulated that has been adopted by the majority to ask whether the government is honoring its obligation to be neutral toward religion neither favoring nor disfavoring.  You look at the contested action and you ask, “Would a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reasonable%20person">reasonable observer</ref> see this as government support for religion?”</p>
</text>
