<text id="autogum_voyage_doc387" title="Erlangen" shortTile="erlangen" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=11066" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Erlangen</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.erlangen-marketing.com/">Erlangen</ref> </hi> is a city in <ref target="Franconia">Franconia</ref>, <ref target="Germany">Germany</ref>. It is home to most of the Friedrich-Alexander University (two faculties are in Nuremberg) and the Siemens company.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>One third of the roughly 100 000 residents are involved with the university (students, researchers, etc.), and another third work for Siemens.</p>

<p>Medicine is one of the specialties of the university, so you are in luck if you fall ill with more than six clinics in the city.</p>

<head>Tourist information</head>
<p>The <hi rend="bold">Erlangen tourist info</hi>, Goethestraße 21a (in the center of the city; coming out of the central station turn left at the end of the square into Goethestraße, the office is in the second building to the right), ☏ +49 9131 8951-0 , ✉ tourist@etm-er.de . M-Th 09:00-17:00, F 09:00-15:00, Sa 10:00-13:00. You can also get VGN tickets and advice on local public transit in the same office. </p>

<head>Early history, the Margraves and the Huguenots</head>

<p>While Erlangen can trace its history back to a first mention (as "Villa Erlangon") over a thousand years ago, it was soon overshadowed by its neighbor, Nuremberg, which is 50-odd years younger. The biggest lasting influence upon Erlangen was its former rulers, the Margraves from the Ansbach-Bayreuth branch line of the Hohenzollern (the leaders of Prussia and later all of Germany) dynasty. They ruled the city for most of the early modern period, but preferred to reside in <ref target="Bayreuth">Bayreuth</ref> and <ref target="Ansbach">Ansbach</ref> respectively most of the time. When the French Protestants were expelled by Louis XIV, the Margrave, much like his distant relatives in <ref target="Brandenburg">Brandenburg</ref>, decided to invite them to come to Erlangen. The old houses, the one-way streets of the "Huguenot-town" (which are almost unnavigable unless you ride a bike like most locals do), and a centrally located rather impressive reformed church (right next to <hi rend="italic">Hugenottenplatz</hi>) still bear witness to this era. With the Huguenots a certain wealth entered town and Erlangen has been a center for various industries, trades and research ever since. This was aided when the Margraves decided to open a new university in Erlangen, which later got two faculties in Nuremberg. A common joke (probably made up by a student of theology from Erlangen) claims that Erlangen is the only German place mentioned in the Bible with the (real sounding but fake) quote "Suchet das Himmelreich zu erlangen". This can be translated either as "seek to reach heaven" or "Search for heaven in Erlangen". However, no such quote is to be found in any common German version of the Bible.</p>

<head>Industrialization and World War II</head>
<p>When Erlangen became part of Bavaria in the first years of the 19th century, all universities in Franconia were to be shut down in favor of the universities of "Old-Bavaria". But someone pointed out that Erlangen had a unique selling point no other university in the new kingdom had: an evangelical theological faculty. As the new king wanted protestant ministers to be educated somewhere, he decided to shut down the university in Altdorf (near Nuremberg), and retain the university of Erlangen. This proved a good decision for the city and with the industrialization, Erlangen became an important center of cotton processing plants. ErBa (Erlangen-Bamberg) and Baumwollspinnerei (Cotton factory) are names from this period and still found in some place names in Erlangen. While Erlangen was not unaffected by the Nazis and the <ref target="World%20War%20II%20in%20Europe">Second World War</ref>, it was much less bombed than Nuremberg or Munich and in the waning days of the war. The mayor (who had been member of the Nazi party since 1933) and a high ranking general called Walter Lorleberg somehow managed to surrender the town to the American army despite orders to the contrary. While the details are not known, Lorleberg died in the waning hours of the war, presumably killed by fanatic Nazis or through suicide. A square in Erlangen is still named after him, which is controversial because he was a high ranking Nazi general.</p>

<head>Post war</head>

<p>After the war Siemens decided to move out of Berlin, which had been almost entirely destroyed. To avoid the Soviets, they decided to build two headquarters in the American Zone, one of which would become Erlangen (the other is in Munich). This decision continues to benefit the city. Siemens' policies and decisions are followed almost as intensely as mayoral politics in Erlangen. Erlangen grew rapidly from just under 30,000 inhabitants in 1925. Between people moving in and the incorporation of suburbs such as Dechsendorf, by 1975 the city had reached 100,000 people. Thus attaining "Großstadt" status, which it still holds at population figures below 110 000 but above 100 000. Erlangen had been the site of a garrison of the Bavarian Army since the mid 19th century and became a garrison of the German Army after <ref target="World%20War%20I">World War I</ref>. After the defeat of the Nazis in 1945, the garrison was taken over by the US Army and expanded. However, in the course of post-cold war downsizing of the troop presence, the garrison was closed in the early 1990s and has been turned into direly needed housing as well as nature reserve. It is sometimes cited as an example of the "peace dividend" that many hoped would result after the cold war as military installations were turned over to civilian uses. Erlangen's mayor from 1972-1996, Dietmar Hahlweg, decided against building more and bigger streets or relying solely on public transport. Instead he encouraged cycling as a means of getting around investing in infrastructure and riding a bike to work himself to set an example. Today many residents (even those working for Siemens and the mayor) get to work on their bikes every day, and the cars clogging the streets often have number-plates of the surrounding villages and suburbs. Erlangen thrives economically today, but is still dependent upon its university and Siemens. If either coughs, the city gets pneumonia.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>The next airport is in <ref target="Nuremberg%23By%20plane">Nuremberg</ref> ( NUE ) with domestic and limited international connections. The U-Bahn (subway) takes you to the Nuremberg main station in roughly 12 minutes, from where you can take a wide variety of inter-city (ICE and IC), regional (RE and RB) and commuter-trains (the S-Bahn) to Erlangen. The subway and regional trains are fully integrated within the VGN tariff union. There is also a direct bus (line 30) from the airport to downtown Erlangen every 20 minutes on weekdays (40 minutes on weekends). This option takes a bit under half an hour.</p>

<p>If you are flying in from <ref target="Frankfurt%20airport">Frankfurt airport</ref> ( FRA ), there are connections with one change (in Nuremberg) from the train station integrated into the airport. Erlangen can be reached somewhat more quickly from <ref target="Munich%20Airport">Munich Airport</ref> ( MUC ), although it is one more stop away on the train. For more on combined train and flight tickets see <ref target="air%20rail%20alliances">this article</ref>.</p>
</text>
