<text id="autogum_whow_doc505" title="Stay Organized in College" shortTile="stay-organized-college" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-06-12" dateModified="2018-10-05" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Stay-Organized-in-College" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Stay Organized in College</head><p>Organization is not only keeping your notes in order, it is much more than that. Follow these steps to help you stay organized in college.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Get yourself a planner. Managing your time in college is the most important thing you can do. Buy yourself a daily, weekly, or even monthly planner. This small investment will move mountains as you progress towards a successful college career.</item>
<item>Track down exam dates. Working backward is the best way to go about planning your next semester. Sit down with all your class syllabuses and highlight all final and midterm exam dates. These will be the first thing you will want to write down in your newly purchased planner.·      Doing this you will see potential hazards with overlapping exams and assignments</item>
<item>Find quizzes and assignments. Collecting quizzes and assignments dates must follow finding exam dates. These lower percentage assignments may seem unimportant but they add up. Finding these dates may require more work than simply looking at the syllabus. You may have to talk to your professor or teaching assistant to find out when homework, projects and quizzes are.</item>
<item>Never forget important information. On the cover of your planner write down all your professors and teaching assistants office hours as well as grade breakdowns for each class. There is nothing worse than finding out that the assignment you ignored was worth more than you expected. This information will allow you to stay aligned in each class and force yourself to participate more therefore keeping up with each class.</item>
<item>One notebook for each class. Purchasing a notebook for each class may seem like a waste of money and weight to slug around but it has been proven to boost grades therefore organization. Only write down notes in the proper notebook and you will never be sent hunting for something again. All loose sleeve papers and handouts go inside as well. On the cover write down exam dates, due dates, office hours and grade break downs for that specific class.</item>
<item>Befriend your professors and teaching assistants. Communication is key. Speaking to your professor one on one is crucial. It is impossible to be organized in a class that you are unaware what is going on. Your professor and teaching assistant are getting paid to serve you as a student. Set up a meeting with both outside of class where you can explain your strengths and weaknesses to them and ask how you think the best way to be successful is. Ask them anything that comes to mind. After this meeting write all of it down and review it. Depict what they said and run with it. Their little tricks and tells will dramatically help you in their class and being a student in general.</item>
<item>Do not work around work. Speaking to your manager is something that should be done at the beginning of every semester. Grab your planner and walk through your manager what you are about to go through for school. Tell them your important dates that you will need time off before to properly prepare. Not all jobs are east going so this is your best bet on balancing school and work. At the end of explaining your next couple months to your manager ask them if it is possible to get your schedule as early as possible. Having a set schedule will allow you to look ahead and know what you will have to do to keep your busy schedule alive.</item>
<item>Set time to breath. Breathing easy may just keep you alive in college.  Becoming overwhelmed is a very common thing to happen during sometime during your hectic semester. Setting time aside for yourself will give you the chance to not worry about school, work, social etc. and just focus on you for a change. Allowing yourself to catch up to your normal will avoid being overwhelmed and keeping you on schedule. This will keep you organized. This will keep you going. ·      Time to yourself could include: Working out, yoga, reading, etc.</item>
<item>Calendars. Looking ahead is one of the main things to stay organization in college. Aside from the planner which will be used on the go and at school. Setting up calendars at your home study area can play a major role in organization. Buy or print off 4-5 months ahead. Write down exam dates, project dates and your work schedule. Then post these pieces in front of where you study at home. The constant reminder as you sit and do your work every night will help remind you of what is coming ahead. This will force yourself to get a jump on assignments and projects.</item>
<item>Review planner daily. Reviewing your planner will keep yourself in your own loop. Your planner is your life line. It has all your information for a successful semester. Setting aside 5-10 minutes a day to review your own planner will remind you of dates and push yourself to tackle assignments earlier. It will also jolt new things to write down like social activities that will alter your regular schedule.</item>
<item>Color coordinate everything. Studying your notes is boring enough, so spice it up a bit and make it more appealing. Add in some color. Underline your titles and highlight key words. This is a proven useful tactic to stay organize. The science behind it is when you come back to your notes you can identify the information on the paper more easily. Seeing an arrange of colors will spark a memory quicker than reading the first paragraph. Looking for key words that are highlighted will also save time and give you a better jump on the new material.</item>
<item>Make a to-do list.  Creating a to-do list will break down your larger goals into much smaller, more accomplishable goals. These lists can be on your phone, laptop or even old fashion and pen and paper. On this list, you want to write down things to do in the next week. Start by writing down larger goals and then break it down into smaller maybe even hourly goals. Having a to-do list will keep you on track to complete all things expected. Try and complete each task rather move them around as they will bunch up quickly and some will eventually be passed on.</item></list>
</text>
