<text id="autogum_interview_doc388" title="part1_The Raveonettes on love, death, desire and war" shortTile="partthe-raveonettes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-16" dateModified="2010-12-23" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Raveonettes_on_love%2C_death%2C_desire_and_war" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  And that's where we fit in, now!  Freaks!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sharin%20Foo">Sharin Foo</ref>:</hi>  Sounds like an interesting job.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  A lot of the questions might be a little different than what you are typically used to; maybe that will make it more interesting for you, or less pleasant.  One of the first questions I like to ask musicians is about the challenge to be innovative when so much has already been done.  How do you not let that affect your output?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  Well, I don't think we really think about it in those terms.  When we started out we had certain guidelines for the music that would ensure that it would sound like no one else, and those were pretty easy to make.  Things like don't use a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/high%20hat">high hat</ref>, don't use cymbals, don't use certain things, play all the songs in the same key, do this and this, and that was really...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Was that your <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dogme95">Dogme</ref> influence?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  Yeah.  I don't know what it was, I guess it was a really silly thing, but it worked and it was very inspiring and creative to work within those constraints, I guess.  But they weren't really constrains for us, it was actually really easy and simple, but I think it has a sound that I have never heard before.  But like I said, I don't really thin that we think...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  I think it's more that we are not scared of being blunt about what the references are in our music. For instance, if you look at our name, The Raveonettes, it's a complete direct reference to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Ronettes">The Ronettes</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buddy%20Holly">Buddy Holly</ref> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rave%20On">Rave On</ref></hi>.  So, in that sense, we're pretty clear about it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You embrace it.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  Yeah, we like it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  Yeah, where the inspiration has come from. So it's not like we have that fear of repetition.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  I think a lot of bands put a lot of emphasis on <hi rend="italic">trying</hi> to be different, and then they make music that is soulless; it doesn't get me anywhere.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It's too self-aware?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  Yeah, what's wrong with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Three-chord%20song">three chords</ref>?  That's what music was founded upon, that's what everyone from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hank%20Williams">Hank Williams</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Ramones">The Ramones</ref> used those three chords.  What's wrong with them all of a sudden?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  Yes.  I think that what it comes down to is whether it strikes a chord in you and hits your gut, some kind of emotion in you, that's really what we care about when we make music.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Since you are so upfront about your influences, you do still have  unique sound.  Do the constant comparison in the music media grow tiresome?</hi></p>
</text>
