<text id="autogum_whow_doc551" title="Practice Being a Vet at a Young Age" shortTile="practice-being-vet" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-10-25" dateModified="2017-07-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Practice-Being-a-Vet-at-a-Young-Age" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Practice Being a Vet at a Young Age</head><p>Do you want to be a vet some day? If you're still a child but you have ambitions to become a vet, you can prepare yourself from a young age for tending to animals by doing basic animal care at home.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Practicing on your pet</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Practice on your pet. Observe your pet daily, and keep an eye out for any signs of bad health or deterioration in well-being. For example, if you have a dog and it's eating grass, it may be sick. On the other hand, this could be a sign of something a healthy dog does, so always do your research in reliable books about animal care. <figure rend="Practice Being a Vet at a Young Age Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Give your pet a weekly checkup. Check its ears, heartbeat, eyes, etc. Talk to your pet's real vet about the things to look for, and let your vet know about your ambitions and how you're trying to get ready for this role later in life.</item>
<item>Be responsible. Feed your pet, give it water, and know what amounts of food are good for it. Learn about the nutritional balance that is good for your pet and check that it is getting this in the foods you feed to it.</item>
<item>Love your pet. Spend time with your pet, talking to it, grooming it and playing with it. Knowing all that you can about animals will set you in good stead if you decide to one day go to college to become a veterinarian.</item></list>
<head>Practicing on your stuffed animals</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Practice on stuffed animals. Imagine a stuffed animal is a real one and there is something wrong with it.</item>
<item>Make up a vet surgery for it and bring the stuffed animal along for a checkup and diagnosis. <figure rend="Practice Being a Vet at a Young Age Step 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>General learning about animals</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Look at vet websites. There are thousands of vet websites with information on health for all animals. <figure rend="Practice Being a Vet at a Young Age Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Volunteer at an animal shelter. When you are old enough to do this, it is a great way to learn all that you can about caring for animals. <figure rend="Practice Being a Vet at a Young Age Step 4.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Becoming a vet, vet nurse or other animal related carer</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Do well in school. In order to be a vet or a vet's assistant, get straight A's, so that you can get into the course of your choice. be sure to choose the right subjects too––ask your teacher for help in finding out which subjects are best to focus on. <figure rend="Practice Being a Vet at a Young Age Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Other ways to help animals is to become a zookeeper, a shelter carer, an animal rescuer, a fundraiser for endangered species, a worker with an NGO for animals, a wildlife photographer, a nature journalist, and so forth. Think of all the possible ways you can work with animals and choose the career that seems best suited to you.</item></list></item>
<item>Keep working towards your goal. Animals are plentiful around the world and need caring people like you to ensure their health and well-being is properly taken care of. <figure rend="Practice Being a Vet at a Young Age Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not give your pet medicine unless told to.</item></list>
</text>
