<text id="autogum_interview_doc486" title="part2_ACLU, EFF challenging US &amp;apos;secret&amp;apos; court orders seeking Twitter data" shortTile="partaclu-eff-challenging" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-04-06" dateModified="2019-09-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/ACLU%2C_EFF_challenging_US_%27secret%27_court_orders_seeking_Twitter_data" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Assange continues, to this day, to argue that his extradition to Sweden for questioning on alleged sexual offences is being orchestrated by the U.S. in an effort to discredit him, and thus WikiLeaks.</p>
<head id="State-of-the-(Black)-Art,_or_CyberWarfare">State-of-the-(Black)-Art, or CyberWarfare</head>
<figure><caption>Logo of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Twitter">Twitter</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> consulted an IT and cryptography expert from the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Belgium">Belgian</ref> university which developed the current <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Advanced%20Encryption%20Standard">Advanced Encryption Standard</ref>; explaining modern communications, he stated: "Cryptography has developed to such a level that intercepting communications is no longer cost effective. That is, if any user uses the correct default settings, and makes sure that he/she is really connecting to Twitter it is highly unlikely that even the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/National_Security_Agency">NSA</ref> can break the cryptography for a protocol such as SSL/TLS (used for https)."</p>
<p>Qualifying this, he commented that "the vulnerable parts of the communication are the end points." To make his point, he cited the following quote from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gene%20Spafford">Gene Spafford</ref>: "<hi rend="italic">Using encryption on the Internet is the equivalent of arranging an armored car to deliver credit card information from someone living in a cardboard box to someone living on a park bench.</hi>"</p>
<p>Continuing, the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Katholieke_Universiteit_Leuven">Katholieke Universiteit Leuven</ref> (KUL) expert explained:</p>
<p>"<hi rend="italic">In the first place, the weak point is Twitter itself; the US government can go and ask for the data; companies such as Twitter and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Google">Google</ref> will typically store quite some information on their users, including IP addresses (it is known that Google deletes the last byte of the IP address after a few weeks, but it is not too hard for a motivated opponent to find out what this byte was).</hi>"</p>
<p>"<hi rend="italic">In the second place, this is the computer of the user: by exploiting system weaknesses (with viruses, Trojan horses or backdoors in the operating system) a highly motivated opponent can enter your machine and record your keystrokes plus everything that is happening (e.g. the FBI is known to do this with the so-called <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magic%20Lantern%20(software)">Magic Lantern software</ref>). Such software is also commercially available, e.g. for a company to monitor its employees.</hi>"</p>
<figure><caption>Seal of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Katholieke_Universiteit_Leuven">Catholic University of Leuven</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>"<hi rend="italic">It would also be possible for a higly motivated opponent to play "man-in-the-middle"; that means that instead of having a secure connection to Twitter.com, you have a secure connection to the attacker's server, who impersonates Twitter's and then relays your information to Twitter. This requires tricks such as spoofing DNS (this is getting harder with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DNSsec">DNSsec</ref>), or misleading the user (e.g. the user clicks on a link and connects to tw!tter.com or Twitter.c0m, which look very similar in a URL window as Twitter.com). It is clear that the US government is capable of using these kind of tricks; e.g., a company has been linked to the US government that was recognized as legitimate signer in the major browsers, so it would not be too large for them to sign a legitimate certificate for such a spoofing webserver; this means that the probability that a user would detect a problem would be very low.</hi>"</p>
</text>
