<text id="autogum_academic_doc667" title="Greater Circulating Copper Concentrations and Copper/Zinc Ratios are Associated with Lower Psychological Distress, But Not Cognitive Performance, in a Sample of Australian Older Adults" shortTile="greater-circulating" author="Michelle Mravunac, Ewa  A. Szymlek-Gay, Robin M. Daly, Blaine R. Roberts, Melissa Formica, Jenny Gianoudis, Stella L. O’Connell, Caryl A. Nowson, Barbara R. Cardoso" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6643/11/10/2503/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Ageing is a naturally occurring physiological process which is characterized by both physical and cognitive decline. Changes are seen in brain neurochemistry as well as in neuroanatomical structures, which negatively affect synaptic plasticity and contribute to atrophy. Ageing is also associated with increased vulnerability of the neurons to oxidative stress, emphasizing the potential importance of changes in the concentration of neurotrophic factors such as a decrease in the concentrations of brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF), which supports the growth and maintenance of neurons. Decreased concentrations of such neurotrophic factors render brain cells more prone to damage caused by inflammatory processes and oxidative stress, which are key events in age-associated cognitive decline and neurodegenerative disease pathogenesis experienced by many older adults. In fact, it is estimated that dementia, a far-end result of cognitive decline, affects approximately 50 million people worldwide. This number is expected to increase to 75 million by 2030 and 132 million by 2050, posing a considerable burden on the health care system. Dementia is intrinsically linked with depression, as both are characterized by neuroinflammation and oxidative stress. Depression is a complex disease involving a chronic low-grade inflammatory response, activation of cell-mediated immunity, and progressive neuropathology, which can lead to neurodegeneration and later on contribute toward the development of dementia. Besides being one of many risk factors for dementia, depression is estimated to be the leading cause of disability by 2030. </p>

<p>Metal ions such as copper and zinc play an essential role in brain function and neuronal homeostasis, and long-term imbalance of these metals has been linked to neurodegeneration and neurological disorder. It is thought that this may be due to the provocation of an unchecked immune response within the brain via the increased production of reactive oxygen species, which can lead to brain damage via the upregulation of inflammatory mediators. Copper is an essential transition metal that acts as a catalyst for several biological processes such as the synthesis of neurotransmitters. However, disturbance of its transport, causing accumulation in the blood and depletion in the brain, has been linked with neurodegenerative diseases such as Alzheimer’s, the most common form of dementia. Copper works synergistically with zinc in several metalloenzymes, such as the antioxidant enzyme superoxide dismutase. Zinc is an essential component of numerous biochemical and molecular processes related to cell survival and, unlike copper, has very low toxicity in humans. However, research suggests that zinc deficiency may increase the risk of dementia, and thus supplementation with zinc may improve cognition and regulation of emotional behavior (such as anger and depression) in cognitively intact individuals. </p>

<p>Zinc and copper are also likely to have a synergistic role in Alzheimer’s disease, with copper promoting oxidative stress and displacing zinc from body tissues. Therefore, not only is the individual nutritional status of copper and zinc of concern, but the balance between these two metals appears to be important. Indeed, studies suggest that calculating the copper to zinc ratio (Cu/Zn ratio) provides valuable information in regard to oxidative stress and inflammatory responses. Ageing is associated with decreased zinc status and hence increased Cu/Zn ratio, which is also observed in individuals with dementia. Therefore, this study aimed to investigate the relationship between plasma copper and serum zinc concentrations, as well as the Cu/Zn ratio, neurotrophic factors, cognitive function, and psychological distress in a sample of Australian community-dwelling older adults. </p>
</text>
