<text id="autogum_voyage_doc309" title="Goslar" shortTile="goslar" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=13058" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Goslar</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.goslar.de/english.html">Goslar</ref></hi> is a medieval town in <ref target="Lower%20Saxony">Lower Saxony</ref> and serves as a regional hub to the wider <ref target="Harz">Harz area</ref>. It lies at the foot of the Harz Mountains (highest elevation 3,744 feet). Goslar is situated some 150 Miles West of <ref target="Berlin">Berlin</ref>. The nearest cities are <ref target="Brunswick%20%28Germany%29">Brunswick</ref>, <ref target="Hanover">Hanover</ref>, and <ref target="Magdeburg">Magdeburg</ref>. Goslar is much older than Berlin and worth a visit. If you are interested in history, outdoor pursuits (especially hiking), tranquility and nature, then Goslar is the right spot for you.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>Goslar was founded in 922 AD, although it is widely assumed that there had been a settlement since pre-Roman times. The town is famed for its magnificent gates and ramparts, the medieval Imperial Palace, Romanesque churches, its half timbered guild houses, the ancient Rammelsberg ore mine... and its witches, the last of which was burned at the stake in 1657 AD. In medieval times the city was a major producer of armouries and coins—the raw ores for their manufacture came from the Rammelsberg mine just outside the city's walls.</p>

<head>History</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">What, Ram + Goat = Goslar?</hi></p>
<p>Not quite...! According to legend, Ramm, a knight to Henry's son Otto the Great, tied his horse to a tree, half way up the Rammelsberg, to continue hunting in the undergrowth. In anticipation of the return of its owner, the horse scraped with its hoof in the ground laying open a ledge of silver so rich that it took over a millennium to mine. Hence the mountain and mine were called the Rammelsberg, after Otto's knight Ramm. As the wife of knight Ramm was called Gosa, they named the town Goslar in her honor.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Emperors, Dukes, and Townsfolk</hi></p>
<p>Essentially Goslar was a Free Imperial City, which was under direct control of the Emperor and there were no regional feudal overlords, who were in charge of the city until the end of the Thirty's Year War. Thus the citizens were largely left to their own devices, since the emperors had mostly better things to do than to sit in their Imperial Palace at Goslar. There were several other imperial palaces throughout the Holy Roman Empire, where the emperors held court. The only problem for the city's craftsmen was that their Free Imperial City ended right behind the city's walls. Unfortunately for them, the mine they depended upon, for the delivery of the ores, was immediately outside these very city walls. So they had to lease the rights to the mine from even such regional feudal overlords, the Dukes of Brunswick, who would have fancied it, if the city was theirs. This inevitably let to regular skirmishes between the Dukes and their men on the one side, and the burghers on the other side, which were not resolved until the end of the Thirty's Year War in 1642 AD with the Goslar Accord.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Goethe's Goslar Gothic Ghosts</hi>. With the onset of the Reformation in 1517 AD Goslar has escaped the interest of the emperor, and its riches declined so that Goethe, Germany's national polymath, writes in 1777 during his visit to Goslar: "Imperial City, which rots 'inside' and 'with' its privileges!"</p>

<head>UNESCO World Heritage Status</head>
<p>This might be a reason why the Rammelsberg Mine and Town have been so uniquely preserved that they hold <ref target="UNESCO%20World%20Heritage%20List">UNESCO World Heritage Status</ref>.</p>

<p>Goslar is the Harz region's festival town, culminating in the annual award of the <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.kaiserring.net">"Imperial Ring"</ref></hi>.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>If you own a plane, a helicopter or even a flying saucer then you might wish to land at the club airport <ref target="http://www.mfc-salzgitter.de">Salzgitter-Drütte</ref> in the immediate vicinity (24 miles) of Goslar or the Brunswick-Wolfsburg Airport. Maybe try the disused military airfield at Goslar itself, but don't get yourselves into troubles over this.</p>

<p>However, as a lesser mortal you need to take a plane into either</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Hanover International Airport ( HAJ ) <ref target="http://www.hannover-airport.de/index.php%3Fid%3D4%26amp%3BL%3D1"></ref> (65 miles)</item>
<item> Leipzig/Halle Airport ( LEJ ) <ref target="http://www.leipzig-halle-airport.de/en/index.html"></ref> (103 miles)</item>
</list>

<p>and make your way to Goslar by car or by train. Both airports are connected to the S-Bahn network of their respective cities from where you can take a train to Goslar.</p>
<p>A further option is flying into <ref target="Frankfurt%20Airport">Frankfurt Airport</ref> ( FRA ) and taking the train from there</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>Goslar can best be accessed by regional trains from <ref target="Hanover">Hanover</ref> or <ref target="Brunswick%20%28Germany%29">Brunswick</ref>. In Hanover and <ref target="G%C3%B6ttingen">Göttingen</ref> there is access to Germany's ICE (Inter City Express) network. Getting to other cities might require changes along the way, often in Hildesheim, Salzgitter or Kreiensen.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>From <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Paris">Paris</ref>/<ref target="London">London</ref>/<ref target="Brussels">Brussels</ref>/<ref target="Cologne">Cologne</ref></hi> take the Autobahn <hi rend="bold">A44</hi>/E331 to <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Kassel">Kassel</ref></hi> and take the <hi rend="bold">A7</hi>/E45 in the direction <hi rend="bold">Hamburg</hi> at the <hi rend="bold">Kassel</hi> intersection. For further directions see below.</p>

<p>From <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Madrid">Madrid</ref>/<ref target="Rome">Rome</ref>/<ref target="Vienna">Vienna</ref>/<ref target="Zurich">Zurich</ref>/<ref target="Munich">Munich</ref>/<ref target="Frankfurt">Frankfurt</ref></hi> take the <hi rend="bold">A7</hi>/E45 and leave it at either the intersection Seesen. Take the Bundesstraße <hi rend="bold">B248</hi> and then the Bundesstraße <hi rend="bold">B82</hi> to <hi rend="bold">Goslar</hi>. If you wish to take the route via the Harz mountains, exit the <hi rend="bold">A7</hi>/E45 at <hi rend="bold">Northeim</hi> and take the Bundesstraße <hi rend="bold">B241</hi> via <hi rend="bold">Osterode</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Clausthal-Zellerfeld</hi> to <hi rend="bold">Goslar</hi>.</p>

<p>Coming from <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Moscow">Moscow</ref>/<ref target="Warsaw">Warsaw</ref>/<ref target="Prague">Prague</ref>/<ref target="Berlin">Berlin</ref></hi>, take the <hi rend="bold">A2</hi>/E39 to the intersection <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Brunswick%20%28Germany%29">Braunschweig</ref></hi> and head via the A395 in the direction of <hi rend="bold">Bad Harzburg</hi>. At <hi rend="bold">Vienenburg</hi> you leave the <hi rend="bold">A395</hi> and take the Bundesstraße <hi rend="bold">B241</hi> to <hi rend="bold">Goslar</hi>.</p>

<p>Arriving from <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Amsterdam">Amsterdam</ref>/<ref target="D%C3%BCsseldorf">Düsseldorf</ref>/<ref target="Ruhr">Ruhr</ref></hi> Basin take the <hi rend="bold">A2</hi>/E39 to <ref target="Hanover">Hannover</ref> and at the Intersection Hannover leave the <hi rend="bold">A2</hi>/E39 and take the <hi rend="bold">A7</hi>/E45. For further directions, see below.</p>

<p>Coming from <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Copenhagen">Copenhagen</ref>/<ref target="Stockholm">Stockholm</ref>/<ref target="Oslo">Oslo</ref>/<ref target="Hamburg">Hamburg</ref>/<ref target="Bremen">Bremen</ref>/<ref target="Hanover">Hanover</ref></hi> you take the <hi rend="bold">A7</hi>/E45 in the direction <hi rend="bold">Frankfurt</hi>. You exit the autobahn at Derneburg-Salzgitter (63) and take the Bundesstraße <hi rend="bold">B6</hi> (mostly two-lane) to <hi rend="bold">Goslar</hi> or you exit at Rhüden (66) and take the Bundesstraße <hi rend="bold">B82</hi> to Goslar.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">N.B.</hi> Goslar is a popular destination for bikers who enjoy riding their bikes through the <ref target="Harz">Harz</ref> mountains.</p>

<head>By bus</head>

<p>Bus services to and from Goslar are relatively frequent and efficient. The regional bus operator <ref target="http://rbb-bus.de/index.php%3Fid%3D61">Brunswick Regional Transport RBB</ref> runs a <ref target="http://www.weser-ems-bus.de/hafas/query.exe/en%3FL%3Drbb%26amp%3B">website</ref> , which assists you with finding the relevant connection. In Goslar, their hub is in front of the central railway station. Here you also find a small travel centre, where staff can provide you with further advise. Essentially, the most frequent routes are between Goslar, Seesen, Harzburg-Spa, Salzgitter and Clausthal-Zellerfeld, with less frequent services to other destinations in the Upper Harz (lines 440, 450, 462, 831, 838, 841, 842, 850, 861, 879). The RegioBus lines are the express ones—the others are slow. The handy thing is that the RBB forms a <ref target="http://www.vrb-online.de/">partnership</ref> with other regional public <ref target="http://www.zgb.de">transport operators</ref>, so that you only have to buy a single transferable ticket. Thus, there is no need to purchase a new one every time you change your train or bus.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.vrb-online.de">Regionalbus Braunschweig GmbH</ref></hi> - Office Goslar, Hildesheimer St. 53. T: +49 5321 34310, F: +49 5321 343160, E: rbb.goslar@rbb-bus.de.</item>
</list>
</text>
