<text id="autogum_academic_doc150" title="An Evaluation Framework for the Planning of Electric Car-Sharing Systems: A Combination Model of AHP-CBA-VD" shortTile="evaluation-framework" author="Yixi Xue, Yi Zhang, Yi Chen" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5627/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 6. Discussion and Conclusions</head><head> 6.1. Discussion</head>
<p>This research takes the specific case of EVCARD in China for study and application; therefore, the evaluation outcomes may provide some useful insights for ECS companies, the government, and other stakeholders in terms of improving the planning of the ECSS and the attractiveness of CS.

<list>
<item>According to the experts’ assessment, the score of each question under VURM was higher than that of the other questions (Table 3). VURM is considered to be the greatest criterion influencing the planning performance of ECSS in China (Table 6). This means that ECS companies must pay more attention in controlling the relocation costs by reducing the relocation distance and relocation staff. Meanwhile, this assessment result shows that the convenience of renting and returning shared vehicles means the most for users and the score for this question was the highest. This demonstrates that the value co-creation between the CS companies and users is essential in the ECSS, in other words, the planning performance improvement of the ECSS must be based on the satisfaction of the consumers’ travel demand.. Operators may have to consider how to increase the convenience through good planning methods such as increasing the reservation time (time between requesting and picking up a vehicle), adequate parking spaces, longer business hours, or the application of intelligent networking technology. The development of CS/ECSS in China greatly relies on government support. It is essential for the government to take appropriate policies to promote the takeoff of CS/ECSS. The results show that policies such as appropriately allocating parking resources to CS/ECSS operators are key for improving the attractiveness of CS/ECSS.</item>
<item>CSS and RI were reported as the second highest factors influencing the planning (Table 6). The importance of CSS on the strategic planning has already been identified in prior studies as described above. For CS companies, station attributes such as the coverage area of each station and the corresponding density and fleet size should be calculated regarding the demand forecast so that use efficiency and construction costs can be balanced. The location of stations is what consumers emphasize, and its choice should consider the built environment.</item>
<item>RI is a negligible but important factor, which is directly related to user satisfaction. How to deal with facility failure and equipment occupancy more effectively and efficiently is what CS operators must focus on. In fact, for CS operators, intelligent and information technology should be integrated to improve the supervision efficiency, and achieve the coordination of vehicles, charging piles, parking spaces, and power grids.</item>
<item>MR was reported as the least important factor (Table 6). This may be due to the operation phase of ECS. After all, most of the ECS companies in China are still in the early stage of development.</item>
<item>According to the evaluation results, the JA district of EVCARD performed better than the CN district (Table 10). The main reasons were the RI and VURM. However, the assessment value of the JD district was lower than the CN district in CSS and MR. The main reason may be due to the geographic location. The JA district is much closer to the urban center, which may cause difficulties in distributing station networks and controlling the relevant costs. In fact, the stations of EVCARD are distributed more in the outskirts of the city rather than in urban centers. How to improve the construction planning of ECSS in urban centers, therefore, should be seriously considered during future development.</item>
</list>
</p>

<head> 6.2. Conclusions</head>
<p>This paper is among the first to evaluate the planning of ECSS from a comprehensive view. In this paper, we contribute to the existing literature by developing a comprehensive evaluation framework consisting of evaluation criteria and an evaluation method. Through a literature review and expert interviews, four major evaluation criteria were determined: construction of stations, routine inspection, vehicle usability and relocation management, and maintenance and replacement of stations. These criteria present a comprehensive consideration of the whole planning process of the ECSS. Then, a combinational decision support tool for evaluating the planning of ECSS is presented in this paper, based on AHP, CBA, and VD. CBA and VD were adopted as a supplement to the AHP method with the aim to increase the accuracy of the evaluation. Based on the CBA method, thirteen sub-factors were introduced to measure the alternatives and some evaluation principles related to the distribution of the station network and station capacity are presented based on the VD method. This evaluation framework is capable of comprehensively evaluating the planning of the ECSS. </p>

<p>The case study of EVCARD contributes to an original analysis of the planning of the most influential ECS business in China. We demonstrate that the planning of EVCARD in different areas has great differences. EVCARD should seek a balanced development between different districts. For EVCARD, the construction planning of the JA district is a key direction for improvement; relocation management and convenience of picking up and returning EVs, however, should be the key improvement direction for the CN district. </p>
</text>
