<text id="autogum_interview_doc806" title="part4_Alex Necochea and Bryn Bennett: the &amp;apos;Guitar Heroes&amp;apos; of Bang Camaro" shortTile="partalex-necochea" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-06" dateModified="2014-03-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Alex_Necochea_and_Bryn_Bennett%3A_the_%27Guitar_Heroes%27_of_Bang_Camaro" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That's important for a lot of people - you see your audience.  You're giving a lot of inspiration to a lot of people.  You don't know who you might be inspiring to pursue music.  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  Oh, kids, don't be like me!  I would definitely go with nature over man made.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What's your favorite curse word?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  Fuck.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What's your favorite euphemism for breasts?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  Big guns.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Have you used that recently?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  Actually, I think I did use that in the last week, and no comment.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I read that you named the band after fast women and fast cars.  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  Who told you that?  No, Bang Camaro were two words out of the English language that were the two sexiest words we could think of.  We put them together and they roll off the tongue.  Bang Camaro.  It says a lot more than it means.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What sort of qualities do you look for in a woman?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  I need a girl who is going to make me laugh.  I need a woman who is smarter than I am.  A woman who will always keep me guessing.  Absolutely.  Calling me out for my own jerky bullshit.  I like a girl who is fiercely independent, knows what she wants, and doesn't need me.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hillary%20Clinton">Hillary Clinton</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barack%20Obama">Barack Obama</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  Oh, man, I'm going to get in a lot of trouble for saying Obama.  I would probably go with Obama.  There's just something in his rhetoric and his oratory that is a lot more inspiring than Hillary.  Hillary, to me, represents not much of a changing of the guard.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What would be the greatest of misfortunes to befall you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Chuckles</hi>]  Oh, if I were to die alone.  No, probably one of my greatest fears is injuring or maiming any of my appendages, to be honest.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you have any special things you do to make sure you don't injure or lose an appendage?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Chuckles</hi>]  I don't keep my hands in my pockets when I am running down stairs.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That's a conscious choice?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  Yes, that's a conscious choice.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What if you are just walking down stairs?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Chuckles</hi>]  You can't realign the stars, man.  Shit will happen, shit will happen.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What possession do you treasure most?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  That's a good question.  Probably my cat.  I love my cat more than anything.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What's your cat's name?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  Sadie.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Like <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sexy%20Sadie">Sexy Sadie</ref></hi>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  Yeah, like Sexy Sadie.  That's exactly what I named her after.  Big John Lennon fan, so I couldn't resist.</p>
</text>
