<text id="autogum_reddit_doc113" title="For an MMO, ESO is extremely solo friendly. Any ideas that can remedy this?" shortTile="mmo-eso-extremely" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-04-30" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8g40yp" speakerList="#Pill_my_funger, #unknown" speakerCount="2">
<head>For an MMO, ESO is extremely solo friendly. Any ideas that can remedy this?</head>
<sp who="#unknown">
<p>I've dabbled in with a few MMOs over the years, and I'm confident eso is the most single player friendly. Things like, World Bosses, were soloable at one point. Hell, some still are. I'd love to see true WBs, like random server/alliance bosses that are timed, and require lots of people (30-50+) and could take up to about 20 ish minutes to kill. Something similar to what GW2 had. Or maybe more zones like Craglorn, that require people to be in your party to complete the quest. Even small area events would be nice. Especially on the alliance zones. They could make it feel more 'war-like.' Example: the covenant are planning an attack on Vulkel Guard. Round up weapons for our soldiers and man our defenses. A come quest that required loads of players to participate. "Craft 10O0 arrows, 200 steel swords, and 300 health potions." Or once it's night time in game, there is a chance a Vampire Lord World Boss may spawn near a city, and we all had to go and kill her. Mechanics could range from, randomly infecting non vampire players, to dropping a cool loot such housing items (vampire skull, blood vials, etc.) crafting items like vampire Ashes, that was required to make a legendary cooking item or potion, or -hear me out- rare armor/weapon/jewelry drops that wasn't necessarily meta, but strong enough to matter. Or any other exclusive shit you can think of. Idk. I know that ZoS are always putting it content, I just wished more if it was group content, that goes beyond harder 4/12 man dungeon and trials. An I won't in this idea?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#Pill_my_funger">
<p>All that stuff seems cool, but two weeks after it goes live it'll be dead in the water and it will only be a pain in the ass to people that have to solo around it. The rewards for doing it won't be awesome enough for the big boys and it will be too difficult for the few casual people that show up. </p>
<p>I like the WB's the way they are. One person is enough for most of them, which is good cause good luck getting anyone to help. Punching something for 20min isn't fun, hell you can't get people to slow down for a 20min dungeon and you want them to stand still for 20min on one mob? </p>
<p>Keep the group content in the 4 12 man areas and out of my overworld. While we're doing the crazy idea thing, I'd like a non-pvp version of Imperial City so I can enjoy it without getting ganked.</p>
</sp>
</text>
