<text id="autogum_bio_doc379" title="Wendel Dietterlin" shortTile="wendel-dietterlin" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-03-03" dateModified="2019-09-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wendel_Dietterlin" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wendel Dietterlin</head>
<figure></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wendel Dietterlin</hi> (c.1550–1599), sometimes <hi rend="bold">Wendel Dietterlin the Elder</hi>, to distinguish him from his son, was a German <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Northern_Mannerism">mannerist</ref> painter, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Printmaker">printmaker</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Architectural_theory">architectural theoretician</ref>. Most of his paintings are now lost, and he is best known<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> for his treatise on architectural ornament, <hi rend="italic">Architectura</hi>, published in its final edition in Nuremberg in 1598.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Dietterlin was born at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pfullendorf">Pfullendorf</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Württemberg">Württemberg</ref>; his original name was Grapp and he may have been a member of a family of artists in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Swabia">Swabia</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> spent most of his life in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strasbourg">Strasbourg</ref> (then Strassburg), where he married Catharina Sprewer on 12 November 1570, and where he is known to have painted frescos for the <hi rend="italic">Bruderhof</hi>, the Bishop's residence, in 1575, but he is later recorded in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hagenau">Hagenau</ref> in 1583 and in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oberkirch_(Baden)">Oberkirch</ref> in 1589. He also worked on large projects in Stuttgart for some time (see below).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref>  He died in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strasbourg">Strasbourg</ref>.</p>
<head>Paintings</head>
<p>In Strasbourg, Dietterlin worked on the decoration of the <hi rend="italic">Neuer Bau</hi> (currently the building of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chambre_de_Commerce_et_d'Industrie,_Strasbourg">Chambre de Commerce et d'Industrie</ref>) in 1589. Between 1590 and 1592 he was employed in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stuttgart">Stuttgart</ref> with the execution of a large (57 metres long and 20 metres wide) ceiling painting in the upper hall of the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neues_Lusthaus">Neues Lusthaus</ref></hi>, a building constructed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duke_of_Württemberg">Duke Ludwig of Württemberg</ref> for entertainment purposes. In addition to the ceiling, Dietterlin painted the walls of the hall. The Renaissance <hi rend="italic">Lusthaus</hi> having later been rebuilt several times and almost entirely replaced in 1845 by the new <hi rend="italic">Hoftheater</hi> (which was destroyed in a fire in 1902, when some of the remains of the original building came to light),<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> nothing is now preserved of the paintings from the hall, but they are depicted in a 1619 etching by the Strasbourg-based painter and engraver <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Friedrich_Brentel">Friedrich Brentel</ref> showing the interior of the large room.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> Other of his paintings are known from engravings by Matthäus Greuter and by his own grandson Bartholomäus Dietterlin. The style, with "exaggerated foreshortenings", appears influenced by North Italian models, such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giulio_Romano">Giulio Romano</ref>'s frescos in Mantua, through German intermediaries.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>His only extant painting is a <hi rend="italic">Resurrection of Lazarus</hi> (in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Staatliche_Kunsthalle_Karlsruhe">Staatliche Kunsthalle Karlsruhe</ref>), signed and dated 1582 or 1587.</p>
<head>The <hi rend="italic">Architectura</hi></head>
<figure><caption>Columns of the Composite order in Wendel Dietterlin's version. From <hi rend="italic">Architectura</hi>, plate 178.</caption></figure>
<p>Dietterlin's architectural treatise <hi rend="italic">Architectvra: Von Außtheilung, Symmetria vnd Proportion der Fünff Seulen</hi> was first published in separate parts in 1593 and 1594, and finally in a combined and expanded edition in 1598. The book described the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Classical_order">classical orders</ref> and their character and proper use, as was traditional in such books. Dietterlin, however, showed less interest in the proportions of the order than in their ornamentation. According to the architectural historian Torbjörn Fulton, Dietterlin treats the orders "more as a basis or excuse for the development of a bizarre ornamental fantasy than as didactic examples of classical architectural ornamentation".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> Like other theoreticians, he ascribed masculine and feminine qualities to the orders. In giving them an appropriate ornamentation that would agree with these qualities, he borrowed from older forms of ornament, including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gothic_tracery">Gothic tracery</ref>. Dietterlin was dependent on many older models, and like other representatives of the Northern Renaissance (such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hans_Vredeman_de_Vries">Hans Vredeman de Vries</ref>) he filled his surfaces with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scrollwork">scrollwork</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strapwork">strapwork</ref>, gemshapes and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grotesque">grotesques</ref>. Dietterlin had Northern European contemporaries who likewise integrated Gothic elements in their designs, but he was unusual in the degree of blending of elements of different origin. While others kept Gothic elements clearly separate from Renaissance forms, Dietterlin would cover Renaissance elements in Gothic tracery or allow one to morph midway into the other.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<head>Primary sources</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Dietterlin, Wendel: <hi rend="italic"><ref target="http://diglit.ub.uni-heidelberg.de/diglit/dietterlin1598">Architectvra: Von Außtheilung, Symmetria vnd Proportion der Fünff Seulen, und aller darauß volgender Kunst Arbeit, von Fenstern, Caminen ...</ref></hi>. Nürnberg, 1598</item>
<item> All the editions on line, website "Architectura".</item></list>
<head>Secondary sources</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>von Borries, J. E.: "Brentel [Brändel; Brendel], Friedrich, I", <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grove_Art_Online">Grove Art Online</ref></hi>. Retrieved on 26 December 2008.</item>
<item>Fulton, Torbjörn: <hi rend="italic">Stuckarbeten i svenska byggnadsmiljöer från äldre Vasatid</hi> [Stucco decoration in Swedish architectural settings of the early Vasa period], (Ars Suetica, 16.) Uppsala: Uppsala University, 1994. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Standard_Book_Number">ISBN</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/91-554-3332-4">91-554-3332-4</ref></item>
<item>Heck, Michèle-Caroline, "Dietterlin, Wendel [Grapp, Wendling]", <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grove_Art_Online">Grove Art Online</ref></hi>. Retrieved on 26 December 2008.</item>
<item>Lambert, A.: "<ref target="http://retro.seals.ch/cntmng?type=pdf&amp;rid=sbz-002:1903:41:42::48&amp;subp=hires">Das ehemalige Lusthaus in Stuttgart</ref>", <hi rend="italic">Schweizerische Bauzeitung</hi>, Vol. 41/42 (1903), pp.41–43</item>
<item>Martin, Kurt, "<ref target="http://mdz10.bib-bvb.de/~db/0001/bsb00016319/images/index.html?seite=718">Dietterlin, Wendel</ref>", <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neue_Deutsche_Biographie">Neue Deutsche Biographie</ref></hi> 3 (Berlin 1957), pp.702–703.</item></list>
</text>
