<text id="autogum_interview_doc070" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Australian wheelchair basketball coach Tom Kyle" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-06-30" dateModified="2015-11-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_wheelchair_basketball_coach_Tom_Kyle" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Australian wheelchair basketball coach Tom Kyle</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 1, 2014</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Toronto">Toronto </ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada">Canada</ref> —
What experiences makes a coach of an international sports team? <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> interviewed Tom Kyle, the coach of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia_women's_national_wheelchair_basketball_team">Australia women's national wheelchair basketball team</ref>, known as the Gliders, in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Toronto">Toronto</ref> for the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2014_Women's_World_Wheelchair_Basketball_Championship">2014 Women's World Wheelchair Basketball Championship</ref>.</p>
<figure><caption>Tom Kyle Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Hawkeye7">Hawkeye7</ref>   . </caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Tell us about yourself. First of all, where were you born?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tom Kyle:</hi> I was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cooma">Cooma</ref>, in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Snowy%20Mountains">Snowy Mountains</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_South_Wales">New South Wales</ref>. Way back in 1959. Fifteenth of June. Grew up in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Snowy%20Mountains%20Scheme">Snowy Mountains Scheme</ref> with my family. At that stage my father worked for the Snowy scheme. And started playing sport when I was very young. I was a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Cricket">cricketer</ref> when I first started. Then about the age of 12, 13 I discovered basketball. Because it had gotten too cold to do all the sports that I wanted to do, and we had a lot of rain one year, and decided then that for a couple of months that we'd have a go at basketball.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  So you took up basketball. When did you decide... did you play for the clubs?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tom Kyle:</hi> I played for Cooma. As a 14-year-old I represented them in the under-18s, and then as a 16-year-old I represented them in the senor men's competition. We played in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canberra">Canberra</ref> as a regional district team. At the age of 16 is when I first started coaching. So I started coaching the under-14 rep sides before the age of 16. So I'm coming up to my forty years of coaching.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>   So you formed an ambition to be a coach at that time?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tom Kyle:</hi> Yeah, I liked the coaching. Well I was dedicated to wanting to be a PE [<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Physical%20Education">Physical Education</ref>] teacher at school. And in Year 12 I missed out by three marks of getting the scholarship that I needed. I couldn't go to university without a scholarship, and I missed out by three marks of getting in to PE. So I had a choice of either doing a Bachelor of Arts and crossing over after year one, or go back and do Year 12 [again].  Because of my sport in Cooma, because I played every sport there was, and my basketball started to become my love.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> } You still played cricket?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tom Kyle:</hi> Still played cricket. Was captain of the ACT [<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australian_Capital_Territory">Australian Capital Territory</ref>] in cricket at the age of 12. Went on to... potentially I could have gone further but cricket became one of those sports where you spend all weekend, four afternoons a week...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I know what it's like.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tom Kyle:</hi> At that stage I was still an A grade cricketer in Cooma and playing in Canberra, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Rugby_league">rugby league</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Rugby_union">rugby union</ref>, had a go at AFL [<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australian_football">Australian Football League</ref>], <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Soccer">soccer</ref>. Because in country towns you play everything. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tennis">Tennis</ref> on a Saturday. Cricket or football on a Sunday. That sort of stuff so... And then basketball through the week.</p>
</text>
