<text id="autogum_reddit_doc021" title="Just caught up on the last ~50 chapters of the manga and have some things that don't sit well with me" shortTile="caught-up-last--chapters" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-05-31" dateModified="2018-05-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8nlxkd" speakerList="#Buffalo_Hill, #Inferno792" speakerCount="2">
<head>Just caught up on the last ~50 chapters of the manga and have some things that don't sit well with me</head>
<sp who="#Inferno792">
<p>So I had taken a break from SnS about a year back, and I was excited to read all the new chapters(I got spoiled about Souma becoming First seat! Damn it!). So, the end of the last arc had a few things that just bugged me. Why did the Nakiris have to have "The Blessing?" Okay, delicious food making people have internal orgasms was fine, but physical clothes being torn just because some guy found it to be delicious? It's just something that really bugged me throughout. Another thing was that Souma saying "I  <hi rend="bold">can't</hi>  beat Erina yet and I  <hi rend="bold">haven't</hi>  beaten Rindou, Tsukasa". Before their training for the regimental Shokugeki began, Souma had already beaten Elite ten members above Erina. Now, I'm not saying that Erina was surely not as skilled as the lower half of the E10, just that she probably wasn't good enough to be in the upper half of the E10 at the very least. And we know Souma's growth rate since he joined Totsuki has been tremendous. So by that rate, he almost surely had to be above her if he was beating a fourth seat in the Elite 10. Also, this is the first time that Souma has accepted that he can't beat someone other than Joichioru. Souma's mild arrogance and confidence that he can beat anyone are a massive part of his character, imo and I loved that about him. Him accepting that he  <hi rend="bold">can't</hi>  beat someone for the first time took a lot of the feels of the victory away for me. Another thing I feel is that Erina could've been a lot more dynamic in the future chapters as part of the student body rather than being in the administration. She's basically gonna be busy with administration work and won't be able to focus much on cooking if she's to do her job as the headmaster right. So yeah, the last few chapters just had these moments that took a lot of the fun away for me. What are your thoughts on these things?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#Buffalo_Hill">
<p>The blessing thing didn't really bug me since Food Wars is by it's nature a very over the top series. From the very beginning of the manga and the anime they establish that food is so good it has people explode out of their clothes and the blessing is really just an exaggeration of an exaggeration. </p>
<p> It's ridiculous for Azami to have others explode out of their clothes and it's cheap fan -service but it's a defining aspect of the series (for better or worse ). All of the Nakiri's have ridiculousness as a defining trait. The grandfather goes bare, one speaks random English when the food is good etc. </p>
<p>Honestly, the hierarchy of characters in Food Wars is pretty loose. While it's established that Rindou and Tsukasa are both stronger than Soma and Erina in general the ranking of the other Elite 10 is a lot more inconsistent. Erina as the 10th Seat is able to defeat the 4th seat. The 6th seat loses twice to non seat members. </p>
<p> A lot of the characters in Food Wars are giving hype by defeating fodder or built up by the author through reputation rather than direct explicit rankings in case the series wants to be flexible over who's stronger than who. Barring a few exceptions like Rindou and Tsukasa. </p>
<p>Soma admitting that he isn't as strong as Rindou, Tsukasa gives his character a direction to go towards. Rather than Soma just trying to directly take on his dad next. </p>
</sp>
</text>
