<text id="autogum_interview_doc669" title="part12_Gay Talese on the state of journalism, Iraq and his life" shortTile="partgay-talese-state" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-27" dateModified="2019-01-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gay_Talese_on_the_state_of_journalism%2C_Iraq_and_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Not any more?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  Now the journalists and the people in power, the government and financial world, they're all of the same class, which is privileged class.  Journalists are people who are distant from those who are "The Deciders", to use Bush's phrase.  I think there is an all-inclusiveness, and I think the Washington Press Corp is representative of what I am saying.  They co-mingle; they live in the same neighborhoods and they go to the same places.  The Washington Press Corp. is the worst.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Did you see Stephen Colbert roast the Washington Press Corp and Bush at the White House Press Correspondence dinner?  Nobody laughed, because they were all coming from the same place.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  And it got a bad review, and then a revised review!  The first account I read--I didn't see it or watch it--was that it was boring.  Then it took on a life of its own!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Because nobody reported about it, or they just said he bombed.  Then it went out on the internet and took on a life of its own and people said, "This isn't bombing, this a roasting of the entire power structure and the power structure decided they didn't like it."</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  I feel the Washington Press Corp. should be broken up.  Just have them distributed around the country.  Put them in state capitals and just feed the state capitals with more reporters and have them feed the big papers.  Cover the country not from Washington.  It's so federalized.  More state's rights kind of reporting; represent power across the country not just overloaded in one place.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  A view of the federal government from the national scene?  "Here in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Denver,%20Colorado">Denver</ref> the reaction to Washington..."</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  That's right!  It would be harder, because they won't be fed.  They'll have to do more...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Reporting?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  That's right!  They wouldn't really like that.  And they would probably be able to report the war better as it is reflected in towns with a lot of soldiers, and returning injured and dead in those towns.  They would really get a feel for the country, and not just those <hi rend="italic">non-participants</hi> in Washington who are mouthing this-and-that and getting defense appropriations.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  The way it is now, they don't get an interview with so-and-so if they write something, or they don't get to go to someone's party!</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  Yeah, well, cut half the leaking.  Just leave the capitol and cover the country.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bob%20Woodward">Bob Woodward</ref> is still an intrepid Washington reporter?  He's often been accused of being too close to the people he covers.</hi></p>
</text>
