<text id="autogum_interview_doc641" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Flame about special effects at New Zealand&amp;apos;s Rock2Wgtn festival" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-22" dateModified="2014-04-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Flame_about_special_effects_at_New_Zealand%27s_Rock2Wgtn_festival" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<figure><caption>Performers Anna and Milly onstage with fire umbrellas</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews (Blood Red Sandman)</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What was the audience reaction to your show like?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Milly Bea:</hi> As we were performing on 2 small stages simultaneously, in the terracing, behind and to the either side of the main stage, we were quite a distance from the audience, so couldn’t really gauge their general reaction…Those faces I could see down below, of the roadies backstage, were all smiles and waving fists of rock…. We did hear back from a few people in the audience that we looked great from the distance and on the screen when we appeared on occasion.  They noted the massive fire and our choreography.</p>
<p>The stunt guys enjoyed our show and apparently Ozzy stopped to whatch us briefly as he moved towards the mainstage!!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews (Blood Red Sandman)</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Just how much fuel did you get through, and at what cost?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Milly Bea:</hi> We had over estimated our fuel usage… better to have more than not enough I suppose. We probably ended up using 8 litres of kerosene for each 15-20minute burn set.</p>
<p>So for 2 burns sets on 2 stages for 2 nights plus 1 rehersal each…Making that a grand total of 10 burns of 8L =80L at $4 L…approx..<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20Zealand%20dollar">$</ref>320</p>
<p>About that..I didn’t do the figures or pay too much attention to how much we were burning..but think that’s a pretty good guess.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews (Blood Red Sandman)</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How has this event changed things at Flame Fire Productions?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Milly Bea:</hi> Flame Fire Productions hasn’t really changed all that much as a result…by the fame I mean.. tahaha hasn’t really been any major influx of gigs as a result..!!? But now, as a result of needing to invest in more &amp; in quality gear for Rock2Wtgn, we have a mass of new and gorgeous fire toys and red hot pvc costumes…that do truly rock! And some great photos and an awesome experience.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews (Blood Red Sandman)</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Do you anticipate a repeat of Rock2Wgtn? If so, do you feel you would get involved with that or a similar event again?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Milly Bea:</hi> It would be great to be involved in the same or similar event. I love the idea of combining big Music gigs with other performing arts and dance… in one night events as well as music festivals. Its awesome to work with other artists and organisers in creating events that surround,  immerse the audience so they are embraced by the experience being communicated and received through all the senses, visual, sound etc.... whether Rock or whatever!!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews (Blood Red Sandman)</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What was your personal opinion of the bands performing?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Milly Bea:</hi> I find my personal opinion of the bands performing quite entertaining really…I never really realized or experienced the art of Rock theatre and I did find it both disturbing and comical as well as rocking.. KISS were outrageous!! Their outfits?! The studs!! The boots!! What are they on? And that man's [<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gene%20Simmons">Gene Simmons</ref>'] tongue is outrageous.. and what he does with it!! I was ooooeing and laughing and rocking my fist in the air.. definately entertaining.. Alice Cooper was also a little disturbing especially  when it came to the hitting the lady dancer routine.. didn't dig it… and the baby in the push chair?.. a clash of psycho &amp; comic...?  althou I did like some of his lyrics…</p>
</text>
