<text id="autogum_interview_doc148" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Irene Villa" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-02-25" dateModified="2013-11-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Irene_Villa" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Irene Villa</hi>: Of course. In the case of the women, it is really hard to get a woman skiing, to have her compete in sit-ski. In fact, in Spain we exist thanks to Fundación También, which insisted in there being a female category. There was no female category, no women who dared. And we're the same who started out in 2007. There has been no new blood because women don't dare, because it is a tough sport, that requires sponsors —that do not exist—, or your own money, and it also demands courage and withstanding bad moments. I've suffered cold and injuries, and had some really tough times. You take away the best with you, but it is very hard, and men resist the cold better. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Claro. Es que en las mujeres cuesta muchísimo que una mujer se ponga a esquiar, a competir en silla. De hecho en España estamos gracias a la Fundación También, que es la que se empeñó en que hubiese categoría femenina. No existía la categoría femenina, no había mujeres que se atrevieran. Y de hecho somos las mismas que empezamos en el 2007. No se ha renovado porque no se atreven, es un deporte duro, que además requiere sponsors, que no hay, o dinero de tu bolsillo, y además requiere valentía y malos ratos. Yo he pasado mucho frío y muchas caidas, y lo he pasado muy mal. La verdad es que te quedas siempre con lo bueno, pero es muy duro, y es cierto que los hombres son más fuertes para el frío.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Your personal experiences have adequately prepared you to hurl yourself down the mountain at high speed?  ((es))Spanish language: ‍¿Sus experiencias personales le han preparado adecuadamente para lanzarse pendiente abajo a máxima velocidad?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Irene Villa</hi>: At the beginning, it was very scary. The first times were very hard: falls, injuries... I even dislocated my vertebra and got a prothesis for the neck because of a hernia, one teammate broke her <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/clavicle">clavicle</ref>, another her <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/femur">femur</ref>... It has a lot of risks, but the truth is, speed hooks you! Once you learn to plant the ski pole, angle yourself, learn the position you must use, which is like a motorcycle rider's, once you see you can run a lot and not fall, speed is addictive and you want to go faster. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Al principio, mucho miedo. Los comienzos fueron muy duros: caidas, lesiones... A mi incluso se me salió el disco del cuello, me tuvieron que poner una prótesis en el cuello por una hernia que tenía, otra se rompió la clavícula, otra el femur, en fin... Tiene mucho riesgo, pero la verdad que la velocidad engancha. Una vez que aprendes a clavar el canto, a angular, la posición en la que tienes que ir, que es como la de un motorista, una vez que ves que puedes correr mucho y no te caes, sí que engancha la velocidad y quieres ir cada vez más rápido.</p>
</text>
