<text id="autogum_voyage_doc320" title="Wausau" shortTile="wausau" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=38697" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wausau</head>

<p>Wausau is a city in <ref target="North%20Central%20Wisconsin">North Central Wisconsin</ref>. While the metropolitan area has a population of around 80,000, it has a big city feel and often leads one to believe they are in a larger city. Wausau has many great man-made and natural features, such as Dudley Tower/First Wausau Tower, the tallest commercial building in the state outside of Milwaukee, and Rib Mountain State Park/Granite Peak Ski Area.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
 
<p>Traveling north and south, Wausau can be reached via I-39/US-51, and traveling east and west, Wausau can be reached by State Highway 29. Wausau can be reached from Minneapolis in about three and a half hours via I-94 and State Highway 29. Milwaukee is about three and a half hours away as well via I-94 and I-39.</p>
<p>Central Wisconsin Airport (CWA)<ref target="http://www.fly-cwa.org/"></ref>, 12 miles south of Wausau, provides daily service to and from Detroit (<ref target="http://www.delta.com">Delta Air Lines</ref>), Minneapolis (<ref target="http://www.delta.com">Delta Air Lines</ref>), Chicago O'Hare (<ref target="http://www.aa.com">American Airlines</ref> or <ref target="http://www.united.com">United Airlines</ref>).</p>
<p>Lamers Bus Lines offers a daily trip<ref target="http://www.golamers.com/%3Fpage_id%3D34"></ref> to/from Milwaukee via the Fox Valley which may be ticketed through Greyhound (or Amtrak if connecting to a rail leg).</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Wausau Downtown Airport</hi> ( AUW ). A <ref target="General%20aviation">General aviation</ref> airport</item>
</list>

 

<head>By bus</head>

<p>Public transportation is limited in the Wausau Area. Metro Ride (formerly WATS or Wausau Area Transit System) operates eight bus routes in the City of Wausau which run at 30-minute intervals; one bus route in the Village of Weston, which runs at 30-minute intervals; and one bus route to Rothschild and Schofield, which operates at 60-minute intervals. Passengers can transfer between routes at the Metro Ride Transit Center, which is located at 555 Jefferson Street in the downtown Wausau, one block from the Wausau Center Mall. Passengers can also transfer between Route C and Route K at Shopko in Rothschild and between Route E and Route I at Aspirus Clinic in Wausau. Buses are clean and uncrowded but the limited schedule makes them somewhat impractical to all but the most dedicated transit user.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>Travel by car is very easy in the Wausau area and the preferred method of transportation. Roads are well maintained and marked. Ample, free, at-door parking is available everywhere outside of the downtown area. Downtown, parking is easy to find and very inexpensive. As the city and surrounding area are oriented north/south, for trips from the far north to far south side or vice versa, it is quicker and easier to use the US 51/I 39 expressway which runs along the west edge of the city.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Leigh Yawkey Woodson Art Museum</hi>, 700 North Twelfth Street, ☏ +1 715 845-7010 . Tuesday - Friday: 9AM-4PM, Saturday-Sunday: Noon - 5PM.. The Museum's permanent collection is known for its focus on nature with historic and contemporary paintings, sculptures, and works on paper that focus on birds. The annual Birds in Art exhibition in September and October attracts both international artists and visitors. The gardens dotted with sculpture invite visitors to "outdoor galleries." The museum building itself is impressive. In 1976, John and Alice Woodson Forester transformed their English Cotswold-style residence into a museum to display her mother's collections of Royal Worcester porcelains and Victorian glass baskets. Consult the schedule of events section of the web site for specific exhibition and program information. Free Admission. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Marathon County Historical Museums</hi>, 403 and 410 McIndoe St, ☏ +1 715 848-6143 . Tuesday - Thursday: 9 am - 4:30 pm, Saturday - Sunday 1 pm - 4:30 pm, Closed Monday, Friday and major holidays.. In 1954, Leigh Yawkey Woodson and her daughters donated the home of her late parents, lumberman Cyrus C. Yawkey and Alice Richardson Yawkey, to the Historical Society. The house was built in 1900 in the Classical Revival style and later remodeled in the Prairie School style and was placed on the National Register of Historic Places in 1974. The Yawkey House has been renovated to its original state with an authentically furnished music room, dining room, and parlor which give a taste of gracious living of a bygone era. The formal gardens displaying a colorful array of native wildflowers, perennials, annuals, and herbs and carriage house are open throughout the summer. The home of A.P. Woodson and Leigh Yawkey Woodson, located across the street at 410 McIndoe Street was built in 1914 and designed by Prairie School architect, George W. Maher. The Woodson House contains the Historical Society’s library, archives, administrative offices, artifact storage, and the educational exhibit area. $2.00 donation. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Rib Mountain State Park</hi> (Four miles southwest off of Highway 51, Exit 188 to Rib Mountain Drive (follow signs)), ☏ +1 715 842-7522 . Daily: 6AM-11PM. Covering over 860 acres, (348 hectares), Rib Mountain State Park boasts a well-maintained network of hiking and nature trails that allows visitors to enjoy many wildflowers and other plants growing throughout the park. Campsites, picnic areas, an interpretive center, scenic overlooks, and a 60 foot observation tower near the top of the peak provide a spectacular view of the Wausau Area and surrounding countryside. Featured events include “Concerts in the Clouds” at the amphitheater during the summer and in the winter, ski or snowboard down one of the many runs at Granite Peak Ski Area on the north side of Rib Mountain. Granite Peak is considered one of the Midwest's leading ski resorts. Fees apply. Special hourly sticker available at park entrance from mid-May through August. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Wausau Depot</hi>, 720 Grant Street. Wausau, no phone. Interior not open to the public. When most people think of Wausau, they probably envision the railroad depot created by Wausau Insurance Companies for a corporate logo. They can't find the depot pictured in the ads because it was drawn by an artist combining one depot building with the view of the city skyline from another depot. The depot featured in the logo still stands at 720 Grant Street. After Wausau Insurance Companies bought the building in 1977, a faithful reproduction was constructed at its corporate headquarters (Bridge Street exit of US Highway 51) for advertising purposes and the Grant Street depot was donated to the Boy Scouts. The Washington Street depot (Washington Street at the Wisconsin River) with the city backdrop depicted in the logo has recently been restored and used as office space.</item>
</list>
</text>
