<text id="autogum_reddit_doc142" title="Your opinion on Neia?" shortTile="opinion-neia" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-03-31" dateModified="2018-03-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/88mnu7" speakerList="#LordSui, #Seraph64, #missingo00" speakerCount="3">
<head>Your opinion on Neia?</head>
<sp who="#missingo00">
<p>As someone who binge read 9 Volumes of Overlord (when only 9 were available), i can only say that I absolutely love this series. But trough the entirety of the series no character had me as riled up as Neia. The thought that Papa bones is going to kill this cinnamon roll because of a misunderstanding just kills me inside. I don't care for any other character as much as i do for her. Am I going crazy? She has only made an appearance in one Volume(half volume) so I don't understand why I even like her that much. I mean, don't get me wrong, there are plenty of great characters in Overlord. But the entire Nazarick cast is pretty much indestructible (with exception of the maids, but i doubt something like this is going to happen again). And other characters like the emperor are fun but, i wouldn't mind if he died for the glory of Nazarick or something. I also read that people liked that worker from vol 7 but i didnt really care about them. Question: You like Neia as much as I do for inexplicable reasons? Or are you a cold and heartless monster? If you are, why? Is she boring to you? (collecting opinions) Also you believe she Ded? (pls no) </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#Seraph64">
<p>I'm not particularly fond of Neia, I kinda knew she was fodder from the beginning. </p>
<p>She is indeed likeable (unless for GraspHeart I guess) since she comes around and understands what Ainz put forward to her, even if it is pure uncensored bullshit. </p>
<p>And yeah, she is very dead, just pray for her to go like Arche and not like Roberdyck </p>
<p>The only way I see she surviving is if she ends in the happy farm. </p>
<p>If you want to get attached to someone either pick Enri or Tsuare</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#LordSui">
<p>I liked her, i believe her inner thought were what made the vol 12 good... It will be very sad when she dies, specially because it was a misunderstanding from Ainz... </p>
<p>Funny thing is that she was bullied her entire life because of that eyes of her, and it was precisely because of that eyes that Ainz was so wary of her. </p>
<p>However, i doubt i will feel as bad for her dying as i felt when Gazef was killed... </p>
<p>About the worker from vol 7... meh, felt nothing... well felt sorry for the sisters, but for the girl itself? meh </p>
</sp>
</text>
