<text id="autogum_reddit_doc145" title="What We Now Know About the Nines: A Group Appearance Analysis of APE’s Revered Squad" shortTile="now-know-nines-group" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-03-31" dateModified="2018-03-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/88md5h" speakerList="#TheIsolator, #unknown" speakerCount="2">
<head>What We Now Know About the Nines: A Group Appearance Analysis of APE’s Revered Squad</head>
<sp who="#unknown">
<p>That group. The white-uniformed puppeteers of Club Lamarck. A haughty squad of elite soldiers highly trained in FranXX combat, manhandling large klaxosaurs with no sweat. A special forces team with no sense of etiquette, yet with high bearing. An octet of few words, yet with pride mindlessly execute APE’s sovereign will. A coalition spreading its influence like a shadow over the other squads, and in so doing give everyone below them the impression that they are to be treated with dignity. These are the Nines, the most potent squad under APE’s control. They first revealed their faces in the opening of episode 2, with a blonde-haired, green-eyed male youth as their proud leader and spokesman, flanked by a green-haired female and a tall, blue-haired teenager to his left, and two other pubescent males of fine stature on his right. In the back of the posing circle are three grey-haired, masked females of identical stature and appearance, whose symbolism has been the subject of much speculation in the DitF community. These pilots are first referred to in Episode 1 by Nana, who indirectly declared a still rational Zero Two as one of the elite’s number when she said, “This is Code 002, a member of a special forces squad APE directly controls.” The Nines are next referenced in the beginning Episode 4 by the sages of Club Lamarck, when Papa talks about the many klaxosaurs of large size appearing all over the place. One of the sages replies, “The Nines are dealing with them for now, but they have other things to do.” An indicator, as I said in an earlier theory, that the Nines are heavily involved in political affairs, not just fighting the underground monsters. Three of them are first seen in the post-credits scene of Episode Six, where their leader, who has been credited in the comments as Nine α, or Nine Alpha (hence my profile name) commends a certain Nine ι (Iota) on “hitting it off,” a phrase meaning to get along. Nine α appears yet again in the following episode, as Hiro is introduced to Dr. Franxx. He states that “I’ve taken an interest in you guys,” adding that Hiro is the first to survive Zero Two’s curse. He also says, “I’m sure we’ll run into each other again in the near future.” Along comes Episode 10, and the parasites are taken to the city to be awarded the medals. The adult acknowledging them for their efforts turns to Zero Two and says, “It is an honor that a former Nine like yourself would join us.” Again, they are treated with much reverence and respect by everyone else, and the adults are no exception. And Nine α is true to his word: Squad 13 finally meets the Nines, and they do so in Episode 12, today’s release. All eight of them make their first appearance as a group, and interestingly enough, α is the only one of the squad to speak, indicating that he himself has a position of very high authority in APE. He says to Zero Two, “It’s a pleasure to see you again, Nine Iota,” confirming she is the one spoken of in Episode Six. When she asks them to stay away, he says something bizarre: “Glad to see you haven’t changed,” indicating that he’s seen Zero Two in that volatile mood before. After asking Squad 13’s identity, α approaches Ichigo, who tells him to his face that they have no etiquette, mirroring Zero Two’s behavior. He replies suavely, “How cold,” before kissing Ichigo’s hand like a nice gentleman. Throughout the episode he continues to reveal certain things to Ichigo that she previously didn’t know about the Partner Killer. He states that she truly is a monster in human form. He also says that she’s the “key to saving the world,” despite the horrifying fact that she had disposed of more than one hundred stamens in her military career. So there you go, guys. It’s only been nothing more than cameo appearances spread out over 12 episodes, but already there’s so much material we can learn from this shady squad. Are they going to accompany our squad for insurance on the Grand Crevasse? Will they be the final enemies of Squad 13, or will they also join in a rebellion against Papa himself? Have a good one! DitFCodeAlpha</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#TheIsolator">
<p>Both s13 and the Nines are on the way to the Crevasse like I always thought and next time they meet it will be as enemies I would say. </p>
<p>Just look at the one frame in ep12 where both teams face each other like they are rivals, a clear sign for me. But I really hoped that we hear other members besides Alpha talking especially the small girl or the two badass looking guys on the left side ;( </p>
<p>Somehow Alpha gives off an intriguing and sinister aura, at the moment I give him a lot of potential for the future big villian. I hope he doesn't dissapoint...</p>
</sp>
</text>
