<text id="autogum_voyage_doc102" title="Eastern Arizona" shortTile="eastern-arizona" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=10352" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Eastern Arizona</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Eastern Arizona</hi> is part of the state of <ref target="Arizona">Arizona</ref>, in the <ref target="United%20States%20of%20America">United States of America</ref>. It is a complex region of remarkable cultural, geological and scenic diversity despite its sparse population.</p>

<head>Cities</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
</list>


<head>Get in</head>

<p>Interstate 40, following the route of the old <ref target="Route%2066">Route 66</ref>, runs along the northern edge of this region, and I-10 through its southern area. There are no major airports in the region; the closest airports with significant commercial service are in <ref target="Phoenix">Phoenix</ref> and <ref target="Tucson">Tucson</ref>.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<p>A car is essential as there is no public transportation.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Casa Malpaís Archeological Site and Museum</hi>, 418 East Main St, Springerville (museum and visitor center) (near Springerville), ☏ +1 928-333-5375 , ✉ casa@springervilleaz.gov . T-S 8AM-4PM (museum); tours at 9AM, 11AM, and 2PM. An ancient pueblo archaeological site, with remains of an astronomical calendar, a great kiva, stairs, and petroglyphs. Tours start from the museum in Springerville. $10 (adults), $8 (seniors), $5 (children under 18).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tonto National Monument</hi>, 26260 N AZ Hwy 188 #2 (near Roosevelt), ☏ +1 928-467-2241 , fax: +1 928-467-2225 . Daily 8AM-5PM. This park contains well-preserved Salado cliff dwellings, Guided tours to the Upper Cliff Dwellings are offered from Nov-Apr; reservations required (tel. 928-467-2241). A museum and bookshop are on-site. $3 (adults), free (children under 16).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tonto Natural Bridge State Park</hi>, Hwy 87 (10 miles north of Payson), ☏ +1 928-476-4202 . Daily 8AM-6PM. The largest natural travertine bridge in the world. $5 (adults 14+), $2 (youth 7-13), free (child 0-6).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Boyce Thompson Arboretum State Park</hi>, 37615 US 60, Superior, ☏ +1 520-689-2811 . Daily 6AM-3PM (summer). Arizona's oldest and largest botanical garden. Walking tours and lectures are held here, along with occasional photography workshops. $9 (adults), $4.50 (children 5-12).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fort Apache National Historic Park</hi>, Hwy 73 (Fort Apache Indian Reservation), ☏ +1 928-338-4525 . Daily 7AM-sunset. This 288-acre National Historic District encompasses the remains of Fort Apache, as well as Kinishba Ruins, a sprawling Zuni and Hope site abandoned around 1400 CE. Also on site is the White Mountain Apache Cultural Center and Museum. $5 (adults), $3 (seniors), free (children under 7).</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Salt River Canyon Wilderness</hi>. A deep river canyon, managed by the Tonto National Forest. There are no maintained trails, although the wilderness can be visited anytime. There are 27 sets of rapids and many side creeks, and white-water rafting and kayaking is popular during the spring. From March 1 - May 15 river-running permits are required; group size is limited to 15 people.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Buckboard City Cafe</hi>, 1111 US 60, Superior, ☏ +1 520-689-5800 . W-Su 6AM-2PM. Simple country fare, popular with locals.</item>
</list>
</text>
