<text id="autogum_voyage_doc370" title="Benelux" shortTile="benelux" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=3392" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Benelux</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Benelux</hi> is an economic union comprising three neighbouring monarchies: <ref target="Belgium"><hi rend="bold">Be</hi>lgium</ref>, the <ref target="Netherlands"><hi rend="bold">Ne</hi>therlands</ref>, and <ref target="Luxembourg"><hi rend="bold">Lux</hi>embourg</ref>. The name is formed from the beginning of each country's name. It was a precursor of the European Union.</p>

<head>Cities</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> — traveller magnet due to its impressive architecture, lovely canals (<hi rend="italic">grachten</hi>), museums and liberal attitudes</item>
<item> — a giant cathedral, medieval streets, artistic heritage, and the second-largest port of Europe, coined the Diamond of the Sea</item>
<item> — unofficial capital of the EU with a nice historic centre and several museums</item>
<item> — one of Europe's wealthiest cities in the 14th century, its large and beautiful historic centre remains intact; a romantic city with pre-Renaissance walls</item>
<item> — largest city of Wallonia (the French part of Belgium), along a wide river, industrial cityscape with hiking and resorts in the nearby hills</item>
<item> — its spectacular valleys and plateaus led it to be nicknamed the "Gibraltar of the North"</item>
<item> — modern architecture, good nightlife and the largest port of Europe, Rotterdam is a hub of excitement</item>
<item> — seat of government, royal family, judicial capital of the world and Madurodam</item>
<item> — historic centre, nice antique stores and the Rietveld-Schröder House are all in this magnificent Dutch city</item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> — The most sparsely populated in Benelux, this is a hilly countryside region covered with forests.</item>
<item> — For three days in February, the town is transported back to the 16th century for one of the most fantastic carnival festivals.</item>
<item> — Largest national park with heathlands, sand dunes and woodlands.</item>
<item> — Millions of tourists visit the tulip fields each Spring.</item>
<item> — These windmills show the typical Dutch landscape in all its glory.</item>
<item> — An area of green fields and small villages, some of which have been portrayed by artists such as Pieter Bruegel.</item>
<item> — Old island evacuated in 1859, a well-preserved ghost village remains.</item>
<item> — Quaint small town presided over by a rather splendid château.</item>
<item> — The Waterloo Battlefield where Napoleon lost the final battle that changed Europe's face forever.</item>
</list>


<head>Understand</head>

<ref target="Luxembourg">Luxembourg</ref> and the East of <ref target="Belgium">Belgium</ref> are a hilly area, but the rest of the Benelux is what is known as the <hi rend="bold">Low Countries</hi>; this is the delta of the rivers Scheldt, Meuse, Rhine and Ems that used to be swamp land. Enterprising fishermen discovered a flair for trade when trading routes started to emerge between the grain markets of the Baltic Sea and the renaissance-bitten luxury goods markets of northern Italy. Here is where stocks were invented. Trade in all kinds of goods as well as enslaved humans made a small elite incredibly rich and the Dutch East India Company (VOC for its Dutch name) became one of the first multinational stock based companies and in its heyday controlled entire countries.

<p>This attention to trade made <ref target="Bruges">Bruges</ref> one of the largest cities in Europe in its day, and the medieval <ref target="old%20town">old town</ref> is still well preserved. When the secession war with Spain progressed, French and Flemish alike fled to <ref target="Amsterdam">Amsterdam</ref>, which became the new world capital of trade, which is still witnessed in the many 'Houses of the Lords' lining the famous canals.</p>

<head>Talk</head>

<p>Dutch is the main language in the Netherlands and in the north of Belgium (Flanders) where it is also known as Flemish, and is also one of the two official languages of Brussels, spoken by about 15% of its inhabitants. French is the main language (85%) in Brussels, and in all of the South of Belgium (Wallonia) with the exception of the eastern side of Wallonia where you will find the Belgian German speaking community. In Belgium, while most Dutch speakers can speak reasonable French, few Belgian francophones speak Dutch, which has caused political tension in the country. Luxembourg has three official languages: Luxembourgish, French and German, but for all practical purposes French is the most important language for travelers.</p>

<p>Many people, especially in the Netherlands and Flanders, the Dutch-speaking part of Belgium, have a very high proficiency of English, and younger people often have near native fluency. This is because foreign television content is aired in its original language, with subtitles. On the other hand, in French-speaking Wallonia, TV is dubbed into French and people hence do not speak English so well. Frisian is a minority language spoken in Friesland (Netherlands).</p>

<p>As Dutch is very close to German, you will be understood with difficulty by most Dutch speakers if you speak German, but not all of them will necessarily speak more than a handful of German phrases themselves.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>Most people get into the Benelux region by plane or train. <ref target="Schiphol%20Airport">Schiphol Airport</ref> in <ref target="Amsterdam">Amsterdam</ref> and Zaventem Airport in <ref target="Brussels">Brussels</ref> are the largest airports in the region; Schiphol is also important as a transfer airport for further destinations in Europe. Smaller airports are present in <ref target="Antwerp">Antwerp</ref>, <ref target="Eindhoven">Eindhoven</ref>, <ref target="Groningen">Groningen</ref>, <ref target="Luxembourg%20%28city%29">Luxembourg</ref>, <ref target="Maastricht">Maastricht</ref>, <ref target="Charleroi">Charleroi</ref> ("Brussels South"), <ref target="Li%C3%A8ge">Liège</ref> and <ref target="Rotterdam">Rotterdam</ref>, which are mostly used by no-frills airlines.</p>

<head>By train</head>
<ref target="High-speed%20rail">High-speed rail</ref> networks connect the Benelux with <ref target="France">France</ref>, <ref target="Germany">Germany</ref>, and the <ref target="United%20Kingdom">United Kingdom</ref> (through the Channel Tunnel). High-speed trains operated by <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.thalys.com/">Thalys</ref></hi> connect <ref target="Paris">Paris</ref> with <ref target="Brussels">Brussels</ref>, <ref target="Antwerp">Antwerp</ref>, <ref target="Rotterdam">Rotterdam</ref>, and <ref target="Amsterdam">Amsterdam</ref> in a little more than three hours. High-speed (and slower intercity) <hi rend="bold">ICE International</hi> trains operated by <ref target="http://www.bahn.com/i/view/USA/en/index.shtml">Deutsche Bahn</ref> (and <ref target="http://www.ns.nl/en">Nederlandse Spoorwegen</ref>) connect Frankfurt (and Cologne) with Amsterdam and Brussels, and <ref target="Basel">Basel</ref> with Amsterdam. High-speed trains operated by <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.eurostar.com/uk-en">Eurostar</ref></hi> connect <ref target="London">London</ref> with Brussels.

<head>By bus</head>
<p>The major companies running <ref target="Intercity%20buses%20in%20Germany">Intercity buses in Germany</ref> all serve stations in the Benelux as well. France liberalized its long distance bus market in 2015, and connections to major cities in the Benelux have either been announced or are planned. Some buses even take you to London, either through the Channel Tunnel or by being loaded on a car ferry.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>As this is a densely populated area in Europe you usually have the choice of several modes of transport and getting around should be a breeze, if sometimes a bit hard on the wallet.</p>
</text>
