<text id="autogum_voyage_doc538" title="Wolmyeongdong" shortTile="wolmyeongdong" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=154114" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wolmyeongdong</head>


<ref target="http://wolmyeongdong.org">Wolmyeongdong</ref> Park is in South Chungcheong, South Korea. 

<head>Understand</head>
<p>It spans an area of approximately 200 hectares and about above sea level in relatively mountainous terrain. The park enjoys four distinct seasons which change the landscape distinctly. The park is owned and run by the <ref target="http://cgm.or.kr">Christian Gospel Mission</ref> and consists of many natural and man-made attractions, including lakes, pavilions, waterfalls, springs, caves, hiking trails, rock landscapes, statues of Jesus, an art museum, eateries, sports facilities, various lodgings, and multi-purpose halls. </p>

<p>Key events are held annually, including the spring flower festivals, autumn rock festivals, and the summer retreats. These events attract thousands of people from around the region and overseas as well. All year round, visitors are welcome to visit but are required to register with the Christian Gospel Mission first. </p>

<p>This park has perhaps the largest rock landscape in the world. Its Ambition Masterpiece rock landscape runs a full 300 m long and is roughly 5 stories high. The rock landscape consists of a variety of standing and flat rocks that form three particular layers.</p>

<head>History</head>
<p>Construction of the Wolmyeongdong Park began in the early 1990s. It was a barren land with no water and the current mountains were so close to each other that they were almost touching. In order to develop the ambitious masterpiece, most of the Front Mountain was cut and reshaped so that the rock landscape could be developed. The Back Mountain was later developed accordingly. The rock landscape construction is reaching its final stages with a new courtyard being developed next to the Holy Son's House of Love.</p>

<p>In 1995, after Pastor Jung Myeong Seok discovered that there were natural water springs under particular parts of Wolmyeongdong, he led a team to develop the current lake and octagonal pavilion, which is in the middle of the lake. During spring or summer, one can row around the lake in a boat. There is even a tunnel that goes under the octagonal pavilion. During winter, the water in the lake freezes over, and the park is covered in snow.</p>

<head>Landscape</head>
<p>The temperate, mountain, climate gives Wolmyeongdong a landscape with pine trees and other green trees and flowing spring waters. Wolmyeongdong is surrounded by 12 mountains/hills, and Wolmyeongdong itself is also hilly in terrain. The middle of wolmyeongdong where the sports field, lake and lawn are situated is relatively flat. Numerous rocks, large and small, were also made into a rock landscape that is more than 300 m long and 5 stories high, perhaps the world's largest rock landscape. The rock landscape is the most famous portion of Wolmyeongdong.</p>

<head>Flora and fauna</head>

<p>There are a multitude of different types of flora and fauna in Wolmyeongdong. Many of the different flowers are showcased during the spring flower festivals when they are in full bloom.</p>

<head>Climate</head>

<p>Since Wolmyeongdong is well above sea level, the temperature changes drastically depending on the season. In the summer, the temperature can reach up to 35°C while in the winter, the temperature can drop to -15°C. There are also summer monsoons between June and September. The best time to go is during autumn when leaves turn red (coincides with the annual Rock festival) or in spring when the flowers are blooming (coincides with the annual Flower Festival). If you like snow, Wolmyeongdong has a deep winter with abundant snowfall.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>From Incheon Airport, you have to drive down to Daejeon and then to Geumsan. If you search for 월명동 수련원 in Google Maps or Naver Maps, then you will be able to find a route that leads directly there. There is a parking lot before the guard house that is free. Once you park, you will have to hike a bit up past the guard house before reaching the entrance where the lake is, but the path up is great if you go during spring or autumn. Along the path are various trees and flowers. One path is for pedestrians and the other path is for cars that have special permits.</p>

<p>From Daejeon to Wolmyeongdong, it takes about an hour drive.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>You can take the express bus from Incheon Airport to the intercity bus terminal in Daejeon. From there, you can take the 105 intercity bus to Geumsan but get off at Majeon. From Majeon, there is a regular shuttle that runs from the front of a nearby church that CGM owns to Wolmyeongdong. You will be dropped off in front of the guard house.</p>

<p>Alternatively, you can also take the public transit from Daejeon city to Jinsan and hike up to Wolmyeongdong through Apseob Valley. From Daejeon, you'll need to get to the 34 intercity bus that goes directly to Jinsan. The time it takes using this route is a little longer (an hour and a half to two hours) than if you went by express bus or car, but it is much cheaper (₩5000 round trip if you have an public transit card).</p>

<head>Fees and permits</head>

<p>Wolmyeongdong Park is open 24/7 and is free. If you are not a member of CGM, you need to apply first on their website before entering. If you want to park directly in Wolmyeongdong, you will need a special permit to pass the guard house.</p>
<head>By foot</head>
<p>Once you are in Wolmyeongdong, every area can be reached by foot. There are some paths that cars can drive through, but for the best experience, going by foot is recommended. There are hiking trails and walking trails of varying difficulties that lead to great viewpoints. Within the main part of Wolmyeongdong, which extends from the entrance to the lawn sanctuary and the Culture Center, there is a sports field that is surrounded by natural image rocks and rock landscapes. Next to the sports field is the lake and the Holy Son's House of Love, where you can buy souvenirs and snacks.</p>

<head>Viewpoints</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Observation Point</hi></item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> The observation point is on Chestnut hill that is a moderate to difficult 10 minutes hike (due to steepness, but with paved and dirt roads) from the entrance of Wolmyeongdong. There are benches to rest and to view the center of Wolmyeongdong from this vantage point.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Donggurae Pavilion</hi></item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> The Dongurae (Circle) Pavilion is an easy to moderate 15-minute hike from the entrance of Wolmyeongdong, past the main lawn and on the hill of Donggurae (and hence its name). This pavilion is popular because it is easy to access for most visitors. It is on the way to the Gamran Mountain Pavilion and Gooki Peak.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lake Pavilion</hi></item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> This is the largest of the pavilions in Wolmyeongdong, with pillars of a circumference of more than . It is entirely made without nails, by using only wooden carpentry to connect the roof to the pillars and the base. Through a bridge that spans from the edge of the lake into the middle of the lake, you can walk across to the bottom of the pavilion. Visitors should remove their shoes to preserve the cleanliness of the pavilion. It is a relaxing and tranquil spot for prayer, praise and meditation. You can also access to free wifi from this location.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Rooftop of the Holy Son's House of Love</hi></item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> The Holy Son's House of Love was designed from the exterior to look like a pulpit, and its rooftop is open air and faces the entire heart of Wolmyeongdong. It is an easy 5-minute hike from the entrance, and there are elevators in the building too.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Gamran (Olive) Mountain Pavilion</hi></item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> The Gamran Mountain pavilion sits on the peak of Gamran mountain and offers a view of Wolmyeongdong and the surrounding mountains, to include the largest mountain in the region - Daedun mountains. It can only be accessed by hiking for approximately 30 minutes from the Lake Pavilion. The hike is of an easy-moderate difficulty of about 1.6 km (1 mile) one-way on a clear dirt path lined with trees and views of the areas.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Gooki (Flag) Peak</hi></item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> The Gooki Peak is the furthest peak within Wolmyeongdong and takes about an hour to hike (one-way) from the Lake Pavilion. You will past by the Gamran Mountain pavilion midway in this hiking journey and travellers would usually visit both places in one trip. Along the way, there are numerous scenic spots where you can view the surrounding mountain ranges. The hike is of a moderate-high difficulty of about 3.2 km (2 miles) one way. Be sure to allow enough time before the sunset (2 hours) when you start this hike because there is no artificial lighting on the trails.</item>
</list>
</text>
