<text id="autogum_interview_doc740" title="part7_Randall Munroe, writer of xkcd, talks about the comic, politics and the internet" shortTile="partrandall-munroe" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-09" dateModified="2016-06-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Randall_Munroe%2C_writer_of_xkcd%2C_talks_about_the_comic%2C_politics_and_the_internet" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Yeah. I think very highly of Wikipedia. I think that’s most of the criticisms about it are completely missing the point. The reason Wikipedia is useful is not because it has a similar error rate to Britannica for example. That’s one thing you often see in comparison. I think that a lot of the criticism of Wikipedia misses a key point -- that the way people interact with Wikipedia is fundamentally different from interaction with any other reference source in history.  Wikipedia is a system for pooling information.  It's where you go to find the consensus of interested parties backed up by citation.  Yes, someone can edit an article and cause harm, but someone can also shoot you in the face while you're walking down a street.  It doesn't make walking on streets a broken behavior.  People use Wikipedia, by and large, properly -- as a glance at the collected pool of information on a subject, to figure out what something is or how it works.  It's not a scholarly reference book, and I don't know anyone who treats it like one.</p>
<head id="Politics_and_religion">Politics and religion</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Now we’re going to move on to something fairly controversial, because just I can’t resist.  Religion and politics. You criticized <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Young%20Earth%20creationism">Young Earth creationism</ref> and in the same strip (Comic 258, <ref target="http://xkcd.com/258/">Conspiracy Theories</ref>) make a bug report to God. It's not clear how much the strip represents your own religious views but how much does that one? How much do others? </hi></p>
<p>R: It’s a hard balance. I try to avoid being preachy  because I can just talk endlessly for anything especially when someone is listening to me because it's part of their job. I could go on and on.  I’ve avoided making the comic too personal just to avoid people feeling like they are reading someone else's stuff. They should feel "that could be me." If I were like this is the part that represents me and this isn’t that takes away from some of that. But I don’t think there’s any contradiction there. I think that Young Earth creationism is such a fringe idea that this concept that the Earth is young is not representative of anything that’s real spirituality. That’s a misunderstanding. They are looking at science and then convincing themselves that their ideas are scientific and then really thinking we’re doing science here and deceiving themselves. It seems much more like a delusion than anything to do with the validity of religion. And for making a bug report to God- Einstein would talk about God all the time. It's sort of a device. Einstein didn’t believe in God not in the way we talk about it today. But he’d talk about understanding what God did when he made the universe in looking at physics. That’s sort of the same way I approach that. It’s a convenient device. It’s a way to make a joke or something. At one point I referred to the “the gods” as a multiple thing because that works just as well I feel like.</p>
</text>
