<text id="autogum_academic_doc652" title="Vitamin D Improves Nitric Oxide-Dependent Vasodilation in Adipose Tissue Arterioles from Bariatric Surgery Patients" shortTile="vitamin-d-improves" author="Abeer  M. Mahmoud, Mary Szczurek, Chandra Hassan, Mario Masrur, Antonio Gangemi, Shane  A. Phillips" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6643/11/10/2521/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Obesity and vitamin-D deficiency are two major global public health concerns that affect over one-third of the population. A body mass index of more than 30 kg/m2 is associated with lower serum vitamin-D levels compared with non-obese individuals. Several mechanisms that contribute to the high incidence of vitamin-D deficiency in obese people were suggested. Ultraviolet radiation from sunlight exposure is required for cutaneous production of vitamin D. It was proposed that obese individuals, overall, have suboptimal levels of vitamin D because they tend to participate in fewer outdoor activities and, accordingly, have less exposure to sunlight. Vitamin D is a lipid-soluble vitamin, and it is thought that the lower bioavailability of vitamin D in obese individuals, compared to lean individuals, is due to vitamin-D sequestration within the adipose tissues. Lastly, vitamin-D deficiency may also be due to inadequate dietary intake or malabsorption of vitamin D. Obesity is a well-established risk factor for the development of cardiovascular disease (CVD), and several mechanisms may contribute to this link. However, a role of vitamin-D deficiency in obesity-associated cardiovascular (CV) risk is yet to be established.  </p>

<p>Epidemiological data reported associations between vitamin D deficiency and left ventricular hypertrophy, hypertension, increased arterial stiffness, and endothelial dysfunction. The pathophysiological underpinnings of these associations remain mostly unexplained. The most reliable and convincing evidence for the involvement of vitamin D in the pathogenesis of CVD comes from studies demonstrating an association between vitamin-D deficiency and hypertension. Vitamin-D deficiency is associated with a higher risk for preeclampsia, a condition that is characterized by hypertension. Also, a significant inverse association was reported between vitamin-D serum levels and arterial blood pressure in the elderly. An interventional study demonstrated that one month of vitamin-D intake (1,5000 IU/day) reduced tissue sensitivity to the stimulation of the renin–angiotensin system manifested by improved renal blood flow and reduced mean arterial pressure during an infusion of angiotensin II. Moreover, vitamin-D intake (2000 IU/day) for 14 days in healthy adults reduced augmentation index, a measure of arterial stiffness that contributes to the development of hypertension. </p>

<p>The discovery of vitamin-D receptor (VDR) widened the scope of biological effects that vitamin D plays in human health. VDR is a transcription factor that enters the nucleus upon binding to vitamin D, where it attaches to specific DNA regions and activates the transcription of a myriad of genes that coordinate several biological responses. VDR is widely expressed throughout the human body in almost all cells and tissues, including vascular smooth muscle cells, cardiomyocytes, and endothelial cells. Animal studies found that loss of VDR signaling increased arterial stiffness and elevated systolic and diastolic blood pressure, independent of the renin–angiotensin–aldosterone system. Another study found that VDR knockout mice have increased arterial stiffness through decreased bioavailability of nitric oxide (NO). These and other studies proposed that the leading mechanism for the association between vitamin-D deficiency and CVD is related to endothelial dysfunction and impaired endothelial-dependent NO production.  </p>

<p>Despite this accumulating evidence of the role of vitamin D in vascular function, direct mechanistic evidence of this role in the microvasculature of morbidly obese population and how it might be modified following massive weight loss are largely unexplored. The purpose of the current study is to investigate the effects of vitamin D on the microvasculature isolated from both subcutaneous (SAT) and visceral adipose tissue (VAT) in morbidly obese adults before and after bariatric surgery-induced weight loss. The central hypothesis is that vitamin D would improve microvascular function in obese adults via improving flow-mediated NO production, and this effect would be of a greater magnitude before compared to after weight loss. In our previous work, we found that flow-induced dilation (FID) is impaired in morbidly obese individuals due to an imbalance of NO and H2O2. H2O2 may serve as a compensatory mechanism for vasodilation during pathological conditions such as obesity. Using the proposed ex vivo system in this study, we are able to explore the contributing vasoactive mediators of vitamin-D effects on microvascular function, mainly NO and H2O2.  </p>
</text>
