<text id="autogum_news_doc584" title="Wikinews interviews Spanish Paralympic swimmer María Delgado" shortTile="wikinews-interviews" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-08-09" dateModified="2013-08-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Spanish_Paralympic_swimmer_Mar%C3%ADa_Delgado" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Spanish Paralympic swimmer María Delgado</head>
<figure><caption><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> interviews <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/María%20Delgado">María Delgado</ref>. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:LauraHale">Laura Hale</ref>.</caption></figure><figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/María%20Delgado">María Delgado</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Madrid–Barajas_Airport">Madrid–Barajas Airport</ref> Thursday. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:LauraHale">Laura Hale</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 10, 2013</hi></p>
<p>Thursday at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Madrid–Barajas_Airport">Madrid–Barajas Airport</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> interviewed <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Spain">Spanish</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Paralympics">Paralympic</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Swimming">swimmer</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/María%20Delgado">María Delgado</ref>, who is scheduled to compete at the 2013 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IPC%20Swimming%20World%20Championships">IPC Swimming World Championships</ref> that start on Monday in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Montreal">Montreal</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada">Canada</ref>. Delgado will be 15 when she is to compete in Montreal.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I'm Laura Hale, I'm interviewing María Delgado who is a Spanish swimmer and who is going to the 2013 IPC Swimming World Championships in Montreal, and you have received a lot of press attention from the Spanish press for being the next great Spanish Swimmer, [...] [Do you expect to medal in this tournament or in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2016_Summer_Paralympics">Río</ref>?] ((es))Spanish language: ‍¿Crees que en este campeonato vas a ganar una medalla o futuro a Río?  [Note: The translated question here differed from the one originally asked in English.]</p>
<hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/María%20Delgado">María Delgado</ref></hi>: [laughs] I don't know. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Yo qué sé jajaja.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  The Spanish newspapers say she is the greatest swimmer, she is the next greatest Spanish Paralympic swimmer. Does she feel pressure from the media saying that she is a great swimmer to perform in a really high level? Does she feel pressure to win because the newspapers say it? Spanish newspapers say she is the next great Spanish Paralympic swimmer, that she is going to go to Río.</p>
<hi rend="bold">Translator</hi>: She has also been future with "plan AXA", who bet on young swimmers Paralympics, and has been going at concentrations, which are younger with future have driven a little to fit in the world level of competition. ((es))Spanish language: ‍ ¿si tienes algún [here I'd say: "alguna presión porque"] ... como que eres el futuro porque eres nueva nadadora, si has salido por ejemplo en el periódico en tu pueblo? Bueno, ella ha sido una apuesta también de un plan que hay de AXA, que apuestan por los jóvenes nadadores paralímpicos, y ha estado yendo a concentraciones, a los que son más jovenes con futuro los han impulsado un poquito para que entren en el mundo de la competición a nivel.
<hi rend="bold">María Delgado</hi>: I'm on a plan for young talent, that is preparing for Rio 2016 and has selected us, and now we go to the World Championship. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Estoy en un plan que es de jóvenes promesas, que nos preparan para Río 2016 y ha apostado por nosotros, y ahora vamos al campeonato del mundo.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Because you are 15, how do you [...] balance going to school and competing?</p>
<hi rend="bold">María Delgado</hi>: It's a little difficult but with hard work and effort it's doable. Study in the morning and train in the afternoon. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Es un poco difícil pero con trabajo y esfuerzo se puede conseguir. Estudio por la mañana y entreno por la tarde.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Are you doing school work while you are in Montreal? How does you balance school? How do you do the school at the 15 years old and swim? Because that seems really hard to do both at once. ((es))Spanish language: ‍¿Estás haciendo las tareas escolares mientras se encuentra en Montreal? ¿De qué manera a equilibrar la escuela? ¿Cómo se hace la escuela a los 15 años de edad y nadar? Debido a que parece muy difícil hacer las dos cosas a la vez. ¿Puedes explicar como por ejemplo qué ¿? vas a hacerlo todo normal, no? Que ¿cómo lo compaginas? Que es muy difícil compaginar y entrenar a la vez natación, o sea, nadar y estudiar.</p>
<hi rend="bold">María Delgado</hi>:  It is very difficult to combine and train while swimming, with swimming and studying. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Sí, es difícil pero se puede cerrar y hay veces que no sé cómo lo hago... estudiando, yo qué sé... Nos explica por ejemplo que en la Universidad pues tienes que ir más ¿? ... start very new... que acaba de empezar y todavía no trae ritmo.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Because you're 15 do your parents go with you? Are your parents going to Montreal or are you all traveling solo by yourself?</p>
<hi rend="bold">María Delgado</hi>: With my coaches. My parents aren't going. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Con mis entrenadores. Mis padres no van.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Only with your coach? ((es))Spanish language: ‍¿Sólo con su entrenador?</p>
<hi rend="bold">María Delgado</hi>: Yes. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Sí.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Is it scary to be on your own? Competing against all these 20 year olds and 30 year olds who've been to Paralympic games, or you just go "I'm 15, I can —<hi rend="italic">el Mundo es mío</hi> [the world is mine]"? ((es))Spanish language: ‍¿Tienes miedo o tú vas con todas las ganas de competir con gente mayor?</p>
<hi rend="bold">María Delgado</hi>: I'm not scared and I go eagerly. ((es))Spanish language: ‍No tengo miedo y voy con muchas ganas.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Thank you. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Gracias.</p>
</text>
