<text id="autogum_bio_doc504" title="Abraham van der Doort" shortTile="abraham-van-der-doort" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-05-21" dateModified="2018-04-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abraham_van_der_Doort" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Abraham van der Doort</head><figure><caption><hi rend="italic">Portrait of Abraham van der Doort</hi>, by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Dobson">William Dobson</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Abraham van der Doort</hi> (c. 1575/1580? - June 1640) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dutch_people">Dutch</ref> artist.  As Keeper of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_I_of_England">Charles I</ref>'s art collections, he was the first <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Surveyor_of_the_King's_Pictures">Surveyor of the King's Pictures</ref>.</p>
<p>Van der Doort's careworn face is familiar from a portrait and engravings held by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Portrait_Gallery_(United_Kingdom)">National Portrait Gallery</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London">London</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> but little is known of his early life: indeed, his date of birth is not known with any certainty.  He was probably the son of Peter van Do[o]rt, an engraver of Dutch descent who was working in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hamburg">Hamburg</ref> in the early years of the 17th century,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> a member of a family of Dutch craftsmen that also specialised in the design and manufacture of coins and medals.  Abraham van der Doort probably came to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/England">England</ref> around 1609, a few years after <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_I_of_England">James I</ref> became <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King_of_England">King of England</ref>.  Van der Doort came into the service of Charles' elder brother, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Frederick_Stuart">Prince Henry</ref>.  After Henry's early death in 1612, his collection of paintings, medals, coins and other <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Objets_d'art">objets d'art</ref></hi> was inherited by Charles, and van der Doort accompanied the collection into Charles' service.  After Charles succeeded his father as king in 1625, van der Doort became Charles' <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Groom_of_the_Chamber">Groom of the Chamber</ref>, Surveyor of the King's Pictures; he designed new coins for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_Mint">Royal Mint</ref>.</p>
<p>About 1639, van der Doort compiled a manuscript catalogue of the art collection of the King, described by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ellis_Waterhouse">Ellis Waterhouse</ref> as "the fullest catalogues of their day in Europe."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref>  The catalogue survives in a complete manuscript that was preserved by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elias_Ashmole">Elias Ashmole</ref> and is now held by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bodleian_Library">Bodleian Library</ref>, and in three fair copies of sections, all covered with van der Doort's annotations in a tight crabbed hand.  Under van der Doort's care, and with the guidance of painter-dealers, painter-ambassadors and English painting <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virtuoso">virtuosi</ref></hi>, Charles had assembled what <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oliver_Millar">Oliver Millar</ref>, in editing a modern edition of catalogue, reckoned was the best single English collection of paintings ever made.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Vertue">George Vertue</ref>'s notes on the former Royal Collection were published in 1757, which is the reason that, following its long series of the Vertue notebooks, a collated edition of the four manuscript catalogues was published by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walpole_Society">Walpole Society</ref> as its Volume 37 (1958–60); it was edited by Millar, who later followed van der Doort as Surveyor of the Queen's Pictures. Millar provides the best biography of van der Doort, and details of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Provenance">provenance</ref> of the pictures, many of which had come from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Gonzaga">Gonzaga</ref> inheritance in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mantua">Mantua</ref>, with a commentary on their later history and their attributions.</p>
<p>Van der Doort committed suicide in the summer of 1640, distraught that he may have misplaced one of his master's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portrait_miniature">miniatures</ref>.  Charles' collection was broken up and sold by auction in 1649, after Charles had been executed.</p>
<p>Van der Doort never lost the Dutch accent that is preserved in his copious annotations to the catalogues in his entirely phonetic spelling.</p>
</text>
