<text id="autogum_bio_doc208" title="William Brassington" shortTile="william-brassington" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-03-10" dateModified="2019-09-30" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Brassington" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>William Brassington</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">William Brassington</hi> (1837/1841 – 3 March 1905) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stonemason">stonemason</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sculpture">sculptor</ref> and builder practising in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christchurch">Christchurch</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Zealand">New Zealand</ref> in the late 19th century. His sculptured carving on many of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/City">city</ref>'s unique <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gothic_revival">Gothic revival</ref> public buildings is regarded as some of the finest in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Southern_Hemisphere">Southern Hemisphere</ref>. His work is celebrated around New Zealand and he died when he was around 65</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Brassington was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nottingham">Nottingham</ref>, England, and trained, like his father, to be a stonemason. In 1863 he and his wife Ellen and two daughters emigrated to New Zealand aboard the ship <hi rend="italic">Brother's Pride</hi>. His youngest child died on the voyage. On arrival in New Zealand he set up business in a Christchurch <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cemetery">cemetery</ref> as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monument">monumental</ref> mason. The quality of his work was noticed by the official Provincial Architect <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benjamin_Mountfort">Benjamin Mountfort</ref> who was working on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canterbury_Provincial_Council_Buildings">provincial council chamber</ref> in Christchurch. Mountfort immediately employed Brassington to carve the decorated stonework. The work Brassington executed at the council chamber is considered to be his best. He decorated the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corbel">corbels</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capital_(architecture)">capitals</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arch">arches</ref> with carvings of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flora">flora</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fauna">fauna</ref> indigenous to the province of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canterbury_Region">Canterbury</ref>. In addition was statuary depicting <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen_Victoria">Queen Victoria</ref>, her consort and other great <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Politician">statesmen</ref> and popular heroes of the day. It was also rumoured that depicted amongst the great and the good was Brassington's favourite <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barmaid">barmaid</ref> and an image of himself.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DNZB_Brassington-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Brassington's work at the council chamber established him as a sought after craftsman in the rapidly developing city of Christchurch; he carved the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pulpit">pulpit</ref> at the church of St. John the Baptist in Latimer Square on 1866, and the font at Flaxton Church on 1867. He was commissioned to work on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ChristChurch_Cathedral,_Christchurch">Christchurch Cathedral</ref>. However, when the project ran out of funds and came to a temporary halt, Brassington turned to building as a source of income, and worked on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lyttelton_Harbour">Lyttelton Harbour</ref> and many other projects at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Teddington,_New_Zealand">Teddington</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allendale,_New_Zealand">Allendale</ref>.</p>
<p>One of his buildings was the Church of The Holy Innocents, Christchurch, which was completed in 1869. The acclaim with which this building was greeted led him to be chosen to work again with Mountfort completing the last stage of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canterbury_Museum,_Christchurch">Canterbury Museum</ref> in the 1870s, and again at the museum to build the great <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portico">portico</ref> in 1876.</p>
<p>Brassington's partnership with John Kennington won the duo the prestigious commission of building the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Castle">castle</ref>-like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lyttelton_Timeball_Station">Lyttelton Timeball Station</ref>, built of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Volcano">volcanic</ref> red stone, and which was completed in 1876. Following this construction he was again employed by Mountfort on the restarted Christchurch <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cathedral">cathedral</ref>, although here his work is not documented.</p>
<p>In 1889 Brassington emigrated again, this time to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Melbourne">Melbourne</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Australia">Australia</ref>, where he seems to have abandoned his masonry career in favour of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Warrandyte,_Victoria">Warrandyte</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gold_mining">goldfield</ref>. He died of an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Human_mouth">oral</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tumour">tumour</ref> in 1905 and was buried at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Footscray,_Victoria">Footscray</ref> cemetery, Australia.</p>
</text>
