<text id="autogum_voyage_doc138" title="Lincoln Park (New Jersey)" shortTile="lincoln-park-new" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=148491" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Lincoln Park (New Jersey)</head>


<p>Lincoln Park is a borough in <ref target="Morris%20County%20%28New%20Jersey%29">Morris County</ref>, <ref target="New%20Jersey">New Jersey</ref>. It is the easternmost municipality in Morris County, and it has a population of about 10,521 people.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>The community that is now Lincoln Park has existed since colonial times. This small community further grew with the construction of the Delaware, Lackawanna, and Western Railroad's Boonton Branch (present-day Montclair-Boonton Line). It was formerly part of neighboring Pequannock. The borough was founded as a township under the name <hi rend="bold">Beavertown</hi> on March 11, 1922. The town was reincorporated as the borough of Lincoln Park in February 26, 1925. It was named after President Abraham Lincoln.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>U.S. Route 202 is the primary road through the borough, linking it with <ref target="Montville%20%28New%20Jersey%29">Montville</ref> and <ref target="Wayne%20%28New%20Jersey%29">Wayne</ref>. Comly/Ryerson Road link the borough to Pequannock, while Chapel Hill/Pine Brook/Two Bridges Road link it to <ref target="Fairfield%20%28New%20Jersey%29">Fairfield</ref>. Lincoln Park can also be easily accessed from Interstates 80 and 287, as well as U.S. Route 46 and New Jersey Route 23 using these roads.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>NJ Transit provides service from Mondays to Saturdays on the <hi rend="bold">871</hi> bus route to Willowbrook Mall in <ref target="Wayne%20%28New%20Jersey%29">Wayne</ref> and <ref target="Morristown">Morristown</ref>. Buses in each direction arrive four times per day. One can transfer to an express bus bound for <ref target="Manhattan/Theater%20District">Port Authority Bus Terminal</ref> at Willowbrook.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Lakeland Buses</hi> also provides occasional service on weekdays, with buses heading directly to <ref target="New%20York%20City">New York City</ref> in early mornings, and buses on the return trip arriving in the late evening.</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>The <hi rend="bold">Montclair-Boonton Line</hi> has a station in the borough. This is not the best way, however, as trains are limited to weekday rush hour service, and a transfer is required further down the line in order to reach New York Penn Station. This will not be a problem however if you are arriving from Hoboken. Additionally, the station is not wheelchair accessible due to its odd layout. <hi rend="bold">Mountain View</hi> station, although it has equally lousy service, is also close to Lincoln Park (and ADA-compliant, too!). However, it is relatively far from the center of the borough.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>Driving by car is the only quick way to get around. Walking around the center of the borough is easy, as it is relatively small in size. Walking up certain roads can be quite a workout however, as they cross over <hi rend="bold">Hook Mountain</hi>, which is part of the Watchung Mountain group. There are multiple bus stops around, but bus service is <hi rend="bold">rare</hi>, making it an impractical way to get around.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">John Dods Tavern</hi>, 8 Chapel Hill Rd (Next to the main business district). This old tavern was built in 1770, and it has since become a dentist's office. It was mentioned as a landmark for routes in <ref target="http://www.revolutionarywarnewjersey.com/new_jersey_revolutionary_war_sites/towns/lincoln_park_nj_revolutionary_war_sites.htm">letters</ref> sent to George Washington by his allies.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Two Bridges</hi>. This area was once referred to as the "two Bridges", or "the Fork of Passaic", in Revolutionary War letters; one of the bridges is today used as the main route linking the borough with <ref target="Fairfield%20%28New%20Jersey%29">Fairfield</ref>. The area directly adjacent to it was also used as a Revolutionary War campsite.</item>
</list>

 

<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Walk along the old Morris Canal.</hi> The historic Morris Canal formerly ran through the borough, and its remnants are still scattered along its former path. The proper way to walk along the Morris Canal in Lincoln Park is to take the bus to or park your car near the bridge over the Pompton River. Then, walk along U.S. Route 202 until you reach the Main Street intersection. Cross Main Street then proceed to walk along Beaverbrook Road. Turn left when you reach the entrance to the condos and you will notice a large board demarcating the canal's path. Cross the road with care, and walk the remainder of the right-of-way via a portion of the Morris Canal Greenway. This will take you to Plane 10 East, located on the Montville border.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Noches de Colombia</hi>, 466 Boonton Turnpike, ☏ +1 973-832-7720 . Colombian restaurant with catering and car delivery. Serves great Pandebono.</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>
<p>There are no places to stay in Lincoln Park. Therefore, you must stay in other towns. There are hotels in Fairfield and Wayne where Lincoln Park can be easily reached.</p>

<head>Cope</head>
<p>The local newspaper is The Star-Ledger, along with others. The town is served by radio and TV stations mostly in New York.</p>

<head>Go next</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Paterson">Paterson</ref></hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Newark">Newark</ref></hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Jersey%20City">Jersey City</ref></hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="New%20York%20City">New York City</ref></hi></item>
</list>
</text>
