<text id="autogum_interview_doc885" title="part10_Author Amy Scobee recounts abuse as Scientology executive" shortTile="partauthor-amy-scobee" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-10-11" dateModified="2015-12-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Author_Amy_Scobee_recounts_abuse_as_Scientology_executive" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>If one gets in trouble while on the RPF program, they can be sent to the RPF’s RPF, which is a mandatory two week sentence and could take longer. One is segregated from the rest of the RPF and suffers twice the penalties of a regular RPF member, works longer hours, gets no pay and experiences other such restrictions. Men and women are not treated differently – as a Scientologist, they think they are not their body but spiritual beings, able to endure anything. You are expected to be able to perform any duty, no matter the excuse. I did all sorts of degrading jobs as a member of the RPF's RPF, including hand shoveling a literal mountain of fermented and maggot-infested garbage for days. Several of these stories are included in my book so one can get the details of what really goes on to "handle" staff members in Scientology.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> During chapter 7, "Scientology Celebrities", you recount how you were ordered to eat "rations of beans and rice for breakfast, lunch and dinner", until you had filled a vacant WDC post. You write that you worked for two months in this capacity, attempting to fill the position and submitting 46 different recommendations. How did such a diet and living conditions affect you during this time? How was your overall health, well-being, and energy levels as compared to that when consuming a healthy full-balanced diet?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS</hi>: There is some writing from L. Ron Hubbard that rice and beans, eaten together, form a complete protein. So that was the justification of why it was okay to put people on such a meager diet as a form of punishment – they can't starve to death eating that. I learned to add things like mayonnaise to make it taste different and slide down easier. Looking back, I can't believe I went through with it – or 99% of everything else I endured, but you're in the frame of mind that any trouble can be overcome because one has to keep their eye on the overall big picture of helping to salvage the planet.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> While serving as executive over the Personnel Division at Commodore's Messenger Organization International, you write that you were given the task of "a special project in LA to establish the Tom Cruise household with staff who were all Scientologists". After interviewing individuals without telling them what they would be hired for, you note that – supervised directly by Shelly Miscavige, David Miscavige's wife and personal assistant – you narrowed down submissions which were then given to Tom Cruise's assistant, Andrea, to hire. Did these members of Scientology that were selected by Scientology management and then hired by Tom Cruise's assistant report back to the chain of command through David Miscavige, or to Tom Cruise, or both?</hi></p>
</text>
