<text id="autogum_interview_doc786" title="part1_Eurovision &amp;apos;73 winner Anne Marie David discusses her four-decade career and the Contest, past and present" shortTile="parteurovision--winner" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-02-15" dateModified="2012-02-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eurovision_%2773_winner_Anne_Marie_David_discusses_her_four-decade_career_and_the_Contest%2C_past_and_present" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You became very well-known in 1972 when you played Mary Magdalene in <hi rend="italic">Jesus Christ Superstar</hi>. How did you get the part? If you had to audition, what were the auditions like, and were you nervous?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AMD</hi>: At the time I played in the musical comedy "The Me Nobody Knows," originating from the United States. Unfortunately the promotion for this presentation was not excellent and it remained confidential. My artistic director at the time, Pierre Hebrard, knew that the casting of <hi rend="italic">Jesus Christ Superstar</hi> was finished but that the role of Mary Magdalene had not yet been definitively [cast]. He asked the production [company] to audition me. I practiced the beginning of the song for a quarter of an hour with Anthony Bowles, the musical director, then I sang the song. They asked me to learn the entire song for the next morning, and to come back to sing it. I did so... I sang the song the next day and in the end, they said OK, we'll take you... I learned that for this role the production auditioned 600 girls! I was stressed out <hi rend="italic">after</hi> the audition... when I realized the challenge. Before I had not been very relaxed [or] comfortable, but I mostly wanted to [sell the song]... The show must go on, no?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You're from the south of France, and some of the French Wikipedians remarked, "But she doesn't have any accent when she's singing!" Did you have to take vocal classes or was it natural for you to sing without an accent?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AMD</hi>: I'm a big fan of accent imitations... accents are also music, and in private I often tell jokes with accents. It's the actress in me... but in fact singing in French for me is singing without an accent; it's a natural thing... I make no particular effort [to remove an accent].</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> After your success in the theatre, you were victorious at Eurovision in 1973. Luxembourg usually selected their entrants internally, so how did RTL [<hi rend="italic">Editor's note: The state broadcaster of Luxembourg</hi>] become aware of you? How were you approached by them, and did you ever consider not participating in the Contest?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AMD</hi>: I had the opportunity to have the director of programs and the director of special programming for RTL [watching me] the night of the premiere of <hi rend="italic">Jesus Christ Superstar</hi>. They saw me and were enthused by my performance. When they asked me that night if I would accept to represent Luxembourg in 1973, I only asked if it wasn't a problem [for them because] they'd won with Vicky Léandros that year (1972). They told me no, that for them winning several times in a row was not a problem... so I said <hi rend="italic">yes</hi> with <hi rend="italic">pleasure</hi>!</p>
</text>
