<text id="autogum_interview_doc807" title="part0_Frank Messina: An interview with the &amp;apos;Mets Poet&amp;apos;" shortTile="partfrank-messina" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-03" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Frank_Messina%3A_An_interview_with_the_%27Mets_Poet%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Frank Messina: An interview with the 'Mets Poet'</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 3, 2007</hi></p>
<figure rend="Frank Messina by David Shankbone.jpg"></figure>In the early <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Olympic%20games">Olympic games</ref>, athletes used to run a mile and then recite a poem.  The first poet-in-residence of an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barnsley%20F.C.">English football team</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ian%20McMillan%20(poet)">Ian McMillan</ref>, remarked that football chants are like huge tribal poems.  Generally, though, sport and poetry have never seemed natural companions in human enterprise.  Until the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20York%20Mets">New York Mets</ref> baseball team suffered in 2007 arguably the worst collapse in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Major%20League%20Baseball">Major League Baseball</ref> history.  To describe the anguish fans felt, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20New%20York%20Times">The New York Times</ref></hi> turned to a poet, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frank%20Messina">Frank Messina</ref>.  "Nothing was really representing the fan's point of view," Messina told <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref> reporter <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref> in an interview.  "There's a lot of hurting people out there who can't express what happened."
<p>And to those who read the <hi rend="italic">Times</hi> last Saturday, Messina wants you to know his father never apologized for raising him as a Mets fans.  "I never asked for his apology, and he never apologized, nor did he owe us one.  I was misquoted in the New York Times."  </p>
<p>Messina's parents taught him about opposite ends of the spectrum of life.  "My mother was supportive even when I made mistakes.  She taught me to never give up no matter what vocation you choose in your life."  Whereas Messina's mother taught him to never give up, his father taught him how to die with grace.  He passed away from cancer in 2005.  "I got to see a man who accepted his fate. He was like the Captain of the Titanic. My mother was also calm. I was the one freaking out inside. I saw someone who had acknowledged his own demise, accepted it, and died at home. He was a tough old guy. It takes a lot to accept that; it takes a very strong person.  Some of the special moments toward the end was sitting with him and watching baseball games."</p>
<p>It is baseball that has garnered Messina attention now.  He has performed in 32 countries and 40 states, and in 1993 he founded the band Spoken Motion, a spoken word band.  What is striking about Messina is that his work has branched two worlds that often don't interact: downtown coffeehouse denizens of poetry and the denizens of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shea%20Stadium">Shea Stadium</ref>.  It is Frank Messina who has personalities as diverse as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joe%20Benigno">Joe Benigno</ref>, the archetype of the New York sportscaster at WFAN, reflecting on love and poetry. "No one would question a poet writing about love for a woman," said Benigno, "but when you’re a fan of a team, the emotional attachment is even stronger...."   Benigno sounded similar to avant-garde writer and musician <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20Amram">David Amram</ref>, who said Messina's poems paint "the stark beauty of the streets, the pain of 9/11, the joy of everyday life, the mysteries of love all fill the pages of this book. It's a feast of images and sounds that stay with you."  </p>
</text>
