<text id="autogum_voyage_doc107" title="Nitra" shortTile="nitra" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=24662" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Nitra</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Nitra</hi> is in <ref target="Slovakia">Slovakia</ref>. It is a beautiful old historic city, with a population of almost 80,000. </p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>The ancient Nitra, ruled by mighty kings and princes once in the past, is nowadays a modern centre of culture and economy in western Slovakia.</p>

<p>Thanks to its dynamic cultural life, you can meet here a number of artists from the field of theatre, creative arts, modern or classical music and experience the unforgettable feeling of the present cultural spirit. Events like Theatre Festival of Nitra, Fascine Carnival, Academic Nitra, Cultural Summer in Nitra or various music festivals will lead you into the world of culture, world of experience. The amount of precious well-preserved buildings and statues builds up the unique colouring of the city with a breath of nostalgia. On the other hand, the hotels with latest equipment and restaurants offering the wide scale of home and international cuisine will convince you about the traditional Slovak hospitality.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>The is situated in the city center, near the and has a regional importance.</p>

<p>Buses connect Nitra with other cities, also foreign.</p>

<p>The best connection from the capital city, Bratislava is by bus links called "Žltý expres" (Yellow express). There are several different bus companies which travel from Bratislava to Nitra (some of which end in Nitra, many of which go further inland).</p>

<p>It is also possible to travel from Bratislava to Nitra by train, but this will entail changing trains at least once (e.g. in Nové Zámky or Leopoldov) and will generally take longer and be more expensive than taking the bus. You may also have to wait quite a while when you change trains as the schedules from Bratislava to e.g. Nové Zámky are not well synchronised with those of the local train from there to Nitra.</p>

<head>By buses</head>
<p>Nitra has a very good public transport. Buses run between each town, city center and tourist attractive places.</p>

<head>By taxi</head>
<p>There are many Taxi services like CD-TAXI, MOJE TAXI, CITY TAXI, TAXI OK and WFR TAXI.</p>

<head>See</head>
<p>The castle (Hrad) is in the old town.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Nitra Castle</hi> (Nitriansky Hrad).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Small Seminary</hi> (Malý seminár).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Marian Sculpture</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Diocesan Library</hi> (Diecézna knižnica).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">St. Emeram´s Church</hi> (Katedrála Sv. Emerána).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Statue of Corgoň</hi> (Socha Corgoňa).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sts. Peter and Paul Church and Monastery of the Franciscan</hi> (Františkánsky kostol Sv. Petra a Pavla).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Region House</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Town House</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Andrej Bagar Theatre</hi> (Divadlo Andreja Bagara).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Synagogue</hi> (Synagóga).</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Park "Sihoť"</hi> (Park Sihoť).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Zobor Mountain</hi> (Zobor).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Pedestrian Zone</hi> (Pešia zóna).</item>
</list>


<head>Learn</head>
<p>Nitra has many elementary and high schools and two universities - Slovak University of Agriculture and University of Constantine, the Philosopher.</p>

<head>Eat</head>
<p>There are many restaurants situated in all parts of city. Many of them are in the center. There are also two McDonald's, first in shopping center "Mlyny" and second near shopping center "Galéria" in which is also TESCO.</p>

<head>Connect</head>
<p>NISYS (Tourist center) - +421377410906</p>

<head>Stay safe</head>
<p>Nitra is a very safe city, there is a city police, which ensures the safety also at night.</p>

<head>Go next</head>
<p>From Nitra you can choose a many following places or cities. To beautiful <ref target="Bojnice">Bojnice</ref> (part of the city Prievidza) you can use train connection. To the lovely spa town Piešťany or capital city Bratislava you can use buses.</p>
</text>
