<text id="autogum_interview_doc693" title="part1_RuPaul speaks about society and the state of drag as performance art" shortTile="partrupaul-speaks" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-06" dateModified="2019-02-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/RuPaul_speaks_about_society_and_the_state_of_drag_as_performance_art" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What did that signify to you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RP:</hi>  What it showed me is that the mentality in Atlanta is that much of their history means nothing.  For so many years they did a good job preserving.   Don’t get me wrong, I’m not a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/preservationist">preservationist</ref>.  It’s just an interesting observation.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  In 2004 when you released your third album, <hi rend="italic">Red Hot</hi>, it received a good deal of play in the clubs and on dance radio, but very little press coverage.  On your blog you discussed how you felt betrayed by the entertainment industry and, in particular, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/gay%20press">gay press</ref>.  What happened?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RP:</hi>  Well, betrayed might be the wrong word.  ‘Betrayed’ alludes to an idea that there was some kind of a promise made to me, and there never was.  More so, I was disappointed.  I don’t feel like it was a betrayal.  Nobody promises anything in show business and you understand that from day one.</p>
<p>But, I don’t know what happened.  It seemed I couldn’t get press on my album unless I was willing to play into the role that the mainstream press has assigned to gay people, which is as servants of straight ideals.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you mean as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/court%20jester">court jesters</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RP:</hi>  Not court jesters, because that also plays into that mentality.  We as humans find it easy to categorize people so that we know how to feel comfortable with them; so that we don’t feel threatened.  If someone falls outside of that categorization, we feel threatened and we search our psyche to put them into a category that we feel comfortable with.  The mainstream media and the gay press find it hard to accept me as...just...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Everything you are?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RP:</hi>  Everything that I am.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It seems like years ago, and my recollection might be fuzzy, but it seems like I read a mainstream media piece that talked about how you wanted to break out of the RuPaul 'character' and be seen as more than just <hi rend="italic">RuPaul</hi>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RP:</hi>  Well, RuPaul is my real name and that’s who I am and who I have always been.  There’s the product <hi rend="italic">RuPaul</hi> that I have sold in business.  Does the product feel like it’s been put into a box?  Could you be more clear?  It’s a hard question to answer.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That you wanted to be seen as more than just RuPaul the drag queen, but also for the man and versatile artist that you are.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RP:</hi>  That’s not on target.  What other people think of me is not my business.  What I do is what I do.  How people see me doesn’t change what I decide to do.  I don’t choose projects so people don’t see me as one thing or another.  I choose projects that excite me.  I think the problem is that people refuse to understand what drag is outside of their own belief system.  A friend of mine recently did the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Oprah%20Winfrey%20Show">Oprah</ref></hi> show about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/transgender">transgendered</ref> youth.  It was obvious that we, as a culture, have a hard time trying to understand the difference between a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/drag%20queen">drag queen</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/transsexual">transsexual</ref>, and a transgender, yet we find it very easy to know the difference between the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American%20League">American baseball league</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National%20League">National baseball league</ref>, when they are both so similar.  We’ll learn the difference to that.  One of my hobbies is to research and go underneath ideas to discover why certain ones stay in place while others do not.  Like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adam%20and%20Eve">Adam and Eve</ref>, which is a flimsy <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/fairytale">fairytale</ref> story, yet it is something that people believe; what, exactly, keeps it in place?</p>
</text>
