<text id="autogum_whow_doc579" title="Follow Gandhian Principles Without Feeling Restricted" shortTile="follow-gandhian-principles" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2006-11-27" dateModified="2019-10-01" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Follow-Gandhian-Principles-Without-Feeling-Restricted" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Follow Gandhian Principles Without Feeling Restricted</head><p>Gandhian principles can sometimes feel too restrictive, especially in the present day. While ideally someone looking to follow Gandhian principles should follow them to the T, sometimes it can feel overly and lead to you abandoning Gandhism altogether. This wikiHow will teach you how to apply the teachings of Gandhi in modern life in a non-restrictive manner, without losing their essence.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Learning About Gandhi's Principles</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><figure rend="Follow Gandhi's Principles Step 1.jpg"></figure>Learn about Gandhi's principles. There are 6 principles that Mahatma Gandhi followed:
<list type="unordered"><item>Truth: learning from your own mistakes and conducting experiments on yourself.</item>
<item>Nonviolence: nonviolent resistance connected in a way to religion.</item>
<item>Vegetarianism: carved in the Hindu and Jain traditions in India.</item>
<item>Brahmacharya: spiritual and practical purity.</item>
<item>Simplicity: giving up unnecessary spending.</item>
<item>Faith: belief in a higher power and that all religions are real and are equal.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Follow Gandhi's Principles Step 2.jpg"></figure>Learn about the differing circumstances under which you and Gandhi lived. These will help you alter the principles so you can live by them without feeling restricted.
<list type="unordered"><item>He lived in India from 1869 to 1948, mainly adhering to these principles in the '30s and '40s.</item>
<item>We live in a society that is more technologically advanced, is more materialistic, and doesn't fight for the same reasons (we have more opportunities to do what we want to do)</item></list></item></list>
<head>Applying Gandhi's Principle Without Feeling Restricted</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><figure rend="Follow Gandhi's Principles Step 3Bullet1.jpg"></figure>Apply the principle of Truth. Fight your own inner demons, fear and insecurities.  Everyone is unique in this world and therefore, one should not compare with others.  Be honest with yourself of who you are and what you want. If you think there is something to fix, then fix it.</item>
<item><figure rend="Follow Gandhi's Principles Step 3Bullet2.jpg"></figure>Practice nonviolence. Control your temper and also your thoughts. What we think, we become and therefore if you always are thinking of hurting someone or feeling extremely angry at someone, those are the vibes you'll be giving to others. Best way to be nonviolent is to think positively and believe that whatever happens is for a good reason. Nonviolence and forgiveness are the higher calling of virtue.</item>
<item><figure rend="Follow Gandhi's Principles Step 3Bullet3.jpg"></figure>Resist eating meat. Not everyone can resist meat, but you can control your consumption. For health reasons, avoiding eating a lot of red meat is a good idea.</item>
<item><figure rend="Follow Gandhi's Principles Step 3Bullet4.jpg"></figure>Avoid premarital sex. Many of us want to get married and have children or be intimate with someone. Therefore, practicing brahmacharya might not be possible. However, you ought not think of the opposite sex as an object. You could also wait to be intimate with someone till after marriage.  Gandhi's life is known to not be a good example of sexual purity, as he used his position to sexually exploit young women. This fact, along with his views about racial purity, help us to view Gandhi as a flawed man. However, we cannot let the imperfections of men and women deter us from pursuing high ideals and sound principles. Principles stand on their own merit, regardless of any individual's life or level of moral uprightness.</item>
<item><figure rend="Follow Gandhi's Principles Step 3Bullet5.jpg"></figure>Avoid consuming more than you need. Life in western countries tends to be quite fast. Do you need the latest fashion clothing or can you wear the clothes you already have? Do you need 50-100 pairs of shoes?  Do you need the latest gadgets? Do you need a brand new BMW? Simplicity doesn't mean foregoing all your desires, but not buying something right away or something you don't really need. Simplicity also means being happy with what you are given and have.</item>
<item><figure rend="Follow Gandhi's Principles Step 3Bullet6.jpg"></figure>Have faith. You don't have to believe in God, but it is good to believe that everyone has equal inherent value - you are no less or more than someone else. It is about knowing your values, ethics and morals.  Faith is not following others blindly - especially when someone else is doing something that your heart says is not right.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Read books on Mahatma Gandhi.</item>
<item>Have patience because it is easy to learn a bad habit, but hard to let go of one.</item>
<item>Understand what you want out of life and know who you are; in this way you will be following these principles.</item>
<item>Watch the film 'GANDHI' (English film) on Mahatma Gandhi and 'Lage Raho Munna Bhai' (Hindi film)</item>
<item>See how these principles can fit in your lifestyle and make modifications to your lifestyle where you see it requires</item>
<item>You can also modify the principles without losing the meaning behind what Gandhi was trying to teach.</item>
<item>Not all 6 principles need to be followed exactly the same way because your desires and wants also matter.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you have decided to change a part of your life, you will need to be patient because there are days when you might fail and then you will need courage to start again.</item></list>
</text>
