<text id="autogum_interview_doc199" title="part0_BDSM as business: Interviews with Dominatrixes" shortTile="partbdsm-business" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-28" dateModified="2008-01-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BDSM_as_business%3A_Interviews_with_Dominatrixes" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>BDSM as business: Interviews with Dominatrixes</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, October 28, 2007</hi></p>
<figure rend="S&amp;M Dungeon 9 by David Shankbone.jpg"></figure>Whether the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American%20Civil%20War">Civil War</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World%20War%20II">World War II</ref> or the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraq%20War">Iraq War</ref>, it can be challenging to face how conflict penetrates the psyche of a nation and surfaces in the nuances of life.  There are thousands—if not millions—of individuals who indulge in fantasies others would deem perverse that have their nascence in some of the darkest moments of human history.  It is possible someone you know pays a person to dress like a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nazi%20Germany">German Nazi</ref> to treat them like a “dirty Jew”, or to force them to pick cotton off the floor like a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American%20slavery">slave</ref>.  
<p>An S&amp;M dungeon is a place where these individuals act out such taboos.  Businesses that operate to meet their needs are often hidden, but they do exist and are typically legal.  The clients want to remain confidential for fear of ostracism in their respective communities.  As <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sigmund%20Freud">Sigmund Freud</ref> wrote, "Anyone who has violated a taboo becomes taboo himself because he possesses the dangerous quality of tempting others to follow his example." </p>
<p>Last week <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> published the first in a two part series on the BDSM business: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BDSM_as_business:_An_interview_with_the_owners_of_a_dungeon">an interview with Bill &amp; Rebecca, the owners of Rebecca’s Hidden Chamber</ref>.  This week we publish the second part: an interview with three dungeon employees, Mistress Alex, Mistress Jada and Mistress Veronica.  In their world, BDSM is a game, a harmless pursuit of roleplaying exercises that satiate the desires of the tabooed.  These Dominatrixes are the kind of women men fantasize about, but they all look like they could be babysitting your children this Saturday night.  Most likely, they will not be.</p>
<p>Mistress Alex has a distinctive sheen when <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref> walks into the room.  Her moist skin cools quickly from the blow of the air conditioner she stands in front of.  Just having finished an hour and a half session, she is dressed in a latex one-piece skirt and matching boots.  Mistress Jada, a shapely Latina dressed in red, joins the conversation and remains throughout.  When Alex needs to tend to a client, Mistress Veronica, who looks like she would be as comfortable teaching kindergarten as she would "tanning a man's hide", takes over for her.  </p>
<p>The interview was neither sensational nor typical, but what you read may surprise, repulse, or even awaken feelings you never knew you had.  Below is David Shankbone's interview with three Dominatrixes.    </p>
<head id="Starting_out">Starting out</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">David Shankbone:  How did you get started as an S&amp;M Mistress?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  I’m from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/California">California</ref> and I started out by playing in various <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fetish%20club">fetish clubs</ref> and I had different play partners.  I just kind of dabbled in my personal life. When I moved to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20York%20City">New York</ref> a few years ago, I was doing the same thing with friends and I realized I was getting bored hanging out with the same people all the time—they became good friends, but I met another <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Professional%20dominant">pro-dom</ref>.  I was talking to her about it and realized I could end up experiencing so many different things in a place like this.  And it’s true.  I meet so many different people who are into all these different things.  I’m all about variety.</p>
</text>
