<text id="autogum_whow_doc121" title="Check Internet Speed" shortTile="check-internet-speed" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-01-11" dateModified="2019-06-13" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Check-Internet-Speed" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Check Internet Speed</head><p>This wikiHow teaches you how to see the upload speed and download speed of your Internet connection, as well as the speed of the connection between your computer and your router. Knowing your Internet speed can help you figure out what you can do with your internet connection.  </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Running an Internet Speed Test</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Go to the Google Speed Test page. Open a Google search page by going to <ref target="https://www.google.com">https://www.google.com</ref> in a web browser or open the Google app on your device and type  into the search field. This will bring up an "Internet speed test" window at the top of the Google search results. <figure rend="Check Internet Speed Step 1 Version 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can use this method on a computer, phone, or tablet.</item>
<item>This method will use Google's built-in internet speed testing tool. There are other alternatives you could use, such as <ref target="https://www.fast.com">Fast.com</ref>, if you prefer an alternative.</item></list></item>
<item>Click . It's a blue button in the bottom-right corner of the "Internet speed test" panel. <figure rend="Check Internet Speed Step 2 Version 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wait for the speed test to complete. Google will measure your Internet connection's upload speed, download speed, and latency. <figure rend="Check Internet Speed Step 3 Version 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Review the test results. In addition to telling you whether your Internet qualifies as "fast" or "slow", Google measures three aspects of your Internet's speed: <figure rend="Check Internet Speed Step 4 Version 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Mbps download</hi> - The number of megabits per second your connection is allowing you to download.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Mbps upload</hi> - The number of megabits per second your connection is uploading.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Latency</hi> - The number of milliseconds it takes for your Internet connection to respond to a command (e.g., a search query or a page loading).</item></list></item></list>
<head>Checking Internet Speed on Windows</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Make sure your computer is connected to your router. To check your Internet speed from your computer's settings, you must connect your computer to your router <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Set_up_Ethernet">via Ethernet cable</ref>. <figure rend="Check Internet Speed Step 5 Version 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Open Start . This icon is in the bottom-left corner of the screen. <figure rend="Check Internet Speed Step 6 Version 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . It's in the bottom-left corner of the Start window. <figure rend="Check Internet Speed Step 7 Version 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click  Network &amp; Internet. It's in the top row of settings on the Settings page. <figure rend="Check Internet Speed Step 8 Version 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . This tab is on the left side of the window. Doing so will open your Ethernet settings. <figure rend="Check Internet Speed Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . It's in the upper-right side of the window. <figure rend="Check Internet Speed Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Double-click the Ethernet connection. You'll see this monitor-shaped icon at the top of the Network Connections window. <figure rend="Check Internet Speed Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Review the "Speed" value. It's near the bottom of the "Connections" section of information on the Ethernet Status window. The number here (e.g., "90.0 Mbps") represents the speed of the connection between your computer and the router. <figure rend="Check Internet Speed Step 12.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Checking Internet Speed on Mac</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Make sure your computer is connected to your router. To check your Internet speed from your computer's settings, you must connect your computer to your router <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Set_up_Ethernet">via Ethernet cable</ref>. <figure rend="Check Internet Speed Step 13 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Open Spotlight . It's in the top-right corner of your Mac's screen. <figure rend="Check Internet Speed Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Type "network utility" into Spotlight, then press . Doing so will open the Network Utility app. <figure rend="Check Internet Speed Step 15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the  tab. It's on the far-left side of the top of the Network Utility window. <figure rend="Check Internet Speed Step 16 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select your Ethernet connection. Click the box below the "Select a network interface for information" heading, then click your Ethernet connection's name. <figure rend="Check Internet Speed Step 17 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Look at the number next to "Link Speed". You'll see something like "100 Mbit/s" here, which would mean the speed of the connection between your computer and your router is 100 megabits of data per second. <figure rend="Check Internet Speed Step 18 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Troubleshooting</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Switch to a wired connection. If your wireless connection is experiencing significant lag, then you may need to connect to a wired connection (usually through Ethernet) in order to boost your Internet performance speed. <figure rend="Check Internet Speed Step 19.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Restart your Wi-Fi access point. Sometimes, routers or other devices that can access wi-fi may need to be restarted in order to fix any performance issues caused by a glitch or broken connection. <figure rend="Check Internet Speed Step 20.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Connect to another network. In order to check if the problem is a network or just your device, connect to another network you have access to and check that network's Internet speed. <figure rend="Check Internet Speed Step 21.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Run a malware scan on your device. In some instances, a slow Internet speed could mean your device is being slowed down by malware in its system. To remedy this, install an antivirus program with a malware scanner included in it. <figure rend="Check Internet Speed Step 22.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Your Internet's true connection speed is often much lower than your router's maximum speed. Using Ethernet allows you to take advantage of your router's speed.</item></list>
<list type="ordered"><item><list type="unordered"><item>Benchmarks for common features include: 5 Megabits per second for HD streaming and 90 kilobits per second for VOiP calling</item></list></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Your Internet speed will never exceed either your router's maximum speed or your Internet plan's maximum speed--whichever speed is lower.</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
