<text id="autogum_whow_doc307" title="Store Fresh Mushrooms" shortTile="store-fresh-mushrooms" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2017-03-16" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Store-Fresh-Mushrooms" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Store Fresh Mushrooms</head><p>Mushrooms can be one of the hardest vegetables to store because of how quickly they can absorb too much moisture and start to go bad. Keeping mushrooms in their original packaging for as long as possible, storing loose mushrooms in a paper bag or paper towels, and freezing mushrooms can all help keep them fresher longer.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Using the Original Packaging</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Keep the mushrooms in their original packaging. If you’re not going to use your mushrooms right away, it’s okay to leave them in their original cardboard and plastic wrap packaging. The plastic wrap usually has holes which allow excess moisture to escape without drying the mushrooms out. <figure rend="Store Fresh Mushrooms Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Rewrap the mushrooms with shrink wrap. If you do need a few mushrooms right away, make the smallest hole possible in the original plastic covering. Once you’ve taken the mushrooms you need out of the package, rewrap the area you removed them from with plastic wrap. <figure rend="Store Fresh Mushrooms Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Refrigerate them. After you’ve brought the mushrooms home, refrigerate them in their original packaging. Putting fresh mushrooms in the refrigerator slows down the growing process and can prevent them from going bad quickly. Using this technique should keep your mushrooms fresh for about a week. <figure rend="Store Fresh Mushrooms Step 3.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Using a Paper Bag</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Put mushrooms into a paper lunch bag. If you don’t want to store your fresh mushrooms in their original packaging, you can instead store them in a paper bag. The size of the bag can vary depending on how many mushrooms you’re storing, but brown paper lunch bags are generally the best choice. <figure rend="Store Fresh Mushrooms Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can also wrap them in damp paper towels before you place them in the bag.</item></list></item>
<item>Leave the paper bag open. Don’t fold over the top of the bag of mushrooms. Leaving it open keeps the level of moisture balanced. The bag will trap some moisture. Leaving it open prevents your mushrooms from soaking up too much moisture. <figure rend="Store Fresh Mushrooms Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Store the bag in your refrigerator. You should store the paper bag of mushrooms in your refrigerator, preferably in one of the crisper drawers. This keeps the scent and taste of other food from getting into your mushrooms. Crisper drawers are also designed to keep fresh vegetables fresher for longer. Using this method should keep your mushrooms fresh for a week to 10 days. <figure rend="Store Fresh Mushrooms Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Freezing Mushrooms</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Clean the mushrooms first. If you don't plan to use your fresh mushrooms within a week or so, you'll want to freeze them to preserve them. Start by rinsing the mushrooms under water and then letting them dry in open air. You can spread them on a paper or tea towel to catch the excess water. <figure rend="Store Fresh Mushrooms Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Brush with towel or mushroom brush. Once the mushrooms are relatively dry, brush them with a paper towel or mushroom brush. This gets some of the more stubborn dirt off of them. <figure rend="Store Fresh Mushrooms Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Slice and sauté the mushrooms. Slice your mushrooms into even pieces before you sauté them. Using an egg slicer can give you uniform pieces. Sauté them in one to two tablespoons of olive oil with some salt and pepper to taste. <figure rend="Store Fresh Mushrooms Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Let the mushrooms cool. Once you’ve finished cooking the mushrooms, let them cool before you freeze them. Spread them out on a cookie sheet in a single layer until they are cool to the touch. <figure rend="Store Fresh Mushrooms Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Freeze in plastic resealable bags. Once the mushrooms have cooled, store them in resealable plastic bags and freeze them. Cooking before freezing them prevents them from absorbing too much moisture when they defrost. <figure rend="Store Fresh Mushrooms Step 11.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Storing in a paper bag can make them shrivel, but it won’t hurt them and you can still use them to cook.</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
