<text id="autogum_academic_doc621" title="Decontamination of T-2 Toxin in Maize by Modified Montmorillonite Clay" shortTile="decontamination-t" author="Bunmi  K. Olopade, Solomon  U. Oranusi, Obinna  C. Nwinyi, Isiaka  A. Lawal, Sefater Gbashi, Patrick  B. Njobeh" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6651/11/11/616/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Maize is grown worldwide, with the United States, China, and Brazil ranked as the leading producing countries contributing approximately 563 of the 717 million metric tonnes per year. However, maize, like other cereals, is susceptible to contamination by mycotoxins, including T-2 toxin. T-2 toxin is common in grains, including oats, soybeans, rice, barley, maize, and wheat. <hi rend="italic">Fusarium langsethiae</hi> and <hi rend="italic">F. sporotrichioides</hi> are some of the <hi rend="italic">Fusarium</hi> species that infect crops in the field and storage during which time they produce T-2 toxin. This toxin belongs to the family of mycotoxins known as the trichothecenes produced mainly by <hi rend="italic">Fusarium sporotrichioides, F. graminearum, F. poae,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">F. culmorum</hi> and causing diarrhea, inflammation, and emesis. They can be grouped into Type A, B, C, and D, with T-2 toxin belonging to Type A trichothecenes, the most toxic group of trichothecenes. Trichothecenes are among the mycotoxins associated with human and veterinary diseases. Like T-2, all trichothecenes have a common tetracyclic sesquiterpenoid 12,13-epoxytrichothec-9-ene ring system together with an epoxide group located at their C12, C13 positions, which accounts for their toxicity. T-2 toxicity is induced via oxidative stress-mediated deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) damage and apoptosis. The chemical structure of T-2 toxin is shown in <figure>Figure 1</figure>. </p>

<p>T-2 toxin is a recognized inhibitor of protein synthesis, which occurs by the binding of peptidyl transferase, present in the 60S ribosomal subunit. T-2 poisoning in man results in alimentary toxic aleukia (ATA). The toxin also causes ulcers as well as necrosis in the digestive tract, hemorrhagic inflammation, and dystrophy in the brain, heart, kidney, and liver. The walls of blood vessels are damaged, provoking hemorrhagic diathesis. T-2 also affects animals, with monogastric animals being more susceptible than ruminants. This is because ruminants, such as cattle, possess a rumen where de-acetylation and de-epoxidation of the toxin take place, thus limiting its toxicity. The toxin also affects poultry, causing ulcerative and necrotic lesions as well as oral lesions, thereby leading to refusal of feed. Studies have revealed that T-2 toxin is easily absorbed in the intestinal tract and is toxic to the organs of animals affecting the digestive system and liver of animals. </p>

<p>Decontamination processes involving physical, biological, and chemical methods are frequently required for the removal, destruction, and decontamination of mycotoxins. Biological approaches include the activity of microorganisms (algae, bacteria, filamentous fungi, and yeasts) against mycotoxins using antibiosis or competition for nutrients and space. Chemical approaches help to degrade mycotoxins by various gases, aldehydes, oxidizing agents, acids, and bases. The EC supports the application of physical methods and sorting procedures for decontaminating mycotoxins. However, neither the mixing of batches to reduce mycotoxins to levels below the maximum tolerable limits nor decontamination using chemicals is permitted by the European Union. Physical methods of detoxification include irradiation (gamma or ultraviolet irradiation), solvent extraction, inactivation by heat, and the use of mineral adsorbents (mainly clays). The disadvantages of food irradiation are the high costs involved and loss of vitamins (avitaminosis), while inactivation by heat may lead to a loss in nutritional properties of the commodities. The use of mineral adsorbents, such as clay, is a cheaper and safer alternative to these methods, revealing their mycotoxin decontamination properties. Clays also serve as anti-caking agents in animal feed, and they are highly regarded as effective mycotoxin binding agents in animal feeds by enterosorption. Enzymes such as oxidoreductases and hydrolases have also been thoroughly explored in the mitigation of mycotoxins in animal feed. </p>

<p>Montmorillonite clay has pharmaceutical applications where it serves as an excipient in drugs for oral or topical use. The cytotoxicity of montmorillonite clay is low both in vitro and in vivo. A study by Wei et al. showed that modified hydrated sodium calcium aluminosilicate (HSCAS) adsorbent could be used in vivo to reduce toxicity induced by T-2 toxin. Therefore, clay can be safely expended in the storage of cereal crops for mycotoxin decontamination purposes. Montmorillonite, when compared with other nanoclays, has an advantage because it is abundant and environmentally friendly. Each layer of montmorillonite has a lateral dimension of 200–600 nm. It is made up of an octahedral sheet sandwiched between two tetrahedral sheets. The arrangement of the sheets is such that the silicon oxide tetrahedron (SiO4) shares three out of four of its oxygen atoms with the central octahedral sheets. Among various clay minerals such as kaolinite, illite, and chlorite, montmorillonite is more ideal for adsorption studies since it has a high cation exchange capacity, swelling capacity, and high surface area. </p>
</text>
