<text id="autogum_interview_doc578" title="part3_Interview with Brazilian blogger Ricardo Serran Lobo" shortTile="partinterview-brazilian" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-01-13" dateModified="2012-05-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Brazilian_blogger_Ricardo_Serran_Lobo" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
Wikinews: Does the "mensalão" continue?
<p>Ricardo Lobo: Not in the exact manner it was managed before, however I believe that it still exists. The election of Aldo [Aldo Rebelo (PCdoB)] for the Presidency of Congress is an example.</p>
Wikinews: Do you believe Lula did know about the mensalão?
<p>Ricardo Lobo: Certainly he knew and he is part of the ruling and creation of the scheme. Otherwise he will enter to History as the most ignorant among all of the Brazilian presidents.</p>
Wikinews: What was the role of the ex-minister and deputy José Dirceu, in you opinion?
<p>Ricardo Lobo: Operator, chief of government and chief of its strategies. He and Lula created the scheme of "mensalão". He, Lula, Hugo Chávez and Fidel Castro created a scheme to turn out South America as a huge continent for the world-wide left. The first step was Lula in Brazil, next Evo Morales in Bolivia, and so on. Jose Dirceu was a part of that.</p>
Wikinews: Do you think that the corruption scandal will end "much ado about nothing" or "pizza" as it is said in Brazil?
<p>Ricardo Lobo: Actually there are a lot of "pizzas". One has already being served: the Vote Buying CPI. They are still trying to serve the others. But I think that it will end in nothing; they, the politicians, are very cooperative with each other.</p>
<p>Ricardo Lobo: They [the deputies] know that their days are numbered, mainly the ones from big cities. As for the ones from  provincial and small cities;  they don't even know what a computer is and they didn't realize the severity of the problem. They think that if their name didn't appear in the newspaper, their names are not in any place. Perhaps I'll create a site closer to the elections, when I will put the names of all incompetent ones from the National Congress.</p>
Wikinews: What will end in nothing? The investigations or the scandal?
<p>Ricardo Lobo: The investigations will continue until an acceptable limit is reached by the major parties: the Workers Party and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brazilian%20Social%20Democracy%20Party">Social Democracy Party</ref>. Then they must stop when it is "enough" for the population.</p>
<head id="Popular_reaction">Popular reaction</head>
Wikinews: In the streets, how do ordinary Brazilian people see this issue?
<p>Ricardo Lobo: Everybody is disappointed because people thought that everything (corruption, politicians etc) would change. And it really changed, but for the worse. The amateur behaviour of the communications team of President Lula contributed very much to this also; it lacked professionalism.</p>
Wikinews: Are the people who live in Brasilia too upset?
<p>Ricardo Lobo:  Nobody gets very upset about the government in Brasilia. Most of the town population works for the federal government, so this is a unique city, really. And it is beautiful.</p>
</text>
