<text id="autogum_academic_doc315" title="Optical Performance Analysis of Single Flow Through and Concentric Tube Receiver Coupled with a Modified CPC Collector Under Different Configurations" shortTile="optical-performance" author="Javed Akhter, Syed  I. Gilani, Hussain  H. Al-Kayiem, Muzaffar Ali" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/21/4147/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Compound parabolic concentrating collectors are non-imaging devices which have great potential to supply sustainable solar thermal energy in the medium (90–300 °C) temperature range. CPC collectors, generally, don’t need continuous tracking mechanisms for lower concentration range (below 3×) and only seasonal or intermittent adjustments are required for medium concentration range (3–10×). The ability of CPC collectors to collect diffuse radiation provides an additional advantage, especially in tropical regions where the percentage of diffuse radiation is relatively higher. Owing to the promising benefits of these collectors, many researchers have designed and evaluated CPC collectors for various low-to-medium temperature applications, including industrial process heat, solar heating and cooling, water treatment and purification, methanol reforming and hydrogen production, building-integrated water heating systems and photovoltaic/thermal (PV/T) hybrid systems. </p>

<p>After the introduction of CPC as a potential candidate for solar energy collection, many research studies have been conducted in this field. Gallagher and Winston reviewed basic principles of the non-imaging optical design of CPCs for some selected arrangements of evacuated and non-evacuated solar collectors. Derrick et al. analyzed different concentrators with non-evacuated tubular absorbers and compared annual energy collection for East-West (E-W) and North-South (N-S) orientations. Aguilar-Jiménez et al. also developed and experimentally tested a CPC collector integrated with a non-evacuated concentric tube receiver. Stationary installation of the collector in an E-W direction exhibited almost 6% better thermal performance than the N-S orientation. The coefficient of heat losses was also 10% higher in the case of E-W arrangement, probably due to the elevated temperature of the bared absorber. It is worth noting that thermal losses from the non-evacuated receivers of concentrating collectors are increased due to higher surface temperatures resulting from solar radiation concentrated on the smaller area of the absorbers. Thus, the benefit of radiation concentration is compromised by increased thermal losses. However, conduction and convection losses can be minimized by employing evacuated tube receiver (ETR) while radiation losses can be suppressed by applying selective coatings at the absorber surface which can also increase energy absorption. An external CPC coupled with counterflow absorber with cylindrical fin enclosed in an evacuated glass tube was designed, developed, modeled and tested by Kim et al.. Acceptance half angles of 34° and 60° were selected for stationary installation in E-W and N-S directions, respectively. The experimental results revealed that N-S arrangement showed better performance at relatively lower temperatures (&lt;165 °C) while E-W installation was best for higher temperatures (with 40% efficiency at 200 °C), probably due to higher concentration ratio for this arrangement. Earlier, Balkoski also analyzed three different evacuated tube receivers coupled with external CPC. Acceptance half angles of 34° and 60° were selected for E-W and N-S installations respectively. During the clear sky conditions, E-W arrangement of all collectors demonstrated superior performance at higher temperatures (&gt;140 °C) as compared to N-S alignment which relatively performed better at lower temperatures. Thermal performance of N-S oriented collectors was slightly better than E-W installation during cloudy or hazy conditions. Nkwetta et al. modified a heat pipe array by integrating it with an internal CPC and compared the thermal performance with another array comprising of an internal CPC coupled with direct flow absorber for both evacuated and non-evacuated options. Evacuated receivers paired with CPC demonstrated better performance than other arrangements. In another study, an internal CPC coupled with direct flow absorbers was integrated with heat pipe array as outlet manifold and was experimentally tested in both N-S and E-W configurations. The experimental results of N-S arrangement exhibited better performance than E-W installation. However, the optical performance was only evaluated for transverse angles of incident radiations and the results for longitudinal direction were not available for comparative optical analysis. </p>

<p>Energy collection in a CPC collector greatly depends on the absorption of concentrated radiations at the absorber surface which is affected by configuration, material and surface properties of collector components as well as manufacturing and alignment accuracy. Ray tracing is a very useful tool to precisely estimate the flux distribution and amount of solar energy available at the receiver. Many research studies have successfully applied this method to evaluate the effect of different parameters on the optical performance of solar collectors. Chen et al. used ray-tracing method to analyze the optical performance of an E-W oriented CPC collector coupled with tubular receiver for different truncation heights of reflectors and tilt angles. Terron-Hernandez et al. also applied the ray-tracing technique to investigate the energy availability at the receiver surface for static and multi-position setups in E-W installations. A past literature review illustrates that stationary installation of a CPC collector is one of the main features to eliminate the need for complex and costly tracking mechanisms. In addition, the orientation also predominantly affects its optical performance which in turn influence the thermal behavior. Therefore, detailed optical performance evaluation under different configurations is imperative for precise performance prediction, selection, and installation to achieve the optimum yield throughout the year. </p>
</text>
