<text id="autogum_interview_doc455" title="part9_US presidential candidate Duncan Hunter speaks to Wikinews" shortTile="partus-presidential" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-12-12" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_presidential_candidate_Duncan_Hunter_speaks_to_Wikinews" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Essentially you would want to revoke Massachusetts' ability to have gay marriage?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  Yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> So that would be anti-States rights to a degree?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  Well, that's your argument.  But my point is that when I said I'm for states rights, I'm also for recognizing the fact that there are some issues in which the nation has an interest.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Why do you think gay marriage is one of those issues?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  I think that's a center piece, the most important institution in our country, is the marriage.  The traditional marriage.  Its most important role is as the protector of children.  I think central to the American family, which is the most central institution in the country, is the marriage between a man and a wife.  I think we need to <hi rend="italic">elevate</hi> that traditional marriage.  Support it, promote it, elevate it.  Not devalue it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> How does gay marriage devalue marriage?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  I think that it devalues it by rendering it less than what it was, by making it something that is not a function of the Judeo-Christian tradition, which most of our laws are built on.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Although we are not a Christian nation--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  As you start to devalue the traditional marriage, people would ask why can't it simply be a contract between a number of people?  What's special about two people?  What's special about a man and a wife?  I think there is something special about a man and a wife, and in a way the traditional marriage is different than many institutions.  It is not a governmentally-formed institution.  It is an institution that has a religious element to it.  It's a part of a our Judeo-Christian tradition.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> The argument against that is should government be involved in it <hi rend="italic">at all</hi> then.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  But it is recognized, and protected, by government.  So that makes it an unusual institution.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> What about when two Muslims marry, then?  Because that's not Judeo-Christian.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  Well, I'm saying that was the basis of the traditional marriage in our society that made it an important institution in this society.  That doesn't mean it is restricted of one religious group, but that it has been a function of Judeo-Christian religion and has become thereby a part of our laws.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Since it exists in all societies, just because it is practiced by a Judeo-Christian society does that make it a Judeo-Christian institution or a human institution?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  Well, I think you can argue that, but--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You don't believe that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  No, I said you could argue that, but in this society it has been a function of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Judeo-Christian%20religions">Judeo-Christian religion</ref>, although it is supported similarly by other religions, and by diverse numbers of ethnic groups.  On the other hand, that's not a reason to <hi rend="italic">not</hi> support it, to not elevate it, and not to honor it.</p>
</text>
