<text id="autogum_voyage_doc415" title="Boston/Fenway-Kenmore" shortTile="bostonfenwaykenmore" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=4385" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Boston/Fenway-Kenmore</head>

<p>The <hi rend="bold">Fenway-Kenmore</hi> neighborhood is named after Kenmore Square, and after the Fens, both of which it encompasses. Kenmore Square is the area's dynamic urban center. This is where trains arrive and shops light up in an effort to entice passing customers. High above, the Citgo sign (now a historical landmark) keeps a watchful eye on new arrivals as they make their way through these congested crossroads.</p>

<head>Neighborhoods</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kenmore:</hi> The area is quite urban, but all the green space makes it feel much more livable than you might think. Like many other areas of Boston, Kenmore is in the middle of a building boom. The closeness of the parks and gardens help to balance the city and nature experiences.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Fens:</hi> Just south and away from the square lies the hushed Fens, a study in contrasts. The Muddy River meanders through rustling reeds and shady, sloping lawns and gardens. Rustic stone bridges and benches offer a place to linger, to admire the water and all its inhabitants. The Fens also work to separate Kenmore from the sprawling medical complex, Longwood Medical Area. Turkeys have even been known call the place home. If you see one, watch out, they can be mean!</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Longwood:</hi> An extremely dense cluster of hospitals and schools.</item>
</list>


<head>By public transit</head>
<p>In this part of town the Green line will usually be your best bet, and <hi rend="bold">Kenmore</hi> is the station to know. The <hi rend="bold">B</hi>, <hi rend="bold">C</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">D</hi> Green line branches all stop here, and a large glass bus depot hovers above. It's also the closest stop to the Fenway Park. From here the B line continues outbound to <hi rend="bold">Blandford Street</hi>, <hi rend="bold">BU East</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">BU Central</hi> before entering <ref target="Boston/Allston-Brighton">Allston</ref>. While the D branch passes through <hi rend="bold">Fenway</hi> before entering the independent town of <ref target="Brookline">Brookline</ref>. The <hi rend="bold">E</hi> branch is great for visiting area museums, it stops at <hi rend="bold">Symphony</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Museum of Fine Arts</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Longwood</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Brigham Circle</hi> stations.</p>

<p>The Orange line shares the <hi rend="bold">Ruggles</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Massachusetts Avenue</hi> stations with several other neighborhoods, but you won't find these stops quite as helpful. The E branch of the Green line is closer to top sights, however, the Orange line can be a good alternative if the E line is experiencing service issues. Ruggles also serves as a stop for Commuter Rail lines headed to <hi rend="bold">Providence/Stoughton</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Franklin</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Needham</hi>. Another Commuter Rail station (especially popular on game days) is <hi rend="bold">Yawkey</hi>, which serves the <hi rend="bold">Framingham/Worcester</hi> line. It's quite close to Fenway Park as well.</p>

<p>By far the most popular bus route is the <hi rend="bold">#57</hi>. Running from Kenmore Square down Comm Ave, into Allston and eventually ending in <ref target="Watertown_%28Massachusetts%29">Watertown</ref>. Also leaving from Kenmore, the <hi rend="bold">#60</hi> and <hi rend="bold">#65</hi> run less frequently into Brookline, while the <hi rend="bold">#8</hi> and <hi rend="bold">#19</hi> take you through the Longwood area and the <ref target="Boston/South_End">South End</ref> via Ruggles. The <hi rend="bold">CT2</hi> and <hi rend="bold">#47</hi> busses can be picked up in Boston University, and take you over the BU bridge into Kendall and Central squares in <ref target="Cambridge_%28Massachusetts%29">Cambridge</ref>. The <hi rend="bold">#39</hi> also runs constantly down Huntington Ave taking you to either inbound to <ref target="Boston/Back_Bay-Beacon_Hill">Back Bay</ref> or outbound to <ref target="Boston/Jamaica_Plain-Mission_Hill">Mission Hill</ref>. Ruggles is a also a major bus hub, fanning lines out citywide.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>For those with deep pockets and endless patience, take the Kenmore Square/Fenway exit from Storrow Drive and follow signs to your destination. Don't even look for on street parking, go right for a garage. You're looking at around $15-20 an hour to park, and on game days expect to be gouged $100 or more for parking, if it's even available in the first place. The twisting roads, congested traffic, and aggressive drivers should all be steering you towards forgoing your four wheels and taking the T instead.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Museum of Fine Arts</hi> (MFA), 465 Huntington Ave (T: Museum of Fine Arts), ☏ +1 617-267-9300 . W-F 10AM-10PM, Sa-Tu 10AM-5PM. As the fourth largest museum in the US, the Museum of Fine Art is known for its impressive assortment of French Impressionist paintings as well as its extraordinary collection of ancient Egyptian, Greek, and Roman art. The MFA also has one of the largest collections of Japanese art outside of Japan. A new modernist Art of the Americas Wing was completed in 2010, architected by Norman Foster. A visitor could simply rush through the highlights in a few hours, or linger all day and take it all in properly. The museum also has a great collection of early American art, including the portrait of George Washington used on the dollar bills you might find in your wallet right now. $25, seniors and students $23. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Isabella Stewart Gardner Museum</hi>, 25 Evans Way (T: Museum of Fine Arts), ☏ +1 617-566-1401 . Tu-Su 11AM-5PM. Not your typical museum experience. Modeled after a 15th century Venetian palazzo, the museum displays Mrs. Gardner's evocative home as it was when she lived here. She collected many masterworks, unappreciated at the time, and displayed them in a most unconventional manner. The juxtaposition of artworks from different cultures and time periods still delights visitors today. While the museum contains works by famous artists like Rembrandt and Velazquez, the main attraction is not in any particular work, but in how each room is laid out: Not only the paintings and tapestries, but also the furniture and architecture in every corner of the building are valuable works of art. Gardner's will stipulates the works of art must remain in her original arrangement. This is the reason one wall remains blank, after an unbelievable art heist in early 1990. Thirteen pieces were stolen, valued at over $500 million dollars, the works of art remain missing to this day. $15 adult, $12 senior, $5 student. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Massachusetts Historical Society</hi> (MHS), 1154 Boylston Street (T: Hynes Convention Center), ☏ +1 617-536-1608 . M-Sa 10AM-4PM. Founded in 1791, the Massachusetts Historical Society is the nation's oldest historical society. The collections of the MHS bring alive the stories of America's past through a series of changing exhibitions and public programs that are free and open to the public. Thomas Jefferson's handwritten copy of the Declaration of Independence is a particularly significant piece in their collection. Many famous people sit on the board of directors, including professor Henry Louis Gates, Jr., historian Doris Kearns Goodwin, and director Ken Burns. Free. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Warren Anatomical Museum</hi> (Countway Library of Medicine), 10 Shattuck Street (T: Brigham Circle), ☏ +1 617-432-6196 , ✉ chm@hms.harvard.edu . M-F 9AM-5PM. This small exhibition is tucked away on the 5th floor of Harvard Medical School's Countway Library of Medicine. It was designed by Mr. Warren in the mid 1800s to teach his medical students about anatomy. The real highlight here—among the charts, specimens and 19th century medical instruments—is the skull of Phineas Gage. Phineas improbably survived 12 years after a large iron bar was driven through his brain. Free. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Panopticon Gallery</hi> (Hotel Commonwealth), 502c Commonwealth Ave (T: Kenmore), ☏ +1 781-718-5777 . Tu-Sa 9AM-3PM. Founded in 1971, Panopticon Gallery is one of the oldest galleries in the United States dedicated solely to fine art photography. The gallery specializes in 20th Century American Photography and emerging contemporary works. Check their calendar for up to date information on their current exhibition. They also carry many interesting, hard to find, fine art books in their store.</item>
</list>
</text>
