<text id="autogum_interview_doc733" title="part0_Randall Munroe, writer of xkcd, talks about the comic, politics and the internet" shortTile="partrandall-munroe" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-09" dateModified="2016-06-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Randall_Munroe%2C_writer_of_xkcd%2C_talks_about_the_comic%2C_politics_and_the_internet" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Randall Munroe, writer of xkcd, talks about the comic, politics and the internet</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 4, 2008</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Randall%20Munroe">Randall Munroe</ref> is the writer of the popular webcomic <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/xkcd">xkcd</ref>. The comic is known for its geeky humor and minimalist drawing style that generally uses stick figures. Munroe worked as a contractor for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NASA">NASA</ref> before writing xkcd full time in 2006. </p>
<p>Wikinews reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:JoshuaZ">Joshua Zelinsky</ref> interviewed Munroe at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vericon">Vericon</ref>, Harvard's annual science fiction convention.</p>
<head id="Interview_with_Randall_Munroe">Interview with Randall Munroe</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">So could you tell us a little about yourself and xkcd?</hi></p>
<p>RM: xkcd is a webcomic that I started while I was in the middle of more productive things, school and work, that sort of by accident turned into a big thing and eventually became what I did professionally. I quit my job and got out of school and started drawing pictures on the internet. A lot of math and computer people like it, science people. It's sort of nerdy in general.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">So, you have a somewhat non-standard style rule for typing out "xkcd" which I know has caused great consternation on Wikipedia and elsewhere.</hi></p>
<p>RM: Well, the first thing is, it started off as a screename and an irc nick, where I’m very used to seeing it all lowercase. There are a lot of trendy things, from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/e.e.%20cummings">e.e. cummings</ref>, the poet, up through businesses that take that sort of thing. It is a big problem for starting sentences. If you want to start a sentence with “xkcd” it seems very wrong not to capitalize it. But I really grew to dislike capital X, lower case “kcd” because that made it seem like a word or a name more than a string of letters. The whole purpose is that it is a really abstract string. Capitalizing it is sort of saying something about it. If you’re used to treating abstract strings in programming, changing case is not a trivial thing. It's changing what the string is. So when it is in its canonical form, that’s the real xkcd, the other forms look wrong to me. So but on the other hand, I try not to make things too hard on people so I say “ok, all lower case is preferred if you want to capitalize, I prefer all caps. Mixed case is my third and least favorite choice” But to some extent that’s just style. Not for any particularly important reason. </p>
<head id="The_comic">The comic</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">When did you realize you had a genuinely successful webcomic?</hi></p>
<p>RM: When it first started out there was a brief flurry of people when <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cory%20Doctorow">Cory Doctorow</ref> linked to me with  Boing Boing and it had only been up for a couple of weeks then, but “whoa there are lot of people reading this. This is a cool feeling. I like. It's neat seeing so many people respond and laughing and it makes me want to write more”. That was really the turning point so then I did it for a little while. I stopped for that winter, 2005-2006, and then started doing it again, and at that point I was picking up readers gradually. It was continual slow, sort of exponential climb. And from then on, it was just a matter of ok, we’ve hit a hundred readers a day, ok we’ve hit 500. and then a thousand. And at some I, you know, realized “whoa this is a lot of people.” But it sort of sneaks up on you. </p>
</text>
