<text id="autogum_voyage_doc283" title="Government Camp" shortTile="government-camp" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=13090" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Government Camp</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Government Camp</hi> is a city in <ref target="Oregon">Oregon</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Government Camp is a small community located on the shoulder of <ref target="Mount%20Hood">Mount Hood</ref> in the Mount Hood national forest. Mt Hood's alpine village was established in 1849 when a mounted Cavalry division was forced to abandon wagons, equipment and draft animals, because heavy snows made conditions impassable. The town was from then on referred to as "government camp" by subsequent emigrants crossing the cascades into the Willamette Valley. Now the town is a destination for recreation and out door activities, best known as the summer time hub for alpine skiing. The local ski area boasts the longest season in North America with 400+ inches of snow year on top of a glacier, lifts are open through September.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>An hours drive from Portland. Take I-84 east to exit 16, turn right off the exit and follow road to the intersection of hwy 26. Turn left on 26 and continue for 40 miles. The turn off for government camp is the loop road on your left at the flashing light. </p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>Government Camp is a small community. Walking is the best mode of transportation in town. There is a shuttle service in the winter that serves Ski Bowl and Timberline, offering transportation between both ski areas and into town. Raz transportation offers bus service in the winter from Portland to Mt Hood Meadows ski area.</p>

<head>See</head>
<p>The Government Camp cultural museum, on the east side of town on the loop road has a exhibits and information about the history of the community.</p>
<p>The <ref target="Oregon%20Trail">Oregon Trail</ref> interpretative center kiosk is directly across the street and has historical information about the first people to come across the pass via the Barlow trail.</p>

<head>Do</head>
<p>In the winter there are plenty of snow related activities near by. You can ski from Timberline lodge 4+ miles into town via the glade or alpine trails. There is a shuttle service that runs in the winter to get you back to the top, or hitching a ride from the many travelers on there way up to timberline lodge is also a popular mode of transport. There are 4 ski areas that are in the vicinity. Timberline, Ski Bowl, Mt Hood Meadows, Summit.</p>
<p>Summer offers many opportunities for hiking and camping. The Pacific Ridge trail comes through town, going north to Canada and south to Mexico.The local trails connect to a network of trails that cover the entire mountain including the 40 mile loop that stretches around the mountain at the 4000/6000ft level.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mt. Hood Adventure Park at Skibowl</hi>. - located in Government Camp</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>
<p>There are a few ski shops in town. Vallians, Mountain Tracks</p>

<head>Eat</head>
<p>Charlie's Mountain View. The Ratskeller, Ice Axe grill, Huckleberry Inn, The Taco Shoppe</p>

<head>Drink</head>
<p>Charlies, Ratskeller, Beer Stube @ Ski Bowl, Brewery</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Charlies Mountain View</hi>, Government Camp loop road. Charlie's is great road house/ ski bar in the center of town. There is also a restaurant. Drinks are cheap and there is a lot of local buzz. $.</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>
<p>Mt Hood Inn, Huckleberry Inn, Collins Lake, Vacation Rental, Timberline</p>
</text>
