<text id="autogum_interview_doc093" title="part20_Wikinews interviews Indiana State Senator Mike Delph" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-03-26" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Indiana_State_Senator_Mike_Delph" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>So we were both supportive of that move, and, you know, as in life, you take positions just like when I did my press conference a couple weeks ago. I decided to do a press conference in the center of the rotunda of the Indiana State House, and I did that going into it knowing there would be consequences. That's part of leadership.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Bayes: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tim%20Durham">Tim Durham</ref>, who is now serving a 50-year sentence for running a Ponzi scheme in Indiana, was a major donator to Republicans, including your campaign. Former Governor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mitch%20Daniels">Daniels</ref> for instance received almost $200,000 dollars. You were the first to give money back donated by Durham in 2011 after he was charged, which was $10,000 dollars. However you kept money donated by <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BP">BP</ref> after the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deepwater%20Horizon%20spill">Deepwater Horizon spill</ref> in 2010. What kind of money do you think should be given back, and what kinds do you think are alright to keep?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MD</hi>: You know, it's interesting, because I got introduced to Tim Durham in, I want to say September or October — I want to say it was October of 2005. It was right before my special caucus or special election for my caucus for the replacement of Murray Clark. Governor Daniels was hosting a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republican%20Governors%20Association">Republican Governors Association</ref> fundraising event at Obsidian headquarters, and that was my first introduction to Tim Durham. And then I have a dear friend of mine who went to high school with him down in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seymour,%20Indiana">Seymour</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jackson%20County,%20Indiana">Jackson County</ref>. I did not know Tim well. I met him a couple times, but my friend Tim Motsinger — who I'd known through politics and Marion County used to be a deputy with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marion%20County%20,%20Indiana">Marion County</ref> Sheriff's Department for Jack Cottey — encouraged me to reach out to him, and I did on a couple occasions, and he wrote me two checks for $5000 dollars.</p>
<p>When the whole fair finance deal was coming out, and I started learning about that, the bankruptcy trustee actually sent out a list, or made a list of people that Durham had made contributions to, asking for voluntary returns of that money. Making the argument that it wasn't his money to donate, it was the retiree's money. I was not on that list. I didn't know about the list. When I found out about the news story, I reached out on my own to the bankruptcy trustee, and said, "Hey, Tim gave me $10,000 dollars, I'd like to return it, what do I need to do?" And they were shocked. They couldn't believe it because they were trying so hard to get all this other money that you mentioned back and they were not getting much cooperation. So. Tor me I felt it was the right thing to do. You know, I pray for Tim Durham. I think that all men have sinned and fallen short of the glory of God. I also believe only one man walked this Earth without sin and his name was not Mike Delph. And so I felt it was the right thing to do to give the money back, and I did that.</p>
</text>
