<text id="autogum_bio_doc326" title="Hannah Twynnoy" shortTile="hannah-twynnoy" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-09-10" dateModified="2019-10-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hannah_Twynnoy" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Hannah Twynnoy</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Hannah Twynnoy</hi> (1669/70-1703) is the first person to have been killed by a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tiger">tiger</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Early_Modern_Britain">Britain</ref>, as attested to by a formal contemporary source.</p>
<p>Twynnoy, by repute and according to a memorial plaque now lost, was an early 18th-century <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barmaid">barmaid</ref> working in The White Lion <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_house">public house</ref> in the centre of the English <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Market_town">market town</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malmesbury,_Wiltshire">Malmesbury</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wiltshire">Wiltshire</ref>.</p>
<p>All that remains from the time, to corroborate the narrative of her death, is her <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gravestone">gravestone</ref>, in a corner of the churchyard of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malmesbury_Abbey">Malmesbury Abbey</ref>.</p>
<head>Gravestone</head>
<p>Her gravestone records her name and death at the age of 33 on 23 October 1703, with a relatively long, evocative poem which reads:</p>
<p>In bloom of Life</p>
<p>She's snatchd from hence,
She had not room
To make defence;
For Tyger fierce
Took Life away.
And here she lies
In a bed of Clay,
Until the Resurrection Day.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-thisiswilts-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Plaque recorded in a local history</head>
To the memory of Hannah Twynnoy. She was a servant of the White Lion Inn where there was an exhibition of wild beasts, and amongst the rest a very fierce tiger which she imprudently took pleasure in teasing, not withstanding the repeated remonstrance of its keeper. One day whilst amusing herself with this dangerous diversion the enraged animal by an extraordinary effort drew out the staple, sprang towards the unhappy girl, caught hold of her gown and tore her to pieces.
<p>Recorded by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_museums_in_Wiltshire">Athelstan Museum</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Historian John Bowen has found a local history with a more detailed account of the death as, it states, placed on a plaque on the wall of the parish church in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hullavington">Hullavington</ref>, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Village">village</ref> 5 miles (8km) from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malmesbury,_Wiltshire">Malmesbury</ref>.  The plaque (see box for wording) that appeared to have been installed soon after her death, in the first years of the 18th century, was recorded in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Victorian_period">Victorian period</ref> by a local historian and may since have been sold, melted down or stolen.</p>
<head>Oral history</head>
<p>The common thread of such stories by word of mouth from generation to generation, matches exactly the plaque, almost always with less formal wording, stating that Hannah Twynnoy was a barmaid working at a pub called the White Lion in Malmesbury (8 Gloucester Street, later converted to a private house) in 1703 when a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Menagerie">menagerie</ref> arrived to set up in the pub's large rear yard. Among the animals there was included a tiger, which Hannah was warned against upsetting. She liked bothering the animal until one day it got tired of it and mauled her. Hannah did not survive.</p>
<head>Unsolved aspects of the death</head>
<head>Wealth or pity?</head>
<p>Poetic <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Epitaph">epitaphs</ref> on gravestones were popular at the turn of the 18th century, but generally only for the wealthy and celebrated.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-thisiswilts-1">[1]</ref> A gravestone and a plot in the churchyard of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malmesbury_Abbey">Malmesbury Abbey</ref> for any woman, who could not have been a priest or a priest's wife, would have been costly, even without engaging the services of a poet. The identity of the patron who paid for her tombstone and plot remains a mystery, although they may have been donated by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church_of_England">church</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vestry">vestry</ref>.</p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>Her connection with the village of Hullavington, which kept family records at this time, seems anomalous. Her sole connection comes from a later local historian giving the wording and location of a plaque.</p>
<p>The parish registers and Bishops transcripts for Malmesbury contain no entry, between 1635 and 1700, for anyone named Twynnoy.
However, the Malmsbury parish register for October 24, 1703, (burials), states:
Hannah Twynney kild by a Tygre at ye White Lyon.
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Enduring legacy</head>
<p>In 1993 a new residential road in Malmesbury was named 'Twynnoy Close'.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>In 2003, on the 300th anniversary of the death, a ceremony was carried out at the grave when every schoolgirl in the town, younger than 11 and named Hannah, placed a flower on the grave.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>Twynnoy was featured in the 'Stupid Deaths' segment of the CBBC programme <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Horrible_Histories_(2009_TV_series)">Horrible Histories</ref></hi> (Series 4, Episode 6).</p>
<head>Notes and references</head>
</text>
