<text id="autogum_news_doc257" title="Israeli air strikes hit government compounds in Gaza" shortTile="israeli-air-strikes" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-12-27" dateModified="2015-09-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Israeli_air_strikes_hit_government_compounds_in_Gaza" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Israeli air strikes hit government compounds in Gaza</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 27, 2008</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Map of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palestinian-Israeli%20conflict">Palestinian-Israeli conflict</ref> area and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War%20on%20Terrorism">War on Terrorism</ref> around the Gaza strip</caption></figure>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Israel">Israel</ref> has launched with at least 30 simultaneous missiles strikes on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hamas">Hamas</ref> installations in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gaza%20City">Gaza City</ref>, causing heavy damage. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/F-16%20Fighting%20Falcon">F-16 fighters</ref> targeted security compounds in the city’s centre.</p>
<p>The “massive” air strikes on Saturday have claimed at least 220 lives, including Gaza police chief Maj. Gen. Tawfiq Jaber. More than 700 were injured, while others were still buried under the rubble, according to Health Ministry officer Moawiya Hassanain. Gaza City hospitals, including Shifa Hospital, Gaza’s main treatment center, are crowded with wounded victims. In response thirteen rockets and mortar shells had also hit southern Israel on Friday, damaging an unoccupied house. </p>
<p>Meanwhile, Hamas declared  it would retaliate, by launching rocket attacks on and sending suicide bombers to Israel. “Hamas will continue the resistance until the last drop of blood,” warned Hamas spokesman Fawzi Barhoum. Palestinian President <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahmoud%20Abbas">Mahmoud Abbas</ref>, Hamas’ rival,  says he “condemns this aggression” and calls for restraint.</p>
<figure><caption>Map of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hamas">Hamas</ref>-run <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gaza%20Strip">Gaza Strip</ref>.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qassam%20rocket">Qassam rocket</ref> fired from the Gaza Strip hits southern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ashkelon">Ashkelon</ref> in Israel.</caption></figure>
<p>When the Egyptian-mediated truce terminated last week, Israel warned of their potential to launch a major offensive on Gaza, amid senior leaders’ call to topple Hamas. “I will not hesitate to use Israel’s strength to strike at Hamas and Islamic Jihad,” Prime Minister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ehud%20Olmert">Ehud Olmert</ref> announced on Thursday, issuing a dire warning that ”tens of thousands of children and innocents” would be at risk “as a result of Hamas’ actions.” Defense Minister Ehud Barak says Israel has temporarily opened some border crossings Friday to allow humanitarian aid into the Gaza Strip in response to the international community’s pleas.</p>
<p>Two hours after IAF missiles targeted Hamas installations in the Gaza Strip, Palestinian gunmen launched on Saturday a massive attack with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qassam%20rocket">Qassam rockets</ref> on Israeli territory. Seven struck <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ashkelon">Ashkelon</ref>, killing one person, while another suffered serious injuries, and four others were moderately wounded when their house was hit. They were rushed to the Soroka hospital in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beersheva">Beersheva</ref>. </p>
<p>According to the IDF, Hamas militants had further launched more than 110 rockets since Saturday, IDF says. Meanwhile, a Palestinian Ambassador Riyad Mansour has called on the United Nations to condemn the deadly violence. "There is no justification for punishing 1.5 million in the Gaza Strip because of the actions of a few. We hope we don't fail in having a reaction from the Security Council tonight," he said. Dr Moawiya Hassanein has said "we have counted 271 dead and 620 wounded since Saturday."</p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2008–2009%20Israel–Gaza%20conflict">2008–2009 Israel–Gaza conflict</ref>, referred to as "Operation Cast Lead" (מבצע עופרת יצוקה - also known as "Operation Solid Lead") by the Israel Defense Forces (IDF), is an Israeli air strike operation launched on December 27, 2008 at 11:30 am local time (9:30 am UTC) against Hamas targets in the Gaza Strip. Israeli officials justified the offensive as a retaliation against daily Palestinian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qassam%20rocket">Qassam</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List%20of%20Qassam%20rocket%20attacks">rocket and mortar fire</ref> on Israel's southern communities.</p>
</text>
