<text id="autogum_whow_doc592" title="Be As a City Upon a Hill" shortTile="city-upon-hill" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-11-12" dateModified="2019-03-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be-As-a-City-Upon-a-Hill" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be As a City Upon a Hill</head><p>"For we must consider that we shall be as a city upon a hill. The eyes of all people are upon us, so that if we shall deal falsely with our God in this work we have undertaken, and so cause Him to withdraw His present help from us, we shall be made a story and a by-word through the world." --John Winthrop, "A Model of Christian Charity"</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Show mercy and justice in equal parts.
<list type="unordered"><item>Sometimes there may be an occasion of showing mercy to a rich man in some sudden danger of distress, and also doing a mere justice o a poor man in regard of some particular contract. .</item>
<item>First, accept that every man afford his help to another in every want or distress.</item>
<item>Second, that he perfomed this out of the same affection which makes him careful of his own goods, according to that of our Savior.</item></list></item>
<item>Give.
<list type="unordered"><item>If the time and occasion are extraordinary, give out in abundance.</item>
<item>If the time and occasion are extraordinary, be ruled by them.</item></list></item>
<item>Lend.
<list type="unordered"><item>Observe whether or not the recipient has present, probable, or possible means of repaying you. If he does not, then give him according to his necessity rather than lend him as he requires.</item>
<item>If he has means of repaying you, do not look at the act as a mercy, but a way of commerce in which you are ruled by justice.</item></list></item>
<item>Forgive.
<list type="unordered"><item>Whether you lended as an act of mercy or as a way of commerce, you must forgive him regardless of whether or not he repays you.</item></list></item>
<item>Love.
<list type="unordered"><item>The love among Christians is a real thing, not imaginary.</item>
<item>This love is as absolutely necessary to the being of the body of Christ as the sinews adn other ligaments of a nutural body are to teh being of that body.</item>
<item>This love is divine, spiritual nature free, active, strong, courageous, permanent. Undervaluing all things beneath its proper object. Of all the graces, this makes us nearer to resemble the virtues of our Heavenly Father.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Accept that God Almighty hath ordained the condition of mankind: That some must be rich, some poor, some high and powerful, others low and subjected. Through this, you will be able to acknowledge that:See the glory of His wisdom in the variety and difference of the creatures, and the glory of His power, in ordering all these differences for the preservation and good of the whole.See that He might have the more occasion to manifest the work of His Spirit upon teh wicked in moderating and restraining them.See that every man might have need of others, and from hence they might al be knit more nearly together in the bonds of brotherly affection.</item>
<item>Know the proper time and place to sell all and give to the poor.</item>
<item>Know the proper time to give beyond your ability.</item>
<item>Know the proper time to unite with the community in some special service for the Church.</item>
<item>Know the proper time to help anyone in distress beyond your ability, rather than tempt God in putting him upon help by miraculous and extraordinary means</item></list>
</text>
