<text id="autogum_whow_doc427" title="Bestow a Blessing" shortTile="bestow-blessing" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2007-09-24" dateModified="2019-09-12" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Bestow-a-Blessing" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Bestow a Blessing</head><p>How to bless a person, group, place or thing.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Figure out exactly who or what the blessing is going to be for.  Using names is always best. <figure rend="Bestow a Blessing Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Think about what attributes you want to create or enhance in the object of the blessing.  Traits such as peace, strength, courage, wit, kindness, grace, good looks, health, happiness, long life, justice, and prosperity are some possibilities. <figure rend="Bestow a Blessing Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you're religious, look at your scripture for ideas.  There might be a verse or quote you want to use, or there may be pre-written blessings you can recite. <figure rend="Bestow a Blessing Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you're not religious or don't want to do a religious-sounding blessing, look up some other kinds of quotes, especially poetry.  Even songs.  These can be inspirational even if you choose to write your own blessing. <figure rend="Bestow a Blessing Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Compose the words of the blessing.  You can write them down or memorize them, but make sure you know what you're going to say before you say it.  Just as with a toast or a speech, you don't want to spoil it by forgetting the words or stumbling.  Keep it concise: it shouldn't take more than two minutes to say the whole thing, and preferably less time than that. <figure rend="Bestow a Blessing Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you want to, you can include a ritual of any sort you like.  Try reading up on rituals, rites and superstitions to get some ideas.  Start with traditions from your own ancestry or ethnicity. <figure rend="Bestow a Blessing Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>To bless a person, place your hand on his or her head.  Traditionally the right hand, which in most people is stronger, is the best one to use.  If touching is unacceptable, hold your hand above the person. <figure rend="Bestow a Blessing Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Recite the blessing. <figure rend="Bestow a Blessing Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have a drink or a special treat to celebrate, or give the object of the blessing a gift. <figure rend="Bestow a Blessing Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't use the blessing as a lecture.</item>
<item>You can also bless a house, a place of business, the food you eat, or anything you make with your hands.</item>
<item>Different people have different ideas of what a blessing actually does; depending on your point of view, it's a request to the higher Power to bestow the real gifts, or it's an expression of your will with the hope that what you want will become manifest.</item>
<item>Use phrases in the future tense, such as "May you ..."</item>
<item>A blessing doesn't guarantee good things, but it might help.</item>
<item>In some cultures, it's traditional to bless children when they reach certain stages of life, or even on a regular basis.</item>
<item>Blessings can be public or private.  You can do it with a large audience or on your own.</item>
<item>Invoke the attributes of people you admire.  You can compare the person you're blessing to somebody who is already great.</item>
<item>Again, keep the words of your blessing short.  It's the thought that counts.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be smart when you're composing the blessing, and word it so that it won't offend the person you're blessing or somebody watching.  If in doubt, skip any mention of deities (God or gods).</item></list>
</text>
