<text id="autogum_whow_doc511" title="Set Up a Tattoo Shop" shortTile="set-up-tattoo-shop" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-05-24" dateModified="2019-09-17" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Set-Up-a-Tattoo-Shop" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Set Up a Tattoo Shop</head><p>Are you an artist or have artistic tendencies? Are you interested in taking your art to the most versatile canvas available, which is the skin? Tattooing is popular in many areas of the world and is found in many different cultures. You can capitalize on the popularity of tattooing by setting up a tattoo shop. If you have ever wanted to run your own business as a tattoo artist, read on to learn how to set up a tattoo shop.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Enroll in a tattoo artist apprenticeship program. This program can take you 12 to 24 months to complete, but it could also be very expensive. You will gain the experience you need to become a tattoo artist, which can come in handy because you typically need to have experience in a hands-on program before you can start your own tattoo business. You won't be tattooing right away, but the program is vital to your experience. <figure rend="Set Up a Tattoo Shop Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find a location for your shop. Set up a tattoo shop in a place where there is a lot of automotive and pedestrian traffic to help increase your potential for walk-ins. When people can see your business from the road or as they are walking past, they may be more likely to remember it and visit later. <figure rend="Set Up a Tattoo Shop Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Follow all laws involving tattoos in your local area. The requirements for starting a tattoo business will vary based on where you want to run it. There are health and safety concerns with the art of tattooing, and you will likely be subject to inspections. You also may need to have special permits to operate. <figure rend="Set Up a Tattoo Shop Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Your local health department can help you determine what licensing is needed for tattooing.</item></list></item>
<item>Purchase all the tattooing equipment you need. You won't need to buy everything at once, and you don't have to buy everything brand new. Look in classified papers and online to find used equipment. You will need things such as a tattoo gun, needles, ink, transfers, furniture for the lobby, and a cash register. <figure rend="Set Up a Tattoo Shop Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Advertise your shop through numerous outlets. You can advertise online through paid campaigns and a business website or through social media. You can advertise locally with business cards and flyers. If your budget allows, you can also try radio or TV advertising. <figure rend="Set Up a Tattoo Shop Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Consider adding a credit card machine to your store so you can accept more than just cash for payment.</item>
<item>If you can include piercing in your apprenticeship, this is an excellent way to bring in more business. If you do not want to do piercing yourself, you may be able to hire someone who will. The requirements for piercing will also be provided by your local health department.</item>
<item>Anyone who is acting as a tattoo artist in your shop must hold the necessary certifications. Employees who are not tattooing or piercing will not need certification.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always make sure to have customers sign the necessary consent and waiver forms before you begin the tattoo. Provide adequate after-care instructions to your customers at the conclusion of the session.</item>
<item>Always check ID to ensure your customers are of the proper age to get a tattoo. Residents must be at least 18 years old to get a tattoo unless they live in Illinois or South Carolina, where they need to be at least 21. While most states allow tattooing of minors with parental consent, it is illegal in Alaska, California, Illinois, Iowa, Kansas, Maine, Maryland, Massachusetts, Mississippi, Nevada, New Hampshire, New York, North Carolina, Oklahoma, Oregon, Rhode Island, Washington, and Wisconsin.</item>
<item>Always check ID to ensure your customers are of the proper age to get a piercing. All states require written parental consent to allow a minor to receive any piercing. Most states define minor as younger than 18, whereas South Carolina and Illinois define a minor as anyone under age 21.</item></list>
</text>
