<text id="autogum_academic_doc319" title="The Effectiveness of Adaptive Beach Protection Methods under Wind Application" shortTile="effectiveness-adaptive" author="Kyu-Tae Shim, Kyu-Han Kim, Jun-Ho Park" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2077-1312/7/11/385/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Conclusions</head>
<p>
The trend of morphological change was verified by applying nourishment, which is one of the typical soft-type methods, to a coast where erosion occurred, and the characteristics of each profile were analyzed by comparing the findings with the results of the submerged breakwater method, which is applied in the field more frequently as a hard-type structure. In addition, the effect of wind intensity change on morphological change when an erosive wave approached the coast was evaluated at the same time. In circumstances where only the wave existed, the erosion increased under the 0.1 mm sand profile in proportion to the wave generation time. In particular, large-scale loss of sand occurred over a wide range from the position of x: 200 cm where waves broke to the backshore area, and a sandbar was formed up to the position of x: 200–400 cm to the seaside. When d50: 1 mm sand was applied to the eroded section based on the shoreline, the sediment transport decreased significantly. This is because the sediment transport caused by wave action was restricted by a fast fall in velocity, and wave runup and rundown did not affect the sediment transport significantly. With regard to the 5 mm material, no suspension or traction due to waves occurred, and when the wave was applied to the material directly, the material was transported to the rear by a momentary impact, but the material accumulated from the position within x: 100 cm, forming a steep rubble dune. When the submerged breakwater was installed, sediment transport decreased because of the effect of wave energy being decreased in comparison with the 0.1 mm profile, and the total amount of sediment transport was similar to the condition with 1 mm material application. </p>

<p>When there was an accompanying wind velocity of 8 m/s, the erosion trend in most profiles was similar to the situation in the case of 0 m/s, but a difference was revealed in that the erosion range was expanded. In the case of the 0.1 mm profile condition, the erosion occurred in most of the backshore area owing to strong wave runup, and in the case of the 1 and 5 mm profile conditions, the undertow developed by the strong rundown phenomenon created large-scale scouring near the boundary between the nourishment section and existing sandy ground. Although a submerged breakwater was installed, the erosion range also increased owing to the effect of increased wave energy caused by wind. The profile with 1 mm and submerged breakwater installation showed the smallest range of sediment transport. On the basis of the wave data collected from the positions of P2 and P6, a clear wave change according to the change in wind velocity did not appear at P6, where no breaking wave or wave deformation occurred in the experiment. However, complicated flows, such as breaking waves, reflection, and standing waves, occurred at P2 on the shoreline, and the overall energy density increased in conditions where wind was applied, although the overall energy density could vary according to the morphological conditions. To summarize the above experimental results, if nourishment is selected for the purposes of reducing erosion, a 1 mm particle size is advantageous for sediment transport, but an increase in the grain size, such as with the 5 mm condition, does not produce greater reductions in sediment transport. In addition, an increase in the magnitude of wind velocity produces a greater range in morphological change. It is deemed appropriate that situations where waves and wind coexist should be considered when establishing measures to reduce erosion in the future.
 </p>
</text>
