<text id="autogum_voyage_doc512" title="Montreal/Côte-des-Neiges" shortTile="montrealctedesneiges" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=22871" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Montreal/Côte-des-Neiges</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Côte-des-Neiges</hi> is a multicultural neighbourhood in <ref target="Montreal">Montreal</ref>. The area is highly influenced by its proximity to the Universite de Montreal. The crowd is highly composed of students and immigrants. The Saint Joseph Oratory perches above the district.</p>

<head>Metro</head>
<p>You can reach Côte-des-Neiges from the Côte-des-Neiges and Université de Montreal Metro stations on the Blue Line and Côte Ste-Catherine and Snowdon stations on the Orange Line.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>The 161 Van Horne runs from Rosemont metro, at the far north of the Plateau. From the south-west of the Plateau the 129 Côte-Ste-Catherine follows the edge of Mont Royal through Outremont. 165 Côte-des-Neiges covers the north-south route from Downtown.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">St. Joseph's Oratory</hi> (Oratoire Saint-Joseph), 3800 Chemin Queen Mary (métro Côte-des-Neiges), ☏ +1 514-733-8211 . The largest church in Canada, it is a favourite pilgrimage for devotees of Brother André, who was reputed to have healed the sick and handicapped. Includes a remarkable collection of crutches and canes from the healed. During the summer, it is also possible to stroll through the beautiful garden next to the Oratory which features the Stations of the Cross in marble sculptures. The garden is peaceful and beautifully maintained. The views from both the Oratory and the garden are magnificent and well-worth the climb. Watch for the faithful climbing on their knees to the top. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cemeteries</hi>. Wander among the more than one million graves covering the north slope of Mont Royal. No bikes or picnicking:</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mount-Royal Cemetery</hi>, 1297 Chemin de la Forêt, H2V 2P9, ☏ +1 514 279-7358 . </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Notre-Dame-des-Neiges Cemetery</hi>, 4601 Chemin de la Côte-des-Neiges. One of the largest cemeteries in Canada. </item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Université de Montréal</hi>, 2900 boul Édouard-Montpetit (métro Université de Montréal or Édouard-Montpetit). The second largest university in Canada in terms of students, Université de Montréal is a French speaking university whose campus is mostly concentrated on the mount Royal, between the metro stations Edouard-Montpetit and Côte-des-Neiges. The Roger-Gaudry building, with it's tall tower and Art Deco architecture, is well worth a look. It is situated just in front of the metro station Université-de-Montréal. Free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Montreal Holocaust Memorial Centre</hi>, 1 Carré Cummings Square (5151 Chemin de la Côte-Sainte–Catherine), ☏ +1 514-345-2605 . The Montreal Holocaust Memorial Centre (MHMC) is dedicated to Holocaust education and awareness. It was founded in 1979 by a group of Holocaust survivors. The Centre's mandate is to educate people of all ages and backgrounds about the genocidal murder of six million Jews by Nazi Germany and its collaborators between 1933-1945. </item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Segal Centre for Performing Arts</hi> (was Saydie Bronfman Center), 5170 Chemin de la Côte-Sainte-Catherine, ☏ +1 514 739-2301 , fax: +1 514 739-9340 . Sun-Thu 10AM-4PM.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Piscine Cote-des-Neiges</hi>, 4880 avenue Van Horne, ☏ +1 514-342-9988 . Indoor swimming pool. Free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Picnic in the park</hi> (square between Gatineau, Swail, Decelle and Jean-Brillant). Relax in the park with your lunch. There are several grocery stores nearby, as well as tons of restaurants who offer take out (mostly on Gatineau and Côte-des-Neiges).</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Plaza Côte-des-Neiges</hi>, 6700 chemin de la Côte-des-Neiges (metro Plamondon and Côte-Des-Neiges). Mon-Wed 10AM-6PM, Thu-Fri 10AM-9PM, Sat-Sun 10AM-5PM. Over 100 shops and services plus Cinema Odeon movie theater.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Victoria Ave</hi> (Plamondon Metro).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Queen Mary Road</hi> (Snowdon Metro).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Côte-des-Neiges road</hi> (metro Côte-des-Neiges).</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>
<p>The multicultural communities of Côte-des-Neiges are all well represented on the dining scene. This is the place to come for Kosher, Lebanese, Caribbean, Tamil, Vietnamese, Filipino, Russian and even Romanian cuisine. Cheap eats line Queen Mary, Decarie, Victoria and Côte-des-Neiges avenue.</p>

<head>Kosher</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Chez Benny</hi>, 5071 ch Queen Mary (between ave de Westbury and rue Lemieux; metro Snowdon, bus 17, 51 or 166), ☏ +1 514 735-1836 . Winter: Su-Th 11AM-11PM, F 11AM-Shabbat time, Sa after Shabbat-3AM; Summer: Su-Th 11AM-midnight, F 11AM-Shabbat time; Sa after Shabbat-1AM. Kosher restaurant with Mediterranean (shawarma, falafel, merguez and the likes) and Chinese dishes. Really busy on weekend evenings.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ernie's and Ellie's Place</hi>, 6900 boul Décarie (in the mall), ☏ +1 514-344-4444 . Kosher meat restaurant. Everything goes: Russian, Chinese, Moroccan, you name it. Regular "Canadian" kitchen isn't bad either. Food served very quickly. Decor is trying to be nice but misses some edge. It doesn't matter though, because this place gets customers no matter what happens.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Exception 2</hi>, 5039 ch Queen Mary (between ave de Westbury and rue Lemieux; metro Snowdon, bus 17, 51 or 166), ☏ +1 514 344-0508 . Su-Th 8AM-9PM, F 8AM-2PM. Kosher restaurant with pizza, pasta, salads, sushi. fish, and more.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Expresti gourmet</hi>, 5335A chemin Queen Mary (Cornrer Coolbrook), ☏ +1 514-482-6688 . Italian, Dairy and Parve</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pizza Pita</hi>, 6415 boul Décarie (between ave Plomondon and ave Van Horne; metro Plamondon, bus 17, 160, or 161), ☏ +1 514 731-7482 . Su-Th 7:30AM-11PM, F 7:30AM-1 hr before Shabbat, Sa 1 hr after Shabbat-4AM. Kosher (and Cholov Yisroel) pizzas, pita sandwiches, burgers. Falafels are generously stuffed and fried eggplants give a tasty twist. Very popular with high schoolers and the frum set, especially on Saturday nights. One of the best veggie pizzas in Montreal.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pizzeria Tatty</hi>, 6540 ave de Darlington (at ave Barclay; bus 160 or 161), ☏ +1 514 734-8289 . Kosher pizzeria.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Reserve</hi>, 5395 ch Queen Mary (between ave Earnscliffe and ave Coolbrook; metro Snowdon, bus 17, 51, 63, 129, or 166), ☏ +1 514 481-3111 . Su-Th 5PM-10PM. Kosher steakhouse and tavern.</item>
</list>


<head>Halal</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Halal 786 Restaurant</hi>, 768 Jean Talon Ouest, ☏ +1 514-270-0786 .</item>
</list>


<head>Budget</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Exception 2</hi>, 5047, chemin Queen-Mary, ☏ +1 514-344-0508 . Kosher dairy restaurant featuring thin crust pizzas.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Chez Jolee</hi>, 5495, ave. Victoria, ☏ +1 514-733-6362 . Delicious Sri Lankan and South Indian meals and snacks, including dosa, kottu roti, string hoppers, idli, vada and more.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Al Amine</hi>, 3549 ave. Lacombe, ☏ +1 514-739-1817 . Typical Montreal style "shish taouk" (chicken shawarma) Lebanese restaurant. Delicious and rather healthy fast food. They have great vegetarian/vegan options (falafel, vegetarian platter), pizza by the slice and Lebanese baklava. 2$-10$.</item>
</list>
</text>
