<text id="autogum_voyage_doc136" title="Nordic cuisine" shortTile="nordic-cuisine" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=144735" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Nordic cuisine</head>


<p>The cuisines of all <ref target="Nordic%20countries">Nordic countries</ref> are quite similar, although each country does have its signature dishes.</p>

<head>Countries and regions</head>
<ref target="Denmark%23Eat">Denmark</ref> is a major exporter of dairy products, pork and beer, and its cuisine has a slight Central European flair. Danes have a justified reputation of being more hedonistic than other Nordic people, eating greasy food, smoking, and enjoying more relaxed alcohol laws than further north.

<ref target="Finland%23Eat">Finland's cuisine</ref> has been influenced by <ref target="Russian%20cuisine">Russian cuisine</ref>, with dishes such as meat pies (<hi rend="italic">lihapiirakka</hi>), dark bread and, of course, vodka. They are the world's leading consumers of <ref target="coffee">coffee</ref> and milk per capita.

<ref target="Iceland%23Eat">Iceland</ref> is known for fish, lamb, and the more spectacular <hi rend="italic">Þorramatur</hi>, a range of cured fish and meat products traditionally eaten during winter. Likely the most exotic of the Nordic cuisines, Iceland has dishes that not everyone may want to try, such as lamb's head and testicles, puffin meat and whale. The <ref target="Faroe%20Islands%23Eat">Faroe Islands</ref> have a cuisine rather similar to that of Iceland, except it is only the long-finned pilot whale (<hi rend="italic">Globicephala melas</hi>) that is a local delicacy.

<ref target="Norway%23Eat">Norway</ref> also has a heritage of seafood. As with Iceland, Norway has a tradition of lamb dishes. Norwegians are said to eat more pizza per capita than people in any other country. Norway is one of the few countries in the world, where it is possible to eat whale at a restaurant.

<ref target="Sweden%23Eat">Sweden</ref>, being the largest country in size and population, has at least one "signature dish" in all categories of food. Some delicacies are freshwater fish, crayfish, game, berries, and the iconic meatballs. <ref target="Scania">Scania</ref> is Sweden's breadbasket and gateway to Denmark, famous for rich meat, poultry and bread dishes.

<p>The cuisine of northern Scandinavia and the <ref target="Sami%20people">Sami people</ref> is based on the few ingredients available in the <ref target="Arctic">Arctic</ref> and sub-Arctic; predominantly reindeer, fish, and berries.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Before modern times, the majority of Nordic people had a very limited range of ingredients, especially in the far north. Famines occurred as recently as the 19th century. While industrialization came late, dining in the Nordic countries has become very cosmopolitan in the 21st century.</p>

<p>Most traditional dishes are based on what used to be poor man's food, such as herring, dried fish, potatoes, and hard bread, although many have developed a certain refinement and are now considered classy enough for middle or even upper class people to enjoy openly.</p>

<head>Ingredients</head>

<p>With a long coastline, the fertile waters of the North Atlantic, and several lakes, fish and other <hi rend="bold"><ref target="seafood">seafood</ref></hi> has a traditional role. The <ref target="right%20to%20access">right to access</ref> and easily available permits allow leisure <ref target="fishing">fishing</ref> to some extent in all Nordic countries, and most restaurant menus feature some kind of seafood.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Pickled <hi rend="bold">herring</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Clupea harengus</hi>, Danish/Norwegian: <hi rend="italic">sild</hi>, Swedish: <hi rend="italic">sill</hi>, Finnish: <hi rend="italic">silli</hi>), used to be the poor man's dish, but has developed into a traditional appetizer, often in a few varieties (such as with mustard, garlic, tomato sauce or dill). <hi rend="bold">Baltic herring</hi>, <hi rend="italic">strömming</hi>, is the same species, though smaller, less fatty, and caught in the Baltic Sea. <hi rend="italic">Sour herring</hi> in Norway should not be confused with <hi rend="italic">surströmming</hi>, Swedish fermented herring. In Norway herring is also dried and smoked. In Denmark and <ref target="Scania">Scania</ref> smoked herring (Danish: <hi rend="italic">røget sild</hi>, Swedish: <hi rend="italic">rökt sill</hi>) is available locally. Smoked herring from the island of <ref target="Bornholm">Bornholm</ref> in the Baltic Sea are especially popular.</item>
<item> Canned <hi rend="bold">sardines</hi> in oil is a traditional Norwegian product (particularly in Stavanger that had a booming canning industry), but is actually made from local brisling (also known as skipper or sprat).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Salmon</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Salmo salar</hi>, <hi rend="italic">lax</hi>/<hi rend="italic">laks</hi>/<hi rend="italic">lohi</hi>) is farmed in Norway, and used to be an everyday dish in northern Sweden, especially smoked or cured. Farmed salmon and <hi rend="bold">rainbow trout</hi> have become the most common fish eaten in Finnish restaurants and non-fisher households. Smoked salmon, <hi rend="bold">trout</hi> and other salmonid fish is served as everyday food in Norway, and can be fished with a rod. Hot and cold smoked are two variants. Cured salmon is known as gravlaks or gravlax. Fermented trout, <hi rend="italic">rakfisk</hi>, is a smelly Norwegian specialty particularly produced and consumed in the interior valleys such as <ref target="Valdres">Valdres</ref>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cod</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Gadus morhua</hi>, <hi rend="italic">torsk</hi>) is the most important catch in Norwegian waters. The winter-spring (february-april) catch of <hi rend="italic">skrei</hi> (the migrating cod) has since prehistoric times been the high season for coastal areas. The fisheries around Lofoten are in particular unusually rich. Fresh <hi rend="italic">skrei</hi> served lightly boiled is a standard dish during the season. In Lofoten and Nordland cod is also served with roe, liver and potatoes in dish known as <hi rend="italic">mølje</hi>. The cod of the Baltic Sea has been overfished, and is vulnerable today.</item>
<item> Wind-dried <hi rend="bold">white fish</hi> such as cod <hi rend="italic">tørrfisk</hi> (stockfish) is an ancient and important product of Northern Norway, used for lutefisk and other dishes. Salt-dried white fish <hi rend="italic">klippfisk</hi>, an important product of western Norway, is used in similar ways.</item>
<item> Freshwater and Baltic Sea fish, such as <hi rend="bold">perch</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Perca fluviatilis</hi>), <hi rend="bold">pike</hi> and <hi rend="bold">zander</hi> can be found at some restaurants and supermarkets, and is rather easy to fish with a rod.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Roe</hi> (fish eggs) is a delicacy in Sweden. The roe from the vendace, <hi rend="italic">Coregonus albula</hi> (<hi rend="italic">siklöja</hi> in Swedish), known as <hi rend="italic">löjrom</hi>, is among the most prized. <hi rend="bold">Caviar</hi> usually refers to roe from the lumpfish, <hi rend="italic">Cyclopterus lumpus</hi> (<hi rend="italic">stenbit</hi> or <hi rend="italic">sjurygg</hi> in Swedish, <hi rend="italic">rognkjeks</hi> in Norwegian). <hi rend="bold">Kaviar</hi> in Sweden and Norway refers to rendered fish roe with some additives, eaten as an everyday, relatively cheap, bread spread kept in "tubes".</item>
<item> Cod liver oil (<hi rend="italic">tran</hi>) is used as dietary supplement particularly during winter for vitamin D. Bottles can be found on many breakfast buffets.</item>
<item> The <hi rend="bold">red king crab</hi> (Russian crab), <hi rend="italic">Paralithodes camtschaticus</hi>, is native to the northern Pacific. Since the Soviets implanted the crab to the Barents Sea in the 1960s, it has become an invasive species spreading to Norwegian waters, becoming a new and popular ingredient.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Crayfish</hi> (European or noble crayfish, Norwegian: <hi rend="italic">kreps</hi>, Swedish: <hi rend="italic">kräfta</hi>) is traditionally fished and eaten during August in Norway and Sweden, and among Swedish-speaking Finns. <hi rend="italic">Kräftskiva</hi> is a traditional Swedish crayfish party.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Norway lobster</hi>, <hi rend="italic">sjøkreps</hi> ("sea crayfish"), <hi rend="italic">Nephrops norvegicus</hi>, is a delicacy of the north Atlantic.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">European lobster</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Homarus gammarus</hi>, is a culinary classic, very similar to the American lobster.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Shrimp</hi>, especially <hi rend="italic">Pandalus borealis</hi>, have a prominent role in Norway, Denmark and western Sweden.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Clams</hi> and <hi rend="bold">mussels</hi> are harvested and eaten, especially in Denmark.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Whale</hi> has a peculiar taste, and can be found in Iceland and Norway. Whaling is a sensitive issue; see <ref target="animal%20ethics">animal ethics</ref>.</item>
</list>

<p>While whole <hi rend="bold"><ref target="meat">meat</ref></hi> remains a bit of a luxury, many traditional dishes are based on mince, offal and blood. Still, all countries have lively <ref target="Travel%20as%20a%20vegetarian">vegetarian</ref> and vegan communities, especially among young city-dwellers. Vegetarians face less understanding in the countryside, where hunting and fishing are popular pastimes.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pork</hi> is the most common meat, and one of Denmark's most important export commodities. Pork dishes are especially eaten around Christmas.</item>
<item> While cattle are primarily held for milk, <hi rend="bold">beef</hi> and <hi rend="bold">veal</hi> are delicacies.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lamb</hi> is a signature dish of Iceland, the Faroe Islands and rural Norway. Several special dishes are based on lamb, for instance "sheep's head" (Norwegian: <hi rend="italic">smalahove</hi>) or "sheep's ribs" (Norwegian: <hi rend="italic">pinnekjøtt</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ribbe</hi>). Dried, salted and smoked meat products are common.</item>
<item> While chicken and other poultry became everyday food only in the late 20th century, <hi rend="bold">goose</hi> is traditionally eaten in Denmark and southern Sweden.</item>
<item> As <ref target="hunting">hunting</ref> is a pastime in the countryside, <hi rend="bold">game</hi> such as elk/moose, deer, and boar, is seasonally available, although mostly consumed in the hunters' households. Wild poultry such as <hi rend="bold">grouse</hi> is a treasured delicacy.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Reindeer</hi> are traditionally bred within the <ref target="Sami%20culture">Sami culture</ref> in the Arctic and sub-Arctic territories. The meat tastes more like game than domestic animal meats. Reindeer meat might be served as whole meat, or as <hi rend="bold">sautéed reindeer</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">renskav</hi> in Swedish, <hi rend="italic">finnbiff</hi> in Norwegian), traditionally eaten with potatoes and lingonberries.</item>
</list>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="Bread">Bread</ref></hi> (Swedish <hi rend="italic">bröd</hi>, Danish/Norwegian <hi rend="italic">brød</hi>, Finnish <hi rend="italic">leipä</hi>) is a daily staple food.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Soft bread comes in dozens of varieties, with dark, heavy rye bread of different types common. Especially Finland, with influences from the east, has many types of traditional bread. For more taste, try to find bread from a local bakery, instead of packed bread in supermarkets.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hard bread</hi> or <hi rend="bold">crisp bread</hi> (Norwegian: <hi rend="italic">knekkebrød</hi>, Swedish: <hi rend="italic">knäckebröd</hi>, Finnish: <hi rend="italic">näkkileipä</hi>) is more known for its traditional value, than its taste. Some types are served with cheese as dessert or snack, some are worth tasting in their own right.</item>
<item> Scandinavian <hi rend="bold"><ref target="pastries">pastries</ref></hi> are well known.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> The <hi rend="bold">Danish pastry</hi> is called <hi rend="italic">Wienerbrød</hi> ("Viennese bread"), since it was introduced by bakers from <ref target="Vienna">Vienna</ref>.</item>
<item> The cinnamon roll presumably originated in Sweden as <hi rend="italic">kanelbulle</hi> (Norwegian: <hi rend="italic">skillingsbolle</hi>), in <ref target="Bergen">Bergen</ref> it is believed to be invented there by the <ref target="Hanseatic%20League">Hanseatic merchants</ref>.</item>
<item> The <hi rend="italic">semla</hi> (in Finland: <hi rend="italic">laskiaispulla</hi>/<hi rend="italic">fastlagsbulla</hi>) is a Swedish pastry eaten during lent.</item>
<item> Saffron buns are eaten for Christmas, traditionally on Saint Lucia's day in December; in Sweden they tend to be known as <hi rend="italic">lussebulle</hi>.</item>
<item> Cream cake (<hi rend="italic">tårta</hi> in Swedish, <hi rend="italic">lagkage</hi> in Danish) is traditionally made of cream, sponge cake and wild berries.</item>
</list>


<p><hi rend="bold">Milk and dairy</hi> products claim a large section of each supermarket, and are important ingredients in Nordic diets. Milk is consumed both as is ("sweet") and fermented ("sour"). Cream (Norwegian/Danish: <hi rend="italic">fløte/fløde</hi>, Swedish: <hi rend="italic">grädde</hi>) and sour cream (Norwegian: <hi rend="italic">rømme</hi>, Swedish: <hi rend="italic">gräddfil</hi>) are also widely used ingredients. <hi rend="italic">Rømmegrøt</hi>, a porridge made from sour cream, is a Norwegian specialty. Buttermilk (Swedish: <hi rend="italic">filmjölk</hi>) and "thick milk" (Norwegian: <hi rend="italic">tjukkmjølk/tettmelk</hi>), are sour variants of yoghurt, another variant on the theme is <hi rend="italic">filbunke</hi> or <hi rend="italic">fil</hi> (Finnish: <hi rend="italic">viili</hi>), common in Finland. Whey butter (Swedish: <hi rend="italic">messmör</hi>, Norwegian: <hi rend="italic">prim</hi>) and whey cheese (Swedish: <hi rend="italic">mesost</hi>, Norwegian: <hi rend="italic">brunost</hi>) are other typical Nordic products.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> The dominant type of <ref target="cheese">cheese</ref> is hard cheese from cow milk. Goat cheese, particularly the special Norwegian caramelised brown type (<hi rend="italic">brunost</hi>, often made from goat milk and called <hi rend="italic">geitost</hi>), is an iconic dish of Norway. Various traditional and novel cheeses are produced, increasingly on farms that sell the products themselves or through local groceries. <hi rend="italic">Gammelost</hi> ("old cheese") is a pungent and rich Norwegian special cheese made from skimmed, sour milk.</item>
<item> Skyr is an Icelandic dairy product, similar to yoghurt. It is traditionally eaten in a bowl with cold milk. Skyr originates from Norway, but the tradition died out in most of Scandinavia 1,100 years ago. Skyr is produced under an Icelandic licence in Norway, Sweden and Finland.</item>
</list>


<p><hi rend="bold">Wild <ref target="mushrooms">mushrooms</ref></hi> are picked and eaten in summer and autumn. This is however a recent tradition in most areas; Karl XIV Johan, a Napoleonic general, who ascended the throne of Sweden and Norway in 1814, is said to have introduced mushroom-eating to his new subjects. Since then, the porcini (<hi rend="italic">Boletus edulis</hi>), one of the most popular mushrooms, is known as <hi rend="italic">karljohan</hi> in Swedish. Eastern Finland has its own older tradition shared with the neighbouring regions in Russia. At restaurants you will mostly find chanterelles and cultivated button mushrooms. At open air markets in Finland, at least chanterelles and funnel chanterelles are available in season; some twenty more species were approved for sale before the market was deregulated, also other ones are often picked by experts. Commonly picked mushroom include <hi rend="italic">Boletus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Russula</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Lactarius</hi> species.</p>

<p>Traditional <hi rend="bold">vegetables</hi> are those that thrive in the Nordic climate, such as cabbage, cauliflower, carrot and turnip (swede). <hi rend="bold">Potatoes</hi> have been the main staple since the 19th century, most often simply boiled, but also made into mashed potatoes, potato salad and more. The almond potato, <hi rend="italic">puikula/mandelpotatis/mandelpotet</hi>, is a variety grown particularly at high altitudes or latitudes, is a delicacy of <ref target="Finnish%20Lapland">Lapland</ref>, <ref target="Norrland">Norrland</ref> and Norway's high valleys. Fresh fruit used to be a luxury until modern times; <hi rend="bold">berries</hi> such as bilberry, lingonberry, cranberry, cloudberries and juniper berries are traditional condiments. Apples and cherries are widely grown both commercially and in private gardens. In Norway, apples and sweet cherries are grown in the fjord areas, notably Hardanger. Strawberries of fine quality are produced in large quantities during July and well into August in several areas.</p>

<p>Traditional <hi rend="bold">spices</hi> are black pepper, juniper, dill and thyme, in low concentration. Salt has been widely used for conservation and features in many traditional meat and fish products. It was however rare in the northern regions, where food was traditionally dried, smoked or fermented instead. Naturally occurring herbs such as "forest garlic" (<hi rend="italic">ramsløk</hi>) have been "rediscovered" and introduced in various products (such as cheese) and dishes.</p>
</text>
