<text id="autogum_voyage_doc164" title="Penrith" shortTile="penrith" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=27236" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Penrith</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Penrith</hi> is a small market town in <ref target="Cumbria">Cumbria</ref>, to the north-east of the Lake District.</p>

<head>By train</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Penrith is located on the West Coast Mainline rail link. There are direct connections to London (3 h), Edinburgh (1 1/2 h) and Glasgow (2h).</item>
</list>


<head>By bus</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> There are direct bus services from Penrith to <ref target="London">London</ref> and <ref target="Scotland">Scotland</ref>, operated by <ref target="http://www.nationalexpress.com">National Express</ref>.</item>
<item> There are local buses <ref target="http://www.stagecoachbus.com"></ref> from <ref target="Cockermouth">Cockermouth</ref> via <ref target="Keswick">Keswick</ref> and <ref target="Threlkeld">Threlkeld</ref> in the northern <ref target="Lake%20District%20National%20Park">Lake District</ref> every hour or two.</item>
</list>


<head>By car</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Penrith is Situated on the M6 (junction 40) towards <ref target="Birmingham%20%28England%29">Birmingham</ref>, A66 from <ref target="Workington">Workington</ref> to <ref target="Grangetown">Grangetown</ref> and on the A6 from <ref target="Luton">Luton</ref> to <ref target="Carlisle">Carlisle</ref>.</item>
</list>


<head>Get around</head>
<p>The town can easily be explored on foot.</p>

<head>See</head>
<p>The town's appeal to visitors is somewhat limited to the many fine pubs, the supermarkets and the railway station. Penrith does however have some hidden historic gems, most imposingly, Penrith Castle.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Penrith Castle</hi>. Building of the castle' began in 1399, when William Strickland (later Bishop of Carlisle and Archbishop of Canterbury) added a stone wall to an earlier pele tower, primarily as a defence against the then frequent raids from the Scottish borders. The castle was improved over the next 70 years, becoming a royal fortress for Richard, Duke of Gloucester before he became King Richard III in 1483. The ruins that can be seen today date from about that time. The striking sandstone remains are situated in Castle Park, opposite Penrith railway station. free. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">St. Andrew's Church</hi>. church often open during the day. The churchyard in the town contains the 'Giant's Thumb', a Norse cross dating from 920 AD erected as a memorial to his father by Owen Caesarius, King of Cumbria from 920 to 937 AD. There is a tradition that the 'Giant's Grave' is the grave of Owen himself. The four hogback stones surrounding the grave are said to represent wild boar he killed in nearby Inglewood Forest. The two Norse crosses are some 11 feet high. The tower dates from 1397, but the church was built in 1722 and has an interesting interior. The church cafe is open Mon - Fri 9:30AM - 2:00PM. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Penrith and Eden Museum</hi>. Open all year: Mon - Sat 10am-5pm and on Sun, April to October, 11am-4pm.. In Robinson's School in Middlegate. The school closed in 1971 after a long history dating back to 1670 and is now a combined Tourist information centre and museum. free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Brougham Castle</hi>, Moor Lane, CA10 2AA, ☏ +44 1768 862488 . adults £4.00, children £2.40, concessions £3.60. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Acorn Bank</hi>, Temple Sowerby, CA10 1SP (8 miles east of Penrith), ☏ +44 17683 61893 , ✉ acornbank@nationaltrust.org.uk . </item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">James &amp; John Graham Grocers</hi>, 6 - 7 Market Square, CA11 7BS. Independent grocer established in 1793, with an excellent selection of cheeses and home baking.</item>
<item> There are three <hi rend="bold">Supermarkets</hi> near the station - Morrisons and Booths in Brunswick Road and Aldi in Ullswater Road. Sainsbury's is on the opposite side of the town centre and the Penrith Co-op <ref target="http://www.penrithco-op.co.uk/19.aspx"></ref> is in Burrowgate.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Agricultural Hotel</hi>. The Castlegate, CA11 7JE. Bar meals and Jennings real ales in this hotel near the station.</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The George</hi>. Is in the town centre</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The North Lakes Hotel and Spa</hi>. Is a four star hotel on the edge of the town</item>
</list>


<head>Go next</head>

<p>Just outside the town is Brougham Castle, which is much better preserved than Penrith Castle which is situated alongside the earth-works of a Roman Fort. The site was later taken by the Norman family of Vieuxpont to build their castle, the ruins the stone keep, and service buildings can still be seen.</p>

<ref target="Ullswater">Ullswater</ref>, the <ref target="Eden%20Valley">Eden Valley</ref> and the Rheged Centre are all very nearby. The neighbouring towns are <ref target="Keswick">Keswick</ref> to the west, <ref target="Appleby%20in%20Westmorland">Appleby in Westmorland</ref> to the south east, and the city of <ref target="Carlisle">Carlisle</ref> to the north.
</text>
