<text id="autogum_whow_doc412" title="Make Your Birthday Wish Come True" shortTile="make-birthday-wish" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2017-06-01" dateModified="2017-06-01" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-Your-Birthday-Wish-Come-True" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make Your Birthday Wish Come True</head><p>Don't you hate when you want to make a wish come true but don't know how to? Here are some really easy steps to get your wish granted, or TRY too. If you want that, then keep reading. Feel free to ask questions.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Start A Wish Journal</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Your counting down to your birthday! And your hoping the wish comes true. But so many wishes! What wish will you choose?
<list type="unordered"><item>Start your Wish Journal. Draw pictures, write down your wishes, do anything you want explaining your wishes.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Get A Charm</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Some people say to get a charm bracelet, choker, or anything you can wear. Find a gold or silver chain and get a charm based on it. Want a phone? Get a phone charm.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you want an animal, get the animal charm of it. Any charm based on what you want will work.</item>
<item>Where it till your wish starts coming true</item></list></item></list>
<head>Set Up A Calender</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>"What day is it? How many more days left?" You probably ask yourself every morning. To keep organized, make a calender to help count down the days.
<list type="unordered"><item>Every day, cross off a number. Keep organized in the calender and journal. This is especially important for the big day.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Calming Down &amp; Sleeping Well</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Every night, don't stay up and watch TV! Goto sleep, and put on some classical music and light some candles {If you're a child, ask your parents to this or buy some lavender}.
<list type="unordered"><item>Remember to wish every night. Do not change the wish. Every night you wish, the more powerful the chance of the wish coming true is.</item></list></item></list>
<head>The Big Day</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Finally! Your birthday's today! And your ready for this wish. Did you do all the steps?
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't tell ANYONE your wish. or it will not come true. But before you do, have complete faith in this.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Blowing Out The Candles</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>This is the big moment. The Birthday Song's playing, everyone's grinning at you, ready for you to blow the candles out.
<list type="unordered"><item>close your eyes, puff up your cheeks with air, and POOF! As you blow out the candles, silently think your wish.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Getting Back-Up {Optional}</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>There's an old tale about writing down your wish after you blow out the candles and getting a flower seed and putting it in a flower pot.Put your paper inside the pot too.
<list type="unordered"><item>As the flower sprouts, your wish is coming more and more true.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Have your candles close together. That way you've more chance to blow them all out at once.</item>
<item>Think about the wish as you blow the candles.</item>
<item>Close your eyes and make sure you have a big, poof of air in your mouth to blow out those candles.</item>
<item>Meditating will have a lot, thinking about your wish.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>DO NOT make the wish harmful, or most likely the nature spirits will never grant your wishes ever, ever again.</item>
<item>Do not open your eyes during the process of blowing the candles.</item>
<item>If after you blow out the candles you light them again, the second time wish will NOT be granted.</item></list>
</text>
