<text id="autogum_fiction_doc40" title="The Tragedy of Pudd'nhead Wilson" shortTile="tragedypuddnheadwilson" author="Twain, Mark" type="fiction" dateCollected="2019-10-22" sourceURL="http://gutenberg.readingroo.ms/1/0/102/102-0.txt">
<head>Dialect used in Pudd'nhead Wilson</head>

<p>English Dialect, Alternative, Another and en against agin, ag'in, ag'in' because 'ca'se going gwine, gwyne more mo' that dat the de then den there dere, dah these dese they dey, deh this dis was 'uz with wid where whah</p>

<p>The above table was presented as a foundation which played into the decision to make some emendations, below, that were not authorized by Twain in 1899. One curious notation is that there was sometimes pronounced dere, but also dah. Along the same lines, they most often became dey, but in one case, deh.</p>

<p>3. This version.</p>

<p>Our version is based on the 1894 publication of this novel in Hartford. This was Twain's original American release of the novel in book form. A scanned copy of this book is available through Hathitrust. The book contained some spaces in contractions: I 'll, dat 'll, had n't, could n't, dis 'll, 't ain't / t ain't, and dey 'll are some examples. These spaces were not retained in our transcription, and are not identified. We did make a few other emendations. These emendations were checked with the 1899 version of Pudd'nhead Wilson published by Harper &amp; Brothers.</p>

<p>4. Notes on emendations.</p>

<p>The errors on Page 233 and Page 288, were not changed in the 1899 book, so the case for making those changes may be found in the Detailed Notes section. The remaining errors were corrected in the 1899 publication, presumably authorized by Twain, who essentially made the case for those emendations.</p>

<p>In the HTML version of this e-book, you can place your cursor over the faint silver dotted lines below the changed text to discover the original text. The Detailed Notes section of these notes describe these emendations.</p>

<p>5. Other versions.</p>

<p>Please note that many print versions of Pudd'nhead Wilson include the phrase 'spelling and usage have been brought into conformity with modern usage,' and editors have been liberal with their renditions of Twain's story.</p>

<p>6. Detailed notes.</p>

<p>The Detailed Notes Section also includes issues that have come up during transcription. One common issue is that words are sometimes split into two lines for spacing purposes in the original text. These words are hyphenated in the physical book, but there is a question sometimes as to whether the hyphen should be retained in transcription. The reasons behind some of these decisions are itemized.</p>

<p>Production Notes Section:</p>

<p>1. Chapter Titles.</p>

<p>The Chapter Titles, such as Doom in Chapter XXI., were not part of Twain's book. They remain from another version of this book. The chapter titles are used in PG's Mark Twain index, so we have retained them.</p>

<p>2. The Author's Note.</p>

<p>The Author's Note to Those Extraordinary Twins is actually the author's introduction to the novella, Those Extraordinary Twins. Twain originally produced this book with two parts: Pudd'nhead Wilson and Those Extraordinary Twins.</p>

<p>Project Gutenberg offers both stories, so we present the Author's Note as the Introduction to Those Extraordinary Twins, as Twain intended. If you want to read the Author's Note, please visit the Introduction of our production of the novella, Those Extraordinary Twins.</p>

<p>Detailed Notes Section:</p>

<p>Chapter 1.</p>

<p>On Page 19, barber-shop was hyphenated between two lines for spacing. The 1899 Harper &amp; Brothers version used "barber shop" in this spot. Even though barber-shop cannot be transcribed as such, the assumption is that the 1894 version put in the hyphen by mistake. We transcribed the word barber shop.</p>

<p>Chapter 2.</p>

<p>On Page 34, changed ca'se to 'ca'se, used as dialect for because, in the clause: "but dat's ca'se it's mine." The author used 'ca'se eighteen other times as dialect for because, and did not use ca'se again.</p>

<p>Chapter 3.</p>

<p>On Page 43, insert missing period after tomb.</p>

<p>Chapter 6.</p>

<p>On Page 81, add a comma after door: "The twins took a position near the door the widow stood at Luigi's side, Rowena stood beside Angelo,..."</p>

<p>Chapter 7.</p>

<p>On Page 88, add a period after fault in the sentence: The Judge laid himself out hospitably to make them have a good time, and if there was a defect anywhere it was not his fault.</p>

<p>Chapter 9.</p>

<p>On Page 114, there is a word missing before the semicolon in the clause: Tom sprang up and seized a billet of wood and raised ; the 1899 Harper &amp; Brothers version provided the missing word, "it."</p>

<p>Chapter 11.</p>

<p>On Page 131, change dicision to decision in the clause: Luigi reserved his dicision.</p>

<p>On Page 133, change comma to a period after years in the sentence: "I never got a chance to try my hand at it, and I may never get a chance; and yet if I ever do get it I shall be found ready, for I have kept up my law-studies all these years,"</p>

<p>On Page 149, Correct spelling of Cappello to Capello. The surname of the twins was Capello in the letter on page 73, and two other times in Chapter 6.</p>

<p>Chapter 13.</p>

<p>On Page 167, Change ' to " in the sentence: "Why, my boy, you look desolate. Don't take it so hard. Try and forget you have been kicked.'</p>

<p>On Page 176, ship-shape was hyphenated and split between two lines for spacing. The 1899 Harper &amp; Brothers version of the novel used shipshape, and so will we.</p>

<p>Chapter 14.</p>

<p>On Page 182, changed period after hatching to question mark in the sentence: What could be hatching. On Page 184, remove comma after sha'n't, in the clause: but if he doesn't, I sha'n't, let on.</p>
</text>
