<text id="autogum_fiction_doc343" title="Tom Swift and His War Tank; Or, Doing His Bit for Uncle Sam" shortTile="tomswiftwartankdoingbit" author="Appleton, Victor" type="fiction" dateCollected="2019-10-22" sourceURL="http://gutenberg.readingroo.ms/9/5/954/954.txt">
<head>Rescued</head>

<p>For a moment Ned and Mr. Damon gazed at the farmer in his rattletrap of an auto, and then they looked at the fluttering piece of paper in his hand. Thence their gaze traveled to the ragged and barefoot lad sitting beside the farmer.</p>

<p>"I found it!" announced the boy.</p>

<p>"Found what?" asked Ned.</p>

<p>"That there note!"</p>

<p>Without asking any more questions, reserving them until they knew more about the matter, Mr. Damon and Ned each reached out a hand for the paper the farmer held. The latter handed it to Ned, being nearest him, and at a sight of the handwriting the young bank clerk exclaimed:</p>

<p>"It's from Tom, all right!"</p>

<p>"What happened to him?" cried Mr. Damon. "Where is he? Is he a prisoner?"</p>

<p>"So it seems," answered Ned. "Wait, I'll read it to you," and he read:</p>

<p>"'Whoever picks this up please send word at once to Mr. Swift or to Ned Newton in Shopton, or to Mr. Damon of Waterfield. I am a prisoner, locked in the old factory. Tom Swift'."</p>

<p>"Bless my quinine pills!" cried Mr Damon. "What in the world does it mean? What factory?"</p>

<p>"That's just what we've got to find out," decided Ned. "Where did you get this?" he asked the farmer's boy.</p>

<p>"Way off over there," and he pointed across miles of fields. "I was lookin' for a lost cow, and I went past an old factory. There wasn't nobody in the place, as far as I knowed, but all at once I heard some one yell, and then I seen something white, like a bird, sail out of a high window. I was scared for a minute, thinkin' it might be tramps after me."</p>

<p>"And what did you do, Sonny?" asked Mr. Damon, as the boy paused.</p>

<p>"Well, after a while I went to where the white thing lay, and I picked it up. I seen it was a piece of paper, with writin' on it, and it was wrapped around part of a brick."</p>

<p>"And did you go near the factory to find out who called or who threw the paper out?" Ned queried.</p>

<p>"I didn't," the boy answered. "I was scared. I went home, and didn't even start to find the lost cow.</p>

<p>"No more he did," chimed in the farmer. "He come runnin' in like a whitehead, and as soon as I saw the paper and heard what Bub had to say, I thought maybe I'd better do somethin'."</p>

<p>"Did you go to the factory?" asked Ned eagerly.</p>

<p>"No. I thought the best thing to do would be to find this Mr. Swift, or the other folks mentioned in this letter. I knowed, in a general way, where Shopton was, but I'd never been there, doing my tradin' in the other direction, and so I had to stop and ask the road. If you can tell me--"</p>

<p>"We're two of the persons spoken of in that note," said Mr. Damon, as he mentioned his name and introduced Ned. "We have been looking for our friend Tom Swift for two days now. We must find him at once, as there is no telling what he may be suffering."</p>

<p>"Where is this old factory you speak of," continued Mr. Damon, "and how can we get there? It's too bad one of you didn't go back, after finding the note, to tell Tom he was soon to be rescued."</p>

<p>"Waal, maybe it is," said the farmer, a bit put out by the criticism. "But I figgered it would be better to look up this young man's friends and let them do the rescuin', and not lose no time, 'specially as it's about as far from my place to the factory as it is to Shopton."</p>

<p>"Well, I suppose that's so," agreed Ned. "But what is this factory?"</p>

<p>"It's an old one where they started to make beet sugar, but it didn't pan out," the farmer said. "The place is in ruins, and I did hear, not long ago, that somebody run a threshin' machine through it, an' busted it up worse than before."</p>

<p>"Great horned toads!" cried Ned. "That must be the very factory Tom ran his tank through. And to think he should be a prisoner there!"</p>

<p>"Held by whom, do you suppose?" asked Mr. Damon.</p>

<p>"By that Blakeson gang, I imagine," Ned answered. "There's no time to lose. We must go to his rescue!"</p>

<p>"Of course!" agreed Mr. Damon. "We're much obliged to you for bringing this note," he went on to the farmer. "And here is something to repay you for your trouble," and he took out his wallet.</p>

<p>"Shucks! I didn't do this for pay!" objected the farmer. "It's a pity I wouldn't help anybody what's in trouble! If I'd a-knowed what it meant, me and Bub here would have gone to the factory ourselves, maybe, and done the work quicker. But I didn't know--what with war times and such-like--but that it would be better to deliver the note."</p>

<p>"It turns out as well, perhaps," agreed Ned. "We'll look after Tom now."</p>

<p>"And I'll come along and help," said the farmer. "If there's a gang of tramps in that factory, you may need some reinforcements. I've got a couple of new axe handles in my machine, and they'll come in mighty handy as clubs."</p>
</text>
