<text id="autogum_academic_doc131" title="Evaluating the Performances of Taiwan’s International Tourist Hotels: Applying the Directional Distance Function and Meta-Frontier Approach" shortTile="evaluating-performances" author="Yi-Lung Lee, Shew-Huei Kuo, Mei-Yi Jiang, Yang Li" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5773/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Methodology</head>
<p>
Conventional DEA models can only consider output expansion or input contraction, but not both. For the hotel industry, the output-oriented approach cannot distinguish between quasi-fixed inputs and variable inputs, while the input-oriented model ignores the existence of quasi-fixed inputs. Moreover, the primary goal of tourist hotels is to expand outputs rather than to contract inputs. The directional distance function, capable of expanding outputs and contracting inputs simultaneously, can fulfill the requirements of this study. In addition, because they may have different national cultures, operational philosophies, and managerial modes, different types of tourist hotels (for instance, domestic hotels and international chain hotels) should thus own different efficiency frontiers. A meta-frontier approach is able to measure efficiencies of decision making units (DMUs) associated with distinctive technologies.  </p>

<head> 3.1. Directional Distance Function</head>
<p>
Suppose that there are <hi rend="italic">H</hi> DMUs. Each DMU employs <hi rend="italic">N</hi> variable inputs  and <hi rend="italic">I</hi> quasi-fixed inputs  to produce <hi rend="italic">P</hi> outputs . The modified directional distance production is defined as:

(1)

where  is the technology set. Equation (1) searches for the largest feasible expansion of output vector  in the  direction and the largest feasible contraction of input vector  in the  direction. Note that we treat quasi-fixed input vector  as fixed. This specification not only can characterize the property of quasi-fixed inputs in the operational management of hotels, but also satisfy the request of output expansion. Let  be the optimal value of Equation (1). An efficient DMU corresponds to . In other words, the technology frontier is constructed by those DMUs associated with . Hence, the larger the value  is, the farther the DMU is from the frontier. </p>

<head> 3.2. Meta-Frontier Approach</head>
<p>
The production possibility set T in the DEA models is generally assumed to be convex, i.e., all DMUs belong to a single operating system. Due to different national cultures, operational philosophies, managerial modes, etc., domestic and foreign-owned hotels distinctly belong to different operating systems and thus the assumption of convexity may not be valid. The meta-frontier approach allows each group to have its own group-frontier. The meta-frontier is defined as a common boundary that envelops the group frontiers. The technology set associated with the meta-frontier could be convex or non-convex. We illustrate this by <figure>Figure 1</figure>. </p>

<p>Assume that there are two groups, A and B. The frontier of group A is the line segment connecting A1, A2, G, and A3. Similarly, the frontier of group B consists of points B1, G, B2, and B3. If the technology set is non-convex, then the relevant meta-frontier is the line segment connecting A1, A2, G, B2, and B3. It is apparent that each part of the meta-frontier belongs to at least one of the group-frontiers. If the technology set is convex, then the relevant meta-frontier is the line segment connecting A1, A2, B2, and B3. Convexity allows for input–output combinations beyond the boundaries of group-frontiers, such as the dot line connecting A2 and B2. It may imply that existing technology can upgrade through spillover and/or mutually learning among the groups for a considerable period. In this sense, the non-convex meta-frontier is suitable for analyzing efficiency in the short run, while the convex meta-frontier may be appropriate for analysis in the long run. We also follow the basic assumption that the quasi-fixed inputs cannot be adjusted in the short run, but they are variable in the long run. </p>

<p>We now describe how to incorporate the directional distance function in the meta-frontier approach. Let  be the meta-technology set that envelopes the G group frontiers such that , where  is the technology set of group <hi rend="italic">g</hi>, . The directional distance function relative to the meta-technology set can be expressed as:

(2)

</p>

<p>The directional distance function relative to the technology set of group <hi rend="italic">g</hi> can be defined as:

(3)

</p>

<p>This study applies the following approach to calculate the direction distance function for the non-convex meta-technology set: (1) calculate the direction distance function of each DMU based on the efficient frontier of group <hi rend="italic">g</hi>, say , <hi rend="italic">g</hi> = 1, 2,..., <hi rend="italic">G</hi>; (2) the relevant value of the direction distance function  for each DMU is the maximum of , i.e., . For G = 2, we write the linear programming of DMU <hi rend="italic">j</hi> under VRS as:

</p>

<p>Here,  and  are the non-radial <hi rend="italic">p</hi>th output slack and the <hi rend="italic">n</hi>th input slack, respectively;  is a small non-Archimedean quantity, usually . The first constraint labeled (4b) seeks the largest contraction of the <hi rend="italic">n</hi>th variable input in the direction . The constraints in (4c) search for the largest expansion of the <hi rend="italic">p</hi>th output in the direction . Expression (4d) holds the quasi-fixed inputs to be fixed in the short run. Constraints (4e) to (4g) ensure the technology is VRS.  </p>
</text>
