<text id="autogum_interview_doc294" title="part0_Shimon Peres discusses the future of Israel" shortTile="partshimon-peres" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-01-06" dateModified="2013-08-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Shimon_Peres_discusses_the_future_of_Israel" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Shimon Peres discusses the future of Israel</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 9, 2008</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Wikinews reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref> with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Shimon_Peres">Shimon Peres</ref>.Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>This year <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Israel">Israel</ref> turns sixty and it has embarked upon a campaign to celebrate its birthday.  Along with technology writers for <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slate.com">Slate</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PC%20Magazine">PC Magazine</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/USA%20Today">USA Today</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BusinessWeek">BusinessWeek</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aviation%20Weekly">Aviation Weekly</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> was invited by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/America-Israel%20Friendship%20League">America-Israel Friendship League</ref> and the Israeli Foreign Ministry to review Israel’s technology sector.  It's part of an effort to '<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Re-brand">re-brand</ref> the country' to show America that there is more to Israel than the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Israeli-Palestinian%20conflict">Palestinian conflict</ref>.  On this trip we saw the people who gave us the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pentium%20processor">Pentium processor</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ICQ">Instant Messaging</ref>. The schedule was hectic:  12-14 hours a day were spent doing everything from trips to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Weizmann%20Institute">Weizmann Institute</ref> to dinner with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Israel_Journal:_The_Holy_Land_has_an_image_problem">Yossi Vardi</ref>. </p>
<p>On Thursday, the fifth day of the junket, David Saranga of the foreign ministry was able to arrange an exclusive interview for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref>   with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/President%20of%20Israel">President of Israel</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nobel%20Peace%20Prize">Nobel Peace Prize</ref> recipient <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shimon%20Peres">Shimon Peres</ref>.  For over an hour they spoke about Iranian politics, whether Israel is in danger of being side-lined in Middle Eastern importance because of Arab oil wealth, and his thoughts against those who say Israeli culture is in a state of decay.  </p>
"<hi rend="bold">The only crime I committed was to be a little bit ahead of time. And if this is the reason for being controversial, maybe the reason is better than the result.</hi>"
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right"><hi rend="bold">—Peres on the ebb and flow of his popularity.</hi></p>
<p>Shimon Peres spent his early days on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/kibbutz">kibbutz</ref>, a bygone socialist era of Israel. In 1953, at the age of 29, Peres became the youngest ever Director General of the Ministry of Defense.  Forty years later it was Peres who secretly gave the green light for dialogue with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yassir%20Arafat">Yassir Arafat</ref>, of the verboten <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palestine%20Liberation%20Organization">Palestine Liberation Organization</ref>.  It was still official Israeli policy to not speak with the PLO.  Peres shares a Nobel Peace Prize with Yitzak Rabin and Arafat for orchestrating what eventually became the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oslo%20Accords">Oslo Accords</ref>.  The "roadmap" that came out of Oslo remains the official Israeli (and American) policy for peace in the Palestinian conflict.  Although the majority of Israeli people supported the plans, land for peace was met with a small but fiery resistance in Israel.  For negotiating with Arafat, former Prime Minister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benjamin%20Netanyahu">Benjamin Netanyahu</ref> shouted at Peres,  "You are worse than <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neville%20Chamberlain">Chamberlain</ref>!" a reference to Hitler's British appeaser.  It was during this time of heated exchanges in the 1990s that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yitzhak%20Rabin">Yitzhak Rabin</ref> was assassinated by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yigal%20Amir">Yigal Amir</ref>, a Jew who thought it against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Halakha">Halakhic law</ref> to give up land given by God (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Names%20of%20God%20in%20Judaism">Hashem</ref>).</p>
<p>Peres is the elder statesman of Israeli politics, but he remembers that he has not always been as popular as he is today.  "Popularity is like perfume: nice to smell, dangerous to drink," said Peres.  "You don’t drink it."  The search for popularity, he goes on to say, will kill a person who has an idea against the status quo.  </p>
</text>
