<text id="autogum_voyage_doc60" title="Pawleys Island" shortTile="pawleys-island" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=27039" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Pawleys Island</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.townofpawleysisland.com/">Pawleys Island</ref></hi> is a city and barrier island in the <ref target="Grand%20Strand">Grand Strand</ref> region of <ref target="South%20Carolina">South Carolina</ref>'s northern coast.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<p>If you are traveling by air, you will want to fly into the <hi rend="bold">Myrtle Beach International Airport</hi> (MYR). Regional carrier Spirit airlines runs regular routes from major airports, New York, Detroit, Atlantic City, etc. Other carriers include American, Delta, and United. Alternate airport is <ref target="Charleston%20%28South%20Carolina%29">Charleston</ref>, SC about 90 miles South.</p>

<p>Heading South on Highway 17 the trip from the Myrtle Beach airport is about 45 minutes when the traffic flow is not heavy. Highway 31 has a South bound expressway that creates greater access and easier traffic flow.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<p>If you're not driving to the island, you'll want to rent a car. There are no stores or restaurants on the island, and while the highly ambitious could walk or bike to the stores on the mainland, it's a long way and the entire trip is on the highway as there are no bike paths or sidewalks. You will be able to walk to the beach from everywhere on the island.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">All Saints Church cemetery</hi>. This cemetery features the graves of the poet James Dickey and the mysterious "Alice."</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<p>Pawleys Island is probably best described as a family vacation destination, and it's most famous for its relaxed atmosphere -- other than the Sea View Inn and the Pelican Bed and Breakfast, there are no businesses on the island. The main thing to do, of course, is hang out on the beach. Because of limited public parking, the beaches are not too crowded, and the type of sand and the shape of the beach make for a good beach experience. Surfing at Pawleys is somewhat popular, but South Carolina is not a surfing destination, and Pawleys is not the best surfing destination in South Carolina. However, there are good waves, and you can have a great time on a body board. Depending on the time of year, you can also catch some fish off the beach.</p>

<p>Pawleys Creek, behind the island, also offers a lot to do. Fishing in the creek can be decent, and if you're fishing from the shore or a dock, you do not need a fishing license. If you do not have access to a dock, you can fish in the creek from one of the two causeway bridges, near one of the two boat landings, or at the extreme north or south ends of the island. You can also get a small boats (skiffs) in the creek, though at low tide, the water gets pretty shallow in some spots. Those who fish from boats usually troll for flounder. Fish to be caught include flounder, red fish (a/k/a red drum, spot tail bass), speckled trout, black drum, and blue fish. Fishing bait and tackle is available at the Pawleys Island Hardware Store at the corner of North Causeway Rd. and US Hwy. 17 or at Pawleys Island Outdoors just north of the South Causeway on Hwy 17.</p>

<p>Crabbing is also a popular past-time in the creek, and the crabbing is almost always good. You can get a hand line and dip net or a ring net at the aforementioned bait stores and entertain the kids with an afternoon of crabbing. If you want to catch some serious crabs, you can leave a crab pot soaking overnight. While there are numerous clams and oysters in the creek, it is illegal to remove shell fish from the creek.</p>

<p>The creek is also a popular kayaking and paddle-boarding venue, and an internet search will provide you with plenty of choices for rentals. If you're in for a more relaxing time on the creek, a lot of folks get rafts or innertubes and just float down (or up) the creek with the tide.</p>

<p>There is a great deal to do off-island. The Grand Strand (the name for the string of South Carolina beaches from North Myrtle Beach in the north to just south of Pawleys Island) has numerous (perhaps a hundred) golf courses, all types of restaurants, amusement parks, water parks and museums. You can charter fishing trips, and the Winyah Bay near Georgetown and Hunting Beach State Park both offer great experiences for the nature lover.</p>

<head>Buy</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Litchfield Books</hi>, 14427 Ocean Hwy, Litchfield Landing, Unit G, Pawleys Island, South Carolina. Mon - Sun: 9am - 6pm. Independent Book Store</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Habanero's: Mexican</item>
<item> Pastaria 811: Italian</item>
<item> Hanser House: Seafood, etc.</item>
<item> Carolina Wings: American</item>
<item> Frank's &amp; Frank's Outback</item>
<item> Island Deli and Cafe</item>
<item> Landolfi's: Italian</item>
<item> Bove</item>
<item> High Hammock</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Louis's at Pawleys and The Fish Camp Bar</hi>, Highway 17 at the Hammock Shops. Open Daily from 11AM till 10PM weekdays and 11PM weekends. Owned and operated by Chef Louis Osteen, this restaurant is defined by his passionate devotion to the foods of his Southern ancestry and the Lowcountry. The chef is widely recognized for leading the charge in the preservation of Southern cooking traditions and an early proponent of using local ingredients. The business includes the elegant Louis's at Pawleys, the more casual Fish Camp Bar, or at the specialty food and fine wine market - Louis's To Go.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Palmetto Cheese</hi>, toll-free: +1-888-406-9823 . A brand of pimento cheese that originated at the Sea View Inn on Pawleys Island. It is still produced locally for the Pawleys Island area and can be found at Food Lion, Piggly Wiggly at Litchfield and Sea View Inn.</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sea View Inn</hi>, 414 Myrtle Ave, ☏ +1 843 237-4253 . Check-in: noon, check-out: 10AM. On a private beach with the ocean on one side, and a pristine salt marsh on the other. Charming and laid back, is smack in the middle of the island.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Vista Inn &amp; Suites</hi>, 7903 Ocean Highway, ☏ +1 843 237-4261 .</item>
</list>
</text>
