<text id="autogum_voyage_doc409" title="Schiphol Airport" shortTile="schiphol-airport" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=123859" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Schiphol Airport</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.schiphol.nl/index_en.html">Schiphol Airport</ref></hi> ( AMS ) is one of the busiest airports in the world. It is southwest of <ref target="Amsterdam">Amsterdam</ref> in the <ref target="Netherlands">Netherlands</ref>. It serves the city of Amsterdam and the rest of the Netherlands. It is one of the major hubs in Europe with flights between many destinations in Asia, Europe and North America. It is home to KLM, the Dutch flag carrier airline. As of 2016, Schiphol airport is the third busiest in Europe behind <ref target="London%20Heathrow">London Heathrow</ref> and <ref target="Paris%20Charles%20de%20Gaulle">Paris Charles de Gaulle</ref> and ahead of <ref target="Frankfurt%20Airport">Frankfurt Airport</ref> as measured by passenger numbers.</p>

<head>Orientation</head>
<p>Schiphol has a one-terminal concept. Which means, that all the departure halls are in one building. However, this can mean long walks from one connection flight to the other. The airport is divided in many different zones. The ground floor before security has the entrance of the airport, the railway station (with the platforms underground), the four Arrivals halls, and <hi rend="bold">Schiphol Plaza</hi>, the central shopping zone. On the 1st floor you can find the check-in desks and Departure Halls 1, 2 and 3. From this floor you can go to security and passport control if catching a non-Schengen flight and enter the transit area.</p>

<p>The terminal is divided into three lounges designated 1, 2 and 3. Piers (also known as concourses) connect to these lounges. It is possible to walk from one concourse to another, even to those connected to different lounges. However, keep in mind that if you're going from lounge 1 to lounge 2 and 3 you must clear immigration as you are leaving the Schengen area.</p>

<p>The exception to this is Lounge 4: it is only connected to Concourse M for low-cost carriers. Once past security, passengers in Concourse M cannot access any other lounges or concourses. Lounge 4 has very few facilities. If catching a connecting flight from one of the M gates, you must exit the secure zone though baggage claim and enter lounge 4 like any departing passenger.</p>

<p>Few airlines and destinations have a dedicated concourse. KLM and Transavia use all gates except for Concourses H and M.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Lounge 1 consists of concourses <hi rend="bold">B</hi> and <hi rend="bold">C</hi>, dedicated to Schengen areas. Gates <hi rend="bold">D59</hi> through <hi rend="bold">D87</hi>, the Schengen flights departing from gates D are reached by escalator from Lounge 1.</item>
<item> Lounge 2 consists of concourses <hi rend="bold">E</hi> and gates <hi rend="bold">D3</hi> through <hi rend="bold">D57</hi>,</item>
<item> Lounge 3 consists of concourses <hi rend="bold">F, G and H.</hi> They serve non-Schengen areas. Concourse H is used by low-cost carriers.</item>
<item> Lounge 4 consists of concourse <hi rend="bold">M</hi>, a dedicated Schengen area for low-cost carriers.</item>
</list>


<head>History</head>

<p>Schiphol opened on 16 September 1916 as a military airbase, with a few barracks and a field serving as platform and runways. When civil aircraft started to use the field (17 December 1920), it was often called Schiphol-les-bains. The Fokker aircraft manufacturer started a factory near Schiphol Airport in 1919. Schiphol's name is derived from a former fortification named Fort Schiphol which was part of the Defense Line of Amsterdam. Before 1852, the Haarlemmermeer polder in which the airport lies was a large lake, in the shallow waters of which sudden violent storms could claim many ships. This was the main reason for reclaiming it. In English, Schiphol translates to 'ship grave', a reference to the many ships lost in the area.</p>

<p>KLM was founded on 7 October 1919 by Albert Plesman, making it the oldest carrier in the world still operating under its original name, though the company stopped operating during World War II—apart from the operations in the Dutch Antilles in the Caribbean. The first KLM flight was on 17 May 1920, from Croydon Airport, London to Amsterdam carrying two British journalists and a number of newspapers. In 1921 KLM started scheduled services, and by 1926 it was offering flights to Amsterdam, Rotterdam, Brussels, Paris, London, Bremen, Copenhagen and Malmö. Intercontinental flights to the Netherlands East Indies started in 1929. This was for several years the world's longest scheduled air route.</p>

<p>On 1 November 1958 the airline opened the trans-polar route from Amsterdam via Anchorage to Tokyo. Each crew flying the transpolar route over the Arctic was equipped with a winter survival kit, including an AR-10 carbine for use against polar bears in the event the plane was forced down onto the polar ice. KLM merged with Air France in May 2004 to form Air France-KLM, but both airlines continue to fly under their distinct brand names.</p>

<head>Flights</head>

<p>KLM offers worldwide connections. Asia, Europe and North America are particularly well served. Delta Air Lines connects Schiphol with nine US destinations.</p>
<p>British Airways offer up to 15 flights per day to three airports in London. Transavia, Easyjet and other low-cost carriers provide a fairly economical way to city-hop to Amsterdam from other cities in Europe.</p>

<head>Ground transportation</head>
<p>For most travellers, the most convenient way to reach Amsterdam or other major destinations in the Netherlands from the airport is by train, with most destinations reachable either directly or with one transfer.</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>Most major destinations in the Netherlands can be reached from Schiphol either directly or with a single transfer. Use the ticket machines or ticket desks. All machines accept credit or debit cards but do require chip-and-PIN cards.</p>

<p>Alternatively, you can buy an <hi rend="italic"><ref target="Amsterdam%23Amsterdam%20Travel%20Ticket">Amsterdam Travel Ticket</ref></hi>, which includes a train return ticket to and from Schiphol to any of Amsterdam's stations, plus unlimited travel on all GVB trams, metro and (night)buses for 1, 2 or 3 days.</p>

<p>The train station at Schiphol is located underground, under the main airport hall; trains to Amsterdam Centraal usually run from platform 1 or 2. Note: this is not specific, one is never sure which platform it arrives. Information signs are updated when the train enters the tunnel. It is the same platform, though it matters on which side the train stops. This is why you'll see a lot of locals and tourists waiting just at the end of the escalators or stairs. They eventually go to the right track when it is updated.</p>

<p>For most destinations there are 1 or 2 trains per hour, for more regional destinations trains are more frequent. There are 4 to 5 trains per hour between Schiphol and Amsterdam in peak times. Regional trains run all night, although between 01:00 and 05:00 only once an hour. The price and duration of the journey are the same as during the day. However, trains for further destinations will generally not run at night. Check before you travel.</p>

<p>International trains to <ref target="Belgium">Belgium</ref> or <ref target="France">France</ref> stop at Schiphol.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Schiphol to Amsterdam Centraal</hi>. There are plenty of direct trains from the Schiphol to the Amsterdam Centraal. A journey takes 16-18 minutes. €4.20 if using an OV-chipkaart; €5.20 single ticket.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Schiphol to Amsterdam Lelylaan</hi>. If your accommodation is located near Vondelpark or Museumplein it's fastest to catch a train to Amsterdam Lelylaan station and connect to a tram from there. Trains leave every 5 to 10 minutes. €3.00 if using an OV-chipkaart; €4.00 single ticket.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Schiphol to Rotterdam Centraal</hi>. If traveling to Rotterdam the fastest way to travel is by taking the IC direct that takes you directly to Rotterdam by high-speed rail in 24 minutes. €14.80 if using an OV-chipkaart; €15.80 single ticket.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Schiphol to Paris Gare du Nord</hi>. Direct high speed Thalys trains run from Schiphol to Antwerp, Brussels-Midi and Paris. Tickets cannot be booked by using the machines at the station and need to be booked in advance or at the ticket office. There is no set price so it's cheapest the earlier you book.</item>
</list>
</text>
