<text id="autogum_voyage_doc488" title="Chickasaw National Recreation Area" shortTile="chickasaw-national" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=144720" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Chickasaw National Recreation Area</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Chickasaw National Recreation Area</hi> is in <ref target="Chickasaw%20Country">Chickasaw Country</ref> of <ref target="United%20States">United States</ref>.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<p>The Chickasaw National Recreation Area is easily accessible from Highway 7 and Highway 77 in <ref target="Sulphur%20%28Oklahoma%29">Sulphur (Oklahoma)</ref>. The National Park Service offices is located in the Chickasaw Visitor Center, adjacent to The Artesian Hotel at Highway 7 and Highway 77.</p>

<head>Fees and permits</head>
<p>There are no fees to enter the park. The Chickasaw National Recreation Area is free for drive-up and walk-up visitors.</p>

<head>Campground fees</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Non-utility campsite</hi>: $14.00 - Cold Springs, Guy Sandy, &amp; Rock Creek Campgrounds.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Non-utility campsite</hi>: $16.00 - Buckhorn and the Point Campgrounds</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Utility campsite</hi>: $22.00 - Buckhorn and the Point Campgrounds, and one site at Rock Creek Campground</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Premium utility site</hi>: $24.00 (May through September) - Buckhorn Campground, Loop D sites #24, 25, 26 and Buckhorn Campground, Loop C sites #4, 5, 6, 7</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Group sites</hi>: $30.00 - Rock Creek, Cold Springs &amp; Central Campgrounds</item>
</list>


<p><hi rend="italic">Persons may camp up to 14 consecutive days, not to exceed 30 days total between Memorial Day and Labor Day.</hi></p>

<p><hi rend="italic">The Senior or Access Pass 50% discount applies only to individual campsites and lake launching permits, not group sites.</hi></p>

<head>Boat launch fees</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Daily Permit: $4.00</item>
<item> Annual Pass: $30.00</item>
</list>


<head>Pavilion reservations</head>

<p>There are covered picnic pavilions located in the Buckhorn and Veteran's Lake areas. They are available by reservation for $30 per day.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lincoln Bridge</hi>.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<p>You can hike, swim, hunt, or go boating in the recreation area.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Travertine Nature Center</hi>. Open year-round, the Travertine Nature Center has opportunities for learning, classes and nature exhibits. Live, interactive learning is available for all ages. Open year-round except Christmas, Thanksgiving, New Year's Day.</item>
</list>


<head>Lodging</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Artesian Hotel, Casino &amp; Spa</hi>. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Chickasaw Retreat and Conference Center</hi>.</item>
</list>


<head>Camping</head>
<p>There are several campgrounds within the Chickasaw National Recreation Area:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Central Campground</hi> (available just off Highway 77 after entering the park), ☏ +1-877-444-6777 . Seasonal public campground in the Chickasaw National Recreation Area's Platt Historic District. 10 sites are available for camping. $30 per night.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cold Springs Campground</hi> (across the road from Travertine Creek), ☏ +1-877-444-6777 . Open May through September. 65 campsites are available for reservation. Sites are non-electrical and best suited for tent camping, but small RVs and pop-up campers may fit. Amenities: Water spigots and restrooms located close to camp sites. $30 per night.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Rock Creek Campground</hi> (near Veterans Lake and Rock Creek). Year-round campground near Veterans Lake and Rock Creek. There is easy access to hiking trails, fishing and mineral springs. 105 campsites and 1 group site are available for tent camping. Non-electrical sites can accommodate some RVs. Amenities include water spigots and restrooms close to campsites. $30 per night.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Buckhorn Campground</hi>, Buckhorn Road, ☏ +1-877-444-6777 . Four loops with 134 campsites available. All sites are first come, first served with showers available in restrooms. Some sites have electrical and water hookups available. utility: $22 per night, premium utility: $24 per night, non-utility: $16 per night.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Guy Sandy Campground</hi>. In the Arbuckle District of the park, Guy Sandy has 40 campsites available on a first come, first served basis. Water faucets and pit toilets available.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Point Campground</hi>, ☏ +1 877-444-6777 . 55 campsites available. Utility: $22 per night, non-utility: $16 per night.</item>
</list>


<head>Go next</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="http://www.turnerfallspark.com/">Turner Falls Park</ref>: A beautiful natural waterfall in the Arbuckle Mountains.</item>
</list>
</text>
