<text id="autogum_news_doc504" title="Götze to make Dortmund return, Schürrle completes Dortmund offensive lineup" shortTile="gotze-make-dortmund" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-07-22" dateModified="2017-12-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/G%C3%B6tze_to_make_Dortmund_return%2C_Sch%C3%BCrrle_completes_Dortmund_offensive_lineup" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Götze to make Dortmund return, Schürrle completes Dortmund offensive lineup</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, July 24, 2016</hi></p>
<p>On Thursday, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">German</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Football_(soccer)">football</ref> club <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Borussia_Dortmund">Borussia Dortmund</ref> (BVB) announced <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mario%20Götze">Mario Götze</ref> would rejoin the club from their arch rivals <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bayern_Munich">Bayern Munich</ref> after obligatory medical tests; Götze is to sign a four-year contract.  On Friday, BVB announced signing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/André%20Schürrle">André Schürrle</ref> from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/VfL_Wolfsburg">VfL Wolfsburg</ref>.</p>
<figure><caption>File photo of Mario Götze, 2011.  Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Steindy">Steindy</ref>.</caption></figure>
<head id="Götze_to_rejoin_his_boyhood_club">Götze to rejoin his boyhood club</head>
<p>2014 FIFA World Cup winning goal scorer Götze has spent twelve years with Borussia Dortmund, joining the youth ranks in 2001. The 24-year-old midfielder has scored 44 goals in 156 <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bundesliga">Bundesliga</ref> appearances; 22 goals for each club.  In three seasons with Bayern, Götze won three Bundesliga titles, two <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DFB-Pokal">DFB-Pokal</ref> titles, and a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UEFA%20Super%20Cup">UEFA Super Cup</ref>. With Dortmund, he won two League titles and a DFB Cup. Making his international debut in November 2010, Götze has played 56 matches and scored seventeen goals.</p>
<p>As both the clubs reached the agreement, Borussia Dortmund's CEO <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hans-Joachim%20Watzke">Hans-Joachim Watzke</ref> said, "Personally, I'm absolutely delighted that Mario has chosen to come back to Borussia Dortmund. Ever since his departure in 2013, I've always hoped that he would return to the club one day" ((de))German language: ‍Ich freue mich persönlich sehr, dass Mario sich für Borussia Dortmund entschieden hat. Ich habe seit seinem Weggang im Jahr 2013 immer gehofft, dass er eines Tages zu uns zurückkehren wird.</p>
<p>Götze said, " If I am now to return to my hometown club, then I want to try to win everyone over – especially those who do not welcome me back with open arms – with my performances." ((de))German language: ‍Wenn ich nun in meine Heimat zurückkehre, möchte ich versuchen, alle Menschen – gerade auch die, die mich nicht mit offenen Armen empfangen – durch Leistung zu überzeugen.</p>
<p>Götze would potentially play against Bayern in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DFL-Supercup">DFL-Supercup</ref> next month. </p>
<figure><caption>File photo of André Schürrle, 2011.  Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Steindy">Steindy</ref>.</caption></figure>
<head id="Schürrle_to_play_for_fourth_Bundesliga_club_of_his_career">Schürrle to play for fourth Bundesliga club of his career</head>
<p>Wolfsburg signed now-25-year-old André Schürrle from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Chelsea_F.C.">Chelsea F.C.</ref> in February 2015. Having also played for other two German clubs, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mainz%2005">Mainz 05</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bayer%20Leverkusen">Bayer Leverkusen</ref>, Schürrle has scored 48 goals in 174 Bundesliga appearances, and provided 29 assists. Schürrle has scored 20 goals for Germany in 55 appearances.</p>
<p>Borussia Dortmund's sporting director <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael%20Zorc">Michael Zorc</ref> said, " André Schürrle is a Germany international with outstanding attacking potential who is also a very good passer of the ball and consistently contributes neatly to his team's defensive play." ((de))German language: ‍André Schürrle ist ein deutscher Nationalspieler mit herausragendem Offensivpotenzial, der zudem sehr passsicher ist und sich auch in der Defensivarbeit immer wieder geschickt einbringt.</p>
<p>Schürrle had three years left in his contact with the Wolves, now signing for a five-year contract with BVB. The clubs did not disclose the transfer sum. Dortmund's sporting director added, "Our offensive lineup is now complete." ((de))German language: ‍Damit ist unsere Offensive komplettiert.
</p>
</text>
