<text id="autogum_whow_doc490" title="Recognize a Fake Ralph Lauren" shortTile="recognize-fake-ralph" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2017-08-22" dateModified="2019-07-13" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Recognize-a-Fake-Ralph-Lauren" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Recognize a Fake Ralph Lauren</head><p>Ralph Lauren is a popular designer company that sells bags and clothing. Unfortunately, given the brand's popularity, counterfeit Ralph Lauren products are common. If you're worried you may have purchased a fake Ralph Lauren, examine small details like the stitching and logos. If you do have a fake product, contact the Ralph Lauren company to report the issue.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Spotting Fake Clothing</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Check the logo. Ralph Lauren shirts often contain a small stitched on graphic of a polo player riding a horse. On a fake Ralph Lauren, the mallet the rider holds will be more circular than rectangular. The tail will be difficult to see and the horse's right back leg will be bent. On a genuine product, the horse's tail is clearly visible and the right back leg is straight. You should also be able to clearly see the outline of the rider's leg. On replicas, the leg often lacks definition. <figure rend="Recognize a Fake Ralph Lauren Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>As differences can be very subtle, it helps to look up an image of the actual logo for comparison. You may also want to use something like a magnifying glass to get a very close look at the Ralph Lauren logo on your product.</item></list></item>
<item>Examine the stitching. Turn your t-shirt inside out and examine the stitching on the bottom. A genuine Ralph Lauren should have one thin line of even stitching running along the bottom of the shirt. No stitching, or jagged and uneven stitching, indicates your product is fake. <figure rend="Recognize a Fake Ralph Lauren Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Look at the collar label. All Ralph Lauren products have labels under the collar indicating the size. The main collar label contains the Ralph Lauren logo and, to the right, a small tag is sticking out with the size written on it. If there is not a separate size label, the product is likely fake. The font should also be easily legible without misspellings. In addition to this, stitching along the collar should be the same color as the shirt. <figure rend="Recognize a Fake Ralph Lauren Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>High quality replicas can be extremely similar to authentic size labels, so look at a picture of a genuine size label online to compare it to your shirt's label. Even small changes in the font, including changes in spacing, can indicate a fake.</item></list></item>
<item>Examine the buttons. Buttons are secured with a neat pearl and cross stitch with thread that matches the color of the shirt. A different type of stitch, mismatched thread, or loose threads indicate a fake. <figure rend="Recognize a Fake Ralph Lauren Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Check the hem. Lay your shirt down a flat surface. The back hemline should be slightly longer than the front hemline. Hemlines of equal length, or a front hemline that's longer than the back, indicate a fake product. <figure rend="Recognize a Fake Ralph Lauren Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Read the care label. There should be a care label somewhere near the bottom of the shirt, which contains a trademark R and neat, evenly spaced copy. Illegible copy, or the absence of an "R," usually mean the product is fake. <figure rend="Recognize a Fake Ralph Lauren Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>As with other aspects of fake products, differences can be very subtle. It can help to look up a picture of a genuine Ralph Lauren label online to compare and contrast.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Identifying Fake Bags</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Check for sloppy stitching. Ralph Lauren is an expensive, high-end product. Stitching anywhere on the bag should be extremely neat and the same types of stitches should be used throughout the bag, including inside the pockets and on the underside of the bag. Inconsistent stitching and loose threads are signs of a fake product. <figure rend="Recognize a Fake Ralph Lauren Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Examine the material closely. Fake purses will have a stiff feel, indicating they're made from cheaper materials than authentic products. Color may be inconsistent throughout the bag, appearing darker or lighter in certain areas. Also, designer purses do not have lining while fake purses do. <figure rend="Recognize a Fake Ralph Lauren Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Check for inaccuracies in the label. The label should be stitched in. Hang tags are an obvious sign of a fake product. Fake labels often have misspellings, illegible font, and have sloppy stitching with loose threads. <figure rend="Recognize a Fake Ralph Lauren Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>In higher quality counterfeit products, differences may be extremely subtle. Look up a photo of a genuine Ralph Lauren label online and compare and contrast this to your bag's label.</item></list></item>
<item>Examine all the small details closely. Sometimes, small details are the only way to spot a fake product. The handles of your bag should be the same length, the logo should not be crooked, and zippers and buttons should be firmly attached and work properly. <figure rend="Recognize a Fake Ralph Lauren Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Designer products tend to be very high quality. It is unlikely that a designer bag would have any obvious flaws and imperfections.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Reporting a Fake Item</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Contact the company directly. Ralph Lauren is invested in cracking down on counterfeits. If you have a counterfeit product, report the issue by contacting Ralph Lauren by phone at 888-475-7674 or e-mailing them at RLcounterfeits@ralphlauren.com. Let them know you think you accidentally purchased a fake product and include the details of where you bought the product. <figure rend="Recognize a Fake Ralph Lauren Step 11 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Report any local counterfeiters to the police. If you bought a product from a local supplier, report the issue to the local authorities. If a business in your area is selling counterfeit products, the local police may want to investigate the matter themselves. The police may also be able to get you a refund for a counterfeit product. <figure rend="Recognize a Fake Ralph Lauren Step 12 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Stick to purchasing merchandise directly from Ralph Lauren. If you purchase products directly from Ralph Lauren stores or their website, this is a surefire way to get a genuine product. You can also purchase products at popular department stores that have a known relationship with the Ralph Lauren brand. <figure rend="Recognize a Fake Ralph Lauren Step 13 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Adhere to the adage, "If it sounds too good to be true, it probably is" when purchasing Ralph Lauren products. Ralph Lauren products will be more expensive than average, so if someone offers you a very cheap Ralph Lauren item, it's probably counterfeit.</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
