<text id="autogum_academic_doc433" title="Following the Water: Characterising de facto Wastewater Reuse in Agriculture in the Netherlands" shortTile="following-water-characterising" author="Jack  E. Beard, Marc  F.P. Bierkens, Ruud  P. Bartholomeus" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5936/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Wastewater, following treatment processes, is generally discharged into surface water bodies, whereupon it is transported and diluted. In areas with high population densities, this leads to a large percentage of water courses being impacted by treated wastewater (TWW). Indeed, a recent study by the EU Commission indicates that TWW is of a near ubiquitous presence in the surface water bodies of EU nations. In many regions, TWW discharge helps to maintain environmental flow capacities in surface water bodies and to recharge shallow aquifers. It is, however, likely that in areas where surface water bodies are highly impacted with wastewater, water quality concerns are an issue. Contaminants found in TWW include pathogenic microorganisms (concentrations in the range of 10−1-105 [cfu l−1), nutrients (nitrates and phosphates, 100-102 [mg l−1]), heavy metals (10−1-102 [µg l−1]) and endocrine disruptors (10−2-102 [µg l−1]). The presence of these in surface water bodies may lead to problems meeting WFD chemical water quality targets, negative impacts on ecology and reduced societal functions. Furthermore, if surface water bodies are infiltrating, the transfer of contaminants to groundwater may occur. This is highly dependent on subsurface characteristics and hydrological conditions, but is indicated by studies which find a range of TWW-related pharmaceuticals and personal care products in groundwater samples. </p>

<p>De facto (or indirect) wastewater reuse is the practice of extracting from a surface water body which is heavily influenced by discharge from a wastewater stream (see Appendix A) for anthropogenic use. In this form, TWW can constitute a freshwater resource for agriculture (irrigation), industry (cooling purposes) and public services (drinking water). The extent of its usefulness is, however, limited by its quality and the regulations associated with reuse. The EU recognise water as a resource which should be managed as a key element of the circular economy. Indeed, literature points to the direct reuse of TWW becoming a more common trend in the future, both internationally and in the EU, if appropriate regulations can be devised and the societal “yuck” factor can be overcome. These reports, however, generally neglect to include the occurrence of de facto reuse as a component of water reuse initiatives. This is reflected in the lack of regulations relating to the practice when compared to direct reuse. Given more knowledge on the topic, strategies could be better developed which would better integrate de facto reuse into freshwater management plans, complimenting existing water reuse schemes. </p>

<p>In the Netherlands, it is likely that wastewater is an important flow component in surface water bodies owing to high population densities and an extensive network of wastewater treatment plants (WWTPs). Moreover, the range of land and water usages located in proximity to WWTPs suggests that de facto reuse is prevalent nationally. Existing studies have shown that TWW exerts a significant impact on many surface water bodies in terms of water quality, but have failed to address the contribution of wastewater to the discharge of surface water bodies. Without this knowledge, it is impossible to draw links between wastewater discharges and societal water uses, hence neglecting the assessment of the occurrence of de facto water reuse. Characterising this problem has been (to date) confounded by difficulties in measuring and tracing the presence of TWW in a dynamic hydrological system. A range of approaches seek to address this; from comparing discharge datasets for rivers and WWTPs to interrogating population and hydrological datasets using GIS methods. This study opts for a new approach to this problem: repurposing a national scale water quality model and labelling TWW as a tracer in and of itself. This methodology gives a more continuous representation of the impaction of surface water bodies than previous efforts. As such, the distribution of TWW within the surface water network of the Netherlands can be characterised (without the need for direct measurements) and subsequently related to agricultural extractions, hence bridging the knowledge gap between TWW emissions and societal water uses.  </p>

<p>Via “following the water”, this study aims to determine whether TWW makes up a significant flow component for surface water bodies in the Netherlands and provide a first estimate of the extent to which de facto wastewater reuse is occurring in agricultural irrigation. This contributes to initiating discussions regarding appropriate regulations for de facto reuse and how the practice can be integrated within the circular economy to increase the responsible reuse of water sources.  </p>
</text>
