<text id="autogum_academic_doc546" title="3D Soft-Tissue Prediction Methodologies for Orthognathic Surgery—A Literature Review" shortTile="d-softtissue-prediction" author="Elena  Carlotta Olivetti, Sara Nicotera, Federica Marcolin, Enrico Vezzetti, Jacqueline  P. A. Sotong, Emanuele Zavattero, Guglielmo Ramieri" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/9/21/4550/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion and Conclusions</head>
<p>
In this systematic review we have summarized twenty-four studies focused on the evaluation of soft-tissue prediction software for maxillofacial surgery. The treated software are commonly used in clinical procedures to have a preview of the patients’ outcome after corrective surgery; the most common methodologies on which these software are based are the mass spring model, the finite element model and the mass tensor model, each of them with its advantages and disadvantages. MSM presents an easy architecture and a low memory usage but it has no real biomechanical foundations; FEM is more relevant from a biomechanical point of view, but it has a high computational cost and a rather long simulation time; MTM tries to combine the advantages of MSM and of FEM. In particular, the lip region is the most difficult to predict, since lips do not rely on bony structures; moreover, it is difficult to replicate the same lip position from one acquisition to another. Due to this particularity, lips are supposed to be particularly involved in involuntary displacements caused by surgeries performed on different facial areas. The difficulty in accurately predicting the appearance of this sub region is a crucial point in the development of a prediction method, since it is particularly related to aesthetic self-perception and satisfaction of the patient. With respect to the traditional algorithms based on hard- to soft-tissue ratio, methodologies involving biomechanical models of viscoelasticity of the soft tissue to mimic its elastic deformation seems to be able to give a more realistic simulation. Despite the number of computer programs dedicated to three-dimensional prediction and surgical planning, maxillofacial practitioners often prefer to rely on conventional two-dimensional methods. This fact could be explained with the overall results given by these methodologies, which seem to be only partially relevant and/or reliable in the practice of daily clinical activity. Concerning the works based on Maxilim, Shafi et al. found that this software makes a clinically satisfactory prediction of soft tissue changes, but with an over-prediction of the position of the upper lip; according to Liebregts et al., its accuracy is influenced by the magnitude of maxillary and mandibular movements, by the age of the patient and by the usage of V-Y closure, and these authors further reported a low predictability of lower and upper lips. Moreover, a general tendency was reported towards an under-prediction in the area around the cheek and chin and towards an over-prediction at the mandibular inferior border. It was suggested that Maxilim inaccuracy in the prediction of the lip region might be due to the modelling algorithm, i.e., mass tensor, and might indicate a non-linear response of the upper lip. The study by De Riu et al., although not directly focused on soft tissue prediction, reports that inaccuracies in virtual planning are primarily due to the soft-tissue virtual model. </p>

<p>With regard to Dolphin software, Resnick et al. reported that the ability to predict 3D soft tissue changes was limited, with an accuracy that may be acceptable for linear changes but not for lateral facial points. Peterman et al. reported various degrees of accuracy at each soft-tissue landmark in the horizontal and vertical axes; lower lip prediction was the least accurate. A similar result of low prediction accuracy for the lower lip region is reported by Pektas et al.. Conversely, two articles affirmed that the statistical differences between Dolphin soft tissue prediction and the real outcome of the patient did not invalidate the software prediction, as it was close to real surgical results. Dolphin 3D imaging uses a landmark-based photographic morphing algorithm that was developed for two-dimensional prediction and then adapted to three-dimensional prediction; this could be an explanation for its imprecisions. Moreover, it requires plotting 79 landmarks on the CT volume (42 for the hard tissue and 37 for the soft tissue); the localization of such a large number of points seems to require too much time for a stable usage in clinical daily practice. </p>

<p>Among the other considered software, SurgiCase_CMF was analyzed by Bianchi et al. and Marchetti et al.; they reported that the percentage of error was less than 2 mm for the majority of patients, but in both studies an important error in the areas of lips and chin was reported. Khambay et al., Terzic et al. and Ullah et al. used 3dMDvultus to predict soft tissue changes; in general, they reported that its use on specific anatomical regions was more meaningful than on the full face. Moreover, they reported an insufficient prediction accuracy particularly for the lower part of the face with errors exceeding 3 mm, and for nasal and paranasal regions. Surprisingly, prediction results seemed to be reliable for lips and chin. </p>
</text>
