<text id="autogum_interview_doc322" title="part9_John Reed on Orwell, God, self-destruction and the future of writing" shortTile="partjohn-reed-orwell" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-18" dateModified="2015-01-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Reed_on_Orwell%2C_God%2C_self-destruction_and_the_future_of_writing" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Clearly a lot can be gained from literature, and as you've have shown talking about Shakespeare here.  But you think there might be a problem with building a new generation of readers, in that we train people to read things that they can't relate to?  It would be like raising kids to watch <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bette%20Davis">Bette Davis</ref> movies, and then you get to watch the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harry%20Potter%20films">Harry Potter film</ref>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Exactly.  I think that is exactly the problem.  It is exactly the problem, and I can't iterate strongly enough that I feel like people should be reading contemporary books, that we should melt down the canon and have people reading contemporary authors.  There are amazing contemporary authors, and if you were to walk around the basement of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strand%20Bookstore">Strand</ref> for a day and look at all the review books down there, and tell me that there aren't amazing contemporary authors, I'll cede the point.  But I know.  I know you won't come out of that basement and tell me that.  There are just so many amazing authors, people who are writing extremely well right now.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is there at all a movement for that?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  I don't know but I actually think that it's going to happen, partly because of the public domain, the downloadable Internet.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But can't you see such a reaction against that change?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Yeah, I can.  No, I can already hear someone harping "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William%20Faulkner">Faulkner</ref> lost to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toni%20Morrison">Toni Morrison</ref>?!?"</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  [laughs]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Well, first of all, Faulkner isn't going to be lost, right?  And second of all, the Toni Morrison books you're talking about are twenty-five years old.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  There's a magical thing that happens when people feel they discover things that went to the wayside--think about bell bottoms!  I remember in the early 90s, the idea of bell bottoms, or even just large pants at the bottom, was just anathema.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Yeah. Yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And then all of a sudden it's like people get bored with the same thing, and boom! Bell bottoms are back.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Yeah.  It doesn't seem so foreign now.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  People who are raised watching "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Die%20Hard">Die Hard</ref>" and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arnold%20Schwarzenegger%20">Schwarzenegger</ref>, all of a sudden they discover old <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joan%20Crawford">Joan Crawford</ref> films.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Yeah, the literary canon is not going to disappear.  Having people read contemporary authors is just going to build a readership of contemporary readers.  I don't know why we're having kids read books that bore them.  There are just so many good books out there.</p>
<head id="On_belief_in_a_higher_power">On belief in a higher power</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you believe in a higher power?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  I think that my feeling about the higher power is in keeping with most of America, in a lot of ways--we think of ourselves as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Religion%20in%20the%20United%20States">Christian nation</ref>, but in fact, we also think we can pick and choose what we want about religion.  Most people, if you press them, their concept of God is something like a divine spark within them or something that we all share.  Which is very in keeping with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gnostic">Gnostic</ref> principle--we call it Gnosticism now--but a Gnostic principle of Christianity.  And I would put myself somewhere in there.</p>
</text>
