<text id="autogum_voyage_doc533" title="Benguet" shortTile="benguet" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=3404" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Benguet</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Benguet Province</hi> is in <ref target="Luzon">Luzon</ref> in the <ref target="Philippines">Philippines</ref>.</p>

<p>Benguet is home to the Ibaloy, Kankana-ey, and Kalanguya peoples. Benguet became a full province in 1968.</p>

<head>Cities and towns</head>
<p>Benguet is divided into 13 municipalities, mostly rural and sparsely populated, each having a central town. Baguio is the only city, but is politically independent from Benguet, but is still part of Benguet geographically.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> – Dubbed the "Summer Capital of the Philippines" and "City of Pines" for its cool climate and pine trees, it is the tourist hub and the commercial center or the province.</item>
<item> – Provincial capitals, with its draws like its strawberry farms and a village with painted houses reminiscent of the favelas of <ref target="Rio%20de%20Janeiro">Rio de Janeiro</ref></item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> – The second highest mountain in the Philippines, and the highest in Luzon.</item>
</list>
<head>Geography</head>
<p>Benguet occupies over of land area, mostly mountainous terrain. The capital is <ref target="La%20Trinidad%20%28Benguet%29">La Trinidad</ref>.</p>

<p>At above sea level, the province lies on top of the Cordillera Mountains containing <ref target="Mount%20Pulag">Mount Pulag</ref>, the second highest mountain in the Philippines. Amidst these mountain peaks is a wide plateau wherein the capital town, La Trinidad, is located.</p>

<p>The province is bounded on the south by Pangasinan and on the west by La Union and Ilocos Sur, Benguet serves as the gateway to the highland provinces of the Cordillera Region.</p>

<head>Climate</head>
<p>Benguet has a more temperate climate due to its altitude. Daytime highs rarely reach , but the nighttime lows can reach below during the cool season, causing frost that can destroy vegetables.</p>

<head>People</head>

<p>In the sparsely populated Cordillera Region, Benguet stands out as having the highest population among the provinces with over 300 thousand and a population density of over 115 people per square km (300 people per square mile). Migrants have joined the local tribes such as the Kankana-eys, Ibaloys and Kalanguyas to settle in this rich highland province. Although the three tribes speak different languages and dialects, they share similar cultures and have common beliefs and rituals.</p>

<head>History</head>

<p>During the Spanish Era, Benguet was not a remote area for the Spaniards to explore. The vastness and promising economic potential of the place lured the Spaniards to conduct a series of expeditions. Series of attempts to pacify the "Igorots" but failed. Finally in 1846, commandante de Galvey established his Commandante at La Trinidad, Benguet (named after his wife). The first Kapitan of Benguet was Pulito of Kafagway, Now Baguio, a minor rancheria of about 20 houses.</p>

<p>The Americans came early in 1900 and established its government with H. Whitmarsh as the appointed governor of Benguet and Baguio City as the capital. This was the first provincial government to be established in the Philippines and this happened a year prior to the inauguration of the civil government of the Philippines. Their best administrators and teachers were fervent boosters and promoters: Worcester, Wright Forbes, Pack Barrows, Eckman and others who together with Filipinos committed to make the place a haven.</p>

<p>The mines near Baguio were developed and became productive. Business in the city flourished with commercial centers put up. Recreation facilities were installed. The city was growing before the outbreak of the war.</p>

<p>Baguio was bombed December 8, 1941 by the Japanese and they occupied it on December 27 of the same year, However, the war changed course and on September 3, 1945, General Yamashita surrendered to the Americans at the US Ambassador's residence in Camp John Hay, after which, Baguio immediately set to the task of rehabilitation.</p>

<head>Talk</head>
<p>The major language is <ref target="Ilocano">Ilocano</ref>, brought by lowland migrants who settled in the province, but there are also many indigenous languages, such as Kankana-ey, Ibaloi, and Kalanguya. The people of the province can also converse in English, especially the younger populations. Ilocano or Tagalog is much useful when communicating with locals.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<p>The province of Benguet can be accessed through five national roads; Kennon Road, Aspiras – Palispis Highway and Naguilian Road are the main routes coming from Manila, while the Benguet-Nueva Vizcaya Road and Halsema Highway offer entry to the Province of Nueva Vizcaya and to the rest of the Cordillera Region.</p>

<p>Benguet can also be reached by air through the Loakan airport in Baguio City, but is limited to general aviation and private aircraft.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<p>One can get around the province by public transportation such as jeepney, bus, and passenger bus. Taxis are limited around Baguio and La Trinidad, and the more ubiquitous tricycle replace them in the towns.</p>

<p>By road, the most important highway is the winding <hi rend="bold">Halsema Highway</hi> (Route 204, officially the <hi rend="bold">Baguio-Bontoc Road</hi>), which starts at La Trinidad and stretching north through the town of <ref target="Bontoc">Bontoc</ref> in <ref target="Mountain%20Province">Mountain Province</ref>. It is a critical lifeline between the mountain towns and <ref target="Baguio">Baguio</ref>, has the highest point in the Philippine highway network, at above sea level over the municipality of <ref target="Atok">Atok</ref>. Driving there is quite dangerous due to the numerous sharp curves, unguarded cliffs, and landslides during rainy season. Halsema Highway is a toll road, and you must pay ₱20 at the toll barriers at each end of the highway.</p>

<p>If you have your own vehicle but are not familiar with the town you want to visit, people will be willing to help you with the directions.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Benguet Museum</hi>, Capitol, La Trinidad, 2601 Benguet. M-F 9AM-5PM. Provincial museum containing ethnographic materials relating to the indigenous people of Benguet. Free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kabayan Branch Museum</hi>, Kabayan. M-Sa 8AM-noon, 1-5PM. Kabayan Museum is established to protect and care the Kabayan Mummy Caves in the province. Mummy Caves are one of the country's national cultural treasures. It is a burial caves that holds mummies sited in Kabayan especially in the Timbac Caves. The building is placed in a lot donated by citizens who value the culture of the Ibaloi and the Kankanaey. It is a one-story building and a basement builds in a 500-m² lot in 1989. Also kept here are ethnographical, ecological and geological collections including artifacts and other relics of the Kabayan Mummies. Free.</item>
</list>


<head>Historical sites and land marks</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Camp Utopia (Sagubo, Kapangan):</hi> This was the camp of the 66th Infantry Battalion during the Second World War. It was also the site where the late Major Bado Dangwa and Major Dennis Molintas led the defense of the Igorotlandia.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kaliwaga Cave (Kaliwaga, Kapangan):</hi> The burial place of the British soldiers of fortune who came to Benguet during the 15th century.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Guerilla Saddle (Km. 26, Atok):</hi> Where the fiercest battle between the advancing Japanese Imperial Forces and the United States Armed Forces - 66th Infantry was fought to the advantage of the guerrilla resistance movement. A lot of Japanese soldiers have fallen and perished on this spot. Thus, Atok is known as the Vanguard of Freedom in Benguet.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Darew Ancient Ruins of Civilization (Kapangan):</hi> Located at the top of the mountain west of Kapangan. It commands a vantage view of the coastline to the west and fertile valley to the east. For many years, the people lived in peace and prosperity. From this area, they traded and intermarried, forged alliances and came to recognize as kin those who lived in more populous settlements of Tagudin, Agoo, Tubao, Ambanganan (Pugo), Lingayen, Dagupan, Binalonan, Tayug, Safid (San Manuel), Imogen, Ituy, Tinok and Ahin.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hill WW II (Mankayan):</hi> Site where the 66th Infantry Battalion and guerrillas fought to make their way to Besang Pass. The capture of Hill WW II opened the right flank guard of the Japanese Imperial Garrison to bombardment and constant attack by Igorot freedom fighters.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lamtang (Puguis, La Trinidad):</hi> The escape route of then President Sergio Osmena and party who were escorted by a detachment of the 66th Infantry Battalion to Camp Valhalla, Kapangan then to San Gabriel, La Union during the World War II.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Klondykes Stone Walls (Klondykes, Tuba):</hi> Remnant of the first American building used by the American engineers who constructed Kennon Road. It is believed to have been built in 1902 and is still visible today.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cariño Cave (Eddet, Kabayan)</hi>: The hiding place of Governor Ora Cariño and the place where he was captured by the Americans in 1900.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Manenchen (Manenchen, Kabayan):</hi> The site of the massacre of Eddet residents by the Japanese Imperial Army during the World War II.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kennon Road (Tuba):</hi> One of the legacies of the American Administration. It was the first Benguet road to be constructed by the Americans in 1902. The completion of this road opened the entire Benguet Province to vehicular traffic and marked the entry of Americans, Europeans, Japanese, Chinese and lowlanders to the Province of Benguet. It was referred as the Benguet Road until it was renamed Kennon Road by virtue of Executive Order No. 9 in 1922, in honor of Col. Lyman W. Kennon, the American engineer who supervised and finished the construction of the road in 1905.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kabayan Pyramid (Poblacion, Kabayan):</hi> It is also called the "Kinepol ni Nabaloi." The burial tomb of Henry A. Kamora, the Grand Old Man of Kabayan which is located at the municipal compound.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Embosi:</hi> It is the first known Ibaloi settlement. The place is found at Gusaran, Kabayan.</item>
</list>
</text>
