<text id="autogum_interview_doc146" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Irene Villa" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-02-25" dateModified="2013-11-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Irene_Villa" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Irene Villa</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 26, 2013</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Irene Villa after the interview with the Wikinews reporters.Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Raystorm">Raystorm</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>Yesterday evening in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/La_Molina_(ski_resort)">La Molina</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Spain">Spain</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> sat down and talked with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irene%20Villa">Irene Villa</ref> to discuss <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Para-alpine_skiing">para-alpine skiing</ref>, disability sport, women's sport, and her own sporting career.  Villa was in town as part of activities taking place around the 2013 <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/IPC_Alpine_World_Championships">IPC Alpine World Championships</ref>, where one of her skiing club teammates is competing as a member of the Spanish team.  Her high profile in Spain has brought additional interest to para-alpine skiing and disability sport in general.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Hi we are interviewing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irene%20Villa">Irene Villa</ref>, who is a disability skier from Spain and professional author, social figure, journalist, and psychologist. You are most well known for being a terrorist survivor, but you're here because of the [2013 Alpine Skiing] World Championships. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Hola estamos entrevistando a Irene Villa, esquiadora española, escritora, figura política, psicóloga y periodista. Aunque se le conoce más por haber sobrevivido a un atentado, se encuentra aquí por el Campeonato del Mundo [de Esquí Adaptado 2013].</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Irene Villa</hi>: I'm here because I love sitting ski, I practice and I compete, but since I got pregnant and my son was born I stopped competing. But before I had my son I competed against the people who will run tomorrow, the Germans who win, and I wanted to be here. I haven't raced in the World Cup, but I did race in the European Cup. And well, I'm also here to support paralympic sports. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Estoy aquí porque me encanta el esquí en silla, lo practico y he competido, pero desde que nació mi hijo dejé de competir, porque me quedé embarazada, pero antes de tener a mi hijo competí contra las que mañana corren, las alemanas que ganan, y quería estar aquí. Nunca Copa del Mundo, he corrido Copa de Europa. Y bueno, para apoyar al deporte paralímpico.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : In 2009 you said you were trying to make the 2010 Winter Paralympics. After giving birth are you going to continue with the sport and hope to make 2018? ((es))Spanish language: ‍En 2009 dijo que quería clasificarse para los Juegos Paralímpicos de Invierno de 2010. Tras dar a luz, ¿va a continuar con el deporte e intentar llegar a 2018?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Irene Villa</hi>: I would love to. The thing is that you need a certain amount of IPCAS points. I'm now competing, on top of that I have an injury, tomorrow and the next day I will be training, and I don't know if I'll have enough time to make it. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2014_Winter_Paralympics">Sochi</ref> [Winter Paralympic Games of 2014] is right around the corner, next year, so it depends on how many point you've got. 2018? For sure. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Me encantaría. Lo que pasa que bueno, eso no se sabe, porque tienes que tener unos puntos IPCAS determinados y yo ahora estoy compitiendo, encima me he lesionado, y mañana y pasado voy a estar esquiando, y no sé si van a dar los tiempos  para llegar... Es que Sochi [Juegos Paralímpicos de 2014] está aquí al lado. Son el año que viene. Entonces depende de los puntos IPCAS que tengas. ¿2018? Seguro que sí.</p>
</text>
