<text id="autogum_academic_doc561" title="Estimating Rainfall Interception of Vegetation Canopy from MODIS Imageries in Southern China" shortTile="estimating-rainfall" author="Jianping Wu, Liyang Liu, Caihong Sun, Yongxian Su, Changjian Wang, Ji Yang, Jiayuan Liao, Xiaolei He, Qian Li, Chaoqun Zhang, Hongou Zhang" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-4292/11/21/2468/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
Water source conservation is one of the most important vegetation functions in the terrestrial ecosystem. As an interface for atmospheric rainfall in the vegetation ecosystem, vegetation canopy influences the redistribution of rainwater as well as the damping and retention of the water that reaches the soil, affecting runoff dynamics through interception. However, previous studies on canopy rainfall interception have mainly focused on individual plants or groups of plants through in situ observation and are limited by spatiotemporal estimation in larger areas. In this study, we applied a canopy rainfall interception model coupled with MODIS_LAI remote sensing data to understand the spatial and temporal variation patterns of canopy rainfall interception at the basin scale in Guangdong Province, China. </p>

<p>From this study, we found that the CRIR at the basin scale in Guangdong ranged from 0.33% and 11.67%, which is similar to results in other studies in China that ranged from 0% and 12%. However, this range is lower than that in forest ecosystems. This is mainly because our study estimated the mean value of the CRIR for all vegetation ecosystems in the basin, which resulted in a lower estimated value when compared with that of a forest ecosystem. It is worth noting that the rainfall interception model applied in our study only considered the parameters of the LAI and rainfall, while rainfall interception was also closely related to many other factors such as atmospheric drivers of evaporation (e.g., wind speed, vapor pressure deficit, etc.), canopy characteristics, rainfall intensity, and rainfall duration. In future research, introducing more meteorological factors into the interception model is necessary to estimate canopy rainfall interception more accurately. </p>

<p>It is important to note that, according to the analysis using the equations of cumulative interception (Equations (1) and (2)) and CRIR (Equation (3)), the spatiotemporal variation of the LAI and rainfall will have a similar influence on the annual and regional variation of vegetation canopy rainfall interception at the basin scale of Guangdong. We also found that the CRIR showed a significant spatial difference pattern that was high in the mountain areas of the eastern and western flanks, but low in the central mountainous region and coastal areas. This spatial pattern was closely related to the LAI of vegetation, which mainly presents a spatial pattern extending from the Pearl River Delta to the periphery, and has little correlation with the spatial pattern characteristics of rainfall that gradually decrease from south to north. Guangdong has many heavy rainfall events, and the leaves tend to reach their maximum saturation of rainfall interception, resulting in vegetation canopy rainfall interception depending mainly on the LAI, but not being restricted by the amount of rainfall. In addition, atmospheric rainfall is the main factor influencing the temporal variation of rainfall interception in the study area. Results showed that the annual mean CRIR in Guangdong continued to decrease from 2004 to 2012, but increased slightly in 2016. However, as time progressed, the difference in CRIRs between the basins decreased. This is because, as the annual mean LAI and annual rainfall increase, the spatial heterogeneity of LAI also increases (<figure>Figure 4</figure>), while the spatial heterogeneity of rainfall decreases (<figure>Figure 2</figure>). Combining the effects of the saturation of canopy rainfall interception and rainfall, the spatial homogeneity of annual rainfall magnifies the effects on the spatial pattern of CRIRs, while the spatial heterogeneity of annual mean LAI further diminishes the effects on spatial patterns of CRIR. This has led to decreases in both the CRIR and its spatial variability over time. </p>

<p>Importantly, broad-leaved forests are the main contributor to canopy rainfall interception in Guangdong. By analyzing the CRIRs of the basin-pairs in the four climatic zones with a similar forest coverage, we found that there was no significant difference in the canopy rainfall interception among the four climatic zones, while there was a significant correlation between forest coverage and the canopy rainfall interception within the basin. This means that canopy rainfall interception is far more affected by vegetation coverage than the background climate. In addition, the proportion of broad-leaved forest to the whole area of forest in the basin plays a critical role in the CRIR in Guangdong, which is similar to other results from previous research. However, many studies conducted in various forests have reached the opposite conclusion, demonstrating that the canopy interception capacity in coniferous forests was higher than that in broad-leaved forests. Researchers have found that the leaf surface area contributes to differences in the interception capacities between broad-leaved forests, coniferous forests, and coniferous and broad-leaved mixed forests, and the total annual interception was greater for the species with a denser canopy (e.g., broad-leaved forest). However, since the canopy interception capacity is also determined by other meteorological and canopy parameters, further research is needed on these other factors. </p>
</text>
