<text id="autogum_interview_doc499" title="part2_Eric Bogosian on writing and the creative urge" shortTile="parteric-bogosian" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-16" dateModified="2014-05-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eric_Bogosian_on_writing_and_the_creative_urge" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  What the book's really about is people who are there at the mall at the time.  There's some kids in the food court; there's a woman shopping; and there's another guy shopping for something else.  A security guard.  All these people get pulled into what happens, and that affects them.  That system of writing a story--it's a pinwheel narrative, which has become very popular in movies these days, where you go from character to character to character; all the stories are happening at the same time--that was a great way for me to focus on what I do best, which is to sit with each character, but at the same time have a very clear story.  The reason that I went into the prose book world was the nature of audiences.  I mainly had written theater, and that audience is such a narrow bandwidth of people, as in those who actually go to the theater at this point.  You know demographics and age and so forth, I--they don't actually really reflect even my tastes.  Because it's generally theater's for sort of an upper middle class--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you have an audience in mind when you write?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  I think of people like myself; people who like the kind of movies I like, the kind of people who read the kind of books I read and listen to my kind of music.  contemporary, you know, just like what somebody who maybe is in their thirties might be going to see or something, because it's got more energy and action and--that's the kind of stuff I like.  I like louder, stronger, more edgy kind of stuff.  That doesn't exist in the theater for the most part, I think because of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amazon.com">Amazon</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think the audience is shrinking for that sort of narrative?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  No, with the advent of online bookstores the audience exploded about ten years ago.  All of a sudden there were audiences for books that weren't upper middle class audiences, but a younger audience that wanted to read more edgy stuff.  And you saw the rise of [Dave] <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dave%20Eggers">Eggers</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20Foster%20Wallace">David Foster Wallace</ref>; really interesting writers suddenly came to the fore and I thought to myself, <hi rend="italic">I can write a book and find an audience--they can be out there anywhere.</hi>  They can be in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alberta,%20Canada">Alberta, Canada</ref>, and they can get my book.  But if I write a play--the play world is just a really different world.  I discovered that when I wrote a book, that the book world is very crowded.  And in fact, I'm already a member of the very-hard-to-get-into theater world, so I have a greater edge; I have a greater sort of built-in advantage when I work in the theater, because I'm a bona fide theater guy.  You can walk into any bookstore, and you will see in terms of literary fiction that there's going to be twenty new titles every two weeks.  They're going to be there for a few weeks, and then they're going to be gone and there will be twenty more titles.  And every once in a while, one breaks out, but they're all competing with each other.</p>
</text>
