<text id="autogum_bio_doc476" title="Thomas Eden" shortTile="thomas-eden" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-03-10" dateModified="2019-09-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Eden" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Thomas Eden</head>For the obstetric physician, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Watts_Eden">Thomas Watts Eden</ref>. For the Treasurer of Ceylon, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Eden_(civil_servant)">Thomas Eden (civil servant)</ref>. For the cricketer, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Eden_(cricketer)">Thomas Eden (cricketer)</ref>.
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Thomas Eden</hi> (died 18 July 1645) was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/England">English</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jurist">jurist</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academia">academic</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Politician">politician</ref> who sat in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Commons_of_England">House of Commons</ref> from 1640 to 1645.</p>
<head>Background</head>
<p>Eden was the youngest son of Richard Eden of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South_Hanningfield">South Hanningfield</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Essex">Essex</ref> and his wife Margaret Payton, daughter of Christopher Payton of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bury_St._Edmunds">Bury St. Edmunds</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suffolk">Suffolk</ref>, and was born in the south part of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sudbury,_Suffolk">Sudbury</ref> within the county of Essex. From Sudbury school, he was sent to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pembroke_Hall,_Cambridge">Pembroke Hall, Cambridge</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Venn-1">[1]</ref> He migrated to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trinity_Hall,_Cambridge">Trinity Hall, Cambridge</ref>, where he was admitted a scholar on 31 December 1596. He was elected to a fellowship 10 July 1599, and afterwards he held the office of reader of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Civil_law_(legal_system)">civil law</ref> in his college for many years. On 10 November 1613, being then <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bachelor_of_Laws">LL.B.</ref>, he was chosen to succeed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clement_Corbet">Clement Corbet</ref> as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Professor_of_Law_at_Gresham_College">Professor of Law at Gresham College</ref>, London. In March 1615, he held a disputation for the degree of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Legum_Doctor">LL.D.</ref>  before <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_I_of_England">James I</ref> at Cambridge, which earned great applause.  He was created doctor in the following year. On 4 November 1615, he was admitted a member of the College of Advocates at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doctors'_Commons">Doctors' Commons</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Venn-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Eden was elected <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Member_of_Parliament">Member of Parliament</ref> (MP) for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cambridge_University_(UK_Parliament_constituency)">Cambridge University</ref> in 1626.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Willis-2">[2]</ref> On 4 September 1626, he was chosen master of Trinity Hall on the resignation of Dr. Corbet.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Venn-1">[1]</ref>  He was re-elected MP for Cambridge University in 1628 and sat until 1629 when King Charles decided to rule without parliament for eleven years.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Willis-2">[2]</ref> He was appointed chancellor of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diocese_of_Ely">diocese of Ely</ref> in 1630 and he was also <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Commissary">commissary</ref> of Westminster, Bury St. Edmunds, and Sudbury, and one of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Court_of_Chancery">masters in chancery</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Venn-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In April 1640, Eden was re-elected MP for Cambridge in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Short_Parliament">Short Parliament</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Willis-2">[2]</ref> He resigned his professorship at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gresham_College">Gresham College</ref> on 27 July 1640.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Venn-1">[1]</ref> In November 1640, he was re-elected MP for Cambridge University for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Long_parliament">Long parliament</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Willis-2">[2]</ref>  On 3 May 1641, he joined with those members of the House of Commons who took the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protestation_of_1641">Protestation</ref>. The speaker informed the house on 7 Sept. 1642 that he had received commission from Dr. Eden and that he was also willing to lend £200 for the service of the king and parliament according to the propositions, to add to previous loans. On 28 February 1644, he took the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solemn_League_and_Covenant">Solemn League and Covenant</ref>. In April 1645, he was one of the committee of parliament, consisting of six peers and twelve commoners, which was appointed by the two houses to manage the affairs of the admiralty.</p>
<p>Eden died in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London">London</ref> on 18 July 1645, and was buried on 2 August in the chapel of Trinity Hall, Cambridge, where a mural monument with a Latin inscription was erected to his memory. A <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Latin">Latin</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_speaking">oration</ref> was delivered at his funeral by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Exton">Thomas Exton</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Eden, who was highly commended as an advocate by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Fuller">Thomas Fuller</ref>, was a munificent benefactor to Trinity Hall.</p>
</text>
