<text id="autogum_whow_doc031" title="Make Paper Shred Art" shortTile="make-paper-shred" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2007-05-01" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-Paper-Shred-Art" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make Paper Shred Art</head><p>Paper shredders are a common home office item.  Shredders provide protection against identity theft, but they can also be used to make beautiful crafts and art projects! Put your shredder on double duty using this guide on how to make paper shredder art.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Selecting a Paper Shredder</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Pick a shredder type. The type of shredder that you have will determine the type of project that you can do. <figure rend="Choose-a-Paper-Shredder-Step-1-Version-3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Go for strip cut shredders for versatility. Strip cut shredders cut paper into strips. The width of the strips depends on the machine, but it is typically between 1/4 and 1/2 inches. Strip cut shredders are great for making collage art, but they are not as good for making confetti art. Most shredder art guides use strip cut machines.</item>
<item>Use a cross cut shredder only for projects requiring very small pieces. Cross cut shredders cut paper into small square pieces varying in size between XX and XX inches. Higher security machines make even smaller shreddings and can even turn paper into dust—such machines are not good for making shredder art. Cross cut shredders are more common than strip cut shredders, but they are not as versatile for creating art.</item></list></item>
<item>Consider other factors as you compare shredder models.  The size and capabilities of your shredder will impact the scale of your project. Waste bin capacity, speed, run time, and multiple page capacity are all factors to consider. <figure rend="Choose a Paper Shredder Step 4 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The size of your shredder will help to determine the size of your project. Waste bin capacity refers to the size, in volume, of the bin that a shredder discards shredder material into. A shredder with a smaller waste bin capacity might slow you down.</item>
<item>Speed and run time can also slow you down. A slow shredder will take longer to shred through your material. Run time is the amount of time that a shredder can run continuously. Do not overload your shredder by running it for longer than intended.</item>
<item>Some shredders can only shred one page at a time, while others can shred multiple or even many pages at once. Never overload your shredder with more papers at one time than it can handle or it will jam or even break.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Selecting Paper</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Create a color scheme. Decide on a color or create a color scheme for your project. If your project has a theme, such as Christmas or Halloween, you may already know what colors to use. If you do not have a preset color theme, consider color theory when selecting colors. You can also choose patterned paper, such as origami paper, to give your project an extra flair.   <figure rend="Match Colors Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Choose the right weight paper. Not all shredders can handle a heavier weight paper like card-stock, and not all art projects require heavily weighted paper either. Consider the parameters for your project as well as the limitations of your machine when selecting paper.  <figure rend="Choose Paper Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Ensure an even mix of color in your project. When adding your paper to the machine, do not add each color all at once. Instead, add a few pieces of one color, then a few pieces of the next color, and so on in a cycle to ensure an even mix of colors in your shredder bag. Alternatively, if you would like to keep the colors separate, consider using a different shredder bag for each color so that they do not mix at all.  <figure rend="Make Paper Shred Art Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Making Art</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Make decorative jars. Using any type of shredder, shred an even mix of colors in your color theme, and fill a jar with your shreddings. These jars can be used as centerpieces at a wedding or party, conversation pieces on a shelf, or any other way that you would like!  <figure rend="Make Paper Shred Art Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make collage art. Using a strip shredder, shred an even mix of colors in your color theme, and make a collage. You can cut the strips to different lengths with scissors to further customize your art. Some ideas for collage are making a Christmas tree or a firework.  <figure rend="Make a Collage of Pictures Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get creative! There are many different kinds of art projects that you can make with shreddings from your shredder: confetti, mosaics, weaving strips, and more! There are endless possibilities. Finally, your shreddings can be useful craft materials as well. Extra shreddings can be used to package a gift, or to add zest to a gift bag. Don’t be afraid to experiment with this fun artform.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Remember to oil your machine. A well-oiled shredder results in fewer jams.</item>
<item>Keep sensitive shredded material separate from your art material. You don’t want to accidentally use a sensitive document in your art!</item>
<item>Use shredder bags to keep your shreddings in order.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Keep your fingers away from the blades</hi>! Even if the shredder is unplugged and off, you can still get cut.</item>
<item>Do not overload your shredder.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Paper Shredder</item>
<item>Colored Paper</item></list>
</text>
