<text id="autogum_fiction_doc77" title="Twenty Thousand Leagues under the Sea" shortTile="twentythousandleagues" author="Verne, Jules" type="fiction" dateCollected="2019-10-22" sourceURL="http://gutenberg.readingroo.ms/1/6/164/164-8.txt">
<head>THE ARABIAN TUNNEL</head>

<p>That same evening, in 21° 30' N. lat., the Nautilus floated on the surface of the sea, approaching the Arabian coast. I saw Djeddah, the most important counting-house of Egypt, Syria, Turkey, and India. I distinguished clearly enough its buildings, the vessels anchored at the quays, and those whose draught of water obliged them to anchor in the roads. The sun, rather low on the horizon, struck full on the houses of the town, bringing out their whiteness. Outside, some wooden cabins, and some made of reeds, showed the quarter inhabited by the Bedouins. Soon Djeddah was shut out from view by the shadows of night, and the Nautilus found herself under water slightly phosphorescent.</p>

<p>The next day, the 10th of February, we sighted several ships running to windward. The Nautilus returned to its submarine navigation; but at noon, when her bearings were taken, the sea being deserted, she rose again to her waterline.</p>

<p>Accompanied by Ned and Conseil, I seated myself on the platform. The coast on the eastern side looked like a mass faintly printed upon a damp fog.</p>

<p>We were leaning on the sides of the pinnace, talking of one thing and another, when Ned Land, stretching out his hand towards a spot on the sea, said:</p>

<p>"Do you see anything there, sir?"</p>

<p>"No, Ned," I replied; "but I have not your eyes, you know."</p>

<p>"Look well," said Ned, "there, on the starboard beam, about the height of the lantern! Do you not see a mass which seems to move?"</p>

<p>"Certainly," said I, after close attention; "I see something like a long black body on the top of the water."</p>

<p>And certainly before long the black object was not more than a mile from us. It looked like a great sandbank deposited in the open sea. It was a gigantic dugong!</p>

<p>Ned Land looked eagerly. His eyes shone with covetousness at the sight of the animal. His hand seemed ready to harpoon it. One would have thought he was awaiting the moment to throw himself into the sea and attack it in its element.</p>

<p>At this instant Captain Nemo appeared on the platform. He saw the dugong, understood the Canadian's attitude, and, addressing him, said:</p>

<p>"If you held a harpoon just now, Master Land, would it not burn your hand?"</p>

<p>"Just so, sir."</p>

<p>"And you would not be sorry to go back, for one day, to your trade of a fisherman and to add this cetacean to the list of those you have already killed?"</p>

<p>"I should not, sir."</p>

<p>"Well, you can try."</p>

<p>"Thank you, sir," said Ned Land, his eyes flaming.</p>

<p>"Only," continued the Captain, "I advise you for your own sake not to miss the creature."</p>

<p>"Is the dugong dangerous to attack?" I asked, in spite of the Canadian's shrug of the shoulders.</p>

<p>"Yes," replied the Captain; "sometimes the animal turns upon its assailants and overturns their boat. But for Master Land this danger is not to be feared. His eye is prompt, his arm sure."</p>

<p>At this moment seven men of the crew, mute and immovable as ever, mounted the platform. One carried a harpoon and a line similar to those employed in catching whales. The pinnace was lifted from the bridge, pulled from its socket, and let down into the sea. Six oarsmen took their seats, and the coxswain went to the tiller. Ned, Conseil, and I went to the back of the boat.</p>

<p>"You are not coming, Captain?" I asked.</p>

<p>"No, sir; but I wish you good sport."</p>

<p>The boat put off, and, lifted by the six rowers, drew rapidly towards the dugong, which floated about two miles from the Nautilus.</p>

<p>Arrived some cables-length from the cetacean, the speed slackened, and the oars dipped noiselessly into the quiet waters. Ned Land, harpoon in hand, stood in the fore part of the boat. The harpoon used for striking the whale is generally attached to a very long cord which runs out rapidly as the wounded creature draws it after him. But here the cord was not more than ten fathoms long, and the extremity was attached to a small barrel which, by floating, was to show the course the dugong took under the water.</p>

<p>I stood and carefully watched the Canadian's adversary. This dugong, which also bears the name of the halicore, closely resembles the manatee; its oblong body terminated in a lengthened tail, and its lateral fins in perfect fingers. Its difference from the manatee consisted in its upper jaw, which was armed with two long and pointed teeth which formed on each side diverging tusks.</p>

<p>This dugong which Ned Land was preparing to attack was of colossal dimensions; it was more than seven yards long. It did not move, and seemed to be sleeping on the waves, which circumstance made it easier to capture.</p>

<p>The boat approached within six yards of the animal. The oars rested on the rowlocks. I half rose. Ned Land, his body thrown a little back, brandished the harpoon in his experienced hand.</p>

<p>Suddenly a hissing noise was heard, and the dugong disappeared. The harpoon, although thrown with great force; had apparently only struck the water.</p>

<p>"Curse it!" exclaimed the Canadian furiously; "I have missed it!"</p>

<p>"No," said I; "the creature is wounded--look at the blood; but your weapon has not stuck in his body."</p>
</text>
