<text id="autogum_interview_doc140" title="part0_North Korea&amp;apos;s rising tensions: Wikinews interviews Scott Snyder and Dr Robert Kelly" shortTile="partnorth-koreas" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-04-04" dateModified="2015-09-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/North_Korea%27s_rising_tensions%3A_Wikinews_interviews_Scott_Snyder_and_Dr_Robert_Kelly" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>North Korea's rising tensions: Wikinews interviews Scott Snyder and Dr Robert Kelly</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 4, 2013</hi></p>
<p>In recent days, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/North_Korea">North Korea</ref> has been issuing threats of war to neighbouring <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/South_Korea">South Korea</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref>. There has been an increase in tensions as well as the decision to close off the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kaesong%20Industrial%20Park">Kaesong Industrial Park</ref> to South Korean workers.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> interviewed Dr. Robert Kelly of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pusan%20National%20University">Pusan National University</ref> (PNU) in South Korea, who specialises in security and diplomacy, about the recent threats; and Scott Snyder, a North Korean specialist from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Council%20on%20Foreign%20Relations">Council on Foreign Relations</ref> (CFR) in the United States.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What is your job role? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Dr. Robert Kelly</hi>:  I am a Professor of International Relations at PNU.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Scott Snyder</hi>: I am a senior fellow for Korea Studies and director of the program for U.S.–Korea policy at CFR.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  North Korea has issued many threats to South Korea, how likely do you think it is that they will carry out these threats?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RK</hi>: Very unlikely. North Korea would lose a war if one began, and if they use <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Nuclear_weapons">nuclear weapons</ref>, they will lose all sympathy in global opinion and China will abandon them. The point of these threats is to shake-down SK [South Korea] and its new president for aid, not to start a war.
</p><p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Special:FilePath/Scott_Snyder.jpg">File:Scott Snyder.jpg</ref></p><figure><caption>File photo of Scott Snyder.  Image: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Council%20of%20Foreign%20Relations">Council of Foreign Relations</ref>.<hi rend="italic">(Image <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Template:Missing_image/message">missing</ref> from commons: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/File:Scott_Snyder.jpg">image</ref>; <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Special:Log?page=File%3AScott+Snyder.jpg">log</ref>)</hi></caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">SS</hi>: North Korea's threats have a variety of purposes. Some are defensive and are primarily meant to deter other countries from taking aggressive stances in the face of North Korea's own weakness; some are designed tactically to set up for negotiations; some are expressions of intent or aspiration that are beyond the capability of North Korea to implement without facing severe consequences, and some are very specific threats that North Korea will attempt to implement as part of a <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/guerrilla">guerrilla</ref> strategy so as to avoid escalation and take advantage of the element of surprise.  NK [North Korean] threats should be taken seriously, but evaluated carefully to determine circumstances under which they might actually be carried out.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How do people in South Korea feel about North Korea's nuclear weapon's programme?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RK</hi>: They do not like it of course, but they worry far less about it than outsiders would expect. South Koreans have been living under this shadow for many years. The North has made many threats in the past. So NK is like the boy who cried wolf. No one expects them to launch a weapon.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SS</hi>: Increasingly unsettled and concerned, especially about the possibility of being subject to nuclear blackmail.  At the same time, this circumstance thus far has had negligible impact on South Koreans' daily lives.</p>
</text>
