<text id="autogum_reddit_doc056" title="[Subreddit] 50,000 Subscribers! Trial Key Giveaway!" shortTile="subreddit--subscribers" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-05-31" dateModified="2018-05-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8nhxv6" speakerList="#LewisUK_, #MarviinR" speakerCount="2">
<head>[Subreddit] 50,000 Subscribers! Trial Key Giveaway!</head>
<sp who="#LewisUK_">
<p>Hello Escapers! We have some very exciting news for you all! We have been gifted some trial keys to celebrate hitting 50,000 subscribers, in just over a year we have managed to go from a small community of roughly 5,000 subscribers to a bustling corner of the internet with 50,000 subscribers, we are now getting over 8 Million page hits each month which is just crazy to think about and we couldn't do it without you, the community. (Image of Stats: https://i.imgur.com/hWXvqAe.jpg ) The Subreddit has become a key source of information for all things Tarkov, as well even helping to shape the game in certain ways (IE. <ref target="https://www.reddit.com/r/EscapefromTarkov/comments/7ry9tx/an_idea_for_bsg_to_make_pistols_a_more_valuable/">Pistol Retention</ref> ) and it is amazing to see this level of participation by the community and the responsiveness of the developer team. I would like to extend my thanks to the team for allowing the Subreddit to become such a cornerstone for the Escape From Tarkov Community through their activity and assisting with this giveaway to give back to the community. Additionally, I would like to give a personal "Thank You" to the Moderator Team here, without them this place would not be here. So, as a way to show our appreciation to the community and to celebrate the 50k Subscribers Milestone, we will be giving away the following: *  <hi rend="bold">One (1) Full Edge Of Darkness Key for "Escape From Tarkov"</hi>  *  <hi rend="bold">Three (3) 31-Day Trial Keys for "Escape From Tarkov"</hi>  *  <hi rend="bold">Five (5) 14-Day Trial Keys for "Escape From Tarkov"</hi>  *  <hi rend="bold">Thirty-Five (35) 7-Day Trial Keys for "Escape From Tarkov"</hi>   <hi rend="bold">UPDATE: The Rewards have been updated as Nikita has kindly given us more keys, including an EoD copy!</hi>  Please see below on how to enter! ###How to Enter Please follow these guidelines  <hi rend="bold">strictly</hi>  or you will not be entered to the giveaway. Leave a top level comment below with the following information: >  <hi rend="bold">A random number between 1 and 100,000.</hi>   <hi rend="bold">(You must check your number has not been posted before, in case of duplicates, the first person to have posted the number will receive the code.)</hi>  > >  <hi rend="bold">A reason of why you want to win the key!</hi>  > >  <hi rend="bold">What is your favourite thing in Escape From Tarkov? / _OR_ / What are you most looking forward to with Escape From Tarkov?</hi>  See the stickied comment as an example of what to post. ###FAQ > When does the giveaway end? The giveaway will end on Friday 8th June 2018. > How will I know I have won? You will receive a PM on Reddit, if you do not reply within 24 hours, we will select another winner. > Can I enter multiple times? No. Multiple entries will disqualify you from the giveaway. > Can I enter with a brand new Reddit account? Yes! Due to the nature of this giveaway, you can enter with new accounts! (But Automoderator _will_ remove your comment, moderators will approve it ASAP.) > Can I enter if I already own the game? Yes! You can enter and gift the key to a friend :) --- <ref target="https://media.giphy.com/media/yziuK6WtDFMly/giphy.gif">Thank you once again, and here's too another year!</ref> --- #Giveaway has ended, I will be PM'ing winners in the coming days.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#MarviinR">
<p>19840 </p>
<p>I want to win because a lot of my friends are playing it, but it's so expensive and i have no money :( </p>
<p>I'm really looking forward to the weapon customization and the realistic gameplay.</p>
</sp>
</text>
