<text id="autogum_whow_doc038" title="Choose Artwork for Your Bedroom" shortTile="choose-artwork-bedroom" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2012-05-31" dateModified="2019-05-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Choose-Artwork-for-Your-Bedroom" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Choose Artwork for Your Bedroom</head><p>Have you been wanting new artwork for your walls? Do you ever get tired of staring at the same old posters and pictures of things that you don't like anymore? If you are, then keep reading this article to find out how you can choose great artwork for your bedroom that you'll want to keep around for a while.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Choosing the Artwork</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Choose artwork with cool colors. Two examples of cool colors are blue and green. Warm colors such as red, yellow and orange should be saved for rooms where you want a more inviting atmosphere, such as your living room. <figure rend="Choose Artwork for Your Bedroom Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure the artwork is simple. Pictures of flowers and other landscapes are good choices. Your bedroom should be calm and peaceful, and you're most likely going to look at this artwork while you're going to sleep. <figure rend="Choose Artwork for Your Bedroom Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Consider your values. For example, some people would rather not have a gory piece of artwork in their room, and some would. What you choose is really dependent on what you think is best for your room. Artwork can be a very personal thing, so buy something that makes you feel peaceful and relaxed, and that you like. <figure rend="Choose Artwork for Your Bedroom Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Consider the atmosphere, size and lighting in your room. For example, if your room is very dark, then you may or may not want artwork that is very dark colored in your room. <figure rend="Choose Artwork for Your Bedroom Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take note of the colors of certain things in your room, such as your bedspread and carpet. Once you take note of this, try and find artwork that contrasts with the colors of the things that are in your room. <figure rend="Choose Artwork for Your Bedroom Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Decide which medium you prefer. When most people think of artwork, they think of pictures, posters and paintings. However, things like mini sculptures, and even curtains could be good artwork examples too. <figure rend="Choose Artwork for Your Bedroom Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Considering Other Things in Your Room</head>
<p>Sometimes, you may not think about it, but other things in your room can be considered artwork as well.</p>
<list type="ordered"><item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Clean_Your_Room">Clean your bedroom</ref>. A clean room can also help evoke a peaceful, relaxing mood, and although you may not think about it, if it is clean enough, it can be considered artwork itself. <figure rend="Choose Artwork for Your Bedroom Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Consider adding a few accents. Accents can help with the mood in a bedroom as well, choose items such as a vase, as well as a plant to go inside it. As with the artwork, avoid getting the vase in a bright color, as your bedroom is a place for you to sleep in. <figure rend="Choose Artwork for Your Bedroom Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have a style in your room for the furniture. Whether it is shabby chic, or modern, your room is where you can be you. So, choose a style for your room that reflects who you are. <figure rend="Choose Artwork for Your Bedroom Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Consider repainting your bedroom walls. As with the artwork, try to repaint your walls a cool color that you really like. If you go to the store, there are often a ton of choices, so you won't be too limited when deciding. <figure rend="Choose Artwork for Your Bedroom Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have a floor that contrasts with the rest of your room. Usually, although it may stain, plain white is a good option, but pick a color that you like and that contrasts with the rest of your room.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You could always make your own work if you'd like. This can sometimes be a cheaper option, as some art supplies can be found at craft and department stores for very low prices. Also, you will have total control over what goes on the canvas.</item>
<item>If you'd rather not paint your walls yourself, although you will most likely have to pay them, you can hire a professional painter that will do your walls for you.</item>
<item>Try not to have a carpet that matches your wall colors, as this may not look nice. For example, if your walls are a dark green color, then try not to have a dark green colored carpet.</item>
<item>If you have a lower headboard, consider securely hanging your artwork above your bed. This way, especially if the artwork is peaceful, you will see the artwork as you are going to get into your bed to go to sleep.</item>
<item>If you are concerned about what people may think, remember that a lot of people won't see it. While almost everyone who comes over to your house will see the bathroom, a very little amount of people will see your room.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try to buy artwork that you'll want to have for a while. Sometimes, artwork can be very hard to get down once it is hung up, so keep this in mind when you are choosing things for your room.</item>
<item>If you're a child or teenager, have your parents change your carpet and walls if you want them changed, and be sure to ask permission before hanging up artwork.</item></list>
</text>
