<text id="autogum_interview_doc644" title="part2_Popular soap opera &amp;apos;The Young and the Restless&amp;apos; celebrates 35 years on the air" shortTile="partpopular-soap" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-25" dateModified="2014-04-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Popular_soap_opera_%27The_Young_and_the_Restless%27_celebrates_35_years_on_the_air" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Melody Thomas Scott</hi>: I really enjoyed the alcoholism storyline. It was very realistic and showed how easily one can get drawn into addiction. (She was also mixing her alcohol intake with pain pills!) Perhaps the story was ahead of its time. The only thing that flawed it for me was not showing the viewers how she recovered. I was really hoping that we could follow her through rehab, counseling, therapy, etc. It would have been a riveting glimpse of what she had to go through to get sober but we never saw any of that. She simply woke up one morning, sober. To this day, I'm always hoping for her to relapse so that we could finally end that story realistically.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Michelle Stafford</hi>: The blackmailing of Dr. Reid.  That was so creepy and fun and wrong, but it ended up being very funny, [and] the Nick/Phyllis affair.  It was a very real story.  I like the way it was told. It was real. It's also fun to play a secret.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tricia Cast</hi>: "Trying to make a lady out of Nina" was fun. I love comedy.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi>: ...which one was your least favorite?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Melody Thomas Scott</hi>: Although <ref target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KQh5g_4GDPg">the stripping</ref> will forever be imprinted in the viewers' minds (especially the men!), I was nervous as a cat each time Nikki performed on stage. I am not a good dancer, so I felt very awkward pretending to know what I was doing! Even though the show hired amazing choreographers to work with me, I always felt like a fraud!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Michelle Stafford</hi>: I didn't have a least favorite. That's my job to make whatever I'm given good. If it comes off – the jury's out on that – that's up to the audience.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tricia Cast</hi>: The "poor Nina" stuff tended to depress me.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi>: If you had the power to bring one past character back to the show, who would you bring back and why?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Melody Thomas Scott</hi>: Selfishly speaking, I would love to have John Enos [who played Bobby Marsino] return. We had a lot of chemistry on camera and it was a pleasure working with him.  His character's not dead, so anything is possible!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Michelle Stafford</hi>: I think I would like to bring Diane Jenkins back because we don't seem to have anyone evil on the show and I think it's important to have some villains in this medium. And Susan [Walters, who played Diane] was a great actress.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi>: How do you feel about the rise of unscripted shows which indirectly breed dramatic situations, like <hi rend="italic">Big Brother</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Starting Over</hi>? Do you think the rise of reality programming is "bad for business" as far as the daytime dramas go?</p>
</text>
