<text id="autogum_fiction_doc208" title="The Little Lame Prince" shortTile="littlelameprince" author="Craik, Dinah Maria Mulock" type="fiction" dateCollected="2019-10-22" sourceURL="http://gutenberg.readingroo.ms/4/9/496/496-0.txt">
<head>CHAPTER VI</head>

<p>The fourth day it happened that the deaf-mute paid his accustomed visit, after which Prince Dolor's spirits rose. They always did when he got the new books which, just to relieve his conscience, the King of Nomansland regularly sent to his nephew; with many new toys also, though the latter were disregarded now.</p>

<p>“Toys, indeed! when I'm a big boy,” said the Prince, with disdain, and would scarcely condescend to mount a rocking-horse which had come, somehow or other,--I can't be expected to explain things very exactly,--packed on the back of the other, the great black horse, which stood and fed contentedly at the bottom of the tower.</p>

<p>Prince Dolor leaned over and looked at it, and thought how grand it must be to get upon its back--this grand live steed--and ride away, like the pictures of knights.</p>

<p>“Suppose I was a knight,” he said to himself; “then I should be obliged to ride out and see the world.”</p>

<p>But he kept all these thoughts to himself, and just sat still, devouring his new books till he had come to the end of them all. It was a repast not unlike the Barmecide's feast which you read of in the “Arabian Nights,” which consisted of very elegant but empty dishes, or that supper of Sancho Panza in “Don Quixote,” where, the minute the smoking dishes came on the table, the physician waved his hand and they were all taken away.</p>

<p>Thus almost all the ordinary delights of boy-life had been taken away from, or rather never given to this poor little prince.</p>

<p>“I wonder,” he would sometimes think--“I wonder what it feels like to be on the back of a horse, galloping away, or holding the reins in a carriage, and tearing across the country, or jumping a ditch, or running a race, such as I read of or see in pictures. What a lot of things there are that I should like to do! But first I should like to go and see the world. I'll try.”</p>

<p>Apparently it was his godmother's plan always to let him try, and try hard, before he gained anything. This day the knots that tied up his traveling-cloak were more than usually troublesome, and he was a full half-hour before he got out into the open air, and found himself floating merrily over the top of the tower.</p>

<p>Hitherto, in all his journeys, he had never let himself go out of sight of home, for the dreary building, after all, was home--he remembered no other; but now he felt sick of the very look of his tower, with its round smooth walls and level battlements.</p>

<p>“Off we go!” cried he, when the cloak stirred itself with a slight, slow motion, as if waiting his orders. “Anywhere anywhere, so that I am away from here, and out into the world.”</p>

<p>As he spoke, the cloak, as if seized suddenly with a new idea, bounded forward and went skimming through the air, faster than the very fastest railway train.</p>

<p>“Gee-up! gee-up!” cried Prince Dolor in great excitement. “This is as good as riding a race.”</p>

<p>And he patted the cloak as if it had been a horse--that is, in the way he supposed horses ought to be patted--and tossed his head back to meet the fresh breeze, and pulled his coat collar up and his hat down as he felt the wind grow keener and colder--colder than anything he had ever known.</p>

<p>“What does it matter, though?” said he. “I'm a boy, and boys ought not to mind anything.”</p>

<p>Still, for all his good-will, by and by, he began to shiver exceedingly; also, he had come away without his dinner, and he grew frightfully hungry. And to add to everything, the sunshiny day changed into rain, and being high up, in the very midst of the clouds, he got soaked through and through in a very few minutes.</p>

<p>“Shall I turn back?” meditated he. “Suppose I say 'Abracadabra?'”</p>

<p>Here he stopped, for already the cloak gave an obedient lurch, as if it were expecting to be sent home immediately.</p>

<p>“No--I can't--I can't go back! I must go forward and see the world. But oh! if I had but the shabbiest old rug to shelter me from the rain, or the driest morsel of bread and cheese, just to keep me from starving! Still, I don't much mind; I'm a prince, and ought to be able to stand anything. Hold on, cloak, we'll make the best of it.”</p>

<p>It was a most curious circumstance, but no sooner had he said this than he felt stealing over his knees something warm and soft; in fact, a most beautiful bearskin, which folded itself round him quite naturally, and cuddled him up as closely as if he had been the cub of the kind old mother-bear that once owned it. Then feeling in his pocket, which suddenly stuck out in a marvelous way, he found, not exactly bread and cheese, nor even sandwiches, but a packet of the most delicious food he had ever tasted. It was not meat, nor pudding, but a combination of both, and it served him excellently for both. He ate his dinner with the greatest gusto imaginable, till he grew so thirsty he did not know what to do.</p>
</text>
