<text id="autogum_voyage_doc271" title="Queenscliff" shortTile="queenscliff" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=3295" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Queenscliff</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Queenscliff</hi> (also known as <hi rend="italic">Queenscliffe</hi>) is an historic maritime community perched on a small spit of land in the south-eastern most corner of the Bellarine Peninsula. Located in the <ref target="South%20West%20Coast%20%28Victoria%29">South West Coast</ref> region of <ref target="Victoria%20%28state%29">Victoria</ref>, the town was settled only a few years after <ref target="Melbourne">Melbourne</ref>, and is characterised by its strong European heritage, maritime and seafaring character and its lasting connection to the sea. The town is dotted with museums, grand hotels and also a fine variety of restaurants and eateries. It is most known as the port of call of the Searoad Ferry, which connections the region to <ref target="Portsea">Portsea</ref> on the <ref target="Mornington%20Peninsula">Mornington Peninsula</ref>.</p>

<p>This guide also covers the adjacent tourist resort of <hi rend="bold">Point Lonsdale</hi>, a popular destination for family getaways with its splendid beach.</p>

<head>Understand</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Queenscliffe Visitor Information Centre</hi>, 55 Hesse St, ☏ +61 3 5258 4843 , toll-free: 1300 884 843 , ✉ info.centre@queenscliffe.vic.gov.au . 9AM-5PM daily except Christmas Day.</item>
</list>


<head>By bus</head>
<p>McHarry’s Buslines <ref target="http://www.mcharrys.com.au/"></ref> run from Geelong to the Bellarine Peninsula towns of Barwon Heads, Ocean Grove, Pt Lonsdale and Queenscliff (30 km).</p>

<head>By ferry</head>
<p>Car/passenger ferries cross the mouth of Port Phillip Bay between Queenscliff and Sorrento on <ref target="Mornington%20Peninsula">Mornington Peninsula</ref>. They depart each terminal on the hour every hour 7AM-6PM every day. From 26 Dec. until end of daylight saving there are also 7PM sailings. Foot passengers adult $<date when="2015-10-05">10, 5-15</date> years $8, under 5 years $1, foot passenger’s bicycle $2, tandem $3; passengers with vehicle adult $7.50, 5-15 years $5.50, under 5 years $1; vehicle rates vary with season – car up to 5.5m between $48 and $54. <ref target="http://www.searoad.com.au/"></ref></p>

<head>By bike</head>

<p>The Bellarine railtrail runs from South Geelong Station to Queenscliff. Bike hire is available in Geelong from <ref target="Geelong">Geelong</ref>.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fort Queenscliff</hi>. was built in the 1880s as a defense against Russian invasion. The Black Lighthouse is in its grounds. There are guided tours at weekends and public holidays, adults $8??. The fort is still a military establishment so you are required to sign in and show identification.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Queenscliff Maritime Museum</hi>, 1 Weeroona Parade.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bellarine Peninsula Railway</hi>. Steam trains run to Drysdale and return.</item>
<item> A number of impressive <hi rend="bold">19th century buildings</hi> remain, particularly along Gellibrand St.</item>
</list>


<head>Point Lonsdale</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> The headland is right at the entrance to Port Phillip Bay. The channel through the heads is known as the Rip for its strong tidal currents. There are short walks linking the Rip View Lookout, the pier and lighthouse.</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Vue Grand</hi>, 46 Hesse St, ☏ +61 3 5258 1544 . A hotel with grand, heritage architecture and rooms. $240-$270.</item>
</list>


<head>Go next</head>

<p>Take the ferry to Sorrento or head to Geelong.</p>

<p>Alternatively drive or bus along the <ref target="Great%20Ocean%20Road%20%28itinerary%29">Great Ocean Road</ref>. You don’t need to drive through Geelong – from Barwon Heads take the Barwon Heads Rd which becomes Lower Duneed Rd then turn left onto the Surf Coast Highway.</p>
</text>
