<text id="autogum_whow_doc473" title="Prune Ferns" shortTile="prune-ferns" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-05-27" dateModified="2019-07-12" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Prune-Ferns" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Prune Ferns</head><p>Ferns are relatively easy to prune. You can prune them in early spring before the new growth begins, or even when the new growth comes in. If you want to create a shape, you can trim around the edges of the plant. When growing ferns indoors, just be sure to cut off dead or dried fronds when they appear.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Pruning Ferns Outdoors</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Check the pruning information for your specific plant. Some ferns, such as the Giant Chain Fern, do not do well with spring pruning. It's best to let the old foliage die out by itself in mid-summer. If you don't, you can cause damage to the plant. <figure rend="Prune Ferns Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Once the fronds die, you can cut them out.</item></list></item>
<item>Cut back the old foliage early in the spring to make pruning easier. It's easiest to cut back the fern in the spring before the new leaves emerge. You should be able to see the tightly rolled fiddleheads, also known as crosiers, in a crown on the plant. Cut the foliage just above the crown with a sharp pair of gardening shears. <figure rend="Prune Ferns Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The old foliage will likely not look as pretty as new foliage in the height of summer.</item></list></item>
<item>Trim the dead branches after the new growth comes in. Alternatively, you can wait until the new growth comes in to cut off the old fronds. It's best to do this early in the season. Shear off the dead fronds near the crown to make your plant healthier and prettier. <figure rend="Prune Ferns Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can also cut out any older fronds that aren't dead yet but look a little bedraggled.</item></list></item>
<item>Cut the outer edges of the fronds to create a desired shape. If you don't like the way your fern is shaped, simply trim the outer edges until it's to your liking. Use sharp scissors or kitchen shears to do the trimming. <figure rend="Prune Ferns Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>It's best to only trim the outer edges after you've removed yellowing or dead fronds.</item>
<item>Keep in mind that the tips turn brown if you clip off the edges.</item></list></item>
<item>Trim a transplanted fern by half to help it thrive. When you move a fern, it may need some help getting settled in its new location. Cut back all the fronds by half, reducing the water your fern needs to support itself. <figure rend="Prune Ferns Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This technique lets the plant focus more attention on getting its roots settled.</item>
<item>Don't worry. Once the plant is settled, it will grow back.</item></list></item>
<item>Avoid pruning right before winter. It can be tempting to cut off dead or dying fronds at the beginning of winter. However, those fronds help protect the root crown throughout the winter. <figure rend="Prune Ferns Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>In other words, leaving the old fronds in place can help your fern survive through the cold of winter and return in the spring.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Trimming Indoor Ferns</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Cut off dead fronds as they appear. Use a sharp pair of scissors to cut the fronds. Dead fronds will be brown or black. Cut them near the base of the frond, just above the joint.  You can use a sharp pair of scissors or a small pair of garden shears. <figure rend="Prune Ferns Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remove any fronds infected with scales. Scales are tiny insects that attack your plants. They are small, reddish brown, and flat. <figure rend="Prune Ferns Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>When scales attack the plant, the leaves will likely turn yellow and may weaken. Look for scales on the underside of leaves along the vein or on the stems.</item>
<item>Scales can spread, so remove any fronds you see with shears or scissors. If you have a bad infestation, you may need to throw out the houseplant so the scales don't spread to other houseplants.</item>
<item>Outdoor ferns also get scales, but you should try controlling them with oil-based spray pesticides instead of pruning.</item></list></item>
<item>Chop the root runners that hang over the side of the pot. Some ferns will get "runners," sort of like a strawberry plant, except these are part of the plant's root system. These will be brown and woody. Chop them near the soil in the pot with shears or scissors to increase the health of your plant. <figure rend="Prune Ferns Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>These runners are draining energy from your plant. By cutting them, you're letting your plant focus on other vital areas.</item></list></item>
<item>Cut back to the base if desired. If you are not liking the look of your plant at all, you can cut it down to just above the crown, much as you do with an outdoor fern. Use sharp, clean scissors to cut off the fronds. <figure rend="Prune Ferns Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The fern will grow back from the crown, if you let it remain.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Shears</item>
<item>Sharp scissors, optional</item>
<item>Gloves, optional</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
