<text id="autogum_interview_doc809" title="part2_Frank Messina: An interview with the &amp;apos;Mets Poet&amp;apos;" shortTile="partfrank-messina" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-03" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Frank_Messina%3A_An_interview_with_the_%27Mets_Poet%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">FM:</hi>  This was a piece that the Times only quoted one stanza, but it's about preparation for a battle, and being prepared to either rise to the occasion, or go down:</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Do you know what it's like</hi>
<hi rend="italic">to be chased by the Ghost of Failure</hi>
<hi rend="italic">while staring through Victory's door?</hi>
<hi rend="italic">Of course you do, you're a Mets fan</hi>
<hi rend="italic">caught in a do-or-die moment</hi>
<hi rend="italic">in late September at Shea</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">As one that's battled hard</hi>
<hi rend="italic">through many a broken dream</hi>
<hi rend="italic">Let me say, "in order to rise to the occasion</hi>
<hi rend="italic">you must be willing</hi>
<hi rend="italic">to go down with the ship",</hi>
<hi rend="italic">Have no fear, no hesitation,</hi>
<hi rend="italic">for Winning shall be it's reward!</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Don't let them get in your head!</hi>
<hi rend="italic">you've kept it up this long</hi>
<hi rend="italic">You're a Mets fan in late September</hi>
<hi rend="italic">and you'll fight til the glorious end</hi>
<hi rend="italic">Cheer the team today;</hi>
<hi rend="italic">(your boys in orange and blue)</hi>
<hi rend="italic">Let them hear you shout</hi>
<hi rend="italic">as they fight for what's mightily due</hi></p>
<p>(copyright Frank Messina; reprinted with permission)</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Sports fans aren't known as patrons of poetry.  Have you had interaction with 'new readers' through your Mets work?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">FM:</hi>  This one person who I never met took a picture of me and sent it to me in an e-mail.  The e-mail said, 'Frank, I have never bothered you during the game, but I just wanted to say thank you for your work and thank you for making some sense of the successes and failures and I wish you much success with your work.'</p>
<p>Last year in my section at the stadium I had a banner that read <hi rend="italic">We Know'</hi>.  That's all it said.  Then earlier this year these shirts started to come out that said, "Poet says <hi rend="italic">We Know</hi>".  It was amazing.  We didn't use the banner this year, though, because we didn't know.  The team wasn't so far ahead that <hi rend="italic">we knew.</hi>  Last year we just <hi rend="italic">knew</hi> we were going to the playoffs; we <hi rend="italic">knew</hi> we were going post-season.  This year we weren't sure.  We were walking on eggshells.</p>
<p>There was a woman, a season ticket holder and a die hard fan.  She was staggered by the loss last year to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St.%20Louis%20Cardinals">Cardinals</ref>.  Last year she came up to me during one of the games late in the season; she was so happy we were going to the post season.  By that point we had clinched it.  She handed me a shirt she bought at the stadium and she gave me a big hug.  With tears in her eyes she said, "Thank you, Mets Poet, thank you."  It's cool...it's like another family.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Moments like that must make you realize you have touched people who aren't normally touched by poetry.</hi></p>
</text>
