<text id="autogum_bio_doc055" title="Sandeep Kulkarni" shortTile="sandeep-kulkarni" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-05-10" dateModified="2019-10-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sandeep_Kulkarni" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Sandeep Kulkarni</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sandeep Kulkarni</hi> (born 16 November) is an Indian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indian_actor">actor</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Painter">painter</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> He has worked in Marathi films as well as theatre.</p>
<head>Early life and background</head>
<p>Born in Pune, Sandeep was raised in a Maharashtrian middle-class family by father Shrikant Kulkarni and mother Lata Kulkarni. He is an alumnus of J. J. School of Arts, Mumbai.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>During his journey of becoming an artist at Sir J. J. School of Art, he was mentored by Prabhakar Kolte and Atul Dodia. In 1986, Kulkarni participated in a group monsoon show — the first exhibition of his work at the Jehangir Art Gallery. In the same year, he completed his graduation (Bachelor of Fine Arts). While pursuing painting, Sandeep was also exploring acting until he met Pandit Satyadev Dubey. Heavily influenced and inspired by his teachings, Sandeep found himself perfectly fit to be an actor.</p>
<head>Career</head>
<p>After intense theatre for four years in English, Marathi and Hindi, his career started to take shape in television. He played varied roles such as that of young Muslim lawyer Salim in love with a local Muslim woman on <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/9_Malabar_Hill">9 Malabar Hill</ref></hi> on Zee TV, a press reporter in <hi rend="italic">Farz</hi> on DD Metro, an underworld don who deals with drugs in <hi rend="italic">Swabhiman</hi> on DD, a counselor in <hi rend="italic">Nyay</hi> on DD Metro. He also played the role of a cop who solves the mystery behind an old couple refusing to accept the dead body of their son in the much-talked-about one-hour suspense thriller <hi rend="italic">First Kill</hi> directed by Shriram Raghavan.</p>
<p>Sandeep’s career in films began with his first role in the movie <hi rend="italic">Mammo</hi> (1994) directed by the legendary Shyam Benegal, set in the backdrop of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/India-Pakistan_partition">India-Pakistan partition</ref> (1947). He was seen playing the role of an immigration officer (Apte) who tries to help the immigrant protagonist Mammo.</p>
<p>He played the role of a gangster, Shankar, who chases the hero throughout the plot wearing a new pair of shoes that bite and eventually hurt him in <hi rend="italic">Is Raat Ki Subaah Nahin</hi> (1996) directed by Sudhir Mishra. His role added to the black humor of the film.</p>
<p>He played a Naxalite who later becomes an activist, in spite of his colleagues being caught and killed in <hi rend="italic">Hazar Chaurasi Ki Maa</hi> (1998), directed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Govind_Nihalani">Govind Nihalani</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shwaas">Shwaas</ref></hi> (2004), directed by Sandip Sawant, put Sandeep’s performance in the spotlight. He played the role of an oncologist who attempts to convince the grandfather of a child suffering from eye cancer to agree to a life-saving surgery although he is faced with the reality of child becoming permanently blind. Sandeep's biggest compliment of his career was earned when, after watching the film, the legendary actor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shabana_Azmi">Shabana Azmi</ref> asked him if he had studied medicine. <hi rend="italic">Shwass</hi> won Sandeep numerous awards: the State Award being one of them. The film won the National Award as well and was India's official entry to the Oscars.</p>
<p>In a 2005 film, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hazaaron_Khwaishein_Aisi">Hazaaron Khwaishein Aisi</ref></hi>, directed by Sudhir Mishra, Sandeep played a Naxal leader, Probir, involved in spreading the Naxalite movement from Bengal to India.</p>
<p>2005 saw another success in Sandeep's career when he played a common man from downtown (Dombivali), on the edge of busy, frustrating, unimproved and deteriorating daily lifestyle who eventually starts straightening things around him in the critically acclaimed <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dombivali_Fast">Dombivali Fast</ref></hi>, directed by Nishikant Kamath.</p>
<p>In 2005 Sandeep also played the role of Sane Guruji, a biopic teacher, poet, freedom fighter, also known as Gandhiji of Maharashtra in <hi rend="italic">Sane Guruji</hi>. Sandeep’s career includes other series of films such as <hi rend="italic">Adhantari</hi> (2005), <hi rend="italic">Maay Baap</hi> (2006), <hi rend="italic">Rajkaran</hi> (2007).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Traffic Signal</hi> (2006) is a national award-winning film, directed by Madhur Bhandarkar, where Sandeep played an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Non-governmental_organization">NGO</ref> volunteer who is seen helping street children.</p>
<p>In the Marathi film <hi rend="italic">Made in China</hi> (2009), he took the role of a young farmer who is literate and updated on technology and who challenges his uncle, a politician who intends to bring in a special economic zone (SEZ). 2009 also saw him perform the double role of a young businessman creating identity crisis for his wife, family and friends. In 2009 Sandeep won the best actor award in the International Nigerian Film Festival for <hi rend="italic">Ek Daav Sansaracha</hi> where he plays the role of a husband with a complex due to a failed marriage, blamed impotency and his struggle to make a second marriage work.</p>
<p>In 2010 other Marathi films that Sandeep acted in include <hi rend="italic">Khel Saat Baaracha</hi> and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pratisaad_-_The_Response">Pratisaad - The Response</ref></hi>. Other films in the pipeline scheduled for release in 2011 included <hi rend="italic">Nirvana 13</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Paranoia</hi> (under production). Sandeep Kulkarni also influenced people by showing his tremendous work in the Marathi movie <hi rend="italic">Duniyadari</hi>.</p>
<p>In 2014, he was a producer of <hi rend="italic">Dombivili Return</hi>, a sequel to the 2005 film <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dombivali_Fast">Dombivali Fast</ref></hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Personal life</head>
<p>Sandeep married Kanchan Naik in 1999.They have a son. Sandeep has a brother named Sachin.</p>
<head>Filmography</head>
<head>Television</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mayanagari-City_of_Dreams">Mayanagari-City of Dreams</ref></hi>(<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hotstar">Hotstar</ref>)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Avantika</hi></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Guntata Hriday He</hi></item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C.I.D._(Indian_TV_series)">CID</ref></hi> (1999)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/9_Malabar_Hill">9 Malabar Hill</ref></hi> (1997)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Swabhimaan">Swabhimaan</ref></hi> (Doordarshan)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Farz</hi> (DD Metro)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nyaay">Nyaay</ref></hi> (DD Metro)</item></list>
<head>Awards and honors</head>
<head>International awards</head>
<p>Sandeep has received the Nigerian International Film Festival Award for Best Actor for his role in <hi rend="italic">Ek Daav Sansaracha</hi>.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>2004 - Official entry for the Oscars: <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shwaas">Shwaas</ref></hi></item>
<item>2008 - Nigerian International Film Festival Award - Best Actor, <hi rend="italic">Ek Daav Sansaracha</hi></item></list>
<head>National awards</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>2004 - <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shwaas">Shwaas</ref></hi></item>
<item>2005 - <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dombivali_Fast">Dombivali Fast</ref></hi></item>
<item>2007 - <hi rend="italic">Traffic Signal</hi></item></list>
<head>State awards</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>2004 - Best Actor, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shwaas">Shwaas</ref></hi></item>
<item>2005 - Best Actor, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dombivali_Fast">Dombivali Fast</ref></hi></item>
<item>2005 - Best Actor, <hi rend="italic">Adhantari</hi></item></list>
<head>Other awards</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>2004 - Zee Award – Best Actor, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shwaas">Shwaas</ref></hi></item>
<item>2005 - Zee Award – Best Actor, Maharashtra Times Awards – Best Actor, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dombivali_Fast">Dombivali Fast</ref></hi></item></list>
</text>
