<text id="autogum_interview_doc739" title="part6_Randall Munroe, writer of xkcd, talks about the comic, politics and the internet" shortTile="partrandall-munroe" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-09" dateModified="2016-06-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Randall_Munroe%2C_writer_of_xkcd%2C_talks_about_the_comic%2C_politics_and_the_internet" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="On_Wikipedia_and_Wikinews">On Wikipedia and Wikinews</head>
<p>R. It is interesting talking to any wikiproject.  You aren’t talking to one person you are reading the words of a community and so now I’m almost feel like I’m not talking to you across the table I’m talking to some random internet mass and so you know “hello, internet, what are you doing on this page? Are you browsing this from work?”  There’s an odd feeling to it. I’ve also have this urge to play with wikirules. I wanted for a while to find something I could say in an interview that couldn’t be repeated on Wikipedia.</p>
<p>I was thinking something almost <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kurt%20Gödel">Godelian</ref> like saying making a sentence that in some way depends on the way it's presented on Wikipedia and if you try to present it on Wikipedia with a neutral point of view by virtue of taking that action you are changing the point of view to do something.</p>
<p>I wanted to do an announcement saying that I could threaten to commit a crime or threatening to donate money to a charity. This money will go the charity determined by the placement of this comment in the Wikipedia article about this. </p>
<p>So by making the decision about where to place it you would be making the decision about how the real life event would go and how the rest of the article would go. And if you make it important enough people can’t just cling to the guidelines and say I’m writing it the best way, and if you make it something like a million dollars to either Africa or Asia,  hunger relief suddenly you have the responsibility</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">I’m almost worried about including that in the interview, just because I could see some sufficiently rich troll actually implementing that. </hi></p>
<p>R:  Hey, if you don’t put it in the article, I’m going to talk about this.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">So in general how has you experience been with Wikipedia? How did you first here of it, and actually have you heard of Wikinews before this interview?</hi></p>
<p>R: I’ve been on Wikinews a number of times. Whenever  there is a news story where the data is still being sorted out, there have been press releases but no one is really sure what’s going on, it's sometimes the place to go, to see. Information will always be being added. I feel that like if there’s a piece of information that got out there it's on Wikinews, it won’t disappear and be ignored. What will happen is sometimes there will be a couple of different sources. You go to the news sources and you don’t know which of those sources they have. And so then you go the next one, and you have a different sort of information. And so Wikinews is sort of sticky, someone with one source came in and gave their information. Someone from this source came in and gave theirs. They’re all going to build up slowly there.</p>
</text>
