<text id="autogum_interview_doc622" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Zahra Stardust about the upcoming by-election in the Bradfield electorate of the Australian parliament" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-10-29" dateModified="2014-09-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Zahra_Stardust_about_the_upcoming_by-election_in_the_Bradfield_electorate_of_the_Australian_parliament" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Zahra Stardust about the upcoming by-election in the Bradfield electorate of the Australian parliament</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, November 1, 2009</hi></p>
<p>With two <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/by-election">by-elections</ref> coming up in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia">Australia</ref>, many minor parties and independents will be looking to gain a seat in the House of Representatives. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zahra%20Stardust%20">Zahra Stardust (real name Marianna Leishman)</ref> is the candidate for the Australian Sex Party.</p>
<p>Wikinews reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:RockerballAustralia">Patrick Gillett</ref> held an exclusive interview with Ms Stardust, candidate for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Division%20of%20Bradfield">Bradfield electorate</ref>.</p>
<p>“In an area that claims 50 years of conservative representation from white, heterosexual, able-bodied, suited, male protagonists, the Australian Sex Party is excited to a provide modern outward looking female candidate with social justice credentials to restore a historical imbalance in the electorate’s policy focus”, the 26 year old human rights advocate, burlesque dancer and trapeze artist said in a press release.</p>
<p>The electorate was vacated by former opposition leader Brenden Nelson.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Patrick Gillett</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why do you want to get into parliament?</hi> <hi rend="bold">/</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why do you represent your party?</hi></p>
<p>I am delighted and thrilled I am to be representing the Australian Sex Party, whose policies on sex, gender, human rights and equality are very close to my heart. We believe that the personal is political, and we’re serious about sex and the way that it directly affects individuals in areas of health, censorship, discrimination, workplace, education and equality.</p>
<p>Rarely do we hear politicians speaking in positive or open-minded terms about issues relating to sex, sexuality and gender. Much rhetoric in Australian politics in fact uses particularly moralising or religious discourses that are governed by heteronormative, patriarchal and hegemonic ideals. Indeed, our party needed an electoral commission ruling that it s' name was not ‘obscene’. In this climate, we aim to disrupt, expose and eliminate the plethora of taboos and stigmas, shame and isolation around sex, sexuality, and gender, to advocate for wider equality and freedom from harm for all Australians.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">PG</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What would the three main policies you are taking into this by-election be?</hi> <hi rend="bold">/</hi> <hi rend="bold">How would you address these policies?</hi></p>
<p>We’re proud to announce that the Australian Sex Party has policies in a diverse number of areas. We are concerned about child protection and education- we would like to convene a Royal Commission into child sex abuse in religious institutions, and assist develop global approaches to child pornography, whilst importantly, establishing a national sex education curriculum for children, an internet education scheme for parents, a uniform classification scheme for non-violent erotica, introducing R and X ratings for computer games, and return Internet censorship to parents and individuals.</p>
<p>One of our fundamental concerns is equality – including paid maternity leave, ensuring equal numbers of women in Parliament, legalisation of abortion, enacting more comprehensive federal anti-discrimination laws in line with the Australian Human Rights Commission recommendations, creating total equal rights in all areas of the law for gay, lesbian and transgender people, overturning discriminatory laws in the Northern Territory banning Indigenous people from possessing erotic media, and ensuring the sexual rights of the elderly and people with a disability. </p>
</text>
