<text id="autogum_interview_doc147" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Irene Villa" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-02-25" dateModified="2013-11-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Irene_Villa" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<figure><caption>Listen to the interview.Audio: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:LauraHale">Laura Hale</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : You compete in a lot of national competitions, and with disability sport in general, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/disability%20sport%20classification">classification</ref> is a big issue. Competing in national competitions, does classification come into play, especially when there is so few women skiers in your group? ((es))Spanish language: ‍Participa en muchas competiciones nacionales, y en el deporte con discapacidad en general, las clasificaciones son un un tema polémico. En la competición nacional, ¿es la clasificación un factor tan determinante, especialmente cuando hay tan pocas esquiadoras en tu grupo?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Irene Villa</hi>: Yes, certainly. You see, I have an advantage because I have buttocks, I have abs. I have an advantage over a teammate who has a spinal injury here [points to the high part of the back] and also competes. So of course classification is very important because we cannot have an advantage. I believe in competing in equal fairness, and disabilities vary so much that you need a good classification. Issues because of classification? Well, I think we are pretty well classified. For example, my fingers [shows hand where she lost three fingers] are not taken into account in classification, there's always going to be a small detail that they don't count. This is a disadvantage when holding the outrigger, and yet I'm classified like someone who is missing half a leg, for example. I'm missing both legs and three fingers. But, it's really complicated to finetune it... Because then we would need to have twenty thousand classifications. This is what we have. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Sí, claro que sí. Porque claro, yo tengo ventaja por ejemplo al tener glúteos, al tener abdominales, tengo ventaja sobre una compañera de mi equipo que tiene una lesión medular desde aquí [señala principio de la espalda] y también compite, así que por supuesto la clasificación es muy importante porque no podemos tener ventaja. Creo que tenemos que estar en igualdad de condiciones, y las discapacidades son tan distintas que tienes que tener una buena clasificación. ¿Problemas porque no te clasifican bien? Hombre pues yo creo que nosotras estamos bien clasificadas. Por ejemplo, a mi estos dedos [muestra mano en la que perdió tres dedos] no me los cuentan en la clasificación, claro, siempre va a haber algo pequeño que no te cuentan. Esto es una desventaja al coger el estabilo, y sin embargo estoy clasificada igual que una a la que le falta media pierna, por ejemplo. A mi me faltan las dos y tres dedos. Pero es que claro, es muy dificil dar justo... Porque entonces tendríamos que tener veintemil clasificaciones. Es lo que hay.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Some of the skiers I've talked to in the mens' side, not in Spain, but from other countries, have complained about the quality of womens' skiing, and that there's not enough high quality competition. That's why I was interested in if classification was impacting women's skiing because there is so few women skiers, that classes seem they'd make it harder to find competitors in classes that are making the sport equitable and fair. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Algunos de los esquiadores de otros países con los que he hablado se quejaban de la calidad del esquí femenino, y la escasa calidad de la competición. Por eso me interesaba saber si la clasificación incidía en el esquí femenino al haber tan pocas esquiadoras, que las clases parece que hacen más dificil encontrar competidoras en clases que hacen el deporte más equitativo y justo.</p>
</text>
