<text id="autogum_interview_doc188" title="part0_Interview with recent Wikimedia Foundation board appointee Domas Mituzas" shortTile="partinterview-recent" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-03" dateModified="2010-09-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_recent_Wikimedia_Foundation_board_appointee_Domas_Mituzas" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Interview with recent Wikimedia Foundation board appointee Domas Mituzas</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 6, 2008</hi></p>
 This article mentions the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Foundation">Wikimedia Foundation</ref>, one of its projects, or people related to it. <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> is a project of the Wikimedia Foundation.
<p><ref target="https://foundation.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Midom">Domas Mituzas</ref> is a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lithuania">Lithuanian</ref> software developer recently given a temporary position on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikimedia%20Foundation">Wikimedia Foundation</ref>'s board. The position lasts until June this year, after which he has stated he will decide whether he will run for a full term of two years. As well as working for the Wikimedia Foundation, he is employed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MySQL%20AB">MySQL AB</ref>.</p>
<p>In light of his recent appointment to the board, <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> conducted the following interview with Domas Mituzas.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Congratulations on your new board position! Can you tell us a bit about your background - previous work with the Foundation, what you do with MySQL AB etc?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Domas Mituzas</hi>: Thanks! Though my first edits to Wikipedia were in 2003, I became actively involved in site technology back in 2004. Then I was working for a major IT company in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baltic%20States">Baltic States</ref>, and was leading the systems group there. Back then I could apply quite a bit of practice I had from my job to maintain <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia">Wikipedia</ref> in its technology infancy. It became increasingly involving, and eventually the things we started doing became far more complex, especially when the exploding growth hit us. Managing the growth and sustaining the site up was quite stressful at that time, and we started both lots of optimization and resource expansion work. Eventually I got involved in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MySQL">MySQL</ref> community, and was suggested to apply for a job in MySQL AB. There I work in services division, assisting our customers with their problems, helping to grow their operations. Now as part of company acquisition I'm joining <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sun%20Microsystems">Sun Microsystems</ref>, and I'm eager to see what possibilities can that provide. </p>
<p>Back in my childhood I was deep into encyclopedias, first dead tree ones, later CDs and online version of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Britannica">Britannica</ref>. I had a dream, that once I get my own home, I'll get full dead-tree version of Britannica on my bookshelves. It didn't happen, as I got into Wikipedia the same year I bought my apartment. Life is full of irony:-)</p>
<p>Actually, back in 2000 I approached university professor and tried to explain him a concept of dynamically edited news repository, where every concept could be explained deeper and deeper into elemental knowledge particles, and later that can be assembled in many dynamic ways. His first question was "Is that some kind of website?", and I was angry at him for not getting the generic concept of knowledge at all. Year or two afterwards I was discussing same concepts with a colleague, and he provided with far more practical visions of all that. Seeing Wikipedia for the very first time was a dejavu, so it was easy to get into the project. That is different from what I imagined, but far more useful.</p>
</text>
