<text id="autogum_interview_doc619" title="part7_Wikinews interviews Joe Schriner, Independent U.S. presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-04-16" dateModified="2019-08-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Joe_Schriner%2C_Independent_U.S._presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What are your thoughts on the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tea_Party_movement">Tea Party movement</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I just recently read a <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newsweek">Newsweek</ref></hi> article about the Tea Party.  An excerpt that particularly caught my eye was:  The Tea Party rejects the idea that “...a government of brainy people can solve thorny problems through complex legislation."  The Tea Party finds its strongest spirit among <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conservatism%20in%20the%20United%20States">conservative</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republican%20Party%20(United%20States">Republicans</ref>.  Yet a powerful current of 'blame both sides' also pulses through the movement.”  Lynne Roberts, a volunteer organizer of a Tea Party gathering in Albany, New York said:  “We're equally disgusted with Republican and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Democrat">Democrat</ref> Congressmen.”  ...The day I was answering this question for this article, I was also interviewed by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Americus,%20Georgia">Americus (GA)</ref> Enterprise newspaper.  I said when you objectively step back from society and take a look—we have a mess.  We have a $13 trillion National Debt and we are mired in a deep recession.  We have just crossed the 50 million abortion threshold.  Global warming looms as a scary doomsday scenario.  Violence and poverty are almost off the charts in many of our big city urban cores.  Our prisons are bursting at the seams.  Children are being shot in schools and abducted from the streets…  And one of the main common denominators in this:  For the last couple decades, we've had 'brainy' presidents who have come out of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yale">Yale</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harvard">Harvard</ref>.  So what does this say?  I believe it says that, apparently, the education one receives at Yale or Harvard (while impressive to many), isn't the type of education that equips people to, well, solve many of the societal problems I just mentioned.  I mean if it was... I told the reporter in Georgia that to solve the National Debt problem, for instance, we need a common sense president – “with a calculator that works.”  I’m serious.  But it's not just the presidents (Congress people, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wall%20Street">Wall Street</ref> bankers, corporate CEOs...), it's us, the American people.  We have gotten ourselves into this mess.  We're in this global warming crisis, as an example, not because the politicians failed to come up with tangible measures at carbon dioxide reduction in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Copenhagen">Copenhagen</ref>; but rather because many of us are failing here.  We drive too much, use too much air conditioning, heat too much, buy too much (it takes the burning of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/fossil%20fuels">fossil fuels</ref> to make the products)...  We're a society addicted to comfort and immediate gratification.  And what's more, just like an alcoholic, we don't want our politicians confronting us about it.  So we elect people who don't confront us – and the dysfunction (read: destruction) continues.  For a candid look at what we propose for global warming, see:  and  </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Which historical figure do you most identify with and why?</hi></p>
</text>
