<text id="autogum_whow_doc550" title="Work with Animals" shortTile="work-animals" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-10-17" dateModified="2017-02-27" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Work-with-Animals" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Work with Animals</head><p>If you have a job, lifestyle or role that requires you to work with animals, you'll soon learn that you need to be gentle, careful and ready to be immersed in how animals view the world. This can be hard work at times, but can also be very rewarding when you finally find out how to train and work with animals. It can be a lifetime of learning but the journey has to begin somewhere.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Know that not all animals will like you.
<list type="unordered"><item>Not every animal likes to be pet, cuddled, held, or gotten too close to. Some are less sociable than others, and like to be left alone more than played with.</item>
<item>Sometimes it's best just to get it another companion of its own kind as its company- some humans don't like animals, and some animals don't like humans.</item></list></item>
<item>Learn as much as you can about the behaviour in animals. If you're around a specific animal a lot do extra research on it to improve you're performance with it. Being able to read the animal's body signals will enable you to know when it's safe to stay near, and when it's safer to go away and let the animal recover from its encounter with you.
<list type="unordered"><item>Use the Internet to research animal behaviour.</item>
<item>Use books and movies from your local library.</item>
<item>Watch nature shows and documentaries.</item>
<item>Spend time with animals, observing their reactions, and behavior.</item>
<item>Talk to someone that has plenty of experience working with animals, like veterinarians or animal patrolmen; they might be able to open up your eyes on how animals see the world and help you translate what animals do into what they feel.</item></list></item>
<item>Approach animals with care. The main thing to be aware of, is that when you go up to the animal, always take it easy and avoid scaring it. This includes walking or approaching the animal slowly and possibly crouching down to near the animal's level, if this is relevant or appropriate.
<list type="unordered"><item>If the animal reacts by moving away, it may be scared or getting ready to attack if you go any further. Very slowly back away and give it time to recover.</item></list></item>
<item>Allow animals to get a good sense of you and your intentions.
<list type="unordered"><item>Once you are near the animal, hold your hand out to allow it to get your sent. This applies for most animals that are able to pick up scents; from dogs and cats to tigers and wolves.</item>
<item>Talk to them in a soft light toned voice to pose as an ally; a loud voice will pose as a threat to them.</item>
<item>It is also important that you are feeling secure and confident around the animal, as many animals can sense fear or uncertainty and will assume that you are either inferior or prey as a result of this.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Sit by it while it's eating, and feed it treats; this will link you to something they like.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Never go near a stray animal unless it comes to you and is friendly. Even then, be cautious animals can be sporadic.</item>
<item>Never approach the animal very fast or it may try to defend it self, as it feels it is under attack.</item></list>
</text>
