<text id="autogum_voyage_doc181" title="Montreal/Quartier Latin-Le Village" shortTile="montrealquartier" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=22895" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Montreal/Quartier Latin-Le Village</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Quartier Latin-Le Village</hi> is in <ref target="Montreal">Montreal</ref>. It contains the Quartier Latin, Le Village, and Sainte-Marie.</p>

<head>Le Village</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Le Village gai</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Gay Village</hi>, often shortened to <hi rend="bold">Le Village</hi>) is the largest gay village in North America, mostly along rue Sainte-Catherine est from rue Saint-Hubert (near metro Berri-UQAM) to avenue Papineau (near metro Papineau). The metro station in the middle of the area, Beaudry, is marked with rainbow pillars. Come to enjoy Montreal's pride celebration, <ref target="http://www.diverscite.org">Divers/Cité</ref> (last week of July, first week of August), which is the second largest in North America after <ref target="Toronto">Toronto</ref>'s. Then the Montreal <ref target="http://fiertemontrealpride.com">Pride Parade event</ref> follows in mid-August with more fabulous fun to be had by all attendees.</p>

<p>Canada's contributions to gay rights are widely known, but Quebec was the first province in Canada to pass a non-discrimination law for sexual orientation and to provide same-sex civil unions. Same-sex marriage is legal in Quebec and across Canada; neither residency nor citizenship are required for a marriage license, but there is a three-week waiting period after you receive the license. Canadian and Quebec immigration law allow residents to sponsor their same-sex partners or spouses.</p>

<head>Sainte-Marie</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sainte-Marie</hi> is a working-class neighborhood to the east of Le Village. It is notably the home of the <hi rend="bold">Maison Radio-Canada</hi>, the radio and television broadcasting headquarters for Radio-Canada, the French language arm of the CBC.</p>

<head>By metro</head>
<p>The Orange, Green, and Yellow lines all intersect at the <hi rend="bold">Berri-UQAM</hi> station, on the south edge of the Quartier. <hi rend="bold">Sherbrooke</hi> station, at the north end of the Quartier and the edge of the <ref target="Montreal/Plateau">Plateau</ref> (literally--it's a steep walk!) is on the Orange line. Other Green line stations of note are <hi rend="bold">Beaudry</hi> (in the middle of the Village), <hi rend="bold">Papineau</hi> (at the east end of the Village near Sainte-Marie), and <hi rend="bold">Frontenac</hi> (in the middle of Sainte-Marie).</p>

<head>By bus</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Station Centrale d'autobus de Montréal</hi> (505 boulevard de Maisonneuve est) is the entry point to Montreal for those arriving by bus from out of the city.</item>
</list>


<p>Buses run east to west along Sherbrooke, Ontario, and Sainte-Catherine and north to south on Saint-Denis.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Grande Bibliothèque du Québec</hi>, 475 boul de Maisonneuve est (at rue Berri; metro Berri-UQAM), ☏ +1 514 873-1100 , toll-free: +1-800-363-9028 . Tu-F 10AM-10PM, Sa-Su 10AM-5PM. The inviting, super-modern home to the Bibliothèque et Archives nationales du Québec, a massive library housing four million works. The building itself is a contemporary style building integrating art and architecture including a glass mural, a kinetic luminous mural, a sculpture garden, and varying museum-style displays in the lower-level gallery. The tiles that cover the outside of the building are made to resemble a closed book. Architectural tours are offered. Free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Centre de Design UQAM</hi> (UQAM design center), 1440 rue Sanguinet (at rue de Boisbriand; metro Berri-UQAM), ☏ +1 514 987-3395 . W-Su noon-6PM. Free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Galerie de l'UQAM</hi> (UQAM Gallery), 1400 rue Berri (at rue Sainte-Catherine, Pavillon Judith-Jasmin, Room J-R120; metro Berri-UQAM). Tu-Sa noon-6PM. Contemporary art exhibits, workshops, lectures, and tours. Closed until Sep 1, 2015. Free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Écomusée du fier monde</hi>, 2050 rue Amherst (between rue Ontario and rue Sherbrooke; metro Sherbrooke or Beaudry). A museum focused on the industrial and working-class history of Montreal (the name literally translates to <hi rend="italic">Ecomuseum of the Proud People</hi>), particularly of the surrounding Centre-Sud district (basically the modern-day Le Village and Sainte-Marie neighborhoods). The museum is housed in the Bain Genereux, a 1920s art deco former indoor public pool. Note that unlike most Montreal museums, the exhibits here are only described in French.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cinémathèque québecoise</hi>, 335 boul de Maisonneuve est (between rue Sanguinet and rue Saint-Denis; metro Berri-UQAM), ☏ +1 514 842-9763 . Tu-Su regular showing 5PM, exhibition hall Tu-F 11AM-8PM and Sa-Su 4PM-8PM. Modern theater complex with 17-screens (most shows in French only), cafe, restaurant and bar. Exhibitions free; film screenings $8 adults, $7 seniors (65+)/students, $5 children (6-15), free for children 5 and under.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cinéma Cineplex Odeon Quartier Latin</hi>, 350 rue Émery (between rue Sanguinet and rue Saint-Denis; metro Berri-UQAM), ☏ +1 514 849-2244 . Showcases mostly mainstream Hollywood films, all dubbed in French. $11.75 general admission, $8.25 children and seniors.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Théâtre Saint-Denis</hi>, 1594 rue Saint-Denis (between rue Émery and boul de Maisonneuve; metro Berri-UQAM), ☏ +1 514 849-4211 . Performing arts centre with two halls.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Maison de la culture Frontenac</hi>, 2550 rue Ontario est (between rue Frontenac and rue du Havre; metro Frontenac, bus 85, 94, 125, or 185), ☏ +1 514 872-7882 . Tu-Th 1PM-7PM, F-Su 1PM-5PM. Cultural centre in Sainte-Marie. Many free shows. Music, dance, cinema, theatre, etc.</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Chlorophylle Montréal</hi>, 1567 rue Saint-Denis (at boul de Maisonneuve; metro Berri-UQAM), ☏ +1 514 845-1712 . M-Tu 10AM-6PM, W-F 10AM-9PM, Sa 10AM-5PM, Su 11AM-5PM. One of two flagship 'concept stores' for Quebec-based outdoor clothing company with shirts, coats, and pants for men, women and children. Their environmentalism even extends to their dressing room-- made out of recycled barn sheds from Northern Quebec.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Boutique Woodstock</hi>, 2080B rue Saint-Denis (between rue Sherbrooke and rue Ontario; metro Sherbrooke), ☏ +1 514 842-9562 . One of the many head-shops along Saint-Denis with all your 'smoking accessories' as well as hemp products including shirts, jeans, bags, and cosmetics.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>
<p>The Latin Quartier is packed two and three stories deep with budget and mid-ranged restaurants catering to students and tourists. The quality can be all over the place, but the portions usually generous. Beer is more common than wine and be sure to check if the mid and high-end place you're dining at is BYOB (<hi rend="italic">Apportez Votre Vins</hi>).</p>

<head>Budget</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Chez Gatsé</hi>, 317 rue Ontario est (at rue Sanguinet; metro Sherbrooke or Berri-UQAM), ☏ +1 514 985-2494 . M-Th 11:30AM-2:30PM and 5:30PM-10PM, F 11:30AM-2:30PM and 5:30PM-10:30PM, Sa 5:30PM-10:30PM, Su 5PM-10PM. Set just below eye level, one of Montreal's only Tibetan restaurants offers momos (Tibetan dumplings), butter-tea, as well as exotic vegetarian and meat dishes spiced with ginger, garlic, and peppers. In the summer there's a shady terrace in the back. Mains $5-9, set meal $6.50 lunch/$7.50 dinner.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Comptoir 21</hi>, 1117 Saint Catherine East, ☏ +1 514 507-3474 . M-F 11:30AM-11:00PM, Sa Su 12:00AM-11:00PM. The fish and chips restaurant offers delicious fresh fishes. One can sit outisde on the street in the middle of the Gay Village.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Juliette Et Chocolat</hi>, 1615 rue Saint-Denis (between boul de Maisonneuve and rue Ontario; metro Berri-UQAM), ☏ +1 514 287-3555 . Su-Th 11AM-11PM, F-Sa 11AM-midnight. While the wafting scent of chocolate may be the main draw to this chocolateria-cum-bistro, they also offer a selection of savory buckwheat crepes, soups, and salads. Quiet during the day, things pick up in the evening when everyone stops by for coffee, fresh ice cream and coffee and, of course, gourmet chocolate to eat on the spot or take away.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Villa Frontenac</hi>, 2563 rue Ontario est (at rue Frontenac; metro Frontenac, bus 85, 94, 125, or 185), ☏ +1 514 521-4233 . Sainte-Marie diner with a large variety of plates (local, Italian, Greek, American, fast food, etc.). Breakfast $3, dinner $6.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Restaurant Bercy</hi>, 2600 rue Ontario est (between rue du Havre and rue Bercy; metro Frontenac, bus 85, 94, 125, or 185), ☏ +1 514 525-9341 . Cheap diner food in a strip mall in Sainte-Marie. Breakfast $3, dinner $7.</item>
</list>
</text>
