<text id="autogum_interview_doc711" title="part1_Canada&amp;apos;s Don Valley East (Ward 33) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-don-valley" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-17" dateModified="2009-04-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Don_Valley_East_%28Ward_33%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Which council decision (since the 2003 election) do you feel the city/your ward should be most proud of, and which was least desirable?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> A high point was when Council supported my Civic Youth Strategy. They approved not only a strategy which demands meaningful employment and empowerment of Youth, but also a process to allow Youth themselves to determine the membership of our Toronto Youth Panel. This panel will report to council as well as have council's initiatives reported to them for direct input.</p>
<p>A low point was when Council turned down my motion to start an office of Civic Engagement attached to the City Manager's office. This is absolutely crucial to a more engaged, united and more equitable City. Informal and upstart community groups need help, advice, access to resources, and networks — things we have to offer, but aren't equipped to share. I will be bringing the concept back to a new term of Council.</p>
<head id="Anderson_Tung"><ref target="http://toronto2006.on.to/">Anderson Tung</ref></head>
<p>33-year-old <hi rend="bold">Anderson Tung</hi> is has served "as a University of Toronto Governor, consultant and advisor to city council, and unofficial lawyer that enforces laws on MP, MPPs, City council, and political parties." Most recently he has been a strategy consultant and "enviro-entrepreneur".</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Tung's answers have not been abbreviated, despite the fact that the questions clearly ask for specific numbers of issues. Wikinews is not aware whether this inconsistency is due to ignorance or lack of numeracy skills.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Describe the <hi rend="bold">three</hi> most important issues in your campaign.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Here is a summary of the major social, political, and economic reforms I will execute in the coming years:</p>
<p>1) Dismantle TTC and Police Unions and ban all "essential services" from strike without arbitration of wage compared to other public professions. AND Freeze all unionized wages for next 10 years. Upload 50% of toronto police officers, resources, and budget to federal RCMP jurisdiction.</p>
<p>2) cut child poverty by 50% this year in TO, by cancelling gardiner demolition and uploading 50% police cost to feds.</p>
<p>3) Reform of justice system, and media so that it cannot be used as a weapon of terror by any public office.</p>
<p>4) Make environmental power generation, biodiesel, ethanol30, and Recapitalize transportation projects and offer strategy for unified transit system in GTA.</p>
<p>5) Engage province to reopen Kirkland lake mine as enviro-friend waste disposal option for longterm</p>
<p>6) Raise property taxes or surcharges on Walmart, Costco, and other multinationals by 100% or more, as permitted by constitutional law. While cutting small biz property taxes by 50% over 5 years.</p>
<p>In short, I am here to ensure that ignorant, incompetence, corruption are not tolerated in government and ensure political power is balanced by informed decision making - not simply fiscal myopia. Please visit my website for a more detailed outline of my priorities at <ref target="http://toronto2006.on.to">http://toronto2006.on.to</ref>.</p>
</text>
