<text id="autogum_voyage_doc116" title="Cycling in the Achterhoek" shortTile="cycling-achterhoek" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=150943" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Cycling in the Achterhoek</head>

<p>If you're visiting the <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Achterhoek">Achterhoek</ref></hi> and would like to take in the stunning landscapes it has to offer, try exploring the region by bike.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>The Netherlands has a high number of bikes per citizen and the Achterhoek is no exception to that. The seventeen million citizens of the Netherlands own a grand total of 19 million bikes in total, which makes it the country with the highest bike density. Don't have a bike available? Find the closest location that may lend you bikes. The local Tourist Office (VVV) will most likely be able to give you an address where you can rent bikes, and if not, some bikeshops (fietsenwinkel) will be willing to lend you a bike, while outdoor companies can lend you (mountain)bikes. If travelling from a train station to another train station, an <ref target="http://www.ns.nl/en/door-to-door/ov-fiets">OV-fiets</ref> may be something you'd like to consider.</p>
<head>Etiquette</head>
<p>The Achterhoek has no different etiquette for cyclists than the rest of the Netherlands. To give you a quick summary:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Always stay on the right side of the road</hi>. If a designated bike lane (see image) is available, use that lane.</item>
<item> When turning a corner, <hi rend="bold">use your hand to indicate where you are planning to go</hi>. If the road consists of multiple turning lanes, move into the lane that corresponds to the way you are going.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Always give way</hi> to other road users coming from your right or on a priority road.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Always keep your eyes on the road</hi>. The scenery may be beautiful, but safety is still the number one priority.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Always obey road signs and other directions given</hi>. If something has happened to disrupt the regular flow of traffic, signs or people will be there to regulate traffic.</item>
</list>


<head>Routes</head>
<p>Below are multiple cycling routes in the Achterhoek listed on the website of the <ref target="http://www.nederlandfietsland.nl/">Foundation National Cycling Platform</ref>(Stichting Landelijk Fietsplatform). The websites link to PDF files available on their website, ready to be printed. They are in Dutch, but visually show the cycling notes and the distance between them, alongside a map of the region with the route on it.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Round Harreveld</hi> (17.1 kilometers).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Round Doesburg</hi> (24.3 kilometers).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Round Beltrum</hi> (27.0 kilometers).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Castle and country route</hi> (30.8 kilometers).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Winterswijk - Groenlo</hi> (32.4 kilometers).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Windmill route</hi> (38.6 kilometers).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Vineyard route</hi> (49.2 kilometers).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Round the Achterhoek</hi> (283.5 kilometers).</item>
</list>


<head>National cycling routes</head>

<p>If you would like to get to your next destination or just spend more than a day cycling through the region, then LF-routes, or Longer Distance routes, may be something you would be interested in. The following LF-routes go through the Achterhoek:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">LF3: Hanzeroute</hi> (135 kilometers) ( Millingen a/d Rijn - <ref target="Arnhem">Westervoort</ref> - <hi rend="bold">Doesburg</hi> - <hi rend="bold">Zutphen</hi> - <ref target="Deventer">Deventer</ref></item>
</list>

 ). A route passing by most of the Hanze-cities, amongst which is <ref target="Zutphen">Zutphen</ref>. Most of the route follows the river IJssel.

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">LF4: Middle-Netherlands route</hi> (300 kilometers) (<ref target="The%20Hague">The Hague</ref> - <ref target="Zoetermeer">Zoetermeer</ref> - <ref target="Utrecht">Utrecht</ref> - <ref target="Arnhem">Arnhem</ref> - <hi rend="bold">Vorden</hi> - <ref target="Enschede">Enschede</ref></item>
</list>

 ). A route cutting straight through the middle of the Netherlands, giving you an impression of all that it has to offer. 

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">LF8: Ommen - Winterswijk</hi> (100 kilometers) (<hi rend="bold">Winterswijk</hi> - <hi rend="bold">Borculo</hi> - Nijverdal - Ommen).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">LF15: Farmland route</hi> (260 kilometers) (<ref target="Alkmaar">Alkmaar</ref> - <ref target="Hoorn">Hoorn</ref> - <ref target="Enkhuizen">Enkhuizen</ref> - <ref target="Lelystad">Lelystad</ref> - Kampen - <ref target="Zwolle">Zwolle</ref> - <ref target="Hengelo">Hengelo</ref> - <ref target="Enschede">Enschede</ref></item>
</list>

 ). A route showing you all the countrysides that the Netherlands has to offer including the tulip industry in <ref target="North%20Holland">North Holland</ref> and farming in newly gained land, <ref target="Flevoland">Flevoland</ref>.

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">LF19: Deventer - Holten</hi> (35 kilometers) (<ref target="Deventer">Deventer</ref> - <ref target="Sallandse%20Heuvelrug">Holten</ref></item>
</list>

 ). 

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Rhine route</hi> (270 kilometers) (Millingen a/d Rijn - <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Arnhem">Arnhem</ref></hi> - <ref target="Rhenen">Rhenen</ref> - <ref target="Wijk%20bij%20Duurstede">Wijk bij Duurstede</ref> - <ref target="Dordrecht">Dordrecht</ref> - <ref target="Hook%20of%20Holland">Hook of Holland</ref></item>
</list>

 ). A route following the entirety of the river Rhine throughout the Netherlands. 

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Round the Netherlands</hi> (1300 kilometers) ( <ref target="Arnhem">Arnhem</ref> - <hi rend="bold">Vorden</hi> - <ref target="Enschede">Enschede</ref> - Hardenberg - <ref target="Emmen">Emmen</ref> - <ref target="Groningen">Groningen</ref> - Den Oever - Beverwijk - <ref target="Haarlem">Haarlem</ref> - <ref target="The%20Hague">The Hague</ref> - <ref target="Bergen%20op%20Zoom">Bergen op Zoom</ref> - <ref target="Breda">Breda</ref> - <ref target="Eindhoven">Eindhoven</ref> - <ref target="Roermond">Roermond</ref> - <ref target="Venlo">Venlo</ref> - <ref target="Nijmegen">Nijmegen</ref> - <ref target="Arnhem">Arnhem</ref></item>
</list>

 ). The ultimate route for a vacation by bike. You will get to see nearly all that the Netherlands has to offer, while staying as close to the borders as possible. 

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Round Twente</hi> (180 kilometers) (<ref target="Enschede">Enschede</ref> - <ref target="Hengelo">Hengelo</ref> - <hi rend="bold">Rijssen</hi> - Ommen - Oldenzaal - <ref target="Enschede">Enschede</ref></item>
</list>

 ). A route that shows you all of <ref target="Twente">Twente</ref>, located directly north of the Achterhoek.

<head>See also</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Cycling%20in%20the%20Netherlands">Cycling in the Netherlands</ref></item>
</list>
</text>
