<text id="autogum_news_doc174" title="Thirteen Israeli soldiers, scores of Palestinians killed in deadly day of fighting in Gaza Strip" shortTile="thirteen-israeli" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-07-21" dateModified="2015-09-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Thirteen_Israeli_soldiers%2C_scores_of_Palestinians_killed_in_deadly_day_of_fighting_in_Gaza_Strip" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Thirteen Israeli soldiers, scores of Palestinians killed in deadly day of fighting in Gaza Strip</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 22, 2014</hi></p>
<p>On Sunday, in the deadliest day of fighting for the Israeli military in several years, thirteen <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Israel">Israeli</ref> soldiers were reported killed in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gaza_Strip">Gaza Strip</ref>.  Over 500 deaths of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Palestine">Palestinians</ref> have been reported in the Gaza Strip in the now-fourteen days of Israel's offensive against <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hamas">Hamas</ref>.</p>
<p>Over 67 deaths of Palestinians on Sunday, by one report well over 100 — both civilians and fighters combined — occurred in one area, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gaza%20City">Gaza City</ref> suburb of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shujai'iya">Shujai'iya</ref>, following heavy fighting and shelling by Israeli forces.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, thirteen Israeli soldiers were killed Sunday, including two soldiers who were <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> citizens. Furthermore, the armed wing of Hamas claimed in a statement, "We have captured a Zionist soldier and the occupation has not admitted that", and displaying a identification card and a serial number. The IDF is investigating the claim. A anonymous senior Israeli military source told <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Guardian">The Guardian</ref></hi> in regards to Hamas fighters, "We have to admit we were facing good fighters, very well equipped with sophisticated weapons systems, accurate weapons, heavy weapons including mortars, booby traps."</p>
<p>All this occurred while a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Nations_Security_Council">United Nations Security Council</ref> meeting was held in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York_City">New York City</ref> at the request of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jordan">Jordan</ref>. Speaking to reporters after the meeting, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Rwanda">Rwanda</ref>'s UN ambassador <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eugène-Richard%20Gasana">Eugene Gasana</ref> said, "The members of the Security Council expressed serious concern about the growing number of casualties. The members of the Security Council called for an immediate cessation of hostilities". Gasana continued saying, "The members of the Security Council called for respect of international humanitarian law including protection of civilians[...] The members of the Security Council emphasized the need to improve the humanitarian situation, including through humanitarian pauses."</p>
<p>United Nations Secretary-General <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ban_Ki-moon">Ban Ki-moon</ref>, who is in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doha">Doha</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Qatar">Qatar</ref> meeting with Qatar's Emir Sheikh <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tamim%20bin%20Hamad%20Al%20Thani">Tamim bin Hamad al-Thani</ref> and Palestinian President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mahmoud_Abbas">Mahmoud Abbas</ref>, said in a statement, "As I travel the region, I will continue to press for an [immediate] ceasefire — an immediate end to the Israeli military operation in Gaza and the rocket fire by Hamas and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Islamic_Jihad_Movement_in_Palestine">Islamic Jihad</ref>". Ban criticized Israel for the civilian death toll saying, “While I was en route to Doha, dozens more civilians, including children, have been killed in Israeli military strikes in the Shejaiyah neighborhood in Gaza[...] I condemn this atrocious action. Israel must exercise maximum restraint and do far more to protect civilians.”</p>
<p>In response, Israeli Prime Minister <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Benjamin_Netanyahu">Benjamin Netanyahu</ref> said in press conference, "We will continue this operation for as long as it takes." Netanyahu also appeared on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CNN">CNN</ref> saying Hamas uses civilians as human shields; "They use telegenically dead Palestinians for their cause. They want the more dead, the better". He further added, "We try to target military targets and unfortunately there are civilian casualties which we regret and we don't seek".</p>
</text>
