<text id="autogum_reddit_doc139" title="Find your Battle Cup Party | March 31" shortTile="find-battle-cup-party" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-03-30" dateModified="2018-03-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/88fjlv" speakerList="#Imagination357, #Weeaboo_Hating_Weeb, #coronaria, #ehmperk, #forennger, #iguessiactuallymade" speakerCount="6">
<head>Find your Battle Cup Party | March 31</head>
<sp who="#coronaria">
<p>#Battle Cup - March 31 Battle Cups this week and for the foreseeable future have a few noteworthy changes from the previous season: - Battle Cups appear not to be limited by when Battle Passes are active. - They still cost $0.99 to participate, however is FREE for Dota Plus Members (more details: https://www.dota2.com/plus). - Winners will be awarded 20,000 shards in addition to the special emotions and profile accolades. ____ This thread is dedicated for you guys to find a party for weekly Battle Cup.  <hi rend="bold">During the event all posts about finding/forming a team will be removed to avoid spam.</hi>   <hi rend="bold">This thread is only for people looking for a team, if you are forming a team simply reply to or PM anyone looking for a team that suits what you're looking for and invite them.</hi>  If you've already found a team please edit your post saying so or delete your post so no one will keep contacting you. ____ Suggested Format:  <hi rend="bold">Steam ID:</hi>   <hi rend="bold">Server:</hi>   <hi rend="bold">Tier:</hi>  What tier do you want to play on?  <hi rend="bold">Preferred Role</hi>  What positions you're comfortable playing with.  <hi rend="bold">Other Information</hi>  Any other info that you would like your party mates to know --- If start to love with playing with a premade and in a competitive setting please check out our friends at https://www.reddit.com/r/compDota2 Have fun! </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#Imagination357">
<p>Tier 6 </p>
<p>Server US East </p>
<p>We are a party of 3 we need 2 more players (pos 4 and pos (3 or 2)) </p>
<p>(Preferable if you speak decent English and have Discord) </p>
<p>My dota ID: 326472964</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#Weeaboo_Hating_Weeb">
<p>Steam ID: http: steamcommunity.com id MarshmallowYDG </p>
<p>Server: USW E </p>
<p>Tier: Tier 5. </p>
<p>Preferred Role: 5, 4, 3 in that order </p>
<p>Other Information: Have MIC &amp; Discord</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#iguessiactuallymade">
<p>http: steamcommunity.com profiles 76561198103482563 </p>
<p>USE W </p>
<p>t6 </p>
<p>prefered 3 4 but will do anything really </p>
<p>i can play all positions pretty well just looking for a team or to start one</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#forennger">
<p>Steam: http: steamcommunity.com profiles 76561198158263268 </p>
<p>Tier: 5 6 </p>
<p>Legend 3 - preferred positions in order 5,4,4 </p>
<p>Mostly play Hard support with a large hero pool </p>
<p>US East</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#ehmperk">
<p>http: steamcommunity.com id Ehmperk +1 </p>
<p>US East </p>
<p>tier 4, Archon 4 5. </p>
<p>There are two of us, we will play any roles. We both have mics and dischord, and don't flame. US East. </p>
</sp>
</text>
