<text id="autogum_voyage_doc35" title="Lochinver" shortTile="lochinver" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=19979" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Lochinver</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Lochinver</hi> is a small fishing village in <ref target="Caithness%20and%20Sutherland">Sutherland</ref> in the <ref target="Scottish%20Highlands">Scottish Highlands</ref>, with a population of 600. It's about 30 miles north of Ullapool.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>From the south, travel via Ullapool along A837 which ends at Lochinver. From the north follow A894 via Kylesku to join A837, or branch onto scenic winding B869 along the coast.</p>

<p>George Rapson Bus 809 runs twice a day M-Sat between Ullapool and Lochinver, taking an hour; no Sunday service.</p>

<p>In July &amp; Aug Durness Bus 804 runs once a day M-Sat from Lairg via Ullapool to Lochinver, continuing north via Kylesku, Laxford Bridge and Kinlochbervie to Durness.</p>

<p>Bikes may be carried between Durness, Lochinver and Lairg, but must be booked at least 24 hours in advance on +44 1971 511223.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ardvreck Castle</hi> (11 miles outside of Lochinver on A837). A ruined castle on a small peninsula on Loch Assynt. There is not much left today, but it is a scenic view just next to the main road, so it is definitely worth a stop. </item>
<item> Lochinver lies within the UNESCO <hi rend="bold"><ref target="North%20West%20Highlands%20Geopark">North West Highlands Geopark</ref></hi> which also covers Durness, Kinlochbervie and Kylesku. Some of the local rocks are over 3 billion years old.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Climb</hi> <hi rend="bold">Suilven</hi>. Distinctive 731 m mountain. It's six miles to the summit from Lochinver, the route is described on <ref target="https://www.walkhighlands.co.uk/ullapool/suilven.shtml">walkhighlands.co.uk</ref>. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fishing:</hi> the area is best known for its fly-fishing (mid-Apr to mid-Oct) on the River Assynt flowing down from that loch. There's also sea fishing from shore.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Assynt Highland Games</hi> are held early August in Assynt Park, two miles south of Lochinver. The next event is on Fri 9 Aug 2019.</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lochinver Stores (Spar)</hi>, Main Street, IV27 4JY, ☏ +44 1571 844207 . Mon - Sat 08:00 - 18:30, Sun 09:00 - 17:30. Small supermarket.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Inverpark Stores</hi>, Inver Park, IV27 4LN. Mon - Sat 09:00 - 20:00, Sun 10:00 - 18:00.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lochinver Larder</hi>, Main Street, IV27 4JY (Second building on the right from the beginning of the village.), ☏ +44 1571 844356 . M-Sa 10:00-17:00, Su closed. Restaurant which serves nice pies and seafood.</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cruachan Holiday Home</hi>, Cruachan, Badnaban, Lochinver IV27 4LR, ☏ +44 01571 608227 , ✉ bookings@highlandsholiday.co.uk . Check-in: 16:00, check-out: 10:00. Self catering accommodation near the North Coast 500 (NC 500) with a view to the ocean. Varies by season.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Inver Lodge Hotel</hi>, Iolaire Rd, IV27 4LU, ☏ +44 1571 844496 . Fine views, but the building is ugly outside and dowdy within. Good food &amp; service but way overpriced. B&amp;B double from £220.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tigh Na Sith</hi>, IV27 4LD, ☏ +44 1571 844588 . It means "House of Peace": no children or pets accepted. B&amp;B double £125.</item>
</list>


<head>Go next</head>

<p>It's either south to <ref target="Ullapool">Ullapool</ref>, for ferries to Stornoway or the road south to Inverness, or north to <ref target="Kinlochbervie">Kinlochbervie</ref> and <ref target="Durness">Durness</ref> on the wild north coast.</p>
</text>
