<text id="autogum_fiction_doc64" title="The $30,000 Bequest, and Other Stories" shortTile="bequeststories" author="Twain, Mark" type="fiction" dateCollected="2019-10-22" sourceURL="http://gutenberg.readingroo.ms/1/4/142/142-0.txt">
<head>Elargizione del Re all' Ospedale italiano</head>

<p>The first line means that the Italian sovereigns are coming back--they have been to England. The second line seems to mean that they enlarged the King at the Italian hospital. With a banquet, I suppose. An English banquet has that effect. Further:</p>

<head><hi rend="italic">Il ritorno dei sovrani</hi></head>

<p>a Roma</p>

<p>ROMA, 24, ore 22,50.--<hi rend="italic">I Sovrani e le Principessine Reali si attendono a Roma domani alle ore</hi> 15,51.</p>

<p>Return of the sovereigns to Rome, you see. Date of the telegram, Rome, November 24, ten minutes before twenty-three o'clock. The telegram seems to say, “The Sovereigns and the Royal Children expect themselves at Rome tomorrow at fifty-one minutes after fifteen o'clock.”</p>

<p>I do not know about Italian time, but I judge it begins at midnight and runs through the twenty-four hours without breaking bulk. In the following ad, the theaters open at half-past twenty. If these are not matinees, 20.30 must mean 8.30 P.M., by my reckoning.</p>

<head>Spettacolli del di 25</head>

<p>TEATRO DELLA PERGOLA--(Ore 20,30)--Opera. BOHEME. TEATRO ALFIERI.--Compagnia drammatica Drago--(Ore 20,30)--LA LEGGE. ALHAMBRA--(Ore 20,30)--Spettacolo variato. SALA EDISON--Grandioso spettacolo Cinematografico: QUO-VADIS?--Inaugurazione della Chiesa Russa -- In coda al Direttissimo -- Vedute di Firenze con gran movimeno -- America: Transporto tronchi giganteschi--I ladri in casa del Diavolo -- Scene comiche. CINEMATOGRAFO -- Via Brunelleschi n. 4.--Programma straordinario, DON CHISCIOTTE -- Prezzi populari.</p>

<p>The whole of that is intelligible to me--and sane and rational, too--except the remark about the Inauguration of a Russian Cheese. That one oversizes my hand. Gimme me five cards.</p>

<p>This is a four-page paper; and as it is set in long primer leaded and has a page of advertisements, there is no room for the crimes, disasters, and general sweepings of the outside world--thanks be! Today I find only a single importation of the off-color sort:</p>

<head>Una Principessa</head>

<p>che fugge con un cocchiere</p>

<p>PARIGI, 24.--Il MATIN ha da Berlino che la principessa Schovenbare-Waldenbure scomparve il 9 novembre. Sarebbe partita col suo cocchiere.</p>

<p>La Principassa ha 27 anni.</p>

<p>Twenty-seven years old, and scomparve--scampered--on the 9th November. You see by the added detail that she departed with her coachman. I hope Sarebbe has not made a mistake, but I am afraid the chances are that she has. <hi rend="italic">Sono dispiacentissimo</hi>.</p>

<p>There are several fires: also a couple of accidents. This is one of them:</p>

<head>Grave disgrazia sul Ponte Vecchio</head>

<p>Stammattina, circe le 7,30, mentre Giuseppe Sciatti, di anni 55, di Casellina e Torri, passava dal Ponte Vecchio, stando seduto sopra un barroccio carico di verdura, perse l' equilibrio e cadde al suolo, rimanendo con la gamba destra sotto una ruota del veicolo.</p>

<p>Lo Sciatti fu subito raccolto da alcuni cittadini, che, per mezzo della pubblica vettura n. 365, lo transporto a San Giovanni di Dio.</p>

<p>Ivi il medico di guardia gli riscontro la frattura della gamba destra e alcune lievi escoriazioni giudicandolo guaribile in 50 giorni salvo complicazioni.</p>

<p>What it seems to say is this: “Serious Disgrace on the Old Old Bridge. This morning about 7.30, Mr. Joseph Sciatti, aged 55, of Casellina and Torri, while standing up in a sitting posture on top of a carico barrow of vedure (foliage? hay? vegetables?), lost his equilibrium and fell on himself, arriving with his left leg under one of the wheels of the vehicle.</p>

<p>“Said Sciatti was suddenly harvested (gathered in?) by several citizens, who by means of public cab No. 365 transported him to St. John of God.”</p>

<p>Paragraph No. 3 is a little obscure, but I think it says that the medico set the broken left leg--right enough, since there was nothing the matter with the other one--and that several are encouraged to hope that fifty days well fetch him around in quite giudicandolo-guaribile way, if no complications intervene.</p>

<p>I am sure I hope so myself.</p>

<p>There is a great and peculiar charm about reading news-scraps in a language which you are not acquainted with--the charm that always goes with the mysterious and the uncertain. You can never be absolutely sure of the meaning of anything you read in such circumstances; you are chasing an alert and gamy riddle all the time, and the baffling turns and dodges of the prey make the life of the hunt. A dictionary would spoil it. Sometimes a single word of doubtful purport will cast a veil of dreamy and golden uncertainty over a whole paragraph of cold and practical certainties, and leave steeped in a haunting and adorable mystery an incident which had been vulgar and commonplace but for that benefaction. Would you be wise to draw a dictionary on that gracious word? would you be properly grateful?</p>

<p>After a couple of days' rest I now come back to my subject and seek a case in point. I find it without trouble, in the morning paper; a cablegram from Chicago and Indiana by way of Paris. All the words save one are guessable by a person ignorant of Italian:</p>

<head>Revolverate in teatro</head>

<p>PARIGI, 27.--La PATRIE ha da Chicago:</p>

<p>Il guardiano del teatro dell'opera di Walace (Indiana), avendo voluto espellare uno spettatore che continuava a fumare malgrado il diviety, questo spalleggiato dai suoi amici tir`o diversi colpi di rivoltella. Il guardiano ripose. Nacque una scarica generale. Grande panico tra gli spettatori. Nessun ferito.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Translation.</hi>--“Revolveration in Theater. <hi rend="italic">Paris, 27th. La Patrie</hi> has from Chicago: The cop of the theater of the opera of Wallace, Indiana, had willed to expel a spectator which continued to smoke in spite of the prohibition, who, spalleggiato by his friends, tire (<hi rend="italic">Fr. Tire, Anglice Pulled</hi>) manifold revolver-shots; great panic among the spectators. Nobody hurt.”</p>
</text>
