<text id="autogum_interview_doc738" title="part5_Randall Munroe, writer of xkcd, talks about the comic, politics and the internet" shortTile="partrandall-munroe" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-09" dateModified="2016-06-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Randall_Munroe%2C_writer_of_xkcd%2C_talks_about_the_comic%2C_politics_and_the_internet" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">That comic made fun of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Xenocide">Xenocide</ref> and didn’t mention the final book <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Children%20of%20the%20Mind">Children of the Mind</ref> at all. Do you have an opinion there? </hi></p>
<p>R. I have not read either of those books since high school, and for me that’s getting further and further away. So I haven’t read either of those books in 6 or 8 years. My memories of  Children of the Mind are that at least had  had the end of the story there and so at least playing out, and being “ok, that happened.” I don’t remember all the details but that there was something to it. All my memories of Xenocide  are a girl with obsessive compulsive disorder and Chinese history for many pages. So I didn’t have very good feelings to Xenocide. But neither of those two did I feel were on the same levels as Ender’s Game or Speaker for the Dead. I just picked Xenocide as the most clear target of them.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Have you seen Orson since this conference started?</hi>
<hi rend="italic">(<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orson%20Scott%20Card">Orson Scott Card</ref> was the featured speaker at Vericon)</hi></p>
<p>R: I have not. I have a t-shirt though that he signed.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Obviously he’s aware this specific one about Xenocide.</hi></p>
<p>R: Xenocide followed from that joke I decided to make. I wanted her to be reading a book and wanted him (the character) to object to it and I worked out how the conversation should go. And then I asked ok who should I pick on? I ended up with Xenocide because I just don’t have great memories of it. It could be if I reread it I’d enjoy it. But um.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">But you did say in the alt-text, “cue nasty emails from all 7 seven fans of Xenocide”.  So it seems you understood that it was one of Orson’s less popular works at best</hi></p>
<p>R: I can’t resist getting in another crack like that. Even if that’s not true, it's funny to say so.  It's like  whenever you say anything about, about “we’ve offended the persons in favor of what we don’t like here” you can always throw in “fortunately that’s not many people that don’t like that thing”. That’s almost a standard gag.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Did you actually try the 28 hour day?(Comic 320, <ref target="http://www.xkcd.com/320/">28-Hour Day</ref>)</hi></p>
<p>R: Yeah. I tried it a couple times in fact. I’m coming off of a 5 day period of doing that when I was rolling my schedule around.  So I found that if I do it for more than a week I start to go crazy. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">That’s exactly what you said in the alt-text actually.</hi></p>
<p>R. Yeah that was. it gets to be the Sunday mornings where you have to stay up until the afternoon and nothing is happening. And no one is awake . The campus is dead. The apartment is dead. The internet is dead. And  you have to stay awake, and you’ve already been awake for 14 hours. That’s when I’d fail at that. And then I’d fall asleep. And then you’re back on the standard college student schedule. And that’s when it always failed for me. And I’d always start to feel really tired in the middle of the day even though from the equations I shouldn’t.</p>
</text>
