<text id="autogum_news_doc089" title="Libya and Switzerland to meet about visa bans" shortTile="libya-switzerland" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-02-16" dateModified="2014-06-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Libya_and_Switzerland_to_meet_about_visa_bans" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Libya and Switzerland to meet about visa bans</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 18, 2010</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Map of Schengen nations <p style="margin:0px;font-size:90%">██Full Schengen EU members</p><p style="margin:0px;font-size:90%">██Non-EU Schengen members</p><p style="margin:0px;font-size:90%">██Future members</p><p style="margin:0px;font-size:90%">██Cooperating countries</p></caption></figure>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Libya">Libya</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Switzerland">Switzerland</ref> have reportedly agreed to meet in an effort to resolve a diplomatic row about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Visa%20(document)">travel visas</ref>.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Micheline%20Calmy-Rey">Micheline Calmy-Rey</ref> of Switzerland and Moussa Koussa of Libya will meet in the presence of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miguel%20Ángel%20Moratinos">Miguel Ángel Moratinos</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Spain">Spain</ref>. All three are the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/foreign%20minister">heads of foreign relations</ref> for their respective countries. The meeting comes at the urging of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Malta">Malta</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Italy">Italy</ref>.</p>
<p>Libya announced on Tuesday that it has suspended and/or revoked visas given to citizens of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schengen%20Area">Schengen Area</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Europe">Europe</ref>. Four Italian citizens have been detained at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tripoli%20International%20Airport">Tripoli International Airport</ref> pending deportation, as their visas have been revoked.</p>
<p>Confirming the situation, a Libyan official told <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Reuters">Reuters</ref>: "This is right. This decision has been taken. No visas for Europeans, except Britain."</p>
<p>Malta has had eight citizens turned back. One of these told <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Times%20(Malta)">The Times</ref></hi> of Malta, "They treated us like hostages, not even allowing us out of the room to stretch our legs."</p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/European_Commission">European Commission</ref> released a statement saying it "deplores the unilateral and disproportionate" action by Libya and that affected nations will consider an "appropriate reaction."</p>
<p>"The Commission also regrets that travellers who legally obtained visas before the suspension measure were refused entry when arriving in Libya," said EU commissioner for Home Affairs, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cecilia%20Malmström">Cecilia Malmström</ref>.</p>
<p>Libya and Switzerland have been in a diplomatic row for many months. In July 2008, the Swiss for two days detained Libyan leader <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Muammar_al-Gaddafi">Muammar al-Gaddafi</ref>'s son, Hannibal, after hotel staff in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Geneva">Geneva</ref> complained of being assaulted. Hannibal was given a suspended sentence and released.</p>
<p>Since then, Libya has withdrawn more than <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_dollar">US$</ref>5 billion (<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Euro">€</ref>3.6 billlion) from Swiss banks and cut of oil exports to Switzerland. Libya then detained two Swiss businessmen and sentenced one to 16 months of prison on visa violation charges.</p>
<p>In November, 2009, Switzerland asked Schengen nations to restrict Libyan visas. Subsequently, Libyan Prime Minister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baghdadi%20Mahmudi">Baghdadi Mahmudi</ref> and other officials have been denied Schengen visas.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Italy">Italy</ref> came down on Switzerland, saying the Swiss must "resolve this bi-lateral issue ... but not at the expense of everyone else."</p>
<p>Sawsan Chebli, a senior <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deutsche%20Gesellschaft%20für%20auswärtige%20Politik">German Council on Foreign Relations</ref> (DGAP) said that, "The EU is Libya’s greatest trade and export partner. This is a leverage the EU could use. However, Italy and other EU member states with close relations with Libya in the past have shown that they are not interested to spoil their relations with Libya whatever Gaddafi’s action may be. That is not likely to change. And the problem is that Gaddafi knows that he is able to divide the EU."</p>
<p>"The Italians care very little about the EU or other states when it comes to business relations," Chebli added.</p>
</text>
