<text id="autogum_fiction_doc171" title="The Magic of Oz" shortTile="magicoz" author="Baum, L. Frank (Lyman Frank)" type="fiction" dateCollected="2019-10-22" sourceURL="http://gutenberg.readingroo.ms/4/1/419/419.txt">
<head>12. Kiki Uses His Magic</head>

<p>Then arose a great confusion of sounds as all the animals began talking to their fellows. The monkeys chattered and the bears growled and the voices of the jaguars and lions rumbled, and the wolves yelped and the elephants had to trumpet loudly to make their voices heard. Such a hubbub had never been known in the forest before, and each beast argued with his neighbor until it seemed the noise would never cease.</p>

<p>Ruggedo the Nome waved his arms and fluttered his wings to try to make them listen to him again, but the beasts paid no attention. Some wanted to fight the Oz people, some wanted to be transformed, and some wanted to do nothing at all.</p>

<p>The growling and confusion had grown greater than ever when in a flash silence fell on all the beasts present, the arguments were hushed, and all gazed in astonishment at a strange sight.</p>

<p>For into the circle strode a great Lion--bigger and more powerful than any other lion there--and on his back rode a little girl who smiled fearlessly at the multitude of beasts. And behind the Lion and the little girl came another beast--a monstrous Tiger, who bore upon his back a funny little man carrying a black bag. Right past the rows of wondering beasts the strange animals walked, advancing until they stood just before the rock throne of Gugu.</p>

<p>Then the little girl and the funny little man dismounted, and the great Lion demanded in a loud voice:</p>

<p>"Who is King in this forest?"</p>

<p>"I am!" answered Gugu, looking steadily at the other. "I am Gugu the Leopard, and I am King of this forest."</p>

<p>"Then I greet Your Majesty with great respect," said the Lion. "Perhaps you have heard of me, Gugu. I am called the 'Cowardly Lion,' and I am King of all Beasts, the world over."</p>

<p>Gugu's eyes flashed angrily.</p>

<p>"Yes," said he, "I have heard of you. You have long claimed to be King of Beasts, but no beast who is a coward can be King over me."</p>

<p>"He isn't a coward, Your Majesty," asserted the little girl, "He's just cowardly, that's all."</p>

<p>Gugu looked at her. All the other beasts were looking at her, too.</p>

<p>"Who are you?" asked the King.</p>

<p>"Me? Oh, I'm just Dorothy," she answered.</p>

<p>"How dare you come here?" demanded the King.</p>

<p>"Why, I'm not afraid to go anywhere, if the Cowardly Lion is with me," she said. "I know him pretty well, and so I can trust him. He's always afraid, when we get into trouble, and that's why he's cowardly; but he's a terrible fighter, and that's why he isn't a coward. He doesn't like to fight, you know, but when he HAS to, there isn't any beast living that can conquer him."</p>

<p>Gugu the King looked at the big, powerful form of the Cowardly Lion, and knew she spoke the truth. Also the other Lions of the forest now came forward and bowed low before the strange Lion.</p>

<p>"We welcome Your Majesty," said one. "We have known you many years ago, before you went to live at the Emerald City, and we have seen you fight the terrible Kalidahs and conquer them, so we know you are the King of all Beasts."</p>

<p>"It is true," replied the Cowardly Lion; "but I did not come here to rule the beasts of this forest. Gugu is King here, and I believe he is a good King and just and wise. I come, with my friends, to be the guest of Gugu, and I hope we are welcome."</p>

<p>That pleased the great Leopard, who said very quickly:</p>

<p>"Yes; you, at least, are welcome to my forest. But who are these strangers with you?"</p>

<p>"Dorothy has introduced herself," replied the Lion, "and you are sure to like her when you know her better. This man is the Wizard of Oz, a friend of mine who can do wonderful tricks of magic. And here is my true and tried friend, the Hungry Tiger, who lives with me in the Emerald City."</p>

<p>"Is he ALWAYS hungry?" asked Loo the Unicorn.</p>

<p>"I am," replied the Tiger, answering the question himself. "I am always hungry for fat babies."</p>

<p>"Can't you find any fat babies in Oz to eat?" inquired Loo, the Unicorn.</p>

<p>"There are plenty of them, of course," said the Tiger, "but unfortunately I have such a tender conscience that it won't allow me to eat babies. So I'm always hungry for 'em and never can eat 'em, because my conscience won't let me."</p>

<p>Now of all the surprised beasts in that clearing, not one was so much surprised at the sudden appearance of these four strangers as Ruggedo the Nome. He was frightened, too, for he recognized them as his most powerful enemies; but he also realized that they could not know he was the former King of the Nomes, because of the beast's form he wore, which disguised him so effectually. So he took courage and resolved that the Wizard and Dorothy should not defeat his plans.</p>

<p>It was hard to tell, just yet, what the vast assemblage of beasts thought of the new arrivals. Some glared angrily at them, but more of them seemed to be curious and wondering. All were interested, however, and they kept very quiet and listened carefully to all that was said.</p>
</text>
