<text id="autogum_voyage_doc273" title="Maizuru" shortTile="maizuru" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=20899" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Maizuru</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Maizuru</hi> (舞鶴 ) <ref target="http://www.city.maizuru.kyoto.jp/"></ref> surrounds an inlet of the Sea of Japan, along the northeastern coast of <ref target="Kyoto%20%28prefecture%29">Kyoto Prefecture</ref>. Maizuru in Japanese means 'dancing crane'.</p>
<head>Understand</head>
<p>One of the main port cities in <ref target="Kyoto">Kyoto</ref> Prefecture. Ferries to <ref target="Niigata">Niigata</ref> and on to <ref target="Tomakomai">Tomakomai</ref> in <ref target="Hokkaido">Hokkaido</ref> leave from here.</p>
<p>Maizuru consists of two parts: Nishi-Maizuru and Higashi-Maizuru.</p>
<p>Maizuru is a key district headquarters for the Japan Maritime Self-Defense Force.</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Higashi-Maizuru Station</hi> (東舞鶴) is served by eight limited express trains daily from <ref target="Kyoto">Kyoto</ref> Station, six under the name <hi rend="italic">Maizuru</hi> and two as <hi rend="italic">Tango Discovery</hi>. Fares for the 96-minute journey range from ¥3,250 for an unreserved seat to ¥3,960 for a reserved seat in peak season.</p>
<p>It is also possible to use local trains when traveling from Kyoto station for ¥1,890. The journey takes around 2 hours and you need to change trains at Sonobe and Ayabe.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>A trip by car takes around 1 hour 10-20 min from Kobe-Sando. The ride from Itami airport takes approximately 1 hour 30 minutes. It takes 1 hour 30 minutes to get to Maizuru from Kyoto city.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>The bus company <ref target="http://www.city.kyoto.lg.jp/kotsu/">Kyoto Kotsu</ref> has buses running from Kyoto central train station to Higashi-Maizuru train station for ¥2,300. The journey takes around 2 hours. The same bus company has buses going to Maizuru from Kobe and Osaka.</p>

<head>By boat</head>
<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.snf.jp/">Shin-Nihonkai Ferry</ref></hi> (新日本海フェリー) This company has lines connecting daily to <ref target="Otaru">Otaru</ref> port at <ref target="Hokkaido">Hokkaido</ref> (21 h).</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>The city occupies a vast territory and public transportation is not well developed. It is better to have a car. It is also possible to arrange a taxi tour for around ¥5,000. Inquire about arranging a tour at the Maizuru tourist information center at Higashi-Maizuru station.</p>

<head>See</head>
<p>There is a nice view of the Maizuru bay from the quay which is a 10-15 minutes walk from Higashi-Maizuru train station.</p>

<p>Maizuru has many buildings made of red brick around town. Some of them used to be military buildings, others warehouses, tunnels and even temples. Maizuru also has a museum of red bricks.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Maizuru World Brick Museum</hi>. Daily 09:00-17:00. The museum displays bricks from all over the world and all over Japan, as well as ancient ones from old Mesopotamia, Egypt, China, and Greece. ¥300.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>
<p>Visit Japanese self-defence force base, Russo-Japanese War Museum including Admiral Togo museum, repatriation museum, brick museum.</p>

<head>Buy</head>
<p>The main shopping place in Maizuru is department store <ref target="http://www.la-port.jp/">LaPort</ref> which is behind Higashi-Maizuru train station.</p>

<head>Drink</head>
<p>There is a very good yakitori close to train station Higashi-Maizuru on Sanjo-dori owned by an ex-self-defense sailor Daikichi who speaks some English.</p>

<head>Go next</head>
<p>Maizuru Port offers ferry services along the Sea of Japan up to <ref target="Hokkaido">Hokkaido</ref>.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Amanohashidate">Amanohashidate</ref> in <ref target="Miyazu">Miyazu</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Ine">Ine</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Kyotango">Kyotango</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Yosano">Yosano</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Fukuchiyama">Fukuchiyama</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Ayabe">Ayabe</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Takahama">Takahama</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Oi">Oi</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Obama">Obama</ref></item>
</list>
</text>
