<text id="autogum_whow_doc563" title="Comfortably Sleep with a Dog in Your Bed" shortTile="comfortably-sleep" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-03-09" dateModified="2018-09-01" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Comfortably-Sleep-with-a-Dog-in-Your-Bed" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Comfortably Sleep with a Dog in Your Bed</head><p>Sometimes you want your furry companion to share a sleep space but you get can't seem to really fit together and sleep comfortably. Use these tips and you and your fuzzy pal will be cuddling comfortably all night long!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Make sure that your dog will sleep in your bed. Some dogs don't like to sleep with their owners and that's perfectly fine. If they don't want then just let it go for a while and maybe try again later. Make sure that you don't force anything. If your dog usually sleeps somewhere that that is not your bed don't be surprised if your dog jumps off and goes back there in the middle of the night. Make sure that your dog can easily get up and down off your bed or you will get very tired very quickly of putting them up there every time. Know that in the wild, dogs tend to find a place to sleep and call it's den for a very long time so don't be surprised if your dog wants to stay there. If your dog is having trouble try moving their crate, pillow or whatever else they sleep on into your room for a while so they get used to sleeping in that room</item>
<item>Have a couple trial nights. Have a couple of nights where you try to sleep with your dog to see some of the patterns the dogs do. Do they like to sleep at the top of the bed? Do they move or bark a lot in their sleep? Do they tend to lick their paws or pant a lot before going to sleep? Make sure that you pick a pretty open week to do this where you don't have to worry about being tired the next day if your dog kept you up all night.</item>
<item>Fix any patterns that you don't like. Now you need to fix any problem that you come across. If your dog has a tendency to do something in bed that you don't like now is the time to fix it. If your dog tends to sleep somewhere that you find difficult to lay down comfortably try moving them to your preferred spot before you go you sleep. If they lick their paws a lot, pant, spin in circles, or something else like that before they go to sleep try to get into bed earlier so they can do that before you need to sleep.</item>
<item>And you are done! Your fluffy friend and you should have no problem sleeping together. hope you enjoyed this article it is my first one. I have slept with my two dogs for four years now so I have picked up a few tips over the years. Thank You!</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Having a nice big bed helps a lot. I used to sleep with my two dogs on a twin sized mattress and it didn't really work. But I've since then gotten a queen and it is much better.</item>
<item>If your dog tends to be a blanket hogger get them another blanket that they can sleep on so you can have yours all to your self.</item>
<item>If your dog is keeping you up because they keep walking around and moving try taking them for a walk or playing fetch before bed to try to wear them out.</item>
<item>Don't be afraid to move them if they are laying somewhere or doing something that you don't like. It doesn't make them not love you any more or anything so just do it and get it over with and then you will be much more comfortable</item></list>
</text>
