<text id="autogum_bio_doc114" title="Bill Freeman (racing driver)" shortTile="bill-freeman-racing" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-07-25" dateModified="2019-10-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Freeman_%28racing_driver%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Bill Freeman (racing driver)</head>For the Canadian author, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Freeman">Bill Freeman</ref>.
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Bill Freeman</hi> is a professional racing driver, race team owner, motorsport racing enthusiast, race car manufacturer, and business entrepreneur.</p>
<head>Racing career</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>1961 - 1967 Go Kart racing in the Midwest. Dual &amp; Triple engine</item>
<item>1967 - 1972 S.C.C.A. Racing, Triumph TR4, MGB, 427 Cobra<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></item>
<item>1972 - 1978 S.C.C.A. Trans-Am, I.M.S.A. GT Racing, Can-Am<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> (Corvette, Camaro, Porsche, Lola, McLaren)</item>
<item>1977 S.C.C.A. B-Production National Champion (SP Division - Porsche 911RSR) Freeman was S.C.C.A. National Champion in his 911 Porsche.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></item>
<item>1979 - 1980 Freeman was the originator and supervisor for all aspects of a new Ferrari IMSA team.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-russoandsteele1980-8">[8]</ref></item>
<item>1976 - 1983 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Newman#Auto_racing">Newman Freeman Racing</ref>  (Can-Am, Indy, I.M.S.A.)</item></list>
<figure><caption>Newman Freeman Racing logo</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>Paul Newman and Bill Freeman at Willow Springs Raceway in 1976 alongside Bill Freeman's Porsche 911.</caption></figure>
<p>In 1978 Paul Newman and Bill Freeman formed a racing partnership to compete in various forms of  auto  racing. The Racing Team was based in Santa Barbara, California. As the team's Managing Partner, Freeman managed all aspects and operations for this professional automobile racing company.</p>
<p>The company specialized in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IndyCar">Indy Cars</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Can-Am">Can-Am</ref>, and other high-performance motorsport racing. The team raced in Chevrolet-powered Spyder NF's, sponsored by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Budweiser_(Anheuser-Busch)">Budweiser</ref>.</p>
<p>The  "Newman  Freeman  Racing" team dominated North America's Can Am series in its Budweiser sponsored Lola team. The partnership attracted several drivers who would go on to become legends in the future, included <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keke_Rosberg">Keke Rosberg</ref>,  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elliott_Forbes-Robinson">Elliott Forbes-Robinson</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bobby_Rahal">Bobby Rahal</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Danny_Sullivan">Danny Sullivan</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Teo_Fabi">Teo Fabi</ref>, and others. Driving for Newman Freeman Racing, these drivers won many competitions including the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1979_Can-Am_season">Can-Am Team Championship of 1979</ref>.</p>
<figure><caption>Paul Newman and Bill Freeman on Princess Grace's balcony overlooking the Monaco Grand Prix, 1979.</caption></figure>
<p>Bill Freeman is credited as the man who introduced Paul Newman to professional auto racing. In addition to the team management, Bill Freeman and Paul Newman drove many S.C.C.A. and I.M.S.A. events together, including the Sebring 12 hour endurance sports car race.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>1983-1984 Gurney Freeman Racing</item></list>
<p>Freeman was General Manager and Team Manager for Gurney Freeman Racing Indianapolis 500 CART championship racing team and partners with Dan Gurney at <ref target="http://www.allamericanracers.com/">All American Racers</ref> in Santa Ana, California.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-indianapolismotorspeedway1982-13">[13]</ref></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>1984–Present: Managing Partner - Newman Freeman Racing and CEO - <ref target="http://www.finesportscars.com">Fine Sports Cars</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Fine_Sports_Cars-14">[14]</ref></item></list>
<head>Other business</head>
<p>In 1979 Freeman also formed Fine Sports Cars with partner <ref target="http://www.finesportscars.com/about/directors.html#marshall">Ashton Marshall</ref>, to remanufacture, restore, and offer for sale legendary sports racing cars.  The company was based in San Diego,  California, with a showroom, The Fine Car Store, located in La Jolla, California.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-russoandsteele1980-8">[8]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[16]</ref></p>
<p>In 2009 the company was expanded. Freeman, Fine Sports Cars CEO, took on an additional partner <ref target="http://www.finesportscars.com/about/directors.html#prior">Dr. Michael Prior</ref>. Prior restructured the company operations to encompass a full range of vintage sports racing cars including both sanctioned and certified cars, established a global network of workshops and suppliers, and established a regional office in Europe.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Fine_Sports_Cars-14">[14]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-17">[17]</ref></p>
<head>Awards</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Freeman was S.C.C.A. National Champion in his 911 Porsche in 1977<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-18">[18]</ref></item>
<item>Newman Freeman Racing won the Can-Am Team championship in 1979<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-19">[19]</ref></item>
<item>Freeman co-managed the race team which Paul Newman drove for in the 24 hours of Le Mans class winning victory in 1979</item>
<item>AAR Gurney Freeman Racing set the fastest stock block qualifying lap in history for the 1982 Indianapolis 500<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-indianapolismotorspeedway1982-13">[13]</ref></item></list>
</text>
