<text id="autogum_bio_doc522" title="Janbirdi al-Ghazali" shortTile="janbirdi-alghazali" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-04-06" dateModified="2019-08-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Janbirdi_al-Ghazali" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Janbirdi al-Ghazali</head><hi rend="bold">Warning:</hi> Page using <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Infobox_officeholder">Template:Infobox officeholder</ref> with unknown parameter "religion" (this message is shown only in preview).
<p><hi rend="bold">Janbirdi al-Ghazali</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arabic_language">Arabic</ref>: جان بردي الغزالي‎; <hi rend="italic">Jān-Birdi al-Ghazāli</hi>; died 1521) was the first governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Damascus_Eyalet">Damascus Province</ref> under the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman Empire</ref> from February 1519 until his death in February 1521.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Peters-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Leeuwen-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Career</head>
<head>Viceroy of Hama and Governor of Damascus</head>
<p>Al-Ghazali was originally the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Na'ib">na'ib</ref></hi> or "viceroy" of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hama">Hama</ref> under the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mamluk_Sultanate_(Cairo)">Mamluk Sultanate of Egypt</ref> in the early 16th century. When the Ottomans invaded Mamluk <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syria">Syria</ref>, Janbirdi fought alongside the latter at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Marj_Dabiq">Battle of Marj Dabiq</ref> in 1516, leading the assault on Ottoman sultan <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Selim_I">Selim I</ref>'s army in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gaza_City">Gaza</ref>. Al-Ghazali was wounded during that confrontation. After the Mamluk defeat, he retreated to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cairo">Cairo</ref> with his army where he took part in the defense of the city from incoming Ottoman forces. The Ottomans again defeated the Mamluks and conquered Egypt and Syria.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Rogan23-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Al-Ghazali then joined the Mamluk governor of Aleppo in defecting to the Ottomans and severed allegiance with Mamluk sultan <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al-Ashraf_Qansuh_al-Ghawri">Qansuh al-Ghawri</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> Selim I was reportedly impressed by al-Ghazali's loyalty to his superiors and in a bid to have him serve under the Ottomans,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Rogan23-3">[3]</ref> Selim appointed him as governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Damascus">Damascus</ref> in February 1519.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> At the time, Damascus Province encompassed much of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Levant">Levant</ref>, including much of central and southern Syria, the Syrian coastline, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palestine_(region)">Palestine</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transjordan_(region)">Transjordan</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lebanon">Lebanon</ref>. He paid an annual tribute of 230,000 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dinar">dinars</ref> to the Ottoman sultan.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Rogan23-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>As governor, he was in charge of safeguarding the pilgrim caravan destined to make <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hajj">hajj</ref></hi> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hejaz">Hejaz</ref> for the pilgrim route from Damascus to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aqaba">Aqaba</ref> in southern Transjordan. In order to do this successfully, he subjugated the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turkmen_people">Turkmen</ref> nomads in the area. After two years, he managed to have those same Turkmen tribes protecting the pilgrims. By 1520, <hi rend="italic">hajj</hi> caravans were traveling without incident.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Peters-1">[1]</ref> In line with Ottoman state policy at the time, al-Ghazali embarked on major development projects in Damascus. Having been appointed the <hi rend="italic">nazir</hi> or "supervisor" of Damascus's main <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waqf">waqf</ref></hi>, he had the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Umayyad_Mosque">Umayyad Mosque</ref> repaired and redecorated. He also had a number of other mosques, schools and canals rebuilt and repaired. Supervisors of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Madrasa">madrasas</ref></hi> ("religious schools") who were deemed negligent were stripped of their position and their school buildings restored.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Leeuwen-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Revolt against Ottomans</head>
<p>Following the succession of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Süleyman_the_Magnificent">Süleyman the Magnificent</ref> to the sultanate after Selim's death in 1520, al-Ghazali revolted against the Ottoman state. He sought to restore Mamluk suzerainty, declaring himself "sultan" or <hi rend="italic">al-Malik al-Ashraf</hi> ("the most noble king"). He banned preachers in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mosque">mosques</ref> from upholding the Ottoman sultan's name in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Friday_prayer">Friday prayers</ref>, purged Ottoman officials and soldiers from Syria, and banned Ottoman dress by the province's citizens. After he declared himself sultan, the cities of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tripoli,_Lebanon">Tripoli</ref>, Hama, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hims">Hims</ref> joined his rebellion.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Rogen24-6">[6]</ref> After failed attempts to enlist the support of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shah_Ismail">Shah Ismail</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Safavid_Empire">Safavid Empire</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kha'ir_Bey">Kha'ir Bey</ref>, the Ottoman governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Egypt">Egypt</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> he nonetheless raised an army and set out to conquer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aleppo">Aleppo</ref>. The residents of Aleppo supported the Ottoman sultanate, however, and resisted al-Ghazali's efforts. His army besieged the city for 15 days, during which over 200 residents and Ottoman soldiers were killed, but to no avail. He withdrew to Damascus soon after to rally his forces.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Rogen24-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>In February 1521, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Army">Ottoman Army</ref> arrived at the outskirts of Damascus where al-Ghazali's troops confronted them. His army was swiftly defeated and he was executed. The Ottoman army sent al-Ghazali's severed head to Süleyman as a trophy. The Ottomans also proceeded to sack Damascus, killing 3,000 residents, and destroying the town quarters as well as nearby villages.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Rogen24-6">[6]</ref> With the deposition of al-Ghazali's revolt, Mamluk influence in Syria came to an end.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Rogen24-6">[6]</ref> The Ottoman contemporary chroniclers report al-Ghazali's revolt as the first major event of the reign of Suleiman the Magnificent. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Şen333-8">[8]</ref></p>
</text>
