<text id="autogum_interview_doc892" title="part17_Author Amy Scobee recounts abuse as Scientology executive" shortTile="partauthor-amy-scobee" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-10-11" dateModified="2015-12-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Author_Amy_Scobee_recounts_abuse_as_Scientology_executive" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Davis further stated to the <hi rend="italic">New York Daily News</hi> that (separate from the earlier intimations from the lawyer for Tom Cruise) the Scientology organization was itself "preparing a lawsuit" against you because of the "disgusting allegations" in the book. Have you received any notice from the Scientology organization with regards such a potential lawsuit?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS</hi>: No and I don't expect to. Everything I've stated in my book are things that I personally observed (and where that wasn't the case, I make it clear). I was careful not to exaggerate, but to be as factual as possible about my experiences. There is so much more I could have said about severe abuse others witnessed and told me about, but I kept it to my story. As there are numerous witnesses now out of Scientology who also saw what I saw while working at the International Headquarters for Scientology, I do not think Miscavige and his attorneys would be very successful trying to prove my "defamation" and their innocence in front of a jury.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Davis proceeded to make claims to the <hi rend="italic">New York Daily News</hi> about your sexual relationships. Additionally, BBC News reported that after you began to make public criticism of the organization and its leader David Miscavige, Scientology provided "intimate details of her sex life" to the Florida newspaper the <hi rend="italic">St. Petersburg Times</hi>. How did you feel when these sexual details were made public by Scientology? How do you feel this behavior by the organization and its officials reflects on its assertions of keeping confidential information secret, and respecting the privacy of priest-penitent privilege?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS</hi>: To me – and MANY other people – it was obvious through their child-like reaction that they have something fairly big to hide. I gave a detailed eye-witness account of the head of the Scientology religion repeatedly beating staff members. That they respond with exaggerated accusations about my sex life is just a red herring. And it also proves that private information you may divulge in confessionals while a member of Scientology could be used against you should you step out of line in the future.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> In an August 2009 issue of the Scientology publication, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freedom%20Magazine">Freedom Magazine</ref></hi>, the issue referred to you multiple times only as "The Adulteress". How did this make you feel when you found out about this publication? When you were still a member of the Scientology organization, what was your opinion at that point in time of <hi rend="italic">Freedom Magazine</hi>? What is your opinion of the publication - its reputability and reliability, at this point in time?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS</hi>: The "Freedom" magazine is the public mouthpiece for Scientology, often used as a medium to expose what they consider to be the ills of society (psychiatry, pharmaceutical companies and major critics of their religion). I was not surprised that they put out a magazine against those who exposed the illegal actions of the Scientology leader, David Miscavige, with his repeated abuse and assault and battery being committed on his junior Scientology executives. They felt that an attack on Miscavige was an attack on the whole religion and therefore those people involved needed to be exposed as rotten to the core.</p>
</text>
