<text id="autogum_whow_doc527" title="Manage a Beauty Salon" shortTile="manage-beauty-salon" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-06-07" dateModified="2018-11-14" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Manage-a-Beauty-Salon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Manage a Beauty Salon</head><p>So you just graduated Cosmetology school, and now want to manage a beauty salon? Well, there's a couple things you should know even before getting your license! It's not all about your experience, and how great you are at hair, but more in customer service!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Build up a staff. You need enough people to cover your open hours, so ideally about 5 stylists. Hopefully 2 can work full-time, and the other 3 can work part-time. Make sure you have every shift covered. If you have salon open Mon-Friday from 10-6, then have one/two stylist come in the morning and one/two in the afternoon.</item>
<item>Advertise. Advertising in a salon is key to getting business in. If you have a newer salon it can be hard finding new customers so running sales like 2 haircuts for $20 can be helpful. Also, hand out business cards to every customer that you can to increase sales.</item>
<item>Set up retail options. Retail sales in a salon is important because it not only brings in money, but helps with styling client's hair. If you did a color you could suggest that she/he gets a color shampoo to help against fading. If you work for a big company it is very important to sell retail with services to boost your combo percent. You also want to sell if you are making commission off retail.</item>
<item>Organize a system for tips. Usually people tip after a service, so make sure you know what to do with tip money. Many salons you can keep your own tips, but some you need to put in a jar and split.</item>
<item>Handle nightly bank deposits. Bank deposits are usually taken every night after closing. You might leave $100.00 in the drawer, and the rest of the profit will go to the bank in a deposit bag. Make sure you hide the bag! Never show the bag to the public eye because you are responsible for the money getting to the bank. If the drawer is short, or people paid only with credit cards, you may not have a deposit.</item>
<item>Keep track of customer records. Customer records should be stored in a computer or paper to keep up with their recent visit, color, and waxing. Also, it should be noted if they get special treatment like they like a 1,2,3 fade or can't bend down to the sink area. Usually nowadays most salons have a computer with customer information.</item>
<item>Set up for incoming shipments. Some salons get a shipment of product every 1-2 weeks. Usually you have to place the correct barcode on the product, and place it on the shelf where it's supposed to go. Keep up with sales.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Coming to work 15 minutes earlier is a great way to get your station prepared before the day starts.</item>
<item>Make sure you dress, act, and look professional. Most salons prefer black or black/white clothing.</item>
<item>Shoes are important to help your back and shoulders if you stand for long periods of time. Do some stretching in between customers.</item>
<item>The customer is usually always right. Not always though. Try your best to help a customer, but some people aren't pleased no matter what you do.</item>
<item>If you are new, you are going to get complaints about haircuts. Just make sure you double check to make sure everything is even. And, if you don't know how to do something be honest.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Never do hair color or perm (chemical) if you don't know how. Even if you do it's a good idea to review the instructions.</item>
<item>Avoid the drama of the salon. It's best not to say anything that you wouldn't want to get back. Keep private life, private.</item>
<item>Keep in mind that hairstylist work long hours plus weekends. Also by ourselves sometimes so it's important to be open minded, but let your boss or district leader know if it's too much.</item></list>
</text>
