<text id="autogum_interview_doc552" title="part4_Ingrid Newkirk, co-founder of PETA, on animal rights and the film about her life" shortTile="partingrid-newkirk" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-20" dateModified="2018-02-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ingrid_Newkirk%2C_co-founder_of_PETA%2C_on_animal_rights_and_the_film_about_her_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is arson a lesser of two evils proposition for you, then?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  Yes, absolutely.  Because if the buildings are standing, if the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slaughterhouse">slaughterhouse</ref> is standing, then the amount of pain and suffering—I mean, why would you preserve it just so someone can make a profit by continuing to hurt and kill individuals who feel every bit as much as we do?</p>
<head id="Newkirk_on_humans_and_other_animals">Newkirk on humans and other animals</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  A critic would say that there is no equating humans with animals.  That by stopping research that saves lives based upon these animals you are valuing chickens or mice over people.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  I think it hokum.  Total hokum.  First, you can’t have it both ways.  They are either like us or not like us.  You’re using them because they’re like us, then recognize the ways they are like us.  They are afraid to be in the cages.  The cages are tiny and uncomfortable and miserable.  They are frightened.  They are not treated well in the course of being experimented on.   It’s not as if it is just a few of them being used in life-saving experiments.  There are millions being used every year for fool things, including, still, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicotine">nicotine</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cocaine">cocaine</ref> experiments.  You know nicotine is bad for you.  Every little single thing is done to them.  But, on the other hand, they’re not like us physiologically in many ways that are important, which is what makes these tests invariably unscientific.  You can’t extrapolate from a mouse to a man.  They have a different <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metabolism">metabolism</ref>.  They have a very different <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Physiology">physiology</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Like the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saccharine">saccharine</ref> experiments, which were ridiculous because they showed it causes cancer in mice when you inject them with eight times their body weight daily with saccharine.  We aren’t mice, and who consumes such amounts?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  Yes!  People are scared, and experimenters who still use animals are only a percentage of all the people who do research in the U.S.  The other research fields are more profitable in terms of applicability; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Human%20clinical%20trials">human clinical work</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Epidemiology">epidemiological</ref> work, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer%20mapping">computer mapping</ref> work, all those things where you use human data, all those researchers are doing more productive work.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cloning">Cloning</ref> human skin, putting <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Human%20DNA">human DNA</ref> on the Internet.  This is where the money should be going.  Not doing things you did five hundred years ago by stuffing chemicals down animals’ throats, or performing some procedure that you later find out doesn’t even work on human beings.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think blocking stem cell research is something that harms animals?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  Yes, absolutely, if it’s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stem%20cell%20research">human stem cell research</ref>, we’re in favor of it.  If you are religiously opposed to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abortion">abortion</ref>, you do not have to take stem cells from the unabortus.  You can take stem cells in other ways such as from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Placenta">placenta</ref> or a live birth.  You can do other things.  You don’t have to violate your religious principles if that’s the problem.</p>
</text>
