<text id="autogum_academic_doc632" title="Nosocomial Vs. Community-Acquired Infective Endocarditis in Spain: Location, Trends, Clinical Presentation, Etiology, and Survival in the 21st Century" shortTile="nosocomial-vs-communityacquired" author="Christian Ortega-Loubon, María  Fe Muñoz-Moreno, Irene  Andrés García, Francisco  Javier Álvarez, Esther Gómez-Sánchez, Juan Bustamante-Munguira, Mario Lorenzo-López, Álvaro Tamayo-Velasco, Pablo Jorge-Monjas, Salvador Resino, Eduardo Tamayo, María Heredia-Rodríguez" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2077-0383/8/10/1755/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
We noted a constant increase in the incidence of IE in Spain, principally because of a dramatic rise in the proportion of NIE concurrent with a decline in the percentage of CIE. NIE showed higher morbidity than CIE, as elderly patients were the most affected group. The North reported the highest CIE incidence. Cox regression analysis revealed that age, Charlson index, hemodialysis, shock, heart failure, and stroke were independent risk factors of mortality for both NIE and CIE. In addition, the female sex, renal disease, and use of pacemakers or defibrillators were mortality-associated factors of CIE. </p>

<p>Numerous studies have confirmed a rising trend of IE rates over time. Olmos et al. found a significant increase in the incidence of IE in Spain from 2003 to 2014. Similarly, Bor et al. reported the rising number of IE episodes is due to <hi rend="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</hi> infections associated with cardiac devices and implants. The growing incidence of NIE could be related to the increase in the prevalence of healthcare-associated interventional procedures in recent years (e.g., hemodialysis, catheterization, intravenous line placement, cardiac implantable electronic devices, prostheses). Furthermore, this probably explains why IE rose in those patients older than 80 years. Another factor explaining the consistently increasing pattern might be the changes in the prevention of IE. The American Heart Association in 2007 revised and changed the consensus for antibiotic prophylaxis, recommending the withdrawal of routine antibiotic prophylaxis for dental procedures in low-risk and moderate-risk patients and most other invasive procedures in all patients. A similar trend occurred in the United Kingdom, where a substantial increase in IE cases was reported after the introduction of these guidelines in 2008. </p>

<p>We identified 45.9% of all IE to be NIE, which is moderately higher than previous reports, accounting for 10% to 30% of all IE episodes. This finding might be related to the increment of invasive procedures, major incidence of degenerative valve disease in elderly patients, and longer intensive care unit and hospital stays. In our study, 24.5% of patients underwent cardiac surgery during admission, which is similar to what has been reported in population-based studies from Italy and the United States. </p>

<p>In terms of gender, a major predominance of men was observed in comparison with women throughout the study period. Likewise, Toyoda et al. found a similar trend in their investigation conducted in the United States in which patients with IE were more likely to be male throughout the study period. In contrast with Toyoda et al., who described a decline in the cases of nosocomial endocarditis, our findings highlight the paramount importance of NIE, the incidence of which steeply rose despite all the coordinated efforts to reduce hospital-acquired infections through mandatory continuous reporting, regulated interventions, or evidence-based consensus recommendations.  </p>

<p>Concerning predisposing factors, a higher Charlson index (reflecting more comorbidities such as diabetes mellitus, hemodialysis, coronary artery disease, peripheral artery disease, cancer, as well as major complications ranging from sepsis, shock, heart failure, and cerebrovascular disease) were present in patients with NIE. This rise in underlying diseases might be related to the aging of the population and explains why those adults with NIE, especially those older than age 80 years, depicted the lowest survival rates.  </p>

<p>Regarding the microbiological profile, Gram-positive pathogens are still the most frequent microorganisms associated with IE, as previously reported in other series. These microorganisms often have a healthcare-associated origin, widely recognized as virulent and resistant organisms, and are related to high rates of complications and high mortality rates. Selton-Suty et al. demonstrated <hi rend="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</hi> as the only factor associated with a higher risk of in-hospital mortality in healthcare-associated IE. Compared with fungi, anaerobic, and streptococcal infection, mortality was higher for Gram-positive and Gram-negative pathogens, which differs from Toyoda et al.’s findings. </p>

<p>Spain’s climate varies across its geography, resulting in three broad regions: the North, where Atlantic weather characterized by a large proportion of humid days and the prevalence of precipitation; the Center, distinguished by a continental plateau with less precipitation; and the South, which is characterized by a Mediterranean climate with almost no precipitation, higher temperatures, and longer, sunny days. The higher IE incidence in the North region may be due to the higher level of humidity experienced there compared to the Center or South regions of Spain. These findings emphasized the importance of the site of acquisition. Indeed, to our knowledge, this is the first study to report a significant difference in IE rates in terms of location. This corresponds with Blanco et al.’s findings, who demonstrated that increasing humidity is associated with greater <hi rend="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</hi> colonization. Certainly, <hi rend="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</hi> infections are more common in humid weather conditions. Wang et al. reported a similar correlation between humidity and <hi rend="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</hi> infections.  </p>
</text>
