<text id="autogum_interview_doc386" title="part7_Wikinews interviews Mark Bunker, producer of anti-Scientology website &amp;apos;XenuTV&amp;apos;" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-05" dateModified="2016-03-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Mark_Bunker%2C_producer_of_anti-Scientology_website_%27XenuTV%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: There are some horrible abuses in other churches. I interviewed a couple people in a Christian cult in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wisconsin">Wisconsin</ref> with horrific stories to tell. I feel I have my hands full fighting Scientology and  hope others speak out for what they feel needs to be redressed. I stumbled upon a great site awhile back from former members of the Children of God. This group's founder promoted sex with kids and sent women out to recruit new members by sleeping with them. Watch some of [their] videos and your jaw will drop.  This kind of thing happens every day and we are unaware of it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">themandotcom</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What do you say to those people that say that Anonymous and the similar groups are religious bigots?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: Just say no. People can believe what they want. Just stop the fraud and abuse and if you speak out against my god Zeus, I will call you a bigot, too!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">StevenFruitsmaak</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Isn't it strange that some countries are recognizing Scientology as an official religion while other countries pursue the Church? What would you say to lawmakers in the former country? Perhaps a short three things you need to know about the Church?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: While there is a shared humanity, there are differences in laws and customs, too. Religion is such a taboo here in the U.S. that cloaking themselves with that was the smartest think Hubbard ever did. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">Germany</ref> has a unique perspective since it is in their charter that they will never again allow an extremist political group to rise again. That is an important thing to point out. They are not just a church. Hubbard wrote about how they should take over the government and be the ones to say what is legal BEFORE Scientology is stopped. Another important thing to know is that Scientology lies. If they are talking to you, they are lying to you. Look for the documented proof. The third thing, DM is a snappy dresser. Sorry couldn't come up with a third thing right now.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Kakama</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What do you think of the fact that Anonymous' motivations are not a moral outrage and are in fact based on the desire to destroy something and get laughs, aka lulz? What about the fact that Anonymous regularly uses illegal activity for its purposes (though we have suspended most in this raid) and is often risque and perverted in nature? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: The thousands in Anonymous who have reached out to me have moved beyond the lulz. There are going to be many who drop out but there are more who will learn and continue. Just this morning a member sent me a link to a Portuguese version of the Anonymous message to get people involved in his country. And a 14-year-old girl in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Finland">Finland</ref> said she gave a class report on Scientology because of this and got an A+ . She also told me she baked a cake for her mom and dad -- and put my name on it. I told her she's done something no one else on the planet has ever done. So the word gets out at the positive succeeds.</p>
</text>
