<text id="autogum_interview_doc688" title="part11_Sam Brownback on running for President, gay rights, the Middle East and religion" shortTile="partsam-brownback" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-12" dateModified="2014-12-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sam_Brownback_on_running_for_President%2C_gay_rights%2C_the_Middle_East_and_religion" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ethanol%20fuel">sugar ethanol</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  Sure.  Sugarcane ethanol?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think we should lower tariffs on sugar in order to be able to import more Brazilian sugar ethanol?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  You're gonna kill the ethanol industry here just as it gets going.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But it would reduce our dependency on foreign oil, thus increasing our national security, wouldn't it?  Or is the ethanol industry here more important?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  Well, I think on the equation you're talking about, I think getting the ethanol industry here going--and particularly on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/cellulosic%20ethanol">cellulosic ethanol</ref>.  And that's our big play to make here; we're--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But the energy that you derive from that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ethanol%20fuel%20energy%20balance">is so much less than it is in sugar ethanol</ref>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  I don't--you may be right on that.  I've not looked at that energy ratio, but--it's a sound environmental way to go, on cellulosic ethanol, and that's, I think, the big play we need to be making and pushing aggressively towards in this country for energy independence and good environmentalism.  I'm the lead Republican on a bipartisan bill that pushes this concept, and a big piece of it is getting plug-in cars on the marketplace than can do the first twenty or thirty miles off of electricity instead of either gasoline or ethanol, because half of the country doesn't drive over twenty or thirty miles a day.  And that way, you can really drop your imported oil use quickly; it's good for the environment, too.</p>
<head id="On_Wikipedia">On Wikipedia</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Senator, do you think that <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikipedia">Wikipedia</ref> is important?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  Yes, a lot of people use it to get a quick kind of reference point review of a lot of different topics, including politics.  And political figures.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Definitely.  What do you find important about it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  Just that.  I mean, it's an easy access; it can be amended.  I've not used it, but I've been with other people that have accessed it and know a lot of people that all say, "Yeah, I looked it up on Wikipedia," so I know it's broadly and widely used.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I tried to get an interview with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/David_Miscavige">David Miscavige</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scientology">Church of Scientology</ref>, and I spoke to their Director of Public Relations; I had about a twenty-minute phone call with him, and he was very hostile to it.  One of the things that I'd said to him--because he was saying that a lot of information is incorrect--I made the point to him that, "You know, it may be incorrect, but the idea is that you can have Scientologists go on there to correct it."  It's not a one-sided place for information; if you feel that there's inaccuracies, the idea is that you can also have people who know the truth go on there and correct it and debate about it, if that is what is necessary to get an accurate view.  Whereas if you say something to Newsweek, and they print something that's incorrect, you're stuck.</hi></p>
</text>
