<text id="autogum_interview_doc060" title="part0_Biologist Nick Bos tells Wikinews about &amp;apos;self-medicating&amp;apos; ants" shortTile="partbiologist-nick" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-09-01" dateModified="2015-10-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Biologist_Nick_Bos_tells_Wikinews_about_%27self-medicating%27_ants" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Biologist Nick Bos tells Wikinews about 'self-medicating' ants</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 1, 2015</hi></p>
<figure><caption><hi rend="italic">Formica fusca</hi>, from file.Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Leviathan1983">Mathias Krumbholz</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>Nick Bos, of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University%20of%20Helsinki">University of Helsinki</ref>, studies "the amazing adaptations social insects have evolved in order to fight the extreme parasite pressure they experience". In a recently-accepted <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evolution%20(journal)">Evolution</ref></hi> paper Bos and colleagues describe ants appearing to self-medicate.</p>
<hi rend="bold">I have no doubt that as time goes on, there will be more and more cases documented</hi>
<p>The team used <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Formica%20fusca">Formica fusca</ref></hi>, an <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ant">ant</ref> species that can form thousand-strong colonies. This common black ant eats other insects, and also <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/honeydew%20(secretion)">aphid honeydew</ref>. It often nests in tree stumps or under rocks and foraging workers can sometimes be spotted climbing trees.</p>
<p>Some ants were infected with <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beauveria%20bassiana">Beauveria bassiana</ref></hi>, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/fungus">fungus</ref>. Infected ants chose food laced with toxic <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/hydrogen%20peroxide">hydrogen peroxide</ref>, whereas healthy ants avoided it. Hydrogen peroxide reduced infected ant fatalities by 15%, and the ants varied their intake depending upon how high the peroxide concentration was.</p>
<p>In the wild, <hi rend="italic">Formica fusca</hi> can encounter similar chemicals in aphids and dead ants. <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Independent">The Independent</ref></hi> reported self-medicating ants a first among insects. </p>
<p>Bos obtained his doctorate from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University%20of%20Copenhagen">University of Copenhagen</ref>. He began postdoctoral research at Helsinki in 2012. He also runs the AntyScience blog. The blog aims to help address "a gap between scientists and 'the general public'." The name is a pun referencing ants, its primary topic, science, and "non-scientific" jargon-free communication. He now discusses his work with <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi>.</p>
<figure><caption><hi rend="italic">Beauveria bassiana</hi> on a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/cicada">cicada</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bolivia">Bolivia</ref>.Image: <ref target="http://www.mushroomobserver.org/observer/show_user/181">Danny Newman</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What first attracted you to researching ants?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Nick Bos</hi> Me and a studymate were keeping a lot of animals during our studies, from beetles, to butterflies and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/mantids">mantids</ref>, to ants. We had the ants in  an observation nest, and I could just look at them for hours, watching  them go about. This was in my third year of Biology study I think. After a while I needed to start thinking about an internship for my M.Sc. studies, and decided to write a couple of professors. I ended up going  to the Centre for Social Evolution at the University of Copenhagen where I did a project on learning in Ants under supervision of Prof. Patrizia d'Ettorre. I liked it so much there I ended up doing a PhD and I've been working on social insects ever since.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What methods and equipment were used for this investigation?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NB</hi> This is a fun one. I try to work on a very low budget, and like to  build most of the experimental setups myself (we actually have equipment in the lab nicknamed the 'Nickinator', 'i-Nick' and the 'Nicktendo64'). There's not that much money in fundamental science at the moment, so I try to cut the costs wherever possible. We collected  wild colonies of <hi rend="italic">Formica fusca</hi> by searching through old tree-trunks in old logging sites in southern Finland. We then housed the ants in nests I made using Y-tong [<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/aerated%20concrete">aerated concrete</ref>]. It's  very soft stone that you can easily carve. We carved out little  squares for the ants to live in (covered with old CD covers to prevent  them escaping!). We then drilled a tunnel to a pot (the foraging  arena), where the ants got the choice between the food with medicine  and the food without.</p>
</text>
