<text id="autogum_interview_doc452" title="part6_US presidential candidate Duncan Hunter speaks to Wikinews" shortTile="partus-presidential" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-12-12" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_presidential_candidate_Duncan_Hunter_speaks_to_Wikinews" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  Listen, I need to go to a conference right now, can I call you back?</p>
<head id="[Break_for_Congressman_Hunter_to_attend_a_conference]">[<hi rend="italic">Break for Congressman Hunter to attend a conference</hi>]</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Hi Congressman Hunter.  How was the meeting?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  Very good.  We wrapped up the defense conference.  That was with Senator Kennedy and Senator Levin, and they agreed to take the hate crimes bill off the defense bill, so we are going to move it forward and pass it, so it was good news.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> That happens a lot where they put disparate bills together in the hopes of moving them together.  What are some of the positives and what are some of the negatives of doing that?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  We do pass out-of-scope legislation in the defense bill sometimes; but the problem is putting in legislation that wouldn’t pass independently.  The downside is passing legislation that probably wouldn't pass or wouldn't be signed by the President otherwise.</p>
<head id="School_prayer">School prayer</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">You support school prayer?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  Yeah, I support folks having a place where young people can go to have a quiet time after their substantive activities and have a prayer.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Not a school mandated prayer?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  Not a state-enacted prayer.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">More a moment of silence?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  Not a moment of silence, but having a place where young people can go and prayer and still having that availability to do that.</p>
<head id="Pornography">Pornography</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You sponsored the Parents Empowerment Act--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  I wrote it.  I was the original author of it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> That Act would allow parents or guardians to sue in federal court anyone that disseminates material harmful to minors.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  Yeah, pornographic material that hurts young people.  That's one way to get to people that put out dirty images.  The key is that if they disseminate it in a way they can expect minors to see it, then they should be held liable for the damages of that material.  I came to that conclusion after watching the FCC operate in a very very haphazard and sluggish manner, very rarely responding to complaints.  And very under-manned even if they did respond energetically to complaints.  It gives parents the ability to hold pornographers liable for the damage to their children.  That's the only way you are going to stop them, to hit them in their pocketbook because they obviously don't care about the children.  They just care about their pocketbook.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Can you explain how that does not limit free speech, especially on the Internet?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  Yes, certainly.  Free speech, for example--nobody disagrees that somebody has a right to yell "Fire!" in a crowded theater; we all agree on that.  And nobody has the right to put pornographic literature in front of children or in the public, and from my perspective, that should be an actionable right that parents would have.  It empowers parents to go after people who are putting filth in front of their children, and to hit these people where they live, which is in their savings account or their check book.</p>
</text>
