<text id="autogum_whow_doc594" title="Understand Your Importance in Life" shortTile="understand-importance" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2008-02-25" dateModified="2016-09-21" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Understand-Your-Importance-in-Life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Understand Your Importance in Life</head><p>In such a confusing, ambiguous society sometimes you never really know what it's all about. Often times people will feel like no one needs them in this world. As much as it can sometimes seem as though the sun is always setting, somewhere on the globe it is also always rising. The beauty of your life is that you can change it all, it all starts with what you want to see.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Always have a reason to live for. Think about all the life on Earth. How in the great wide galaxy did something like this come to happen? No matter if you believe in the Big Man in White, Jesus, or even Extraterrestrial Pancakes there is something special here. Maybe you should see it all, or maybe you should help someone else see what you do. It's all in your perspective! <figure rend="Understand Your Importance in Life Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Those who fear change won't. So Don't! If you don't feel important or you feel inadequate, then you must make a change to live differently. Maybe you should just try something new, call up some old acquaintances, make some friends, or even start a garage band. Branch out and try something that isn't just based on your own efforts. Friends can always have an impact on each other. <figure rend="Understand Your Importance in Life Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Teamwork! You're not alone. You have something that you can give that can change someones life. Sometimes our time is the most valuable thing we can  give to each other. <figure rend="Understand Your Importance in Life Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Join a religion. Many people find purpose by believing in a higher power. Religion is a great way to change your perspective and even if you don't believe you can always meet some new people. <figure rend="Understand Your Importance in Life Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find yourself! Certainly if you had a map you could circle where you're standing, but maybe you should look for something that drives you. <figure rend="Understand Your Importance in Life Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>You Don't Have to Change the World. We don't live in a fly or die society. There is plenty of room to sight see and blaze a different trail. The most important person to be important to is yourself. <figure rend="Understand Your Importance in Life Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Many people have done selfless deeds, and didn't even notice. But little do they know, the receiver of your kind actions is probably very thankful. Like if you offered your unfinished bagel to someone in a restaurant, and paid no mind to it. They could have been having financial difficulties, and weren't able to afford food the day of their job application. Your kindness could have put them in a good mood, and allowed them to get the job. But if you weren't alive, they probably would've failed to get the job, and would still be in difficult times now. You perform countless kind actions everyday without even knowing, and your actions greatly impact others. <figure rend="Understand Your Importance in Life Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Understand the impact you've made on the world.</hi> In your mind, you may be just another face in the crowd. Another pair of hands, another imperfect human. But this is wrong. Your attitude defines everything about you, and all attitudes are contagious. Consider changing attitudes if yours isn't where it should be. <figure rend="Understand Your Importance in Life Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Have a good attitude. If you simply smile to everyone you see, they are much more likely to have a good day, and so are you. The simple act of smiling makes you happy, and your mood will spread to others.</item>
<item>Don't spread your bad attitudes. When you're having a bad day, and just can't seem to snap out of your funk, don't let others know. Try your hardest to show others a smile throughout your day. This will make them happier, and after smiling to so many people, you'll probably be happy too. If you frown at everyone you see, your vibe will rub off on them, and they'll all have bad days too.</item></list></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Know what you are capable of.</hi> Understand that if you really try, you can accomplish anything you'd like to do. If you truly believe in something enough, and continually make an effort to stand up for your beliefs, you <hi rend="italic">will</hi> make a difference in the world. Almost all famous people you've heard of have made huge differences in the world, most for the better. And many people you haven't heard of have made differences that affect your life to this day. Such as Rosalind Franklin. If it weren't for this unknown woman, we wouldn't know what DNA looks like. If she decided that she didn't make a difference in the world, we still probably wouldn't know. <figure rend="Understand Your Importance in Life Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always make an effort to help those in need.</item>
<item>Everyone is on this Earth for a reason. You're here, aren't you?</item>
<item>Understand who you are before trying to understand your importance in life.</item>
<item>Respect and explore religions. Humans who believe in a higher power, whether through Christianity, Buddhism, Judaism, Islam, or just spirituality, share a sense of their own place and importance in the world and a sense of inner peace and strength, no matter how they relate to their God.</item>
<item>Consider finding a religion to believe in. This will help you understand your purpose in life.</item>
<item>Gain perspective. Volunteer, even if just for an hour or two, at a soup kitchen, free clinic, homeless shelter, etc. Such life experiences are truly a "win-win." Not only do you help other people, you will likely have a greater appreciation for your own circumstances and opportunities.</item></list>
</text>
