<text id="autogum_interview_doc240" title="part1_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green Party candidate Torbjorn Zetterlund, Willowdale" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-06" dateModified="2013-05-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Green_Party_candidate_Torbjorn_Zetterlund%2C_Willowdale" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why? What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?</hi></p>
<p>The older parties are a challenge because people tend to vote along party lines and that is hard to change. However, I believe people, young and old, are realizing the importance of a healthy environment, as I have done, and are starting to realize that the Green Party is a viable alternative to those parties that have failed to lead on this issue.</p>
<p>I am an open and friendly person and will be approachable to my constituents. My willingness to communicate is the key strength I bring to the table.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>The top three issues for voters in Willowdale are Environment, Health Care and Schools. My priorities are similar, except I would add Proportional Representation. This election, we have a once in a lifetime opportunity to change the electoral system and make sure that every vote counts.</p>
<p>The Green Party has a comprehensive platform for addressing Environment, Health Care and Schools, based on sensible and affordable choices. We would shift taxes from income or payroll to waste and pollution. This will promote good policy without costing more. Cleaner air and water will mean lower health costs. Last year 88,000 people went to Emergency Rooms because of air pollution-caused difficulties. We also need to focus on preventive medicine and encourage our Health Care system to use alternative medicine, where appropriate, to keep us healthy. We should be encouraging children and adults to eat right and be active by providing nutrition education and counselling and exercise programs.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly?</hi></p>
<p>The Green Party would implement its economic plan of shifting taxes to shift behaviours and to upload services to the province that has been downloaded by previous governments, so we can start building stronger more sustainable cities in our province.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are the property taxes in your riding at a fair level for the amount of services received in the municipality?</hi></p>
<p>At the centre of the Green Party’s platform is a new way of thinking about taxes – where we shift from taxing what you earn to what you burn. With regards to property taxes, this would mean replacing the existing system with a "location value  tax" based only on land and not building values, to encourage denser growth in urban areas.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How can the province lead the way in stimulating job creation?</hi></p>
</text>
