<text id="autogum_whow_doc574" title="Show Your Pride As a Dog Owner" shortTile="show-pride-dog-owner" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2016-11-03" dateModified="2019-05-02" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Show-Your-Pride-As-a-Dog-Owner" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Show Your Pride As a Dog Owner</head><p>You love your dog and want to show your pride as a pet owner. You can do this by setting a good example for other pet owners through respectful behavior, like cleaning up after your dog and keeping your dog on a leash.You can also show your pride as a dog owner by entering your dog in competitive events. Talent and costumes contests are great examples! You can also show your pride as a dog owner by putting your dog to work. Training your pooch as a rescue or therapy dog is a great way to show off your pride while helping others.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Demonstrating Pride through Actions</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Clean up after your dog. One of the best ways to demonstrate your pride through action is to set a good example for others. Make sure you always leave the house with the supplies you need to clean up after your pup. Never leave your doggy’s doo unattended. After your dog does their business, clean it up and throw it away in a proper trash receptacle. <figure rend="Show Your Pride As a Dog Owner Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Always keep your dog on a leash. When you’re out for a walk with your dog, you can set a good example and show your pride as a pet owner by keeping your dog properly leashed. In most places, your dog is required to be on a leash, except in places where dogs can safely be off leash such as dog parks. <figure rend="Show Your Pride As a Dog Owner Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Respect your neighbors. Setting a good example as a dog owner means respecting those who live and work near you. This includes keeping your dog on your property, not letting your dog wander around the neighborhood, and preventing your dog from barking incessantly or excessively. <figure rend="Show Your Pride As a Dog Owner Step 3.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Showing off Your Dog’s Talents</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Enter your dog in a costume contest. A great way to be a proud dog owner is to enter your pooch in a costume contest. While Halloween is a common time for canine costume contests, you can also find them at other community celebrations throughout the year. Strive for a costume that is comfortable, yet clever. <figure rend="Show Your Pride As a Dog Owner Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Check out the festivities for local celebrations like independence day or other holidays, which are also popular times for dog costume contests.</item></list></item>
<item>Consider a dog race. Is your dog quick on their paws? If so, you can show your pride as a dog owner by entering them in a local race. Different communities have different options, often reflecting the climate and culture of the place where you live. Check with your local chamber of commerce or community board for events near you. <figure rend="Show Your Pride As a Dog Owner Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try a talent contest. Does your dog have a special talent? Some dogs can howl along to a song, while others are great at balancing balls on their noses. Whatever your dog’s talent, you can show be a proud dog owner by entering them in a contest. <figure rend="Show Your Pride As a Dog Owner Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Contact your local chamber of commerce, tourism board, or humane society to inquire about events going on near you.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Putting Your Pooch to Work</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Consider search and rescue training. Dogs can do amazing things like locating lost children, following a missing Alzheimer’s patient’s path from a nursing home, and assisting law enforcement officers at crime scenes. If your dog has a good nose, consider showing your pride as a dog owner by training them as a search and rescue dog. <figure rend="Show Your Pride As a Dog Owner Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can find out about opportunities for search and rescue training by contacting your local search and rescue or law enforcement organization.</item></list></item>
<item>Certify your dog as a therapy dog. Dogs who are certified as therapy dogs can bring joy and healing to a wide variety of people struggling with a vast array of issues or situations. Therapy dogs can help children, the elderly, and those fighting mental or physical illness. Consider getting your dog certified as a therapy dog if you want to show your pride by helping others. <figure rend="Show Your Pride As a Dog Owner Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Contact the American Kennel Club to find out how you can certify your pooch as a therapy dog.</item></list></item>
<item>Volunteer with your dog. Whether it’s a charity run with your pet, or taking them to a local nursing home to visit residents, there are many opportunities to show your pride as a pet owner through volunteerism. Contact your local animal shelter or community volunteer board to seek out opportunities near you. <figure rend="Show Your Pride As a Dog Owner Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Some ideas for volunteering with your dog include donating pet blood, taking in a foster dog who needs to socialize with other pets, or visiting a local hospital that welcomes dog interactions with patients.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
