<text id="autogum_voyage_doc301" title="Swedesboro" shortTile="swedesboro" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=34814" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Swedesboro</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Swedesboro</hi> is a borough in <ref target="Gloucester%20County%20%28New%20Jersey%29">Gloucester County</ref>, <ref target="New%20Jersey">New Jersey</ref>. It is a small quaint little town of a little over 2,500 people. Swedesboro was formed as a borough by an Act of the New Jersey Legislature on April 9, 1902, from portions of <hi rend="bold">Woolwich Township</hi> (population over 3,000), which completely surrounds it.</p>
<head>Understand</head>
<p>Swedesboro is situated on the south side of Raccoon Creek, about 5 miles from its mouth. It is an enclave within Woolwich Township, located 10 miles from Woodbury, NJ and about 18 miles from Camden. Swedesboro is one of only two Swedish settlements in New Jersey, along with <ref target="Bridgeport%20%28New%20Jersey%29">Bridgeport</ref>.</p>
<p>What is now known as the Borough of Swedesboro, was originally part of the colony named New Sweden, and was made up of Finnish and Swedish settlers [the present nation of Finland was then a part of Sweden]. From 1638 until 1656 the land along both shores of the Delaware River was the colony's territory, and ships continued to bring additional settlers, ruled by royal governors.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>Swedesboro is a relatively small town so the best (and only way if your not in walking distance) Is by car</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">From Delaware/Maryland</hi></p>

<p>1.Take I-295N exit toward New Castle/Del Memorial Bridge Entering New Jersey.</p>

<p>2.Take exit 11A to merge onto US-322 E toward Mullica Hill</p>

<p>3. Turn right at Paulsboro Rd</p>

<p>4. Turn right at County Rd 551 S</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">OR</hi></p>

<p>1. Take I-95 N</p>

<p>2. Take exit 4 to merge onto US-322 E/Barry Bridge Appr toward Comm Barry Bridge/New Jersey</p>

<p>3. Turn right at Paulsboro Rd</p>

<p>4. Turn right at County Rd 551 S</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">From The Philadelphia region</hi></p>

<p>1. Take I-76 E</p>

<p>2.Take exit 1A on the left to merge onto I-295 S toward Del Memorial Bridge</p>

<p>3. Take exit 11 to merge onto US-322 E toward Mullica Hill</p>

<p>4. Turn right at Paulsboro Rd</p>

<p>5. Turn right at County Rd 551 S</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">From Trenton</hi></p>

<p>1.Take the New Jersey Turnpike S</p>

<p>2. Take exit 2 for US-322 toward Swedesboro/Chester. Pa.</p>

<p>3. Turn left at US-322 W/Swedesboro Rd/Swedesboro Bridgeport Rd</p>

<p>4. Take the 1st left onto County Rd 551 S</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>Getting around Swedesboro is actually very simple The town is so small that everything is within walking distance. Walking from one end of the town to the other would take the average person no more than fifteen minutes.</p>

<p>Free parking is readily available behind any local retailer or restaurants. There is also meter parking available along Country Rd (the main street of the town) the cost of the meters is $.25 every 30 minutes</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Klein Memorial Auditorium</hi>, 177 State St, ☏ +1 203-259-1036 . a performing arts theater with a variety of performances throughout the year. If you enjoy the symphony, the Greater Bridgeport Symphony performs regularly.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Barnum Museum</hi>, 820 Main St, ☏ +1 203-331-1104 . Tu-Sa 10AM-4:30PM, Su 12PM-4:30PM.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Klein Memorial Auditorium</hi>, 177 State Street, ☏ +1 203-345-4800 . a performing arts theater with a variety of performances throughout the year. If you enjoy the symphony, the Greater Bridgeport Symphony performs regularly.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Beckett Golf Club</hi>, 2387 Kings Highway, ☏ +1 856-467-4700 . Public, 54 holes, $18.00 - $35.00. This club offers three nine hole courses that are played in three eighteen hole combinations. The White Course has open fairways and large greens. The Blue Course has tight, tree-lined fairways and fast greens. The Red Course has flat fairways and large greens. There are water hazards that come into play on all three courses.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Stratton Hall</hi>. Charles C. Stratton was borne here, <date when="1796-03-06">March 6, 1796</date>. He was the first New Jersey governor elected by the people, 1845.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lake Narraticon</hi>. This lake is known for great bass fishing.</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Petals and Paints</hi>, 1330 Kings Hwy, ☏ +1 856 467-7667 . A local flowers and gifts shop serving the needs of local customers for the past 10 years</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Scarecrow Factory</hi>, 25 East Ave, ☏ +1 856 769-1050 . a unique Victorian shope the cozy rooms are filled with country, primitive and Victorian decor. Each room is displayed with decorating ideas in mind.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Rode's Fireside</hi>. For a great small town home cooked meal look no farther then Rode's Fireside probably the most unique dining experience available for visitors of Swedesboro.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tavro 13</hi>, 1301 Kings Hwy, Swedesboro, NJ, ☏ +1 856-467-8413 . Steakhouse.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Vesuvio's</hi>. Hands down the best Italian cuisine available in a 30 mile radius. The food has been prepared for the past 10 years by the local Piscarte family and has an exceptional taste that comes from years of experience. The portions are plentiful and the prices are very reasonable</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Village Center</hi>, 5 Village Center Drive, Swedesboro, NJ, ☏ +1 856 467-9030 . 12:00pm-2:00am. Small town Bar visited by the same locals regularly. Has daily specials and affordable prices. nice quite place to go and grab a drink</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hampton Inn</hi>, 2 Pureland Dr, ☏ +1 856 467-6200 . Check-in: 3PM, check-out: noon. Has a pool, jacuzzi, and gym and as all Hampton Inns is known for being exceptionally clean and comfortable. $79+ per night.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Holiday Inn</hi>, 1 Pureland Dr, toll-free: +1-888-467-3322 . Check-in: 3PM, check-out: 11AM. Has a pool, gym, 24 hour room service, free weekend brunch, florist, and a restaurant inside the hotel. $120+.</item>
</list>
</text>
