<text id="autogum_interview_doc196" title="part5_Andrea Muizelaar on fashion, anorexia, and life after &amp;apos;Top Model&amp;apos;" shortTile="partandrea-muizelaar" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-25" dateModified="2012-02-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Andrea_Muizelaar_on_fashion%2C_anorexia%2C_and_life_after_%27Top_Model%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> These girls were set up by the producers [and were asked] devious questions about me.  I did not even know that anyone went through my personal belongings until I watched the show myself.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> What did the producers say? On TV, due to editing, it comes across as Alanna and Brandi deciding to be nosy and poke through your things.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> They were asked questions such as, "Soooo, what do you think of all the candy that Andrea has in her suitcase?"</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> And they didn't know you had any before that time?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> Not to my knowledge.  I was pretty good at hiding things due to my eating disorder.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> After the final runway show, you did a private interview and you said something that stuck out. "I have learned so much about being a woman, about being a model, about being beautiful." Considering what happened to you during the competition and later on, do you still feel what you learned was genuine? If not, what do you feel isn't genuine, and what good things did you bring from the experience?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> The whole show was a learning experience; I learned many tips about modelling and tricks of the trade and will have them in my back pocket forever.  The thing that I brought from the experience is that the industry is not glamorous in the least and by the grace of God all these experiences brought me to my senses and the healthy and real woman that I am today.</p>
<head id="The_message_she_wrote_to_her_fans_on_her_facebook_group">The message she wrote to her fans on her facebook group</head>
<p><hi rend="italic">Andrea first told her story via facebook. You can read her statement <ref target="http://usf.facebook.com/group.php?gid=18792047424">here</ref>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> You wrote that you decided to audition for Canada's Next Top Model knowing that you would have to perpetuate an image of unhealthiness and false images of beauty. Why did you choose to go down that road if you knew of the risks?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> At the time I did not feel that I was unhealthy - it was part of the requirements for CNTM.  I had no idea of the risks, plus my eating disorder took 5 years of my life and I had to prove to myself and my family that it was all because of this disorder.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> You seem to describe a battle of what you wanted more, which in this case, modeling almost won out over your health. What finally made you realize that modeling became too much to bear, and why did modeling mean that much to you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> I had no friends or family to support me [in Toronto].  My health started to slip (i.e., toenails falling off). My health was in severe jeopardy.  Modelling meant a lot to me as any young girl's dreams [would].</p>
</text>
