<text id="autogum_voyage_doc223" title="Iran" shortTile="iran" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=15713" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Iran</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.tourismiran.ir/">Iran</ref></hi> (<ref target="Persian%20phrasebook">Persian</ref>: <hi rend="bold">ایران</hi>) is a large country between the Gulf of Oman, the <ref target="Persian%20Gulf">Persian Gulf</ref>, and the Caspian Sea. It was renamed Iran in the early 20th century; before that it was known as <hi rend="bold">Persia</hi>. It is bordered by <ref target="Iraq">Iraq</ref> to the west, <ref target="Turkey">Turkey</ref>, Azerbaijan's <ref target="Nakhchivan">Nakhchivan</ref> enclave, <ref target="Armenia">Armenia</ref>, and <ref target="Azerbaijan">Azerbaijan</ref> to the northwest, <ref target="Turkmenistan">Turkmenistan</ref> to the northeast, and <ref target="Afghanistan">Afghanistan</ref> and <ref target="Pakistan">Pakistan</ref> to the east.</p>

<p>Iran can be considered part of the <ref target="Middle%20East">Middle East</ref>, and thus it is included as part of that region here. However, it is also very much a part of <ref target="Central%20Asia">Central Asia</ref>; indeed the <ref target="Persian%20Empire">Persian Empire</ref> was the dominant power in that region for many centuries.</p>

<head>Cities</head>
<p>Nine of the most notable cities are:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> (Persian: <hi rend="bold">تهران</hi>) – the vibrant capital, a beautiful city that suffers horrendous traffic and air pollution</item>
<item> (Persian: <hi rend="bold">همدان</hi>) – one of the oldest cities in Iran</item>
<item> (Persian: <hi rend="bold">اصفهان‎</hi>) – a former capital with stunning architecture, great bazaar, and tree-lined boulevards. Most popular tourist destination in the country. There's a Persian saying that "Isfahan is half the world."</item>
<item> (Persian: <hi rend="bold">کرمان</hi>) – this south-eastern city is one of the five historical cities of Iran.</item>
<item> (Persian: <hi rend="bold">مشهد</hi>‎‎) – the greatest city of eastern Iran, with an important mosque, the shrine of the Imam Reza</item>
<item> (Persian: <hi rend="bold">قم</hi>‎‎) – one of the holiest cities in the Middle East, considered the Jewel of Iran</item>
<item> (Persian: <hi rend="bold">شیراز</hi>) – a former capital, home of famous Persian poets such as Hafiz and Sa'di; known for gardens, especially roses. Very close to the famous ruins of Persepolis.</item>
<item> (Persian: <hi rend="bold">تبریز</hi>) – a former capital with a great historical bazaar, now a provincial capital in western Iran; it's been suggested that this is the site of the Biblical "Garden of Eden"</item>
<item> (Persian: <hi rend="bold">یزد‎‎</hi>) – a remote desert city – circumstance influenced special architectural themes where water streams run in underground rooms in houses and wind-towers to keep them cool.</item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> (Persian: <hi rend="bold">الموت‎‎</hi>), near <ref target="Qazvin">Qazvin</ref> – castle of the legendary Assassins.</item>
<item> (Persian: <hi rend="bold">دیزین</hi>) – one of the highest ski resorts in the world, two hours north of <ref target="Tehran">Tehran</ref>. Great powder snow, cheap prices and few international visitors makes this is a great place for a ski holiday.</item>
<item> (Persian: <hi rend="bold">کیش‎‎</hi>) – a free trade zone in the Persian Gulf, it is regarded as a consumer's 'paradise', with numerous malls, shopping centres, tourist attractions, and resort hotels. There is also Iran's first marina on the east side of the island.</item>
<item> (Persian: <hi rend="bold">قشم</hi>) – Iran's largest and the Persian Gulf's largest island. Qeshm island is famous for its wide range of ecotourist attractions such as the Hara marine forests. According to environmentalists, about 1.5% of the world birds and 25% of Iran's native birds annually migrate to Hara forests which is the first national geo park.</item>
<item> (Persian: <hi rend="bold">پاسارگاد</hi>) – the first capital of the Achaemenid Empire, and home to the tomb of Cyrus the Great.</item>
<item> – impressive ruins of a vast city-like complex built over 2,500 years ago, near the modern city of Shiraz. It was set on fire by Alexander of Macedon and further ruined by Arabs. Called TakhteJamshid in Persian, Persepolis is the symbol of Iranian nationality.</item>
<item> (Persian: <hi rend="bold">شوش‎‎</hi>) – 200 km north of Ahvaz, was Iran's most ancient city. The Ziggurat of Chughazanbil, Darius the Great's palace, the Jewish prophet Daniel's temple and Artaxerxer II 's palace are among the historical sites.</item>
</list>


<head>Understand</head>
<p>Iran, the wellspring of one of the world's great civilizations, is a country of striking natural beauty and gorgeous tiled mosques. Its landscape is incredibly varied. Its recent history has been tumultuous.</p>

<head>People</head>
<p>Humans have inhabited the area that makes up modern Iran since the Stone Age. There are paintings in Dusheh cave that date back to 15,000 BC.</p>

<p>The ancient Persians arrived about 1500 BC, one branch of the great movement of people that also brought northern India and most of Europe their modern populations. The name Iran is from the same root as "Aryan" which, until Hitler perverted it, was just an ancient name for those arriving peoples. <ref target="Persian">Persian</ref> (natively known as Farsi) is an Indo-European language; ancient Persian was related to Sanskrit, ancient Greek, and all the others in that family. Persians are ethnically and linguistically unrelated to their neighbours on the west, the Arabs and Turks, but are related to various groups to the east and north.</p>

<p>Iran has many people other than ethnic Persians; there are substantial minorities with their own languages, Minorities with Indo-European languages related to Persian include Kurds in parts of the west and northwest, Baluchis in parts of the southeast, and Armenians in the north and in <ref target="Isfahan">Isfahan</ref> where one of the Shahs transported them a few centuries back. Minorities with Turkic languages include the Azeris who make up much of the population of <ref target="Iranian%20Azerbaijan">Azerbaijan</ref> in the northwest and the Qashqai, a nomadic people in the region around <ref target="Shiraz">Shiraz</ref>. There are also Arabs and, last but not least, Jews, who have been living in Iran peacefully for centuries.</p>

<p>There are also two substantial communities of people of Iranian descent in India and Pakistan - Parsis who have been there for over 1,000 years, and Iranis who arrived in the 19th and 20th centuries - both Zoroastrians who fled religious persecution in Iran.</p>

<head>History</head>
<p>Persia has always exerted a large cultural influence on its neighbors, especially <ref target="Afghanistan">Afghanistan</ref>, the <ref target="Caucasus">Caucasus</ref> and <ref target="Central%20Asia">Central Asia</ref>. Persian influence can be seen in the art, architecture and languages of these areas, and in the <ref target="Indian%20Subcontinent">Indian Subcontinent</ref>.</p>

<p>The <ref target="Persian%20Empire">empire</ref> existed over most of the time period from about 500 BCE until the revolution of 1979, but its fortunes varied enormously over the centuries. During the Achaemenid Empire, Persia controlled most of what we now call the <ref target="Middle%20East">Middle East</ref>, and after Cyrus the Great's conquest of Ionia, Persia came close to conquering <ref target="Greece">Greece</ref> in the Greco-Persian Wars of 499-449 BC. In 331 BC, Alexander conquered (among other places) the entire Persian Empire.</p>

<p>Sassanid rule from 205 AD to 651 AD is considered to be the most influential period of ancient Persia. In 651 AD, immediately after the death of Muhammad, the brutal conquest of Persia by the Arabs brought an end to the Sasanian Empire. Persian and other languages of the region are still written with the Arabic alphabet. In 1221 AD, Persia was overrun by Genghis Khan and the <ref target="Mongol%20Empire">Mongols</ref>. <ref target="On%20the%20trail%20of%20Marco%20Polo">Marco Polo</ref> passed through later in that century, learned Persian, and wrote extensively of the region. Tamerlane conquered Persia in 1383, and after a revolt in 1387, killed hundreds of thousands of people and built a tower with their skulls.</p>

<p>The Safavid dynasty re-united Persia as an independent state in 1501, established Shi'a <ref target="Islam">Islam</ref> as the official religion, and ushered in a golden age of Persian culture. The dynasty was overthrown in 1736 by Nader Shah, the last great Asian conqueror, who expanded the empire to again include Afghanistan and much of India. His short-lived dynasty and its successor, the Zand dynasty, lasted until 1795.</p>

<p>The Qajar dynasty ruled from 1795-1925. While many of the historic buildings in Iran are from this period, this era is considered to be one of decline for Iran, as the rulers were more interested in building their collections of art and jewels and succumbed to heavy pressure from foreign powers, notably Britain and Russia who jointly occupied Iran during World War I. In 1906, Qajar rule became a constitutional monarchy and the Majlis (Persian for parliament) was established.</p>
</text>
