<text id="autogum_interview_doc914" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Donald K. Allen, independent candidate for US presidency" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-10-02" dateModified="2009-03-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Donald_K._Allen%2C_independent_candidate_for_US_presidency" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What is your opinion on the war in Iraq? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Donald K. Allen</hi>: I believe it is coming to a resolution with both the Iraqi government seeking a timetable and both Iraqi and US military forces finding success in quelling hostility.  I cannot change what is in the past, but I can shape the future.  I would seek total drawdown in Iraq within two years.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What is your opinion on the war in Afghanistan? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Donald K. Allen</hi>: The real focus of our "war on terror" should be where al Qaeda is, and that is primarily in eastern Afghanistan.  The war against bin Laden and his group will continue, as will the war against the Taliban.  It will not be an easy task, as we have already seen.  More troops will be needed and more international cooperation to wipe out this societal cancer.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What is your opinion on the creation of a North American Union?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Donald K. Allen</hi>: I am totally against the formation of a North American Union.  This is a goal of the Council on Foreign Relations, which you could call America's "shadow government."  Both Obama and McCain are members of the CFR, as are many of President Bush's administrative staff.  Who needs foreign affairs experience when the CFR is going to tell you what to do?  I will investigate all work to date on this effort to create the NAU, including the NAFTA superhighway and Rudi Giuliani's law firm's involvement in it.  There is a lot of "quiet" work that has already been done on the NAU project without the American public's knowledge.  This will make the Teapot Dome scandal look like kids' play.</p>
<head id="On_other_issues">On other issues</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Is there anything else you would like to say to people reading this article? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Donald K. Allen</hi>: If you think the safe thing to do Nov. 4 is vote for the Republican or Democratic candidate of your "choice," then you are sadly mistaken.  Both will continue to lead this country down the road to a North American Union and the New World (socialist) Order.  The only way "we the people" can shake up Washington and bring about revolutionary change in our government is through the election of a true independent President - our first since George Washington!  Following is a list of my intentions.</p>
<p>As President I Will:</p>
<p>1.   Complete a secure border fence on our southern border.</p>
<p>2.   Sign The Fair Tax Bill to rejuvenate economy.</p>
<p>3.   Establish “loser pays” litigation reform and work tirelessly for real tort reform.</p>
<p>4.   Transition our monetary system to a specie-backed currency and close the Federal Reserve System.</p>
<p>5.   Seek to overturn Roe vs. Wade and return the decision to the States.</p>
<p>6.   Work to establish term limits for Congress.</p>
</text>
