<text id="autogum_interview_doc764" title="part2_Canada&amp;apos;s Parkdale—High Park (Ward 13) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-parkdalehigh" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-16" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Parkdale%E2%80%94High_Park_%28Ward_13%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>While already recognized as a world class City and among the best in the world, the potential for Toronto to lead in all aspects is there and waiting to be utilized.</p>
<p>Through engagement of our City's populous I foresee that Toronto can make the transition from greatness to becoming the recognized world's best if we act on and make use of our untapped local resources in a more effective manner.</p>
<head id="Aleksander_Oniszczak">Aleksander Oniszczak</head>
<p>39-year-old <hi rend="bold">Aleksander Oniszczak</hi> is a freelance journalist.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Describe the three most important issues in your campaign.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Taxes and Spending: Lawn signs, billboards, flyers - have you noticed that my opponents are spending a lot of money on their campaigns? Do you think they will stop spending a lot of money if they get elected? I believe fiscal responsibility is not just a phrase to drop in interviews. Intelligent and resourceful solutions are needed to get full value for our tax dollars. I don't just say it, I do it. Did I spend thousands of dollars on a flashy website? No, I created it myself. A can-do attitude can go far. Councillor wages need to be rolled back as well. We need to do our part. Of course, the flip side of the coin has Toronto paying a disproportionate amount of money in taxes compared to the services it receives. The Province, the Federal government and most importantly, the people of Canada need to have this made clear to them. It simply will not change until we have their support. Toronto is the economic engine of Canada and when that engine needs an oil change, it is best not to wait until it seizes up.</p>
<p>No More Ugly Buildings: Rampant uncontrolled overdevelopment needs to stop. We need to listen to the concerns of our citizens. Why is it that banks are allowed to build such monstrously ugly buildings in the area while other businesses like the McDonalds in Bloor West Village manage to be good corporate citizens and build to integrate with the neighbourhood? Why are condos being built where they are not wanted? Council needs a vision and a plan.</p>
<p>Traffic calming measures have backfired in the Ward. Traffic is worse than ever. We need a real integrated plan rather than a patchwork of band-aid solutions.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What one election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Property Tax: It affects everyone in the area homeowners and tenants alike. Our taxes have gone up but our services have gone down. Although it is less expensive to service homes in our area for garbage collection than it is in the more spread out suburbs, we pay more. Our infrastructure is already built, but our taxes go to build new, less efficient suburban ones outside our ward. Long time residents are being forced to move due to spiraling cost increases. Common sense is needed to put an end to this injustice.</p>
</text>
