<text id="autogum_reddit_doc079" title="The last (?) update about The Fucking Car and Forgetful Custodian" shortTile="last--update-fucking" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-04-30" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8g2tmh" speakerList="#dannoseverin, #zlooch" speakerCount="2">
<head>The last (?) update about The Fucking Car and Forgetful Custodian</head>
<sp who="#dannoseverin">
<p>See BB for post history. The Fucking Car has been sold to my friend and all is great! Wait. What sub is this again? Ah, yeah. No. The car has been sold, the paperwork has been sent in and money has been handed over to me. Now, that fucking car is now my friends car. Her husband is in love with it (like, seriously in love, he signs the Toyota song every time he drives it), and my friend is still trying to get to know the car. All is good on that front. Kind of. My friend has her own just no relatives that's pissed about the whole purchase, but this is not the sub for that. Anyway. Last week on my birthday I bought myself my very own (and very first!) car. All is good right?! Yes and no. I love the car! It's just what I wanted in a car. What kind of car is it, you ask? A 3yo MINI Cooper. I didn't think I could love a car at all, but dammit I love it! Like stupidly much. It's totally my car! Forgetful Custodian? Ahahahahaha ahaaaa. No. Much CBF was had when I got home with it. Dad did a 180 and was all over it with questions about it. Suddenly he had no problem at all with the selling of the old car they pushed on me. FC sat in my car and looked like she had sucked the biggest batch of lemons ever. She was NOT happy. Why? The car had cheaper tax than the fucking car she forces upon me, it is cheaper fuel wise, and generally a lot newer (and more fancy) than any car she even "suggested" to me while I looked for a car. This Saturday FC wanted to go to town. Despite my better knowledge (yeah, I'm fucking stupid) I accompanied her, and we took my car for a spin. FC told me I drive like a car thief. Well, she's not wrong. Kind of. I drove a bit like one because the car is fun to play with you know. The handling is fantastic! Okey, enough about the car. FC didn't say anything bad about it the whole trip to the store in town, the only thing indicating she disapproved of the car was a silent treatment and crossed arms. I didn't care. I have a car! I sang along with the music and loved the hell out of MY car. MY CAR YALL! Me, mine, my car! Anyway, when we got out of the first store I stupidly asked FC if she wanted to try and drive the car. Yep, I'm stupid. So fucking stupid. FC:  <hi rend="bold"> sighs </hi>  "okey then." Thankfully I don't have to hand over the keys to get the car going (keyless car!). I instructed her how to turn it on and such, and off we go. When we get to the next store she reluctantly says: "it was nice to drive". Damn straight it is! She wouldn't dare say anything else about it. Yesterday I went out with friends. I left my car keys at home in the pocket of my work pants (important detail), and left without telling. I seriously don't want FC to know where my car keys are, nor where I store my wallet and home keys when I'm not at home. I don't trust her any more. Anyway, we have fun my friends and I. I get home late and that's it. Right? Nope. This morning dad tried cornering me. Dad: "You should have told us where the car keys where." Me: "Why? Did you need to move it or something?" Dad: "No. But..." Me: "Then you don't need to know where the car keys are. Period." Dad: "What if..." Me: "If you needed to move it for god knows what, then you could've called me. You know, it ain't that fucking hard to pick up the phone." Queue dad repeating himself for a moment, then goes silent as the ongoing car war between our neighbors flairs up again outside (seriously! Is there a sub for just no neighbours?). Later today around noon FC comes home, and (yup, you guessed it) she starts about the car keys. FC: "You should tell us where you keep the car keys!" Me: "Why? Did you need to move the car?" FC: "No. How did you know I was going to say that?" Me: "Because dad said the same thing. Why do you need to know where the keys are?" FC: "What if..." Me: "What if you need to move the car because sudden snow fall? Then you could have called me and asked where the keys are. Period." FC: "You have spare keys... Where are they?" Me: "That's for me to know, and I choose not to tell you. You don't have to know where they are. Period." Much CBFs were had today about that. My car, my keys, my rules. It did cross my mind that both dad and FC might take the car out for a spin without telling me. I told my friends about this whole exchange, and they said basically the same. They also gave the suggestion to hide the keys in different spots each time. And knowing what FC is afraid of (rats) I intend to buy a fuckload of rubber rats and hide around the house for her to find whenever she tries to find my car keys to sneak off with my car. </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#zlooch">
<p>OK, I may be thinking the worst, but hey, you know what sub we're in. </p>
<p>I AM extremely worried that if FC knew where the keys were, would have some totally transparent reason for driving your car, and OOPS!!! When you get home, you discover that either the car has a nice new big ugly disfiguring dent in it, maybe still driveable, but cosmetically it would be trashed and every time you looked at it you would feel discouraged. </p>
<p>OR </p>
<p>The car ends up totalled, and undriveable, and not covered by insurance because it was an at fault accident or because FC isn't on the insurance. And then she will graciously offer to lend you the money to get another car, on the condition that it is a car of her choosing. </p>
<p>Either way, you end up miserable and all your good feelings about your awesome new car is tainted by her. </p>
<p>I really really really hope that doesn't happen!! Stay firm and try and cover all eventualities to make sure that never happens. </p>
<p>Other than that, your car sounds awesome!! </p>
</sp>
</text>
