<text id="autogum_voyage_doc48" title="Tennessee" shortTile="tennessee" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=35597" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Tennessee</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Tennessee</hi> is a <ref target="United%20States%20of%20America">US</ref> state in the <ref target="South%20%28United%20States%20of%20America%29">South</ref> known for its rich history, music, and the <ref target="Appalachian%20Mountains">Appalachian Mountains</ref> along its eastern border.</p>

<head>Regions</head>
<p>Each region is known for its distinctive musical heritage: Bluegrass (East), Country-western (Middle), and Blues (West).</p>

<head>Cities</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> – Country music capital of the world and the Tennessee state capital.</item>
<item> – home of the Chattanooga Choo Choo and the Tennessee Aquarium.</item>
<item> – a City with Spirit and home of Lee University</item>
<item> – Gateway to the <ref target="Great%20Smoky%20Mountains%20National%20Park">Great Smoky Mountains National Park</ref></item>
<item> – one of America’s Most Charming Towns &amp; Villages</item>
<item> – site of East Tennessee State University and the USVA Mountain Home.</item>
<item> – Home of the University of Tennessee at Knoxville</item>
<item> – Home of the blues and the birthplace of rock 'n' roll.</item>
<item> – Home of Dollywood – Country Legend Dolly Parton's amusement park.</item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
</list>


<head>Time zones</head>
<p>Tennessee is the only state in the U.S. to have more than one metropolitan area in each of two time zones. Roughly the eastern third of the state is in the Eastern Time Zone—this includes Knoxville and Chattanooga. The rest of Tennessee is on Central Time (same as Chicago). If you have to be somewhere at a certain time in the Eastern zone (and are in the Central zone), don't forget to allow for an extra hour to get there.</p>

<head>Talk</head>
<p>Many native Tennesseans speak in the dialect of the American South. This dialect changes slightly as you cross through each region, and is especially pronounced in rural areas</p>

<p>Generally speaking, it is accepted that people in the South speak more slowly, and carefully than those from the North. In particular, visitors from larger cities will have to adjust to the different pace of speech if they visit Tennessee's smaller mountain towns; speaking quickly and bluntly can be perceived as inconsiderate and may engender a negative response. Some Tennesseans in especially rural or mountainous areas may be difficult to understand by those not familiar with American South or Appalachian colloquialisms, slurring or speech cadence.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>Interstate 40 criss-crosses the state from west to east, connecting Memphis, Nashville, Knoxville and the Smoky Mountain Region. Interstate 55 is entirely situated in Memphis. Interstate 155 crosses from Missouri into northwest Tennessee, ending in Dyersburg. Interstate 24 enters from Kentucky near Clarksville, passes through Nashville and ends in Chattanooga (but not before briefly dipping into Georgia for about three miles). Interstate 65 runs through Nashville in its trek from Kentucky to Alabama. Interstate 75, coming from Kentucky, links Knoxville with Chattanooga before heading into Georgia. Interstate 81 starts at Interstate 40 just east of Knoxville and heads northeast to Bristol before moving into Virginia. In the Kingsport area, Interstate 26 runs south from Interstate 81 into North Carolina (towards <ref target="Asheville">Asheville</ref>), while Interstate 181 heads toward Kingsport and the Virginia state line.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>There are several airports in the state. Memphis International Airport is a hub for Delta Air Lines and is served by several other airlines. Nashville International Airport is also served by many other airlines. There is air service at smaller airports at Maryville (Knoxville), Chattanooga and Bristol. Southern Tennessee is easily accessible to the <ref target="Huntsville%20%28Alabama%29">Huntsville</ref>, Alabama, airport.</p>

<head>By train</head>
<ref target="Rail%20travel%20in%20the%20United%20States">Amtrak</ref> service in Tennessee is limited to the <hi rend="italic">City of New Orleans</hi> service stopping in Memphis and Newbern.

<head>By bus</head>
<p>Greyhound offers service throughout Tennessee. Megabus offers service to Memphis (from <ref target="Chicago">Chicago</ref>, <ref target="Champaign-Urbana">Champaign-Urbana</ref>, <ref target="St.%20Louis">St. Louis</ref>, <ref target="Atlanta">Atlanta</ref>, <ref target="Birmingham%20%28Alabama%29">Birmingham</ref>, <ref target="Dallas">Dallas</ref>, and <ref target="Little%20Rock">Little Rock</ref>), to Nashville (from Atlanta), to Chattanooga (from Atlanta), and to Knoxville (from <ref target="Washington%2C%20D.C.">Washington, D.C.</ref>, <ref target="Christiansburg">Christiansburg</ref> and Atlanta).</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>As in most American states, automobiles are the primary form of travel. In larger cities you will find public bus systems, and Greyhound buses are an option for travel in between cities. There are also major airports in all large cities (Nashville, Memphis, Knoxville, Chattanooga, and the Tri-Cities) and many smaller airports scattered across the state.</p>

<p>There is no option for rail travel to Middle or East Tennessee. However, Amtrak runs the fabled "City of New Orleans" line through Memphis and Newbern. This is certainly worth considering if you are planning to visit those areas, especially if you are heading along the Mississippi River. Also, the city of Nashville operates a commuter rail from the suburbs to the downtown area.</p>

<head>Eat</head>

<p>It is becoming increasingly rare to locate truly authentic "Southern" cuisine in places other than a privately owned family kitchen table, but the state still offers some truly wonderful regional fare.</p>

<p>In <ref target="Memphis">Memphis</ref>, missing <ref target="http://www.hogsfly.com/">Rendezvous</ref>, host to American presidents and prime ministers, would be a sin.</p>

<head>Do</head>
<p>The Great Smoky Mountains National Park is a World Heritage Biosphere Reserve and draws millions of visitors from around the region and the world annually. Covering nearly 1,000 square miles it is home to temperate rainforests and some of the rarest and most unique plant life in North America. The park suffers from high levels of air pollution due to surrounding cities such as Knoxville and Sevierville as well as the numerous coal-fired power plants of the Tennessee Valley Authority.</p>

<p>Traffic congestion is fairly severe within the Park's Cades Cove "loop," as many people stop to take in the vistas of the sprawling valley and its many deer and bears that freely roam the area. If you plan to go, car pool if you can.</p>

<p>Depending on where you plan to visit, there are many things to do in Tennessee from white water rafting on the Ocoee River, to visiting Gatlinburg, and seeing the Music City of Nashville. For outdoor adventures, you must go visit the Ocoee River rafting, which was home of the Olympics. You can have an all day adventure going down the Ocoee River and experience the fun of the outdoors.</p>

<head>Floods</head>
<p>During the spring months, the state is often heavily affected by major rain storms which lead to a risk of major flood potential. These floods are by <hi rend="italic">no means</hi> on a small scale; they are often widespread and last for several days or even weeks. In May 2010, the state experienced a "1000-year flood" which resulted in numerous fatalities and over $2 billion of property damage statewide.</p>

<p>Travelers to the region during this season should consider planning ahead; stay informed about weather events in the region before making your journey. If there is an eminent flood warning or an ongoing threat of a flood occurring in the area at which you plan to travel to or through, consider deferring your travel plans or take an alternate route to your final destination. Avoid flood ravaged areas, as these areas are unsafe for any non-essential travel.</p>
</text>
