<text id="autogum_bio_doc065" title="Abdullah H. Abdur-Razzaq" shortTile="abdullah-h-abdurrazzaq" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-12-15" dateModified="2019-09-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abdullah_H._Abdur-Razzaq" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Abdullah H. Abdur-Razzaq</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Abdullah H. Abdur-Razzaq</hi> (December 20, 1931 – November 21, 2014) was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/African-American">African-American</ref> activist and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muslim">Muslim</ref> known for being one of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malcolm_X">Malcolm X</ref>'s most trusted associates. Born <hi rend="bold">James Monroe King Warden</hi>, he was known as <hi rend="bold">James 67X</hi> when he belonged to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nation_of_Islam">Nation of Islam</ref> and <hi rend="bold">James Shabazz</hi> in the years after he left the organization.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ColumbiaUniversity-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>James Monroe King Warden was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brooklyn">Brooklyn</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_York_(state)">New York</ref>, and raised in the impoverished <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morningside_Heights_(New_York_City)">Morningside Heights</ref> neighborhood of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manhattan">Manhattan</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Daily_Local-2">[2]</ref> He attended <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Bronx_High_School_of_Science">the Bronx High School of Science</ref>, from which he graduated with honors.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Black_Lives-3">[3]</ref> He enrolled in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/City_College_of_New_York">City College of New York</ref> but transferred to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lincoln_University_(Pennsylvania)">Lincoln University</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chester_County,_Pennsylvania">Chester County, Pennsylvania</ref>, after a year.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Daily_Local-2">[2]</ref> He soon left that school as well to join the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Army">Army</ref>. Following his discharge, he returned to Lincoln and graduated with honors in English in 1958.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Black_Lives-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Philly-4">[4]</ref> He received a master's degree from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Columbia_University">Columbia University</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ColumbiaUniversity-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>His work</head>
<p>In 1958,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ColumbiaUniversity-1">[1]</ref> Warden joined the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nation_of_Islam">Nation of Islam</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mosque_No._7">Mosque No. 7</ref>, on 102 West 116th Street in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_York_City">New York City</ref>, under Minister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malcolm_X">Malcolm X</ref>. As was the custom among Nation of Islam members, he abandoned the surname of Warden as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slave_name">vestige of chattel slavery</ref> and became the 67th James in Mosque No. 7.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>By 1960,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ColumbiaUniversity-1">[1]</ref> he had been promoted to lieutenant in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fruit_of_Islam">Fruit of Islam</ref>, subordinate to Captain Joseph X. Gravitt (later known as Yusuf Shah).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> Subsequently, he was appointed circulation manager for New York, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Jersey">New Jersey</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Connecticut">Connecticut</ref> of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muhammad_Speaks">Muhammad Speaks</ref></hi>, and answered directly to Malcolm X.</p>
<p>After the split between Malcolm X and the Nation of Islam, Malcolm X formed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muslim_Mosque,_Inc.">Muslim Mosque, Inc.</ref> and appointed James, then still known as James 67X, secretary of the organization, as well as captain of the men. Based on Malcolm X's instruction, he took the name James Shabazz.</p>
<p>Brother James, as he was sometimes referred, was also responsible for the formation of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Organization_of_Afro-American_Unity">Organization of Afro-American Unity</ref>, a secular organization that Malcolm X had also formed, patterned after <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Addis_Ababa">Addis Ababa</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ethiopia">Ethiopia</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Organisation_of_African_Unity">Organisation of African Unity</ref>, and through which Malcolm X intended to charge the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> with violating the human rights of its chattel slave descendants.</p>
<p>Shabazz was a constant and willing aide to Malcolm X, in his capacity as head of Muslim Mosque, Inc.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> and as head of the Organization of Afro-American Unity. He remained with, and vigorously assisted Malcolm X until the leader's murder on February 21, 1965.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<head>Post-Malcolm X days</head>
<p>Abdur-Razzaq spent the years following Malcolm X's murder raising a family and co-founding Al-Karim School (which would later become Brooklyn's famed Cush Campus Schools) with Ora Abdur-Razzaq. He later moved to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guyana">Guyana</ref>, where he worked as a farmer. Returning to the U.S. in 1988, he earned a nursing degree, and he worked in as a nurse until his retirement in 2004.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Philly-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>In his later years, Abdur-Razzaq's work as staff consultant for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schomburg_Center_for_Research_in_Black_Culture">Schomburg Center for Research in Black Culture</ref> was invaluable in cataloging rare photographs, letters and accounts of Malcolm X's life and times. Furthermore, his expertise was widely solicited by journalists, authors, film makers and educators. In addition to his contributions to a wide array of published works, such as Bruce Perry's <hi rend="italic">Malcolm X: The Last Speeches</hi>, Abdur-Razzaq was featured in several television interviews and films, including <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malcolm_X:_Make_It_Plain">Malcolm X: Make It Plain</ref></hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gil_Noble">Gil Noble</ref>'s <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Like_It_Is_(TV_series)">Like It Is</ref></hi>. The DVD version of Jack Baxter's documentary <hi rend="italic">Brother Minister: The Assassination of Malcolm X</hi> includes an "Exclusive Interview with Abdullah Abdur-Razzaq, Malcolm X's closest associate".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref></p>
<head>Final years and death</head>
<p>In April 2013, Abdur-Razzaq returned to Lincoln University to speak about his memories and experiences working with Malcolm X.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Lincolnian-11">[11]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Daily_Local-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Philly-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Battling leukemia, Abdur-Razzaq was admitted to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harlem_Hospital_Center">Harlem Hospital</ref> in late 2014. After several weeks, he was transferred to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bellevue_Hospital_Center">Bellevue Hospital Center</ref>, where he died on November 21, 2014, at the age of 82.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Black_Lives-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>He is survived by children, grandchildren, and a large extended family.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref></p>
</text>
