<text id="autogum_news_doc072" title="Egyptian archaeologist finds artifacts which may lead to Cleopatra&apos;s tomb" shortTile="egyptian-archaeologist" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-04-19" dateModified="2011-02-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Egyptian_archaeologist_finds_artifacts_which_may_lead_to_Cleopatra%27s_tomb" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Egyptian archaeologist finds artifacts which may lead to Cleopatra's tomb</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, April 19, 2009</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zahi%20Hawass">Zahi Hawass</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Egypt">Egypt</ref>'s pre-eminent <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Archaeologist">archaeologist</ref>, revealed the first <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Artifact%20(archaeology)">ancient artifacts</ref> which may lead to the discovery of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cleopatra%20VII">Cleopatra</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marc%20Antony">Marc Antony</ref>'s resting place.</p>
<p>The expedition has found <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/amulet">amulet</ref>s, 22 bronze coins cast with Cleopatra's image and her name, a royal statue, an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/alabaster">alabaster</ref> mask resembling Marc Antony, and a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bust%20(sculpture)">statue bust</ref> of Cleopatra. "If you look at the face of Mark Antony, many believed he had this cleft on his chin and that's why I thought this could be Mark Antony," said Hawass. </p>
<p>"In my opinion, if this tomb is found, it will be one of the most important discoveries of the 21st century because of the love between Cleopatra and Mark Antony, and because of the sad story of their death. This is the perfect place for them to be hidden," said Hawass.</p>
<p>Recently, outside the temple colourful mummies of nobles were excavated at a neighbouring <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/necropolis">necropolis</ref>. These discoveries have lead the archaeologists to believe that a ruler or person of royalty is interred within the temple itself. It was the practice of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greco-Roman%20world">Greco-Roman era</ref> to assemble the tombs of persons of status and other high ranking officials near their rulers.</p>
<p>"The discovery of the cemetery this week really convinced me that there is someone important buried inside this temple. No one would be buried outside a temple without a reason. We saw that in the pharaonic days, they were always <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ancient%20Egyptian%20burial%20customs">buried beside pyramids</ref>," explained Hawass.</p>
<p>"She needed a place to be protected in the afterlife. If she had used the other burial site, she would have disappeared forever," said Kathleen Martinez, a Dominican archaeologist. She feels that "it could be Taposiris Magna because it was the most sacred temple of its time."</p>
<p>Dr. Roger Vickers team used radar to locate three chambers within the rocky hill atop of which is the Temple of Taposiris Magna dedicated to the goddess <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isis">Isis</ref>. The temple was constructed about 300 BC by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ptolemy%20II%20Philadelphus">Ptolemy II</ref>. </p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Supreme%20Council%20of%20Antiquities">Supreme Council of Antiquities</ref> (SCA) expedition led by Hawass has yet to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archaeology#Excavation">excavate</ref> the burial chambers 40 feet (12 meters) underground where they hope to find a crown or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Egyptian%20hieroglyph">Egyptian hieroglyph</ref> {{w|cartouche]]s revealing the names of royalty. The team will employ radar again on April 22.</p>
<p>The Supreme Council of Antiquities expedition consists of Zahi Hawass, Secretary General of the SCA, and Martinez who has extensively researched the life of Cleopatra.</p>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zahi%20Hawass">Zahi Hawass</ref> Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Hajor">Hajor</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>According to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plutarch">Plutarch</ref> who studied <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman">Roman</ref> history, Caesar allowed Marc Antony and Cleopatra to be buried in the same tomb.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Alexandria">Alexandria</ref> is located about 30miles (48km) from the Temple of Taposiris Magna. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/archaeological%20site">archaeological site</ref> is on a hill along the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mediterranean_Sea">Mediterranean Sea</ref> overlooking the summer home of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hosni_Mubarak">Hosni Mubarak</ref>, president of Egypt. The archaeologists fear they may have to postpone work for security reasons over the summer months.</p>
</text>
