<text id="autogum_voyage_doc93" title="Hakone" shortTile="hakone" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=13895" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Hakone</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.hakone.or.jp/en/">Hakone</ref></hi> (箱根) is a mountainous area west of <ref target="Tokyo">Tokyo</ref> in <ref target="Japan">Japan</ref>. The Hakone checkpoint on the historical <ref target="The%20T%C5%8Dkaid%C5%8D%20road">Tokaido road</ref> marks the beginning of the <ref target="Kanto">Kanto</ref> region.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>The nearest airports to Hakone are in Tokyo. If you have a reservation at a ryokan in Hakone, unless your plane lands in the morning, it is recommended that you spend your first evening in <ref target="Tokyo">Tokyo</ref> or <ref target="Yokohama">Yokohama</ref>, or else you might miss out on (and be charged for) dinner at the ryokan, or worse, you may be locked out of (and be charged for) your room at the ryokan's curfew time, if there is one.</p>

<p>Allow 2½-3 hours to reach Hakone from <ref target="Narita%20Airport">Narita Airport</ref> by train, and 1½-2 hours from <ref target="Haneda">Haneda</ref> Airport.</p>

<head>By train</head>

<p>The fastest and most expensive method of reaching Hakone from Tokyo is to take a <hi rend="bold">Tokaido Shinkansen</hi> hourly all-stop <hi rend="italic">Kodama</hi> (こだま) train from Tokyo to <ref target="Odawara">Odawara</ref> (several <hi rend="italic">Hikari</hi> runs per day also make this stop - check the schedule), then transfer to the <hi rend="bold">Hakone-Tozan Line</hi> for the run to Hakone-Yumoto (trains operated by Odakyu Railway). The one-way fare starts from ¥3730 for unreserved seating, but with a <hi rend="bold">Japan Rail Pass</hi> you need only to pay ¥310 for the Hakone-Tozan line - easily done with a Suica or PASMO card (Limited Express trains require an extra ¥200 surcharge). With a good connection, the trip takes one hour.</p>

<p>Be aware that the <hi rend="bold">JR East Rail Pass</hi> does not provide access to the Tokaido Shinkansen and to make use of this pass you will need to ride the regular Tokaido Main Line to Odawara. From Tokyo, a convenient choice that is valid with the JR East Pass is the "Odoriko" limited express train service. These trains have bigger windows and better seating than the regular commuter trains, and seat reservations can be made. There are at least 3-4 runs during the day in either direction.</p>

<p>Rail Pass holders can also use regular JR commuter trains to Odawara, which cost ¥1490 and take 75-90 minutes from Tokyo Station or Shinjuku Station. <hi rend="bold">Green Car</hi> (First Class) seats are available; you can purchase an electronic Green Car ticket prior to boarding with a SUICA card, then touch the card over the seat you wish to sit in, available on a first-come first-serve basis. The surcharge for Green Car seats between Tokyo and Odawara is ¥980 on weekdays and ¥780 on weekends and holidays; you can also purchase a Green Car seat on the train for an additional fee. Holders of the Green Car Japan Rail Pass can use these seats at no additional charge, and with no fare tickets required.</p>

<p>The affordable method of reaching Hakone from Tokyo is to take the <hi rend="bold">Odakyu Odawara Line</hi> from <ref target="Tokyo/Shinjuku">Shinjuku</ref> station. The fastest train on the Odakyu Line is the <hi rend="italic">Hakone</hi> (はこね) Limited Express train (特急 <hi rend="italic">tokkyū</hi>), which runs twice an hour for most of the day. The 85-90 minute journey costs ¥2080. Note that some trains, called <hi rend="italic">Super Hakone</hi> (スーパーはこね), use newer train equipment, while evening rush hour runs from Shinjuku are called <hi rend="italic">Home Way</hi> (ホームウェイ). The slower Odakyu express train (急行 <hi rend="italic">kyūkō</hi>) runs twice an hour at a cost of only ¥1190, reaching Hakone in two hours.</p>

<p>Odakyu <hi rend="italic">Super Hakone</hi> services also offer saloon seating - private compartments with a table that can seat up to 4 people. The saloon fare from Shinjuku to Hakone is ¥3560 for the compartment, plus the basic ¥1190 fare per person.</p>

<p>Rail connections can be made at Odawara from <ref target="Nagoya">Nagoya</ref> (2 1/2 hrs), <ref target="Kyoto">Kyoto</ref> (3 hrs) and other locations throughout Japan.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Odakyu Hakone Highway Bus</hi> operates several buses from the Tokyo area to Hakone-Togendai via <ref target="Gotemba">Gotemba</ref> Station. Most buses leave from the Shinjuku Expressway Bus Terminal (<hi rend="italic">Busta Shinjuku</hi>) every 30 minutes between 6:35 and 14:05, then hourly until 19:05. Return buses leave Togendai at 7:30, 8:30, 9:30, then every 30 minutes until 18:00 (2 hr 30 min, ¥2010 each way). Odakyu Bus also operates four daily round-trips between <ref target="Haneda%20Airport">Haneda Airport</ref>, <ref target="Yokohama">Yokohama</ref> and Togendai (¥2260/¥1950 respectively) and two express round-trips between Haneda, Yokohama and Hakone-Yumoto train station (¥1950/¥1540 respectively).</p>

<p>Both Odakyu and <hi rend="bold">JR Bus</hi> operate a total of six daily round-trips between Tokyo Station and Togendai (¥2160; ¥1900 if purchased in advance).</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<p>Modes of transport in the Hakone region are many and varied. Your options include:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> The scenic <hi rend="bold">Hakone-Tozan Line</hi> mountain railway from Odawara to Gora via Hakone-Yumoto</item>
<item> The <hi rend="bold">Hakone-Tozan Cablecar</hi> up the mountainside from Gora to Sounzan</item>
<item> The <hi rend="bold">Hakone Ropeway</hi> <hi rend="italic">(suspended as of 19 May 2019)</hi> from Sounzan down to Togendai on Lake Ashinoko via the boiling sulphur pits of Owakudani</item>
<item> The <hi rend="bold">Hakone Sightseeing Ships</hi>, decked out like Disneyland versions of pirate ships, sailing across the lake from Togendai to Moto-Hakone and Hakone-machi</item>
<item> And positively dull in comparison, the <hi rend="bold">Hakone-Tozan Bus</hi> back to Hakone-Yumoto or Odawara. On their <ref target="https://www.hakone-tozanbus.co.jp/english/">website</ref> there is a journey planner, info on how to pay the fare and route maps. The last bus from town to some of the faraway places leaves around 8PM.</item>
</list>


<p>Some modes of transportation - in particular the ropeway - close from time to time for regular inspections, or in windy conditions. Buses will run replacement services in these cases.</p>

<p>Most people opt for the <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.odakyu.jp/english/deels/freepass/hakone/">Odakyu Hakone Free Pass</ref></hi>, which includes a return trip from Shinjuku and allows unlimited use of all of the above forms of transport for several days. In addition, pass holders can receive discounts at many hot springs, museums, restaurants, and other locations by showing their pass.</p>

<p>The 2-day Free Pass costs ¥5140 from Shinjuku and ¥4000 from Odawara. A 3-day pass can be purchased for an extra ¥500. Additionally, if you have a Free Pass from Shinjuku you can use the <hi rend="italic">Hakone</hi> Limited Express train by paying a surcharge of ¥870 each way. You can also travel in a saloon compartment, if offered, at a cost of ¥3560 for the compartment. Holders of the Japan Rail Pass and JR East Rail Pass should travel to Odawara station by JR using the methods described earlier, and pay for the Free Pass from Odawara.</p>
</text>
