<text id="autogum_interview_doc018" title="part6_Wikinews attends 2018 Bangalore ComicCon" shortTile="partwikinews-attends" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2018-11-21" dateModified="2019-07-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_attends_2018_Bangalore_ComicCon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How do you manage the continuity of your work?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DW</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I tend to plan stuff out in story arcs. So I'll plan, I'll plot something that's maybe four issues long to six issues long and have that quite nailed down before I start writing the first issue. So I try to think of a volume, [...] as the finished book. So every book should have kind of its own tone, and its own story-line, even if you are writing something much longer, it's going to be split up into volumes, and I would like each volume to have its own feel.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  As a child whom did you aspire to be?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DW</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I mean I wanted to be a writer, kind of always. There was a times where I took it more seriously than others, there was times I just sort of didn't write very much, like, "Oh yeah, that's fine, I will get back to it".</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What are the projects you are currently working on?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DW</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Projects I am currently working on: <hi rend="italic">Lucifer</hi>. Issue two comes out on this coming Wednesday, and we are way out ahead with the scripts and with the art, so that's taking a lot of my time. I'm also just finishing up <hi rend="italic">Deep Roots</hi> of Vault Comics which is sort an "eco-thriller" create-your-own-thing, it's a great book. And I have been working on, I think three other things I can't talk about yet.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Have you seen the movie adaptation of <hi rend="italic">Assassin's Creed</hi>?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DW</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I have, yeah!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What do you think about that movie?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DW</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  It's great. I mean, the exciting thing about <hi rend="italic">Assassin's Creed</hi> as a franchise is that everything is a single continuity and I don't think any other franchise has really done that. If you look at, like the Marvel films and the Marvel comics: they're separate things and they don't affect each other. But with <hi rend="italic">Assassin's Creed</hi>, the film, the games, and the comics are all one direct continuity. So watching stuff from that film, which I know affects stuff in the book I write and vice-versa was really really cool.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  If you had a message for your younger self, what it would be?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DW</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  My younger self? Probably just tell him to just actually start writing stuff. Start writing stuff. Carry a notebook! When you carry a notebook, that's when you start, I think that's when I became an actual writer.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I guess that was all. Do you mind if I take a photo of yours?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DW</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Yeah, sure! No problem.</p>
<head id="Interview_with_Cuban_comic_book_artist_Vanesa_Del_Rey">Interview with Cuban comic book artist Vanesa Del Rey</head>
</text>
