<text id="autogum_bio_doc203" title="Solomon Zeitlin" shortTile="solomon-zeitlin" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-12-26" dateModified="2019-06-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solomon_Zeitlin" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Solomon Zeitlin</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Solomon Zeitlin</hi>, <hi rend="bold">שְׁלֹמֹה צײטלין</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Шломо Цейтлин</hi> <hi rend="italic">Shlomo Cejtlin</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Tseitlin, Tseytlin</hi>) (28 May 1886 or 31 May 1892, in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chashniki">Chashniki</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vitebsk_Governorate">Vitebsk Governorate</ref> (now in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vitebsk_Region">Vitebsk Region</ref>) in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russia">Russia</ref> – 28 December 1976, in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref>) was a Jewish historian, Talmudic scholar and in his time the world's leading authority on the Second Commonwealth, also known as  the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second_Temple_period">Second Temple period</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> His work <hi rend="italic">The Rise and Fall of the Judean State</hi> is about the Second Temple period.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<head>Russia</head>
<p>Born in Chasniki, Russia, he attended the Gymnasium and later the Academy of Baron Günzburg. There he met and formed a lifelong friendship with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zalman_Shazar">Zalman Shazar</ref>. In 1904, while in Russia, he obtained <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Semikhah">Semikhah</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-HalivniHoenig-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Paris and USA</head>
<p>In Paris in 1916 he was awarded a Th.D. from the École Rabbinique and an Élève Titulaire de la Section des Sciences Religeuses from the University of Paris. In 1915 he emigrated to America. He received his doctorate in 1917 and became professor of Rabbinics.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-HalivniHoenig-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Zeitlin taught at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yeshiva_College_(Yeshiva_University)">Yeshiva College</ref> in New York for two years before going to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dropsie_College">Dropsie College</ref> in Philadelphia, where he served as a Fellow in Rabbinics. He edited the academic journal, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jewish_Quarterly_Review">Jewish Quarterly Review</ref> (JQR)(1940-1976). With A.A. Neuman he co-edited volumes 31–57, and continued as sole editor until his death in 1976. He controversially devoted considerable page-space of the JQR between 1949 and 1964 to engage in scholarly claim and counterclaim over the authenticity and pre-Christian origin of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dead_Sea_Scrolls">Dead Sea Scrolls</ref>. Publishing some two dozen articles on the subject, he remained convinced of their late date.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> In the JQR July 1961 edition he published an article "Jewish Rights in Palestine" by British philosopher and historian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arnold_J._Toynbee">Arnold J. Toynbee</ref> and his own response "Jewish Rights in Eretz Israel (Palestine)" where he rebukes Toynbee for lack of scholarship.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> In addition to history he taught <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talmud">Talmud</ref>, wrote more than 400 articles and books and was instrumental in organizing the American Academy of Jewish Research.</p>
<head>Private life</head>
<p>He never married and had no immediate survivors.</p>
<head>Works</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>"An Historical Study of the Canonization of the Hebrew Scripture", <hi rend="italic">American Academy for Jewish Research</hi>, Vol.3, 1931-1932.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-aajr.org-7">[7]</ref></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Who Crucified Jesus?</hi>, New York: Harper &amp; Brothers, Publishers, 1942, 1947.</item>
<item>"The Hoax of the 'Slavonic Josephus'". <hi rend="italic">The Jewish Quarterly Review</hi>, New Series. 39/2 (October 1948): 172–177.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Maimonides - A Biography</hi>, New York: Bloch Publishing Company, 1955.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">The Rise and Fall of the Judean State: A Political, Social and Religious History of the Second Commonwealth</hi>. New York: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jewish_Publication_Society_of_America">Jewish Publication Society of America</ref>, 1967.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">The Book of Judith</hi>: Greek text / with an English translation, commentary and critical notes by Morton S. Enslin; edited with a general introduction and appendices by Solomon Zeitlin.</item>
<item>"The Origin of the Synagogue", <hi rend="italic">American Academy for Jewish Research</hi>, Vol.2, 1930-1931.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-aajr.org-7">[7]</ref></item>
<item>"The Tobias Family and the Hasmoneans", <hi rend="italic">American Academy for Jewish Research</hi>, Vol.4, 1932-1933.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-aajr.org-7">[7]</ref></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Studies in the Early History of Judaism</hi>, (four volumes), KTAV Publication House, 1978.</item></list>
</text>
