<text id="autogum_interview_doc579" title="part4_Interview with Brazilian blogger Ricardo Serran Lobo" shortTile="partinterview-brazilian" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-01-13" dateModified="2012-05-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Brazilian_blogger_Ricardo_Serran_Lobo" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
Wikinewss: But some Brazilians still trust in President Lula, right?
<p>Ricardo Lobo: This number gets smaller each day. But there are people who still believe in Santa Claus. (laugh) You excuse me but I dont know how to speak about Lula without joking. (laugh)</p>
<head id="Roberto_Jefferson">Roberto Jefferson</head>
Wikinews: Why did Roberto Jefferson expose the scandal, in your opinion?
<p>Ricardo Lobo: Good question. He had a rope around his neck. Actually he detonated an atomic bomb, without knowing who was attacking him. Actually the people who attacked him were his party mates and not José Dirceu. This is related to those 4 millions reals and the sharing amongst them. There were a lot of more money, but only 4 [million] were shared. This is the root of the crisis detonated by him.</p>
Wikinews: It seems that you got close to the ex-deputy Roberto Jefferson. Could you tell us something about it?  What does he think about your blog?
<p>Ricardo Lobo: We became friends and he was thankful for my correction, with him and with his family. He said that I am very competent and that I am one of the best products of the whole crisis.</p>
Wikinews: There is some deputy from the Workers Party (PT) who is a neighbor of Roberto Jefferson?
<p>Ricardo Lobo: Yes, all of them live over there. By example: deputy Greenhalg [Luiz Eduardo Greenhalg] from PT lives there, next door too.  Rebelo [Aldo Rebelo], the President of the Congress, too. Almost all of them live at 302 North.</p>
Wikinews: Is that a pretty wealthy neighborhood?
<p>Ricardo Lobo: Brasília is different from other cities in the world; it is formed by blocks and not streets.  I am a neighbor of a block where there are only federal deputies, among them, Roberto Jefferson. Deputies are very rich, sure. Politics in Brazil makes people rich. (laugh)</p>
Wikinews: Is Roberto Jefferson still having instructions about singing? What does he like to sing?
<p>Ricardo Lobo: He continues. Now he is having instructions with a baritone from the  Municipial Theatre of Rio de Janeiro. He is instructed in the afternoon, when he is in the city. He likes romantic singers and lyrical songs. He sings: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/My%20Way%20(song)"><hi rend="italic">My Way</hi></ref>, <hi rend="italic">Io che amo solo te</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Dio come ti amo</hi>  and other Italian songs like the one of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrea%20Bocelli">Andrea Bocelli</ref>.</p>
Wikinews: Would Roberto Jefferson accept to take part in a interview in Wikinews?
<p>Ricardo Lobo: I believe so, he is very open-minded person, to everything. The trouble is that he has litle experience with the keyboard. Another day he wrote a post in my blog and he had a hard time to find himself with the keyboard. However someone could type for him, that is a solution.</p>
Wikinews: Obviously we need to work on our tech for interviews, we'd like to interview people who aren't familiar with technology and may have telephone interview facilities in the future.
</text>
