<text id="autogum_interview_doc915" title="part0_Scientology protest group celebrates founder&amp;apos;s birthday worldwide" shortTile="partscientology-protest" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-05" dateModified="2019-02-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scientology_protest_group_celebrates_founder%27s_birthday_worldwide" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Scientology protest group celebrates founder's birthday worldwide</head>
Correction — March 19, 2008
The next protest is scheduled for <hi rend="bold">April 12, 2008</hi>. The article below states April 18 which is incorrect.
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 15, 2008</hi></p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Internet">Internet</ref> group <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Anonymous_(group)">Anonymous</ref> today held further protests critical of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Church_of_Scientology">Church of Scientology</ref>.</p>
<p>The global protests started in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia">Australia</ref> where several hundred protesters gathered at different locations for peaceful protests.</p>
<p>In a global speech, the Internet protest movement said Scientology "betrayed the trust of its members, [had] taken their money, their rights, and at times their very lives." The protesters welcomed the public interest their protests have led to, and claimed they witnessed "an unprecedented flood of Scientologists [joining] us across the world to testify about these abuses." The group said it would continue with monthly actions.</p>
<p>In a press statement from its <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Europe">European</ref> headquarters, Scientology accused the anonymous protesters of "hate speech and hate crimes", alleging that security measures were necessary because of death threats and bomb threats. This also makes the Church want to "identify members" of the group it brands as "cyber-terrorists".</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> had correspondents in a number of protest locations to report on the events.</p>
<p>Anonymous states that the next protest is scheduled to take place on April 18, which happens to be the birthday of Suri, the daughter of Tom and Katie Cruise.</p>
<head id="Location_reports">Location reports</head>
<head id="Adelaide,_Australia"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adelaide">Adelaide</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia">Australia</ref></head>
<p><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/News.com.au">News.com.au</ref></hi> reported that approximately 200 masked protesters gathered outside of the Church of Scientology's headquarters in Adelaide. An anonymous spokesman told <hi rend="italic">News.com.au</hi> that their group feels Scientology should not have tax-exempt status, and should not be considered a religion.  At one point six police officers came by the protest; four members of a security firm stood outside the Scientology building throughout the protest.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Adelaide Gallery</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="http://www.news.com.au/adelaidenow/large-gallery/0,25543,5030375-5014156-1,00.html">Adelaide protest in pictures</ref></item></list>
<head id="Atlanta,_Georgia"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Atlanta,_Georgia">Atlanta</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Georgia_(US_state)">Georgia</ref></head>
<p><hi rend="italic">Main article: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Protesters_arrested_at_anti-Scientology_event_in_Atlanta">Protesters arrested at anti-Scientology event in Atlanta</ref></hi></p>
<p>In Atlanta, police arrested two protesters for, supposedly, using a bullhorn without a permit although reports confirm that there is no law or ordinance in Atlanta necessitating one.  The police were under the impression that they were arresting the leaders of the protesters. The anonymous protesters reacted by shouting that they have no leader, but they made no attempts to free those arrested. The police also pulled over cars for honking at the protesters, causing them to make signs "Do not honk".</p>
<head id="Austin,_Texas"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Austin,%20Texas">Austin</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Texas">Texas</ref></head>
<p><hi rend="italic">Volunteer Correspondent: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Bhig3">Bhig3</ref></hi></p>
<p>Almost 135 protesters protested outside of the Church of Scientology location in Austin, Texas.  Protesters received a permit to protest from 11AM to 4PM and stayed the full time allowed.  Law enforcement officers were stationed outside the doors of the Church.  These officers were very kind and open to conversation with Anonymous members.  Protesters gathered across the street from the building as well as directly in front of it, waving signs and chanting.  A UHaul van was converted to a Party Van which was eventually parked directly in front of the Church building for most of the day.  Reports of Scientologists calling the UHaul company office, illegally claiming to be police officers, reached protesters soon after the van was parked.  The protesters responded with a loud speaker saying "Impersonating a police officer is illegal, even on the phone!"</p>
</text>
