<text id="autogum_interview_doc627" title="part1_Adela Lupșe, outburst TV presenter, gives her side" shortTile="partadela-lupse-outburst" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-02-21" dateModified="2014-05-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Adela_Lup%C8%99e%2C_outburst_TV_presenter%2C_gives_her_side" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>After participating in <hi rend="italic">Noră pentru mama</hi>, Lupșe was asked to audition for her first call-in program and was quickly hired. She describes a typical day: "One hour and a half before the show I'm in the make-up room. After I'm done with hair and make-up I go down to the studio for the before the show to talk to the producer. And then is the result that anyone gets to see." All of her banter on-air is improvised: "Definitely there is no script! Everything that you see comes out spontaneosly during the show."</p>
<p>On any given day, Ms Lupșe is on camera for between one and five hours, presenting a number of different call-in shows on several different networks: not only Național TV but also <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prima%20TV">Prima TV</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antena%201%20(Romania)">Antena 1</ref>, all broadcast from the same studio. Despite the repetition, she doesn't get bored. "For me it's always exciting. I enjoy it very much! If I'm tired at the end of the show it means I've done a good show. But I'm never tired during the show." When I play a clip of one of her energetic show presentations – not the one she's become best known for – she elaborates on her exuberance. "I'm always excited when I'm about to give big prizes! There is no show without winners!"</p>
<hi rend="bold">I was just involved in the moment!</hi>
<p>Adela Lupșe's December 6 broadcast was a normal day. She went to the studio, prepared her hair and makeup, spoke to the producer, and went onscreen. The only thing out of the ordinary, she says, was the size of the prize: 1500 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Romanian%20leu">leu</ref>, about $US 450, or roughly a month's wage for a typical Romanian. She describes the critical moment in nonchalant terms:</p>
<figure><caption>Wikinews</caption></figure> <p><hi rend="bold">How did you feel, then, when you began shouting? Many people have said you seemed angry...</hi></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Adela Lupșe:</hi> I was just involved in the moment! People have different opinions.</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">You weren't angry at all?</hi></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Adela Lupșe:</hi> I would rather use the word excited.</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Even when you put your foot on the telephone.</hi></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Adela Lupșe:</hi> Even then, the whole moment was just my way to express my excitement!</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">All we in most countries have seen is those two minutes. What happened afterward?</hi></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Adela Lupșe:</hi>  Well the show went on, I got my winner and moved on!</item></list></p>
<p>She says she and her show weren't fired or fined. The first inkling she had, in fact, that there was something unusual about that day's broadcast was when, on January 9 2009, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MTV%20Russia">MTV Russia</ref> aired the clip of her shouting and stomping on the phone, mixed with some dramatic orchestral rock music. That same clip, uploaded onto video service <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/YouTube">YouTube</ref>, quickly garnered over one million views.</p>
</text>
