<text id="autogum_interview_doc583" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Australian Paralympic skiers Toby Kane, Cameron Rahles Rahbula, and Mitchell Gourley" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-12-10" dateModified="2014-05-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_Paralympic_skiers_Toby_Kane%2C_Cameron_Rahles_Rahbula%2C_and_Mitchell_Gourley" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Can you go and tell me your <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Para-alpine%20skiing%20classification">classifications</ref>?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Toby Kane:</hi> Yeah, we all ski in the standing class. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LW6/8">LW6/8</ref>-2</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Like L1...</p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Mitchell Gourley:</hi> These guys are both <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LW2%20(classification)">LW2s</ref> because they've both got on leg.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Cameron Rahles-Rahbula:</hi> So we ski with just one leg, with crutches, whereas you've got people who've got below-knee amputations, they may have a longer stump and they ski with a prosthetic leg. Toby and I have got to legally ski on one ski.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Toby Kane:</hi> And what you were referring to before was the three classes of alpine skiing is standing, sitting, and blind.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  So you've all been to Paralympics before?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Toby Kane:</hi> Cam's been to three, I've been to two, and Mitch has been to one.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  And what was your favorite one? Do you have one? </p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Mitchell Gourley:</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2010_Winter_Paralympics">Vancouver</ref>. (laughter)</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Cameron Rahles-Rahbula:</hi> Vancouver it would have been.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Because you love <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada">Canadians</ref>?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Cameron Rahles-Rahbula:</hi> It's also, obviously, skiing comes down to results. So, I loved <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2002%20Winter%20Paralympics">Salt Lake City</ref>. I was there for experience, that was great. My second one, I had bit of a disaster Paralympics. I didn't ski too well. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2006%20Winter%20Paralympics">Sestriere in 2006</ref>. The last one, I was able to come away with a couple of medals, so it was... I enjoyed that obviously. They all had different aspects.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How did the ski slopes compare?</p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Toby Kane:</hi> Vancouver, they're good slopes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Cameron Rahles-Rahbula:</hi> Salt Lake City, was a little bit flatter. Probably the type of hill... it was still good, it was my first games, I enjoyed it. Yeah, they usually prepare the courses reasonably well, 'cause they've got a lot of course workers on the slopes. That has a big influence on condition, not just the actual hill itself. Vancouver was a challenge in the sense that we had terrible weather, terrible conditions and snow, even though it's a good hill, whereas I think Sestriere we had sunshine virtually every day. So a lot of it comes down to weather as well as the hill, the time of year.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  In Australia, the big visibility Paralympics are the summer. Do you guys ever feel vaguely — I know it's the wrong question to ask — but do you ever feel vaguely cheated because you're doing neglected, you don't get the attention, the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australian_Broadcasting_Corporation">ABC</ref>'s like "nah, we don't want to cover you"? </p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Cameron Rahles-Rahbula:</hi> umm...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Toby Kane:</hi> Give us the official answer? (laughter, interjections from elsewhere in the room)</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Cameron Rahles-Rahbula:</hi> Australia being a summer sport [country], we're aware that there's going to be more focus on the summer games and particularly because there's a larger... there's more athletes, there more events, there more medals. There will always be more coverage for the summer games. There's no winter athlete that could walk away with more than five gold medals. There's not enough events for that. Whereas I think you can get a swimmer who might get eight gold medals. So, it's a different sort of exposure.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mitchell Gourley:</hi> And realistically, it's pretty unlikely for anybody in winter sport no matter how good they are, to walk away with more than one or two, just because of the nature of the sport, which is that anyone can crash. You can be a great skier all the year and then crash.  [uncertain] can tell you about that in Vancouver. It's a pretty unpredictable sport.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Toby Kane:</hi> The way that our sport moved after Salt Lake City is that instead of Cam and I skiing against each other, and only people with one leg, to being really competitive across those three classes, means that we think that the winter games are really, really competitive. Quite difficult to win a medal. I think, if you took <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael%20Milton%20(skier)">Michael Milton</ref> as an example, he won four gold at Salt Lake out of four events. He won one silver in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2006%20Winter%20Paralympics">Torino</ref> out of four events with the new system, and he compared both events to be equal. So, yeah, I think you've got to look at the value of the medals at the winter games now has been quite high.</p></p>
</text>
