<text id="autogum_whow_doc583" title="Bring the Right Quality to Human Life" shortTile="bring-right-quality" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-02-16" dateModified="2018-10-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Bring-the-Right-Quality-to-Human-Life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Bring the Right Quality to Human Life</head><p>We all have our own rights to do things that we want to do but do we make the right choice if we do it? If you want to bring the right quality to human life, here are some steps you can use as a guide.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be friendly to others. We all have to be friendly to each other. We are all the same, all human, but all different to each other and being different is a good thing. We don't even look the same, so our personalities are all different too. We can't judge someone because they are different from us. Think about what would happen if everyone was the same? Would our life be interesting? Would their be anything different in life to learn? <figure rend="Bring the Right Quality to Human Life Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Help others. We should all help each other if we see others are struggling with things. Imagine you had something that you were struggling with and no one to help you. What would you do? How would you do it? Will it work if you are doing what you are doing? <figure rend="Bring the Right Quality to Human Life Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take care of those in special need. We should all try to go to visit someone who is in hospital and take care of this we know that are ill or in pain. Think how it feels to be all alone without any friends when you are suffering. Would you like it if no one came to visit you? <figure rend="Bring the Right Quality to Human Life Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't let others risk their lives. Someone is drowning. What do you do? (You think of anything that will save them, the best thing that will save them would be some think that floats) throw them a floating hoop, if there is nothing that floats go and dive to save them. <figure rend="Bring the Right Quality to Human Life Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Never break the laws. Like stealing, killing someone, rape etc. These are the worst things that you could do in life to someone. <figure rend="Bring the Right Quality to Human Life Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be happy with the things in life. If you are not happy, think why are you not happy. Think how can you improve it or do it? Will I be able to do it? If you can't do it think to yourself that you are lucky for the things you have that some people might not have? <figure rend="Bring the Right Quality to Human Life Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be a better person. Some people do mean things because of how they were treated when they where younger. But you can change your life into a better life then being mean. We all have good and bad things in us. Find yourself some good friends to hang around with, to play basketball, go to the cinema, go to the club and shopping. <figure rend="Bring the Right Quality to Human Life Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Understand that some people steal because they take drugs. There is a good drug called the African Iboga plant. But it costs a lot of money. If you could make this for free this would change the whole world. Imagine a place where no one takes drugs, doesn't smoke and doesn't have any silly habits. There will be less criminal things happening around the world like killing, stealing, etc. People don't do things without a reasons there is a reason to why people do it. <figure rend="Bring the Right Quality to Human Life Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Encourage children to meditate. People should make every child do meditation. In schools they should teach them how to relax. If somebody really wants to something bad they could meditate and relax and not do anything bad at all but instead, go and do something nice. In schools they should do a relaxation room where they do meditation. If someone gets bullied they could go and meditate to make themselves feel better. It might be a good idea if they teach children about differences. <figure rend="Bring the Right Quality to Human Life Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Learn and teach self defence. They should teach children how to protect themselves from bullies and how to react and not react. There are some reaction that could make a bully want to bully you even more. Go and read some articles about bullying. They should teach children some stuff from wikiHow. <figure rend="Bring the Right Quality to Human Life Step 10.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
