<text id="autogum_interview_doc220" title="part1_Wikinews interviews former New Mexico governor Gary Johnson, presidential nominee of the Libertarian Party" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-11-05" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_former_New_Mexico_governor_Gary_Johnson%2C_presidential_nominee_of_the_Libertarian_Party" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">So it wouldn't be an immediate cut?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Johnson</hi>: Well it would be immediate...You know it's not really a cut because student loans are student loans. You can't escape a student loan even under bankruptcy. So these loans are going to get paid back but the argument is is that student loans, government-guaranteed student loans are a direct cause of tuition being as high as it is.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Okay. I have a question here about entitlements: During the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tea_Party_movement">Tea Party</ref> Republican Party Debate on September 12, 2011, one of which you were not invited to, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wolf%20Blitzer">Wolf Blitzer</ref> [the debate’s moderator], he provided the following scenario to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ron_Paul">Ron Paul</ref>, this is what he said, he said:</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">"A healthy thirty-year-old young man has a good job, makes a good living, but decides, you know what? I'm not going to spend $200 or $300 a month for health insurance because I'm healthy, I don't need it. But something terrible happens, all of a sudden he needs it. Who's going to pay if he goes into a coma?"</hi></hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Now Ron Paul answered that question. If you were at that debate, how would you have responded to that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Johnson</hi>: Well, first of all, I think there are those who are truly in need. So you're talking about a thirty-year-old who doesn't have health insurance; there conceivably could be government step in and it would be state government, not federal government. I really believe that we have to slash <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Medicare">Medicare</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Medicaid">Medicaid</ref> spending; that Medicare is a program that you and I put $30,000 into in our lifetimes and we receive $100,000 plus benefits and by that whatever we contribute in we get back three times, more than three times what we contribute in. So it's not sustainable. Federally funded healthcare is not sustainable. So with that said, I would leave it to the states to draw new lines of eligibility and when it comes to this hypothetical kid that you're talking about that falls into a coma, I'm believing that state governments will come up with a program to address that kind of individual.</p>
<head id="Foreign_affairs">Foreign affairs</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">William S. Saturn</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Let's shift to foreign affairs. On your website, you say "America simply cannot afford to be engaged in foreign policy programs that are not clearly protecting U.S. interests." In the case of a humanitarian crisis as in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Syria">Syria</ref> right now, does the U.S. ever have a moral obligation to intervene militarily even if it is not clearly in the U.S. interest?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Gary Johnson</hi>: No. To intervene in Syria...Look, we end up supporting a new dictatorship that takes over from the old dictatorship. The results are no better or even worse than the old. So we intervene in the name of humanity, and the result is like I say, more times than not, a situation that is worse, not better.</p>
</text>
