<text id="autogum_reddit_doc098" title="Projecting the 53 man roster, depth chart and a quick look at the moves made so far in the offseason" shortTile="projecting--man-roster" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-04-30" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8g313k" speakerList="#BananaGooP" speakerCount="1">
<head>Projecting the 53 man roster, depth chart and a quick look at the moves made so far in the offseason</head>
<sp who="#BananaGooP">
<p>#Projecting the 53-man roster and depth chart: ###Offense: 25 ##Quarterback: 2 1. Cam Newton 2. Taylor Heinicke ##Running Back: 3 1. Christian McCaffrey 2. Cameron Artis-Payne 3. Reggie Bonnafon ##Wide Receiver: 7 1. Devin Funchess 2. Torrey Smith 3. Curtis Samuel 4. Jarius Wright 5. D.J. Moore 6. Brenton Bersin 7. Damiere Byrd ##Tight End: 3 1. Greg Olsen 2. Chris Manhertz 3. Ian Thomas ##Full Back: Alex Armah ##Offensive Tackle: 3 1. Matt Kalil 2. Daryl Williams 3. Taylor Moton ##Offensive Guard: 4 1. Trai Turner 2. Jeremiah Sirles 3. Dorian Johnson 4. Brendan Mahon ##Center: 2 1. Ryan Kalil 2. Tyler Larsen ###Defense: 25 ##Safety: 4 1. Mike Adams 2. Da’Norris Searcy 3. Colin Jones 4. Andre Smith ##Cornerback: 6 1. James Bradberry 2. Ross Cockrell 3. Captain Munnerlyn 4. Donte Jackson 5. Corn Elder 6. Rashaan Gaulden ##Linebacker: 6 1. Luke Kuechly 2. Shaq Thompson 3. Thomas Davis 4. David Mayo 5. Ben Jacobs 6. Jermaine Carter ##Defensive End: 5 1. Mario Addison 2. Julius Peppers 3. Wes Horton 4. Daeshon Hall 5. Marquis Haynes ##Defensive Tackle: 4 1. Kawann Short 2. Dontari Poe 3. Vernon Butler 4. Kyle Love ###Special Teams: 3  <hi rend="bold">Kicker:</hi>  Graham Gano  <hi rend="bold">Punter:</hi>  Michael Palardy  <hi rend="bold">Long Snapper:</hi>  J.J. Jansen *** #Veteran Acquisitions: ####Dontari Poe, DT This was a much-needed signing. Poe represents what the Panthers wanted Star Lotulelei to grow into. With Lotulelei gone Poe will start alongside Kawann Short and should be an instant upgrade over the departed space eating defensive tackle. All-in-all grabbing Poe was a huge thing for the Panthers defense. ####Ross Cockrell, CB The Panthers initially signed Bashaud Breeland, Breeland failed his physical due to a lingering injury and the Panthers moved on to Ross Cockrell. The Panthers will be the fourth team that Cockrell has played for since being drafted in 2014 by the Buffalo Bills. After only playing seven games his rookie year and being released after the season, Cockrell has played in 47 out of 48 possible games and has recorded 36 passes defended and five interceptions during those three seasons. Cockrell is at his best when lined up across from another good corner and should have an immediate impact for the Panthers since Daryl Worley was traded, and subsequently arrested. ####Torrey Smith, WR Speaking of Worley being traded… At the time I hated the trade, but with Worley showing obvious character flaws, the trade looks much better. Smith offers the Panthers a deep threat with experience which is something they have lacked since Ted Ginn left(40% of Smith’s yards in 2017 came from deep passes). With two injury prone young guns behind him(Curtis Samuel and Damiere Byrd) Smith will see a lot of snaps in the coming season. In all likelihood he will enter the season as the Panthers #2 receiver behind Devin Funchess and hopefully he can resolve his drop issues and give Newton a legitimate deep threat. ####Jarius Wright, WR I don’t have much to say about Wright because offensive coordinator Norv Turner said it best. > “I think his style really fits the way we’re going to go about doing things,” said Turner, who spent two-and-a-half seasons coaching Wright in Minnesota. “Very quick starter – explosive. And he’s a very natural player in the slot. He’s been very successful in that area.” (Taken from <ref target="http://www.panthers.com/news/article-2/Panthers-sign-Jarius-Wright-to-three-year-contract/9ffad351-2849-48e0-9dee-144ca5678895">this article on Panthers.com.</ref>) Basically Wright is a better developed version of Curtis Samuel and fits the type of offense that Turner wants to utilize. He will likely be the starting slot receiver and could have a real impact on the Panthers offense. ####Da’Norris Searcy, S Unfortunately for the Panthers they are going to need Searcy to become a great safety quickly. With Colin Jones being the only other option for free safety reps the Panthers passing defense will rely heavily on Searcy making the right reads and being in the right position. ####Jeremiah Sirles, G Sirles will be replacing Andrew Norwell, which if you haven’t guessed by now means the Panthers downgraded immeasurably at the LG position. Sirles has not proven to be a quality guard in his four years in the league, furthermore he had a hard time solidifying a backup role on the Vikings offensive line which was anything but inspiring during that time. ####Zach Banner, T Brought in due to his rare size and upside, but until he can prove able to control his weight and keep up with faster rushers he won’t see the field and could be relegated to the practice squad. I highly doubt he makes it as a tackle, but that doesn’t mean he can’t step up and find a role on the interior of the offensive line. ####Dorian Johnson, G Was a fourth round pick a few years ago but has bounced around practice squads and failed to stuck anywhere. I remember being high on his upside and if any team can get him to be a contributor it will be the Panthers. He could quickly become a solid backup especially with the departure of Andrew Norwell.  <hi rend="bold"> ###Draft Picks: </hi>  D.J. Moore, WR  <hi rend="bold"> Donte Jackson, CB </hi>  Rashaan Gaulden, CB  <hi rend="bold"> Ian Thomas, TE </hi>  Jermaine Carter, LB  <hi rend="bold"> Andre Smith, LB/SS </hi>  Marquis Haynes, DE  <hi rend="bold"> Kendrick Norton, DT ###UDFAs: </hi>  Kyle Allen, QB  <hi rend="bold"> Dre Hall, WR </hi>  Chris Frey, LB  <hi rend="bold"> Taylor Hearn, G </hi>  Kyle Bosch, OL  <hi rend="bold"> Brendan Mahon, G </hi>  Reggie Bonnafon, RB  <hi rend="bold"> Tracy Sprinkle, DT ##Thoughts on draft as a whole: I like the D.J. Moore pick, personally I had Ridley graded higher, but I understand why the Panthers picked him and truly think that he can make an impact on the franchise. Moore was used poorly in Maryland’s offense, likely because of the constant rotation at quarterback and thus the oversimplification of the scheme to help the latest quarterback out. Moore showed flashes of brilliance with explosive cuts, good physicality, strong hands, and an ability to create separation. However, at other times he didn’t show any of these traits. Moore worked back to the ball frequently, made adjustments regularly, found the soft spots in coverage easily and was electric with the ball in his hands. If he can show an ability to run a more diverse route tree and consistently explode out of breaks then the Panthers have found a number one receiver. In my opinion, the second round went terribly. If the Panthers were going to take a cornerback I would have preferred Isaiah Oliver, but disregarding my opinion on cornerbacks for a second, Justin Reid was still on the board and I think it was a huge mistake to take Donte Jackson over him considering the impact Reid could have at the safety position considering the average age of the safety group is 29 and the only players younger than 29 are Dezmen Southward(27), Demetrious Cox(24) and Damian Parms(25). Neither Cox nor Parms are likely to make the final roster which would push the average safety age to 31. Simply by adding a young talented player to the mix, the group would have been in a much better position for not only the upcoming season but for the future as well. Let’s say that Jackson was the Panthers guy and move on to round three. In round three they took another cornerback, with players like Ronnie Harrison,(good not great safety prospect) Harrison Phillips,(defensive line pick that should have gone higher) and Arden Key(yet another interesting defensive line pick, although he has a few too many question marks to really be mad about them passing on him) still on the board. Any of those three would have been picks that have higher upside and more potential to help the team long term than Gaulden. Overall I was pretty disappointed with the 2nd and 3rd round choices. Donte Jackson checks all of the physical boxes the Panthers look for in a cornerback, but he has a lot of room to grow intellectually. He is terrible at anticipating breaks, gets left behind by good route runners and almost never takes the right angles. He has the fluidity, burst, and speed to match elite receivers and as such if the Panthers can hone his mental game he will make a big impact. As for Rashaan Gaulden, well he is the exact opposite. He plays with instincts and knowledge but lacks burst and speed. Ian Thomas in the fourth was a great futures pick, he has a lot of potential and really fits the prototype the Panthers are looking for at tight end. Marquis Haynes is another high upside pick that specializes in pass rushing and could make an immediate impact on passing downs if Addison or Peppers get injured. Carter fits the mold the Panthers love at linebacker and should see special teams snaps. Andre Smith is basically a run-stopping defender. I could see him being used as a box safety or linebacker, but his best chance to make the roster would be as a safety. Kendrick Norton is an athletic player, but there is a reason he was available in the 7th round. My main gripe is that the Panthers took Haynes over Shaquem Griffin who in my opinion proved himself in college and at the combine. The fact that Griffin was available at the end of the fourth is ridiculous. </hi>  If I missed anything, you think I'm crazy, you want to see more indepth coverage of certain things, or you just want to know more, comment below!</p>
</sp>
</text>
