<text id="autogum_academic_doc636" title="Berberis Plants—Drifting from Farm to Food Applications, Phytotherapy, and Phytopharmacology" shortTile="berberis-plantsdrifting" author="Bahare Salehi, Zeliha Selamoglu, Bilge Sener, Mehtap Kilic, Arun Kumar Jugran, Nunziatina de Tommasi, Chiara Sinisgalli, Luigi Milella, Jovana Rajkovic, Maria Flaviana B. Morais-Braga, Camila F. Bezerra, Janaína E. Rocha, Henrique D.M. Coutinho, Adedayo Oluwaseun Ademiluyi, Zabta Khan Shinwari, Sohail Ahmad Jan, Ebru Erol, Zulfiqar Ali, Elise Adrian Ostrander, Javad Sharifi-Rad, María de la Luz Cádiz-Gurrea, Yasaman Taheri, Miquel Martorell, Antonio Segura-Carretero, William C. Cho" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2304-8158/8/10/522/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Cultivation of <hi rend="italic">Berberis</hi> Plants</head>
<p>
The genus <hi rend="italic">Berberis</hi> include about 500 different species and commonly grown in Europe, United States, South Asia and some northern areas of Iran and Pakistan (<figure>Figure 1</figure>). In Pakistan, majority of <hi rend="italic">Berberis</hi> species are found in high mountains (1400 m–3500 m above sea level). In Iran, five <hi rend="italic">Berberis</hi> species are present, including two important species, i.e., <hi rend="italic">B. orthobotrys</hi> and <hi rend="italic">B. khorassanica</hi>, which are grown in eastern, northern and southern regions of Iran. Other important local species <hi rend="italic">zereshk</hi> is also widely cultivated in the South-Khorasan province of Iran. In Iran, 11,000 hectares of area is under cultivation of common barberry (<hi rend="italic">B. vulgaris</hi>) species, and one of the most leading producers of barberry fruit in the world. Annually, Iran produces more than 10,000 tons of dried barberry fruits, while maximum production comes from the Southern Khorasan. More than 97% of the area located near Ghaenat County and Southern Khorasan province is cultivated with common barberry that produces 95% of fruit in Iran. <hi rend="italic">B. vulgaris</hi> is gathered from the wild in Eastern Europe in countries like Poland. In addition, it is known as <hi rend="italic">K’otsakhuri</hi> in Georgia, where it is grown and collected from the southeast forests of the country. The yield-related important traits of many <hi rend="italic">Berberis</hi> species are significantly affected by environmental factors, biotic stresses, seasonal variations, the climatic condition of an area, planting and harvesting date or methods, irrigation source, fruit processing and storage methods, etc. </p>

<p>The fruit remains a vital part, producing many important secondary metabolites and used in pharmaceutical and food industries. In this section, we have highlighted the cultivation of different <hi rend="italic">Berberis</hi> species, its status and various factors affecting its cultivation. Common barberry is a native plant in Asia’s western and middle mountains and non-native to North America. The hybrid species <hi rend="italic">Berberis</hi> × <hi rend="italic">ottawaensis</hi> are widely cultivated in Europe and North America. The European settlers introduced common barberry to New England, and used it as a source of medicine, food, and for other aesthetic purposes. The colonists of New England determined its cultivation spread <hi rend="italic">Puccinia graminis</hi> fungus, causing wheat rust and important reduction of its crop. </p>

<p>The seedless type (<hi rend="italic">B. vulgaris</hi> var. <hi rend="italic">asperma</hi>) is commonly cultivated in the southern parts of the Khorasan province of Iran for domestic purposes. <hi rend="italic">B. lyceum</hi> represents a native species of Nepal and distributed in the temperate and subtropical regions of the world, including some part of Australia. It is distributed from Kashmir to Uttaranchal North-western Himalayas. Sixteen species, and some varieties of barberry, were found in the Boaxing country, situated on the Eastern side of Hengduan Mountains in Sichuan Province, Southwest China. The Japanese barberry is invasive in twenty different states of the world and five other provinces of Canada. According to Reference there are 21 <hi rend="italic">Berberis</hi> species in Nepal, including two new species <hi rend="italic">Berberis pendryi</hi> Bh. Adhikari and <hi rend="italic">Berberis karnaliensis</hi> Bh. Adhikari. <hi rend="italic">Berberis crataegina</hi> DC. is commonly grown in Turkey, Asia and European regions. The fruit are locally known as “karamuk” and “kadıntuzluğu” in Turkey and used as traditional medicine. </p>

<p>In Pakistan, twenty species and six subspecies of <hi rend="italic">Berberis</hi> have been reported, and the majority of these is growing in northern parts of the country. The other dominant species of <hi rend="italic">Berberis</hi> is <hi rend="italic">B. aristata</hi>, grown in Nepal, Pakistan and India. In Pakistan, it mainly cultivated in the Hazara division of Khyber Pakhtunkhwa (KP), and Azad Jamu and Kashmir (AJK) regions. In AJK it is locally named s<hi rend="italic">umbal</hi> and commonly known as <hi rend="italic">daruharidra</hi>. <hi rend="italic">B. lyceum</hi> is another key species, highly distributed in different Asian countries, including, Afghanistan, Pakistan, Nepal, India and Bangladesh. In Pakistan, it grows in different areas of KP, Punjab and Baluchistan. The fruit part locally called <hi rend="italic">kashmal</hi>, is used as a source of food, and for preparing the sauce in Himalayan regions of Jammu and Kashmir, and Himachal Pradesh. </p>
</text>
