<text id="autogum_bio_doc205" title="Kiweewa of Buganda" shortTile="kiweewa-buganda" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-08-31" dateModified="2018-12-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kiweewa_of_Buganda" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Kiweewa of Buganda</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mutebi Nnyonyintono Kiweewa</hi> was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kabaka_of_Buganda">Kabaka</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buganda">Kingdom of Buganda</ref> from 2 August 1888 until 21 October 1888. He was the 32nd Kabaka of Buganda.</p>
<head>Claim to the throne</head>
<p>He was born at Nakatema prior to 1856, the eldest son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muteesa_I_of_Buganda">Kabaka Mukaabya Walugembe Mutesa I Kayiira</ref>, Kabaka of Buganda, who <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reign">reigned</ref> between 1856 and 1884. His mother was Kiribakka of the Mamba clan. He <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enthronement">ascended</ref> to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Throne">throne</ref> following the defeat of his younger brother, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mwanga_II_of_Buganda">Kabaka Mwanga II</ref> by the combined <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christians">Christian</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muslim">Muslim</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baganda">rebel Baganda</ref> forces. The defeat of Mwanga II occurred on 2 August 1888. Kiweewa was crowned on 11 September 1888. He maintained his capital at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mengo,_Uganda">Mengo Hill</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Married life</head>
<p>He is recorded to have married twenty (20) <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wives">wives</ref>:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<list type="ordered"><item>Lady Bukirwa Nassaza</item>
<item>Lady Butema</item>
<item>Lady Kajja</item>
<item>Lady Lozaliya</item>
<item>Lady Luleba, Omusenero</item>
<item>Lady Namubiru</item>
<item>Lady Balirwa</item>
<item>Lady Namuli, Omufumbiro</item>
<item>Naabakyaala Namusoke, Kaddulubaale</item>
<item>Lady Nambajjwe</item>
<item>Lady Nambi I</item>
<item>Lady Nambi II</item>
<item>Lady Nambi III</item>
<item>Lady Tebalyayeebwa, Omulindamazzi</item>
<item>Lady Teyansigira</item>
<item>Lady Lwandeeta</item>
<item>Naabakyaala Zandaba, the Namasole, previously the Kaddulubaale</item>
<item>Naabakyaala Mbagumidde, the Kabejja</item>
<item>Lady Bwangu</item>
<item>Lady Sabaddu</item></list>
<head>Issue</head>
<p>He fathered 23 children, 21 sons and two daughters:</p>
<list type="ordered"><item>Prince Kiweewa Ssimbwa, whose mother was Lady Butema</item>
<item>Prince (Omulangira) Walulyo I, whose mother was Lady Butema</item>
<item>Prince (Omulangira) Kibuuka, whose mother was Lady Kajja</item>
<item>Prince (Omulangira) Nabadda, whose mother was Lady Lozaliya</item>
<item>Prince (Omulangira) Muyinda, whose mother was Lady Luleba, Omusenero</item>
<item>Prince (Omulangira) Agustin [Gusito] Tebandeke, whose mother was Lady Namubiru. He was educated at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Namilyango_College">Namilyango College</ref>.</item>
<item>Prince (Omulangira) Lulaba, whose mother was Lady Namuli</item>
<item>Prince (Omulangira) Kagunya, whose mother was Lady Namuli</item>
<item>Prince (Omulangira) Lukongwa, the Ssaabalangira (Chief Prince), whose mother was Lady Namusoke</item>
<item>Prince (Omulangira) Kiwanuka, whose mother was Lady Namusoke</item>
<item>Prince (Omulangira) Walulyo II, whose mother was Lady Namusoke</item>
<item>Prince (Omulangira) Kalubagwiire, whose mother was Lady Nambajjwe</item>
<item>Prince (Omulangira) Sekamaanya, whose mother was Lady Nambi I</item>
<item>Prince (Omulangira) Namulinzi I, whose mother was Lady Nambi II</item>
<item>Prince (Omulangira) Mwanga, whose mother was Lady Nambi III</item>
<item>Prince (Omulangira) Chwa, whose mother was Tebalyayeebwa</item>
<item>Prince (Omulangira) Ngenza, whose mother was Tebalyayeebwa</item>
<item>Prince (Omulangira) Namulinzi II, whose mother was Teyansigira</item>
<item>Prince (Omulangira) Namika, whose mother was Lady Lwandeeta</item>
<item>Prince (Omulangira) Musisi, whose mother was Lwandeeta</item>
<item>Prince (Omulangira) Nasuswa, whose mother was Lady Zandaba</item>
<item>Princess (Omumbejja) Hana Mazzi, whose mother was Balirwa</item>
<item>Princess (Omumbejja) Agaati Kagere, whose mother Tebalyayeebwa</item></list>
<head>His reign</head>
<p>Kabaka Kiweewa Nnyonyintono's rein is the shortest in the recorded history of Buganda. He was the Kabaka-in-waiting for around six weeks; after he was crowned, he lasted a mere forty days on the throne. His reign was characterized by conflict and rebellion among the members of the royal court and intrigue and plotting among the Arabic Muslim and European Christian forces that supported the warring factions.</p>
<head>The final days</head>
<p>He was deposed by the Muslim forces of his brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kalema_of_Buganda">Kabaka Kalema Muguluma</ref>, who reigned from 21 October 1888 until 5 October 1889. He was captured and thrown in jail. He was killed in prison by his Muslim captors in July 1889. He was buried at Masanafu, Kyaddondo.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Succession table</head>
</text>
