<text id="autogum_interview_doc860" title="part0_Wikinews interviews World Wide Web co-inventor Robert Cailliau" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-07-22" dateModified="2014-09-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_World_Wide_Web_co-inventor_Robert_Cailliau" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews World Wide Web co-inventor Robert Cailliau</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 16, 2007</hi></p>
<p>The name <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert%20Cailliau">Robert Cailliau</ref> may not ring a bell to the general public, but his invention is the reason why you are reading this: Dr. Cailliau together with his colleague <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tim%20Berners-Lee">Sir Tim Berners-Lee</ref> invented the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World%20Wide%20Web">World Wide Web</ref>, making the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Internet">internet</ref> accessible so it could grow from an academic tool to a mass communication medium. Last January Dr. Cailliau retired from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CERN">CERN</ref>, the European particle physics lab where the WWW emerged.</p>
<p>Wikinews offered the engineer a virtual beer from his native country <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Belgium">Belgium</ref>, and conducted an e-mail interview with him (which started about three weeks ago) about the history and the future of the web and his life and work.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi>: At the start of this interview, we would like to offer you a fresh pint on a terrace, but since this is an e-mail interview, we will limit ourselves to a virtual beer, which you can enjoy <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/nl:Afbeelding:Stella%20Artois.JPG">here</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Robert Cailliau</hi>: Yes, I myself once (at the 2nd international WWW Conference, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Chicago">Chicago</ref>) said that there is no such thing as a virtual beer: people will still want to sit together. Anyway, here we go.</p>
<head id="History_of_the_WWW">History of the WWW</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi>: Why did the WWW emerge at a particle physics lab such as CERN? What need did it serve the scientific community at its origin? Was the making of the WWW a case of the right time and the right place/circumstances for someone with the right IT knowledge?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Robert Cailliau</hi>: There were quite a number of hypertext systems around:  the Microcosm, Hyper-G, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gopher%20(protocol)">Gopher</ref>, even Xanadu.  Everyone was experimenting.  There were even two independent attempts inside CERN (Tim's and mine)!  CERN is an infrastructure used by physicists from all kinds of universities who after their experiments at CERN go back to their institutes.  A single experiment brings together many physicists from universities scattered over the globe.  Obviously they stay in contact: they have been users of networks and computers for a long time.</p>
<p>It's therefore not so surprising that we looked for a system that would allow such a group to consult documents  without having to know where the author was or which of the different computers, operating systems, usernames or passwords was needed.  There was a need for an automated library.</p>
<p>The two attempts at CERN were personal initiatives.  When I learned that Tim wanted to use the internet and had made progress towards an implementation, I immediately teamed up with him. But it remained for quite a time a project that was looked at with some apprehension by CERN management.</p>
<p>It was partially the result of the right people in the right place, partially chance, but partially driven by a real need. And everything happened under the benevolent eyes of Mike Sendall, Tim's boss.</p>
</text>
