<text id="autogum_voyage_doc23" title="Crosby" shortTile="crosby" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=8553" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Crosby</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Crosby</hi> is a town in <ref target="Merseyside">Merseyside</ref>.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>Crosby doesn't have an airport, but Liverpool Airport is within under an hour's drive. If coming from inside of the North West of England, then Merseyrail offer the cheapest train rides in the country. Train stations in Crosby include Hall Road, Blundellsands and Crosby and Waterloo.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> ♡❤♡Anthony Gormley's <hi rend="italic">Another Place</hi>♡❤♡. Many visitors visit Crosby because of the sculptures all over Crosby Beach.</item>
<item> The Captain of the <hi rend="italic">Titanic</hi> lived on Marine Crescent in Waterloo and this road, together with neighbouring Marine Terrace, Adelaide Terrace and Beach Lawn provide some excellent examples of Georgian and Victorian architecture.</item>
<item> The Ismay family, owners of the White Star line which owned the <hi rend="italic">Titanic</hi>, lived at Beach Lawn, Waterloo.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lakeside Adventure Centre</hi>, Waterloo. A large fully equipped gym and a centre of excellence for water sports, using the marine lake. It provides special assistance for the disabled. It also has a bistro/bar and 16 bedrooms.</item>
</list>

<p>The promenade stretches from Seaforth Radar Tower at Waterloo all the way up to Hall Road Coastguard Station. This is an interesting walk in all types of weather, but it can get very windy! The prom is a good vantage point for viewing the iron men.</p>

<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Pioneer</hi>. Amazing brasserie who also do functions for all occasions. One of the few eating and drinking establishments open until very late.</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>

<p>Crosby has a flourishing bar scene. Although a little quiet at times during the week, weekends are usually standing room-only in the village. Top watering holes include:</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">George Hotel</hi>. Very popular with a (often very) young crowd at the weekends. Good for cheap eats during the day.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Blues' Bar</hi>. Good laid back atmosphere with a mixed crowd.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Village</hi>. Grab a granny. The Grafton of the north end.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Stamps</hi>. Nice split level bar with excellent kitchen. Sophisticated crowd, quiz nights on Wednesday.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Crosby</hi>. Real boozer very good for the football. Especially popular with the blue half of the population.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Birkey</hi>. Some would say the premier pub in the area. Split between a very comfortable lounge and a slightly grungy rock bar. Good times to be had by all.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Crow's Nest</hi>. One of the few remaining traditional pubs in the area. Unchanged for many years, this establishment has a very loyal following. Call in for a pint of excellent beer, but don't count on a seat any night of the week!</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Royal Hotel</hi>, Waterloo. 22 bedrooms and a good standard restaurant. The bar is well frequented during day and evenings by locals as well as residents</item>
</list>


<head>Stay safe</head>
<p>Crosby is an affluent and safe area.</p>
</text>
