<text id="autogum_academic_doc264" title="Application and Evaluation of Energy Conservation Technologies in Wastewater Treatment Plants" shortTile="application-evaluation" author="Yongteng Sun, Ming Lu, Yongjun Sun, Zuguo Chen, Hao Duan, Duan Liu" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/9/21/4501/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Performance Evaluation of Energy Conservation Technologies and WWTPs</head>
<p>
Before introducing the evaluation methods and indicators, we use a table to summarize the main energy-saving technologies mentioned in this paper. These technologies include green energy technologies and optimization technologies, it is difficult to evaluate them with a unified indicator, so we will explain them in the form of cases. Table 6 shows some common energy-saving technologies and their energy efficiency performance. </p>

<p>Many factors, such as processes, scale, water quality, have a great impact on energy consumption, which has been explained in Section 1.2.2. This review introduces a variety of energy-saving technologies from the aspects of energy supply and system optimization in Section 2 and Section 3. Therefore, some indexes and methods are needed to evaluate the application value and comprehensive performance of these energy conservation technologies.  </p>

<head> 4.1. Evaluation Indexes</head>
<p>
The appropriate evaluation index can not only evaluate energy the performance of WWTPs horizontally but also evaluates the differences of processes vertically, which can provide guidance for technological improvement. Besides, it can help researchers confirm the application value of energy conservation technologies. The diversity of energy-saving technologies makes some indexes that can comprehensively compare their differences more valuable. In Section 1.2.1, EI is used to describe energy performance. Energy consumption per volume of treated wastewater and energy consumption per unit of pollutant removal are two widely used energy indexes, both of which have some problems. Energy consumption per unit of pollutant removal needs to consider a variety of pollutants, which will cause difficulties, while energy consumption per volume of treated wastewater ignores the difference of wastewater (water quality, scale, process, etc.). This problem has been described in Section 1.2.1. The premise of using energy consumption per volume of treated wastewater is that the fluctuation of influent water quantity and water quality (COD, BOD, SS, TN, and TP, etc.) of sewage treatment plants is relatively small, and the situation of influent water quality and water quantity of each sewage treatment plant is comparatively close. In general, energy conservation technology needs to consider energy, feasibility, treatment capacity, economy, environment, policy, water supply safety, risk, and other factors. This is also the premise of energy-saving applications such as multi-objective optimization and optimal control. </p>

<p>There are various performance evaluation indexes for WWTPs. Table 7 shows the indexes used by some researchers. These different indexes with different concerns can show the various situations of WWTPs. This makes the data on energy performance, application value and popularization potential of energy-saving technology more reliable. </p>

<p>However, many researchers pay attention to a unit but do not set indexes from the whole life cycle, which makes indexes not comprehensive. It is not a good choice, because the indexes have a great impact on the audit results of WWTPs. To establish a unified analysis method for energy consumption in WWTPs, the ENERWATER project was launched in Europe to conduct index studies on WWTPs. Water treatment energy index (WTEI), a comprehensive index formed by weighting and a combination of multiple indexes, is used to evaluate the energy efficiency of WWTPs in the ENERWATER framework. After confirming the type of WWTP, indexes are constructed according to the data of energy consumption, pollutant concentration, and flow rate. </p>

<head> 4.2. Evaluation Methods</head>
<p>
Appropriate evaluation methods can help managers to understand the energy utilization of the entire process through various data of the wastewater treatment plant, and to find opportunities for energy efficiency optimization. Only when the above objectives are achieved, can the results of energy research and technical analysis be used to guide technological transformation and engineering practice. Stefano Longo et al. study three benchmark methods: normative method, statistical method, and programming method, and conducted energy efficiency evaluation. </p>

<p>The Key Performance Indicators (KPIs) method is the most common and simplest evaluation method. KPIs, the most commonly used evaluation method in WWTPs, is usually expressed as the ratio of output to input. The KPIs method is simple and easy to implement, but it can only evaluate specific parts, and it cannot systematically evaluate the status of WWTPs. Although the KPIs can be created by weighting, the complexity of the WWTPs process makes the method unsuitable. Similarly, the KPIs method ignores the differences in WWTPs (location, size, process).  </p>

<p>Data Envelopment Analysis (DEA) is a tool using mathematical programming technology for performance evaluation. It can be used to evaluate energy performance in complex systems such as wastewater treatment because it can deal with multiple inputs and outputs problems. The BCC model and the CCR ratio model are two types of DEA models. The CCR model can evaluate the overall efficiency of a unit while the BCC model evaluates the pure technical efficiency of a unit. Guerrini et al. used DEA to study the relationship between sewage characteristics and energy efficiency. They gave some suggestions for efficient operation. </p>
</text>
