<text id="autogum_whow_doc506" title="Keep a Busy Life Organized" shortTile="keep-busy-life-organized" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2009-03-28" dateModified="2019-05-02" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Keep-a-Busy-Life-Organized" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Keep a Busy Life Organized</head><p>After being so busy day after day, your life could become one giant mess. Hopefully this wikiHow will help you to keep a busy life organized. You may have to adapt some of the steps to fit your lifestyle.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Wake up early to get things done. When you get up, clean up your room.  If you work until late, you might consider taking your showers at night so you can sleep an extra 20 minutes or so. If pets, children or work schedules don't allow you to do this, just try not to use the snooze function and shower when you get the chance. <figure rend="Keep a Busy Life Organized Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure you wake up early enough to actually get ready. You may feel run down but you sure don't have to look like it. It will also help if you have everything that you need for the day packed up and ready to go. <figure rend="Keep a Busy Life Organized Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Assuming you go to school, use every second of your time wisely. Study halls, lunch breaks, and free time shouldn't be wasted. It's easy to daydream but instead of sitting in a sleepy stare, you could be working on homework you already know is going to be due or even other assignments. Make it your goal to get as much done as possible at school. Use planners and schedulers to plan time to get projects, readings, and other assignments finished. Try not to procrastinate. It's something everyone is guilty of, but by doing a little work day by day it will ultimately be easier. <figure rend="Keep a Busy Life Organized Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Eat_Healthy">Eat healthy</ref>. This might not seem important, but really it is. You'll have more energy and feel better. Try to avoid take out foods, especially if you work in a restaurant! Everyone realizes by now that coffee, snack cakes and McDonald's meals really do add up and hit your wallet. <figure rend="Keep a Busy Life Organized Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pump yourself up for work. Many people hate their jobs. There  will always be someone who you don't like. A task that you hate to do. So on your way to work, try listening to your favorite songs. Listen to songs that make you feel good or remind you of good times. Make sure you get to work on time and are ready for the job. Getting yelled at when you walk in the door first thing is never a good way to start a day's work or shift. Remember that's it's only a few hours of your day and you are making money. And as hard as it, try to be pleasant to your coworkers. Starting drama will not help anyone or solve any problems. <figure rend="Keep a Busy Life Organized Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be thankful when you get your paycheck that you have a job. Some money is better than no money. Make sure your bills are paid. If you're young, you probably have few bills to pay. It helps to make a list of things you want and need. Put the things you really need at the top. Maybe your jeans are getting a little too thin to be considered nice, or your shoes are a bit worn out. Think of things you really need. Those should be the things you purchase first. Then later come the wants. Before you go splurge on one item, also think of future wants. Will you want to get your hair done in a few weeks? Will you want to go to that concert later this summer? Do you want to redo your room? All of this things are wants and ultimately cost money as well ; think long term. <figure rend="Keep a Busy Life Organized Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't waste time when you get home. It could be very easy to plop down in front of the computer and waste 2 hours on Facebook or staring at the TV screen for the night. Try to avoid this because before you know it, it'll be 1 AM and you still haven't moved since you got home. Make sure you make time to spend with your loved ones and find ways to relieve your [[Reduce Stress|stress}}. Don't spend all your free time sleeping. That may actually make you feel even more run down in the long run. Go to bed at a reasonable time. Try to get 8 hours of sleep ; it's easier said then done for most of us. <figure rend="Keep a Busy Life Organized Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make life easier on yourself by doing the little things. Make sure you have gas in your car. Don't put off stopping just because you're tired. If you ran out of gas in the middle of the road one day, you know you'd not be happy. Make sure you get your laundry done. There's nothing worse then doing a smell check to see what's clean and what's not. Make sure you don't carry around more than you need. And do everyone a favor by not constantly complaining about your life. Everyone goes through hard times and no one can really do anything to fix your problems. <figure rend="Keep a Busy Life Organized Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remember that work is just work. It's something you have to do and will most likely have to do for a very long time. Do your job and do it well, and then leave the stress there as you walk out the door. Don't let school, work, and other stresses take over your life. Remember it's just apart of your day. You are in actually a person! <figure rend="Keep a Busy Life Organized Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
</text>
