<text id="autogum_bio_doc393" title="Juan de Plasencia" shortTile="juan-de-plasencia" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-01-16" dateModified="2019-09-23" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juan_de_Plasencia" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Juan de Plasencia</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Juan de Plasencia</hi> (Spanish:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Help:IPA/Spanish">['xwan de pla'senθja</ref>]) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Habsburg_Spain">Spanish</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Friar">friar</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franciscan">Franciscan</ref> Order. He was among the first group of Franciscan missionaries who arrived in the Islands on July 2, 1578.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-acad-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>He spent most of his missionary life in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philippines">Philippines</ref>, where he founded numerous towns in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luzon">Luzon</ref> and authored several religious and linguistic books, most notably the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doctrina_Cristiana">Doctrina Cristiana</ref> (Christian Doctrine), the first book ever printed in the Philippines.</p>
<head>Early years</head>
<p>Juan de Plasencia was born in the early 16th century as Juan Portocarrero in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plasencia">Plasencia</ref>, in the region of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Extremadura">Extremadura</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spain">Spain</ref>. He was one of the seven children of Pedro Portocarrero, a captain of a Spanish schooner.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Barrantes-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Juan de Plasencia grew up during the period known as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spanish_Golden_Age">Siglo de Oro</ref>, a Golden Age when arts and literature flourished in many parts of Spain, among them his native Extremadura.</p>
<p>It is not well known when or where he first entered the Order of the Franciscans. Some scholars point at the Convento de Villanueva de la Serena, in Plasencia, while others speculate that he might have traveled to Italy and joined a convent there, at a time when a large part of Italy was under Spanish rule. According to researchers, he took the habit as a young man at the Cloister of Saint Francis in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sorrento">Sorrento</ref>, Italy.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Gómez-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Life in the Philippines</head>
<p>He is believed to have arrived to the Philippines in July 2, 1578,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-acad-1">[1]</ref> after a stopover in Mexico. As soon as he arrived, he joined forces with another missionary, Fray Diego de Oropesa, and they both started preaching around <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laguna_de_Bay">Laguna de Bay</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tayabas,_Quezon">Tayabas, Quezon</ref>, in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quezon_Province">Quezon Province</ref>, where he founded several towns.</p>
<p>During the following years they are also credited with the foundation of a large number of towns in the provinces of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulacan">Bulacan</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laguna_(province)">Laguna</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rizal">Rizal</ref>, such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tayabas">Tayabas</ref>, Caliraya, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lucban">Lucban</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Majayjay">Majayjay</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nagcarlan">Nagcarlan</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liliw">Lilio</ref> (Liliw), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pila,_Laguna">Pila</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santa_Cruz,_Laguna">Santa Cruz</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lumban">Lumban</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pangil">Pangil</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siniloan">Siniloan</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morong,_Rizal">Morong</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antipolo">Antipolo</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taytay,_Rizal">Taytay</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meycauayan">Meycauayan</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>As a friar, Juan de Plasencia lived up to his pledge, leading a lifestyle devoid of any luxury and in constant contact with the people he was trying to convert to Christianity. He was also known to be a defender of the native population, looking after the poor, ill, or neglected, and standing up for their rights on numerous occasions.</p>
<p>He was also very keen on creating primary schools, and requested official sanction for the creation of educational centers where "Filipinos could not only learn Christian doctrine, but also reading and writing, and some arts and crafts, so they would become after, not only good Christians but also useful citizens", an initiative that was approved by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domingo_de_Salazar">Domingo de Salazar</ref>, the first Bishop of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/See_of_Manila">See of Manila</ref> (1512–1594).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Bazaco-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>Written works</head>
<p>Juan de Plasencia wrote a number of books designed primarily to promote the understanding of both the Spanish language among the natives, and the local languages among the missionaries, to facilitate the task of spreading Christianity. He acknowledged at an early stage the need of mastering the language of the natives in order to facilitate evangelization, and in a letter to the King of Spain, dated June 18, 1585, he mentioned some of his works to that effect:</p>
<p>He is the author of what is believed to be the first book printed in the Philippines, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doctrina_Cristiana">Doctrina Cristiana</ref>, that was not only printed in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spanish_language">Spanish</ref>, but also in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tagalog_language">Tagalog</ref>, in both <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Latin_script">Latin script</ref> and the commonly used <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baybayin">Baybayin</ref> script of the natives of the time, and it even had a version in Chinese.</p>
<p>Other works attributed to him are the "Relacion de las Costumbres de Los Tagalos" (1589), that not only helped understand and preserve many of the traditional ways of the local population, but also provided the first form of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Civil_Code">Civil Code</ref>, used by local governors to administer justice.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Gutay2007-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>A mystical work which he entitled "La Santina", was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Opus_number">Opus number</ref> on prayer and contemplation entirely done in the Tagalog language so the natives who did not know Spanish could also engage in the spiritual exercises of their teachers.</p>
<head>Death</head>
<p>Juan de Plasencia died in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liliw">Liliw</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laguna_(province)">Laguna</ref> in 1590.</p>
</text>
