<text id="autogum_interview_doc100" title="part0_Cold as ice: Wikinews interviews Marymegan Daly on unusual new sea anemone" shortTile="partcold-ice-wikinews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-01-20" dateModified="2015-01-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Cold_as_ice%3A_Wikinews_interviews_Marymegan_Daly_on_unusual_new_sea_anemone" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Cold as ice: Wikinews interviews Marymegan Daly on unusual new sea anemone</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 21, 2014</hi></p>
<p>In late 2010 a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Geology">geological</ref> expedition to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Antarctica">Antarctica</ref> drilled through the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ross_Ice_Shelf">Ross Ice Shelf</ref> so they could send an <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Remotely_operated_underwater_vehicle">ROV</ref> under it. What they found was unexpected: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sea%20anemones">Sea anemones</ref>. In their thousands they were doing what no other species of sea anemone is known to do — they were living in the ice itself.</p>
<figure><caption><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edwardsiella%20andrillae">Edwardsiella andrillae</ref></hi> and its habitat Image: Daly et al.</caption></figure>
<p>Discovered by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ANDRILL">ANDRILL</ref> [Antarctic Drilling] project, the team was so unprepared for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Biology">biological</ref> discoveries they did not have suitable preservatives and the only chemicals available obliterated the creature's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DNA">DNA</ref>. Nonetheless Marymegan Daly of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ohio_State_University">Ohio State University</ref> confirmed the animals were a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Species_discovery">new species</ref>. Named <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edwardsiella%20andrillae">Edwardsiella andrillae</ref></hi> after the drilling project that found it, the anemone was finally described in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PLOS%20ONE">PLOS ONE</ref> paper last month.</p>
<p>ANDRILL lowered their cylindrical camera ROV down a freshly-bored 270<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/metre">m</ref> (890<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/foot%20(unit)">ft</ref>) hole, enabling it to reach seawater below the ice. The device was merely being tested ahead of its planned mission retrieving data on ocean currents and the sub-ice environment. Instead it found what ANDRILL director Frank Rack of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University%20of%20Nebraska–Lincoln">University of Nebraska–Lincoln</ref>, a co-author of the paper describing the find, called the "total serendipity" of "a whole new ecosystem that no one had ever seen before".</p>
<p>The discovery raises many questions. Burrowing sea anemones worm their way into substrates or use their tentacles to dig, but it's unclear how <hi rend="italic">E. andrillae</hi> enters the hard ice. With only their tentacles protruding into the water from the underneath of the ice shelf questions also revolve around how the animals avoid freezing, how they reproduce, and how they cope with the continuously melting nature of their home. Their diet is also a mystery.</p>
<hi rend="bold">What fascinates me about sea anemones is that they're able to do things that seem impossible</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—Marymegan Daly</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">E. andrillae</hi> is an opaque white, with an inner ring of eight tentacles and twelve-to-sixteen tentacles in an outer ring. The ROV's lights produced an orange glow from the creatures, although this may be produced by their food. It measures 16–20mm (0.6–0.8in) but when fully relaxed can extend to triple that. </p>
<p>Genetic analysis being impossible, Daly turned to dissection of the specimens but could find nothing out of the ordinary. Scientists hope to send a biological mission to explore the area under the massive ice sheet, which is in excess of 600 miles (970km) wide. The cameras also observed worms, fish that swim inverted as if the icy roof was the sea floor, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/crustaceans">crustaceans</ref> and a cylindrical creature that used appendages on its ends to move and to grab hold of the anemones.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NASA">NASA</ref> is providing funding to aid further research, owing to possible similarities between this icy realm and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Europa%20(moon)">Europa</ref>, a moon of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jupiter">Jupiter</ref>. Biological research is planned for 2015. An application for funding to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S._National_Science_Foundation">U.S. National Science Foundation</ref>, which funds ANDRILL, is also pending.</p>
</text>
