<text id="autogum_academic_doc564" title="Dynamical Transitions in a One-Dimensional Katz–Lebowitz–Spohn Model" shortTile="dynamical-transitions" author="Alessandro Pelizzola, Marco Pretti, Francesco Puccioni" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1099-4300/21/11/1028/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Results</head>
<p>
In the present section we compute the relaxation rate of the 1D KLS model with bulk-adapted boundary conditions, for  (that is, in the case of the dashed line in <figure>Figure 1</figure>), as a function of the reservoir densities. We choose this particular value because in this case the NESS phase diagram, reported for convenience in <figure>Figure 2</figure>, has already been determined in Reference by means of extremal current principles which turn out to be exact in the case of bulk-adapted boundary conditions. In Reference, it has been shown indeed that, as far as the NESS is concerned, this case exhibits all relevant new features of the model. </p>

<p>This NESS phase diagram exhibits 7 different phases and a symmetry with respect to the diagonal  due to the particle–hole symmetry of the model. In the portion of the phase diagram corresponding to each phase we report an identifier of the phase (I to VII) and the value of the bulk density. This is indeed a quantity which characterizes the NESS because, in the thermodynamical limit , the local density tends to the bulk density over the whole lattice, except in boundary regions whose size remains finite as . Phases I and VI are LD phases, whose bulk density  is determined by the left reservoir. Symmetrically, phases III and V are HD phases, whose bulk density  is determined by the right reservoir. In addition, there are the 2 maximal current phases II and VII, whose bulk densities  and  correspond to the maxima of the fundamental diagram along the dashed line in <figure>Figure 1</figure>, and the minimal current phase IV, whose bulk density  corresponds to a minimum in the fundamental diagram. Among the various NESS transitions separating these phases, it is important to observe here that LD and HD phases are always separated by discontinuous (in the bulk density) transitions, denoted by solid lines in <figure>Figure 2</figure>. Exactly at these transitions, the 2 phases coexist. </p>

<p>In the following we will compute the relaxation rate , using the PA, the mDWT and extrapolation of finite size exact results, in the HD phases. The corresponding results for the LD phases can be obtained by symmetry, and  vanishes at the discontinuous transitions between LD and HD phases. In the maximal and minimal current phases instead the relaxation is not exponential, so the relaxation rate is not defined. More precisely, the relaxation is power-law in these phases, and the relaxation rate vanishes upon approaching these phases from LD or HD phases. </p>

<p>We will be especially interested in singularities in the relaxation rate, representing dynamical transitions, which separate regions where  depends only on the bulk density (that is, on just one reservoir density) from regions where it depends on both reservoir densities. In order to exemplify the various possible transitions, we shall consider three cases in detail, corresponding to the thin solid lines in <figure>Figure 2</figure>, that is  (HD phase V), 0.98 (HD phase V) and 0.45 (HD phase III). </p>

<p>Before turning to a detailed analysis, let us anticipate our main results. For  a situation similar to pure TASEP is found, that is a slow phase close to the coexistence line, separated from a fast phase by a dynamical transition. For , due to the proximity of the minimal current phase, new features appear, suggesting the possibility of a new dynamical phase and additional dynamical transitions. Finally, for , we clearly find 2 slow phases close to the coexistence lines. According to the PA, these slow phases are separated by 2 dynamical transitions from a central phase which is a TASEP-like fast phase, although this picture is not fully confirmed by BST results, maybe due to small system sizes. </p>

<p>As previously mentioned, we start our analysis with the simplest case, that is , in HD phase V. The relaxation rate  as a function of  is reported in <figure>Figure 3</figure>. The PA results (black lines) clearly suggest that, in the thermodynamical limit , 2 phases can be distinguished. For small  (slow phase), close to the (discontinuous) transition with the LD phase VI,  depends on , starting from 0 at the transition and then increasing. Notice that in this phase the size dependence is very weak, in particular the asymptotic value is approached with an exponential decay in <hi rend="italic">N</hi>. For large  (fast phase),  becomes independent of  (while the size dependence can be appreciated, the approach to the asymptotic value is ) and a singularity, corresponding to a dynamical transition, can be clearly identified. This is the same behaviour observed in pure TASEP. We can approximately locate the dynamical transition by extrapolating, using the BST algorithm with , the relaxation rate in the fast phase for  and by looking for the point where the  results reaches this value. The corresponding estimate of the transition point, computed for , will be reported in the dynamical phase diagram with a blue line. </p>
</text>
