<text id="autogum_interview_doc191" title="part0_Andrea Muizelaar on fashion, anorexia, and life after &amp;apos;Top Model&amp;apos;" shortTile="partandrea-muizelaar" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-25" dateModified="2012-02-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Andrea_Muizelaar_on_fashion%2C_anorexia%2C_and_life_after_%27Top_Model%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Andrea Muizelaar on fashion, anorexia, and life after 'Top Model'</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, November 26, 2007</hi></p>
<p>In the 18 months since <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrea%20Muizelaar">Andrea Muizelaar</ref> was crowned winner of the reality TV series <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canada's%20Next%20Top%20Model">Canada's Next Top Model</ref></hi>, her life has been a complete whirlwind. From working in a dollar store in her hometown of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Whitby,%20Ontario">Whitby, Ontario</ref>, to modeling <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/haute%20couture">haute couture</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toronto">Toronto</ref>, she had reached her dream of becoming a true Top Model.</p>
<p>But at what cost? Unknown to casual television viewers, Muizelaar had been enveloped in the eating disorder <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/anorexia%20nervosa">anorexia nervosa</ref>, which inevitably became too much for her to bear. She gave up modeling and moved back to Whitby, where she sought treatment for her disorder, re-entered college, and now works at a bank. Where is she now? Happy and healthy, she says.</p>
<p>Recently Andrea Muizelaar sat down with Wikinews reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:TheCustomOfLife">Mike Halterman</ref> in a candid interview that stretched to nearly two hours, as she told all about her hopes and aspirations, her battle with anorexia, and just what <hi rend="italic">really</hi> happened on <hi rend="italic">Canada's Next Top Model.</hi></p>
<head id="Andrea's_beginnings">Andrea's beginnings</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman:</hi> Tell us a bit about your background. We know all about the Andrea we saw on Top Model, but we're interested to hear where you came from. What do your parents do? Did you have any hard times growing up?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Andrea Muizelaar:</hi> I am from Whitby, Ontario. My Dad works in the nuclear industry and my Mom is a stay-at-home mom.  I had a lot of trouble from my peers at school due to my "geeky" appearance - braces, etc.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> How geeky are we talking here? Worse than any other teenager?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> Probably not extremely geeky; more of being a victim of a bully who liked to pick on me continuously and influenced other kids to do likewise.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> How long did that last?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> I would say from Grade 2 to Grade 9.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> What happened after that point? Did they stop, or did you grow into your looks, or was it something else?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> I definitely grew into my looks, the braces came off; high school is a bigger place and the bullying subsided because I had new friends.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> This was also around the time you wanted to model, right?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> Correct.  Once I transitioned into a pretty young lady, people started telling me that I should model.  Going from one extreme, to this one, it went to my head and I started dieting over the summer of Grade 9 to make sure that I was the perfect candidate.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Is that when you first became anorexic?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> Yes - I lost 20 pounds that summer and then starting losing my control and modelling became my new excuse for this weight loss and soon-to-be disorder.</p>
</text>
