<text id="autogum_interview_doc387" title="part0_The Raveonettes on love, death, desire and war" shortTile="partthe-raveonettes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-16" dateModified="2010-12-23" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Raveonettes_on_love%2C_death%2C_desire_and_war" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>The Raveonettes on love, death, desire and war</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 16, 2007</hi></p>
<figure rend="The Raveonettes by David Shankbone.jpg"></figure>"We're only two days in and we're already fucking tired," says Sune Rose Wagner to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref> as he walks into the dressing room at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bowery%20Ballroom">Bowery Ballroom</ref>.  Wagner and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sharin%20Foo">Sharin Foo</ref> comprise the Raveonettes, a group made for "nostalgists who long for Everly Brothers 45's and diner jukeboxes, the Raveonettes tweak "American Graffiti"-era rock with fuzzed-out surf-guitar riffs," said <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20New%20York%20Times">The New York Times</ref></hi>.  They recently left <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Columbia%20Records">Columbia</ref> and signed with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fierce%20Panda">Fierce Panda</ref> because they felt constrained by their Columbia contract:  "The major label system sometimes doesn't allow for outside "help" to get involved, meaning that we don't get to choose who we wanna work with. That can be a pretty terrible thing and bad things will surely come of it," said the band on their <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/MySpace">MySpace</ref> site.   Originally from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Denmark">Denmark</ref>, both musicians live in the United States now.
<p>Their first <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EP">EP</ref>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chain%20Gang%20of%20Love">Chain Gang of Love</ref></hi>, was a critical and commercial success.  "Few albums provoke such amazing imagery," said the BBC.  "<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pretty%20in%20Black">Pretty in Black</ref></hi> is virtually fuzz-free," said <hi rend="italic">Rolling Stone</hi> of their next album, "highlighting the exquisite detail in the Raveonettes' gift for pastiche: the prowling, garage-surf guitars in <hi rend="italic">Love in a Trashcan</hi>; the ghost dance of <hi rend="italic">Red Tan,</hi> wrapped in Phil Spector-style sleigh bells."  Of their current album, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lust%20Lust%20Lust">Lust Lust Lust</ref></hi>, set to be released on November 5th (although Amazon says March 4, 2008), Sune told <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NME">NME</ref></hi> that, "There are a lot of songs that deal with desire, restlessness and the tough choices you have to make sometimes."  Fans can hear some of the new material at <ref target="http://www.myspace.com/theraveonettes">MySpace.com/TheRaveonettes</ref>.</p>
<p>Below is <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> reporter David Shankbone's interview with Sune Rose Wagner and Sharin Foo.</p>
<head id="On_influences">On influences</head>
<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sune%20Rose%20Wagner">Sune Rose Wagner</ref></hi>:Would you like something to drink?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref>:  No, I drank so much <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Green%20tea">green tea</ref> today I am worried I am going to need to pee throughout the interview.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  At least you're peeing healthy.  Can you mix <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vodka">vodka</ref> with green tea?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <hi rend="italic">I</hi> used to.  How is the tour going?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  It's good.  We're only two days in and we're already fucking tired.  But we're in great spirits here.  We're leaving town tomorrow...we're happy.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You guys played in Southpaw right; how was that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  It was beautiful.  I love that place.  We played <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maxwell's">Maxwell's</ref> last night, which is my favorite place.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  This interview may be something different than you guys are used to, because although the questions will be about your music, they will be more about the both of you.  They are surveys of the landscape.  For instance, in the last week I have interviews the proprietors and mistresses of an S&amp;M dungeon; Evangelical Christian Presidential candidate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sam%20Brownback%20on%20running%20for%20President,%20gay%20rights,%20the%20Middle%20East%20and%20religion">Sam Brownback</ref>, the President of the ACLU, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Augusten%20Burroughs%20on%20addiction,%20writing,%20his%20family%20and%20his%20new%20book">Augusten Burroughs</ref>, and the High Priest of the Church of Satan, and now you.</hi></p>
</text>
