<text id="autogum_fiction_doc308" title="The Tarn of Eternity" shortTile="tarneternity" author="Tymon, Frank" type="fiction" dateCollected="2019-10-22" sourceURL="http://gutenberg.readingroo.ms/8/2/822/822-8.txt">
<head>12. Poseidon's Wrath</head>

<p>"A family reunion would be nice. I really don't get around as much as I used to. The job, you know. Duties. Responsibilities. You humans! You just don't understand how vexing it can be, being a God. Why, every day, day in and day out, I've got to have the sun rise. No big chore, but it's only one of many." Zeus shook his head.</p>

<p>"The moon, if I don't watch her, goes wandering off. Messes up the tides terribly. Disconcerting to young lovers, too!"</p>

<p>He looked, head cocked to the side, at Demo.</p>

<p>"So, what may I ask, do you want here at Olympus?"</p>

<p>For a moment Demo was nonplused.</p>

<p>"Sire, I gathered you had sent for me. I came not of my own volition. Perhaps some other has need of my services . . . ?"</p>

<p>"Somebody is playing games, and they are surely going to get themselves into a mess of trouble. Yes! A mess . . . of . . . trouble!" Zeus glanced around, a thoughtful expression on his face.</p>

<p>A titter sounded from the inner hallway.</p>

<p>Zeus glanced at Demo to see whether he had noted the sound.</p>

<p>Demo was silent. Best to leave all surmises alone. After all, he thought, who am I to criticize the dalliances of Zeus.</p>

<p>Zeus smiled.</p>

<p>"Anyway, you are here, so let's get you started on another exciting excursion. By the way, you've really done remarkably well, and I am proud of you. Here, let me give you a slight token."</p>

<p>He thought a moment, smiled once more, and waved his hands nonchalantly in the air. The medal was large and shiny as Zeus slipped the supporting chain over Demo's head. Demo took the medal in his hands, read the legend thereon. Although the words were difficult to read in an inverted position he managed to decipher them.</p>

<p>"For Ungodly Support to the Gods."</p>

<p>Zeus kissed him on one cheek, then the other. "I'm never sure the order in which I'm supposed to do that. Never mind. If I got it wrong, we'll merely change the ritual."</p>

<p>He glanced rather anxiously toward the hallway.</p>

<p>"Young man, rather quickly now. I want you to drop in on Poseidon. Lovely fellow, you'll like him. Eh, don't ever discuss fishing with him. He has a dread of the subject. I was fishing one day and he nibbled at the bait, and . . . Anyway, a subject not to be discussed. Where was I . . . ?" Zeus glared at Demo as though the boy had stolen his train of thought.</p>

<p>"Take this bag with you, and give it into his hands, and his only. He'll know what to do. By the way, do you own a bathing suit?"</p>

<p>Zeus, Olympus, and all else seemed to be fading away. Demo seemed to hear, faintly, Zeus scolding. "Now, you know you aren't supposed to play with my powers. You just leave that young man alone, my dear. I'm such an ogre when I'm jealous."</p>

<p>He landed with a splash.</p>

<p>Zeus' aim was plainly off.</p>

<p>Almost always he had landed in his home, the forest. But this?</p>

<p>The middle of a stream, of course. He slipped under the water, propelled himself upward, glancing quickly around at the height of his watery leap. A shudder went through him.</p>

<p>No river, this!</p>

<p>Neither shores, nor the green forest, nor the high mountains of home!</p>

<p>Water, only water! Deep blue water, extending as far as eye could see. Blue . . . and salty. Surely he had landed in the ocean!</p>

<p>"Zeus, Oh, Zeus! I do think you may have erred . . . only slightly, of course. Zeus . . . ?"</p>

<p>"Who dares call on Zeus, when he swims in my domain? How come you here, earthling? Where is your ship? Do you not fear my watchdogs, the great sharks that guard my kingdom. And why call you on Zeus. Poseidon rules these waves!</p>

<p>"I . . . My name is Demo. I was merely doing an errand for Zeus. And, through some mischance, I landed in these waters. Perhaps you can direct me to the nearest shore?"</p>

<p>"Mischance, eh? Well, Zeus is putting on the years . . . Odd, but he may be losing his grip. Oughta spend more time at the seashore. Relaxing. Yes indeed." The voice seemed to emanate from a puff-fish, which floated rather nonchalantly at arms length away.</p>

<p>"The nearest shore. Of course. You earthlings. I would invite you down for a meal, but you lack the necessary organs to join me. Toward the setting sun. A small island. I'll race you!"</p>

<p>Demo looked to the west. Water, only water.</p>

<p>"Is it, well, very far?"</p>

<p>"No, no! Just a good swim away. Ah, forgive me. It could be a bit strenuous for you. I'll take care of it, though." The puff-fish whistled loudly, popped up above the water to peruse its surface.</p>

<p>"Here he comes."</p>

<p>Demo followed the puff-fish's gaze. He wished he hadn't!</p>

<p>The shark was approaching at alarming speed. Its fin split the water's smooth surface, drawing ever closer. Demo's eyes widened.</p>

<p>"Hey, that's a shark!"</p>

<p>"Yes, yes indeed! Actually, merely a minnow as sharks grow. Actually, he was the only one in the area, so I flagged him down. Oh, taxi, right this way."</p>

<p>The shark circled slowly, at times rising to the surface, its cold eyes regarding Demo with hungry interest.</p>
</text>
