<text id="autogum_academic_doc338" title="High-Sensitivity Pixels with a Quad-WRGB Color Filter and Spatial Deep-Trench Isolation" shortTile="highsensitivity-pixels" author="Yongnam Kim, Yunkyung Kim" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1424-8220/19/21/4653/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The advances in camera technology now necessitate the development of a high-resolution complementary metal-oxide-semiconductor (CMOS) image sensor. However, a high-resolution camera requires a pixel pitch smaller than 1.0 μm to allow accumulation of numerous pixels in the limited sensor area. Accordingly, the aspect ratio is worsened by maintaining the pixel height in a small pixel pitch. If the pixel depth gets thinner, the color filter (CF) or the photodiode should also be thinner. However, the thickness of the CF has pigment limitations, and making the photodiode thinner is difficult because of the lower light absorption at long wavelengths. Therefore, the optical performance of a small-sized pixel deteriorates due to low sensitivity and high crosstalk, which lead to a lower performance of CMOS image sensors. </p>

<p>Many approaches are available for enhancing the sensitivity and crosstalk for a small pixel. Particularly good examples include new optical pixel structures, such as the stacked grid structure between color filters, the lensed CF, and the front-inner lens image sensor. The stacked grid structure is located between the color filters, and it blocks the optical crosstalk to increase sensitivity. However, the grids cannot be adapted to small pixels because the CF width reduces and adversely affects the sensitivity by shrinking the absorption area. In, a lensed CF is proposed to reduce crosstalk and enhance the sensitivity by uniting the micro lens and a color filter. However, the height and the radius of curvature (ROC) of this structure are difficult to process equally. The front-inner lens is proposed to enhance the sensitivity by adding a lens to the front side to serve as the interconnection layer in a shallow photodiode. However, the complicated structure of the front inner lens creates substantial difficulty in conducting general processes. </p>

<p>Conversely, different approaches are available to obtain high sensitivity by changing the color filter array (CFA). A CFA with a white color filter has been studied because a white color filter transmits incident light at all wavelengths. The WRGB (white, red, green, blue) CFA indicates that one of the green pixels of the Bayer CFA was replaced with a white pixel. The RGBW CFA consisting of 50% white CF has also been developed to improve the sensitivity and resolution. Fifty percent of the total area of the RGBW CFA is occupied by the white CF, 25% by the green CF, and 12.5% by the red and blue CF. The RGBW CFA consisting of 75% white CF with a color separation process was also introduced. The low-illumination signal-to-noise ratios of the luminance signal are improved by increasing the white CF area. Moreover, the color reproducibility of the WRGB pattern is comparable with the Bayer pattern. According to this research, the WRGB CFA demosaicing result has a similar spatial resolution, color reproduction, and better color aliasing artifact levels compared to the Bayer CFA demosaicing result by the post-processing method. However, much crosstalk is induced with increasing sensitivity, especially for a small pixel. Because the white color filter transmits a lot of light, some of the light enters the other pixel’s photodiode. This problem still requires a solution. </p>

<p>In this work, we propose a quad-WRGB structure with spatial-deep trench isolation (S-DTI) and a spatial-tungsten grid (S-WG) to solve the small pixel problems, such as low sensitivity and high crosstalk. The quad-WRGB CFA provides a four-fold expansion of each color filter. The S-DTI and S-WG are located every four pixels for efficient reduction of the crosstalk. The optical performance is investigated by simulating the suggested structure and comparing it with typical structures with the CFA, DTI, and WG using a commercial 3D optical simulator for precise analysis. Section 2 describes the concept of the quad-RGBW pixel structure having S-DTI and S-WG, and Section 3 presents the simulation results and discusses the results. Conclusions are presented in Section 4. </p>
</text>
