<text id="autogum_academic_doc215" title="Reusable Surface-Enhanced Raman Spectroscopy Substrates Made of Silicon Nanowire Array Coated with Silver Nanoparticles Fabricated by Metal-Assisted Chemical Etching and Photonic Reduction" shortTile="reusable-surfaceenhanced" author="Shi Bai, Yongjun Du, Chunyan Wang, Jian Wu, Koji Sugioka" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2079-4991/9/11/1531/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The three-dimensional (3D) surface-enhanced Raman spectroscopy (SERS) substrate is a powerful analytical method with applications in the fields of medicine, environmental monitoring, and spectral imaging. Compared to two-dimensional (2D) SERS substrates, the 3D SERS substrate offers two unique advantages. Specifically, because a 3D SERS substrate provides a larger surface area and a higher density of so-called “hot spot” zones along the vertical direction compared to a flat 2D substrate, the former allows increased sensitivity and greater enhancement. The other advantage is that a 3D SERS substrate has a more wettable nanostructure, which will improve the SERS sensitivity and repeatability. A 3D SERS substrate is typically composed of a combination of nanowires and metallic nanoparticles. The metallic nanoparticles act as sensing units to generate hot spots in association with localized surface plasmon resonance, which greatly enhances the extent of Raman scattering. The nanowires serve as the backbone of the 3D structure and the nanowire array also serves to further increase the repeatability of the Raman signal due to its periodic structure. As an example, Oh et al. reported a 3D SERS substrate comprising a glass nanopillar array with silver nanoislands. This substrate was found to have a high enhancement factor (EF) and increased the SERS signals by more than one order of magnitude compared to a 2D SERS substrate. This improved performance was attributed to the ability of the silver nanoislands to generate a high density of hot spots on both the top and side of the glass nanopillar array. Park et al. used an Ar+ plasma to treat a polyethylene terephthalate surface to form polymeric nanopillars. Gold nanoparticles were subsequently generated by evaporation to create a 3D gold-rich nanopillar structure that induced the self-clustering of plasmonic nanogaps due to capillary forces and increased the concentration of analyte on the substrate surface. In 2018, Wang et al. developed a 3D gold-rich nanopillar plasmonic substrate for use in SERS analyses that anchored mycotoxins via nanotags. Their work determined that the surface tension induced a leaning effect in groups of two or three adjacent nanopillars that resulted in the self-assembly of hot spots, which, in turn, significantly enhanced the SERS signal. </p>

<p>Some SERS substrates, typically containing materials such as TiO2 and ZnO, can be reused following a self-cleaning process based on the photocatalytic degradation of residual analyte. Following the SERS analysis, such substrates are exposed to either ultraviolet (UV) or visible (VIS) light to degrade residual analyte molecules, after which ions are removed using water wash. Based on this procedure, the refreshed SERS substrate can be reused several times. However, the structure and morphology of a metal layer deposited on a 3D structure are difficult to control, which results in a relatively low SERS enhancement. </p>

<p>In the present work, we developed a simple means of fabricating the 3D SERS substrates, based on coating silicon nanowire arrays with silver nanoparticles (Ag-NP/Si-NW). The morphology of these SERS substrates, which is critical to their performance, could be controlled using metal-assisted chemical etching (MACE) followed by photonic reduction. Herein, we discuss the formation of silver nanoparticles via photonic reduction and their contribution to the SERS enhancement. These 3D SERS substrates are also shown to be reusable after employing UV radiation to degrade dye molecules following an analysis. Finally, these 3D SERS substrates were applied for the analysis of dopamine (DA) to verify that they provide both high sensitivity and reliability. </p>
</text>
