<text id="autogum_interview_doc792" title="part7_Eurovision &amp;apos;73 winner Anne Marie David discusses her four-decade career and the Contest, past and present" shortTile="parteurovision--winner" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-02-15" dateModified="2012-02-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eurovision_%2773_winner_Anne_Marie_David_discusses_her_four-decade_career_and_the_Contest%2C_past_and_present" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>As for the jury, it must stay visible. Previously, each country sent its two judges and during the contest were kept apart from everyone... Tricking votes would be seen on the screens the night of the Contest and thus it almost never happened. What a strange idea also to distinguish between countries which are qualified for [the final] and the others! It's a total injustice. </p>
<p>You see [Eurovision today] is not neutral, and don't [anyone] tell me that it's reasoning from a different age... It's just a series of observations... Nobody can contest the fact that certain generations who were the success of Eurovision no longer find their satisfaction in it and are therefore disinterested. Nobody can contest, also, that for decades the great Eurovision [winners] were international hits that everyone still sings today. Who today is capable of singing the titles which win? And what will remain of [the contest] in the future?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Some viewers were not happy about last year's entrant, Sébastien Tellier. Singing his entry in essentially "franglais," [<hi rend="italic">Editor's note: A mix of words and sentences interchanged between French and English</hi>] even a member of Parliament demanded that the next entry be purely in French. How did you feel about Tellier's performance, and do you feel every French entry must be sung in French? Do you feel not singing in English hinders France as an entrant in today's contest?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AMD</hi>: Once again, I think we must return to the fundamentals. Turn the problem however you'd like but in the end you will arrive at the same conclusions. Germany won in German, Spain won in Spanish, Holland won in Dutch, Norway won in Norwegian, etc... What else? </p>
<p>I see no reason to abandon everything to English; anyway I will fight that it not be the case with French! I sing in English, I speak English, I love the language of Shakespeare, but if I must represent my country in an international contest, I want to do it in French, and I also want it to be done in French. It's not an issue of chauvinism, it's an issue of respect with regards to all those who paid with their blood so that France is a full nation. It's the same for the national anthem of my country. And I would have the same reasoning whatever my nationality. I was born under the sun of France, it's normal that I love that sun.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> In our first Eurovision interview, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eurovision_'82_winner_Nicole_talks_about_'Ein_bißchen_Frieden',_her_success_and_the_Contest_today">we asked the 1982 winner, Nicole</ref>, how she felt about the alleged "bloc voting" taking place between the nations of eastern Europe. She replied, "The eastern European countries obviously support each other with the so-called 'bloc voting.' It's now a political affair and no longer a 'song contest.'" Do you feel that way as well? What exactly are your feelings about the results from the past few years, which place countries like France, the United Kingdom and Germany at the bottom nearly every time?</hi></p>
</text>
