<text id="autogum_interview_doc498" title="part1_Eric Bogosian on writing and the creative urge" shortTile="parteric-bogosian" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-16" dateModified="2014-05-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eric_Bogosian_on_writing_and_the_creative_urge" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  If you could only choose one of these careers, what would you most want to go with?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  In temperament, I'm best suited to the writing, but it isn't what I enjoy the most.  I mean, I really enjoy acting, because it's a lot of fun. But there's a certain self-involvement that's required with acting, and a certain thick skin that I just don't have.  I'm much more a writer, because I can have a homebody quality, and I can be in the house; I can be away from people.  I have sort of a problem in that I like people a lot, and I really hate people, and so it's kind of difficult to decide where I'm at on any given day.</p>
<head id="How_Bogosian_approaches_his_writing">How Bogosian approaches his writing</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When you tackled your first novel, was there ever a time when you were like, 'I don't even know how people get an entire novel out of their heads,' and you had to actually sit down and plot it?  How did you approach your first novel?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  Well, my first prose book wasn't a novel; it's a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Novella">novella</ref> called, <hi rend="italic">Notes from the Underground</hi>.  The way I did that--and this is a long time ago--I wrote it by creating diary entries and just filling them in every day.  So every day, I would give myself the assignment of writing a diary entry for this character.  And I'd say that that's pretty much the easiest way to sit down and write a book, because you say to yourself every day, "I'm going to write one of these things," and one day it'll be long, and another day it'll be short.  I eventually found out what that character was about.  My current book I'm writing now is also written in journal entry form, although in a much more complex way.  When I sat down to write <hi rend="italic">Mall</hi>, which was really my first novel, I wrote it by understanding that I'm not the most sophisticated prose writer.  I had been writing a lot of screenplays and even some television, so I had learned a lot about how to tell a story.  I decided to create a very clear spine on which to hang a lot of things, a very clear arc.  That arc was kind of a thriller.  <hi rend="italic">Mall</hi> is about a guy who's a disgruntled employee and he goes to a shopping mall to shoot the place up.  And it was just kind of strange, because since I've written this book this keeps happening!  This happened a few days ago.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I saw that.</hi></p>
</text>
