<text id="autogum_bio_doc537" title="Bagrationi, wife of John IV of Trebizond" shortTile="bagrationi-wife-john" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-07-08" dateModified="2019-08-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bagrationi%2C_wife_of_John_IV_of_Trebizond" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Bagrationi, wife of John IV of Trebizond</head><p><hi rend="bold">Bagrationi</hi> (c. 1411/2 – before 1438) was the first Empress consort of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_IV_of_Trebizond">John IV of Trebizond</ref>. Her name is unknown.</p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>She was a daughter of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_I_of_Georgia">Alexander I of Georgia</ref> and his first wife Dulandukht, the daughter of Beshken II <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orbelian_Dynasty">Orbeliani</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> Dulandukht had died or was repudiated before 1415, when Alexander married his second wife, the heiress of Imereti, daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_I_of_Imereti">Alexander I of Imereti</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Empress</head>
<p>In about 1426, she married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_IV_of_Trebizond">John IV of Trebizond</ref>, the son of Emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexios_IV_of_Trebizond">Alexios IV of Trebizond</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theodora_Kantakouzene_(wife_of_Alexios_IV_of_Trebizond)">Theodora Kantakouzene</ref>, who had fled from Trebizond after a violent episode.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> According to a passage considered to be an interpolation in the history of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laonikos_Chalkokondyles">Laonikos Chalkokondyles</ref>, he had accused his mother Theodora of having an affair with an unnamed <hi rend="italic">protovestarios</hi>, whom he killed, then held his parents captive in the citadel until the palace staff released them.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Sometime after marrying Bagrationi, John left Georgia for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caffa">Caffa</ref>, where he sought to charter a large <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Galley">galley</ref> and its crew. By 1429 he had found one, for in that year he returned to Trebizond. Alexios IV prepared to face his son in the battlefield. John suborned some of his father's retainers, who assassinated Alexios IV while he slept. He executed the assassins of his father in order to deny any connection with them, then succeeded his father, presumably with Bagrationi as his Empress.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>Their daughter <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Despina_Khatun">Theodora Komnene</ref> was betrothed to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uzun_Hassan">Uzun Hassan</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ak_Koyunlu">Ak Koyunlu</ref> in 1457, whom she married the next year. According to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anthony_Bryer">Anthony Bryer</ref>, this is the "most celebrated Trapezuntine-Muslim marriage", and for which the terms of their marriage can be determined. These terms included: a dowry of properties in the villages of Halanik and Sesera; a "bride-price" in that Uzun Hassan would extend some kind of effort to help defend Trebizond; Theodora's right to continue to profess the Christian faith, keep a chaplain, and act as protector of Christians subject to Uzun Hassan; and "as it turned out, Theodora's considerable (and probably unusual) right to influence Akkoyunlu foreign relations" Theodora's tomb in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diyarbekir">Diyarbekir</ref> was shown to an Italian visitor in 1507. Her two daughters found their way to Damascus where Caterino Zeno met them in 1512.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>An account by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caterino_Zeno">Caterino Zeno</ref> dated to 1474 names another daughter, Eudokia-Valenza of Trebizond. This Valenza was a reported wife of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_Crispo,_Lord_of_Syros">Niccolò Crispo</ref>, Lord of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syros">Syros</ref>. However she is reported as having a daughter who married in 1429. John IV and her are unlikely to have been the grandparents of a married woman only three years following their own marriage. Valenza is considered likely to have been a sister of John IV, instead of a daughter.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> Niccolò Crispo had eleven children. According to his own correspondence, Niccolò was also a son-in-law of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacopo_of_Lesbos">Jacopo of Lesbos</ref>. His children could be from either of his two marriages. They included (among others) <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francesco_II_Crispo">Francesco II Crispo</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_the_Archipelago">Duke of the Archipelago</ref> and Fiorenza Crispo, mother of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catherine_Cornaro">Catherine Cornaro</ref>.</p>
<head>Death</head>
<p>According to the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Europäische_Stammtafeln">Europäische Stammtafeln: Stammtafeln zur Geschichte der Europäischen Staaten</ref></hi> (1978) by Detlev Schwennicke, she was dead by 1438. John IV went on to marry an unnamed Turkish lady. The <hi rend="italic">Europäische Stammtafeln</hi> considers this second wife to have been a daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dawlat_Berdi">Dawlat Berdi</ref>. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pero_Tafur">Pero Tafur</ref>, in his travel memoirs, records that when he visited Trebizond in 1438 John IV had a Turkish wife.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
</text>
