<text id="autogum_bio_doc319" title="William Babell" shortTile="william-babell" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-03-23" dateModified="2019-09-19" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Babell" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>William Babell</head><p><hi rend="bold">William Babell</hi> (or <hi rend="bold">Babel</hi>) (c. 1690<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> - 23 September 1723) was an English <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Musician">musician</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Composer">composer</ref> and prolific arranger of vocal music for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harpsichord">harpsichord</ref>.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>He received his musical training from his father, Charles Babel, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bassoon">bassoonist</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theatre_Royal,_Drury_Lane">Drury Lane orchestra</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Christoph_Pepusch">Johann Christoph Pepusch</ref> and possibly <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Frideric_Handel">George Frideric Handel</ref>. He played violin in the private band of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_I_of_Great_Britain">George I</ref> and appeared as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harpsichord">harpsichordist</ref> from 1711, often appearing with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Corbett_(composer)">William Corbett</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Paisible">James Paisible</ref> and later <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matthew_Dubourg">Matthew Dubourg</ref>. He was associated with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lincoln's_Inn_Fields_Theatre">Lincoln's Inn Fields Theatre</ref>. From November 1718 until his death, he was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pipe_organ">organist</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/All_Hallows,_Bread_Street">All Hallows, Bread Street</ref>, and was succeeded by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Stanley_(composer)">John Stanley</ref>.</p>
<p>He wrote numerous keyboard arrangements of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aria">arias</ref> from popular <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Opera">operas</ref> of his time. These were published in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/France">France</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Netherlands">Netherlands</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Germany">Germany</ref> as well as in England, and formed the basis of his musical reputation. His style was strongly influenced by his close acquaintance with Handel. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Mattheson">Johann Mattheson</ref> thought he surpassed Handel as an organ virtuoso, but music historian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Burney">Charles Burney</ref> criticised his manner of playing arrangements, charging that he:</p>
<p>Despite Burney's criticism, fellow music historian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Hawkins_(author)">Sir John Hawkins</ref> thought they 'succeeded so well … as to make from it a book of lessons which few could play but himself, and which has long been deservedly celebrated.' Babell's transcription of arias from Handel's opera <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rinaldo_(opera)">Rinaldo</ref></hi> includes 'Vo' far guerra', which Handel intended as a showpiece for his harpsichord playing and is quite remarkable in its virtuosity; Babell's transcription was made from his memory of how Handel improvised in performances.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> In 1894, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Friedrich_Chrysander">Friedrich Chrysander</ref> published Babell's arrangement of 'Vo' far guerra' in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Händel-Gesellschaft#Volumes">Händel-Gesellschaft</ref> volume 48.</p>
<p>Babell also wrote original sonatas for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Violin">violin</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oboe">oboe</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Figured_bass">continuo</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Concertos">concertos</ref> and other miscellaneous works, most notably an Ode for St. Cecelia's day now lost. His slow movements are thought to show valuable insight into early 18th-century practices of ornamentation and extemporization.</p>
<p>His early death was attributed to 'intemperate habits’. He died in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canonbury">Canonbury</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Islington">Islington</ref> and was buried in All Hallows Church, Bread Street.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Printed works</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">The 3rd Book of the Ladys Entertainment, or Banquet of Musick</hi> [harpsichord arrangements] (1709)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">The 4th Book of the Ladys Entertainment</hi> [harpsichord arrangements] (1716)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Suits of the Most Celebrated Lessons</hi> [harpsichord arrangements of Handel, some original material] (1717), reprinted as <hi rend="italic">Suits of Harpsichord and Spinnet Lessons</hi> (1718)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">The Harpsichord Master Improved … with a Choice Collection of Newest and Most Air'y Lessons</hi> (1718)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Trios de diefferents autheurs choises &amp; mis en ordre par Mr Babel</hi> [harpsichord arrangements] (1720)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">XII Solos … with Proper Graces Adapted to Each Adagio</hi>, book 1 (violin/oboe, harpsichord) (c. 1725)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">XII Solos … with Proper Graces Adapted to Each Adagio</hi>, book 2 (violin/oboe/flute, harpsichord)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Concertos in 7 Parts</hi> for violins and small flute, or sixth flute (soprano <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Recorder_(musical_instrument)">recorder</ref> in D), op. 3 (c. 1726)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Mariana's Charms Wound my Heart.</hi> A new Song for the Spinnet by W. B.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Would You I the Thing Discover.</hi> A Song. Design'd to be Sung ... in the third Act of the Play called 'Tis well if it Takes, the words by Mr. Theobald, etc.  (1720?)</item></list>
<head>Works in manuscript</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">Overture in A major,</hi>  for two solo violins, solo violoncello, orchestra and continuo, with a cembalo solo part in the last movement.</item>
<item>Add. MS 71209, which contains original and arranged music for harpsichord in Babell's own hand. Among the pieces are an arrangement of the allegro from Handel's Il Pastor Fido with indications for string accompaniment, and two aria arrangements each with an original prelude. The first aria being Caro bene from the pasticcio Clotilda (a similar arrangement in GB-Lfom, Coke 1257) and the second being an early version of Babell's arrangement of Handel's aria Vo' far guerra from Rinaldo found in <hi rend="italic">Suits of the Most Celebrated Lessons</hi>.</item>
<item>GB-Lfom, Coke 1257; contains a collection of preludes and arrangements similar to Babell's <hi rend="italic">Suits of the Most Celebrated Lessons</hi> with several having original preludes unique to this collection.</item>
<item>I-BGi, Ms XIV 8751 H.1 (the Bergamo manuscript) contains eleven toccatas, two suites, seven preludes, a single allemande and a fragmentary arrangement of Henry Carey's 'Sally in our alley'. Several concordances suggest Babell’s authorship of most if not all of the music in the manuscript.</item></list>
<head>Sources and references</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Gerald Gifford (with Terence Best): 'Babell [Babel], William', Grove Music Online ed. L. Macy, <ref target="http://www.grovemusic.com/shared/views/article.html?section=music.01648#music.01648">http://www.grovemusic.com/</ref>, (accessed 2007-05-01)</item>
<item>J. A. F. Maitland, ‘Babell, William (1689/90–1723)’, rev. K. D. Reynolds, Oxford Dictionary of National Biography, Oxford University Press, 2004, <ref target="http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/963">http://www.oxforddnb.com/</ref>, (accessed 2007-05-01)</item></list>
<head>Scores</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://imslp.org/wiki/Category:Babell,%20William">Free scores by William Babell</ref> at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Music_Score_Library_Project">International Music Score Library Project</ref> (IMSLP)</item>
<item><ref target="https://imslp.org/wiki/Works_for_Organ_&amp;_Harpsichord_(Handel,_George_Frideric)">Works for Organ and Harpsichord</ref>: Scores at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Music_Score_Library_Project">International Music Score Library Project</ref> (IMSLP) - the transcriptions from Handel in the complete Handel edition (includes 'Vo' far guerra').</item></list>
</text>
