<text id="autogum_voyage_doc208" title="Raleigh" shortTile="raleigh" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=29138" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Raleigh</head>

<p>The capital of <ref target="North%20Carolina">North Carolina</ref> and the largest city of the <ref target="Research%20Triangle">Research Triangle</ref>, <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://visitraleigh.org">Raleigh</ref></hi> is the primary political and economic driver of the metro area. Indeed, business and politics are the main draws to Raleigh, which lacks the more trendy feel or active arts scene of <ref target="Durham%20%28North%20Carolina%29">Durham</ref> or <ref target="Chapel%20Hill">Chapel Hill</ref> to the west. However, a concerted effort to expand the residential base and move events downtown has led to significantly expanded retail and restaurant options in the downtown core. Also, visitors will find many of the state's cultural institutions here, namely a major performing arts center downtown and three state museums, and a college town atmosphere in the neighborhood around the campus of North Carolina State University, the state's largest university.</p>

<head>History</head>

<p>Raleigh is one of the few U.S. state capitals that was specifically established and planned to serve as a capital. Its location was chosen partly for being near the center of the state and partly because it was close to Isaac Hunter's Tavern, where North Carolina legislators and other government officials liked to stay. The story goes that the commissioners couldn't decide on an exact plot of land until Isaac Hunter and his friend Joel Lane had the idea of throwing a big party with plenty of local jam and whiskey. The next morning, the hungover commissioners voted 5–1 for a plot owned by Joel Lane himself.</p>

<p>The new city was officially established as the state capital in 1792 and was named for Sir Walter Raleigh.</p>

<head>Visitor information</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">The Greater Raleigh Convention and Visitors Bureau</hi> operates the <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.visitraleigh.com/">Raleigh Visitor Information Center</ref></hi>. The Visitor Information Center (VIC) is located at 500 Fayetteville Street between the Raleigh Marriott City Center and The Raleigh Convention Center. Phone: +1 919-834-5900 / +1-800-849-8499. The VIC is open Monday thru Saturday, 9AM to 5PM and offers brochures, event calendars, coupons, maps, and other visitor information. Stop by and pick up a brochure or visit the website to view a visitor guide online or order one to be mailed before your trip.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.rdu.com/">Raleigh-Durham International Airport</ref></hi> ( RDU ). A former hub of American Airlines and Midway Airlines, the airport today is a fairly large focus city for Delta Airlines. The airport has bus service in the form of <ref target="https://gotriangle.org/">GoTriangle</ref> Route 100, which stops at the airport on the way from the Regional Transit Center to downtown Raleigh.</p>

<head>By car</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Interstate 40</hi> goes to points west including <ref target="Durham%20%28North%20Carolina%29">Durham</ref>, <ref target="Chapel%20Hill">Chapel Hill</ref>, <ref target="Greensboro">Greensboro</ref>, <ref target="Winston-Salem">Winston-Salem</ref>, and <ref target="Asheville">Asheville</ref>. Two and a half hours east on I-40 is <ref target="Wilmington%20%28North%20Carolina%29">Wilmington</ref>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Interstates 85 and 95</hi>, though they do not directly enter Raleigh, provide easy access to the city from up and down the Eastern Seaboard; large access routes from these interstates provide easy access to the city.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="U.S.%20Highway%201">US 1</ref></hi>, the East Coast corridor route, cuts through Raleigh on its way from New York to the Florida Keys; within the city limits US 1 is known as Capital Blvd.</item>
</list>


<head>By train</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.amtrak.com">Amtrak</ref></hi> provides train services to Raleigh; the <hi rend="italic">Piedmont</hi> runs three times per day from <ref target="Charlotte">Charlotte</ref>, a trip of just over three hours. There are also two daily long-distance routes: the <hi rend="italic">Carolinian</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Silver Star</hi> lines, both of which head north through <ref target="Richmond">Richmond</ref>, <ref target="Washington%2C%20D.C.">Washington, D.C.</ref> and <ref target="Philadelphia">Philadelphia</ref> to <ref target="New%20York%20City">New York City</ref>. Southbound, the Carolinian follows the Piedmont south to Charlotte and the Silver Star heads south through <ref target="Columbia%20%28South%20Carolina%29">Columbia</ref> and <ref target="Savannah">Savannah</ref> to <ref target="Florida">Florida</ref>. The new , at 510 W Martin St, has completely replaced the old station.</p>

<head>By bus</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.greyhound.com">Greyhound</ref></hi>, 2210 Capital Blvd, +1 919 834-8275.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.megabus.com">Megabus</ref></hi> stops in nearby Durham.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.triangletransit.org/">Triangle Transit</ref></hi>, +1 919 549-9999. The Triangle's inter-city bus service runs routes between Raleigh, Durham, Chapel Hill and RDU, with a hub near the Research Triangle Park. Fares are $2.25 per trip and $4.50 for a day pass.</item>
</list>


<head>Get around</head>

<p>Within the <hi rend="bold">I-440</hi> Beltline are mostly fashionable older neighborhoods and the NC State University area. The North Raleigh neighborhoods are aligned along the "spokes of the wheel"—major thoroughfares emanating from the I-440 Loop and passing through the northern edge of the much larger I-540 loop.</p>

<p>Downtown Raleigh provides easy travel and access through its grid of one-way streets. If you're just passing through, the major thoroughfare is Capital Boulevard (US 401), which splits into Dawson Street heading south and McDowell Street heading north. From the west, it is Hillsborough Street, interrupted midway by the state Capitol building. To the east, it continues as New Bern Avenue (US 64).</p>

<p>The I-440 Beltline was once denoted with "Inner" and "Outer" labels, but they have been phased out in favor of "East" and "West." I-440 West was previously the Outer Beltline, and I-440 East was previously the Inner Beltline. I-440's concurrency with I-40 through the souther portion of Raleigh has also been removed; therefore, the Beltline no longer loops back on itself.</p>

<p>Raleigh is known for particularly aggressive parking enforcement and towing, so be sure to follow all parking signs and rules. Most parking meters have been converted to electronic pay stations that accept coins and MasterCard/Visa. Most metered areas are only enforced on Mon-Fri from 8AM-5PM. Some parking garages are free on evenings and weekends as well, but "special event" rates are common during major downtown events regardless of the time or day.</p>

<head>By bus</head>

<p>For information on routes, schedules and fares, check <ref target="http://www.gotriangle.org">GoTriangle.org</ref>, for a helpful trip planner.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.gotriangle.org/">Triangle Transit Authority (TTA)</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic">+1 919</hi> 549-9999. Routes between Raleigh, Durham, Cary, and Chapel Hill as well as Research Triangle Park and the Raleigh-Durham International Airport.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://www.raleighnc.gov/transit/">Capital Area Transit (CAT)</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic">+1 919</hi> 828-7228. Routes within Raleigh city limits including a free downtown circulator bus, the R-Line.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www2.acs.ncsu.edu/trans/transportation/wolfline/">Wolfline</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic">+1 919</hi> 515-9653. Routes in and around NC State University; free and open to the public.</item>
</list>


<p>Note that Triangle Transit passes ($4.50 for a 1-day pass) can also be used on CAT and buses in Durham and Cary. But the reverse is not true; CAT passes ($2 for 1-day) are only usable on CAT.</p>
</text>
