<text id="autogum_academic_doc239" title="Why the Development of Internal Combustion Engines Is Still Necessary to Fight against Global Climate Change from the Perspective of Transportation" shortTile="development-internal" author="José  Ramón Serrano, Ricardo Novella, Pedro Piqueras" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/9/21/4597/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">

<p>Internal combustion engines (ICE) are the main propulsion systems in road transport. In mid-2017, Serrano referred to the impossibility of replacing them as the power plant in most vehicles. Nowadays, this statement is true even when considering the best growth scenario for all-electric and hybrid vehicles. The arguments supporting this position consider the growing demand for transport, the strong development of cleaner and more efficient ICEs, the availability of fossil fuels, and the high energy density of said conventional fuels. Overall, there seems to be strong arguments to support the medium-long-term viability of ICEs as the predominant power plant for road transport applications. However, the situation has changed dramatically in the last few years. The media and other market players are claiming the death of ICEs in the mid-term. Politicians from several G7 countries, such as France, Spain, and the United Kingdom, have announced the prohibition of ICEs in their markets, in some cases, as early as 2040. Large cities, such London, Paris, Madrid, and Berlin, are also considering severe limits to ICE-powered vehicles. What is the analysis that can be made from this new situation? </p>

<head> 1. What Is the Problem with ICE (Internal Combustion Engines)?</head>
<p>The media’s arguments against ICEs range from the need to reduce CO2 emissions (global warming) to the need to improve the air quality in cities (NOx and particulate matter emissions). </p>

<p>Much of this debate about the future of ICEs has arisen from the Dieselgate scandal. A horrible wrong decision from a management and engineering point of view at a specific time and place has generated a worldwide butterfly effect in the automotive industry. However, making the problem a virtue, Dieselgate has forced new regulations to obtain much more efficient and cleaner ICEs. </p>

<p>As commonly takes place, old and lax pollutant regulations have now resulted in a pendular effect toward radically contrary positions, delighting the media and generating excessive political reactions without a clear scientific basis. All this is reflected in the look to publish a sufficiently popular or good news novelty. We could define the situation as energy populism. Although new regulations that force ICE technology to be more environmentally friendly must always be welcome, prohibitions motivated by a poor diagnosis of the situation will not help at all, neither to improve air quality nor to mitigate global warming. </p>

<head> 2. What Is the Problem with Electric Vehicles?</head>
<p>What should be the alternative to the current ICE in the mid-to-long term? Combining the pendulum effect of public opinion with the excellent marketing of new actors in the passenger car sector, a confusion cocktail is served for the media. After all, one might ask if the use of the conventional propulsive systems over 120 years was the right path. How can such an old concept be innovative? How can the ICE be great and technologically advanced at burning fossil fuels? An easy but wrong conclusion comes without the need of reflection: Let us welcome “new electric motors and batteries” in zero-emission cars! </p>

<p>The bad news is that energy is neither created nor destroyed, only transformed. Electric motors and batteries are not new, nor are they clean and, in general, are not free from problems. One can directly identify two relevant problems. </p>

<p>The first problem is that vehicle propulsion involves energy transformations and the electric motor does not use a primary energy source but an energy vector. Although public opinion has a clear idea of how some processes like friction can negatively affect transport applications, the understanding of the impact of the second law of thermodynamics is limited. The problem is that electricity must be produced, most usually from non-renewable energy sources, which equals around 60% in energy losses, and then transported, which adds 20% of additional losses. Unfortunately, renewable sources are barely 10% of the global energy mix, as observed in <figure>Figure 1</figure> without a medium-term forecast of significant increase. </p>

<p>In some countries like the USA, China, Russia, Poland, South Korea, or Germany, fossil fuels, including a good percentage of coal, remain the largest source of energy as a raw material for electricity production. In a first approach, the only G8 country with real alternatives to CO2-emitting technologies is France due to its continued commitment with nuclear energy. Therefore, with the current energy mix and with an analysis of the complete life cycle, the so-called analysis from the cradle to the grave, the alternative to electric motors will not eliminate global CO2 emissions. </p>
</text>
