<text id="autogum_academic_doc739" title="Mediating Climate, Mediating Scale" shortTile="mediating-climate" author="Anne Pasek" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-0787/8/4/159/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Conclusions </head>
<p>
The role of aesthetics in climate communication has been largely confined to the field of ecocriticism and related studies of global warming in art, literature, and film—in short, objects of study that are understood to be interpretive representations of climate within a predominantly humanist tradition (Siperstein et al. 2016; Svoboda 2016; Davis and Turpin 2015). There are few attempts to apply humanist analyses of aesthetics and visual culture to scientific representations of climate and climate data.5 Yet, as evidenced by the climate spirals and, to a degree, the hockey stick graphs that precede it, data visualization is a rich site of aesthetic and affective responses—responses that can best be evaluated through tools of formal analysis and reception germane to the arts.  </p>

<p>These examples of charismatic data images suggest that climate change communication continues to be a complicated, unpredictable task, resistant to easy summary in formulas for best practices or optimized psychological reach. This is in large part because of the paradox of scale that endures within the political, scientific, and aesthetic problems of climate: Global warming requires inherently trans-scalar modes of engagement, calling our attention simultaneously towards each other and far beyond the scope of individual or everyday experiences. We must forget neither side of this equation. </p>

<p>I conclude not with an answer that resolves this tension, but instead a call for pluralism in approaches to negotiating scalar contradictions. I find encouraging signs to this end in the continuing experiments with form and visual narrative emerging from communication practitioners, both professional and informal. Animation is fast becoming a more commonly utilized technique, now formally recommended to climate researchers looking to share datasets and summaries with a wider public (Harold et al. 2017). Recent efforts by Antti Lipponen, Kevin Pluck, Robert Rohde, Neil Kaye, and John Nelson are examples of this trend, including gif, video, and scrolling animations that dramatize the speed and size of global temperature anomalies, sea level rise, and fossil fuel consumption on sites including Twitter, Reddit, Flickr, and YouTube. More broadly, during the recent Global Climate Strike Week, millions of youths and their allies marched with signs that mixed climate data and collective demands, as well as humour and despair, local grievances and global imperatives, the personal and the political. Online and offline, in professional contexts and in memes, data and people are on the move, circulating affects. </p>

<p>Ed Hawkins, meanwhile, has sparked another viral success: “warming stripes” that graphically mark the global drift in average temperatures through shifting bands of blue and red colours. The formula has been localized by individuals and groups and transported off the Internet and onto cars, clothes, murals, and mugs, traveling through everyday spaces and sparking new conversations. I was astonished to discover one such visualization in a city council meeting in August. Among the activists and advocates delivering testimony in support of a declaration of climate emergency was a small group holding aloft a scarf, knitted to display stripes of rising temperatures across scales greater than a human lifetime. The declaration passed, not by virtue of the scarf, but through the mixed emotions and collective demands that brought it and so many others into the chamber.
 </p>
</text>
