<text id="autogum_reddit_doc095" title="CMV:Trickle down economics does not and will not ever work" shortTile="cmvtrickle-down-economics" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-04-30" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8g37up" speakerList="#gotinpich, #softhandsam" speakerCount="2">
<head>CMV:Trickle down economics does not and will not ever work</head>
<sp who="#softhandsam">
<p>There is no example of this actually working that I am aware of, and the entire idea behind it is patently ridiculous. The crux of the argument seems to be that if we make the rich richer, they will find the kindness that they currently lack, and raise working wages. I just don't see why that would happen. What incentive is there? By providing an inefficient working wage, they have already demonstrated their selfishness/greed. So you are basically saying "the rich will stop being so greedy if we give them more money." This is absurd. I would love to hear someone actually form a good argument.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#gotinpich">
<p>While I agree with you that  <hi rend="bold">trickle down economics</hi> , a.k.a.  <hi rend="bold">reaganomics</hi> , a.k.a.  <hi rend="bold">supply side economics</hi> , a.k.a.  <hi rend="bold">voodoonomics</hi> , a.k.a.  <hi rend="bold">wishful thinking</hi> , a.k.a.  <hi rend="bold">magic</hi> , is complete and utter nonsense, I would like to challenge your view on the following: </p>
<p>&gt; I just don't see why that would happen. What incentive is there? By providing an inefficient working wage, they have already demonstrated their selfishness greed. So you are basically saying the rich will stop being so greedy if we give them more money. </p>
<p>This is not what voodoonomics is about. It does not assume any benevolence on the part of the rich, but it assumes that the poor are fed by the wastefulness of the rich. </p>
<p>Imagine it like a medieval banquet where the feudal lord enjoys the finest game prepared by the best cooks in his realm. While he's eating the meat from the bones, he throws the bones he's done with on the floor and the dogs will run to scramble for the remaining meat on the bones. Now when the dogs (or the peasants) go hungry, voodoonomics says that instead of giving the dogs more food, we should hold more and more lavish banquets so that the bones that are thrown on the floor contain more meat. Of course the other possibility is that the lord becomes more greedy and gluttonous. </p>
<p>Or in a more modern day example: if we want to fight poverty, instead of giving money to the poor, we should give more money to the rich. That way they can buy more over-the-top, luxurious yachts that they'll visit only a few days every year. That way jobs are created for people that build and sell the yachts, people that perform maintenance on or clean the yachts, construction workers that build the ports and the docks. Etc., etc., etc. </p>
<p>And actually, for very few places around the world, this has actually worked out (e.g. Saint Tropez).</p>
</sp>
</text>
