<text id="autogum_interview_doc818" title="part3_Satanism: An interview with Church of Satan High Priest Peter Gilmore" shortTile="partsatanism-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-04" dateModified="2018-10-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Satanism%3A_An_interview_with_Church_of_Satan_High_Priest_Peter_Gilmore" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why do you think there are those who need to have a God or supernatural parental figure?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  I think it’s natural to them.  I don't think it is something developmental, but that it’s just part of their own nature.  That they <hi rend="italic">feel</hi> a need  for something above them, whether it be human or supernatural.  And they can't get away from that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  In the history of a lot of religions, a doctrine was developed by people who were oppressed as a way to explain their lot, and that their oppressors were going to "get theirs in the end."  That’s where <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karl%20Marx">Karl Marx</ref> was saying religion is the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Opium%20of%20the%20People">opiate of the masses</ref>, because it creates complacency with oppression <hi rend="italic">now</hi> because in some other ethereal dimension equality will be achieved. </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  Well, see the idea of the “God” comes from the oppressors, and it’s a way of controlling folks, by saying, “I have communication with this authority figure but <hi rend="italic">you can't</hi>.  I’m special.”  That’s where priesthoods come in, but also governmental authorities and parties, let's say the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Communist%20Party">Communist Party</ref> or the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nazi%20Party">Nazi Party</ref> at one point.  <hi rend="italic">They</hi> have the key to the way the universe should exist, and everyone needs to be subservient to them and take what they say as holy writ whether they are actually claiming it is divine or not.  That’s why so many of those fascist and totalitarian systems function like religions, because they put the leaders and whatever they wrote as some kind of scriptural authority that is not supposed to be debated or examined, but simply swallowed whole.</p>
<p>Now some people might come up with a religious belief that may counter an existing system that will help them feel better about their underdog status, and then sometimes that develops into a major religion and sometimes it doesn't.  Sometimes it is crushed and snuffed out.  That’s natural to our species, that people have to find a way for dealing with their existence.</p>
<p>The Satanist, we look at our existence and say, “We’re not going to look for something outside of ourselves.  We’re going to be <hi rend="italic">proactive</hi>."  We’ll go out there and try to make a change, and we’ll deal pragmatically with whatever life situations we have.  So the Satanist, regardless of where he is living and under what kind of conditions, he is going to try to find a way to make his life as good as it can be based upon his own abilities and the world around him.  We don't expect everybody in Satanism to be a genius, we expect people to take whatever they have by nature, and do the best with it.  So in that sense, we challenge people who are our members; the only idealism we have is directed at ourselves.  We try to look at ourselves and try to realize what our potential possibly could be, what talents do we have.  And then we try to take those, through whatever work is needed, to take those as far as we can.</p>
</text>
