<text id="autogum_interview_doc459" title="part3_Former &amp;apos;Top Model&amp;apos; contestant Whitney Cunningham defends plus size models, celebrates the &amp;quot;regular woman&amp;quot;" shortTile="partformer-top-model" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-12-03" dateModified="2012-06-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Former_%27Top_Model%27_contestant_Whitney_Cunningham_defends_plus_size_models%2C_celebrates_the_%22regular_woman%22" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">WC:</hi> Adversity?! Absolutely not. I don't think people understand that I am a <hi rend="italic">regular</hi> woman. I wear a [size] ten for God's sake. It's so funny because people come up to me and they say, "Wow, you're not fat at all? You must have lost a lot of weight." I think I just came off looking heavier on TV...that, or people just had a distorted perception of what I <hi rend="italic">should</hi> look like in person. As a matter of fact I'm about 10 pounds heavier than I was on the show now and people can't believe how "normal" I look. But that was my aim in going on the show, that a normal woman can actually have a place in the industry. She doesn't have to be a size 2 nor does she have to be a size 18.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Another fan writes: Do you feel like "plus size" models are treated fairly? (I put "plus size" in quotes because I don't believe you are "plus size"!)</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WC:</hi> No, I don't. I don't think that plus-sized models are given enough respect and I don't think that folks value the plus-sized industry the way it should be valued. But I think it's because people don't know how much the plus-sized industry varies. Hell, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kim%20Kardashian">Kim Kardashian</ref> could be considered a plus-sized model! But people automatically assume that plus-sized means obese and that no one who is obese could possibly be attractive, or sexy, or a model. But that's not the case.</p>
<head id="Whitney's_views_on_production_and_editing">Whitney's views on production and editing</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  Do you believe the producers for shows such as <hi rend="italic">Top Model</hi> intentionally pick people who are perhaps unstable, for better television?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WC:</hi> Absolutely. I understand it, though. When I have my own production/entertainment company and I'm brainstorming ideas for a show, or a book, or a commercial, etc., I'll think of what sort of concepts will accrue me the largest profit. The producers of <hi rend="italic">Top Model</hi> think along the same lines. Mass consumers want to see stuff that's juicy! They don't want to watch boring characters every Wednesday night. They want someone who's fun and out of the ordinary.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Can you explain what types of things the producers allow you to say or not say following your departure from the show?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WC:</hi> Well, the show is not taped live, so of course you're sworn to secrecy about what's happened during taping until the show actually airs.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Who selects your best photo for each panel and do you think there are ulterior motives involved?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WC:</hi> Tyra says she selects the photos, but who knows. I don't know about ulterior motives, but there were numerous times where I knew that I had taken a better photo than the one that appeared on the screen during panel. Every season girls say the same thing as well. It's interesting because in the last photo shoot I had before I was eliminated, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jay%20Manuel">Mr. Jay</ref> told me that I had finally figured out the art of modeling and I have successfully pulled off my shoot. Needless to say, I was eliminated and never saw it coming. I figured it was smooth sailing since the director of the photo shoot told me I looked like I knew what I was doing. It is what it is though. What can I say?</p>
</text>
