<text id="autogum_interview_doc166" title="part1_Interview with Stephanie Beaumier, City Council candidate for Wards 1 &amp; 5 in Brampton, Canada" shortTile="partinterview-stephanie" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-24" dateModified="2007-06-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Stephanie_Beaumier%2C_City_Council_candidate_for_Wards_1_%26_5_in_Brampton%2C_Canada" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I have been involved in all levels of politics from a very early age and have a bachelors degree in political science for The University of Western Ontario.  I have also been a Brampton resident for over 30 years.  I am not a rookie.  I care about this city and the people who live and work here.  I want to put people back as top priority in any political agendas and decision-making.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> The Rose Theatre recently launched. What are your thoughts on this facility? Have you had a chance to tour it yet? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Yes, I have toured the theatre.  It is beautiful from the inside out.  I love the name as it coincides with Brampton's history.  To date, the theatre is operating on budget and I hope it will continue.  I commend the theatre group for attracting very popular entertainment.  We must watch the theatre closely and work with local media and community groups to ensure its continued success.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> The province has strongly encouraged the development of high-density residences near the downtown. Do these buildings fit in with your vision of the downtown? How much say should other levels of government have in urban planning? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I have been a resident of downtown Brampton for over 13 years.  The development of high-density residences in downtown Brampton is of great concern to the residents and to me.  Potential problems with increased traffic, crime and pollution must be addressed at the onset of any decision-making.  Improving public transit within Brampton and with GO Transit is a priority and the establishment of parking areas for the residents of these new buildings is key.  I appreciate the feedback and recommendations of both provincial and federal governments in urban planning, however, we must fight for what is right for Brampton and its' residents first and foremost.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How do you feel about Brampton's rate of expansion? Council recently capped the annual amount of new development; do you agree completely with this decision, would you have slowed development even further, or not have imposed a cap at all? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> The current council allowed the growth of Brampton to get out of control to begin with.  Capping the growth rate now is another example of reactive governance.  However, it is the only option to best manage a bad situation.  With more effective planning in the building of major roads, park lands, schools and recreation centres that meet the needs of the community, there would have been no reason to impose a cap.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why should businesses be attracted to locating in Brampton?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Brampton is ideally situated near many major road access routes. It has an excellent labour pool with the full range of general labour to high in demand skill sets.</p>
</text>
