<text id="autogum_academic_doc563" title="Evaluation of Current Signature in Bearing Defects by Envelope Analysis of the Vibration in Induction Motors" shortTile="evaluation-current" author="Isac  Antônio dos Santos Areias, Luiz  Eduardo Borges da Silva, Erik  Leandro Bonaldi, Levy  Ely de Lacerda de Oliveira, Germano Lambert-Torres, Vitor  Almeida Bernardes" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/21/4029/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>Currently in industry, fault detection and identification of causes and consequences of failures are performed by operators. If any of these tasks are not performed correctly, adverse effects can occur, such as: reduction of product quality, process safety and lifetime of machinery. In this scenario, condition-based maintenance helps reduce unplanned downtime and maintenance costs. Since the induction motor is widely used in industries, fault detection in induction motors becomes an indispensable tool in condition-based maintenance. According to statistical evidence, most induction motor failures occur in bearings (40% to 90% of large to small machines). Of all the techniques for diagnosis and detection of roller bearing failures, the most common is vibration analysis. Recently, stator current-based bearing failure detection has been shown to have relevant results with the advantage of being non-invasive and without the need for special sensors, significantly reducing maintenance costs. </p>

<p>The identification and fault diagnosis must be able to provide alert signals when the fault is still incipient. Thus, still at an early stage, a maintenance action should be taken to avoid fault evolution and catastrophic failure, avoiding also unnecessary costs from unscheduled repairs and shutdowns. </p>

<p>Bearing failures are classified as distributed or localized. In the first kind, the deterioration occurs in a generalized way, producing a vibration that, in the frequency domain, does not present a spectral component at a certain frequency but an increase in a broad frequency band. Consequently, its detection becomes more difficult. The second kind, the localized one, is the one addressed in this work and its produced vibration is associated with certain frequencies that depend on the affected bearing element (outter race, inner race, ball and cage). It should be noted that a localized fault can spread to other bearing components as the level of degradation becomes more pronounced. </p>

<p>The traditional monitoring method, vibration analysis, requires the installation of accelerometers or speed sensors that require accurate positioning, making this analysis costly, complex, and invasive. So, the investments in the motor current signature analysis (MCSA) in the detection of roller bearing failures are justified. This technique has become an attractive alternative because it is more accessible, simple and it does not even require the physical access to the motor itself. </p>

<p>However, the MCSA technique presents a great difficulty in an accurate diagnosis of localized roller bearing faults due to issues such as: the low energy of the fault related spectral components and the close presence of high energy spectral components related to the power supply or to other mechanical sources. When the localized fault is in the early stage, the energy associated to the generated impacts is not strong enough to be detected directly in the acquired vibration signal. Therefore, according to Salomon, the energy is even lower in the stator current, because the effects of this impact are obtained indirectly as a variation of torque. The motor RMS current can be understood as an image of motor torque: more motor torque implies more RMS current; less motor torque implies less RMS current. So, periodic variations in the motor torque due to specific faults will cause periodic variations in RMS current and, consequently, amplitude modulation of the instantaneous current in specific frequencies. </p>

<p>Another challenge presented by localized bearing faults for both, vibration analysis and MCSA, is the variation of the element fault frequencies. Roller bearing manufacturers provide the nominal fault frequencies for each of the elements in a roller bearing:
<list>
<item>BPFO—Ball Pass Frequency in the Outer Race;</item>
<item>BPFI—Ball Pass Frequency in the Inner Race;</item>
<item>BSF—Ball Spin Frequency;</item>
<item>FTF—Frame Train Frequency.</item>
</list>
</p>

<p>Those frequencies depend on the bearing geometrical characteristics, and can present an error from external factors such as: geometric variations imposed by the failure itself, incorrect bearing installation, cage locking, improper lubrication and ball slip, for instance. Thus, care must be taken to avoid the analysis of spectral components not related to the defect. In MCSA, this is a more critical concern, since it is not uncommon to have high energy supply frequency harmonics near the bearing fault frequencies, which can demand a very high-resolution spectrum to distinguish spectral components of diverse nature. </p>

<p>In order to correctly identify, in the current spectrum, the correct localized fault frequencies of roller bearings, this paper proposes the use of the envelope analysis of vibration signal as a first step. The envelope analysis is successfully used for decades in the detection of incipient roller bearing faults. In this technique, the vibration signal is bandpass filtered in a frequency range corresponding to the mechanical resonance of the system, which tends to amplify the impacts produced by a localized fault in any element of the roller bearing. The filtered signal is then amplitude demodulated using the Hilbert transform, which results in the amplitude envelope of the mechanical resonance region. The envelope spectrum is then obtained by the Fourier transform. This spectrum presents the localized fault frequencies with great sensitivity. </p>
</text>
