<text id="autogum_interview_doc507" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Jeremy Hanke, editor of MicroFilmmaker Magazine" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-11" dateModified="2019-08-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Jeremy_Hanke%2C_editor_of_MicroFilmmaker_Magazine" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Shortly after that, I found a company called Redrock Micro, which had built a 35mm lens adapter for less than $1K which allowed low-budget filmmakers to get film-like depth of field from $2000-$4000 cameras and SLR lenses.  This was about 15 times cheaper than the closest competitor from P+S Technik.  Not only that, but they had such a passion for low-budget filmmakers, that they were offering kits with plans and a key part so you could build your own 35mm adapter for $45.  I was so blown away by an equipment manufacturer caring that much about low-budget filmmakers that it inspired me to create the first magazine aimed specifically to help other ultra-low budget filmmakers who had to struggle as much as I did.</p>
<p>As you can imagine, the name “MicroFilmmaker” came from a combination of the word “Microcinema” (with its low budgets and community approach) and Filmmaking (which we specifically chose over “videomaking,” because we feel that filmmaking is able to be accomplished with any medium, since “films” are a product, not a recording medium).</p>
<p>As I inferred, I wanted to connect low-budget filmmakers via a feeling of community, as many low-budget filmmakers often compete so viciously against one another in film festivals for coveted “shots” with Hollywood, that they can quickly forget their similarities.  (We also wanted to remind them that low-budget filmmakers actually substantially outnumber their counterparts in Hollywood, which can be an amazing source of power if we all work together, rather than in isolated groups.)  The best way we saw to do this was by providing a vast resource library of articles on low-budget filmmaking with a serious eye for stretching a dollar, in-depth reviews of software and equipment specifically evaluated from a low-budget perspective, DIY tutorials on building helpful equipment, listings of special readers-only discounts of different products, and an area for finding fully deferred musicians and score composers for your films.</p>
<p>Of course, one of the most unique things at MFM is something no other magazine offers: in-depth critiques of current low-budget films by trained low-budget directors and producers to help filmmakers become better at their craft.   This last piece of our magazine’s offerings is the only thing that we charge any money for, because it is so specialized to a specific filmmaker’s film. (Although there is a charge, the amount is no more than the cost of a submission to a film festival with shorts running $25 and feature-length films running $50, which is used to provide a small reimbursement to the critic for their hard, detailed work and is substantially less than the $300-$500 most film analysis companies charge.)</p>
<p>With this publicly viewable critique service, we’ve had films submitted from every continent (with the exception of Antartica <hi rend="italic">[sic]</hi>).  Filmmakers have ranged from total film beginners to former Hollywood people who’ve become passionate about low-budget filmmaking, which is a really awesome swath of filmmaking humanity.  It’s always cool when we’ll have a filmmaker submit a film that has problems and then, after the critique, change their approach for the next film so that the upcoming film has a much better score.  We’ve had filmmakers jump from relatively low scores with one film to getting our coveted “Best of Show” award with the very next film.</p>
</text>
