<text id="autogum_bio_doc306" title="William Gregg (clerk and spy)" shortTile="william-gregg-clerk" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-05-23" dateModified="2019-07-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Gregg_%28clerk_and_spy%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>William Gregg (clerk and spy)</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">William Gregg</hi> (died 1708) was a Scottish <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spy">spy</ref>  who had been a  clerk to  the  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secretary_of_State_(England)">Secretary of State</ref>,  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Harley,_1st_Earl_of_Oxford_and_Earl_Mortimer">Robert Harley</ref>. He was executed for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treason">treason</ref> after it was discovered that he had been selling State secrets to the French. The affair gravely damaged Harley politically, as  he was rightly criticised for facilitating Gregg's treason through his lax security arrangements, although it is generally accepted that he had no knowledge of the treason itself.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Vernon">James Vernon</ref>,   Secretary of State 1697-1702,   had known Gregg's  father, also  named William Gregg, who was a  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diplomat">diplomat</ref>.  No doubt on his father's account, Vernon   took  the young Gregg into his service as  his secretary, but had to dismiss him 'for his ill qualities', according to  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gilbert_Burnet">Gilbert Burnet</ref>. Gregg was indeed an unsuitable choice for such a position, as he had a criminal record and had narrowly escaped being found guilty of  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Counterfeiting">counterfeiting</ref> in 1697.  His wife, who attempted to take all the blame on herself, was  found guilty and, despite being pregnant, was  sentenced to  being <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Human_branding">branded</ref>  on the hand. Nevertheless, when Robert Harley became secretary of state in 1706, he appointed Gregg to an underclerkship in his office, and even extended to him an exceptional amount of confidence.
That, at any rate, was one explanation for the disaster which ensued; another, which  has the authority of the celebrated author <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniel_Defoe">Daniel Defoe</ref>,  then Gregg's fellow secretary,  was that Harley's office was always in a state of the most complete disorder, and that papers of the gravest import were open to the inspection of every clerk, doorkeeper, or laundress in the establishment.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESeccombe1901-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Antagonism was at its height between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_Godolphin,_2nd_Earl_of_Godolphin">Godolphin</ref> and Harley at the close of 1707, and the Whigs were plotting to exclude Harley from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Privy_Council_of_England">Privy Council</ref>. Intelligence came from the postmaster at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brussels">Brussels</ref> that a packet of letters had been opened from the secretary's office and addressed to French minister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michel_Chamillart">Michel Chamillart</ref>, and they contained copies of important state papers; a covering note indicated that the copies were sent by Gregg.
Gregg was arrested on 1 Jan. 1708, was examined by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Spencer,_3rd_Earl_of_Sunderland">Sunderland</ref> on 3 January, and forthwith committed to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newgate">Newgate</ref>.
He was tried at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old_Bailey">Old Bailey</ref>  on 9 January for  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treason">treasonable correspondence</ref>  with France, pleaded guilty, and was sentenced to death.</p>
<p>The culprit pleaded in extenuation of his crime his poverty and heavy  debts, but swore positively that he had no accomplice in his crime. He seems to have felt a strong sense of loyalty to Harley, despite his  previous betrayal of him, and refused steadfastly to implicate him.
The Whig leaders, however, were eager to obtain evidence against Harley, and were in great hopes that the unfortunate man would say something to convict his chief of complicity.</p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Lords">House of Lords</ref> formed a committee of seven to examine Gregg, and placed upon it   <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Seymour,_6th_Duke_of_Somerset">Charles Seymour, 6th Duke of Somerset</ref>  and two other dukes, besides  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Wharton,_1st_Marquess_of_Wharton">Thomas Wharton, 1st Marquess of Wharton</ref> ,  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Townshend,_2nd_Viscount_Townshend">Charles Townshend, 2nd Viscount Townshend</ref>,   <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Montagu,_1st_Earl_of_Halifax">Charles Montagu, 1st Earl of Halifax</ref>,  and  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Somers,_1st_Baron_Somers">John Somers, 1st Baron Somers</ref>.
The committee went to Newgate on 7 February and informed Gregg that, if he would make a full confession, he might rely upon the intercession of the house.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESeccombe1901-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In spite of the temptation thus dangled before him, the poor fellow adhered manfully to the truth of his first statement.
The committee had the cruelty to keep the condemned man in suspense for three months.
At length, they sent <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen_Anne_of_England">Queen Anne</ref>  a recommendation that the execution should take place, bitterly disappointed at making no other discovery than that the business of the secretary's office was conducted in a strangely lax manner.
Gregg was hanged and quartered at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tyburn">Tyburn</ref> on 28 April 1708, and his head was placed on Westminster Hall.
Before he met his fate, he delivered a paper to the ordinary in which he solemnly exculpated Harley from all participation in his offence.
He also left a letter, the contrite tenor of which was warmly commended by Hearne.
Harley found it necessary during the second week in February 1708 to resign his secretaryship, but he had the generosity to allow  Gregg's  widow a pension of fifty pounds annually out of his private purse.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESeccombe1901-1">[1]</ref></p>
</text>
