<text id="autogum_news_doc462" title="European football: Real Madrid wins third consecutive Champions League beating Liverpool 3-1" shortTile="european-football" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2018-05-29" dateModified="2019-08-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/European_football%3A_Real_Madrid_wins_third_consecutive_Champions_League_beating_Liverpool_3-1" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>European football: Real Madrid wins third consecutive Champions League beating Liverpool 3-1</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 29, 2018</hi></p>
<p>On Saturday, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Spain">Spanish</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Soccer">football</ref> club <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Real_Madrid">Real Madrid</ref> defeated <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/England">English</ref> side <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Liverpool_FC">Liverpool</ref> 3–1 in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ukraine">Ukrainian</ref> capital <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kiev">Kiev</ref>, to win their third consecutive UEFA Champions League trophy. Two goals from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gareth_Bale">Gareth Bale</ref> and one from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Karim_Benzema">Karim Benzema</ref> led Real Madrid to win their thirteenth European title victory.</p>
<p>Real Madrid dominated the match in ball possession. Real Madrid won an early free-kick, in the first minute as Liverpool's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dejan%20Lovren">Dejan Lovren</ref> committed soon after the start of the game. Liverpool's attack had multiple attempts for the goal early in the first fifteen minutes, none crossing the goal line. In the eighteenth minute, Liverpool's defender <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virgil%20van%20Dijk">Virgil van Dijk</ref> missed a chance to score a close-range header.</p>
<p>Liverpool's <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mohamed_Salah">Mohamed Salah</ref> was substituted off in the 30th minute after a tackle by Madrid's captain <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sergio_Ramos">Sergio Ramos</ref>. Salah, who had scored 44 goals for the English side in all competitions this season, was later taken to a hospital because of a shoulder injury. The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Egypt">Egyptian</ref> was replaced by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adam%20Lallana">Adam Lallana</ref>. Just seven minutes later, Real made their first change in the game, as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nacho%20Fernández">Nacho</ref> replaced <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dani_Carvajal">Dani Carvajal</ref> who was also substituted off due to injury. The first half ended with 0–0 on the scoreboard.</p>
<p>Three minutes into the second half, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isco">Isco</ref> almost gave Madrid the lead with his shot on goal, but it hit the goal post. In the 51st minute, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">Frenchman</ref> Karim Benzema scored the first goal of the match, but the lead was short-lived. Four minutes later, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sadio%20Mané">Sadio Mané</ref> scored an equaliser for Liverpool, from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dejan%20Lovren">Dejan Lovren</ref>'s assist. Gareth Bale was substituted on for Isco. The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wales">Welshman</ref> came on in the 61st minute, and three minutes later, Bale scored an overhead goal, assisted by <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Marcelo_Vieira">Marcelo</ref>. Mané came close to score another equaliser in the 70 minute, but his shot deflected off the post. He was later booked in the 82nd minute for a bad foul, which was the only yellow card issued in the match. A minute later, Bale added a third goal for the defending champions. Liverpool's goalkeeper <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loris%20Karius">Loris Karius</ref> tried to block the goal, but could not keep the ball away from the net. The match ended after four minutes of added time after 90 minutes of play.</p>
<p>After the match, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jürgen_Klopp">Jürgen Klopp</ref> spoke about Salah's injury saying, "It's a serious injury, a really serious injury." Klopp said Salah was "in the hospital for an X-ray. It's either the collarbone or the shoulder itself. It doesn't look good".</p>
<p>This was the second Champions League final for Klopp in five years. His led his former club <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Borussia_Dortmund">Borussia Dortmund</ref> to the final in 2012–13, losing 2–1 to their arch rivals <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bayern_Munich">Bayern Munich</ref>. Klopp has lost six out of seven major finals in his managing career.</p>
<p>Real Madrid's manager <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Zinedine_Zidane">Zinedine Zidane</ref> won the third consecutive Champions League trophy as the club's manager, joining <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bob%20Paisley">Bob Paisley</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Carlo_Ancelotti">Carlo Ancelotti</ref> who won the European Cup three times.</p>
<p>This was fifth Champions League title for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Cristiano_Ronaldo">Cristiano Ronaldo</ref>, who won four titles with Real Madrid in the last five seasons, and one during his time at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Manchester_United">Manchester United</ref>, a decade ago.</p>
May 26, 2018
<hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Real_Madrid">Real Madrid</ref></hi>
<hi rend="bold">3–1</hi>
<hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Liverpool_FC">Liverpool FC</ref></hi>
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NSC%20Olimpiyskiy%20Stadium">NSC Olimpiyskiy Stadium</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kiev">Kiev</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ukraine">Ukraine</ref> Referee:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milorad%20Mažić">Milorad Mažić</ref> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Football%20Association%20of%20Serbia">Serbia</ref>)
<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Karim_Benzema">Karim Benzema</ref>  51'<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gareth_Bale">Gareth Bale</ref>  64'<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gareth_Bale">Gareth Bale</ref>  83'<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dani_Carvajal">Dani Carvajal</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nacho%20Fernández">Nacho</ref>  37'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isco">Isco</ref>  61'Gareth Bale  61'Karim Benzema  89'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marco%20Ascensio">Marco Ascensio</ref>  89'
(0–0) <hi rend="bold">HT</hi>
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sadio%20Mané">Sadio Mané</ref>  55'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sadio%20Mané">Sadio Mané</ref>  82'<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mohamed_Salah">Mohamed Salah</ref>  30'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adam%20Lallanaa">Adam Lallanaa</ref>  30'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James%20Millner">James Millner</ref>  83'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emre%20Can">Emre Can</ref>  83'
</text>
