<text id="autogum_interview_doc012" title="part0_Wikinews attends 2018 Bangalore ComicCon" shortTile="partwikinews-attends" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2018-11-21" dateModified="2019-07-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_attends_2018_Bangalore_ComicCon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews attends 2018 Bangalore ComicCon</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 29, 2018</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Cosplayers cosplaying Marvel Cinematic Universe's Iron Man (left) and Spider-Man (right).Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Acagastya">Agastya</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>On November 17 and November 18, Wikinews attended the 2018 <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bangalore">Bangalore</ref> Comicbook Convention, in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Karnataka">Karnataka</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/India">India</ref>. Beginning on Saturday morning, the ComicCon continued till Sunday. Organised by ComicCon India, who organised Comic Con in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hyderabad,_India">Hyderabad</ref> in October, this event was held at Karnataka Trade Promotion Organisation (KTPO)'s convention hall. <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> spoke to convention's international guests Ryan O'Sullivan, Dan Watters, and Vanesa Del Ray.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UK">UK</ref>-based freelancer comicbook writer Ryan O'Sullivan, who has worked for Image Comics and Vault Comics, and wrote video game comics including <hi rend="italic">Eisenhorn</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Warhammer 40,000</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Dark Souls</hi>, was one of the guests attending ComicCon. Along with him, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/London">London</ref>-based freelance comic book writer Dan Watters was also one of the attendants. Watters has worked with Image Comics on <hi rend="italic">Limbo</hi>, as well as <hi rend="italic">Lucifer</hi> for Vertigo Comics. Watters has also written comics for <hi rend="italic">Assassin's Creed</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Wolfenstein</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Deep Roots</hi>. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Cuba">Cuban</ref> comic book artist Vanesa Del Rey was also one of the guest attendants, who has illustrated <hi rend="italic">Scarlet Witch</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Daredevil Annual</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Spider-Women Alpha</hi> for Marvel Comics; and <hi rend="italic">Redlands</hi> for Image Comics.</p>
<figure><caption>Cosplayer as Wonder Woman.Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Acagastya">Agastya</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>The convention started at 11 AM. Crossing between the genres of science fiction, horror, anime, fantasy and comics, the event sprawled throughout all corners of the facility. Marvel Zone, Amazon Video zone, AXN Live RED Special Session, Warner Bros' Aquaman and Fantastic Beasts: Crimes of Grindelwald experience, and Sony Pix zone attracted large number of audience.</p>
<p>On day two, Sumit Kumar, creator of Chin Chin, inspired by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chacha%20Chaudhary">Chacha Chaudhary</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Adventures%20of%20Tintin">Tintin</ref>, had a panel in the afternoon.</p>
<p>At 1:30 PM, there was a video presentation by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yali%20Dream%20Creations">Yali Dream Creations</ref>. The video was about <hi rend="italic">The Village</hi>. Yali Dream Creations' Shamik Das Gupta said the story of their comic <hi rend="italic">The Village</hi> is "supernatural, social, horror". Later, there was another presentation about their other comic, <hi rend="italic">Rakshak ((hi))Hindi language: ‍Protector — A Hero Among Us</hi>, about a masked vigilante in India. The first part of the four-part comic was released in 2016's Delhi ComicCon, Gupta said. Gupta also added "Delhi gang rape story pushed me". The session ended around 1:45 PM.</p>
<figure><caption>Rahil Mohin sketching during the launch.Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Acagastya">Agastya</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>After Yali Dream Creations, there was a comic launch by Rahil Mohin. Mohin had previously launched <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sufi%20Comics">Sufi Comics</ref> in 2008, <hi rend="italic">The Wise Fool of Baghdad</hi> and two comics about Persian poet Rumi and now <hi rend="italic">Blame it on Rahil</hi>. While he was on the panel, he was sketching cartoon, while the host was asking questions that Mohin had prepared, focused on the 90s cartoon themes. The questions were "[What was the] breed of Courage the Cowardly Dog?", "Catchphrase of Flintstone", and "Arch nemesis of Dexter". His session finished by 2 PM.</p>
</text>
