<text id="autogum_bio_doc029" title="Jim Hall (computer programmer)" shortTile="jim-hall-computer" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2003-12-16" dateModified="2019-09-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jim_Hall_%28computer_programmer%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Jim Hall (computer programmer)</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jim Hall</hi> (<hi rend="bold">James F. Hall</hi>) is a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer_programmer">computer programmer</ref> and advocate of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free_software">free software</ref>, best known for his work on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FreeDOS">FreeDOS</ref>. Hall began writing the free replacement for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MS-DOS">MS-DOS</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operating_system">operating system</ref> in 1994 when he was still a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Physics">physics</ref> student<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FLOSS-1">[1]</ref> at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Wisconsin-River_Falls">University of Wisconsin-River Falls</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Past-2">[2]</ref> He remains active with FreeDOS, and is currently the coordinator for the project.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-History-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Hall has said he created FreeDOS in response to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microsoft">Microsoft</ref> announcing end of support for MS-DOS in 1994,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FLOSS-1">[1]</ref> a year before <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Windows_95">Windows 95</ref> was released. As a user and fan of MS-DOS, Hall did not want the functionality of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DOS">DOS</ref> to go away. Prompted by a March 31, 1994 post on comp.os.msdos.misc asking if "anyone, for example <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNU">GNU</ref> et al. ever considered writing a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_Domain">Public Domain</ref> DOS",<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Valente_1994-4">[4]</ref> Hall decided to garner support for a free version of DOS, written under a free or public domain model.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Past-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-History-3">[3]</ref> In a June 29, 1994 post, Hall announced an effort to create a free DOS, called PD-DOS, writing:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Hall_1994_Announcement-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>A few months ago, I posted articles relating to starting a public domain version of DOS.  The general support for this at the time was ong, and many people agreed with the statement, "start writing!" So, I have …</p>
<p>Announcing the first effort to produce a PD-DOS. I have written up a "manifest" describing the goals of such a project and an outline of the work, as well as a "task list" that shows exactly what needs to be written. I'll post those here, and let discussion follow.</p>
<p>If you are thinking about developing, or have ideas or suggestions for PD-DOS, I would appreciate direct email to me. If you just want to discuss the merits or morals of writing a PD-DOS, I'll leave that to the net. I'll check in from time to time to see how the discussion is going, and maybe contribute a little to what promises to be a very polarized debate!:-&gt;</p>
<p>I am excited about PD-DOS, and I am hoping I can get a group started!</p>
<p>Within a few weeks, other programmers including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pat_Villani">Pat Villani</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tim_Norman">Tim Norman</ref> joined the project. A <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kernel_(computer_science)">kernel</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/COMMAND.COM">COMMAND.COM</ref> command line interpreter (shell) and core utilities were created by pooling code they had written or found available.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Past-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-History-3">[3]</ref> Hall wrote over a dozen of the first DOS utilities for the project, mostly file and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Batch_file">batch</ref> utilities. In a July 26, 1994 post, Hall announced the PD-DOS project had been renamed to "Free-DOS", having updated the project's goals to intend to distribute source code under the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNU_General_Public_License">GNU General Public License</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Hall_1994_Project-6">[6]</ref> The project would later be renamed "FreeDOS", without the hyphen, after the publication of <hi rend="italic">FreeDOS Kernel</hi>, by Pat Villani.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Villani_1996_Kernel-7">[7]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-History-3">[3]</ref> Hall was the project's release coordinator from Beta1 until about Beta7, and also released the first alpha <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_distro">distribution</ref> of Free-DOS, as announced in a post on comp.os.msdos.misc.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Hall_1994_Alpha-8">[8]</ref> He is again the project coordinator since April 2011 after Pat Villani's departure.</p>
<p>Hall is also the original developer of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNU_Robots">GNU Robots</ref>, but he is no longer active on this project and has since handed maintainership over to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tim_Northover">Tim Northover</ref>. It is now being developed by Bradley Smith.</p>
</text>
