<text id="autogum_reddit_doc143" title="[Serious] Urban Explorers of Reddit, what was the creepiest or most mysterious thing you’ve seen or found during your exploration?" shortTile="serious-urban-explorers" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-03-31" dateModified="2018-03-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/88jjy9" speakerList="#Rtux, #U_N_Owen1939, #olybib, #wooogirl" speakerCount="4">
<head>[Serious] Urban Explorers of Reddit, what was the creepiest or most mysterious thing you’ve seen or found during your exploration?</head>
<sp who="#Rtux">
<p>As a kid, me and friends used to freqent an old disused hospital on an airfield base from World War 2. There was a corridor we named mile long because it went on forever and at the end was the surgical room with all the metal tables and instruments still out. </p>
<p>We used to skateboard in the old gym there because the floor was wooden, but then one day someone had smashed all the windows and there was glass everywhere which put a stop to it. </p>
<p>If anyone wants to research about it, it's called Nocton Hospital.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#U_N_Owen1939">
<p>A while back, a friend took me back to the small country town he grew up in. We spent the day wandering around and exploring, mostly for lack of anything better to do, and ended up finding some weird shit. </p>
<p>We went into this abandoned house, and I think we may or may not have accidentally stumbled across the local devil worshippers’ lair. There were weird drawings on the walls, of supernatural creatures like topless mermaids with angry faces, and sort of hybrid creatures, and death threats scrawled with black paint. In a hallway, surrounded by four doors there was a massive hole in the floor, like a giant had take a big bite out of the floorboards. We couldn’t see what was down there; it was too dark. On the walls above the hole, things like “THERE IS NO ESCAPE” and “WE’RE GOING TO KILL YOU HERE” were painted. In the overgrown garden outside, there was a pentagram drawn on the concrete, half hidden by a rusted old car which was parked over it. My friend and I legged it when we heard voices coming.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#olybib">
<p>Me and some pals were hiking in the woods and we found an abandoned house. Looked to be abandoned in like the 70s or 80s. The door was opened and when we went in there was tons of books and Polaroids laying all over the floor. It looked like someone was In then process of moving out. When we checked out the polaroids, there were all of this couple that were together but they never looked happy. Also there was some really weird nude photos (weird as in they both looked super uncomfortable). Idk it creeped us out and just got the hell out. </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#wooogirl">
<p>Usually I just find one beer cans but as a kid I found huge jug of moonshine and brought it home not knowing was. I just like the vintage glass jug. He cleaned it out and let me keep it. Another time i lived in a house at the foot of a mountain and we had cows as neighbors. There was a big rock behind the house I was climbing around on and found several purses but there were pills, makeup, and just normal purse things in them. The weird thing is the id and credit cards were still there all different women. </p>
</sp>
</text>
