<text id="autogum_voyage_doc153" title="Delhi/Central Delhi" shortTile="delhicentral-delhi" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=154078" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Delhi/Central Delhi</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Central Delhi</hi> is a district in <ref target="Delhi">Delhi</ref>. The district contains (in its southern part) the historic core of Delhi, also known as <hi rend="bold">Old Delhi</hi>. The northern parts of the district were developed mainly during the days of British rule, and are known for their Raj era buildings and institutions. The most important attractions here are the <hi rend="bold">Red Fort</hi> and the <hi rend="bold">Jama Masjid</hi>.</p>

<head>By metro</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Yellow Line - <hi rend="bold">Chandni Chowk Station.</hi></item>
<item> Violet Line - <hi rend="bold">Jama Masjid Station</hi></item>
</list>


<head>By bus</head>
<p>Kashmere Gate is the major bus terminal in Delhi. There are buses to/from Kashmere that go to much of Northern India and <ref target="Nepal">Nepal</ref>.</p>

<head>Red Fort</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Red Fort</hi> (Lal Qila) (Lal Qila metro station (Violet Line)). is one of Delhi's top tourist sights and listed as a <ref target="UNESCO%20World%20Heritage%20Site">UNESCO World Heritage Site</ref>. A brilliant red sandstone fort built by the Mughal Emperor Shah Jahan (who also built <ref target="Agra">Agra</ref>'s Taj Mahal) as his ruling palace. Completed in 1648, the years since have not treated the buildings kindly: the rooms have long since been stripped of all objects, the marble inlays are long gone and quite a few buildings are off limits. Still, the scale remains imposing and the gardens are kept lush and green even in midwinter. The Red Fort buildings within include</item>
</list>

 


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Chatta Chowk</hi> (Covered Bazaar). True to the name, this is a covered bazaar between the gate and the fort itself, now filled with souvenir hawkers.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Diwan-i-Am</hi> (Hall of Public Audience). This building separates the outer court from the inner court, and has a marble platform for the emperor's throne.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hayat Bakhsh Bagh</hi> (Life-Bestowing Gardens). Once a grand garden of full of fountains and streams, now sadly all dry — only dry channels and acres of green grass remain. Near here will you find the Sawan Pavilion</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Diwan-i-Khas</hi> (Hall of Private Audience). Built completely of marble, this is where the emperor received special visitors.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Khas Mahal</hi> (Private Palace). The Emperor's main residence. The octagonal <hi rend="bold">Mussaman Burj</hi> tower looks out toward the Yamuna River, and is where the Emperor used to appear before the public for each morning.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Rang Mahal</hi> (Colour Palace). The residence of the Sultan's main wife.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mumtaz Mahal</hi> (Jewel Palace, Persian/Urdu ممتاز محل [mumˈt̪aːz mɛˈɦɛl]; meaning "beloved ornament of the palace"). Contained six apartments for the Sultan's harem. Now used as a museum of court textiles, carpets, weapons, etc. free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Daawat Khana</hi> (at the northmost end of the Fort). A minor palace, this was originally the residence of a prince, but it was converted into a tea house by the British, a function it continues today. Basic meals cost around ₹ 60, drinks ₹ 10-20, and it also has the cleanest toilets around.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Swatantra Sangrama Sangrahalaya</hi> (Museum of the Independence Movement). To the left after the Chatta Chowk, this is a reasonably well-presented museum on the history of independence activism in India, starting from the Mutiny of 1857 all the way to Gandhi.</item>
</list>



<p>The only open entrance is <hi rend="bold">Lahore Gate</hi>, on the west side. Security in and around the Fort is very heavy, as it was the scene of a terrorist attack in 2000 that killed three people. Bags are allowed, but they'll be X-rayed and you'll be patted down. Tickets cost ₹ 30/500 for Indians/foreigners, photography free, video cameras ₹ 25 extra. Open sunrise to sunset daily except Monday. Allow for 3-4 hr in your schedule in case of long weekends and national holidays as lot of tourists flock around then. The most scenic way of reaching the fort is to take the Metro to Chawri Bazaar and then a cycle-rickshaw through the incredibly packed bazaar to the Fort (price negotiable, aim for ₹ 20).</p>

<p>The fort has a <hi rend="bold">light and sound show</hi> (₹ 50) in the evenings from 19:30-21:00, depending on the season.</p>

<p>Be careful buying tickets at the booth, as the ticket sellers will attempt to shortchange you. Try to have a small bill. Due to enhanced security the parking can be a bit tricky as the walk from the now distanced away parking at nearby alternative slots is quite a bit. The congested traffic makes crossing the road even trickier.</p>
<head>Feroz Shah Kotla</head>
<p>Feroz Shah Kotla is the Delhi's cricket stadium. It also houses the ruins of the fifth city of Delhi Feroz Shah Kotla or Ferozabad. It was founded by Feroz Shah Tughlaq. The are also houses the notorious Khooni Darwaza.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Feroz Shah Kotla</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Khuni Darwaza</hi> (Bloody Gate), Bahadur Shah Zafar Road (Opposite Feroz Shah Kotla Palace. Metro: Delhi Gate (Violet)). It is here in this gate that Major William Hodson beheaded last Mughal ruler Bahadur Shah Zafar's sons Mirza Mughal and Mirza Khizr Sultan as well as grandson Mirza Abu Bakr after the defeat in Revolt of 1857 forcing him to go to Yangoon. It is also believed that the beheaded heads of criminals were put on display in this gate. Here Jahangir ordered the killing of two sons of Rahim Khan-I-Khana who was a Navaratna in Akbar's court.</item>
</list>


<head>Mahatma Gandhi sites</head>
<p>These three sites are located in close proximity, 5 minutes walk east of Delhi Gate metro station (Violet Line).</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Raj Ghat</hi>, Satyagraha Marg, Gandhi Smriti. 09:30-17:30. Memorial to Mahatma Gandhi at the site of his cremation. Check for closure dates/security checks around national holidays/Gandhi's death anniversary. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Gandhi Smriti</hi>, ☏ +91 11 2301 2843 . 10:00-17:00 (closed Monday). This estate is the site of Mahatma Gandhi's martyrdom. Includes a museum celebrating his life and the room he lived in during his final days.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">National Gandhi Museum</hi> (தேசிய காந்தி அருங்காட்சியகம்), Vikram Nagar.</item>
</list>
<head>Kamal Nehru Ridge (Delhi North Ridge)</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mutiny Memorial</hi> (Ajitgarh).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ashokan Pillar</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pir Ghaib</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hindu Rao Hospital Baoli</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Chauburja Mosque</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Southern Gurad House</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Flagstaff Tower</hi>, Kamla Nehru Ridge, Civil Lines New Delhi (Half km East of North Campus. Bus #212 stop 'University of Delhi' (300m west.). - Eastwards 300m to Vidhan Sabha Metro Station). It was built in 1828 as a signal tower. This one storey tower was used to take shelter for European people during Revolt of 1857. - The <hi rend="bold">Sankatmochan Hanuman Mandir</hi> is 100 m to the west.</item>
</list>
</text>
