<text id="autogum_reddit_doc040" title="Trying to narrow in on low BIAB efficiency issues" shortTile="trying-narrow-low" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-05-31" dateModified="2018-05-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8njvmh" speakerList="#blacklabel8829, #timberrrrrrrr" speakerCount="2">
<head>Trying to narrow in on low BIAB efficiency issues</head>
<sp who="#timberrrrrrrr">
<p>Hi! Done a few BIAB brews so far, all of them hitting right around 50% efficiency. Here are some of the details I figure are important: • I use Beersmith, and did the Brulosophy tutorial for setting up mash profile and equipment profile. All looks good there, and my water amounts seem correct (I end up with the right amount of wort at the end of the boil to put in the fermenter) • I use Portland, OR water. I am assured by the brew store people that our water is insanely good and mash PH is not an issue. • I do a full volume mash, and I insulate my pot. I lose about a degree over the hour. • Crush shouldn't be an issue. The brew store has an adjustable crusher and I've been setting it at .025 • I squeeze the bag real well, and jostle it around to make sure I'm really letting the trapped wort escape the bag. Plus, I'm hitting my water volumes based on Beersmith, so this doesn't seem to be an issue. As far as I can tell, the two things that I don't do right now are sparging and mashing out. I don't sparge because I'm trying to come up with a process where I can hit 70% without sparging, and it seems like everyone on here swears up and down that they don't sparge when BIAB and they hit well over 70%. As for mashing out, I haven't been doing that yet because I don't have a false bottom, but I am ordering one. Once I get it, I'll feel comfortable enough that I won't burn my bag in the bottom of my pot. Could sparging and mashing out really be the 20% difference here? I am at a loss, and throughout all of my searching in this sub, it seems like the #1 thing that everyone says is a problem is crush. But I _know_ my crush is good. Any advice is greatly appreciated! Thanks all!</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#blacklabel8829">
<p>Your process looks nearly the same as mine except two things. First, I've had my water tested by Ward Labs and use BruNWater to figure out what additions my water needs. Second, I give the grains a quick stir twice during the mash. </p>
<p> </p>
<p>I am able to consistently hit the high 70s, occasionally the 80s.</p>
</sp>
</text>
