<text id="autogum_academic_doc444" title="Silicon and Plant Natural Defenses against Insect Pests: Impact on Plant Volatile Organic Compounds and Cascade Effects on Multitrophic Interactions" shortTile="silicon-plant-natural" author="Nicolas Leroy, Félix de Tombeur, Yseult Walgraffe, Jean-Thomas Cornélis, François  J. Verheggen" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2223-7747/8/11/444/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Soil and Climate Control Si Accumulation in Plants</head>
<p>
Although phylogenetic variation explains most of the highly contrasted Si concentrations in terrestrial plants, the environmental factors are key for understanding intra-specific variation. In soils, Si is available for micro-organisms and plants as uncharged monomeric monosilicic acid, H4SiO4, at common soil pH values. Its concentration in soil solution generally ranges from 0.1 to 0.6 mM. Nevertheless, variations of two orders of magnitude have been reported in literature (from 1 to more than 100 mg of Si per kg of soil in CaCl2-extractable solution). Such differences are mainly governed by soil mineralogy. Indeed, the concentration of plant-available Si decreases with increasing soil weathering degree and decreasing pH, given soil desilicification. Nevertheless, it has been recently highlighted that alkaline pH lead to a decrease of plant-available Si given increasing adsorption of Si on soil mineral surfaces. Soil pH is thence a key driver of Si plant-availability. Besides, the magnitude of Si biocycling in soil-plant systems and the resulting amount of phytoliths returned on topsoil also play a key role in the replenishment of Si in soil solution. An integrated understanding of Si mobility in soil-plant systems is therefore essential for optimizing Si benefits in terms of plant protection. </p>

<p>Climate also plays a key role in Si accumulation by plants, mainly through soil water availability and plant evapotranspiration. Ryalls et al. showed that plant Si concentration increases in roots and shoots under elevated rainfall, and thence soil moisture, in <hi rend="italic">Microlaena stipoides</hi> Robert Brown. Quigley &amp; Anderson made the same observation in <hi rend="italic">Themeda triandra</hi> Forsskål. Jenkins et al. showed that the number of silicified cells per phytoliths increased with irrigation. Si uptake is thence largely dependent on soil moisture. Besides soil water availability, the rate of plant evapotranspiration—driven by net irradiance, air density, air heat capacity, vapor pressure deficit and latent heat of vaporization among others-also controls plant Si uptake and concentrations. As a result, Henriet et al. showed that Si concentration in different shoot organs of banana plants was directly related to its transpiration rate. Cornélis et al. attributed the higher Si uptake by Douglas fir leaves compared to Black pine leaves to a higher transpiration rate and Euliss et al. showed that the leaf Si concentration of different grasses and wetland species was directly linked to its transpiration rate. Field studies showed that Si uptake increases under drought stress as a defense mechanism. Fulweiler et al. observed that anthropogenic changes (elevated atmospheric CO2 concentrations) may increase biological Si pumping in forest. Climatic variable (air temperature, CO2 concentrations) and pedoclimatic variable (soil water content) are therefore two key properties that must be integrated for better understanding of Si accumulation in plants. </p>

<p>Understanding the drivers of Si accumulation as a natural plant defense is key because seven of the top 10 most widespread crops in the world are Si-accumulating Poaceae species, especially in the face of expected climate changes and the lack of resilience of conventional agriculture. Sugarcane crops are concentrated in India, Brazil, China and the Caribbean Islands under tropical/subtropical climate where highly weathered soils lead to low Si plant-availability. In contrast, wheat and barley crops are concentrated in the United States, Europe, Canada and on drier areas of China and India (compared to sugarcane), at more temperate climate. In this environment, soils are less desilicated, leading to higher Si plant-availability. The climate variables in tropical and temperate agro-ecosystems will also strongly affect Si accumulation in plants through very contrasting air temperature and soil water content. The natural ability of plants to accumulate Si is therefore highly variable at the global scale, and far from being understood. </p>
</text>
