<text id="autogum_interview_doc255" title="part1_Wikinews interviews English mathematician Marcus du Sautoy" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-24" dateModified="2010-08-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_English_mathematician_Marcus_du_Sautoy" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">How do you explain the success of your book <hi rend="italic">The Music of the Primes</hi></hi>?</p>
<p>Well, I think people love stories, and I tried to write that book rather like a murder mystery. I really think that solving a mathematical puzzle is a little bit like trying to find who done it in a murder mystery. And I tried to keep that narrative line very strong in the book, so people read it like a novel, and I think a lot of people have said that it does read in that way. You actually do not find out who done it in the end because it is an open problem. So for me in a novel it is important to have a good narrative structure which the mathematics provided, but the people as well, that was important to me, to bring the people alive who did the maths. Even if people do not get the maths, they enjoy the stories about the people, the period of history that is being talked about and they can still follow the paths of mathematical narrative even if they do not get the details so I  that is why it was so successful.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">And what about your last book <hi rend="italic">Finding Moonshine</hi>?</hi></p>
<p>This is a slightly more challenging writing project for me, because it combine both historical story on symmetry with a personal story of what I do as a mathematician. It is divided into twelve chapters each one a month in a year of me being a mathematician. As I tried to combine what I do - I think people find deeply mysterious what a mathematician does all day - so I tried to give people a little bit of access to the world that I live in. But you are seeing also some historical story, a bit like The Music of the Primes but looking at symmetry instead.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you think of the Italian title, <hi rend="italic">Il disordine perfetto</hi> ("The perfect disorder")?</hi></p>
<p>My editor chose the title and I really love it actually. In England it is called <hi rend="italic">Finding Moonshine</hi> because it's a quote from  a play that I love, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A%20Midsummer%20Night's%20Dream">A Midsummer Night's Dream</ref></hi> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William%20Shakespeare">Shakespeare</ref>, and also there is a mathematical idea, something called <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monstrous%20moonshine">moonshine</ref> which is the climax of the book. And the Italian title I rather like because it what that sums up that tension in mathematics between everything looking so disordered and chaotic and yet so perfect because it just has to be like that. So I think it really is a title that catches the beautiful tension in mathematics between things with a lot structure yet with complexity.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Do you know <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia">Wikipedia</ref>? What do you think of it?</hi></p>
<p>My impression is that science in Wikipedia has an incredible high standard. And I think it is scientists of different levels - senior, junior - taking their time to record things on Wikipedia. Early on there was a lot of mistrust about how accurate something created by the public for the public could be. But I think the evidence is that in mathematics and science it has an incredibly high standard. I really think it's incredible valuable tool for people exploring mathematical ideas. When I get questions from general readers about some of a little bit more technical side of - say - things about primes it'll be either Wikipedia, that I would refer them to for some more details or another (right good) website which has great mathematical material which is Wolfram Creative Mathematica have a very good encyclopaedic resource for mathematics. That is slightly more technical maybe than Wikipedia. They together I think do a great service.</p>
</text>
