<text id="autogum_bio_doc255" title="Kameʻeiamoku" shortTile="kameeiamoku" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-11" dateModified="2019-07-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kame%CA%BBeiamoku" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Kameʻeiamoku</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Kameʻeiamoku</hi> (died 1802) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Native_Hawaiian">Hawaiian</ref> high chief and the Counselor of State to King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kamehameha_I">Kamehameha I</ref>. He was called Kamehameha's uncle, but he was really the cousin of Kamehameha's mother, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kekuiapoiwa_II">Kekuiapoiwa II</ref>.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<head>Family</head>
<p>Along with his twin brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kamanawa">Kamanawa</ref>, Kameʻeiamoku's father was the aliʻi (Hawaiian nobility) <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keawepoepoe">Keawepoepoe</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> His mother was Kanoena, also Keawepoepoe's sister. Because their parents were siblings, Kameʻeiamoku and Kamanawa were known as <hi rend="italic">nīʻaupiʻo</hi>, the offspring of a royal brother and sister.</p>
<p>His grandmother was Princess <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kalanikauleleiaiwi">Kalanikauleleiaiwi</ref> of Hawaiʻi, who was also the grandmother of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keōua">Keōua Nui</ref> (Kamehameha's father), making the twins cousins once removed of Kamehameha. Kameʻeiamoku was among the first to support Kamehameha I in his rebellion against his cousin <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kīwalaʻō">Kīwalaʻō</ref>; his fellow supporters were his brother Kamanawa, his half brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keeaumoku_Pāpaiahiahi">Keʻeaumoku Pāpaʻiahiahi</ref>, Kamehameha's warrior teacher Kekūhaupiʻo, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keawe-a-Heulu">Keawe-a-Heulu</ref>. These were known as the "five Kona chiefs". Kamehameha took power in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Moku'ohai">battle of Mokuʻōhai</ref> in 1782, which strengthened his influence.</p>
<p>In 1790, the American <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maritime_Fur_Trade">maritime fur trader</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simon_Metcalfe">Simon Metcalfe</ref> of the ship <hi rend="italic">Eleanora</hi> mistreated Kameʻeiamoku when he boarded his ship. Metcalfe later fired his cannons on the villagers of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Olowalu,_Hawaii">Olowalu</ref>, killing about one hundred. In retaliation, Kameʻeiamoku attacked the next American ship to appear, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schooner">schooner</ref> <hi rend="italic">Fair American</hi>, under the command of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Humphrey_Metcalfe">Thomas Humphrey Metcalfe</ref>, the son of Simon Metcalfe. All but one of the schooner's crew was killed, including Thomas Humphrey Metcalfe. The lone survivor was Welsh sailor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isaac_Davis_(Hawaii)">Isaac Davis</ref>. Another sailor from the <hi rend="italic">Eleanora</hi>, Englishman <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Young_(Hawaii)">John Young</ref>, was sent ashore to find out what happened, and was also captured. Davis and Young would both become military advisors and translators for Kamehameha.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Kameʻeiamoku participated in negotiating a treaty in February 1795 with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Vancouver">George Vancouver</ref> for British support of Kamehameha.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-vancouver-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Kameʻeiamoku had three or four wives and at least three sons. His first wife, Kamakaʻeheikuli, was the mother of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kepookalani">Kepoʻokalani</ref> (c. 1760–?) who was the double great-grandfather of the last two monarchs of the Kingdom. His second wife Kealiʻiokahekili was the mother of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hoapili">Ulumāheihei Hoapili</ref> (c. 1776–1840). His third wife Kahikoloa was mother of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hoolulu">Hoʻolulu</ref> (1794–?).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> Kameʻeiamoku's descendants succeeded him in assisting Kamehameha after his death in 1802 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lahaina,_Hawaii">Lahaina</ref> on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maui">Maui</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-punahou-6">[6]</ref></p>
<head>Legacy</head>
<p>Through his son Kepoʻokalani came the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Kalākaua">House of Kalākaua</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> One of his other sons Hoʻolulu would be the father of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kinooleoliliha">Kinoʻole o Liliha</ref> who married the notable American businessman <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benjamin_Pitman_(Hawaii)">Benjamin Pitman</ref>. Daughter <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kekikipaa">Kekikipaa</ref> would marry Kamehameha I, but then marry <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keawemauhili">Keawemauhili</ref> and become the mother of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chiefess_Kapiolani">High Chiefess Kapiʻolani</ref>.</p>
<p>He lives on the coat of arms of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Hawaii">Kingdom of Hawaii</ref>. On each side of the coat of arms was the figure of a chief in a feather cloak and a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahiole">feather helmet</ref>. The one on the left, bearing a spear, was Kamanawa and the one on the right, with a <hi rend="italic">Kahili</hi> (feather standard), was Kameʻeiamoku.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref>
The land he was given in 1795 was used by his granddaughter <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kuini_Liliha">Kuini Liliha</ref>, who donated it to Christian missionaries. It eventually became <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Punahou_School">Punahou School</ref> in 1841.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-punahou-6">[6]</ref></p>
</text>
