<text id="autogum_interview_doc397" title="part10_The Raveonettes on love, death, desire and war" shortTile="partthe-raveonettes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-16" dateModified="2010-12-23" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Raveonettes_on_love%2C_death%2C_desire_and_war" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Chuckles</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  But we don't think about it right now because now we are really excited about the new album coming out.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  I could see it go many ways.  I have a difficult time seeing myself touring when I'm 55 years old; I probably wouldn't want to do that.  Not the way I do it now, at least.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You couldn't imagine being <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/867-5309/Jenny">867-5309</ref> guy?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  Yeah, it is difficult to see myself as a grandmother on stage.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are there venues that you guys haven't played that is your dream venue?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Madison%20Square%20Garden">Madison Square Garden</ref>!  I always really, really want to play that as a headliner.  That would be really great, I think.  The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hollywood%20Bowl">Hollywood Bowl</ref> would be really amazing.  There's some good places.  And we were lucky enough to play the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wembley%20Stadium">Wembley Arena</ref> once, but the only thing that happened was they put us on the program at the wrong time, so we actually had to go on before the doors even opened!  We actually ended up playing for <hi rend="italic">four</hi> people in this <hi rend="italic">big</hi> arena: our producer, his wife and a few of our friends.  It was really cool; we enjoyed it.  At least we played there. And then halfway through the set they actually <hi rend="italic">opened</hi> the doors and people started coming in so in the end we maybe played for a few thousand.  But we liked it.  It was like a dream come true.  We always wanted to play Wembley Arena!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  For no one! [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  You made it!</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  It was a really good show, actually.  It was fun.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you have a venue, Sharin?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  Yeah, like Sune was saying, Madison Square Garden would definitely be something very...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  If Jay-Z can do it, we can too!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are there any bands you guys would love to play with?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Rolling%20Stones">The Rolling Stones</ref>.  Yeah, that would be really great.  I always wanted to tour with Primal Scream.  That would be one.  I don't know...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  I would like to open for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bob%20Dylan">Bob Dylan</ref>, but I would be a little scared of meeting him, I think.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  I don't know.  He would be intimidating.  <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dont%20Look%20Back">Dont Look Back</ref></hi> - have you seen that?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are you more worried about him being intimidating or disappointing?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  I would worry about him being disappointing.  I would worry about him being--which I have heard that he is--pretty grumpy; mean.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  That can happen!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  Too smart.</p>
<head id="On_metaphysics">On metaphysics</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you believe in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Higher%20power">higher power</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  Sometimes I do.  Sometimes I feel more connected.  I do sort of believe in a higher power in a very scientific way; I believe in the fourth dimension and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Time%20travel">time travel</ref>...</p>
</text>
