<text id="autogum_bio_doc497" title="Aleksander Korwin Gosiewski" shortTile="aleksander-korwin" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2004-12-23" dateModified="2019-10-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aleksander_Korwin_Gosiewski" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Aleksander Korwin Gosiewski</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Aleksander Korwin Gosiewski</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lithuanian_language">Lithuanian</ref>: <hi lang="lt" rend="italic">Aleksandras Korvinas Gosievskis</hi>)  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Armiger"><hi rend="italic">de armis</hi></ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ślepowron_coat_of_arms">Ślepowron</ref> (b. – d. 1639), was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Szlachta">Polish nobleman</ref>, military <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Commander">commander</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diplomat">diplomat</ref>, Lithuanian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Offices_in_the_Polish–Lithuanian_Commonwealth">Field-Quartermaster</ref> since 1630, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Voivode">Palatine-Governor</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smolensk_Voivodeship">Smolensk</ref> from 1625, Lithuanian Great-Quartermaster since 1615, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marshal_of_the_Sejm">Speaker of the Parliament</ref> in 1613, Great-Secretary of the Grand Duchy of Lithuania from 1610 and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Starosta">District-Governor</ref> of Wieliż, Puńsk, Kupise, Biel, and Markowa.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<head>Youth</head>
<p>He came from the noble family Gosiewski of Zambrowski county in the land of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Łomża">Łomża</ref>, a family entitled to use the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coat_of_arms">coat of arms</ref> Ślepowron. He lived in the first half of the 16th century, son of John Gosiewski who was married to Ewa (<hi rend="italic">née</hi> Pac, the Chamberlain of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brest,_Belarus">Brest</ref>’s daughter).</p>
<p>Already in his youth, as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lew_Sapieha">Lew Sapieha</ref>’s courtier, was involved in the affairs of the state. In 1600, as member of Lew Sapieha's retinue, he played a significant role in the negotiations with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russia">Moscovia</ref>, editing the planned alliance acts between Poland-Lithuania with the Muscovite state. In 1602, even as District-Governor of Wieliż, attended the drawing of the border between Poland-Lithuania and Moscovia – he became famous repelling a Russian troops attack on his own district. Then, during the wars of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sigismund_III_Vasa">Sigismund III Vasa</ref> against his uncle <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_IX_of_Sweden">Charles</ref>, the usurper King of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sweden">Sweden</ref>, he served in the Lithuanian army. In 1605, he fought in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Kircholm">Battle of Kircholm</ref>. In 1606, as a member of the retinue of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mikołaj_Oleśnicki">Mikołaj Oleśnicki</ref>, he escorted <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marina_Mniszech">Maryna Mniszchówna</ref> to Moscow, where he led negotiations for an alliance with Tsar <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/False_Dmitriy_I">Dmitri</ref>.</p>
<head>Military career</head>
<figure><caption>Aleksander Korwin Gosiewski, Grand Envoy of the Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth holding the letters of credence to Tsar <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/False_Dmitriy_I">Dimitry Ivanovich the Pretender</ref></caption></figure>
<p>He was an ardent supporter of Polish military intervention in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moscow">Moscow</ref> during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Time_of_Troubles">time of Troubles</ref>. In July 1609, he conducted his own expedition to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wielkie_Łuki">Wielkie Łuki</ref>. Then he became famous for planting firecrackers to the walls of the fortress during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siege_of_Smolensk_(1609–1611)">siege of Smolensk</ref>. In 1610 at the head of a sizeable branch of the military operation conducted independently in the north of Smolensk, which was to get <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bely,_Tver_Oblast">Bely</ref> fortress. Subsequently, he reached Moscow, which, after the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Klushino">battle of Klushino</ref> was taking by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hetman">Great-Commander</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stanisław_Żółkiewski">Stanisław Żółkiewski</ref> <hi rend="italic">de armis</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lubicz_coat_of_arms">Lubicz</ref>. In 1610, he was appointing by Commander Żółkiewski to lead the Polish army commander of the Moscow <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kremlin">Kremlin</ref>. In 1611 the Russians betrayal their old Polish patrons, at the head of a branch off insurrected led to the great fire of Moscow. In the year 1612 over the command of the Polish garrison <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mikołaj_Struś">Mikołaj Struś</ref> <hi rend="italic">de armis</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Korczak_coat_of_arms">Korczak</ref> and returned to Lithuania. Residents of the city under the leadership of a merchant <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kuzma_Minin">Kuzma Minin</ref> and Prince <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dmitry_Pozharsky">Dmitry Pozharsky</ref> began to lock the Kremlin. The commander of the Polish garrison in the Kremlin, Mikołaj Struś, deprived of relief from the Polish king Sigismund III Vasa, surrendered on 4 November 1612. To commemorate the event tsar <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mikhail_Romanov">Mikhail Romanov</ref> instituted a holiday named <hi rend="italic">Day of Moscow’s Liberation from Polish Invaders</hi> in 1613, in 2004 the public holiday became the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unity_Day_(Russia)">Unity Day</ref>, which was first celebrated in 2005.</p>
<p>In 1612, the Polish garrison commander at Smolensk fending off all these years numerous attacks of the Russian troops. In 1615, as Lithuanian Field-Quartermaster, he led a small army to block the insurrected Russian army. In 1617 and 1618, Polish Lithuanian troops participated in a failed expedition to Moscow led by Prince <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Władysław_IV_Vasa">Wladyslaw</ref>. In 1618, he commanded the garrison during the siege of Smolensk. After the arriving of the king's troops he camped together with the Commander <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jan_Karol_Chodkiewicz">Jan Karol Chodkiewicz</ref>’ troops besieging the city (Chodkiewicz <hi rend="italic">de armis</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chodkiewicz_coat_of_arms">Kościesza</ref>.</p>
<head>Politics</head>
<figure><caption>Tomb of Aleksander's son Wincenty Korwin Gosiewski</caption></figure>
<p>He was the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marshal_of_the_Sejm">Speaker of the Parliament</ref> extraordinary held in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Warsaw">Warsaw</ref> on 3 December to 24 December 1613. During the war with Sweden (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polish–Swedish_War_(1621–1625)">1621–1625 war</ref>) and the (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polish–Swedish_War_(1626–1629)">war 1626–1629</ref>) fought in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Livonia">Livonia</ref> winning to the Swedish army at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Kroppenhof">Kroppenhof</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lixna">Lixna</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slavskoye,_Russia">Slavskoye</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dyneburg">Dyneburg</ref>. It is because of fighting with the Swedes until 1629, he was appointing Palatine-Governor of Smolensk region, but the nomination was already in 1625. Seeing the threat from Russia, Gosiewski immediately upon taking the governorate of Smolensk began to renovate the walls of the city. He personally oversaw the construction of Sigismund Fortress, which strengthened the eastern part of the stronghold. Intensively collected supplies of food and ammunition, and developed a business intelligence gathering valuable information about Moscow's war preparations. In the spring of 1632, he made review the fortifications in Dorogobuzh and other frontier forts.</p>
<p>During the war with Russia, in the year 1632 and 1634 after a particularly famous defense of Smolensk – for ten months he defended the city against besieging forces led by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mikhail_Shein">Mikhail Shein</ref>, repelling all assaults, until the advent of the battle led by Prince Władysław. He fought at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vitebsk">Vitebsk</ref>, Alder and Mstislav. He participated as a Commissioner in peace negotiations, topped the conclusion on 14 June 1634, in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treaty_of_Polanów">Treaty of Polanów</ref>.</p>
<p>For his services, he received numerous goods in the province of Smolensk. He founded the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesuit">Jesuits</ref>’ College in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vitebsk">Vitebsk</ref> and the female Monastery of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brigit_of_Kildare">Holy Brigit</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brest-Litovsk">Brest-Litovsk</ref>.
As Palatine-Governor, he commemorated the death of his longtime client – <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jan_Kunowski">Jan Kunowski</ref>, who in 1640 wrote a series of poems dedicated to his late patron.</p>
<head>Death</head>
<p>He died in April 1639.</p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>Aleksander Korwin Gosiewski came from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gosiewski_(Ślepowron)">Ślepowron branch of the family</ref>.</p>
<p>He was married to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ewa_Pac">Ewa Pac</ref>. They had one daughter, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zuzanna_Korwin_Gosiewska">Zuzanna</ref>, and two sons; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wincenty_Korwin_Gosiewski">Wincenty</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Krzysztof_Korwin_Gosiewski">Krzysztof</ref>.</p>
<head>References and sources</head>
<p>This new article is a roughly translation after Polish Wikipedia, version 12 March 2013.</p>
</text>
