<text id="autogum_whow_doc192" title="Be an Organized Parent" shortTile="organized-parent" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-04-22" dateModified="2019-07-27" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be-an-Organized-Parent" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be an Organized Parent</head>Being a parent is hard, and keeping everything tidy and organized on top of that can be very stressful, so read below for advice on how to be an organized parent.
<head>Steps</head>
<head>At Home</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><figure rend="Have a Daily Routine Step 1.jpg"></figure> Make a routine. Having a routine can really help keep everything organized and promote things to run smoothly throughout the day. Brainstorm on a piece of paper with your children about all the things you need/like to do throughout the day. then write it up a big sheet of paper and decorate it with your kids if you want then put it somewhere everyone can see like the fridge door or up on the wall in the living room. You can have a test run of it in the weekend to see how it works, if you find something wrong with it then fix it. it might take a bit of getting used to with your child/children so don't forget to remind them if they seem to have forgotten something in the routine.
<list type="unordered"><item>You can also make a weekend routine or just do what you want on weekends</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Decide on Age Appropriate Chores for Your Child Step 2 Version 3.jpg"></figure> Assign chores to everyone in the household. Younger children shouldn't be given hard chores like washing the dishes or mowing the lawn, instead give them simple chores like putting away their toys or putting away their clean laundry. if they want to do "big kid chores" just give them a bit of help. for older children they can have a little harder jobs, you should also encourage older children to help their younger siblings. you should also offer your child/children a reward for participating in chores, most of the time parents offer pocket money which is a good idea but you can also offer a new toy, an outing at the end of the week, a special dinner, etc. if your children don't do their chores or forget about them then they won't receive their reward. if your kids aren't accustomed to doing chores it might take them a bit of getting used to, but be patient. Writing up a chore chart is helpful.</item>
<item><figure rend="Be Clean Step 9.jpg"></figure> Keep the house tidy and organized. Make a special place for everything and make sure it's always returned to that spot after being used. Don't let mold grow and dust things every once in a while. if you need to buy baskets or boxes to put things in, do so, you can put labels on them so you know where to put things in what, for example, you can have labels such as "pens and pencils basket" or "silverware drawer". You can also do a fun project with your kids and make your own storage containers.</item>
<item><figure rend="Cook With Your Kids Step 2.jpg"></figure> Cook meals beforehand if you have a busy schedule. If you have quite a busy day to day life you might benefit from cooking up meals in bulk and storing them in the freezer to reheat at dinner or lunch or whenever. you can also involve your children in cooking, let them choose something they like from a recipe book and help them make it.
<list type="unordered"><item>Avoid buying frozen meals or ordering takeaways too often, they aren't always the healthiest option and too much can lead to your children becoming overweight and unhealthy.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Make Your Children Go to Bed Earlier Step 13.jpg"></figure> Make a set bedtime for your children. Having a regular bedtime can benefit you and your child/children. it helps your child form a good sleeping pattern and have enough energy for the day and school. it should leave enough time between their bedtime and yours so that you (and your partner if you have one) can have some time to yourself/yourselves. for 7 and under a time around 7 and 8 pm works, for over 8 somewhere between 8 and 9 pm and for children over 12 between 9 and 10.</item>
<item><figure rend="Go to Bed on Time Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure> Have your own bedtime. You need proper sleep as well as your children so you can be a good and organized parent and be ready for your children's' energy from day to day. Adults need 8 hours of sleep each night so try to fit that in. If you don't get enough sleep, you won't be much help for your kids or spouse! Once your children are in bed, focus on winding yourself down for sleep. have an herbal tea, read, have a hot bath, and avoid going on technology before bed and this can stimulate you and prevent you from sleeping.</item>
<item><figure rend="Make a School Lunch Step 3 Version 3.jpg"></figure> Pack children's lunches the night before each school day. If your child doesn't eat food from the cafeteria (unhealthy!) you should pack their lunch the night before. many people choose to do it in the morning but that can just add more things to do when its already a busy time. Pack a healthy but filling lunch for your children. You don't always have to pack a sandwich; get creative, maybe pack some sushi or some leftover dinner. your children can always help out with buying and making their lunch.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Talk to your partner or a close friend/family member if you ever feel stressed or depressed. They might be able to watch the kids and give you a day off as well.</item>
<item>If you have money and you need a bit of help you can hire a maid/babysitter.</item>
<item>If you are stressed and tense your children will pick up on it and feel that way too, so your well-being benefits their well-being.</item>
<item>Getting colored bins can help significantly to enable you to remember which bin is for what. For example, a yellow bin is for the kids' toys, etc..</item></list>
</text>
