<text id="autogum_reddit_doc024" title="Guidance on becoming an Electrician" shortTile="guidance-becoming" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-05-31" dateModified="2018-05-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8nkx8o" speakerList="#Azothian, #oly_oly" speakerCount="2">
<head>Guidance on becoming an Electrician</head>
<sp who="#Azothian">
<p>I am currently 20 and live with my grandmother. Since I was little she has wanted me to go to college and be her prodigy child she never had (or at least that is what it feels like). For reason not relevant to this post (particularly money) , I cannot fulfill this dream of hers of me completing my Master's degree in some STEM Program. Even without the hold-up, I would much rather do a trade and I have a particular interest in being an electrician. She seemed okay with it ,but is now putting me down and making me worried. To start, she keeps bringing up the possibility of me being raped. I am very upset by her even bringing it this up and I do not know how to convince her that this won't happen. Now her issue is transportation. I just applied for IBEW's Inside Electrical Track. I live in Maryland and she is insisting that they will have me job sites possibly hours away from my home. She believes that my car is not reliable enough for this. I mean...will they put me far away? Can I take some on my classes at my community college's trade school? Will I be being paid enough to get a better car? My car really is not that bad off, however it is almost at 150,000 miles. I guess I just want some opinions from people who have been through it.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#oly_oly">
<p>Both the other commenters are super right and i agree 100%, i just want to add a few things in case you're worried about the things she's bringing up, since i basically was you (currently 2nd year inside app, in the bay area): </p>
<p>1. I personally feel very safe at work. It's still a professional environment, even if it is a very casual one. it is like, 99% men, that's true, but the sites tend to be busy, your coworkers are usually around, there's lots of supervisors from all companies safety people office people inspectors, so it's not a lawless free-for-all feeling. It feels structured, which to me, makes me feel safe at work. </p>
<p>2. Far away sites: I don't know if your local is different, but this is an excellent question you can ask! Just google local # ibew hall (i don't know your number for your area) and ask where your jobsites would be - are they in one particular county only? The ones around me specify you can only work in your one county (doesn't matter where you live - if i live in San Francisco county, but apply and get accepted to San Mateo county, my work will always be in san mateo county). A very valid question for your hall! </p>
<p>3. The classes - i'm not super sure what this means. For us, we have classes at our JATC (the school for the program, joint apprenticeship training committee) and they are mandatory, scheduled for us, and only taken there. it's affiliated with the community college nearby , to get us credits i think, but we never do anything there or with the school teachers etc. it's just a way to get credit towards a AA or something (sorry i'm not super familiar with it all!) </p>
<p>4. Pay - another thing you can ask is about the pay scale! Or it'll be on the website, on the 'where when to apply' flyer. You start at a certain percentage of full wages, and work your way up. </p>
<p>Overall, it's not as scary as it seems! It's a big undertaking but you can really adapt well and I've found people to be very happy to teach an admitted beginner who has a good attitude and is determined to learn. </p>
<p>You'll be great!!! Don't worry!! </p>
</sp>
</text>
