<text id="autogum_reddit_doc022" title="[TFRP] Cops &amp; the balance recently need to be discussed." shortTile="tfrp-cops--balance" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-05-31" dateModified="2018-05-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8nmsij" speakerList="#DaBombDiggidy, #onemellowguy" speakerCount="2">
<head>[TFRP] Cops &amp; the balance recently need to be discussed.</head>
<sp who="#DaBombDiggidy">
<p>The in game balance has been a bit bull shit lately to say the least. I can't speak to the streamers playing criminals, but as a viewer and donator this has been a more then a bit off putting lately. - First = What happens in an LEO's eyes goes, even if it's desync. Today Gambino was given the 9's by dazzler because 3x manslaughter of AI while fleeing and assault on an LEO for hitting his bike (even though the bike was behind the car). None of that stuff happened in gambino's eyes or was his intent. It was 100% a desync issue and thad knew this, but if it happens on the LEO's screen that's what goes. That's not to mention dazzler shot gambino in the back multiple times even though he didn't have a gun (but announced on the radio he did) &lt; never any ramifications for this stuff. edit: for my first point, comments have kind of changed my mind. Not that desync shouldn't be a thing (if abused that's bannable) but that this may have been an in RP thing by thad. Appreciate the discussion everyone. - Second = Cops get to choose when killing AI has weight. If a criminal kills AI during a 1080 = you're in a hold until court. If a cop kills AI during a 1080 "whoops, god damn it why did you get in my way?!?" Cops kill easily 10x more AI than criminals so it's BS they get to basically choose what kind of RP goes. - Third = Cops get to create $ charges for things on the fly. People have been getting downed a lot at the skate park, it's harmless fun for those out there and has been a good hub for starting RP. It was too many calls so they instituted a 1,100 charge to get revived. Keep in mind money isn't easy on the server. - Fourth = Investigation RP. There is merit to cops doing investigations but getting to a point that cops are camping the chop shop and driving in/walking in by themselves "just to check" is dumb. What kind of realistic RP is it for a cop to solo camp a location with known violent and armed criminals? - Fifth = vehicle balance. The chopper and bike are OP. Sanchez RP has died down there's no reason they need those things to chase down cars that are already slower and less durable than their cop cars. Both vehicles should be taken out in response to special circumstances IMO and only then. - Sixth = I don't know if penta was joking but apparently his DOC character got fired for hitting Iceman with a baton while actively assaulting wrangler > he perma'ed. - Seventh = wtf is up with if you kill an AI in 1st or 2nd degree you're going to court? that shits dumb and not fun to watch. If it's the crims intent to kill peds sure but cops, most of all, should know how they act sometimes. This court stuff should be 99% a result of PvP interaction. ~~While this is about "realistic RP" I think were inching to a point where some cops are only focused on winning rather than RPing with their "family". Shit like this may be why you're only seeing 10-15 people on and half of those being cops.~~ edit: think this was more of a reaction, my bad, but it really does seem like less people are interested in civ/crim rp lately as cops are typically always full but the other side has been bare outside of the usual. - extra credit : Eighth = theres a new rule that you must announce you have a weapon on you, even before you are asked. Multiple people have been reprimanded for not stating they had a weapon on them before even being searched/asked.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#onemellowguy">
<p>First = far as the whole Gambino thing I honestly believe all of that was Dazzler getting back at Gambino for killing Wrath and fucking with the 1%. In story Dazzler is a corrupt cop and I think he lied about Gambino having a gun so he could shot him, so its all part of the story(just a theory). </p>
<p>Second = Agreed </p>
<p>Third = Thats more EMS than cops and agreed to a certain extent however from EMS perspective I would hate having to go to the skate park every two minutes </p>
<p>Fourth = Let's be real, with that many people stealing and chopping cars it wasn't gonna last long. Not to mention the cops already knew about the location cause Surfer dude told them. </p>
<p>Fifth = Kinda agree to an extent </p>
<p>Sixth = Don't care enough to comment </p>
<p>Seventh = Agreed unless killing AI is part of someone's story(ie Chief's Adrian character). </p>
<p>Eighth = You really think they are going to enforce that rule. The only cop I've heard bring it up is Katie. </p>
</sp>
</text>
