<text id="autogum_academic_doc424" title="Improving the Accuracy of Fine-Grained Population Mapping Using Population-Sensitive POIs" shortTile="improving-accuracy" author="Yuncong Zhao, Qiangzi Li, Yuan Zhang, Xin Du" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-4292/11/21/2502/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Results and Analysis</head><head> 4.1. Population-Sensitive POI Categories</head>
<p>
The PSP categories were selected by spatial association rule mining (see Section 3.1), which has a strong spatial association with the population hotspots extracted from Easygo heat map data. The two parameters of the spatial association rules between the POI categories and the population hotspots are shown in Table 3. Various categories had significant differences in the support and confidence of the association rule between the population hotspots and the POI categories. A total of 3092 hotspots were extracted to establish the two-dimensional association rules between population hotspots and POI records. The minimum support (min_sup) and minimum confidence (min_conf) values were determined to analyze the relationship between the number of association rules and different min_sup and min_conf values. </p>

<p>The number of association rules corresponding to the different min_sup and min_conf values showed obvious regularity (<figure>Figure 3</figure>). With increasing min_sup and min_conf values, the number of rules decreased. By analyzing the support values and confidence values, it was that some association rules contained certain categories of POIs, such as catering and corporation, that had high support but low confidence. This was because many of those POIs had a low proportion of spatial association rules with population aggregation points, which means that those association rules were important but not accurate. Other rules, such as the rules containing financial services and scientific research and technical services, had high confident and low support. Those categories of POIs were more likely to have association rules with population gathering points, but the number was small, which means that those association rules were accurate but not important. To obtain sufficient association rules that were important and improve the accuracy, the values of min_sup and min_conf should be set to be as large as possible and to obtain as many rules as possible at the same time. In this study, the value of min_sup was set to 27,450 and the value of min_conf was set to 0.0019, which is the abscissa of inflection points of <figure>Figure 3</figure>a,b. Finally, four categories were selected as PSPs, including residential community, wholesale and retail, education services, and resident services. The PSPs accounted for only 52% of the total POI records. This means that the other 48% were PIPs that would have inevitably introduced noise into the dasymetric model if all POIs were used. </p>

<p>The residential community contained POIs representing residential buildings, apartments, and hotels, where people lived and gathered. Wholesale and retail, education service, and resident service were the three categories of POI that were most relevant to people’s daily life, and they were also the attraction factors for residents. Therefore, all the PSP categories selected through the spatial association rule mining were closely related to the spatial distribution of the population and can be used in dasymetric mapping. </p>

<head> 4.2. Population Map from the PSP-Driven Model</head>
<p>
A RF-based dasymetric model was built with all the covariates described in Section 3.2. This model was used to downscale the log-transformed population density in each county. The fine-grained population map was built by back-transforming the result of the dasymetric model. </p>

<p><figure>Figure 4</figure> shows the value of %IncMSE for each covariate in the RF model. The importance of covariates to the PSPs was significantly higher than those of most other the covariates, which shows that PSP had a great impact on the accuracy of the dasymetric mapping. In addition to the covariates related to the PSPs, the distance to the nearest build-up area, DEM and NTL also has a large impact on the dasymetric modelling. This result is consistent with those of previous studies. </p>

<p>The fine-gridded population map at a 100-m spatial scale in the experiment showed visually satisfactory results (<figure>Figure 5</figure>). <figure>Figure 5</figure>a shows the population distribution map generated by the PSP-driven dasymetric model proposed in Section 3.2. As a comparison, the WorldPop (<figure>Figure 5</figure>b) and the LandScan (<figure>Figure 5</figure>c) datasets from the same region were also shown. Generally, the distributions of the population from three datasets were similar and agreed with the actual topography. The population of the plains and urban areas in the southeast was significantly higher than those in the mountains and grasslands in the northwest. The population was concentrated in the two municipalities of Beijing and Tianjin and aggregated in second-tier cities such as Shijiazhuang and Tangshan, which is consistent with the actual population distribution. Nevertheless, the results from the proposed methods also highlight the population gradient around small towns and villages. </p>
</text>
