<text id="autogum_voyage_doc125" title="Marmaris" shortTile="marmaris" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=21460" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Marmaris</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Marmaris</hi> is a town in <ref target="Turkey">Turkey</ref>, along the <ref target="Mediterranean%20Turkey">Mediterranean</ref> coast in the <ref target="Lycia">province of Muğla</ref>. It has around 28,000 inhabitants, however the population can be up to 250,000 during the height of the tourist season.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>You can get flights to <ref target="Dalaman">Dalaman</ref>, the nearest regional airport, which is 100 km away from Marmaris. Coach transfers are 1½ hours. Airport is served by many operators such as thomsonfly, flythomascook, EasyJet and Turkish airline OnurAir. </p>

<p>Transfers are easily arranged on-line and there are frequent bus connections which correspond to the arrival of domestic flights provided by Havas costing 25 TL single. Havas bus transfer times are detailed outside the airport terminal building.</p>

<head>By boat</head>
<p>There are ferries from <ref target="Rhodes">Rhodes</ref> operated by <ref target="https://feribotlines.com/marmaris-rodos-adasi-feribot-bileti/%23">Feribot Lines</ref> and <ref target="http://www.yesilmarmarislines.com/en/">Yeşil Marmaris Lines</ref>. Catamaran ride takes 1 hr and costs €40 (Feb 2019), however, it's not available on a daily basis, especially during winter.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<p>Cheapest way of getting around is using the dolmus minibuses. These are 11-seaters which travel the main road in Marmaris and Icmeler, the neighbouring resort. The fee is 4 TL (2.55 TL paying Pay pass) anywhere in Marmaris and 3 TL between Icmeler and Marmaris. Marmaris dolmuşes have a green band across them and orange for Icmeler. Other dolmuş services serve Armutalan which is a suburb of Marmaris. The Armutalan dolmuş has a blue band across them.</p>

<p>You can pick them up from the side of the road by hailing for them and they will stop wherever you want on the route.</p>

<p>Other buses are frequently available and compete with dolmus services. They are slightly cheaper and are council owned buses which are similar in concept but slightly larger than dolmus minibuses.</p>

<p>Taxis are also available on the meter or arranging prices up front but are very expensive (prices are negotiable).</p>

<head>See</head>
<p>There's plenty to do in Marmaris. Busy beaches, lots of bars and restaurants, plenty of shopping with fabulous bargains if you don't mind wearing fake designer labels. Marmaris has a busy nightlife with a street devoted to dance music and all the high tech clubbing scene. Bar Street is opposite the busy bazaar and will satisfy the most discerning clubbers with it's huge outdoor dance venues and all of the latest tunes.</p>

<p>Marmaris has lots for families too. Great inexpesive boat excursions can take you out round the bay and to neighbouring towns like <ref target="Icmeler">Icmeler</ref> and <ref target="Turunc">Turunc</ref> with all inclusive food and drinks all day for as little as 25 TL. Marmaris also has two water parks and local travel agents offer a range of trips to <ref target="Dalyan">Dalyan</ref>, <ref target="Fethiye">Fethiye</ref>, <ref target="Pamukkale">Pamukkale</ref>, <ref target="Ephesus">Ephesus</ref> and other popular locations in <ref target="Aegean%20Turkey">Western Turkey</ref>. Another worthwhile trip is to <ref target="Mugla">Mugla</ref>, the regional capital which can be reached by frequent bus service from Marmaris Bus station (Otogar) for 12 TL. Journey time over the mountains is about 1 hour and is well worth the effort as Mugla is a real Western Turkish town not affected greatly by tourism.</p>

<p>The town of Marmaris is not just for the package holiday visitor as a trip to the harbour area will confirm. There you can see ocean going yachts costing $10 million and rub shoulders with those who can blow $1000 on a pair of sunglasses in the exclusive upmarket designer harbour shopping area.</p>

<p>Marmaris is primarily a resort that caters for British holidaymakers but recently has become popular with Russian and other Eastern European visitors.</p>

<head>Do</head>
<p>You can have a <hi rend="bold">daily cruise</hi> taking you around the turquoise coves, mountainous shoreline, ruins of ancient cities, and a cave (the only entrance of which is from the sea) surrounding Marmaris with a stop at the beach of leafy <hi rend="italic">Cennet Adası</hi> ("Paradise Island"—actually a peninsula named <hi rend="italic">Yıldız</hi>, however it does not have a connecting road to the rest of the mainland), which encloses the Bay of Marmaris. Just take one of yachts (which have a capacity of 20 people) which can be found all along the waterfront of city centre, you can easily recognize them by their boards and touts—who will try to convince you to take <hi rend="italic">their</hi> tour, but basically all tours are the same. A tour doing the Bay in an anti-clockwise fashion (i.e. Turunç first, Paradise Island last) may be worthwhile to look for, as most tours ply around the Bay in clockwise direction, and thus you don't have to be with hundreds of others who took other boats all the time. Book or buy a seat at least one day beforehand. Such an excursion cost about 25 TL per person in Summer 2010 (including a meal). This type of cruise is good value but even better when offered with all-inclusive local drinks which can be expensive once on board a boat!</p>

<p>Many of the local tour companies offer trips such as:</p>

<p>Jeep Safari - drive around mountains surrounding Marmaris and visit villages, waterfalls and picturesque beaches. A tour around the Peninsula of Bozburun to south of Marmaris usually combines a visit to the Kızkumu sandbar, see below, <ref target="Marmaris%23Go%20next">"get out" section</ref> for more information. Great value fun day out at about 25 TL per person.</p>

<p>Turkish baths - a traditional turkish bath (Hamam) with sauna, body peel, foam massage and oil massage. From 20 TL per person including transport to and from the baths.</p>

<p>Turkish night - entertainment night with traditional Turkish food, dancing and entertainment including belly dancers. Many hotels do their own Turkish nights and prices range from 15-30 TL for the buffet and entertainment.</p>

<p>Also, trips to further afield such as Dalyan turtle beach and mud baths, Pamukkale, Lycia etc.</p>

<head>Buy</head>

<p>Lots of shops selling usual tourist fodder and local specialities such as Turkish Delight, carpets etc. Most of the branded clothing on offer is fake and is very cheap but the quality can be surprisingly good (Check sizes before committing to buy, especially when buying in markets). Beware of pirate DVDs and games as many will not work despite assurances from vendors. </p>

<p>Real leather can be bought for a good price if you're prepared to haggle. Starting prices are normally at least 2-3 times the final price!</p>

<p>Hairdressing and beauty treatments are good value but beware of tattoo hygiene issues if you decide to be inked permanently. </p>

<p>For food, there is a large supermarket at the end of the main road before the harbour and marina called Tansas which stocks virtually everything including international brands. Tansas has a sister company caled Migros which has two stores in Marmaris, one at the harbour and another larger store on the main road close to the Marmaris Court building. Another hypermarket is situated on the main road beyond the suburb of Armutalan, Kipa is the Turkish division of Tesco and offers a huge range of international and own brand products at competitive prices.</p>

<p>Most tourists enjoy visiting markets in Marmaris (Armutalan) and Icmeler. The markets sell most of the same things the local shops stock but one can haggle a bit more. Beware of pickpockets in these places. The market in the Armutalan area of Marmaris is on a Thursday and the Icmeler market is every Wednesday.</p>

<p>Beware some unscrupulious Turks try to sell baby <hi rend="bold">tortoises</hi> to tourists and encourage them to smuggle them back home in luggage as pets. They will die, of course, in aircraft holds and can be picked up by airport x-ray machines in hand baggage. It is an offence to attempt to import a tortoise into most EU states as they are an endangered species.</p>
</text>
