<text id="autogum_interview_doc418" title="part3_Canada&amp;apos;s Don Valley West (Ward 26) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-don-valley" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-16" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Don_Valley_West_%28Ward_26%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Least Desirable: The purchase of the Green Lane landfill site without lengthy consultation or discussion with the entire City Council.  The City must start investigating proposals for alternative methods of waste management that could prove to be more sustainable such as incineration.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> If you were elected as a "rookie" councillor, What would you bring to the table beyond the incumbent?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> The FIT approach - Forward, Innovative Thinking.    I am forward with a fresh start and futuristic outlook, innovative with beyond the box ideas, and thinking, as a natural communicator with a multitude of experience dealing with a variety of stakeholders.  Coming to City Hall with no political baggage and such experience would position me well to become a consensus builder not just within council, but with both the federal and provincial levels of government.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What does Toronto mean to you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Toronto has enormous potential that has not been tapped in to yet. I would like to see Toronto become a world class city that embraces zero tolerance for urban decay, Safe communities that encourage residents to keep active, responsible development for our neighbourhood, and most of all, accountability to it's taxpayers.</p>
<head id="John_Parker">John Parker</head>
<p>52-year-old <hi rend="bold">John Parker</hi> is a lawyer.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Describe the three most important issues in your campaign.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Get the budget under control; achieve value for money in City Hall spending; protect our neighbourhoods.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi>What one election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Protect our neighbourhoods.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I am concerned that Toronto is falling far short of its potential due only to lack of committed responsible leadership. I want to help change that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent this particular ward on council?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Ward 26 has been my home all my adult life.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Over the past several years I have served in many capacities of local, provincial, and national scope. This involvement has ranged from consulting to the Canadian Council of Ministers of the Environment to coaching pee-wee hockey.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What does Toronto mean to you? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Toronto has always been my home. I always assumed it to be the best city in North America. I feel it is starting to slip. I want to get it back on track to where I think it belongs as the best city on this continent in which to to live, work, and raise a family.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Which council decision (since the 2003 election) do you feel the city/your ward should be most proud of, and which was least desirable?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Not much to be proud of. Outraged at secret vote to try to slip a pay raise past the voters. Seriously disappointed at decision to commit $500M to buy a hole in the ground as another temporary solution to the issue of waste management.</p>
</text>
