<text id="autogum_news_doc186" title="Leaked Syrian government emails indicate weapons supplied to Hamas" shortTile="leaked-syrian-government" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-11-27" dateModified="2015-05-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Leaked_Syrian_government_emails_indicate_weapons_supplied_to_Hamas" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Leaked Syrian government emails indicate weapons supplied to Hamas</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, December 2, 2012</hi></p>
<p>Emails allegedly hacked from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Syria">Syrian</ref> government accounts, leaked onto the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Internet">Internet</ref>, indicate <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iran">Iran</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Syria">Syria</ref> are supplying weapons made in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ukraine">Ukraine</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Belarus">Belarus</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hamas">Hamas</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Palestine">Palestine</ref>.</p>
<figure><caption>One of the leaked letters from the Syrian Embassy in Tehran, requesting Iranian tourist visas for the Syrian Ambassador's brother and son, who have <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Romania">Romanian</ref> citizenship. Image: Syrian Embassy.</caption></figure>
<p>The online activist group known as <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Anonymous_(group)">Anonymous</ref> takes responsibility for the leak, which comprises over 2,000 emails and other files totaling around 1 gigabyte. The leak is part of Anonymous' ongoing campaign known as '#OpSyria' or 'Operation Syria' on the social networking website <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Twitter">Twitter</ref>. </p>
<p>On Monday at 2030<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coordinated%20Universal%20Time">Coordinated Universal Time</ref> (UTC), 'Par:AnoIA,' one of many Twitter accounts connected to Anonymous, stated that the group would "release a stash of Syrian Government emails in the next 24h, featuring <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kofi_Annan">Kofi Annan</ref> correspondence, cash &amp; weapon deliveries." Three hours later the same user announced a leak of "1 Gigabyte [of] internal emails from [the] Syrian Ministry of Foreign Affairs" onto the internet. </p>
<p>The first email leaked was called a "teaser", from the Syrian embassy in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tehran,_Iran">Tehran</ref> on November 20, to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Kingdom">British</ref> embassy in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Belarus">Belarus</ref>. In the communique, the embassy confirms the Iranians are supplying helicopters and Ukrainian made weapons to Hamas, which operates mostly from the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gaza_Strip">Gaza Strip</ref> in Palestine. "1.2D projectiles of Ukraine origin found in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Egypt">Egypt</ref> and Syria" are some of the weapons being sent to Palestine along with "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eurocopter%20EC725">EC725 Helicopters</ref>". </p>
<p>"Since 2008 Iran is the main transit point for Palestine armament", says the email. It also goes on to say the weapons are made in Ukraine as part of "2008 arms trade operations sanctioned by The [Ukrainian] Minister of Defense Anatoly Gritsenko. </p>
<p>Although evidence could suggest Iran's willingness to supply arms to Hamas, in a report compiled on November 2, by the Syrian Ministry of Foreign Affairs and Emigrants, Iran is trying to stop weapons from being sent into Syria for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free%20Syrian%20Army">Free Syrian Army</ref> (FSA). The report quotes Iran's Supreme leader <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ali_Khamenei">Ali Khamenei</ref>, who called for the FSA "to lay down their arms to be able to deliver their demands to the Syrian government." ((ar))Arabic language: ‍بإلقاء السلاح لتتمكن من إيصال مطالبها إلى الحكومة السورية In regards to the civil war in Syria, Khamenei went on to say that if outside entities "were to provide the opponents in every country of weapons from outside the country, it is natural that the regime responds to opponents" ((ar))Arabic language: ‍لو تم تزويد المعارضين في كل بلد بالأسلحة من خارج البلاد فمن الطبيعي أن يتصدى النظام الحاكم للمعارضين. </p>
<p>This is not the first time Anonymous has hacked into Syrian government email accounts. In February, the group hacked into 78 Syrian government email accounts and leaked the usernames and passwords associated with them. The accounts accessed reportedly belonged to aides of Syrian president <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bashar_al-Assad">Bashar al-Assad</ref>. One of the leaked emails, allegedly written by a press aide at Syria's mission at the UN in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York_City">New York</ref> named Sheherazad Jaafari, talks about Assad's preparation for a December 2011 television interview with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/ABC_News">ABC News</ref>' <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barbara%20Walters">Barbara Walters</ref>. In it, Jaafari wrote about ways the Syrian president might be able to manipulate the television audience. </p>
<p>"The American audience doesn't really care about reforms. They won't understand it and they are not interested to do so.... American Psyche can be easily manipulated when they hear that there are 'mistakes' done and now we are 'ﬁxing it.' ... Its worth mentioning also what is happening now in Wall Street [<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Occupy%20Wall%20Street">Occupy Wall Street</ref>] and the way the demonstrations are been suppressed by police men, police dogs and beatings," wrote Jaafari.  </p>
</text>
