<text id="autogum_reddit_doc069" title="Share Your Most Embarrassing, Noobish SC II Moments" shortTile="share-embarrassing" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-04-30" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8g08uu" speakerList="#Rogeryangy, #SymphoniCsC" speakerCount="2">
<head>Share Your Most Embarrassing, Noobish SC II Moments</head>
<sp who="#SymphoniCsC">
<p>I'll go first: 1) When my friend first introduced me to SC II, the concept of invisible/burrowed units and detectors was new to me as the RTS I was coming from, Age of Mythology, had nothing comparable. When I first started using cloaked Banshees, I felt as though I'd discovered the key to the universe, not to mention some quick-and-easy wins. Now you see me, now you DON'T. Muahaha. Then, one dark and stormy night, I lost my cloaked Banshee to a squad of Stalkers outside of my base. After the game, I remember telling my friend how good I thought Stalkers were--they kill my Marines, they blink into my base, and on top of that, they detect my cloaked Banshees! This is when my friend told me about the Observer--an  <hi rend="bold">invisible</hi>  detector.  <hi rend="bold">mind explosion</hi>  2) AoM's lack of deceptive units left me ill-prepared for my next learning experience. I was in Gold league at this point and felt like I was finally getting a grasp on the game (no, seriously). It was a fateful TvZ on Ohana that taught me otherwise. As I was constructing some buildings at my third base, suddenly, an army of Roaches  <hi rend="bold">appeared</hi>  on top of it. For those of you who have played AoM, you may recall something called the "Ajax hack" or the "spawn hack." To those who never played AoM, this was a game-breaking hack which would cause units to appear en masse wherever the hacker chose. The units would literally appear out of thin (virtual) air. I knew about Zerg's ability to burrow, but I had no idea about the Roach's ability to move while burrowed. As furious as I was, I resisted the urge to accuse my opponent of cheating, but I left the game immediately and began cursing and proclaiming to myself that I couldn't believe how another game was plagued by this mother-of-all hacks. I watched the replay, felt like an idiot, and proceeded to rush Engineering Bays to blindly make turrets against Zerg for the next month or so. On the plus side, I don't recall ever losing to 2-Base Muta during that time period. 3) This is a short one, but while in Silver league, and having just discovered Filtersc's Bronze-to-Masters series, I learned how important it was to keep constant production in this game and how far good macro can take you. My friend, u/_Nakamura, played Protoss at that time and was also in Silver league. While theorycrafting with him, I remember making the suggestion that perhaps he should have 1-2 Warp Gates to use for forward/proxy warp-ins, but to keep the remaining buildings as un-upgraded Gateways! To my Silver-league Terran mind, this would be the perfect way to keep production queued and not have to worry about being late (or waiting) for warp-in cycles. Brilliant. Now that I've sufficiently humbled myself before you, please share some of your own similar experiences! *edited for wording*</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#Rogeryangy">
<p>I was a loyal fan of C&amp;C series before getting into starcraft, so I had no concept of A move, for months I engaged enemy by clicking on their units : </p>
</sp>
</text>
