<text id="autogum_bio_doc014" title="Fritzi Gordon" shortTile="fritzi-gordon" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-24" dateModified="2019-05-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fritzi_Gordon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Fritzi Gordon</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">Fritzi Gordon</hi> (1905 or 1916<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-birth-1">[lower-alpha 1]</ref> – 8 February 1992) was an Austrian-born British <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Contract_bridge">bridge</ref> player, half of the most famous and tempestuous female partnership in the game's history. Following her long-time partner <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rixi_Markus">Rixi Markus</ref>, she was the second woman to attain the rank of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World_Bridge_Federation">WBF</ref> World Grand Master. She won four world titles, eight European championships and numerous other tournaments.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Gordon was born <hi rend="bold">Frederika Leist</hi> in either <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Graz">Graz</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-truscott-2">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-birth-1">[lower-alpha 1]</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vienna">Vienna</ref> to middle-class Jewish parents. After school, she became the buyer for a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salzburg">Salzburg</ref> store, married Paul Gordon and moved to Graz.</p>
<p>The annexation of Austria by Germany in 1938 (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anschluss">Anschluss</ref>) disrupted her life, as it did to so many others. She fled to London with her husband, though the details of this abrupt transition are not known. Her brother, Dr. Hans Leist, also came to Britain. (Also a fine bridge player, he was a member of five <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gold_Cup_(bridge)">Gold Cup</ref>-winning teams between 1946 and 1953.)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[2]</ref></p>
<p>When Gordon left Austria, Markus recalled in her obituary tribute, "[she] was not known in the bridge world while I was already a world champion.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-IBL-4">[lower-alpha 2]</ref> But she made up for it soon after arriving in Britain... Paul served in the war with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_Pioneer_Corps">Pioneer Corps</ref> so Fritzi was freed of all restrictions imposed on aliens."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-markus92-5">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Despite their shared cultural heritage and experiences, Gordon and Markus were not personal friends. Success tied them together, but they were often at odds despite their success. Their "discussions" at the table were quite famous, and earned them the soubriquets Frisky and Bitchy. Mrs Gordon was not a bridge writer and her private life remained private. She is consequently the less well known of the pair.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-dormer-6">[4]</ref></p><p>
The actress <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tara_Summers">Tara Summers</ref> is her granddaughter.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[5]</ref> In 2005, Summers described in the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daily_Telegraph">Daily Telegraph</ref></hi> the unusual circumstances in which her grandmother gave birth to her (Summers') mother:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[6]</ref></p><p>My mother was born under a poker table. My grandmother, a world champion bridge player, had been dealt a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_flush_(poker_hand)">royal flush</ref> just as she went into labour, and she chose to play the hand, rather than go to hospital. She was excited about having a child but adamant that she was not going to let it get in the way of her game.
Her gambling addiction, although it may sound glamorous, proved to be just as damaging as any substance or alcohol dependency.</p>
<head>Bridge career</head>
<p>According to Truscott, Gordon had learned bridge from her brother Hans in Austria, and she was a "world-class player" by the end of the war.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-truscott-2">[1]</ref> Even at the European-level, however, international competition resumed only with the 1948 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/European_Bridge_League">European Bridge League</ref> championships.</p>
<p>Gordon's tournament bridge career began after World War II, and her first partnership with Markus began half-way through the European Championships of 1950. In 1955 they agreed to form a regular partnership,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[7]</ref> which became one of the most successful women's pairs in bridge history.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-markus92-5">[3]</ref> The partnership lasted until 1975.</p>
<p>Gordon won the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World_Team_Olympiad#Women_Teams_winners">World Women's teams</ref> 1964; World Mixed teams 1962; World Women's pairs 1962 and 1974 (placed second in 1970). She won the European Women's teams in 1950, 1951, 1952, 1959, 1961, 1963, 1966 and 1975. These were Britain's first eight wins in the tournament, the 1975 win coming in her final appearance in the event.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[8]</ref></p>
<p>She represented Britain on nine other occasions and toured the USA in 1953 as part of the British women's team. Her national successes include the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gold_Cup_(bridge)">Gold Cup</ref> in 1957 and 1961.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[9]</ref></p>
<p>Ewart Kempson thought she was "Our own greatest woman player, [able] to play on equal terms with the greatest men players".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[10]</ref></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Victor_Mollo">Victor Mollo</ref> agreed that she played like a man:</p>
"Few men play as well as Fritzi Gordon. No woman plays better. But it is with the men... that she should be compared for Fritzi's bridge is intensely masculine and he-man stuff at that."
"Where Rixi Markus is fiery, Fritzi Gordon is icy cold. Where Rixi takes her contracts by storm, Fritzi makes hers through merciless efficiency..."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[11]</ref>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terence_Reese">Terence Reese</ref> thought she was at least as good as her more famous partner:</p>
"Fritzi played like a top-class man – like her brother Hans Leist, in fact. To tell the truth – and why not? – Rixi was not quite the equal of Fritzi as an all round player." <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[12]</ref>
<p>Rixi Markus herself wrote:</p>
"Fritzi Gordon was a wonderful player. She may even have had a slight advantage over me in that she was more controlled and less impetuous."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-markus92-5">[3]</ref>
<head>Bridge accomplishments</head>
<head>Wins</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World_Women_Pairs_Championship">World Women Pairs Championship</ref> (2) 1962, 1974</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World_Team_Olympiad">World Olympiad Women's Teams Championship</ref> (1) 1964</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gold_Cup_(bridge)">Gold Cup</ref> (2) 1957, 1961 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Gold_Cup_Winners-15">[13]</ref></item></list>
<head>Runners-up</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Venice_Cup">Venice Cup</ref> (1) 1976 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-WBF_Winners-16">[14]</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World_Women_Pairs_Championship">World Women Pairs Championship</ref> (1) 1970</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World_Team_Olympiad">World Olympiad Women's Teams Championship</ref> (1) 1976</item></list>
</text>
