<text id="autogum_interview_doc597" title="part2_Wikinews interviews John Wolfe, Democratic Party presidential challenger to Barack Obama" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-05-19" dateModified="2013-09-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_John_Wolfe%2C_Democratic_Party_presidential_challenger_to_Barack_Obama" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Well that might have happened in West Virginia, where there was more voters that participated in the Democratic primary than the Republican primary. So what is your reaction to the showing of prison inmate Keith Russell Judd in that primary?</hi></p>
<hi rend="bold">[The American people] may not be able to articulate it the way I just did but they know in their heart what's true and what isn't. And they know for sure that [President Obama's] not on their side. And they're right.</hi>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wolfe</hi>: Well it shows that Obama's left a void. His lack of leadership has left a void and people are upset. He should be out there with the people. He should be in those coal mines. He should be in those towns, where those factories have left, and he ought to be out there with the homeowners who've been foreclosed on by his campaign contributors. People know this man is nothing but a Wall Street creature.  They know that his advisers in the White House are all failed executives of failed banks that have been bailed out: people like Emil [Michael], people like [Jacob] <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacob%20Lew">Lew</ref>, [William] <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William%20M.%20Daley">Daley</ref>, they're all from the big six: the big corporations we had to bail out. Yes. What did they get for their failures? Promoted to the White House. People know that. Most of the guys who are raising his campaign money. They're sick of it. And that's why people in West Virginia, and lot of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blue-collar%20worker">blue collar people</ref> don't like Obama. It's his own fault because he is not of the people. He is of Wall Street. People are finally starting to see that.</p>
<p>John Wolfe isn't [of Wall Street]. John Wolfe worked his way up through. I've worked in factories. I've worked in grocery stores.  I almost cut my thumb off doing agricultural work. When I went to college, I didn't have any transportation.  I had to hitchhike up and down <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Interstate%2075">I75</ref> to get an education. So I know what it's like to work in the real world. I know what it's like to have to strive hard to get ahead. But Obama doesn't relate to those people. He's too professorial. He's too detached.  He is of Wall Street. Those are the people he pals around with: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert%20Wolf%20(business)">Bob Wolf</ref> that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Banking%20in%20Switzerland">Swiss banker</ref> is his favorite guy. The guy that loves speculation on Wall Street. He gets paid billions and billions of dollars for failed banks to get back up. Him and Obama are like twins. I mean you see Bob Wolf, you see Obama. I mean, this is the sort of thing people sense. They may not be able to articulate it the way I just did but they know in their heart what's true and what isn't. And they know for sure that he's not on their side. And they're right.</p>
</text>
