<text id="autogum_interview_doc615" title="part3_Wikinews interviews Joe Schriner, Independent U.S. presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-04-16" dateModified="2019-08-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Joe_Schriner%2C_Independent_U.S._presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Describe to me an average day in the life of Joe Schriner. How do you spend your time?</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Schriner's family Image: Joe Schriner.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> When I'm on the road campaigning, my day looks something like this.  (Incidentally, we often move from town to town daily, where versions of this template repeat over, and over, and...).  First, we generally get up early and either go to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mass%20(liturgy)">Mass</ref>, or do family prayer.  Then after breakfast (often oatmeal), Liz starts to do homeschooling – or as we colloquially refer to it: “motor-home schooling” – with our three children.    Meanwhile I'll go, often unannounced, to a local newspaper (radio stations, TV stations...) and inform them about a corner whistle-stop event we'll be doing at noon in their town.  Sometimes they'll have me stay to do an interview right then, other times they'll send a reporter to the event.  Around 10:30 a.m., we'll go to a local library where Liz will continue with the homeschooling and I'll update our campaign website blog about the events of the day before.    Shortly before noon, we'll arrive at the downtown venue where we'll unfurl banners, flags and go into “street corner whistle-stop mode.”  We'll wave and call out to passing motorists, the kids and I will walk about passing out fliers, our young Jonathan will try to get passing truck drivers to honk...  It's all rather festive.  Afterward we do media interviews,   then head out to lunch at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taco%20Bell">Taco Bell</ref>, or wherever.  After some Dollar Menu bean burritos, we'll take the kids to a park or local <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/YMCA">YMCA</ref> where we all exercise a bit.  Afterward, a variety of things might happen.  Sometimes we go door-to-door in a town passing out fliers and putting them up in downtown businesses as well.  Other times, there's a brief window of time in the late afternoon, and early evening, to write the speech for an event we're doing later that night.  Other times we'll take the kids to, say, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Little%20League%20Baseball">Little League</ref> ballgame early in the evening.  And as they watch the game, I go about passing out campaign literature and talking with folks.  Other evenings, we're meeting with supporters in their homes, or I'm out doing research on one of the projects we've come across, or for that matter, I'm sometimes out throwing the football around with the boys... Then, as the evening starts to wind down, we'll look for somewhere to park – whether a campground, church parking lot, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wal-Mart">Wal-Mart</ref> parking lot...  And as the kids settle in, we tell “stories from the road,” or read the kids a book, or the kids will draw, write letters, do <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lego">Lego</ref> stuff on their own...  We then say evening prayers together as a family before the kids go to sleep.  And finally, Liz and I will often stay up late playing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scrabble">Scrabble</ref>, or talking about the day, or working on the scheduling and itinerary for the next several stops.  Or some nights, after a day of, well, too close quarters with the kids, Liz and I will simply sit and stare out the camper windows, in silence.  Silence that is only occasionally broken by an exhausted Liz, or an exhausted me, repeating the refrain:  “I think we need a staff.”</p>
</text>
