<text id="autogum_reddit_doc058" title="Is modern science simply a redefinition of magic?" shortTile="modern-science-simply" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-05-31" dateModified="2018-05-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8nm3p1" speakerList="#FloRaider, #Sagwort" speakerCount="2">
<head>Is modern science simply a redefinition of magic?</head>
<sp who="#Sagwort">
<p>The title probably sounds a little cooky but hear me out. I figured I'd entertain this thought to consider what magic actually is. When we look at modern dictionary definitions of magic it is described as something along the lines of having "the power of apparently influencing the course of events by using mysterious or supernatural forces." Sounds about right. Now let us consider what "mysterious" and "supernatural" mean. Mysterious is defined as being "difficult or impossible to understand, explain, or identify." And supernatural is defined as being "attributed to some force beyond scientific understanding or the laws of nature." First off, the whole "supernatural" definition of magic is rather vague and misleading. What is nature? Can ALL thing be eventually understood through scientific understanding? For centuries astronomers and astrologers attributed the heavenly bodies as just that, 'heavenly'. One could argue that this view did not consider space as "nature" but rather "divine" and/or "supernatural". Yet, as time has passed science has allowed us to understanding space and we view it as natural as a tree. If demons existed would we not eventually consider them as a part of nature or the natural order of things? In fact, the only thing we like to call "unnatural" is human activity. (e.g. cities, cars, clothing, etc...). Besides, if you asked a scholar from an era where magic was believed to exist, Renaissance Europe, for instance, they would likely describe certain kinds of magic as natural. In other words, they believed in natural magic. This kind of magic was considered different from the ritual magic of thaumaturgy and involved having an acute understanding of nature through such disciplines as botany, astronomy, alchemy, chemistry, etc... Low and behold, many of these disciplines which were considered "natural magic" or are now considered natural science. Now you might be thinking, could we not classify the above fields of study as natural philosophy? The precursor to modern science? We certainly could; however, I would like to insert my own opinion here. From a literary perspective, it seems as though magic must involve not just an understanding of nature, but the ability to manipulate it. This is where natural philosophy and natural magic differ, I believe. Botany, astronomy, physics, etc... generally only deal in the understanding of nature. We might define science in the same way. But it is through fields such as alchemy and astrology that this knowledge is put into use and the natural world is manipulated by the "magic user". Now we know alchemy and astrology as protoscience, as well as magic, but let allow me to introduce you to chemistry. Chemistry was born from alchemy, you probably already knew that, and remains as one of the most applied forms of science in comparison to pure biology or physics. On top of this, the goals of chemists are largely the same as the goals of alchemists, to manipulate matter on a fundamental level, to produce wondrous medicines, materials, etc... The only thing that has changed between chemists and alchemists is the paradigm they use to explain the natural world. However, both could be considered mysterious to those not in-the-know and I would argue that modern chemistry is more complex and difficult to grasp than alchemy which had relatively simple explanations for natural phenomena. So it seems as though chemistry has filled in any criteria that a magic system might require. It has specific laws by which it functions, it seems mysterious and arcane to those who are not aware of these laws, and it allows to practitioner to actively manipulate nature on a fundamental level. If having that knowledge and power is not magic, then I don't know what is. In conclusion, it seems as though the difference between magic and science is a matter of perspective and definition. After all, are "scientific magic" systems not just a form of fictional science? I think a lot of people, especially when considering works of fiction, believe that magic must look like magic to be considered magic. That it must stir some sense of awe or wonder. We are largely desensitized to the marvels of modern chemistry; however, when we take a step back we notice that chemistry has led to the creation of powders and liquids which sooth pain, allow us to become hyper focused and awake, allow us to build muscle faster, the list goes on. Chemistry has allowed us to evoke toxic air which has caused innumerable amounts of suffering, hurl metal at hundreds of miles per hour, and create explosions to wipe out entire cities. We call this science and engineering, but place it in a fantasy world and you have magic. Sure, these could also be considered feats of physics or engineering but the line between particle physics and chemistry has always been fuzzy and engineering is a matter of application. tl;dr chemistry is magic</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#FloRaider">
<p>TL;DR: Clark's Third Law: Any sufficiently advanced technology is indistinguishable from magic. </p>
<p>Any magic that works by do X and get Y could be demystified and made into a science. </p>
<p>Magic that has some sentience and vague rules behind it, like the force would stay a mystery and truly magical.</p>
</sp>
</text>
