<text id="autogum_bio_doc210" title="Gracie Pierce" shortTile="gracie-pierce" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-01-19" dateModified="2019-04-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gracie_Pierce" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Gracie Pierce</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Grayson S. "Gracie" Pierce</hi> (before 1865— August 28, 1894) was an American <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Major_League_Baseball">Major League Baseball</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second_baseman">second baseman</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Center_fielder">center fielder</ref> for three seasons, playing for five teams from 1882 to 1884.  He later became a regular <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Umpire_(baseball)">umpire</ref> in both the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_League">National League</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Players'_League">Players' League</ref>.</p>
<head>Playing career</head>
<head>1882</head>
<p>Pierce began his major league career on May 2, 1882 for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louisville_Eclipse">Louisville Eclipse</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Association_(19th_century)">American Association</ref>.  He played a total of nine games, all as a second baseman, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Batting_average_(baseball)">batted</ref> .303 in 33 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/At_bat">at bats</ref>.  He scored three <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Run_(baseball)">runs</ref>, and hit one <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Double_(baseball)">double</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-retrosheet-1">[1]</ref>  Later that season, he played in 41 games for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baltimore_Orioles_(19th_century)">Baltimore Orioles</ref>, also of the American Association.   His batting average dropped to .199 in 151 at bats with Orioles, as well as his production, scoring just eight runs, two doubles, and one <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Triple_(baseball)">triple</ref>.  His season average between the two teams was .217, and he led the league among second basemen with 65 errors.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-retrosheet-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>1883</head>
<p>He began the season with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Columbus_Buckeyes_(AA)">Columbus Buckeyes</ref> of the American Association, hitting .171 in 41 at bats, scored five runs, and did not gather one <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Extra-base_hit">extra-base hit</ref>.  Later in the season, he joined the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_York_Gothams">New York Gothams</ref> of the National League, playing in 18 games, totaling just five <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hit_(baseball)">hits</ref> in 62 at bats for a .080 batting average.  He also began to play more in the outfield, mainly as a center fielder, rather than at second base.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-retrosheet-1">[1]</ref>  His batting average for the season was .117, but he did hit the second (and last) triple of his career.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-retrosheet-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>1884</head>
<p>His last major league season was spent with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_York_Metropolitans">New York Metropolitans</ref>, where he played in just five games, splitting his time between second base and the outfield.  He batted .250 for the season, with records indicating his participation in the game played August 1.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-retrosheet-1">[1]</ref>  His career totals include a .186 batting average, 21 runs scored, four doubles, and two triples in 84 games and 307 at bats.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-retrosheet-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Post major league career</head>
<head>Minor leagues</head>
<p>He signed and played for an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elmira,_New_York">Elmira, New York</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minor_league_baseball">minor league baseball</ref> team in 1886, along with fellow Metropolitans <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ed_Kennedy_(outfielder)">Ed Kennedy</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dasher_Troy">Dasher Troy</ref>, when players began to leave the team due to speculation that the American Association was going to eliminate them from the league.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-kennedybio-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>As an umpire</head>
<p>Pierce had, during his playing days, filled in for the regular umpire from time to time.  He registered three games in 1882 and one game in 1884.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-retrosheet-1">[1]</ref>  He began to umpire games regularly in 1886, when he called 47 games, and 1887, when he called 33, all in the National League.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-retrosheet-1">[1]</ref>  He didn't appear as an official umpire at a major league game until 1890, when he officiated at 57 games in the Players' League.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-retrosheet-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>During his major league umpiring career, he was involved in one <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Forfeit_(baseball)">forfeited</ref> game, and umpired game six of the 1886 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World_Series">World Series</ref>.  The forfeited game was played between the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Louis_Maroons">St. Louis Maroons</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Washington_Nationals_(1886-89)">Washington Nationals</ref> on September 29, 1886.  In the seventh inning, after a St. Louis player had <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strikeout">struck out</ref>, the Maroons refused to play, complaining that it was too dark to continue.  Pierce ruled that due to their refusal to play, they forfeited the game to the Nationals.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-retroforfeit-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>On October 23, 1886, he umpired the sixth and final game of the 1886 World Series.  The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Louis_Browns_(NL)">St. Louis Browns</ref> of the American Association were up on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chicago_White_Stockings_(1870–89)">Chicago White Stockings</ref> of the National League, three games to two entering the game.  The game ended with St. Louis winning after ten innings of play, sealing the series victory, the only undisputed championship that the Association could claim over the National League.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nemecbeer-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>He was relieved of his umpiring duties in 1887 after allegedly misusing a railroad pass.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>Eight years later, Gracie Pierce died in his hometown of New York City.  His age cannot be determined with certainty due to the unavailability of his birth year, but if he was in his twenties during the earliest years of his playing career, his death occurred while he was still in his mid-thirties.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-retrosheet-1">[1]</ref></p>
</text>
