<text id="autogum_voyage_doc68" title="Santa Clarita" shortTile="santa-clarita" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=31358" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Santa Clarita</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Santa Clarita</hi> is the third largest city in <ref target="Los%20Angeles%20County">Los Angeles County</ref> in <ref target="Southern%20California">Southern</ref> <ref target="California">California</ref>.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>The closest and most convenient airport is in <ref target="Burbank">Burbank</ref>. Other nearby airports include <ref target="Los%20Angeles%20International%20Airport">Los Angeles International Airport</ref>, <ref target="Ontario%20%28California%29">Ontario</ref>, and <ref target="Orange%20County%20%28California%29">Orange County</ref>.</p>

<p>Supershuttle and Primetime are shared-ride vans which serve the Santa Clarita area from LAX. Stand under the orange "shared ride vans" sign in the center concrete island outside the LAX airport. Tell a customer service representative that you need a ride to Santa Clarita. They are easy to identify by their blue jackets (Supershuttle) or red jackets (Primetime). If no representative is available, then flag down a blue van (Supershuttle) or red van (Primetime) with a "Santa Clarita" placard in the windshield. Approximate cost is $30 per person. Approximate time to Santa Clarita is 1 hour.</p>

<p>The cheapest way to get to Santa Clarita from LAX is to use Metrolink. Stand under the green "FlyAway, Buses and Long-Distance Vans" sign in the center concrete island outside the LAX airport. Board a blue FlyAway bus heading to Union Station (there are FlyAway buses going to Van Nuys and Westwood as well). It will cost you $4 one-way (a 30-minute trip). The blue FlyAway is a large charter-style bus, and is occasionally not labeled. FlyAway buses operate every half hour, 24 hours a day. If you are boarding at the airport, you will not be charged until you get to your destination. At Union Station follow the Metrolink signs. Walk to the Antelope Valley Line (typically platform 4B, but varies so check signage) in Union Station. Inside the terminal is an automated kiosk for purchasing tickets. One-way tickets for the AV Line are $7.50, or $10 for a day pass on the weekends. There is a discount for seniors, students, and people with documented disabilities, which generally includes any disability that would prevent them from walking or driving a car. The travel time is approximately 1 hour, which cuts off as much as 45 minutes with the traffic conditions at times.</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>The closest full-service Amtrak station is Los Angeles Union Station. From there, you would take the Metrolink Antelope Valley line up to Santa Clarita. At Union Station follow the Metrolink signs. Walk to the Antelope Valley Line in Union Station (typically platform 4B, but varies so check signage). Inside the terminal is an automated kiosk for purchasing tickets. One way tickets are $7.50, or $10 for a day pass on the weekends. There are discounts for seniors and people with disabilities, which reduces the one-way ticket price to $3.75. The student discount reduces the one-way ticket price to $5.75. The travel time is approximately 1 hour, which cuts off as much as 45 minutes with the traffic conditions at times.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>From <ref target="Los%20Angeles/Downtown">Downtown L.A.</ref> or other southern cities take Interstate 5 North, which is called "the 5 freeway" locally. Santa Clarita starts with Lyons Avenue/Pico Canyon Exit and ends around Hasley Canyon Exit. Slightly West of the 5 freeway in Los Angeles is the 101 North to the 170 North which ends at the 5 North freeway. In South West Los Angeles the 405 North also connects to the 5 freeway North. From the North East, the 14 (Antelope Valley) freeway South will take you to Santa Clarita, exiting at Soledad Canyon.</p>

<head>By taxi</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Southland Yellow Cab Co</hi> +1 661 723-2227</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">United Taxi of Los Angeles</hi> +1 661 267-9850</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Yellow Cab of Santa Clarita</hi> +1 661 260-2227</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Yellow Star Cab Santa Clarita</hi> +1 661 288-7800</item>
</list>


<head>By bus</head>
<p>There are several <ref target="http://www.santaclaritatransit.com/">Santa Clarita Transit</ref> bus routes throughout the city. Full fare for a single ride is $1, with children 5 and under free. Adults over 60 ride for a reduced fare of $.50/single ride. Transfers are free.</p>

<head>By bicycle</head>
<p>Santa Clarita is known for its wealth of bike paths and paseos. You can easily get around by bicycle as everything is connected by paseos where you can avoid waiting for traffic lights. A map of the bike paths is available at the <ref target="http://www.santa-clarita.com/trails">City of Santa Clarita's main website</ref>.</p>

<head>By horse</head>
<p>There is a large equestrian community in Santa Clarita. There are horse trails throughout the city with plans to construct more in the future. The horse trails can be found on the following map supplied from the <ref target="http://www.santa-clarita.com/trails">City of Santa Clarita's website</ref>.</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>On weekdays, four bus lines have service to/from the Metrolink station that connects Santa Clarita to Los Angeles. Routes 501-504. They are designed to run for commuters, but work great for those wanting easy/fast access to Los Angeles without the hassle of traffic. Details of times the run and stops are on the <ref target="http://www.santaclaritatransit.com/">Santa Clarita Transit website</ref>.</p>

<p>There are two Metrolink Stations in Santa Clarita operating on the <ref target="http://www.metrolinktrains.com/">Antelope Valley Line</ref> which ends at downtown Los Angeles (Union Station). From there you can connect to other <ref target="http://www.metro.net/">Metrolink</ref> train lines or LA's subway/bus system as well as <ref target="Amtrak">Amtrak</ref> or the <ref target="http://www.lawa.org/welcome_LAX.aspx%3Fid%3D292">Van Nuys Flyaway buses</ref> with service to the LAX airport :</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Jan Heidt Newhall Metrolink Station</hi>, 24300 Railroad Ave. Directions: From the 5 Fwy., exit Lyons Ave. Go East on Lyons to San Fernando Rd. Go South on San Fernando Rd. to Market. Go East on Market to Railroad Ave. There are 150 parking spaces available, and there is no fee for parking.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Santa Clarita Metrolink Station</hi>, 22122 Soledad Canyon Rd. Directions: From the 5 Fwy., exit Valencia Ave. Go East on Valencia Ave. Valencia becomes Soledad Canyon Road. There are 350 parking spaces available, and there is no fee for parking. Bike lockers are available.</item>
</list>


<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Six%20Flags%20Magic%20Mountain">Six Flags Magic Mountain</ref> </hi>. Open since 1971, is the leading attraction in Santa Clarita. Movie buffs will recognize this park as "Wally World" in the 1983 film <hi rend="italic">National Lampoon's Vacation</hi>. Buy your tickets online at their website and you'll usually get a deal like $10 off or buy one get one free Parking is $17 for self parking and $30 for valet. Six Flags Magic Mountain, the Thrill Capital of the World, firmly holds the coveted "Coaster Capital of the World" crown — with a total of 18 roller coasters — more than any other theme park on the planet.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Six Flags Hurricane Harbor</hi>. Adjacent to Six Flags Magic Mountain is its sister Park Six Flags Hurricane Harbor. This tropical themed water park provides an entire day of fun for the whole family! The attraction lineup features more than 23 slides and activities that keep you cool in the summer months.</item>
</list>
</text>
