<text id="autogum_bio_doc218" title="Theodosius of Sinai" shortTile="theodosius-sinai" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-10-29" dateModified="2019-09-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theodosius_of_Sinai" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Theodosius of Sinai</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Theodosius of Sinai</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulgarian_language">Bulgarian</ref>: Теодосий Синаитски), (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Macedonian_language">Macedonian</ref>: Теодосиј Синаитски), was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulgarians">Bulgarian</ref> priest, writer and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Printer_(publisher)">printer</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> He founded the first Bulgarian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Printer_(publisher)">printing-house</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> Theodosius of Sinai is considered an ethnic <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Macedonians_(ethnic_group)">Macedonian</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North_Macedonia">North Macedonia</ref>.</p>
<figure><caption>Teodosy's introduction to "Solace of the sinner"</caption></figure>
<p>Teodosius was born in the late 18th century in the town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dojran">Dojran</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman Empire</ref> (today in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North_Macedonia">North Macedonia</ref>).  His birth name was Teohar (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulgarian_language">Bulgarian</ref>: Теохар). After he had finished <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greek_language">Greek language</ref> school in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Istanbul">Istanbul</ref>, Teohar went back to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dojran">Dojran</ref>, where he got married and was later ordained a priest.  The death of his wife however drove him into a pilgrimage to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holy_Land">Holy Land</ref>. In 1828 Teohar became a monk in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint_Catherine's_Monastery">Saint Catherine's Monastery</ref> and there he adopted the monastic name Teodosiues (<hi rend="italic">Theodosiy</hi> in Bulgarian).</p>
<p>After returning to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Balkans">Balkans</ref>, Theodosius was appointed a priest in "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Minas">St. Minas</ref>" church in Solun (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</ref>) in 1831. While in Solun, he established the firsts printing house in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulgarian_language">Bulgarian language</ref> in 1838. Theodosius used the movable type <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Printing_presses">printing press</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daskal_Kamche">Daskal Kamche</ref> from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vatasha">Vatasha</ref>.  The moveable types of the press were crafted by a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russians">Russian</ref> immigrant type-founder.  The first books, typed in Teodosius's printing house, were <hi rend="italic">"Primary study through Slavonic-Bulgarian and Greek Orthodox morning prayers"</hi> (<hi rend="italic">„Началное учение с молитви утренния славяноболгарский и греческия“</hi>) and <hi rend="italic">"Jewish ceremony and all of the harms, they've done"</hi> - an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anti-Semitic">anti-Semitic</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parody">lampoon</ref>, which was initially translated "to simple and plain Bulgarian language" by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nathanael_Ohridski">Nathanael Ohridski</ref>. In 1839 Teodosius typed his own "<hi rend="italic">A Brief description of twenty monasteries that are situated in the Holly <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mount_Athos">Mount Athos</ref>"</hi>.</p>
<figure><caption>"Jewish ceremony.."</caption></figure>
<p>In 1839 Teodosius' printing-house was burned down, but it was soon restored with the finansical support of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kiril_Peychinovich">Kiril Peychinovich</ref>. Peychinovich's book <hi rend="italic">Utesheniе Greshnim</hi> ("Solace of the sinner") was typed in the restored printing-house in 1840. Teodosius wrote an introduction to the book, where he mentioned that the book was written by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kiril_Peychinovich">Kiril Peychinovich</ref> into "...the plainest Bulgarian language, spoken in Lower <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moesia">Moesia</ref>, and the region of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Skopje">Skopje</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tetovo">Tetovo</ref>...". There Teodosius also praised the Bulgarian language and compared it to a key, which can unlock the heart of the Bulgarian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nation">nation</ref> for the light of the truth.</p>
<p>In 1841 Teodosius typed a book, called "A book for studying three languages - Slavonic-Bulgarian, Greek and Karamanlian".  The book was a Bulgarian-Greek-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turkish_language">Turkish</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dictionary">dictionary</ref>, designed to be of use for merchants.</p>
<p>In 1843 a fire destroyed Teodosius's printing house for a second and final time. Theodosius returned to Dojran, where he began working as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miller">miller</ref> in his sons' <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Water-mill">water-mill</ref>. According to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arseniy_Kostentsev">Arseniy Kostentsev</ref>, the usable remains of Theodosius' printing press were taken to the village of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vataša">Vataša</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>Theodosius died in an accident in March 1843. He was killed by a collapsed roof.</p>
<p>Nine years after Theodosius' death, the brothers Kiryak and Konstantin Darzhilovi opened a new Bulgarian language printing press in Thessaloniki.
</p>
</text>
