<text id="autogum_academic_doc535" title="Droplet Microfluidics-Enabled High-Throughput Screening for Protein Engineering" shortTile="droplet-microfluidicsenabled" author="Lindong Weng, James  E. Spoonamore" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-666X/10/11/734/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Engineered proteins with tailored properties evolved from natural precursors have been playing an increasingly important role in a spectrum of agricultural, industrial, and biomedical applications. For example, protein engineering holds the potential of transforming the metabolic drug landscape through the development of smart, stimulus-responsive drug systems. In industrial processes, protein engineering enables the production of enzymes that offer unique advantages compared with chemical catalysts, such as biodegradability, stereoselectivity, substrate specificity, functionality under relatively mild solvents, temperatures, pHs and pressures, and stability at extreme conditions. Today, protein engineering also plays a critical role in advancing the emerging field of synthetic biology, including optimizing pathway enzymes and regulatory elements, balancing pathway redox equivalents, as well as tuning the expression of pathway genes. </p>

<p>There are two main strategies in protein engineering: rational design and directed evolution. Rational design, which is mostly carried out in silico, is knowledge-based, deterministic engineering of proteins. Thus, it needs prior information on the target protein such as a structural model, sequence relationship to homologs, and insights into its biophysical function. As a powerful approach to test general theories in protein chemistry, rational design can be achieved either by single-point mutation, exchange of elements of secondary structure, exchange of whole domains, or by fusion of enzymes. Novel computational tools have constantly improved, resulting in dramatic increase in the sizes of mutant libraries that can be designed. Genome-scale metabolic models (GEMs) have informed and expanded variant design for many industrially relevant microorganisms. Furthermore, multiplex automated genome evolution (MAGE) and CRISPR/Cas systems have significantly improved the throughput of genome editing with precision and reduced cost and time required to explore many protein targets. For example, MAGE enables the rapid generation of billions of mutants by repeated insertion, deletion or mutation of DNA at multiple chromosomal targets. Overall, the unprecedented capability of designing and building a large number of variants for rational protein design has placed increased demands on the throughput of screening and selection. </p>

<p>Directed evolution, on the other hand, mimics the process of natural selection through random mutagenesis to steer proteins or nucleic acids toward desired traits. Unlike rational protein design, directed evolution requires neither prior knowledge of a protein’s detailed structure nor prediction of the effects of various mutations. Indeed, directed evolution makes it possible to identify undiscovered protein sequences which have novel functions. Moreover, synthetic biologists also increasingly rely on directed evolution to optimize engineered biological systems. However, for directed evolution to be truly effective, very large libraries of mutants must be screened under conditions that closely match the desired functionality. Thus, the throughput of screening for variants with improved traits is a major factor dictating the efficiency of directed evolution given that the libraries of random mutants can be easily on the scale of 108–109. </p>

<p>Proteins are engineered for properties such as affinity, selectivity, stability or enzymatic activity. Often, when a cell based fluorescent readout is achievable, screening of engineered protein libraries is performed with fluorescence-activated cell sorting (FACS) to separate a population of cells into sub-populations based on fluorescent labeling. In this case, the phenotype-genotype connection is unbroken because the cells are selected directly. For example, Lipovšek et al. reported in vitro selection of catalytically active enzymes (horseradish peroxidase) from large libraries of variants displayed on the surface of the yeast <hi rend="italic">S. cerevisiae</hi> and separated by FACS. To improve substrate specificity of glycosyltransferases by directed evolution, Aharoni et al. screened a library of over a million sialyltransferases mutants using FACS and found a variant with up to 400-fold higher catalytic efficiency for transfer to a variety of fluorescently labeled acceptor sugars. In their study, the formation of sialosides in intact <hi rend="italic">E. coli</hi> cells was detected by selectively trapping the fluorescently labeled transfer products within the cell and the resulting cell population was analyzed and sorted using FACS. However, many desirable properties are not amenable to direct interrogation via FACS because the phenotype is not inherent in a single cell, for example, when improving a protein excreted into growth medium. Properties such as extracellular analyte consumption, product secretion and cell-cell interactions are not readily detectable with flow cytometry. Screening for ‘non-cellular’ phenotypes necessitates the compartmentalization of single cells or an alternative expression system to maintain the linkage between the phenotype that the selection acts on and the genotype in which the evolutionary information is encoded. Compartmentalization of assays in arrays of wells makes microtiter plates by far the most widely used screening platform. However, the microplate-based method becomes problematic when the assay volume is less than 1 µL due to evaporation and capillary forces. Even with robotic automation for liquid handling using 1536-well plates and assuming a processing rate of 1 plate per minute, the throughput of a well based assay is approximately 25 samples/sec for a prompt optical measurement. </p>
</text>
