<text id="autogum_academic_doc741" title="Do Political Connections Affect the Conservative Financial Reporting of Family Firms?" shortTile="political-connections" author="Hsin-Yi Chi, Tzu-Ching Weng, Guang-Zheng Chen, Shu-Ping Chen" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5563/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Research Design and Methodology</head><head> 3.1. Measures of Family Firm </head>
<p>
A family firm refers to an enterprise in which the family can exert a substantial influence by virtue of the ownership structure and/or seats on the managerial/supervisory board. Following prior research, we defined a founding family’s influence, <hi rend="italic">FAM</hi>, taking a value of one if family members, by blood or marriage, are chief executive officers, directors, or block holders; otherwise, <hi rend="italic">FAM</hi> took a value of zero. In addition, the continuous variable, <hi rend="italic">FAMOWN</hi>, is defined as the fractional equity ownership of the family. </p>

<head> 3.2. Measures of Political Connections</head>
<p>
To capture the political influence of government officials, we followed Faccio et al. and Fan et al. and defined political connections as an indicator variable, PC, which takes the value of one if a firm’s largest shareholders, senior officers, or board members currently satisfy any one of the criteria of political connection as follows: (1) a former official in central or local government; (2) a current or former congressperson or elected representative; or (3) a current or former party representative, such as party chief, party secretary, or party committee member. </p>

<head> 3.3. Methodology of Testing Model</head>
<p>
Based on Khan and Watts’, our measure of conservative financial reporting was firm-year-specific asymmetric timeliness score. First, we established Basu’s asymmetric timeliness measure, which regresses earnings on return and allows the return coefficient to vary with the sign of the return.

(1)

where, for firm <hi rend="italic">i</hi> and period <hi rend="italic">t</hi>: <hi rend="italic">NI</hi> is the net income before extraordinary items are deflated by the market value of the equity at the beginning of the period; <hi rend="italic">RET</hi> is the buy-and-hold return over the fiscal year; and <hi rend="italic">NEG</hi> is an indicator variable coded to one when <hi rend="italic">RET</hi> is negative, and zero otherwise. In Equation (1), <hi rend="italic">β</hi>1 captures the timeliness of earnings with respect to positive returns, and <hi rend="italic">β</hi>1 + <hi rend="italic">β</hi>3 capture the timeliness of earnings with respect to negative returns. If <hi rend="italic">β</hi>1 + <hi rend="italic">β</hi>3 &gt; <hi rend="italic">β</hi>1 (or <hi rend="italic">β</hi>3 &gt; 0), it will be conservative reported earnings; that is, a positive and significant <hi rend="italic">β</hi>3 represents earnings that reflect bad news more quickly than good news and, hence, is the measure of conservatism (i.e., the asymmetric timeliness coefficient). </p>

<p>Second, we developed an estimation of the timeliness of good news (<hi rend="italic">G_Score</hi>) and the incremental timeliness of bad news (<hi rend="italic">C_Score</hi>) as linear functions of size, market-to-book value, and financial leverage.

(2)

(3)

where, for firm <hi rend="italic">i</hi> and period <hi rend="italic">t</hi>: <hi rend="italic">MVE</hi> is the natural logarithm for the market value of the equity; <hi rend="italic">MTB</hi> is the market value of the equity divided by the book value of the equity; <hi rend="italic">LEV</hi> is the total liabilities divided by total assets; and the empirical estimators of <hi rend="italic">μ</hi>1–<hi rend="italic">μ</hi>4 and <hi rend="italic">λ</hi>1<hi rend="italic">–λ</hi>4, are constant across all firms, but vary over time. After estimating <hi rend="italic">β1</hi> and <hi rend="italic">β3</hi> in Equations (2) and (3), we placed them into Equation (1) to yield Equation (4) as follows:

(4)

</p>

<p>Following Khan and Watts, we included an additional term in the last parenthesis of Equation (4) to control for the firm’s characteristics separately (the main effect). We first estimated Equation (4) in annual cross-sections to obtain the coefficient estimates for <hi rend="italic">λ</hi>1<hi rend="italic">–λ</hi>4, which we then applied to Equation (3) to calculate the <hi rend="italic">C_Score</hi>: a higher <hi rend="italic">C_Score</hi> represents a higher degree of conservatism. </p>

<p>To test the hypothesis, we applied the firm-specific timeliness measure of conservatism in the following regression:

(5)

where, for firm <hi rend="italic">i</hi> and period <hi rend="italic">t</hi>, <hi rend="italic">C_Score</hi> is the firm-specific measure of conservatism; <hi rend="italic">PC</hi> is the political connections indicator; and <hi rend="italic">CONTROLS</hi> is a vector of control variables. This vector includes: <hi rend="italic">PCOWN</hi>, the politician ownership; <hi rend="italic">OUTOWN</hi>, the fractional equity ownership of the outside largest shareholder; <hi rend="italic">INST</hi>, the fractional equity ownership of the institutional shareholder; <hi rend="italic">SIZE</hi>, the natural logarithm for the book value of total assets; <hi rend="italic">LEV</hi>, the total liabilities divided by total assets; <hi rend="italic">MTB</hi>, the market value of the equity divided by the book value of the equity; <hi rend="italic">CFO</hi>, the cash flows from operating activities scaled by lagged total assets; <hi rend="italic">LAGNI</hi>, prior net income scaled by market value of equity; <hi rend="italic">AGE</hi>, the number of listed firm years; <hi rend="italic">VOLRET</hi>, the standard deviation for the daily stock returns; <hi rend="italic">LINC</hi>, the depreciation expense scaled by lagged total assets; and <hi rend="italic">LIT</hi>, an indicator variable set to one if the firm is in a technology industry, otherwise zero. </p>
</text>
