<text id="autogum_interview_doc180" title="part2_Wikinews interviews former Republican U.S. Senator Bob Smith on his latest run for office" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-06-21" dateModified="2014-12-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_former_Republican_U.S._Senator_Bob_Smith_on_his_latest_run_for_office" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">J.F.</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Your opponents in the Republican primary are current Governor Charlie Crist and former Speaker of the Florida House Marco Rubio. Why do feel that you are a better candidate than either of them?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Smith</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> :I have great respect both for Governor Crist and Speaker Rubio.  They have served the state well.  My entrance into this race is a unique opportunity for Florida to elect a non-incumbent that has the knowledge and experience provided by two terms in the Senate.</p>
<p>I started my career in the U.S. Congress in 1984.  I fought alongside President Reagan on cutting taxes and strengthening the military.  My service on the Armed Services Committee for 12 years, where I was the Chairman of the Strategic Forces and Acquisition and Technology Subcommittees, provided me with critical knowledge in the areas of missile defense, intelligence and other national security issues.</p>
<p>With all due respect, Governor Crist and Speaker Rubio do not have the experience to provide leadership on the national and international issues that Florida and America face.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">J.F.</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Both Governor Crist and Speaker Rubio are currently raising funds and building up grassroots support for their respective campaigns. They also hold commanding leads over you in recent polls. Are you going to begin campaigning aggressively this summer? Do you believe that you will be able to substantially increase your standing in the polls anytime in the foreseeable future?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Smith</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> :I formally announced my candidacy in the first week of June, and I have just begun to actively campaign and raise funds throughout the state.  I admit that I will have to work hard to achieve name recognition among Floridians equivalent to Governor Crist and Speaker Rubio. The election is over a year away, and polls this far out are not relevant.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">J.F.</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">If you are able to win the primary, do you feel that you will be able to defeat U.S. Representative Kendrick Meek, the presumptive Democrat nominee, in the general election?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Smith</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> :As a preliminary matter, it is up to the Democratic Party to select their nominee.  I can defeat whomever the Democratic Party nominates.  I believe I can unite the Republican Party in Florida, and united we will prevail.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">J.F.</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">If elected to the Senate, what will be your top priorities upon taking office?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Smith</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> :In 2010, we must deliver a message that appeals to all members of the Republican Party, and that will appeal to Floridians in the general election.  I believe this message encompasses:
<list type="unordered"><item>fiscal prudence – not just tax breaks, but controlling the growth of government,</item>
<item>ensuring that our veterans are protected and that our military has the resources it needs to protect our country,</item>
<item>reestablishing the integrity of the financial system,</item>
<item>expediting the disposal of government ownership interests in American business,</item>
<item>working with healthcare providers and other experts to achieve the goal of affordable health insurance, while ensuring that the government is not in the business of providing healthcare and that patient choice comes first,</item>
<item>fixing Social Security so that it is self-funded, as it was originally intended, and</item>
<item>revising our immigration policies so that they actually work.</item></list></p>
</text>
