<text id="autogum_interview_doc532" title="part5_Billy West, voice of Ren and Stimpy, Futurama, on the rough start that shaped his life" shortTile="partbilly-west-voice" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-13" dateModified="2013-06-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Billy_West%2C_voice_of_Ren_and_Stimpy%2C_Futurama%2C_on_the_rough_start_that_shaped_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  Sure. That’s what I mean about some people having naturally quirky voices. You’ve heard people in your life, like you meet a girl, a full-grown woman, who goes [<hi rend="italic">in high pitched squeal</hi>], “I wanted to ask you.” And you go, 'Drop the act. Is this a put-on?'  And I go, “Shit, you should be doing cartoons!”</p>
<head id='"It_was_a_horror_chamber_where_I_grew_up"'>"It was a horror chamber where I grew up"</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is how you developed your talent when you were younger based upon imitating others? You would hear things that would leave impressions on you and you would want to imitate them? But <hi rend="italic">why</hi> would you want to imitate them?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  Because I had no role models.  My dad was a certifiable <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/sociopath">psycho</ref> and he made my life a living hell and it was a horror chamber where I grew up and when I grew up.  The guy used to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Child%20abuse">beat the daylights out of me</ref> left and right, for any random reason. He was a raving <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alcoholic">alchie</ref>. I grew up with him making fun of me. I was forced to retreat into a world where I couldn’t get hurt or beat up or anything like that.</p>
<hi rend="bold">[My father] used to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Child%20abuse">beat the daylights out of me</ref> left and right, for any random reason. He was a raving <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alcoholic">alchie</ref>. I grew up with him making fun of me. I was forced to retreat into a world where I couldn’t get hurt or beat up or anything like that.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right"><hi rend="bold">—Billy West on beginning to do voices</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It was escapism ...?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  Well yeah. You gotta understand, it was like I was a little kid. I’m not a magical being. My dad tried to kill me about fifteen times.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So when you would escape into those voices, you felt a sense of safety?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  Yes. 'Cause I was surrounded by things that wouldn’t be a threat to me.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And things that you could control through your own voice.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  Yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Whereas you couldn’t control what an alcoholic authority figure was going to do.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  I was like an alien; I was an observation unit, trying to study the human condition, not consciously, but because I had to. I could tell you the kind of night I was going to have from the sound of the key in the door or the way the car pulled up. I was hyper vigilant. So all I was, was this unit from space that had nothing but data gathering and sensory equipment.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What was your dad’s reaction to your doing voices?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  It didn’t register on the radar because, number one, I wasn’t really doing it in the time I spent with him. The other thing was that he was a frustrated talent. He could sit down at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/piano">piano</ref> and just start playing it, having no lessons or training. He could do dialogs and he could do voices.  He was very funny, you know, among his friends and all that. He was also a musician, a drummer. And I became a musician except I wasn’t a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/drummer">drummer</ref>, I was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/guitar%20player">guitar player</ref>.  The thing is, he could never make it pay. All he had was a string of jobs. Driving a beer truck then driving a soda pop truck then driving an ice cream truck. You know what I mean? Like a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ralph%20Kramden">Ralph Kramden</ref> kind of thing.</p>
</text>
