<text id="autogum_whow_doc124" title="Create an Apple ID for Children" shortTile="create-apple-id-children" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2016-11-29" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Create-an-Apple-ID-for-Children" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Create an Apple ID for Children</head><p>This wikiHow teaches you how to set up Family Sharing in your iCloud Settings, and how to use Family Sharing to create an Apple ID for a child.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>iPhone or iPad</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open your iOS device’s settings. Do this by tapping the gear icon on one of the device’s home screens. You may see it inside of a folder called Utilities.</item>
<item>Scroll down and tap . You may have to scroll down a few times to find it.</item>
<item>Tap . When you set up Family Sharing, you become the family “organizer,” which means you can add a child account for which you’ll have full administrative control.</item>
<item>Tap .</item>
<item>Tap  to use confirm that you want to be the organizer for this family.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you see a different account listed than your own, click the link at the bottom that says “Not [xxx] or want to use a different ID?” and then sign in.</item></list></item>
<item>Tap  to make your iTunes and App Store purchases available to the family. Now you won’t have to pay for the same app twice if you want it on multiple family members’ devices.</item>
<item>Enter your credit card information. This is required to prove that you’re an adult.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you’ve already entered your credit card information, tap  to confirm that you want to use the card on file.</item></list></item>
<item>Tap . This allows other members of your family to see your whereabouts in <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Find_Your_Friends_in_iOS_9">Find My Friends.</ref> When finished, you’ll return to the Family screen.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you don’t want to share your location, tap .</item></list></item>
<item>Tap the blue  link. You may have to scroll down to locate it.</item>
<item>Enter the child’s birth date and tap .</item>
<item>Tap  to accept the Parental Disclosure.</item>
<item>Verify your credit card information and tap .</item>
<item>Enter your child’s name and tap .</item>
<item>Enter an Apple ID for your child and tap . This is the name your child will use to sign in to Apple devices and services.</item>
<item>Follow the on-screen instructions to set up a new password and security questions.</item>
<item>Make sure “Ask to Buy” is on and tap . When enabled, iTunes or App Store purchases your child attempts to make will require your permission.</item>
<item>Tap so your child’s location appears in <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Find_Your_Friends_in_iOS_9">Find My Friends.</ref> Only family members will see your child’s location.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you don’t want to enable location sharing for your child, tap  instead.</item></list></item>
<item>Tap  to accept the Terms and Conditions. Once this step is complete, your child’s account is ready to use. Your child can now sign in to any Apple device or service with their new Apple ID.</item></list>
<head>Mac</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Click the Apple menu. It’s the black apple-shaped icon on the far left of the menu bar at the top of the screen.</item>
<item>Click .</item>
<item>Click . If you don’t see this option, click the button that looks like three rows of dots at the top of the screen, or .</item>
<item>Click . It’s on the left sign of the screen, beneath your name and photo.
<list type="unordered"><item>When you set up Family Sharing, you become the family “organizer,” which means you can add a child account for which you’ll have full administrative control.</item>
<item>If you’ve already set up Family Sharing, you’ll see  instead. Click this and then skip to step 11.</item></list></item>
<item>Read the description of Family Sharing and click .</item>
<item>Click  to confirm that you want to be the organizer for the family. The Family organizer is able to add people to the family, including child accounts.</item>
<item>Click  to confirm that your iTunes and App Store purchases will be available on your family’s devices.</item>
<item>Enter your credit card information and click . This is required to add an Apple ID for a child, though your card will not be charged.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you already have a credit card associated with your account, it should appear here with only the last 4 digits visible.</item></list></item>
<item>Choose whether or not to share your location with other members of your family. If you choose “Share your location,” other members of your family will be able to see you in “Find My Friends.”</item>
<item>Click . Now you’ll return to the Family Sharing screen.</item>
<item>Click  or . The appearance of the button may vary depending on your version of macOS.</item>
<item>Click .</item>
<item>Enter your child’s information into the “Enter the child’s information” screen.
<list type="unordered"><item>Choose your child’s birthday from the dropdown menus.</item>
<item>Type a new Apple ID (the username they’ll use to log into Apple products and services) for your child.</item>
<item>Enter and verify a new password.</item>
<item>Place a check next to “Share your child’s location with your family” so that you can find your child under <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Find_Your_Friends_in_iOS_9">Find my Friends</ref>.</item>
<item>Click .</item></list></item>
<item>Follow the prompts to complete the account setup. You’ll create security questions, confirm your credit card, and accept the Apple ID agreement. When the setup is complete, you’ll return to the Family Sharing screen.</item>
<item>Click your child’s account on the left side of Family Sharing.</item>
<item>Make sure “Ask to Buy” is checked. This makes it so every purchase your child attempts to make from iTunes or the App Store will prompt you to give permission.</item>
<item>Click . Your child can now sign in to any Apple service or product using their new username and password.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Your email address becomes the rescue address for your child’s account. If your child loses their password, the recovery email will be sent to you.</item>
<item>Your child must stay a member of the Family account until they are 13.</item></list>
</text>
