<text id="autogum_reddit_doc067" title="I think I picked the wrong daycare" shortTile="think-picked-wrong" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-04-30" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8g0d2p" speakerList="#bananasmcgee, #jayjay191918" speakerCount="2">
<head>I think I picked the wrong daycare</head>
<sp who="#jayjay191918">
<p>So I’ll do my best to keep this brief. My son is 8 months old and has been going to daycare 2 days a week for about a month. It is a really nice facility with large classrooms a gym and a playground. Aesthetically speaking it is a 10/10. My wife and I are first time parents so we aren’t sure if we are overreacting and so I guess I’m looking for your opinions. I handle drop offs in the morning and my wife “Jen” does pickups on her way home from work. We have been noticing things lately that are minor but when put together seem to paint a worrisome picture. For example: It took them 2 weeks to assign him a cubby for his stuff. The daily report isn’t always filled out when Jen picks him up. Jen then has to ask a bunch of questions about the day in order to know how things went. We live in the northeast and finally got some nice weather but They didn’t take the kids outside even though they have a beautiful fenced in playground. And there are some other things that all together show laziness. Now for what I consider to be the really bad part. Yesterday the school sent us an email informing us that teacher appreciation week is coming up. They have events planned which consist of Things like “bring breakfast for the teachers on Monday” “bring flowers on Tuesday” “lunch on Wednesday” etc I thought this was a little strange and inconvenient but then it got worse. Attached to the email was what I can only describe as Christmas lists for each teacher. The stores they want gift cards to. Favorite restaurants etc. The lists also included things like “Victoria secrets gift card” “Jack daniels” “cash money”. ARE YOU KIDDING ME! How unprofessional is this? Do other daycares do this? This place seems bad and I think we are pulling him out. Am I overreacting? It feels like they are holding me hostage. If I don’t buy you a nice gift are you not going to change my kids diaper? I’m obviously happy to participate in the week. I would get you a Starbucks gift card or something but this just seems crazy. Thanks for listening to a concerned daddy. </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#bananasmcgee">
<p>I guess I must be in the minority too because I think the teacher appreciation week is completely inappropriate. Don't get me wrong. We've given gift cards as a token of our appreciation at Christmas time, brought the teachers chocolates at Valentine's Day, etc. However, flat out asking for specific gift cards and making a whole week of it sounds so gift grabby. </p>
</sp>
</text>
