<text id="autogum_voyage_doc452" title="Iriomote" shortTile="iriomote" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=15731" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Iriomote</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.iriomote.com/">Iriomote</ref></hi> (西表) is the largest of the <ref target="Yaeyama%20Islands">Yaeyama Islands</ref> of <ref target="Okinawa">Okinawa</ref>, <ref target="Japan">Japan</ref>.</p>
<head>Understand</head>
<p>While the second-largest of all Okinawa islands, Iriomote's population is barely over 2,000 and visitors, at over 150,000 a year, outnumber residents by almost 100:1. 90% of the island is covered in dense jungles and swampy mangroves, most of which are either part of the <ref target="http://www.env.go.jp/en/nature/nps/park/iriomote/index.html">Iriomote National Park</ref> or protected state land, and the island is unquestionably one of the few remaining great wildernesses of Japan.</p>

<p>Pretty much all of the island's population lives along the coast. Clockwise from the west, the major settlements are <hi rend="bold">Shirahama</hi> (白浜), <hi rend="bold">Uehara</hi> (上原), <hi rend="bold">Funaura</hi> (船浦) and <hi rend="bold">Ōhara</hi> (大原). The southern stretch between Ohara and Shirahama is effectively untouched coastline, with no roads and only a few isolated fishing villages near the western end.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>Despite its size Iriomote does not even have a landing strip, so all visitors must arrive by boat. The nearest airport is in neighboring <ref target="Ishigaki">Ishigaki</ref>.</p>

<p>Two ports on the island have services from Ishigaki, operated by <ref target="http://www.aneikankou.co.jp/">Anei Kankō</ref> and <ref target="http://www.yaeyama.co.jp/">Yaeyama Kankō Ferry</ref> (which share tickets offices and boat schedules), and by <ref target="http://www.ishigaki-dream.co.jp/">Ishigaki Dream Kankō Ferry</ref>. Almost all visitors use the rapid services listed below, but dedicated penny-pinchers may opt for Yaeyama's thrice-weekly slow cargo boats to Ohara (2 hours, ¥1070) and Uehara via <ref target="Hatoma">Hatoma</ref> (3 hours, ¥1380) instead. Round-trip tickets are generally available at about 10% discount.</p>

<p>Apparently (unverified) there is also a 4-trip ticket for ¥5,000 which is an especially good deal when going to Uehara which costs about ¥4,000 round-trip to Ishigaki.</p>

<head>East coast</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ohara</hi>, in the south-east coast, is the busiest port on the island and accessible in all but the very worst weather. Anei, Yaeyama and Ishigaki Dream operate boats roughly hourly for a fixed ¥1540 and take about 35 minutes.</p>

<head>Northwest coast</head>
<p>Anei and Yaeyama boats both service to <hi rend="bold">Uehara</hi> in the north of the island. Both services cost ¥2000 and take about 40 minutes. Some of them also stop in Hatoma, which makes the trip 15 minutes longer. Ishigaki Dream also offers this route, but its two daily ferries stop in Hatoma and the whole trip takes around 70-80 minutes (¥1420).</p>

<p>As of summer 2006, nearby Funaura port is no longer used by regular ferry traffic.</p>

<p>Note that northwest coast services are subject to cancellation (欠航 <hi rend="italic">kekkō</hi>) if there is a strong north wind, which happens particularly frequently in the winter (in autumn-winter 2016, in average half the time). In this case your ¥2000 will get you to Ohara by boat and then a free bus transfer to anywhere between Ohara and Shirahama. In case of cancellation for the return to Ishigaki, allow one hour to go by bus from Uehara to Ohara where you will be able to take a ferry (which follows Ohara schedule); relevant time-tables for buses and ferries available at the <ref target="http://www.aneikankou.co.jp/files/manager/pdf/iriomote_bus.pdf">bottom of this page</ref>.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>The port Uehara is probably your preferred place to start exploring the island. Most sights are relatively easy to reach from here. Bike, Scooter, and Car rental is possible very close to the harbor.</p>

<p>Public transport on Iriomote is rather limited, but most lodges on the island offer free transfers to/from the nearest port, and both Anei and Yaeyama operate free shuttle services timed to meet ferry departures.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>Iriomote Kōtsū runs 5 services per day in each direction from Shirahama to Funaura (30 min, ¥390), 3 of which continue across the north coast to Ohara on the east (from Funaura 50 min, ¥670). Tell the driver where you're going when getting on and pay when you get off. A three-day bus pass is also offered at ¥1000 per person.</p>

<head>On foot</head>
<p>The 20-km-long and demanding "Iriomote-jima Island Nature Trail" crosses the island. The southern terminus is over 1 km from the Ohara port, and not labeled well, so a north-to-south passage, beginning with the Urauchi River cruise, is the recommended route. The jungle is home to <hi rend="bold">habu vipers</hi>, which though rare, are venomous. After a Japanese hiker went missing in 2003, signs now ask hikers attempting the cross-island hike to submit a proposal to the local police department.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>You can rent a car at several locations on the island. One of them is at a gas station just outside of the Uehara port ( ). <hi rend="bold">Important</hi>: An international driver licence will <hi rend="italic">not</hi> suffice. An additional official translation into Japanese is required (October 2016). The same conditions apply for scooter rentals, which are also available and a fun way to explore the island.</p>

<head>By bike</head>
<p>If all else fails or you like the idea, you can rent a bike. Locks are usually not necessary and as a result you won't get one with you rental. Bikes may be a cheap alternative (as low as ¥500) but are usually very small (people up to 165 cm can ride comfortably), which makes distances beyond 3 km a nuisance.</p>

<p>The Uehara gas station above also rents roadster bicycles with several gears and an integrated lock. They are comfortable for people 180-cm tall and rental for several days is available.</p>

<p>Another place to rent out bikes, which is very close to the Uehara port, is Murata's School of Nature ( ). Bikes are in good technical condition have a gear shift, but also have the size limitations as mentioned above.</p>

<head>See</head>
<p>Around a third of the island is designated as the <hi rend="bold">Iriomote National Park</hi> (西表国立公園 <hi rend="italic">Iriomote-kokuritsukōen</hi>), the only national park in all of Okinawa. The park's most famous denizen is the <hi rend="bold">Iriomote wildcat</hi> (イリオモテヤマネコ <hi rend="italic">Iriomote yamaneko</hi>), an endangered creature found only on this island. Alas, the critter is nocturnal and very rarely seen. Other more readily viewable flora and fauna include the giant mangrove trees known as <hi rend="italic">sakishimasuo-no-ki,</hi> a range of water birds, and lizards, including Japan's largest lizard, a skink, reaching up to 2 feet in length.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Iriomote Wildlife Center</hi>, on the east side of the island, provides information on Iriomote wildlife including the Yamaneko wild cat. The center is open most days until 16:00.</item>
</list>
</text>
