<text id="autogum_reddit_doc026" title="Advice needed: I want to resign but an email agreement holds me back" shortTile="advice-needed-want" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-05-31" dateModified="2018-05-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8nnbtr" speakerList="#computer_d, #nyenyo" speakerCount="2">
<head>Advice needed: I want to resign but an email agreement holds me back</head>
<sp who="#nyenyo">
<p>To give context, I'm working as a Software Tester in a small 30-people company. 2 months ago, my lead/supervisor left the company. After her leaving was announced, the rest of the test team were asked if any of us wanted to take some of the responsibilities. I thought about it a lot and then considered the offer as it would be a good chance for me to progress in my career. I sent them an email that I am interested, and they offered me the new title plus a new base salary. I do understand that this new position means additional responsibilities -- cue "With great power comes great resposibility". They sent me an email of my new responsibilities and new salary (they said it will be included in the new contract which they have not provided until now). Also included in the email is them saying that I will "stay in the role or the medium term and not look to move" as they are expecting "my commitment to match their commitment to me". Before my previous lead left, there are 3 of us in the team. After she left, we hired a new member of the team. A week ago, my other team member announced his resignation. In a months time, there will only be two of us left. Yesterday, my supervisor told me that they will be hiring a new employee, only that this new employee will be for a different team. Since that email, I can honestly say that I have worked very hard to fulfill the responsibilities included in my new position. But I have underestimated the pressure they will be putting me in. Each and every one-on-one meetings that I had with my supervisor, I have informed them of the increasing work being passed on to our team. Now that we will have one less member, they still haven't considered having an additional test resource. Instead, they will be adding a new developer -- which means there's more work for us. In addition to this, the developers are always delayed in their deployment to our test environment, thus passing the pressure for the test team to complete it by the deadline. I have been very vocal about these issues but it seems like they are not even considering any of my opinions on these matters. Yesterday, when I met with my previous lead, and my co-worker that will be leaving, they mentioned that they felt like the company does not value them and they do not feel appreciated. My girlfriend told me the same thing. She even asked me if we have a yearly engagement survey as they do have that in their company -- but we do not have those surveys. I don't know what to do next. I wanted to move on to a different company because of these things, but I am not sure if I am legally bound to stay here for a year more. I do not have a new contract, only the email with my new title, reposibilities and salary. But I did respond to the email that I do understand the details mentioned. TLDR; Stupid me asked for a promotion to forward my career even though I have not been happy with the company. I had a verbal agreement and in email (no signature given or whatever) that I will stay for medium term with the company but now I want to go. Am I legally bound to stay? Are they likely to hold me accountable or sue me if I resign? Any advice? Update: Sorry for the confusion. I am on a permanent role. The agreement proposed by the company is that I stay for a medium term. </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#computer_d">
<p>&gt;but I am not sure if I am legally bound to stay here for a year more. I do not have a new contract, only the email with my new title, reposibilities and salary. But I did respond to the email that I do understand the details mentioned. </p>
<p>You're free, mate. Short of some awkwardness if they try to screw you on annual pay-out, you should be sweet to leave. If you haven't signed shit you're fine. An email agreement is not a legal contract. </p>
<p>Don't burn bridges though. Perhaps you can sit down with your manager and explain you're giving them your notice due to the issues you feel they have not addressed. It'll either push them to do more to meet your requests or they'll just let you go like you wish. </p>
<p>Good luck!</p>
</sp>
</text>
