<text id="autogum_interview_doc842" title="part12_ACLU President Strossen on religion, drugs, guns and impeaching George Bush" shortTile="partaclu-president" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-30" dateModified="2019-02-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/ACLU_President_Strossen_on_religion%2C_drugs%2C_guns_and_impeaching_George_Bush" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But they see it as voluntary service.  It’s a voluntary army.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  I wish that it really were.  I think nobody who volunteered for it was volunteering for the tours of duty—even forget the danger they are facing—but the extended time, it’s off the charts.  Chuck Hagel today gave us the exact details, so don’t quote me on this because he’s an expert and I’m not, but the order of magnitude used to be 7 months, but now it’s 15 months, or 18 months, or 21 months, and then it’s being doubled and you are not able to have leave in between.  So, they volunteered for one type of duty in terms of the amount of time, but they are getting something entirely different from that.  Number two is query how realistic the choice is for the people who are going into it if they don’t have many other options—or any other options—to get an education, to get a job, to get the skills and the training—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  --That’s what Talese said.  <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sam_Brownback_on_running_for_President,_gay_rights,_the_Middle_East_and_religion">Senator Brownback told me</ref> he is against conscription, and it’s interesting that the people who are most for the war are the people who are most for a voluntary army.  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  Maybe they believe that those would be the people who are most highly-motivated.  I mean in theory, you would see that advantage.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Rangel’s bent is that if people were actually fighting in the wars, or forced to fight, that it would bring public opinion against the war.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  I think in terms of Constitutional Law terms, but remember that famous old case by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20Marshall">John Marshall</ref>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/McCulloch%20v.%20Maryland">McCulloch v. Maryland</ref></hi>, where the state of Maryland was not allowed to tax the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bank%20of%20the%20United%20States">Bank of the United States</ref>, and he set out a principle that is a pervasive equal protection principle, that those who are going to bear the burden should have an opportunity to participate in the decision-making.  This is the flip side of it; you may not impose the burden unless you are sharing in the responsibility.  There’s an accountability, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reciprocity">reciprocity</ref> that State A may not impose a tax on State B is the same thing as saying, people who are not fighting the war may not send off those who are.</p>
<head id="Should_George_Bush_be_impeached?">Should George Bush be impeached?</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Movement%20to%20impeach%20George%20W.%20Bush">George Bush should be impeached</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  I think there is a case for him to be impeached, but I don’t think it would be a good idea.  The reason I say there is a case because partly under the Constitution it’s high crimes and misdemeanors, which are not defined and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Impeachment%20of%20Bill%20Clinton">latest precedent we have is having a blow job</ref> in the Oval Office and lying about it is considered to be a high crime and misdemeanor.  Well, Bush, has clearly lied to Congress, the American People, to the media about much more serious infractions and violations of the Constitution.  He’s had a view that as Commander-in-Chief he can do whatever he wants, that he’s above the law, that he doesn’t have to abide by the laws that are duly passed by Congress.  In one breath he is signing them, and in another breath he is saying he doesn’t have to follow them.  So, I think if what Clinton did can be considered a high crime and misdemeanor then what Bush did could be.</p>
</text>
