<text id="autogum_voyage_doc90" title="Watford" shortTile="watford" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=38684" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Watford</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Watford</hi> is one of the larger towns in <ref target="Hertfordshire">Hertfordshire</ref>, <ref target="England">England</ref>, and has approximately 80,000 citizens.</p>

<head>By road</head>
<p>Watford, like <ref target="Hounslow">Hounslow</ref> &amp; <ref target="Waltham%20Cross">Waltham Cross</ref>, originally rose to prominence as a coaching town (a kind of 18th-century motorway services) because many roads pass through the area.</p>

<head>Non-Motorway Road Access</head>
<p>Watford, as a coaching town, has many road passing through it, but the fastest one is the A41, a 'green' (semi-motorway) A-road. Exit at M1J5 (A4008) or Hunton Bridge roundabout (A411).</p>

<head>M1</head>
<p>Watford Herts is NOT near the Watford Gap: that is named after Watford Northants. Watford Herts is served by Junction (1|5) Watford, the 1st universal-access junction (unless you count Junction (1|3) Scratchwood, which requires prior arrangement). Leave at (1|5) Watford &amp; take the A4008.</p>

<head>M25</head>
<p>Take Junction (25|19) Hunton Bridge or (25|21A) Bricket Wood East.</p>

<head>By rail</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Watford Junction station</hi>. Watford Junction is a large station that offers many connections. </item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Virgin Trains</hi>: Virgin Trains run express services on the West Coast Mainline &amp; branches, some of them stopping at Watford Junction. The service has buffet, Wi-Fi &amp; at-seat electricity sockets. They are more expensive than regular trains &amp; do not sell tickets solely between London &amp; Watford Junction, but are useful if travelling from further north.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">London Midland</hi>: This regional rail provider serves Watford Junction with most trains. Most of these go non-stop into <ref target="London%20Euston">London Euston</ref>, but the line has dedicated platforms at Bushey, Harrow &amp; Wealdstone, Wembley Central &amp; Queens Park. A non-stop train will generally take 12 minutes. They accept general tickets &amp; Oyster cards.</item>
<item> <ref target="https://tfl.gov.uk/overground/stop/HUBWFJ/watford-junction"><hi rend="bold">London Overground</hi></ref>: The Watford DC line of the London Overground runs local services to Watford every 10 minutes. It serves Watford Junction &amp; Watford High St. These trains take a long time, but serve Willesden Junction, which is useful as an interchange, &amp; have interchange with the Bakerloo line. Watford High St. is closer to the town centre than Watford Junction &amp; cheaper, as the boundary of zones 8 &amp; 9A runs between the two stations.</item>
<item> <ref target="https://tfl.gov.uk/tube/stop/940GZZLUWAF/watford-underground-station"><hi rend="bold">Metropolitan Line</hi></ref>: The London Underground's Metropolitan line runs from Watford station, actually located 0.8 miles away from the High St. in Cassiobury Park. Direct trains run every 10 minutes to Baker St. (Although an extension of the line though Watford High St, to Watford Junction has been formerly proposed, no firm date for construction or opening has been announced.)</item>
</list>



<head>By coach or canal</head>
<p>Frequent coaches serve Watford town centre from <ref target="Heathrow%20Airport">Heathrow Airport</ref> (Bus 724, 45 mins) and <ref target="Luton%20Airport">Luton Airport</ref> (Bus <date when="321-01-01">321, 1.5</date> hours).</p>

<p>The Grand Junction Canal also passes to the West of Watford, bordering Cassiobury Park.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>Most attractions in Watford are within walking distance of each other and do not require buses or trains.</p>

<p>It is worth noting all Hertfordshire buses offer an 'Explorer' ticket which permits a maximum of 2 adults, 2 adults and 2 children or 1 adult with 3 children to unlimited travel for £7. It is often worth doing as it can save money even if you are on your own.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Warner Bros. Studio Tour</hi>, ☏ 08450 840 900 (high cost number) . Take a tour around the studios where Harry Potter was filmed and visit the large gift shop. Buses to the studio can be taken from Watford Junction. (must be purchased in advance, 2019 prices) Adult: £45, Child (5-15 years old): £37, Infant (0-4 years): Free. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Watford Palace Theatre</hi>, ☏ +44 1923 225671 . </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Watford Museum</hi>, ☏ +44 1923 232297 . </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Watford Football Club</hi>. They are one of the smaller clubs in English football but of late have seen their fortunes improve, returning to the premiership for the first time in 10 years. </item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>
<p>There are plenty of things to do in Watford. For example, visit the Warner Bros Studios in north Watford, shop in the town centre, stroll through Cassiobury Park, play golf at Watford TopGolf or even visit Woodside Leisure Park, home of Vue cinema, indoor play areas and some restaurants. Watford is also home to many leisure centres, for sporting activities, including a running and athletics track in Garston. Watford Coloseum hosts many comedy shows and live music concerts, check out their website for upcoming shows.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Watch football</hi> (ie soccer) at Watford FC. They play in the Premier League, the top tier of English football. Their stadium (capacity 21,500) is at Vicarage Road, half a mile west of town centre. It's shared with Saracens rugby club.</p>

<head>Buy</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">intu Watford</hi> (The Harlequin), 201 The Harlequin, Watford, WD17 2UB, ☏ +44 1923 250292 , ✉ watford.information@intu.co.uk . Mon-Wed 09:00-18:00, Thu 09:00-21:00, Fri 09:00-18:00, Sat 09:00-19:00, Sun 11:00-17:00. This is the main shopping mall with John Lewis, Jane Norman, French Connection Outlet, Monsoon and separate Accesorize in addition to Acessorize in the Monsoon, River Island, Anne Summers, La Senza, Zara, WHSmith (post office at the back), Pineapple, Lush, GAME and many other shops. There are also New Look, Topshop (inc Topman), Computer Exchange, The End and Next to Choice (a Next outlet) on the High Street. </item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>
<p>There are <hi rend="italic">many</hi> choices.</p>

<p>For <hi rend="bold">Restaurants</hi>, there is Middletons Steakhouse and Grill, Flower Drum (Chinese), Flame (Chinese buffet), various Pizza restaurants (Pizza et pizza, Zinco, Ask, Pizza Hut, Pizza Express), Caribbean, Japanese (Hanko)...</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Fast food</hi> - Two McDonald's (With an extra 2 in the north of the town), Five Guys, two Subways, various pizza takeaway places (Dominos, Pizza hut, Pizza express and various kebab shops. Roosters Peri Peri Chicken is halal and serves very inexpensive but absolutely delicious chicken meals, including wraps, burgers, etc. and even apple pies and ice cream in the summer. Try the chicken burger meal. Yum. For a sit down, go to Pepe's, opposite the indoor market (behind Poundland) which serves Greek Cypriot fare as well as burgers, steaks, sandwiches, puddings etc.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Vegetarian</hi> - GoKula Vegetarian Cafe, a vegetarian and vegan fast food restaurant with links to the nearby Hari Krishna Temple. A breakfast &amp; brunch restaurant but not evenings . At 65 Market Street.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Halal</hi> - Roosters (burgers, chicken wings, chips...), various kebab shops.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Cafés</hi> - Presence coffee shop with paninis, muffins, with a spa upstairs and a gift shop out front. TJ Hughes has a restaurant/café. For the more traditional fry up, head to Aroma at the bottom of the high street for relatively healthy and delicious breakfasts, chips, burgers etc. Toast, next to Roosters and almost opposite the Palace Theatre, serves sandwiches, juice etc. Try Go Kula cafe on Market Place for vegetarian food but it is a bit hit and miss. Best to go there for a chat, read a few books and meet the local mums and toddlers. The YMCA serves good food - it is behind Poundland/next to the indoor market.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Coffee</hi> Starbucks and Costa in the Harlequin, Caffe Nero by St. Mary's Church on the High Street, Presence in the north end of the High Street, McDonald's on either end of the High Street. Plenty of places with plenty of choice.</p>
</text>
