<text id="autogum_academic_doc593" title="Post-Disaster Building Database Updating Using Automated Deep Learning: An Integration of Pre-Disaster OpenStreetMap and Multi-Temporal Satellite Data" shortTile="postdisaster-building" author="Saman Ghaffarian, Norman Kerle, Edoardo Pasolli, Jamal Jokar Arsanjani" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-4292/11/20/2427/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Materials and Methods</head>
<p>
In this paper, we propose a framework for updating the building database after a disaster through an automated ResUnet-CRF, using outdated OSM building data and multi-temporal satellite images (<figure>Figure 1</figure>). The proposed approach consists of four main steps. </p>

<head> 2.1. Step 1: Co-Registration of OSM Data and Satellite Images</head>
<p>
Since the aim of this study was to use OSM building data as a mask to extract building training samples from the pre-disaster image for a CNN-based approach, we implemented simple preprocesses to create accurate training samples. Since it was observed that the shift on the building footprints was not systematic and the shift direction and amount differs substantially across the area, initially the downloaded OSM data for the pre-disaster time were separated into five sections/regions. Then, rubber sheeting was implemented in ArcGIS, which can also handle small geometric correction as well as shifting the vector maps to adjust and align the building map to the building rooftops in the pre-disaster image (<figure>Figure 2</figure>). In order to achieve good results from the application of the rubber sheeting method, five geographically well-distributed points within each region of interest were used so that the points cover at least the center and the four main directions. Furthermore, the post-disaster satellite images were co-registered/rectified according to the pre-disaster image using ArcGIS by selecting geo-rectification points. </p>

<head> 2.2. Step 2: Training Patch Generation from the Pre-Disaster Image</head>
<p>
Pre-processed data from step 1 were used to automatically generate training samples from the pre-disaster image. Although the mismatch between OSM building footprints and the actual buildings in the pre-disaster images was mostly corrected for in step 1, some matching errors remained. For example, in the case where a building near a vegetated area has a mismatch, the building mask might contain vegetation pixels. In addition, even for a correct match of building and OSM map, some non-building pixels might end up inside the training samples, e.g., a tree may partially cover a rooftop of a building. This might also occur where buildings are next to the sea/water bodies, which may lead to the inclusion of water pixels in the training samples. Hence, to overcome these issues, the Normalized Difference Vegetation Index (NDVI) and Normalized Difference Water Index (NDWI) indices were computed for the pre-disaster image to exclude vegetated areas, trees, and water bodies from the building mask. To do so, NDVI and NDWI masks were computed based on pre-defined thresholds and those pixels falling into the masks were removed from the building training class. Training patches with a height and width of 512 pixels were extracted from the entire image. Moreover, in order to increase the training samples, more patches were generated from the same area by shifting the starting point of the generation of the patches by 100 pixels in both x and y directions. This procedure was conducted three times to obtain different image patches from the same area and then the suitable training samples were selected from those to train the network. In total, 780 image patches were selected to be used as the initial training sample set. In addition, 542 image patches were selected for each of the disaster and post-disaster images to be used for fine-tuning of the model. </p>

<head> 2.3. Step 3: Detecting Damaged and Demolished Buildings</head>
<p>
The OSM building map represents the pre-disaster time; however, since some buildings get damaged during the disaster and are later demolished, direct use of those maps for the training area selection from post-disaster images will lead to inaccurate results as rubble and damaged buildings are included. Hence, the damaged and destroyed buildings should be excluded from the building footprint map before using them for training area selection for post-disaster time images. Since the extraction of the buildings will be based on the advanced proposed deep learning approach, a simple yet accurate method was developed only for the identification of the intact and damaged buildings from the provided OSM building map. </p>

<p>Two measurements based on the Histogram of the Oriented Gradients (HOG) and the edge detection results of the satellite images, namely Variation-HOG (V-HOG) and Edge Density Index (EDI), were used to conduct the change detection between the pre-disaster and post-disaster satellite images. The change detection was performed only on the building masks of the images to distinguish the damaged/demolished and intact buildings in the post-disaster image. </p>

<head> 2.3.1. Variation of HOG (V-HOG)</head>
<p>
HOGs provide powerful features for image representation, which are particularly robust for image-based object classification. They were initially developed for pedestrian identification, however they were then found to be robust features in different applications, including for remote sensing data and for image-based damage detection. </p>
</text>
