<text id="autogum_whow_doc355" title="Find Interesting Stargazing Targets" shortTile="find-interesting" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2016-01-08" dateModified="2016-04-13" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Find-Interesting-Stargazing-Targets" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Find Interesting Stargazing Targets</head><p>Sometimes stargazing can get a bit boring. When it does, it's time to find some interesting targets.You want to see stars big enough to fill half the solar system, black holes heavier than galaxies - you know, the <hi rend="italic">interesting</hi> stuff.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>VY Canis Majoris - one of the galaxy's biggest stars</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find Sirius. It should be fairly obvious, it's the big bright star just below Orion. <figure rend="Find Interesting Stargazing Targets Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find Omicron 2 Canis Majoris and Beta Canis Majoris. A star map is very helpful here. <figure rend="Find Interesting Stargazing Targets Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Imagine that Sirius, Beta and Omicron 2 form the corners of a giant parallelogram. VY Canis Majoris is at the fourth corner. You'll need some good binoculars to see it (7x50's at least), it's a bit dim. <figure rend="Find Interesting Stargazing Targets Step 3.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>T Tauri - a cute little baby star</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find Aldebaran. It's the bright red one in Taurus. <figure rend="Find Interesting Stargazing Targets Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Aldebaran, Theta Tauri, Gamma Tauri, Delta Tauri and Epsilon Tauri form a V-shaped pattern. This is the core of the Hyades star cluster. Aldebaran and Epsilon are at the tips of the V, and Gamma is at the bottom. All five of these stars are visible with the naked eye. <figure rend="Find Interesting Stargazing Targets Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find Delta Tauri. It's the one between Epsilon and Gamma. The one between Gamma and Aldebaran is Theta. You don't want Theta. <figure rend="Find Interesting Stargazing Targets Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Look at it through binoculars. Hundreds of other stars should appear in the vicinity. This is the Hyades star cluster. It can be pretty confusing, but keep looking at Delta and you'll be OK. Using a telescope is good because it's easier to focus on one spot. <figure rend="Find Interesting Stargazing Targets Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>From Delta Tauri, move up (increase declination) slightly. T Tauri is embedded in a nebula (NGC 1555) called Hind's variable nebula, so look for the star in a fuzzy patch. <figure rend="Find Interesting Stargazing Targets Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you're up for a challenge, try to find Struve's lost nebula. This nebula, catalogued as NGC 1554, is near to T Tauri, both physically and in the sky. However, since it's first observation (by Otto Wilhelm von Struve), it has disappeared, earning it the name Struve's lost nebula. Perhaps it's disappeared, perhaps it never existed. We'll probably never know. <figure rend="Find Interesting Stargazing Targets Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>TX Piscium - a red beauty</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find the Great Square of Pegasus. This is one of the most obvious asterisms in the sky, after the Big Dipper and the W of Cassiopeia. It's usually used to find the Andromeda galaxy. <figure rend="Find Interesting Stargazing Targets Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Just below the square should be a faint ring of stars. This is part of the constellation of Pisces. It's very faint, so use binoculars. There should be seven stars in the ring. As TX is variable, you may only see six. If so, come back tomorrow or even later in the night. <figure rend="Find Interesting Stargazing Targets Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find TX Piscium in the ring. Look on Wikipedia's star map of Pisces: it shows five stars in the ring. The white circle to the left of the line connecting Iota and Lambda is TX Piscium. If you can make out the colours of the stars in the sky, TX Piscium is among the reddest that can be seen. <figure rend="Find Interesting Stargazing Targets Step 12.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>The Alpha Persei cluster</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find Capella and Aldebaran. Capella's the really bright one in Auriga. It's very obvious, but don't confuse it with Vega, Deneb, Sirius etc. Aldebaran is the red one in Taurus. <figure rend="Find Interesting Stargazing Targets Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Going up from Aldebaran and right from Capella should lead to Perseus. It should look like two reasonably bright stars (Alpha Persei and Algol the demon star) surrounded by a smattering of dimmer stars. The left-hand bright star (closer to Capella) is Alpha Persei. <figure rend="Find Interesting Stargazing Targets Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Look at Alpha Persei through binoculars. The other stars in the cluster should jump into view. <figure rend="Find Interesting Stargazing Targets Step 15.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Holmberg 15A - a galaxy-sized black hole</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find Beta Ceti, Eta Ceti and Iota Ceti. the best way to do this is to grab a star map and use that. <figure rend="Find Interesting Stargazing Targets Step 16.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Imagine two lines: one connecting Eta and Iota, the other from Beta going north (i.e. from Beta Ceti to Polaris). The black hole is where the lines cross. Holmberg 15A is the central black hole of another galaxy, and has a currently accepted mass of 10 billion times the mass of the Sun (although estimates range up to 310 billion suns), about equal to the Large Magellanic Cloud. <figure rend="Find Interesting Stargazing Targets Step 17.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't bother with binoculars or even a telescope. The galaxy is far too dim to see. You'll have to content yourself with knowing that it's there. <figure rend="Find Interesting Stargazing Targets Step 18.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't expect too much. From Earth, here's what these objects actually look like: 1) Fuzzy dot 2) Fuzzy dot 3) Fuzzy dot 4) Cloud of dots 5) Dim fuzzy dot.</item>
<item>Remember that the Northern and Southern hemispheres have different constellations visible.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't look at the sun</item></list>
</text>
