<text id="autogum_bio_doc409" title="George Gordon, 5th Earl of Huntly" shortTile="george-gordon-th" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-05-28" dateModified="2019-03-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Gordon%2C_5th_Earl_of_Huntly" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>George Gordon, 5th Earl of Huntly</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">George Gordon, 5th Earl of Huntly</hi> (died 19 October 1576), was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Chancellor_of_Scotland">Lord Chancellor of Scotland</ref> and major conspirator of his time.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Second son of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Gordon,_4th_Earl_of_Huntly">4th Earl</ref>, he was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sheriff">Sheriff</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inverness">Inverness</ref> from 1556. As Captain of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Badenoch">Badenoch</ref>, he was in charge of carrying letters sent from Edinburgh to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary_of_Guise">Mary of Guise</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inverness">Inverness</ref> from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunkeld">Dunkeld</ref> throughout the summer of 1556.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary,_Queen_of_Scots">Mary, Queen of Scots</ref> came north to reduce the power of the Gordons and take <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inverness_Castle">Inverness Castle</ref> in 1562. The Earl was captured at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Corrichie">Corrichie</ref> with his other sons, John Gordon and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adam_Gordon_of_Auchindoun">Adam Gordon</ref>, and the Earl suddenly died. John, the eldest, was executed three days later. George (called Lord Gordon) was imprisoned at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kinneil_House">Kinneil House</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> He was attainted and sentenced to death for treason in 1563. He was then imprisoned at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunbar">Dunbar</ref> castle until the marriage of Queen Mary to Darnley in 1565, when his lands and dignities were nominally restored.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>He allied himself with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Hepburn,_4th_Earl_of_Bothwell">James Hepburn, 4th Earl of Bothwell</ref>, who was married to his sister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean_Gordon,_Countess_of_Bothwell">Jean</ref>, and joined Queen Mary at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunbar">Dunbar</ref> after <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Rizzio">Rizzio</ref>'s murder in 1566. He became <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Chancellor_of_Scotland">Lord Chancellor of Scotland</ref> in 1567, and joined Bothwell in the plot to murder the Regent Moray at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jedburgh">Jedburgh</ref>. He signed the bond at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Craigmillar_Castle">Craigmillar Castle</ref> for Darnley's murder, and accompanied Bothwell and Mary on the visit to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Stuart,_Lord_Darnley">Darnley</ref> before his murder.</p>
<p>His estates were fully restored after Bothwell's acquittal in 1567. Bothwell's divorce from his sister was facilitated by his influence over her, and he witnessed the marriage contract between Mary and Bothwell. He connived at the capture of the Queen, and accompanied her to Edinburgh, escaping to the north after her flight. He joined the partisans at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dumbarton_Castle">Dumbarton Castle</ref>, and after a temporary agreement with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Stewart,_1st_Earl_of_Moray">Regent Moray</ref> he conspired for her deliverance from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loch_Leven_Castle">Loch Leven Castle</ref> in 1567. After the Queen's escape to England in 1568, he held all the north in alliance with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archibald_Campbell,_5th_Earl_of_Argyll">Argyll</ref>, but received Mary's order to disperse.</p>
<p>Huntly made an agreement with Regent Moray at St Andrews on 14 May 1569. Huntly was to make up his quarrel with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regent_Morton">Earl of Morton</ref>, repress rebellion amongst his former allies, and surrender a royal cannon kept at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Huntly_Castle">Huntly Castle</ref>. In return, Regent Moray would give the Earl and his followers a remission for all their crimes against the King since 11 June 1567, and promised an Act of Parliament to forgive his role as 'pretended Lieutenant to the Queen's Grace' between August 1568 and March 1569.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>After this temporary submission, continuing the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marian_civil_war">Marian civil war</ref>, he gained possession of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edinburgh_Castle">Edinburgh Castle</ref>, held a parliament, and captured <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matthew_Stewart,_4th_Earl_of_Lennox">Regent Lennox</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stirling">Stirling</ref>. His brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adam_Gordon_of_Auchindoun">Adam Gordon of Auchindoun</ref> was his lieutenant in the north, and fought for Queen Mary in Aberdeenshire and the Mearns.</p>
<p>In 1572 the Earl came to terms with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Douglas,_4th_Earl_of_Morton">Regent Morton</ref>. He died at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Huntly_Castle">Strathbogie</ref>, four years later. An eyewitness description of his death, compiled by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Bannatyne">Richard Bannatyne</ref> describes how he suffered a stroke, or a collapse caused by food-poisoning, while playing football. After the Earl died a number of alleged supernatural events occurred beginning with the sudden collapse of one of the servants. Three companions also collapsed and when revived complained of feeling cold. After the Earl's body was embalmed and taken to the chapel, his brother sat in the hall and heard unexplained sounds from the earl's chamber.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>He married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anne_Hamilton,_Countess_of_Huntly">Anne</ref>, daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Hamilton,_Duke_of_Châtellerault">James Hamilton, Duke of Châtellerault</ref> and had a daughter Jean, and his successor, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Gordon,_1st_Marquess_of_Huntly">George Gordon, 6th Earl of Huntly</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
</text>
