<text id="autogum_whow_doc203" title="Measure Your Child&apos;s Pupillary Distance for Eyeglasses" shortTile="measure-childs-pupillary" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-02-14" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Measure-Your-Child%27s-Pupillary-Distance-for-Eyeglasses" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Measure Your Child's Pupillary Distance for Eyeglasses</head><p>Pupillary distance, or PD, is the measurement of distance in millimeter between the pupils. This information allows opticians to place the optical center of the lenses directly in front of the pupils, allowing for the best vision possible. PD is often included on a prescription. If the measurement is <hi rend="italic">not</hi> included, it is easy to measure for yourself or your child.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Starting Out</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Note the average pupillary distance for children. This measurement ranges from 41 to 53 millimeters. <figure rend="Screen Shot 2018 02 14 at 1.16.35 PM.png"></figure></item>
<item>Choose an appropriate measuring option for your child. There are three options that you may choose from, to get the measurement you need:</item></list>
<head>Measuring PD on a Child who Wears Glasses</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Have your child put on their glasses.</item>
<item>Ask the child to cover one eye. Have them look at an object that is at least 20 feet away.
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, the child could sit inside and focus on a tree or building out of the window.</item></list></item>
<item>Obtain a non-permanent marker. Place a single dot on the lens over the center of the pupil.</item>
<item>Repeat this process with the other eye.</item>
<item>Ensure that the process was completed correctly. With both eyes open, the child should see the dots overlap when they are looking through their marked glasses at a distant object.</item>
<item>Remove the glasses. Measure the distance between the two dots with a millimeter (mm) ruler.</item></list>
<head>Measuring the PD if Your Child Does Not Wear Glasses</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Have your child look at an object that is at least 20 feet away. Again, they could sit inside and focus on a tree or building outside.</item>
<item>Take a millimeter (mm) ruler and measure the distance from the center of one pupil to the center of the other pupil.</item>
<item>Checking your measurement for accuracy. You can make this measure even more accurate by taking a flashlight and shining it in your child’s eyes. The reflection on the pupils will help you to find the center of the pupils. When doing this, make sure that the child continues to look at the distant object.</item>
<item>Repeat the measurement two more times. Whether you are using a flashlight or not, take this measurement at least three times to ensure that your measurements are consistent.</item></list>
<head>Measuring the PD if Your Child has an Eye Muscle Imbalance</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Understand the term <hi rend="italic">eye muscle imbalance</hi>. This imbalance can be the result of some form strabismus. This is a condition the results in an abnormal alignment of the eye, typically causing one to squint, the eyes to cross, or the inability for both eyes to focus on an object at the same time..
<list type="unordered"><item>Extropia is a condition where one or both eyes tend to turn outward.</item>
<item>Esotropia is a strabismus condition where one eye focuses inward.</item></list></item>
<item>Try to obtain the pupillary distance from your optician or doctor. If this is not an option, this is how you take the measurement.
<list type="unordered"><item>If your child’s eyes turn inward or outward when looking at distance, cover one eye and have them look at an object that is at least 20 feet away with the uncovered eye. For example, they could sit inside and focus on a tree or building outside. It is important that the child’s pupils are facing forward when you take this measurement.</item>
<item>Take the measurement in millimeters from the center of the bridge of the nose to the center of the pupil.</item>
<item>By doubling this measurement, you will get an accurate measurement of the distance PD. <hi rend="bold">Note:</hi> You only need to take this measurement for one eye, not both.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Obtaining the Measurement from an Optician</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Use the most comfortable method. For young customers receiving their first pair of glasses, getting the measurement from an optician is the easiest method. As well, it is the best method if you are ordering glasses for a child with an eye muscle imbalance (strabismus). Most opticians will measure PD for free or a small fee.</item>
<item>Measure a child with Strabismus. In the event that you are unable to get the measurement from a doctor or optician, you can take the measurements yourself, as outlined above. You <hi rend="bold">will</hi> need to ensure that your child’s pupils are facing forward when you take the measurement.</item></list>
<head>Locating Pupillary Distance on a Prescription (Rx)</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Understand the PD can be written a number of ways: <figure rend="Screen Shot 2018 02 14 at 1.17.12 PM.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>A single PD number is measured from pupil to pupil. Average PD measurements for kids are between 41 and 53.</item>
<item>The second method results in two PD numbers (one for each eye) and is called a ‘Monocular PD’. This is a measurement from each pupil to the center of the face.</item>
<item>Average measurements for kids are between 20 and 27, for each side.</item></list></item>
<item>Reading an optician's prescription. A prescription can also have two PD numbers. One PD is for close vision and reading, while the other is for distance. The PD for close vision and reading will typically be 3 mm less than the distance PD reading.</item></list>
</text>
