<text id="autogum_interview_doc535" title="part8_Billy West, voice of Ren and Stimpy, Futurama, on the rough start that shaped his life" shortTile="partbilly-west-voice" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-13" dateModified="2013-06-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Billy_West%2C_voice_of_Ren_and_Stimpy%2C_Futurama%2C_on_the_rough_start_that_shaped_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="How_West_dealt_with_his_father's_abuse">How West dealt with his father's abuse</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You said your father was a victim of abuse himself and that pattern often repeats. How did you stop that pattern? Was it through your voice work?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  No, not really. I had a mean streak. But I’m such a dyed-in-the-wool animal lover. I’ve always had pets.  I would be so filled with anger and rage that on my way to school, it was literally a “kick at the cat” as they used to say. You’re angry and you don’t know where to direct it. You’ll kick a wall that has wet paint on it. That’ll teach them.  And hurt yourself doing it. I’d go out and kick the shit out of some little cat or something, just like you know, smack it. You know, go over and go to pet it, then whack it because that’s all I knew. In a weird way, in a weird permutation of the whole situation, to me that was supposed to be love. Cause why would your parent hit you, hurt you? Why? It never makes sense to a kid. And they all used to say, “It’s because I care about you.” But I got over that stuff and what I did was start to hurt myself.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How so?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  I started drinking and doing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drug%20abuse">drugs</ref> when I was about 21. I was playing in a band and it was all part of the picture, you know. It could be rosy for you. You couldn’t survive anywhere else, but in a band you were like golden.  I used to punch walls, cause ruckuses and get into fights wherever I went. You know, throw things at people.</p>
<head id="Rehabilitation_and_sobriety">Rehabilitation and sobriety</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How did you stop the fights and the drugs?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  I had to go to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drug%20rehabilitation">rehab</ref>. I had a job in radio. I stopped playing music. I tried to do some standup comedy, but I don’t have the discipline for it. I used to just go out there and not care if I died or lived or whatever. You know, I’d just say stuff. I was always searching. I just couldn’t go up there and do twelve minutes and pretend like I’d just thought of it, you know, for three years.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are you still <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sobriety">sober</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  Oh yeah. I’ve been sober for 22 years. But I had to go into rehab. I had a series of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Car%20accident">car accidents</ref>.  I almost got killed one night but I just walked away from it chuckling, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drunkenness">smashed</ref>.</p>
<hi rend="bold">I got away with this kind of behavior and it was awful because I was terrorizing people. Not during the day. At night. And stories. There would always be stories and then it would make the papers.</hi>
</text>
