<text id="autogum_academic_doc421" title="Crustose Calicioid Lichens and Fungi in Mountain Cloud Forests of Tanzania" shortTile="crustose-calicioid" author="Stella  Gilbert Temu, Sanja Tibell, Donatha  Damian Tibuhwa, Leif Tibell" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-2607/7/11/491/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
Twenty-six (26) crustose calicioids reported here occur in Tanzania, most of them in mountain cloud forests, but some lowland species have also been included to make the list of crustose calicioids of Tanzania complete. Most species belong to <hi rend="italic">Calicium</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Chaenotheca</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Chaenothecopsis</hi>. </p>

<head> 4.1. Habitats of Cloud Forest Crustose Calicioids</head>
<p>
Calicioids have been shown to occur mainly in undisturbed forests with a long forest continuity, and they have frequently been used as bioindicators of habitats with high species diversity and as indicators of “key habitats”. In addition, many are included in Red lists of several countries. In Tanzania this pattern is also clearly discernable and calicioids mainly occur in mountain cloud forests (middle and upper forest zones) and their niches are found on the bark of old trees and on lignum. </p>

<head> 4.2. Distribution of Tanzanian Cloud Forest Crustose Calicioids</head>
<p>
Most of the Tanzanian crustose calicioids belong to a group of species with wide distributions in cool areas of both hemispheres and occasional occurrence in high mountains of low latitudes. Consequently, they form an important biota in mountain cloud forests and deserve attention in the context of preserving biodiversity and developing conservation policies. The wider distribution of Tanzanian cloud forest calicioids may be detailed on several levels. On the most general level two patterns may be discerned: </p>

<head> 4.2.1. Species with a Main Distribution in Cool Temperate Areas—“Temperate Species”</head>
<p>
Many of the species are widely distributed, with high frequencies in temperate to cool temperature areas of both hemispheres, as well as at high altitudes in mountains at lower latitudes. Thus several are, apart from on the high mountains of Africa, also found along the Andes, but at low latitudes only in its high mountains, e.g., in Equador and Venezuela. Similarly, some of these species occur in high altitudes along the Himalaya and its continuation to the Tasman Belt, e.g., in Papua-New Guinea. <hi rend="italic">Calicium</hi> species, such as <hi rend="italic">C. indicum</hi> Tibell, <hi rend="italic">C. laevigatum</hi> Tibell, <hi rend="italic">C. nobile</hi> Tibell, <hi rend="italic">C. pyriforme</hi> Tibell, <hi rend="italic">C. tenuisporum</hi> Tibell and <hi rend="italic">C. verrucosum</hi> Tibell, are representatives of this group. </p>

<p>In Africa occurrences of this “cool temperate element” are found from the Atlas, at high altitudes of the African volcanoes and the East Arch Mountains down to lower altitudes in Southern Africa. Some of these distributions nowadays appear very disjunct, but dispersal might have happened during Ice Age temperature depressions and associated widening of areas with temperate forests over large parts of Africa in connection with the quaternary glaciations. </p>

<p>The following species are good African representatives: <hi rend="italic">Calicium abietinum</hi> Pers., <hi rend="italic">C. lenticulare</hi> Ach., <hi rend="italic">C. salicinum</hi> Pers., <hi rend="italic">Chaenotheca chrysocephala</hi> (Ach.) Th. Fr., <hi rend="italic">C. furfuracea</hi>, <hi rend="italic">C. hispidula</hi>, <hi rend="italic">C. stemonea</hi>, <hi rend="italic">C. trichialis</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Chaenothecopsis debilis</hi>. </p>

<head> 4.2.2. Species with Main Occurrences in Warm Temperate to Tropical Areas—“Pantropical Species”</head>
<p>
The other type of distributions encountered among Tanzanian cloud forest calicioids comprises species with an often wide distribution in warm temperate to subtropical areas. Here belong, for example, <hi rend="italic">Calicium hyperelloides</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Chaenotheca olivaceorufa</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Chaenothecopsis pilosa</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Heterocyphelium leucampyx</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Mycocalicium victoriae</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Pyrgillus javanicus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Sphinctrina tubaeformis</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Tylophoron moderatum,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">T. protrudens.</hi>
 </p>
</text>
