<text id="autogum_academic_doc653" title="Removal of High Concentrations of Ammonium from Groundwater in a Pilot-Scale System through Aeration at the Bottom Layer of a Chemical Catalytic Oxidation Filter" shortTile="removal-high-concentrations" author="Wushou Zhang, Ruifeng Zhang, Yanfeng Yang, Tinglin Huang, Gang Wen" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/20/3989/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Ammonium is one of the major pollutants found in water sources in China, especially in groundwater. Excessive ammonium in drinking water can cause nitrification in the water distribution system, leading to many problems including corrosion, aesthetic issues and pH decrease. In China, the maximum permitted concentration of ammonium in drinking water is 0.5 mg/L. Therefore, it is meaningful to explore various techniques that can efficiently remove ammonium from drinking water. </p>

<p>Breakpoint chlorination is an effective way to remove ammonium from drinking water. It has low spatial requirement, non-sensitivity to temperature variations and adaptability to existing facilities. However, it can lead to high chlorine consumption and stimulate the formation of undesirable chlorinated by-products in the drinking water. Biological filter and catalytic oxidation are good methods to remove ammonium from drinking water. However, in biological filtration, the removal activity is limited at lower temperatures and the deficiency of some required nutrition. Therefore, some measurements should be taken to improve the ammonium removal efficiency in biofiltration. </p>

<p>An alternative method to biofiltration would be abiotic removal of ammonium, using catalytic oxidation technology. Traditional catalytic oxidation processes can remove ammonia from municipal wastewater effectively using platinum and RuO2/Ti anode as catalysts. However, these processes are used rarely in drinking water treatment systems. Recently, studies report that iron–manganese co-oxide filter film (MeOx) can remove ammonium from drinking water by chemical catalytic oxidation. It has good tolerance to low temperatures and requires a shorter start-up time compared to the conventional biofiltration method, making it a good alternative for ammonium removal from drinking water. </p>

<p>The application of chemical catalytic oxidation technology and its mechanism for ammonium removal has been studied, which showed that ammonium with an average concentration of approximately 1.5–2.0 mg/L could be removed effectively. However, its effectiveness in removing high concentrations of ammonium has not been investigated. Moreover, the ammonium concentration in drinking water can be high in China. It can be up to 2–3.9 mg/L in ground water and 1.45–3.89 mg/L in surface water. In some cases, it can reach up to 8.4 mg/L in raw water sources. Therefore, exploring new methods to remove high concentrations of ammonium is significant to environmental engineering. </p>

<p>With respect to the low concentration of ammonium, high concentrations of ammonium are more difficult to remove based on the limitation of the inadequate dissolve oxygen (DO) concentration in water sources. </p>

<p>DO concentration is generally lower in groundwater than that in surface water and the DO limitation is more critical for ammonium removal. On the one hand, the impact of oxygen transfer is a key factor that influences the ammonium removal and some previous researchers suggested that increasing irrigation velocity could increase the oxygen transfer for satisfying the metabolic requirements of both heterotrophs and autotrophs. On the other hand, the required oxygen was usually supplied by multi-stage water-dropping and spray aeration in drinking water treatment processes when the concentration of ammonium was not too high. However, the aeration method mentioned above cannot supply adequate oxygen to meet the required levels of ammonium oxidation, especially if the ammonium concentration is higher than 2 mg/L. Consequently, exploring new methods to provide adequate oxygen to remove high concentrations of ammonium is significant. </p>

<p>Different from the traditional multi-stage water-dropping and spray aeration, aeration with pure oxygen and compressed air via a microporous aeration set was used in this study to establish a new way for removing high concentrations of ammonium from groundwater by chemical catalytic oxidation filter. The effects of aeration types, aeration rates, and aeration position on ammonium or turbidity removal were investigated. Moreover, ozone, which can inactivate bacteria effectively, was also fed into the filter system to investigate the role of the abiotic chemical catalytic oxidation and the characteristics of the filter materials were examined to explore the removal mechanism of high concentrations of ammonium. </p>
</text>
