<text id="autogum_academic_doc498" title="Dietary Supplementation with Silicon-Enriched Spirulina Improves Arterial Remodeling and Function in Hypertensive Rats" shortTile="dietary-supplementation" author="Joanna Arthur-Ataam, Patrice Bideaux, Azzouz Charrabi, Pierre Sicard, Bérengère Fromy, Kiaoling Liu, Saadia Eddahibi, Côme Pasqualin, Nicolas Jouy, Sylvain Richard, Anne Virsolvy" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6643/11/11/2574/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
Considering the properties and biological role of silicon, we evaluated the effects of nutritional supplementation with silicon-enriched spirulina on vascular remodeling induced by hypertension in a SHR rat model. Our study showed highly beneficial effects including attenuation of arterial pressure and improvement of vascular reactivity. These benefits were associated with reduction in arterial thickness and stiffness caused by the structural remodeling of the aortic wall in SHR. They were mainly attributable to Si enrichment. </p>

<p>Beneficial and safe effects of SpSi supplementation were previously reported in high fat diet-induced models of atherosclerosis in hamsters and metabolic syndrome in rats. Improvement of glucose tolerance, insulin resistance, or dyslipidemia were evidenced with both SpSi and Sp supplementation. However, only SpSi had beneficial effects on arterial function. No toxicity or side effects of SpSi supplement were otherwise observed. Increase of arterial stiffness, reduction of arterial compliance, and distensibility marked by fragmentation of elastin are the main consequences of arterial remodeling occurring in hypertension, obesity and aging. Vascular remodeling in hypertension is characterized by altered ultrastructure due to reduction in elastin and increase in fibrous tissue. Here, we assessed the effect of SpSi on the ultrastructural, mechanical and functional changes characterized in SHR thoracic aorta. These modifications consisted of (i) arterial wall hypertrophy, (ii) fragmentation, linearization, and refolding of elastic fibers, and (iii) impaired contractile and vasorelaxant responses. These changes typified the degenerative processes leading to the reduction of compliance and distensibility described in hypertension and associated with aging. Indeed, in SHR aorta, our results showed enlarged internal diameter and media thickening, increased elastin fragmentation ratio, and lower elastin and collagen levels than in normotensive animals. Consequently, contractility was impaired as evidenced by the decreased response and sensitivities to KCl-induced depolarization and PE. The vasorelaxant responses to both Ach and SNP were also reduced. The enhanced effect of L-NAME on PE-induced contraction suggested that the decrease in the vasodilator capacity of aorta in SHR is due to both the alteration of vascular smooth muscle function and NO bioavailability.  </p>

<p>After three months of supplementation, SpSi substantially corrected and even normalized most of the defects identified in SHR aorta. First, aortic hypertrophy was reduced as shown by morphologic analysis. Higher level of elastin fiber density and mRNA level were associated to a decrease in MMP-9 expression, suggesting that both enhanced elastin biosynthesis and reduced extracellular matrix contributed to media thinning. It is known that hypertensive vascular remodeling involves reorganization and impairment of the extracellular matrix and that MMPs play an important role in this remodeling. Second, we observed an improvement of vascular function after SpSi supplementation. Contractile and vasorelaxant responses were increased in association with an increased sensitivity to the agonists and antagonists tested and a better NO bioavailability. Finally, we found that SHR animals supplemented with SpSi had lower arterial pressure than control SHR. Arterial pressure, although significantly reduced, was still higher than normal pressure which may explain the lack of benefit on cardiac parameters in our experimental conditions (hypertension already established, 3 months of supplementation).  </p>

<p>Another interesting result in our study is that supplementation with Sp alone had no effect in SHR suggesting that the benefits observed with SpSi are genuine effects of Si. The nutritional essentiality of Si is undeniable. This organic element appears as an important structural component of the aortic wall which contributes to elastin and collagen synthesis and stability. Data from animal and human studies demonstrated that dietary Si mitigates the risk of cardiovascular diseases. Si in drinking water has been inversely correlated with mortality rates due to coronary heart diseases in Finland. Reduced damage and thickening of elastic fibers were observed in the aortic wall after silicon supplementation in rabbit models of diet-induced atherosclerosis. Moreover, our results are in line with a previous study reporting reduction in systolic arterial pressure after supplementation with soluble silicon in SHR. In that study, arterial structure was not investigated and enhancement of intracellular magnesium uptake was evoked as a possible mechanism. This is not inconsistent with our findings as Si is supposed to contribute to biological function and affect retention or function of other minerals, such as aluminum or magnesium. Various mechanisms are potentially involved in the beneficial effects of Si. Here, a major result in our study is that SpSi supplementation reverses elastic fiber degradation which is likely to contribute to the overall benefit. The observed regenerative changes of the vascular wall are in line with a Si-related beneficial effect. However, quantification of Si level in the aortic tissue is warranted to validate this hypothesis. </p>
</text>
