<text id="autogum_reddit_doc047" title="Don't Drive For Lyft: The 85 and 105 ride Express Drive Ride Count Requirement is Ridiculous." shortTile="dont-drive-lyft-" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-05-31" dateModified="2018-05-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8nn7cp" speakerList="#SophisticatedPeasant" speakerCount="1">
<head>Don't Drive For Lyft: The 85 and 105 ride Express Drive Ride Count Requirement is Ridiculous.</head>
<sp who="#SophisticatedPeasant">
<p>Yeah, so, honeymoon period is completely over with this gig. I live in the SF Bay Area and am renting the car through Lyft + Car Max at $210 a week. If I do 85 rides, 30 of them Peak Rides, and have a 90% acceptance rate my weekly rental fee is reduced by $100. I seem to be averaging 2 rides an hour during Peak Hours on Weekdays (7-9 am and 5-7 PM). I just made $86 working 5 hours last night between 4 and 9 PM, assuming I get the reduced rental rate that's $15 out of that going towards the rental (or $30 a day, which it may be at this rate), and at 22-25 mpg in the city that's around 3-4 gallons of gas (2018 Nissan Sentra) or around $15 towards gas leaving me with maybe $55 for 5 hours? (having to go Offline to avoid getting pinged and then peeing in your pants every 1.5 hours or more to then spend 5-10 minutes finding somewhere to urinate and not getting paid for it makes a 5 hour drive time day into actually working 6-6.5 hours which makes the proposition that much more absurd, am I down to $9 an hour in the SF Bay area now? Remember, real jobs you can take a bathroom break on the clock). This is my second week into this, the first week I did a little better, earning $640 after the rental deduction ($112, a pro-rated amount after meeting the pro-rated 85 ride count bonus) and 34-35 hours of drive time, which after fuel cost ($100) made for $17 an hour (not counting bathroom breaks, which probably bring this down closer to $15). But that's only because it was busier than normal here in the SF Bay Area on the weekend because of Memorial Day. I literally worked 6 consecutive 6 hour days (going solely by "Drive Time", bathroom breaks bring this closer to 7 hours) I don't know about you but, that's about all I can handle both physically and mentally (sitting for 6 hours a day and dealing with suicidal pedestrians and people who shouldn't even have a drivers license, if youre not from here, come to SF and drive around for a few hours, you will be done, guaranteed). $17 in the SF Bay area is basically minimum wage, and this week I'm not even making that. I just viewed this video from only Jan 2017 and back then apparently the ride count requirement was only 65 rides for NO RENTAL FEE, not 85 rides for $100 off of the $200 rental fee but 65 rides for NO RENTAL FEE with only 30 required for the $100 rental fee. https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gMgeghIj4bM I see "Drive for Lyft" ads willy nilly on craigslist, and just as with the amazon.com warehouse job that similarly had them willy nilly on craigslist (and ended up being grueling slave labor) this job is basically just that, slave labor. You may have read my recent post, where to my dismay in just my first week I had to deal with someone vomiting, mostly out the window of the car while I was moving and made the startling discovery that Lyft is taking 45% of the fare paid by a passenger. https://www.reddit.com/r/Lyft/comments/8n0kjy/the_bonus_scheme_seriously_needs_to_be_a_mix_of/ They don't have to spend 45 minutes off of the clock cleaning up puke parked on the side of the road near a public park, they don't have to nearly get a heart attack from every near miss accident nor the health consequences of prolonged sitting, nor dealing with drunks and their belligerence, so why is their cut nearly 50%? Because of the app? The GPS? LMFAO. No. Sorry, but I'm averse to slave labor, I'm returning the car after hitting the 150 ride requirement for the $500 sign-on bonus this upcoming Monday. Thank god I didn't use a friend's referral code for $500 for him and me but requiring not 150 rides but 430 rides within 90 days. I have a near miss every single day in this city, there is no chance I would have made it 90 days without an accident. Fingers crossed I make it just 4 more days. That's how insane this job is. Oh and getting home and peeing in my pants while I'm running to the bathroom because there's a lack of public restrooms in SF, particularly in the evening, yeah that's fun. I've already had to pull over and urinate right in broad daylight basically standing between the car and a tree on the sidewalk. No health insurance. No upward mobility. This job is the equivalent of a pyramid scheme. And I'm hearing that management is making record profit and throwing lavish parties etc. Nice. I mean how fucking greedy are you? You could dial back your cut percentage from 45% to say maybe 40-42% and it would be doable for many of us (taking us from $17 to $20 on good weeks and $12 to $15 on days like my yesterday). If youre reading this and contemplating driving for Lyft, DON'T. This job is a joke. Lyft is absolutely anally raping all Lyft drivers at the moment and laughing all the way to the bank. Apparently Lyft is taking advantage of the perilous economic situation faced by many Americans, (real unemployment around 22-25%). Don't be another sucker. Find something, anything else. I'm absolutely not kidding when I say that if I had to continue doing this I would rather commit suicide. Update: Talk about a coincidence to what I wrote here. At the end of my shift tonight, around midnight in the Mission district I witnessed another Lyft driver hit a bicyclist. Bicyclist was thrown to the ground, not seriously injured (as far as I could tell) but made a big deal out of it and Lyft driver had to pull over and presumably provide identification and insurance etc. The car was also the same kind of car that is rented out so I'm assuming she was in the Express Drive program. I decided I had enough after that and on the way home, while turning off the Lyft app, two men wearing all black just started walking into the street and had I not stopped messing with the phone when I did (all I did was click to go offline) I would have probably hit them. What is also retarded is that at night the Lyft UI doesn't change to a darker theme and literally blinds you in a way making these two pedestrians that much harder to spot. They weren't in a crosswalk but still, I had to kinda swerve to avoid them, I think they may have been drinking, not sure. 15 more rides to go and I'm done. I plan on doing my rides tomorrow in the day. I made 20 rides today for a whopping total of $97.23 an although the app is only reporting 4.5 hours of drive time I was actually out closer to 7 hours, minus maybe 1 hour for a lunch break, bathroom breaks, and a stop at the gas station. 7 hour day for $97 and I burned through 4 gallons of gas making for $97 - $16 / 6 hours (because our breaks, including having to use the bathroom, is "off the clock" otherwise it would be $80 / 7 = $11.50 an hour) = $13 an hour risking life, limb or an expensive accident on my record? Yeah no thanks. I can do basically anything for minimum wage here (which is currently $14 an hour and going to $15 soon) and make a mistake, say as a bus boy in a restaurant, and it's not going to result in me or someone else ending up in the hospital or an expensive, $250 consuming boo boo. Speaking of which, if you manage to get the slightest cosmetic damage on the rental they won't hesitate to take your entire $250. Happened to a friend of mine. Steer clear. Related: http://www.latimes.com/business/technology/la-fi-tn-uber-lyft-work-study-20180530-story.html https://www.reddit.com/r/collapse/comments/8no3sl/most_uber_and_lyft_drivers_in_la_work_full_time/ 85 rides and I still pay you $100 to work for you and pay for gas, yeah I don't think so buddy, go fuck yourself. </p>
</sp>
</text>
