<text id="autogum_news_doc188" title="Iranian news agency apologises for reproducing The Onion article" shortTile="iranian-news-agency" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-09-30" dateModified="2015-09-23" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iranian_news_agency_apologises_for_reproducing_The_Onion_article" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Iranian news agency apologises for reproducing The Onion article</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 1, 2012</hi></p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iran">Iranian</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fars%20News%20Agency">Fars News Agency</ref> (FNA) yesterday apologised over an article it reproduced Friday, originally written by <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">US</ref> satirical news website <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Onion">The Onion</ref></hi> on Monday September 24. The parodic article reported "a Gallup poll" suggesting "the overwhelming majority of rural white Americans" would vote for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mahmoud_Ahmadinejad">Mahmoud Ahmadinejad</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/President%20of%20Iran">President of Iran</ref>, instead of US <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/President_of_the_United_States">President</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref>. <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi> article also said "77 percent of rural <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caucasian%20race">Caucasian</ref> voters"  would prefer to drink beer with Ahmadinejad or attend a baseball game with him as opposed to Obama.</p>
<p>The FNA's English service Editor-in-chief said the article had been "extracted" from <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi> and that FNA gives "our formal apologies for that mistake", as well as pointing out the article was "taken down from our outlook in less two hours".</p>
<p>However, the editor-in-chief also said "we do believe that if a free opinion poll is conducted in the US, a majority of Americans would prefer anyone outside the US political system to President Barack Obama and American statesmen". He stressed that this belief does not constitute justification for the error. </p>
<hi rend="bold">[W]e do believe that if a free opinion poll is conducted in the US, a majority of Americans would prefer anyone outside the US political system to President Barack Obama and American statesmen</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fars%20News%20Agency">Fars News Agency</ref></hi> Editor-in-chief</p>
<p>In <hi rend="italic">The Onion'</hi>s article, fictional <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/West_Virginia">West Virginia</ref> resident Dale Swiderski says about Ahmadinejad: "I like him better". 'Swiderski' is also quoted by the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Chicago,_Illinois">Chicago</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Illinois">Illinois</ref> website as saying the Iranian President "takes national defense seriously, and he'd never let some gay protesters tell him how to run his country like Obama does."</p>
<p>In Iran, <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/homosexuality">homosexuality</ref> is a criminal offence which can carry a penalty of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Incarceration">incarceration</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Capital_punishment">capital punishment</ref>. Just over five years ago, when he participated in a debate at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Columbia%20University">Columbia University</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York,_New_York">New York</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York">New York</ref>, Ahmadinejad said: "In Iran we don't have homosexuals like in your country".</p>
<p>The FNA's error made international headlines, including in the United States, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada">Canada</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Kingdom">United Kingdom</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/India">India</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia">Australia</ref>. Will Tracy, editor of <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi>, said their website "freely shares content with Fars and commends the journalists at Iran's Finest News Source on their superb reportage", a humourous reference to <hi rend="italic">The Onion'</hi>s slogan, 'America's Finest News Source'.</p>
<p>On the original web page on <hi rend="italic">The Onion'</hi>s website, the satirical news organisation added a reference to "our Iranian subsidiary organization", providing a link to a screenshot of the FNA's page.</p>
<p>On the article page, in which <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi> was not attributed as a source, the FNA copied <hi rend="italic">The Onion'</hi>s article verbatim and in its entirety, save for part of a sentence saying Ahmadinejad was "a man who has repeatedly <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holocaust%20denial">denied</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Holocaust">the Holocaust</ref> and has had numerous political prisoners executed".</p>
<p>This is not the first time <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi> has caused the mistaken belief of their material being factual. In a November 2007 interview with <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi>, <hi rend="italic">The Onion'</hi>s Editorial Manager Chet Clem recounted an incident in which the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beijing%20Evening%20News">Beijing Evening News</ref></hi> reproduced a story from <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi> created in 2002, copied entirely verbatim, headlined "Congress threatens to leave DC unless new capitol is built". When the error was highlighted to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China">Chinese</ref> newspaper, Clem said "their response was not to print a correction, but just to say that some newspapers in America make money by printing lies." In a separate incident, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Christianity">Christians</ref> forwarded a story on the Internet from <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi> saying children were converting to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Satanism">Satanism</ref> as a result of reading the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harry%20Potter">Harry Potter</ref> book series.</p>
<p>The FNA statement released yesterday went on to say "[a]ctive and well-known media occasionally make mistakes, and no media is an exception to this rule", before going to provide a list of errors made by such publications as <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_New_York_Times">The New York Times</ref></hi> and <hi rend="italic">Beijing Evening News</hi>, as well as television broadcasters like the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BBC">BBC</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/ITV">ITV</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CNN">CNN</ref>.</p>
<p>The bottom of the FNA's statement introduces a list of notable BBC errors reported by <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Daily_Telegraph">The Daily Telegraph</ref></hi> on December 6, 2010. While the FNA referenced <hi rend="italic">The Daily Telegraph</hi> and the order of the mistakes was changed from the original article, the wording was reproduced verbatim, excluding one omitted sentence under the subheading '<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicky%20Campbell">Nicky Campbell</ref> and hunting mark II' which reads: "Campbell, who is also the presenter of the BBC's flagship programme for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holy%20Week">Holy Week</ref>, apologised profusely for the mistake."</p>
<p>According to <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BBC_News_Online">BBC News Online</ref></hi>, the FNA is associated with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Army%20of%20the%20Guardians%20of%20the%20Islamic%20Revolution">Army of the Guardians of the Islamic Revolution</ref>, an Iranian military branch.</p>
</text>
