<text id="autogum_whow_doc132" title="Make a USB Robot" shortTile="make-usb-robot" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2016-03-30" dateModified="2016-03-30" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-a-USB-Robot" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make a USB Robot</head><p>Want a to build a simple robot? Then follow these steps..</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Buy electrical wires almost 2 metres in length, 1 metre of colour red and another one metre coloured blue. Also buy wire of lenght 5 metres a extend the lenght of reach of your robot.
<list type="unordered"><item>Get two experimental motors, say the motors which are used in remote cars. Check these motors whether they work properly or not before you buy it.</item></list></item>
<item>Get a USB wire, a mobile back panel, extremely adhesive glue, 2 compact discs, tape, a eraser, 6 paper clips, a computer and a small switch which is used in simple circuits.
<list type="unordered"><item>Now follow the steps given below to make a USB operated robot.</item></list></item>
<item>First we have to work with the motors.
<list type="unordered"><item>First take the red wire, cut half of it and connect it to the positive side of the motors, say one half for one motor and another half for the other.</item>
<item>Do the same for the blue wire and negative sides of the motors.</item>
<item>Now tightly tape the positive and negative side of each motor, so that it will not pluck out.</item></list></item>
<item>Now its time to fix the motors to mobile back panel.
<list type="unordered"><item>Take the motors and fix opposite to each other on the longest side of the panel by using glue.</item>
<item>Place them in the middle of the panel as much as possible to prevents the panel from leaning to particular side.</item>
<item>Fix two paper clips at the end of the panel by using the glue.</item></list></item>
<item>Now we have reached the final step.
<list type="unordered"><item>Take other 4 paper clips and beat them into round shape.</item>
<item>Fix these 4 rounded clips to end of each wire of the motors [That each motor with two round shaped clips.</item>
<item>Take an eraser, cut it into two equal halfs and fix it to the middle of the disc.[Say each disc with one half of the eraser.]</item>
<item>Pierce in the middle of each eraser half to connect it with the motors.</item>
<item>Each motor must be connected to a single motor.</item>
<item>Take the USB, if its a mobile USB cut the mobile connection port form it.</item>
<item>Some USBs may contain 4 wires inside. With colour red, white,green and black.</item>
<item>Connect colour red and white to each other and green and black to each other.</item>
<item>Note: Be extremely sure before you do this, check on the internet about it because it may later lead to severe accidents.</item>
<item>Now connect these ends to the 2 paper clips at the end of the panel. Red and white colour for one paper clip and black and green colour for the other.</item></list></item>
<item>Now its time to test your robot.
<list type="unordered"><item>Raise the middle portion of each clip which are at the end of the panel.</item>
<item>Take red colour wire of the each motors with the rounded paper clip end and connect them with one of the paper clip which is at the end the panel do same with the blue wire of each motor and the other clip which is at the end of the panel.</item>
<item>Now connect to a computer USB port and enjoys the motion of your robot.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>To make your robot wireless you could use  batteries a power source.* You could use the 5 meter wire between the USB wire and the paper clips to increase the movement    length.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Please check the internet to confirm every step mentioned in this article and then start building it.*The robot may get extremely hot during the running time because of some fault or wrong wiring. So I kindly beg my readers to make the robot properly and check every step on the internet before testing.</item></list>
</text>
