<text id="autogum_news_doc535" title="Senior Telegraph writer Peter Oborne alleges paper suppressed reports on HSBC" shortTile="senior-telegraph" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-02-19" dateModified="2015-09-23" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Senior_Telegraph_writer_Peter_Oborne_alleges_paper_suppressed_reports_on_HSBC" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Senior Telegraph writer Peter Oborne alleges paper suppressed reports on HSBC</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 19, 2015</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter%20Oborne">Peter Oborne</ref>, former chief political commentator at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UK">British</ref> broadsheet newspaper the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Daily_Telegraph">Daily Telegraph</ref></hi>, has alleged the paper suppressed and under-reported stories involving banking giant <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/HSBC">HSBC</ref> so as to avoid a loss of advertising revenue. In a public resignation from the paper published on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/openDemocracy">openDemocracy</ref> website on Tuesday, the veteran journalist and columnist alleges the division between advertising and editorial had not been kept watertight and that editors were committing a form of "fraud" on readers of the newspaper.</p>
<p>In Oborne's article, he details how he submitted a story to the <hi rend="italic">Telegraph</hi> regarding HSBC closing a number of prominent British <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Islam">Muslims</ref>'s accounts — despite assurances to the contrary, the story was not published by the paper. This led to Oborne investigating other coverage of HSBC in the newspaper. He cites the example of a story written by the <hi rend="italic">Telegraph</hi> banking correspondent Harry Wilson on problems with HSBC's accounts, which Oborne claims was quietly removed from the <hi rend="italic">Telegraph</hi> website. Oborne says the failure of the <hi rend="italic">Telegraph</hi> to cover HSBC is also present in the relative coverage given in November 2014 after the bank had to allocate a fund of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/pound%20sterling">£</ref>1 billion to compensate customers, as well as an investigation into manipulation of the currency market: Oborne argues these developments were given considerable coverage in competing newspapers including the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Guardian">Guardian</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Times">Times</ref></hi>, and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Daily_Mail">Mail</ref></hi> but the <hi rend="italic">Telegraph</hi> covered them only briefly several pages into the business section.</p>
<p>Oborne's article alleges a number of other examples of suppression — calling the coverage of pro-democracy protests in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hong_Kong">Hong Kong</ref> "bizarre", and noting that the paper under-reported news of false accounting at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tesco">Tesco</ref> but gave significant prominence to stories about the company without a critical edge.</p>
<p>Following Oborne's article, a spokesman for the Telegraph responded: "Like any other business, we never comment on individual commercial relationships, but our policy is absolutely clear. We aim to provide all our commercial partners with a range of advertising solutions, but the distinction between advertising and our award-winning editorial operation has always been fundamental to our business. We utterly refute any allegation to the contrary. It is a matter of huge regret that Peter Oborne, for nearly five years a contributor to the Telegraph, should have launched such an astonishing and unfounded attack, full of inaccuracy and innuendo, on his own paper."</p>
<p>Media commentator <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roy%20Greenslade">Roy Greenslade</ref>, writing for the <hi rend="italic">Guardian</hi>, described Oborne's allegations against the <hi rend="italic">Telegraph</hi> as "dynamite" and said they go "to the heart of a paper's credibility". The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20and%20Frederick%20Barclay">Barclay brothers</ref>, owners of the <hi rend="italic">Telegraph</hi>, "are being held to account", according to Greenslade, and Oborne "has shone a light on a dark reality".</p>
</text>
