<text id="autogum_interview_doc844" title="part0_Canada&amp;apos;s Etobicoke Centre (Ward 3) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-etobicoke" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-24" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Etobicoke_Centre_%28Ward_3%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Canada's Etobicoke Centre (Ward 3) city council candidates speak</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 30, 2006</hi></p>
<p>On November 13, Torontoians will be heading to the polls to vote for their ward's councillor and for mayor. Among Toronto's ridings is Etobicoke Centre (Ward 3). One candidate responded to Wikinews' requests for an interview. This ward's candidates include Doug Holyday (incumbent), Peter Kudryk, Lillian Lança, and Ross Vaughan.</p>
<p>For more information on the election, read <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toronto%20municipal%20election,%202006">Toronto municipal election, 2006</ref>.</p>
<head id="Lillian_Lança"><ref target="http://www.lanca.ca/">Lillian Lança</ref></head>
<p>53-year-old <hi rend="bold">Lillian Lança</hi> is an Office Assistant, Department of Astronomy and Astrophysics, Faculty of Arts and Science, University of Toronto.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Describe the three most important issues in your campaign.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Ward 3 in Etobicoke Centre, has one of the largest populations of seniors in Canada.  There are many issues unique to seniors.  Many seniors are on fixed incomes and are often property rich and cash poor.  A better method than the present property tax assessment could be explored for collecting tax dollars easing seniors' financial burdens.  Some other ideas such as allowing seniors to work part-time without the government clawing back benefits would enable more seniors to remain in their homes.  An improved TTC system would maintain seniors' independence.</p>
<p>Community safety is an issue facing most urban communities, not just ward 3.  We need to keep our children in school, off the streets and away from gangs.  Parks and recreation, and after school programs need to be expanded and more accessible.  I have learned of mentoring and tutoring initiatives in conjunction with community organizations, businesses and institutes of higher learning that have proven successful in reducing drop-out rates and absenteeism.  A culture of achievement should be encouraged for our children.  Keeping our youth in school will turn potential delinquents, criminals and welfare recipients into good citizens who will earn salaries and pay taxes.</p>
<p>Lastly, there needs to be more fiscal responsibility through better planning with our tax dollars, the money is there.  Toronto is one of the main engines driving a booming Canadian economy.  However, our infrastructure is deteriorating while taxes keep increasing.  This is not good for business.  Our public services are being eroded while our communities are suffering.  Upper levels of government have been downloading responsibilities onto municipalities while decreasing funding, without allowing municipalities a voice in the decision-making process.  This needs to change.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What one election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> While ward 3, Etobicoke Centre, has one of the oldest populations in Canada, the demographics of this ward are gradually changing.  Ward 3 is becoming more ethnically diverse particularly with a growing Somali community.  This ward needs to be ready to accommodate these new Canadians with programs and facilities that will better integrate them into the mosaic that is Canada.  Housing, English as a Second Language, health care, and so importantly, jobs are only a few of the ingredients needed to enable them to become active participants in making this country great.</p>
</text>
