<text id="autogum_voyage_doc461" title="Erongo" shortTile="erongo" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=11079" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Erongo</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Erongo</hi> is a region in eastern central <ref target="Namibia">Namibia</ref>.</p>

<head>Cities</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> , a mining town in the middle of the Namib Desert</item>
<item> , a coastal holiday town, famous for its angling opportunities</item>
<item> , a small town halfway between the capital <ref target="Windhoek">Windhoek</ref> and the coast of the Atlantic</item>
<item> , a small town in the northeast of the region</item>
<item> , a coastal town and holiday destination with plenty of German colonial architecture</item>
<item> , Namibia's most important harbour town</item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> , a mountain massif that contains Namibia's highest mountain, the Königstein, as well as San rock art, with the <hi rend="bold">White Lady</hi> the most famous of it</item>
<item> The northern part of the <ref target="Namib-Naukluft%20National%20Park">Namib-Naukluft National Park</ref></item>
<item> , a group of <hi rend="italic">inselbergs</hi> rising from the Namib Desert</item>
</list>


<head>Understand</head>
<p>Erongo is situated on the Atlantic Ocean and has domestic borders with <ref target="Hardap">Hardap</ref> in the south, <ref target="Khomas">Khomas</ref> in the southeast, <ref target="Otjozondjupa">Otjozondjupa</ref> in the northeast, and <ref target="Kunene">Kunene</ref> in the north. Most of its area is desert—rocky north of the Kuiseb River and sandy south of it.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>Due to the scarcity of other options, most travellers will arrive by car. The major highway in the region is the Trans-Kalahari Highway (B2) that leads from Walvis Bay to <ref target="Okahandja">Okahandja</ref>.</p>

<head>By air</head>
<p>Walvis Bay has a regional airport with scheduled flights to the capital <ref target="Windhoek">Windhoek</ref>, and to <ref target="Cape%20Town">Cape Town</ref> in South Africa.</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>There is a train service from Windhoek to Walvis Bay via Karibib, Usakos, Arandis and Swakopmund. It runs a few times a week during the night. The train is predominantly for freight, with only one or two passenger cars, and it stops at every tree rock, as there are few trees in the desert. But the 11-hour trip is cheap and safe, and safes a night of accommodation. Bring a sleeping bag; the desert is cold at night.</p>

<head>By public transport</head>
<p>Between towns you can catch a minibus. Karibib, Usakos, Arandis and Swakopmund have local shared taxis that can take you around.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>The B2 highway is tarred and in very good condition, as is the C33 from Karibib to <ref target="Otjiwarongo">Otjiwarongo</ref>. The C34 from Swakopmund to <ref target="Terrace%20Bay">Terrace Bay</ref> is paved with a sand-salt mix. It behaves like tar when it is dry, and like soap when it is wet, drive carefully. The Bosua Pass on the C28 can be problematic when driven uphill (from the coast inlands): It starts off with patches of sand and layers of rock which have to be navigated very slowly in order not to damage the car, and it then becomes very steep for a few meters. All other C-roads are gravel roads and in fair condition, easily passable with an ordinary sedan. Other roads (D-roads, F-roads, and those without letters or numbers) tend to be rough, sandy, heavily corrugated, and will further deteriorate after rainfall.</p>

<p>Within the <ref target="Namib-Naukluft%20National%20Park">Namib-Naukluft National Park</ref> there are plenty of smaller tracks for which a <hi rend="bold">permit</hi> is required. See our <ref target="Namib-Naukluft%20National%20Park">our park article</ref> for details. Most of these tracks require a 4x4.</p>

<p>Farms are private properties. Don't drive onto a farm road, even if the gate is open, unless your destination is signposted there, or you intend to visit that farm. If you open a farm gate to drive through, close it again.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> seal colony, 44km north-west of Hentiesbay</item>
<item> , an area of unreal results of the erosion of the Swakop River, 25km east of Swakopmund. The road there further extends to the <hi rend="bold">Welwitschia Plains</hi> which contain one of the largest of these plants that exist. The entire trip has roadside markers every now and then to explain selected plants, artefacts, and geological features. The road is very rough and crosses the sandy Swakop. You <hi rend="italic">will</hi> feel sorry for your car. If you don't have nerves of steel, come in a 4x4, or do the trip by joining one of the frequent organised tours that start in Swakopmund.</item>
<item> , one of the largest open-pit uranium mines in the world. There is a guided tour every first Friday of the month, departing from Swakopmund. The machinery shown is impressive, particularly for kids, but you are also forced to watch a boring PR movie. Tickets at the Swakopmund Museum.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Visit , an environmental research center for desert conditions. The center holds an annual open day on which you will be shown around. If you miss that one you might still <ref target="mailto:gobabeb%40gobabeb.org">contact them</ref> to ask if you are welcome. All roads to Gobabeb require a permit for the Namib-Naukluft National Park</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>
<p>Erongo is touristically well developed. There is tourist accommodation in all towns and villages.</p>

<head>Stay safe</head>
<p>The Ugab riverbed in northern Erongo is inhabited by desert elephants. If you are driving through it, remember that the area is theirs, not yours. They certainly know it. Don't drive too close towards a herd of elephants. 10-15 m is close enough for good holiday pictures and will normally not put your party in danger. Otherwise, the younger ones might play with your car, the older ones might get angry, either way your car might end upside down. You'll know that an elephant is angry when it shakes its head. In this case, stay in the car, switch off the engine, and avoid all unnatural noise (cell phone, camera, such things). They will eventually walk away; wait for this to happen instead of trying a daring escape.</p>

<head>Go next</head>
<p>The following regions of Namibia border with Erongo:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Hardap">Hardap</ref> in the south</item>
<item> <ref target="Khomas">Khomas</ref> in the southeast</item>
<item> <ref target="Otjozondjupa">Otjozondjupa</ref> in the northeast</item>
<item> <ref target="Kunene">Kunene</ref> in the north</item>
</list>
</text>
