<text id="autogum_whow_doc339" title="Maintain Wellbeing in a Mobile World" shortTile="maintain-wellbeing" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2009-06-03" dateModified="2019-10-25" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Maintain-Wellbeing-in-a-Mobile-World" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Maintain Wellbeing in a Mobile World</head><p>As a style statement and useful communication device, the mobile phone is perhaps the most sought-after gadget of our times. It has also become a vital part of daily life for billions of people around the world. Whether used for keeping tabs on children or running a business, the mobile phone has made a huge difference in how we do things today.</p>
<p>But our increasing dependence on the benefits of wireless communication has also come with a cost. If something goes wrong – like the phone is lost or it gets infected with a virus – this can quickly cause some serious life complications. It's no exaggeration to say that the security of our mobile phones now affects our well being in the broadest sense.</p>
<p>While we are enjoying the technological advances that make mobile phones ever more versatile, we are also facing new security risks. Mobile phones have always been a popular target for thieves working the streets, but they are now also increasingly targeted by cyber criminals who have been using the Internet to make money through all kinds of scams, frauds, identity theft and extortion. This is especially the case with the new generation of feature-packed smartphones.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Use Common Sense Security Measures: Try not to make things easy for thieves by showing off your phone in public places where it can be snatched, or by leaving it visible inside a car. You can also preempt trouble by spending a little time on your phone's security settings. Always keep the phone locked and protected with a password if you must leave it unattended somewhere. <figure rend="Maintain Wellbeing in a Mobile World Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Educate Your Children: Statistics show that most mobile phones are lost by teenagers, so educate them about security issues and think twice before investing in expensive models that could easily disappear tomorrow. If your family has a history of dropping mobile phones down the toilet or leaving them on top of the car and driving off, consider taking out insurance. <figure rend="Maintain Wellbeing in a Mobile World Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Backup Your Information: Treat your SIM card with care and make sure you have a backup record of all the information it contains. Also make a record of your phone's unique 15 digit <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Find_the_IMEI_or_MEID_Number_on_a_Mobile_Phone">IMEI number</ref> which can be found by typing *#06# on the keypad. This helps the police identify a recovered phone. Marking the phone with your contact details makes it easy for honest people to return a lost phone as well. <figure rend="Maintain Wellbeing in a Mobile World Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't Talk To Strangers: Think of your mobile phone in the same way as your computer. Only accept messages, downloads and applications from reliable sources, just like you would when using your PC. Any multimedia message (mms) that prompts an installation should be refused. Disable your phone's Bluetooth discoverability. <figure rend="Maintain Wellbeing in a Mobile World Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Consider Mobile Security Software: As mobile threats increase in number and sophistication, consider protecting your mobile phone with software like F-Secure Mobile Security – especially if you are using a smartphone for business or online banking. It lets you enjoy the mobile world to the full, safe in the knowledge that your privacy and valuable information remain protected. <figure rend="Maintain Wellbeing in a Mobile World Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>When you are web browsing on your phone, remember that the interface is different so you may not be able spot the telltale signs of dubious websites. Be on the lookout for 'phishing' attempts that ask you to reveal personal information such as credit card details.</item></list>
</text>
