<text id="autogum_interview_doc383" title="part4_Wikinews interviews Mark Bunker, producer of anti-Scientology website &amp;apos;XenuTV&amp;apos;" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-05" dateModified="2016-03-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Mark_Bunker%2C_producer_of_anti-Scientology_website_%27XenuTV%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: People need to stand up and speak out.  If Anonymous can do that legally and you've shown me you can, then I will happily support that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">I've seen your response to their protest on YouTube. You almost seemed proud that a younger generation had "taken up the torch".</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: People have been attempting to get Scientology to reform for close to 60 years. They have resisted all change. When I reached out to Anonymous, I thought I may well get attacked myself but I saw immediate reform in the group. Scientology could learn a lot from Anonymous. The biggest protest in the past was maybe 50 - 60 people. Anonymous got thousands of people out everywhere around the globe and did so peacefully. I am proud of them for that. We've laid the groundwork for years. Now hopefully, some of Anonymous will continue to learn more and to speak out. There will be attrition but so far there seems to be an eagerness to make a real positive impact.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What happened to Bob Minton? He is alleged to be in favor of Scientology now. Did they give him an 'incentive' to stop his protests of the Church? In a video of yours, posted on YouTube (Scientology: Clearwater Trip - Day 3 - Pt 2), Minton says that the Church attempted to "pay him money" several times. Did they finally succeed? Or was he blackmailed into shutting up?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: I wrote about Bob on my blog last week.  He is my friend and I was there through most of his struggle. Scientology launched a global assault on Bob which we came to describe as having the Terminator coming after you. Rather than type it all out again, check out the blog. [xenutv.wordpress.com/about-bob-minton-and-the-lmt]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How many members of Scientology do you estimate are within the organization?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: Far fewer than Scientology estimates. They now say ten million but I think they are counting me for coming in and playing with the e-meter. The best source would be the census reports which put the number pretty low. More people claimed to be Jedi Knights than Scientologists in the UK for example.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What is your opinion on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free%20Zone%20(Scientology)">Free Zone Scientologists</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: I consider them friends. I support their wish to follow Hubbard's technique. They do so without the criminal aspects of Scientology itself. People can knock themselves [out] auditing as far as I'm concerned. I'm worried about the fraud and abuse. I believe Hubbard was a conman and we have the documents to prove it. If the freezoners don't care, I can't stop them. They aren't emptying people [of their] accounts and breaking up families.</p>
</text>
