<text id="autogum_interview_doc297" title="part3_Shimon Peres discusses the future of Israel" shortTile="partshimon-peres" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-01-06" dateModified="2013-08-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Shimon_Peres_discusses_the_future_of_Israel" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: The future is only peace.  The problem is how long will it take and how many victims will it call for.  Why do I say peace?  Because when you look historically, at the development of humanity, most of our lives we are living on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Land%20rights">land</ref>.  The history is written with red ink.  The reason for it is because people were fighting for our land, either defending it or extending it, because that was the main source. The land, the natural resources, the markets, all these go together.  The minute the land was replaced by science, what is there to fight about?  Armies cannot conquer science.  Customs cannot check what a scientist has in his mind, they can see what he has in his pocket but not what he has in his mind so it’s uncontrolled; it means that borders aren’t important and distances aren’t important.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: How do you approach the difficult challenge of talking to the Palestinians when, in the end, they don’t want Israel to exist.  How do you come to an understanding to make peace possible?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: Well, what is the problem?  I mean, is the problem national, say between Jews and Arabs; or is it a matter of generations between an old age and a new age?  You see, the terrorists are protesting against modernity.  They think that modernity may endanger their tradition.  They are simply afraid and hate modernity.  They consider modernity as their enemy, but then they have two problems.  First of all, can they exist on tradition?  They cannot.  Sooner or later they will have to enter the new age.  All the talks about nationalities, etcetera, well, the new age has very little patience for history.  History is becoming more and more irrelevant.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: How do you feel about that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: Well, I distinguish between two histories, the spiritual and the material.  Or the history of events and the history of values.  The history of values is okay because wisdom is ageless; it doesn’t grow old, like material.</p>
<p>But events are totally unimportant for 2 reasons.  First, the event is unimportant.  Tell me, what events is today important such as how many elephants Hannibal had on the Alps,  when you can have helicopters?  Why should I bother my children with all this nonsense?  What sort of a nose did Cleopatra have?  God, I don’t know!  You can invite people to war over noses, but nobody will go to fight for noses any more.  On the other hand, there are already machines that can replace our memory.  Why should I bother my child with memory when he can buy a computer that will remember everything you asked him to remember?</p>
</text>
