<text id="autogum_interview_doc433" title="part0_Ahmedi of Iran&amp;apos;s PDKI discusses Kurdistan&amp;apos;s general strike and the democratic future of Iran" shortTile="partahmedi-irans" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-07-15" dateModified="2009-11-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ahmedi_of_Iran%27s_PDKI_discusses_Kurdistan%27s_general_strike_and_the_democratic_future_of_Iran" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ahmedi of Iran's PDKI discusses Kurdistan's general strike and the democratic future of Iran</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 15, 2009</hi></p>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ethnoreligious">Ethnoreligious</ref> map of Iran</caption></figure><p>Unrest in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iran">Iran</ref> following the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iranian%20presidential%20election,%202009">2009 Iranian presidential election</ref> has now continued for over a month. Despite the focus of international attention on continued demonstrations against the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mahmoud_Ahmadinejad">Ahmedinejad</ref> government, an ongoing press blackout means little of the news, which does arrive from Iran, comes from the provinces which are home to 74% of Iran's population.</p>
<p>On July 13, unconfirmed reports began to emerge of a general strike in the four largely-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kurdish%20people">Kurdish</ref> provinces in the north-west of Iran which make up <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iranian%20Kurdistan">Iranian Kurdistan</ref>. Videos showed empty, deserted streets and shuttered shops in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahabad">Mahabad</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saghez">Saghez</ref> and other Kordestani cities. The reports of the strike coincide with the twentieth anniversary of the murder of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abdul%20Rahman%20Ghassemlou">Abdul Rahman Ghassemlou</ref>, the leader of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kurdistan%20Democratic%20Party%20of%20Iran">Kurdistan Democratic Party of Iran</ref> (PDKI).</p>
<p>Loghman Ahmedi, a Kurdish exile and the PDKI's representative to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Kingdom">United Kingdom</ref>, spoke with <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi>.</p>
<figure><caption>Wikinews</caption></figure><p><hi rend="bold">It seems like often, discussion of the politics in Kurdistan, whether in Iran, Iraq or Turkey, is dominated by discussion of communist or guerilla groups like the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kurdistan%20Workers'%20Party">Kurdistan Workers' Party</ref> (PKK) or the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Communist%20Party%20of%20Iran">Communist Party of Iran</ref>. Do you think moderate, western-style democratic groups are shut out of the conversation in the international media, and if so, why? What is PDKI's place in the conversation within <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iranian%20Kurdistan">Iranian Kurdistan</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Loghman Ahmedi</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Different organisations use different methods to raise awareness about issues they regard as important. Naturally, international media outlets give attention to more militant actions. The Democratic Party of Iranian Kurdistan is the oldest Kurdish political party in all four parts of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kurdistan">Kurdistan</ref> and the most experienced political organisation in Iranian Kurdistan; we have in the past waged a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/guerrilla%20war">guerrilla war</ref> against the Islamic Republic from 1979 to 1997, and although we are not rejecting armed struggle as a method, we think that there are other opportunities that are less costly in terms of human lives that are worth pursuing.</p>
<p>We have always believed that it is of strategic importance to engage in different forms of political protest that are less costly in terms of human lives; for example, in the form of general strikes and other forms civil disobedience – which we witnessed all over Iranian Kurdistan on the occasion of the 20th anniversary of the assassination of the Kurdish leader <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abdul%20Rahman%20Ghassemlou">Dr. Ghassemlou</ref> on July 13, 1989, by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Islamic%20Republic%20">Islamic Republic</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vienna">Vienna</ref>. </p>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/President%20of%20Iran">President</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Islamic%20Republic%20of%20Iran">Islamic Republic of Iran</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mahmoud_Ahmadinejad">Mahmoud Ahmadinejad</ref> Image: <ref target="http://www.flickr.com/photos/90271651@N00/1435157946/">Daniella Zalcman</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>The PDKI is the leading Kurdish political party in Iranian Kurdistan; in the first rounds of elections to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Majlis%20of%20Iran">Majlis</ref> after the revolution, our party won an overwhelming majority of the votes in Iranian Kurdistan and our party leader at the time, Dr. Ghassemlou, was elected to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Council%20of%20Experts">Council of Experts</ref>, which had the task of drafting the constitution, as the only secular member. During the past 63 years, and in particular during the past 30 years, we have shown that we act in the interest of our people and as a consequence of that our party is popular and respected by the Kurdish people. Thus, even though we think it is important that international media pays attention to the situation in Iranian Kurdistan, for us it is more important to engage in forms of political activity that are of long-term significance. It should also be mentioned that the general strike on July 13 did not receive any attention by international media for the simple reason that the Islamic Republic has created a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/North_Korea">North Korea</ref>-like situation in Iranian Kurdistan where not only international media cannot gain access to the region, but it is also difficult for the Kurds themselves to inform the outside world about their plight.</p>
</text>
