<text id="autogum_voyage_doc332" title="Morioka" shortTile="morioka" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=23023" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Morioka</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Morioka</hi> (盛岡) is the capital of <ref target="Iwate">Iwate</ref> Prefecture, <ref target="Japan">Japan</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>For a traveller, Morioka is perhaps not high on any itinerary and is best known as a major transport hub for Tohoku. From here, one can branch off on the Shinkansen towards Akita and some of the tourist towns on the Akita Shinkansen line. It serves well as a stopover town on the way to either Akita or Hokkaido and there is enough to see and do for a day or two if you need somewhere to sleep or stock up on supplies. Morioka can also be used as base for day trips to Kakunodate or some of the other small towns in the area. </p>

<p>Morioka is an ancient city; it has been inhabited since prehistoric times. You're not likely to see much of its history, however, as it presents itself as much like any Japanese city of its size. </p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>Morioka is a major Shinkansen (bullet train) station on the <hi rend="bold">Tohoku Shinkansen</hi> line. It is also a major transit station for regular trains. </p>

<p>The most frequent Shinkansen services from <ref target="Tokyo">Tokyo</ref> to Morioka are the all reserved <hi rend="bold">Komachi</hi> (こまち) and <hi rend="bold">Hayate</hi> (はやて), which normally run coupled together as a single train. The ride takes 2 1/2 hours at a cost of ¥13,840 each way, so you may want to consider purchasing a JR East Rail Pass or Japan Rail Pass beforehand.</p>

<p>Faster <hi rend="bold">Hayabusa</hi> (はやぶさ) services make two daily round-trips between Morioka and both <ref target="Tokyo">Tokyo</ref> and <ref target="Aomori">Aomori</ref>, complementing the other services. Fares for the Hayabusa are slightly higher (¥14,340 from Tokyo). </p>

<p>The Japan Rail Pass and JR East Rail Pass are valid for travel on the <hi rend="bold">Hayate</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Komachi</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Hayabusa</hi>. On the other hand, rail passes will only cover the basic fare if you are willing to try out the premium first class seating on the <hi rend="bold">Hayabusa</hi> called "GranClass". To use "GranClass" the limited express and GranClass fare has to be paid (¥14,640 from Tokyo). Without a rail pass, "GranClass" costs ¥22,830 between Tokyo and Morioka.</p>

<p>Morioka is a good option for a stopover if you are travelling by train to either <ref target="Hakodate">Hakodate</ref> or <ref target="Akita">Akita</ref> during peak times where it can sometimes be impossible to get a seat to your final destination. Depending on where you are going, you will be allocated a seat on either the Hayate or Komachi, which travel together as a joined train until Morioka where they split off to go to Shin-Hakodate and Akita respectively. If you are only travelling as far as Morioka you can be allocated a seat on either part of the joined train. It's then possible to spend the night in Morioka and get an early train in the morning to the place you want to go, or to jump on a local train if you're only going so far as an intermediate Shinkansen stop between Morioka and Akita or Shin-Hakodate, for example if you're going to <ref target="Kakunodate">Kakunodate</ref>. </p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>An overnight bus service, the <hi rend="italic">Rakuchin</hi>, runs twice nightly from Tokyo Station to Morioka (about 7 1/2 hours, ¥7,850 one way). Other companies offer cheaper, less comfortable rides for as little as ¥5,000.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>Morioka is a small enough city to walk around. The furthest you're likely to want to go is the Morioka Castle site which is about a 30 minute walk from the front of the train station over the steel arch bridge and through the central business district. You can otherwise get the bus to the castle site (below), but the walk through the city is quite pleasant, though can be slippery, snowy and just plain cold in winter and unpleasantly hot and humid in summer. </p>

<p>From the station, the easiest and safest way to into the city proper is to use the underground tunnels from the station which go underneath the bus station and the main road. This can be slightly confusing at first for people who cannot read Japanese signs and is not wheelchair accessible. </p>

<p>There is a wide and flat walking trail along the Kitakami river that makes for a pleasant walk or a good jogging spot with nice views of Mt Iwate. It's about a five minute walk from the front of the station, walking straight ahead to the steel arch bridge and then taking the stairs on either side of it down to the river. </p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>There is a large and sometimes confusing bus centre at the front of the station. Watch where you're going here as buses come from all directions while you're trying to cross the short distance to the shops in front of the station. Sometimes there will be a security guard who will stop traffic for you to cross. </p>

<p>Iwateken Kotsu bus operates the <hi rend="bold">Den-Den-Mushi Bus</hi> (でんでんむし、Japanese for 'snail', which seems a strange name for a bus; it's easy to spot with a picture of a multi-coloured snail on the side of each bus) which encircles the city central area starting from Morioka main station via castle park and Bus Center. The cost is ¥100 per ride, and run every 10 min both clockwise and anti-clockwise during daytime. For such a low price it is a good way to get your bearings if you're new to Morioka. </p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Morioka Castle</hi> (盛岡城), ☏ +81 19-639-9057 . Morioka Castle was built in the 16th century by Nanbu Nobunao, the first daimyo of the area. The castle was used as a residence during its heyday until it was dismantled during the Meiji Period. The area was converted into a park in 1906 and is known today as a popular place to see cherry blossoms in the spring. It is also very pretty in winter when the snow falls on the varied landscape and old castle walls, but it can be slippery and you can expect to trudge through thick snow. Free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Morioka History and Culture Museum</hi> (もりおか歴史文化館).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Morioka Museum of Great Predecessors</hi> (盛岡市先人記念館), ☏ +81 19-659-3338 . A museum with rotating exhibits about people who have been influential in Morioka. ¥300.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Nansho-so</hi> (南昌荘).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Morioka City Science Center</hi> (盛岡市子ども科学館), ☏ +81 19-634-1171 . A children's museum with a educational science exhibits and a planetarium. Museum entrance is ¥200, Planetarium is ¥300..</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hoonji</hi> (報恩寺). Contains 500 rakan statues.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Oyakuen Garden</hi> (御薬園). The garden was originally constructed in the early Edo Period as an herb garden and was later converted into a garden for the local lord. It became a villa in 1908 until the buildings around the garden were turned into a museum. Today the garden is a popular spot to see autumn foliage.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Takuboku Shinkon House</hi> (啄木新婚の家). The Takuboku Shinkon House is the former residence of Takuboku Ishikawa, a famous local poet. He lived here as a newlywed with his wife albeit only for less than 3 weeks. Free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Iwate Prefectural Art Museum</hi> (岩手県立美術館). 9:30AM-6PM.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Shiwa Castle</hi> (志波城, shiwa-jō). Reconstruction of an ancient jōsaku fort (城柵).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Former Nakamura Residence</hi> (旧中村家住宅).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">HARA-KEI Memorial Museum</hi> (原敬記念館), ☏ +81 19-636-1192 . 9AM-5PM. The former home of Takashi Hara which has been converted into a museum. Takashi Hara was a Morioka native who served as Prime Minister of Japan from 1918 to 1921. He is also known for being Japan's first Christian Prime Minister. The building contains documents and personal possessions. ¥200.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fukazawa Kōko Nonoha Art Museum</hi> (深沢紅子野の花美術館, fukuzawa kōko nonoha no bijutsukan), ☏ +81 19-625-6541 . 10AM-6PM. A Morioka native, Fukazawa was a 20th century painter of European-style art. ¥500.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Morioka Hachimangu</hi> (盛岡八幡宮).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sixteen Arhats</hi> (十六羅漢).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Daijiji</hi> (大慈寺).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ishikawa Takuboku Memorial Museum</hi> (石川啄木記念館, ishikawa takuboku kinenkan). A famous tanka poet who was born here in the Tamayama district. The museum has information and displays about him and his poetry. ¥300.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Iwate University Museum and Botanical Garden</hi> (岩手大学ミュージアム, iwate daigaku myūjiamu), ☏ +81 19-621-6082 . 10AM-3PM. A museum established by the university with a nice botanical garden outside.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Morioka Zoo</hi> (盛岡市動物公園, morioka-shi dōbutsuen). The Morioka Zoo a great place to check out the animals in a peaceful surrounding. ¥500.</item>
</list>
</text>
