<text id="autogum_whow_doc195" title="Build a Better Relationship with Your New Stepchild" shortTile="build-better-relationship" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-05-13" dateModified="2019-03-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Build-a-Better-Relationship-with-Your-New-Stepchild" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Build a Better Relationship with Your New Stepchild</head><p>So you just got married. That's great! If your new spouse has children already then you’re also a new stepparent. Stepchildren can be a blessing and a curse depending on your relationship, and if you’re reading this article, you probably feel it’s a curse. It may seem difficult now, but with help and time, you may start to get along. Read this article to start the journey of building a better relationship with your new stepchild.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Think of why he may be acting the way that he is. Is he uncomfortable with the relationship? Perhaps you said something to him that he took the wrong way? Did you marry his mother right after causing the death of his father? These are all good questions to ask yourself in trying to assess your relationship and understand your new step son.</item>
<item>Since you are new to the child, let them set the pace of the relationship. Younger children may be quicker to bond with you, while older children may be more reluctant to get close. Don’t force them to become close to you, as you cannot force trust or love. Remember that you are not their real parent and that they will still feel devoted to the biological parent that you have replaced. They may also only listen to your spouse before warming up to you. Do not begin calling them “son” or “daughter.” Let the relationship grow before jumping into that.</item>
<item>Do be strong in the household, whether they listen to you or not. Make sure the stepchild knows that they are to respect you and are not free to do whatever they please. Your spouse should have your back and do their best to encourage the child to cooperate. Enforce the rules. If they do not listen to you, let them suffer the consequences. Appropriate punishments would be grounding them or not letting them do a fun thing. Plotting to kill your stepchild may be too much.</item>
<item>Don’t let your new stepchild feel rejected by you. How you act towards them will seem amplified. If you get angry, it will feel stronger than what they receive from their parents. Make sure that your stepchild understand why you’re angry with them. Ask them questions to make them feel heard and understood. Children don’t like to feel unloved, and they are quick to feel rejected. How you treat them in the beginning can have a huge impact on your future relationship.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always consider the perspective of the stepchild</item>
<item>Don't be too strict, or too much of a pushover</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Plotting to kill your stepchild will result in chaos.</item>
<item>Do not employ his/her friends as spies. This leads to distrust.</item></list>
</text>
