<text id="autogum_news_doc390" title="FAA orders review of Boeing 787 Dreamliners following week of incidents" shortTile="faa-orders-review" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-01-11" dateModified="2016-12-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/FAA_orders_review_of_Boeing_787_Dreamliners_following_week_of_incidents" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>FAA orders review of Boeing 787 Dreamliners following week of incidents</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, January 13, 2013</hi></p>
<figure><caption>A Japan Airlines Boeing 787 Dreamliner sits idle on the tarmac at Boston's Logan International Airport following a electrical fire on board. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:TUFKAAP">Patrick Mannion</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Federal_Aviation_Administration">Federal Aviation Administration</ref> (FAA) ordered a review Friday into the design and manufacture of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Boeing">Boeing</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boeing%20787%20Dreamliner">787 Dreamliner</ref>, following five incidents in five days involving the aircraft and two <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Japan">Japanese</ref> airlines.</p>
<p>On Monday, an electrical fire broke out aboard a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Japan_Airlines">Japan Airlines</ref> 787 at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Boston,_Massachusetts">Boston</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logan%20International%20Airport">Logan International Airport</ref>, when a battery pack which powers the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/auxiliary%20power%20unit">auxiliary power unit</ref>, for when the plane is on the ground, caught fire. The fire was discovered by maintenance workers after passengers and crew disembarked following their flight from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tokyo">Tokyo</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Narita_Airport">Narita Airport</ref>.</p>
<p>The next day, a separate Japan Airlines 787, also at Logan International Airport, heading to Tokyo, suffered a fuel leak that spilled around 40 gallons, which was spotted by the crew of the aircraft taxiing behind them. "That Japan Air may know it, but they’ve got fuel or something spilling out the outboard left wing. Quite a bit," said the pilot of aircraft behind them on local air traffic control frequencies.</p>
<p>Wednesday, in Japan, an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/All%20Nippon%20Airways">All Nippon Airways</ref> 787, the launch customer for the aircraft, cancelled a flight after a brake problem was reported.</p>
<p>Earlier Friday, two All Nippon Airways suffered separate incidents in Japan.  An oil leak was noticed in the engine after one aircraft had landed in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miyazaki,%20Miyazaki">Miyazaki</ref>, coming from Tokyo's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haneda%20Airport">Haneda Airport</ref>. Another flight, flying between Haneda Airport and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matsuyama">Matsuyama</ref> said the pilot's side window in the cockpit suffered a crack.</p>
<p>The FAA in a statement said "In light of a series of recent events, the FAA will conduct a comprehensive review of the Boeing 787 critical systems, including the design, manufacture and assembly." Further adding, "The purpose of the review is to validate the work conducted during the certification process and further ensure that the aircraft meets the FAA’s high level of safety."</p>
<p>According to the statement, "The review will also examine how the electrical and mechanical systems interact with each other." The Boeing 787 relies more on electrical, as opposed to mechanical, systems than past aircraft from the manufacturer including having electronics operate hydraulic pumps and using electric brakes. Large portions of the plane's structure use lightweight <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/carbon%20fiber%20composite">carbon fiber composite</ref> instead of more traditional metal airframe.</p>
<p>U.S. Transportation Secretary <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ray%20LaHood">Ray LaHood</ref> said, "The safety of the traveling public is our top priority [...] This review will help us look at the root causes and do everything we can to safeguard against similar events in the future."</p>
<p>"We are confident that the aircraft is safe.  But we need to have a complete understanding of what is happening," said newly sworn-in FAA Administrator <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael%20P.%20Huerta">Michael P. Huerta</ref>. "We are conducting the review to further ensure that the aircraft meets our high safety standards."</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Boeing">Boeing</ref> released a statement saying, "[The company] is confident in the design and performance of the 787. It is a safe  and efficient airplane. The airplane has logged 50,000 hours of flight and there are more than 150 flights occurring daily."</p>
</text>
