<text id="autogum_whow_doc160" title="Start a DUI School" shortTile="start-dui-school" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-05-10" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Start-a-DUI-School" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Start a DUI School</head><p>An arrest for a DUI, <hi rend="italic">driving under the influence of alcohol</hi> (or "drunk driving") is a serious offense that comes with major legal repercussions. A DUI is defined as driving with a blood alcohol concentration (BAC) over the legal limit, which is 0.8 percent in over 45 states. In the past 10 years, over 1.4 million people have been arrested each year for drunk driving offenses. Drivers arrested and charged with DUI are legally required to attend a DUI education course as part of their punishment for this offense. Since the person arrested for DUI is legally required to pay for their classes (at an average cost of $500), someone who knows how to start a DUI school can create a profitable business while serving a social need. Here are the steps to creating a DUI school.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Learn the basics of DUI schools so you are knowledgeable about the legalities of the offense and what the requirements are in your state for offenders who must undergo DUI educational classes. This is a major step in knowing how to start a DUI school. <figure rend="Start a DUI School Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>DUI requirements vary from state to state and county to county. The DUI class requirements are also affected by the nature of the offense. The driver's BAC, whether or not the driver has had a prior offense, and whether or not the driver is willing to submit to a breathalyzer test at the time of arrest all have an impact on their legal situation and how long they will be required to attend DUI School.</item></list></item>
<item>Write a business plan for your DUI school. Enlist a business plan writer, if necessary. <figure rend="Start a DUI School Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Study the competing schools in your area to see the kind of plans they offer. Find out what kind of educational techniques will fulfill the legal requirements for DUI in your locality.</item></list></item>
<item>Establish your school by creating a name, business bank account, and logo. Study the local requirements for starting a business and be aware of insurance, safety, and tax requirements in your area. <figure rend="Start a DUI School Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Create a marketing plan for your company and let people know you are offering classes. <figure rend="Start a DUI School Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>According to Gaebler Ventures, Resources for Entrepreneurs, DUI schools are not marketed to the people who must attend the school. Most people arrested for DUI do not know what is required and must be advised by law enforcement officials or legal counsel. Thus, the smart plan is to market your DUI School directly to local police and lawyers in your area who specialize in DUI.</item></list></item>
<item>Create a teaching system for your DUI school. Study the programs offered by well regarded DUI schools that are recommended by local law enforcement offices. <figure rend="Start a DUI School Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>DUI schools use various techniques, including instruction from certified educators and educational films to teach drivers in the dangers of alcohol use and driving under the influence. Some schools refer to programs like Alcoholics Anonymous that offer counseling for drunk drivers.</item></list></item>
<item>Hire certified instructors who know the realities of drunk driving  and who can successfully teach classes in your school. <figure rend="Start a DUI School Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Study the requirements for licensing a school in your area. <figure rend="Start a DUI School Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>In the state of California, for example, a school must first apply to the county's Board of Supervisors. Upon approval, the board will then submit the application to the Department of Alcohol and Drug Programs. Schools are approved when they show they have the fiscal and administrative means to run a DUI program. They must also show that their program is drug and alcohol free and works within all local legal regulations.</item></list></item>
<item>Set an opening date for the school and begin advertising the school and registering students. <figure rend="Start a DUI School Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Meet with representatives from MADD (Mothers Against Drunk Drivers) and Alcoholics Anonymous to gather information on the realities of drunk driving.</item>
<item>Consider franchising an existing DUI school. DUI franchises can be found in your area by consulting a franchise directory. Buying into a franchise may be a cost effective way of really knowing how to start a DUI school and may ultimately come with less financial risk.</item></list>
</text>
