<text id="autogum_reddit_doc147" title="How Darth Vader got his lightsaber" shortTile="darth-vader-lightsaber" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-03-31" dateModified="2018-03-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/88laow" speakerList="#nahakra, #unknown" speakerCount="2">
<head>How Darth Vader got his lightsaber</head>
<sp who="#unknown">
<p>The current Star Wars comics are awesome for a number of reasons. But one of the greatest aspects of them is that they are filling a lot of gaps between the movies and explore the stories of various major characters. One of those characters is Darth Vader. Since the current films all take place long after Vader died, the character has instead been explored extensively in novels and comic books that fill the gaps in his story between the films and add quite a lot of depht and canonical material to it. Vader was featured in the novels "Lords of the Sith" and "Tarkin" (both take place around 5 years after ROTS) and will also play a significant role in the upcoming novel "Thrawn: Alliance". The first Darth Vader comic series that ran for 25 issues took place between ANH and TESB chronicled several major events in Vaders life such as his discovery that his son was alive, his fall from grace in the eyes of the Emperor after the Death Star debacle and his subsequent rise within the Empire to supreme commander of the imperial fleet. A second Vader comic series launched about a year ago and explores the earliest years in his life as a Sith Lord. The series begins right after he wakes up in the suit in ROTS and learns about Padmes death. It is that series that I want to talk about here. In the first arc, Darth Sidious teaches Vader how a Sith Lord must obtain their lightsaber. Since lightsaber crystals are living beings and attuned to the light side and thus will only choose a Jedi as their master, Sith have to take such a crystal from a Jedi they have defeated and use the dark side to break and enslave the crystal to their will, making it "bleed" and thus turning it red. Vader is then sent on a mission to find a Jedi, kill him and take his lightsaber crystal to corrupt. After infilrating an imperial outpost and murdering dozens of clone troopers (remember that nobody really knew Vader at this point yet), Vader eventually locates a powerful Jedi named Kirak Infila, who decades ago took something called the Barash Vow. Jedi who feel like they have failed or shamed themselves take this vow and exile themselves to an isolated place to atone for their failure. During their vow they are forbidden from taking any action for the Jedi Order and involve themselves in any Jedi business (This is remarkably similar to how Luke exiled himself to Ahch-To 50 years later). Since Infila had taken the Vow long before Anakin ever became a Jedi, he was not involved in the Clone Wars or Order 66 and thus was still alive after the Purge. Vader sought out Infila in his exile and attacked him but was far too arrogant and overconfident. Infila severely damaged Vader`s body and threw him off a mountain. Vader barely survived and used various droid parts to reinforce his broken armor and body. He eventually was able to defeat Infila by using the Force to drown an entire town of innocent people and thus distracting Infila long enough to kill him. Interestingly, before he died Infila told Vader that he is a monster to which Vader replied "Yes I am". This greatly mirrors a scene from The Last Jedi where Rey tells Kylo that he is a monster to which he also replies "Yes I am". Coincidence ? Vader takes Infilas lightsaber and guided by Sidious takes the crystal to Mustafar. Sidious reveals that Mustafar is in fact a nexus of the dark side and guides Vader to a cave, that is like some ancient Sith shrine. Here Vader attempts to break the crystals will but the crystal fights back and shows Vader a vision of what would happen if he would turn back to the light side. In the vision Vader chooses to not break the crystal, kills Darth Sidious and tracks down Obi-Wan to ask for his former friends forgiveness. However Vader refuses to choose this path, believing that the dark side is truly the only thing he has left now and channels all his rage and countless memories of pain and loss into the crystal, ultimately enslaving it and turning it red. Vader then returns to Sidious and shows him his new red blade, much to the Emperor's great satisfaction. For a while Vader uses Infilas lightsaber with the red crystal but after he is ambushed by Bounty Hunters, several weeks later his lightsaber is destroyed (the red crystal remains intact) and he eventually builds himself the iconic lightsaber that he wields in the movies (and Rebels).</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#nahakra">
<p>Which specific comic series contains the story arc that follows Vader between RotS and ANH? I would love to read it. I just want to be sure to start with the correct run.</p>
</sp>
</text>
