<text id="autogum_news_doc160" title="Israel issues travel ban on 20 non-government organizations over pro-Palestinian boycotts" shortTile="israel-issues-travel" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2018-01-08" dateModified="2018-01-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Israel_issues_travel_ban_on_20_non-government_organizations_over_pro-Palestinian_boycotts" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Israel issues travel ban on 20 non-government organizations over pro-Palestinian boycotts</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 10, 2018</hi> </p>
<p>On Sunday, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Israel">Israel</ref>'s Ministry of Strategic Affairs published a list of 20 specific non-government organizations (NGOs) now forbidden to enter the country.  These organizations were associated with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boycott,%20Divestment%20and%20Sanctions">boycott, divestment and sanctions movement</ref> (BDS), which supports <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/boycotts">boycotts</ref> of Israel as a state and other actions as a means of protesting Israel's treatment of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Palestine">Palestine</ref>.</p>
<p>"Forming the list is another step in our struggle against the incitement and lies of the boycott organizations, and no state would allow visitors who come to harm the state to enter it, and certainly with the goal of destroying Israel as a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Judaism">Jewish</ref> state," Minister of Strategic Affairs Gilad Erdan told the press.</p>
<p>The proscribed organizations include the BDS organizations from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">France</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Italy">Italy</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Chile">Chile</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/South_Africa">South Africa</ref>, BDS national committee, and BDS Kampagne; the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/France%20Association%20Palestine%20Solidarity">France Association Palestine Solidarity</ref>, the Ireland Palestine Solidarity Campaign, the European Coordination of Committees and Associations for Palestine, Friends of Al-Aqsa, the Palestine Committee of Norway, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War%20on%20Want">War on Want</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palestine%20Solidarity%20Campaign">Palestine Solidarity Campaign</ref>, and the Palestine Solidarity Association of Sweden from Europe; and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American%20Muslims%20for%20Palestine">American Muslims for Palestine</ref>, U.S. Campaign for Palestinian Rights, National Students for Justice in Palestine, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Code%20Pink">Code Pink</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jewish%20Voice%20for%20Peace">Jewish Voice for Peace</ref>, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American%20Friends%20Service%20Committee">American Friends Service Committee</ref> from the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref>. "Friends" is another name for the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Quakers">Quakers</ref>, a Christian sect with egalitarianism as a central tenet.   Officials from these organizations and any activist known to be associated may be barred from entering Israel.  Other public figures who advocate boycotts of Israel, such as the mayors of towns, may also be denied entry.
The American Friends Service Committee was awarded the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Nobel_Peace_Prize">Nobel Peace Prize</ref> in 1947 for its work helping refugees displaced by <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/World_War_II">World War II</ref>; principally, noted Israeli newspaper <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haaretz">Haaretz</ref></hi>, families of Jewish refugees married to non-Jews.</p>
<p>"For me as a Palestinian, it means a lot that they are going to ban me from going to see my family and people. It is absolutely horrible," said Fatin al-Tamimi, head of the Ireland Palestine Solidarity Campaign.</p>
<p>Israeli Minister of the Interior Arye Derry issued a statement: "These people are trying to exploit the law and our hospitality to act against Israel and to defame the country. I will act against this by every means."</p>
<p>Rebecca Vilkomerson, executive director of one of the listed groups, Jewish Voice for Peace, responded on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Facebook">Facebook</ref>, "As someone with considerable family in Israel, this policy will be a personal hardship. But I am also heartened by this indicator of the BDS movement's growing strength, and hope that it will bring the day closer when just as I go to visit my friends and family in Israel, so will Palestinian friends and colleagues be able to return home."</p>
<p>Human rights groups sharply criticized the prohibition as opposing <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Free_speech">free speech</ref>.</p>
</text>
