<text id="autogum_voyage_doc252" title="Lipa" shortTile="lipa" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=154089" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Lipa</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://lipa.gov.ph">Lipa</ref></hi> is a city in <ref target="Batangas">Batangas</ref> in the <ref target="Philippines">Philippines</ref>; it is the largest city in the province. The city lies approximately in the center of the province, with Malvar to the north, <ref target="San%20Pablo%20%28Laguna%29">San Pablo</ref> and Alaminos (in Laguna), and San Antonio (in Quezon) to the east, Padre Garcia, San Jose and Ibaan to the south, and Cuenca, Mataasnakahoy, and <ref target="Taal%20Volcano">Taal Lake</ref> to the west.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>The articles covers also the nearby towns, while independent municipalities, are commonly associated with the city. Locals generally speak of Lipa to include these nearby suburban and rural towns where the daily life and tourism is essentially connected to the city.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lipa city proper</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Balete</hi>, to the northwest</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mataasnakahoy</hi>, to the west</item>
</list>


<p>Lipa is a medium-size city, with a population of 332,386, according to the 2015 Census. The city is undergoing fast urbanization, and is the largest city in Batangas, but <ref target="Batangas%20City">Batangas City</ref> still comes first in terms of economic development, as it has the Philippines's second most important port and interisland transport hub. </p>

<p>To Manileño folks, Lipa is associated with the Batangueño favourite, the <hi rend="italic">kapeng barako</hi> (Arabica coffee), introduced by the Spaniards. <hi rend="italic">Kapeng barako</hi> production once served an important source of income to locals, but it died out in favor of other agricultural products and commercial developments.</p>

<p>The town of Mataasnakahoy is practically a suburb of Lipa, just behind the Fernando Airbase, and is closer to the city in its growth. Balete does not have much growth as Mataasnakahoy, but can still be considered a suburb, connected by a national road through the eastern slope of Taal Lake. Their local population rely on fishing and agriculture, and usually travel to Lipa to shop, study, and work.</p>

<p>Lipa is the seat of its namesake Roman Catholic archdiocese, the Archdiocese of Lipa, founded in 1910. Majority of the city's population are Catholic, and church attendance remains high despite slight drops in numbers. </p>

<head>History</head>

<p>The original town center of Lipa lied in what is now Mataasnakahoy, in the slopes of Taal Lake. The old town center (<hi rend="italic">Lumang Lipa</hi>) was destroyed by the 1755 eruption of <ref target="Taal%20Volcano">Taal Volcano</ref>, and only a bit of it remains today. The current downtown became the new site of the town center after 1755. Under royal decree, the new Lipa was elevated into a city in 1887.</p>

<p>Lipa sustained heavy damage during World War II, and was almost destroyed by Japanese dive bombers. Lipa also caught international attention in 1948 after the supposed Mary Mediatrix apparition, which has not been been confirmed true by the Vatican.</p>

<head>Climate</head>

<p>The climate is tropical, heavily influenced by the monsoon. Daily temperatures can be as high as or low as , and there is less variation in temperature. Precipitation is influenced by the monsoon, and the wet season is from May to December. The city has a very short dry season. Average annual rainfall is comparable to Manila.</p>

<head>Orientation</head>
<p>Lipa is split into 72 barangays, including the 13 barangays in the Poblacion. Some barangays of interest are:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Dagatan</hi> - The Malarayat Golf Course and County Club and Fiesta World Mall lies in this barangay. International schools are also concentrated around this area</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Marawoy</hi> - Here, you may find the City Hall and SM City Lipa.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mataas Na Lupa</hi> - This area has a growing nightlife and a gentrifying environment. Here you can find Robinsons Place Lipa, the Big Ben shopping center, and the city's top educational institution, <hi rend="bold">De La Salle Lipa</hi>. You can also go into classy restaurants and cafés on the rise in the area.</item>
</list>


<p>Local orientation divide Lipa City proper into two parts, the <hi rend="bold">Downtown</hi> and the <hi rend="bold">Uptown</hi>. The "Downtown" included the Poblacion area, where Lipa Cathedral and the public market are found. The area along Ayala Highway (Jose P. Laurel Highway, or Route 4) is called "Uptown", a fastly gentrifying section of the city, composed of barangays Mataas na Lupa, Balintawak, and Marawoy. With developments of large malls, commercial space, and development of mid-range restaurants, bars and cafés (e.g. Starbucks, The Coffee Bean and Tea Leaf, Army Navy, Shakey's), the Uptown also houses Lipa's growing nightlife.</p>

<head>By bus</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">SM City Lipa Grand Terminal</hi> (At SM City Lipa). Central terminal for buses headed for Lipa. Jeepneys and tricycles are available from the terminal.</item>
</list>


<p>Buses come from Manila and Batangas City, mainly via STAR Tollway or the older Jose P. Laurel Highway.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Jam</hi> has services departing from their Buendia (Pasay) or Cubao (Quezon City) terminals every 30 minutes; most head to <ref target="Lemery">Lemery</ref>. <hi rend="bold">DLTB</hi> has hourly departures from Buendia and Cubao as well. Fares are at about ₱160-180 per head.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">ALPS the Bus</hi> and ito regional bus line, <hi rend="bold">JAPS</hi>, has frequent trips from Batangas City. Fare is at about ₱50 </p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>Lipa is well accessible from the tolled Southern Tagalog Arterial Road (STAR Tollway). Those avoiding tolls may take the Jose P. Laurel Highway, but watch out for traffic jams, especially during school days.</p>

<p>From <ref target="San%20Pablo%20%28Laguna%29">San Pablo</ref>, <ref target="Laguna">Laguna</ref>, the main route is the <hi rend="bold">Lipa-Alaminos Road</hi>, which mostly takes you through coconut plantations, mountains and jungle. From <ref target="Quezon%20Province">Quezon Province</ref>, take the <hi rend="bold">Batangas-Quezon Road</hi> (Route 435), then follow <hi rend="bold">Lipa-Padre Garcia Road</hi> (Route 431), which becomes <hi rend="bold">P. Torres Street</hi> as it approaches downtown. There is a bypass road being constructed from Route 435 in Padre Garcia to Lipa-Alaminos Road in Dagatan, providing a bypass to Route 431 and Lipa's downtown, but is not expected to open until around 2020 or 2021.</p>

<head>By jeepney</head>
<p>You can take the Batangas–Lipa jeepney route if coming from <ref target="Batangas%20City">Batangas City</ref> or San Jose, with frequent service from Balagtas or San Jose Poblacion. Fares range from ₱12-42 depending on originating point.</p>

<head>Express service</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Balibago-Lipa City via Tanauan</hi>. Departs from Target Mall in Santa Rosa, with a stopover at Tanauan, and arrives at Robinsons Place Lipa's jeepney and van terminal. Fare is at around ₱96 .</item>
</list>


<head>Get around</head>

<p>Lipa's old downtown, the <hi rend="bold">Poblacion</hi>, is characterized by a rough grid of streets, characteristic of Spanish-era town centers. Many streets are narrow, more suited for pedestrian traffic than cars. With the exception of large shopping malls, the downtown hosts most local businesses and the public market, a staple of Philippine city/town centers. Car travel is inadvisable in the Poblacion, as parking is hard to find, and pedestrians practically cross everywhere. Most parts of the city can be reached by jeepney and tricycle.</p>
</text>
