<text id="autogum_whow_doc523" title="Start a Sleep Spa" shortTile="start-sleep-spa" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-09-25" dateModified="2018-02-19" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Start-a-Sleep-Spa" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Start a Sleep Spa</head><p>A Sleep Spa is a place you can create with little or no capital. It is not a business but a mindset. It is a place for your client to feel comfortable, happy, and calm.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Get an Apartment. If you are sleeping under a bridge that's ok, just be aware that you may not be ready to start a world class Sleep Spa. First you're going to need a clean and comfortable apartment in a pretty nice neighborhood. You don't want your client to have to fight criminals or wolves on the way to your doorstep. <figure rend="Pick_The_Right_Edmonton_Pillow.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get some amenities. Its important to have a way to differentiate yourself from other Sleep Spas. That's the surest way to attract high quality clientele. Clients like things like sleep masks, clean sheets, cooling fans, warm furnaces, and pleasing lighting schematics. Definitely make sure you have these and once your operation is underway start to add new features as frequently as possible. Some of the most notable full service Sleep Spas offer personal chefs, chauffeurs, and in-house physical therapists. Building a Sleep Spa from the ground up can be daunting but its important to remember that new amenities and features can be added slowly over time. <figure rend="Sleepmask Ocean close up by Love Me Sugar.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pick a a motto. You may consider focusing on the sleep experience when creating a tag line for your Sleep Spa. A motto like "The Sleep Spa, where everybody gets nine hours" is a great way to market and draw attention to your budding business.</item>
<item>Get a client. A Sleep Spa is just an apartment without a lovely client to bring your services to life. Clients come in many shapes and forms, but keep in mind that the best Sleep Spas cater to only one client at a time so make sure you chose your client wisely! <figure rend="Auguste_Renoir_Lovers_Google_Art_Project.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Continue to provide world renowned sleep services. A Sleep Spa is live-changing undertaking. As many small business owners say, you will have to work 24/7 when you are operating a Sleep Spa, but at least you can pick the days and the hours! <figure rend="2000px_US_Census_Population_Graph_from_1790.svg.png"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't overbook your Sleep Spa. It's ok to have more than one guest at the Spa on occasion, but keep this to a minimum. When running a Sleep Spa, your product is a luxury experience. You don't want to diminish this by creating a Youth Hostel.</item>
<item>If you are eventually considering turning your Sleep Spa into a franchise, consider reinvesting all of your dividends for rapid grow.</item>
<item>Make sure to ask your client for constant feedback about the climate, conditions, and amenities at your Sleep Spa. She will have definite ideas and preferences and this is an invaluable guide while you are starting out.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Remember to let your client get at least 9 hours of sleep!</item>
</list>
</text>
