<text id="autogum_interview_doc782" title="part2_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green Party candidate Brett McKenzie, London North Centre" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-06" dateModified="2008-10-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Green_Party_candidate_Brett_McKenzie%2C_London_North_Centre" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">What are your views on the mixed member proportional representation (MMP) referendum?</hi></p>
<p>Ontario must change the way we vote. FPTP works when there are two parties.  We haven't had that for a long time.  What we get now is artificial majorities, where as little as 38% of the vote gets a majority of the seats.  MMP is not perfect.  But it takes the best aspects of FPTP and PR, and combines them into a workable system that will better serve voters.  Especially voters who aren't happy with traditional politicking in Ontario.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What role, if any, does "new media" play in your campaign, and the campaign of your party? (websites, blogs, Facebook, YouTube videos, etc) Do you view it as beneficial, or a challenge?</hi></p>
<p>I had wanted to do more, but there is so much tradtional politics that new media got sidelined a little.  I did get a couple of videos filmed, and they are posted.  The GPO is aggressively pursuing new media exposure, because we are being largely ignored by big media.  Local media is doing a much better job, but big papers and TV have left us out of the discussion.  It is largely beneficial, since our focus as a party is on a sustainable future, and that appeals to younger demographics who are more likely to pay attention to new media.  It is, however, a challenge.  The Internet is a really big place, and you have to be loud, funny or interesting to be noticed.  "Hipness" becomes an issue the way charisma did when TV got involved, and the well orchestrated soundbite can now when an election.  I wish it was different, that ideas would carry the most weight, but ideas can be spread by YouTube and Facebook pretty well.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Of the decisions made by Ontario's 38th Legislative Assembly, which was the most beneficial to your this electoral district? To the province as a whole? Which was least beneficial, or even harmful, to your this riding? To the province as a whole?</hi></p>
<p>The best decision was to replace lost funding for health care and education.  We've taken steps that will help repair these vital social services.  More must be done, but immediate funding was desperately needed.  This helped my riding and every other riding in Ontario.  The worst decision was to not close the coal fired generating plants.  They are responsible for about a quarter of Ontario's GHG emissions, and climate change is going to cost us a hell of a lot, and not just in economic terms.  This costs all Ontarians, even those not born yet.  If we had focussed on conservation, rather than nuclear, would have been able to get those plants shut down, and been well on our way to meeting our Kyoto targets.</p>
</text>
