<text id="autogum_interview_doc067" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Asaf Bartov, Head of Wikimedia Grants Program and Global South Partnerships" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-12-05" dateModified="2015-03-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Asaf_Bartov%2C_Head_of_Wikimedia_Grants_Program_and_Global_South_Partnerships" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Asaf Bartov, Head of Wikimedia Grants Program and Global South Partnerships</head>
 This article mentions the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Foundation">Wikimedia Foundation</ref>, one of its projects, or people related to it. <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> is a project of the Wikimedia Foundation.
<p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 16, 2014</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Buenos_Aires">Buenos Aires</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Argentina">Argentina</ref> —
<hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> interviewed the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Foundation">Wikimedia Foundation</ref>'s <ref target="https://foundation.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Ijon">Asaf Bartov</ref>, the Head of Wikimedia Grants Program and Global South Partnerships, at the <ref target="https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Special:MyLanguage/Iberocoop:Iberoconf%202014">Fourth Ibercoop</ref> — Ibero-American Wikimedia Summit; where, hosted by <ref target="https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Wikimedia%20Argentina">Wikimedia Argentina</ref>, a cooperative group of wiki contributors and supporters from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Spain">Spain</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Portugal">Portugal</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Latin_America">Latin America</ref> met to foster collaboration and experience sharing related to the Wikimedia Foundation movement in these countries. The Wikimedia Foundation is a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US">US</ref> non-profit and charitable organization, that encourage <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikipedia">Wikipedia</ref></hi> readers to become contributors and editors of the Internet encyclopedia that ranks in the top-ten most-visited websites worldwide, </p>
<figure><caption>Asaf Bartov Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:guillom">Guillaume Paumier</ref>.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>The attendees to Iberoconf 2014 Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:ProtoplasmaKid">Iván</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Besides your assistance as a representative of the Wikimedia Foundation, in what other ways does the Foundation support Iberoconf?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Asaf Bartov:</hi> So, the Wikimedia Foundation supports Iberoconf because we see value in having Wikimedians with a shared culture, mostly shared language, get together and be able to share experiences and form collaborative plans in their own language. This is something very unique to Iberoconf in terms of the size. There are very few groups other than the Ibero-American group that share a language and ability to communicate in that way. That's <hi rend="italic">why</hi> we support it. The ways we support it is, well, we fund it, we provide the funding for having this meeting, the travel, [...] etcetera, and we support it by being here, by taking the time to attend the conference and be available to have conversations, both group conversations and one-on-one conversations with the delegates, many of whom do not have other opportunities to speak to us face-to-face. So this is the opportunity. Even though we live in the 21st century, the world is digital and technological, and theoretically we could do a lot of communication on video-calls, etc., and we <hi rend="italic">can</hi>, the truth of the matter is that a lot of people feel distant from the Foundation, hesitant to approach, even though we are very welcoming and friendly I hope, a lot of people need to see us and talk to us, and have dinner with us, before they feel comfortable approaching us with issues and problems and things, and so there is value just in the social aspect which is being here, and being accessible, and being human. But in addition to that, we are here to also share our knowledge, our expertise, our suggestions, in the more formal part of the program. This particular year I am here with two colleagues of mine. [...] Both of them also speak Spanish so they can contribute more freely and have delivered presentations on their topics of expertise. This is support that Iberocoop gets and all other Wikimedians can get. So I think it's a valuable opportunity.</p>
</text>
