<text id="autogum_voyage_doc419" title="Pécs" shortTile="pcs" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=27064" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Pécs</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.iranypecs.hu/en/index.html">Pécs</ref></hi> (<hi rend="italic">PEH-ch</hi>) is a town in the south-west of <ref target="Hungary">Hungary</ref>. Pécs is the administrative and economical centre of Baranya County The city has Mediterranean atmosphere and a treasure-house of science, arts and sacrality. It had famous and glorious periods. Here are several values of the Roman times, the Middle Ages, the Turkish occupation and the development of the middle-class are built on one another or next to one another such as Gothic, Renaissance, baroque dwelling houses, Christian churches and Islamic houses of prayer, djamis and minarets, baths and public buildings.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Located on the slopes of the Mecsek mountains. The heritage of the past goes back to the neolithic age. The territory always provided good essential conditions for the different ethnic groups who settled down here, which is proven by the arcaheological findings excavated here. Founded as <hi rend="bold">Sopianae</hi> 2000 years ago by the <ref target="Roman%20Empire">Romans</ref> (most relics date back to the this period) and known as <hi rend="bold">Fünfkirchen</hi> by the Germans.</p>

<p>After the period of migration, St. Stephen founded an episcopate in Pécs around 1009.</p>

<p>Pope Urban signed the foundation document of the university during the reign of Lewis the Great, in 1367, - consequently the town of Pécs became the seat of the first university of Hungary.</p>

<p>Today's Pécs is a pleasant small (but still one of the largest in Hungary) university town that has largely escaped the ravages of both communist-era architecture and modern-day mass tourism.</p>
<p>In 2000, the Early Christian Necropolis of Pécs was inscribed on the <ref target="UNESCO%20World%20Heritage%20List">UNESCO World Heritage List</ref>. It is one of the European Capitals of Culture in 2010.</p>

<head>By train</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Railway Station</hi> (MÁV), Szabadság út 39. (South of the Old Town, ten min by walk), ☏ +36 40 494949, +36 72 215611 , ✉ eszrevetel@mav-start.hu . M-Th 07:30-14:00, F 07:30-13:00. There are frequent trains to Pécs from <ref target="Budapest">Budapest</ref>'s Déli or Keleti station - see Hungarian <ref target="http://elvira.mav-start.hu/elvira.dll/xslms/index%3Flanguage%3D2">Railway Timetable</ref>. The trip can be as fast as 2hr 40min on an express, but several hours longer by local clunker.</item>
</list>



<head>By bus</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bus Station</hi> (Autóbuszállomás Pécs, Pécsi Távolságiautóbusz-állomás), Nagy Lajos király útja (Northeast 600m of Railway Station), ☏ +36 72 502-500 , fax: +36 72 311-055 . Season ticket Cashdesk M-F 06:30–18:00, 06:30–12:00. Numerous buses from all directions (including from cities in northern Croatia) serve the city. Buses to Budapest's Nepliget station operate numerous times daily (<ref target="http://ujmenetrend.cdata.hu/uj_menetrend/en/index.php">timetable</ref>), though the trip is slower than the train, and far less scenic or comfortable.</item>
</list>


<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pécs Airport</hi> (Pécs-Pogány Repülőtér), Pogány Village (6 km south), ☏ +36 72 526 140 , fax: +36 72 526-144 , ✉ info@airportpecs.hu . Year-round flights to <ref target="Corfu">Corfu</ref> in <ref target="Greece">Greece</ref>. There are no timetabled, domestic flights operating in Hungary.</item>
</list>



<head>Get around</head>

<p>The core of Pécs is small enough to cover on foot, but for those who wish to explore the town, there is a cheap and efficient bus service, single tickets are available for Ft 400 from the driver or Ft 300 from the many kiosks dotted around the city. Make sure you have tickets, the bus inspectors have no mercy and will fine clueless foreigners.</p>

<p>Volan Taxi and Euro Taxi are both safe.</p>

<head>Holy Places</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Early Christian monuments</hi> (Kora keresztény síremlékek), Multiple ( Szent István tér, Apáca utca) (in the Old Town, close to Csontváry Museum). Remains of Sopianae, the Roman city of some 8-10,000 people in Pannonia Province, are found at several points below the inner city. The most important one is the Early Christian Necropolis, a World Heritage site dating back to the 4th century and the largest necropolis remaining in the European provinces. Seven of the burial chambers are open to the public under the name <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.septichora.hu/en/">Cella Septichora</ref></hi>; the main visitors’ complex includes Cella Septichora, the <hi rend="bold">Peter-Paul Chamber</hi> (Péter-Pál - sírkamra), the <hi rend="bold">Chamber of Jugs</hi> (Korsós sírkamra), a baptismal chapel converted into a burial site and chambers III, IV, XIX and XX. Many of the chambers are unadorned; some have surviving figurative and geometric frescoes dating back to the date of their construction and similar to Roman catacomb paintings in their style and symbology, including the St. Peter and Paul Chamber with one of the earliest depictions of Virgin Mary. A unique feature of the site is the presence of two-level chambers, which served a dual role for burial site (cubiculum) and ceremonies (memoria). The <hi rend="bold">Chamber in Apaca Street</hi> was built in 390.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Mosque of Pasha Quasim</hi> (Gázi Kászim pasa dzsámija - Belvárosi Plébániatemplom), Széchenyi István square, 2 (Near to Hotel Főnix), ☏ +36 30 474 0175 . Built on site and from the stones of Saint Berthold’s gothic church by Pasha Quasim the Victorious, the Turkish character of the church was restored during the most recent, early 1940s renovations. Inside the building, which functions as a Catholic church, frescoes depicting quotes from the Qur’an from the 16th century are visible. The other mosque in the city, built by Yakovali Hassan, is in Kórház Square at the western terminus of the main pedestrian street, and is also open for visit when not in religious use by the city’s Muslim community. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cathedral</hi> (Pécsi bazilika és székesegyház), Szent István tér 14 (Right north of Early Christian monuments), ☏ +36 72 513030 . The Cathedral of Pécs dates back to the 11th century and the times of Peter Orseolo, second king of Hungary. Bearing the traces of the Romanesque, Gothic and Renaissance periods as well as the Turkish conquest when it was partially used for storage. It was renovated in Rococo and Classicist styles, but gained its modern form in the 1880s, when it was mostly restored to its imagined Romanesque origins, destroying much of the subsequent decorations. On John Paul II’s papal visit in 1990, the Cathedral gained the rank of Basilica Minor.</item>
</list>


<head>Museums</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Archaeological Exhibition</hi> (Early Christian Mausoleum, Régészeti Kiállítás), Széchenyi tér 12. (By buses 34, 35 and 36 from the railway station – get off at Barbakán bus stop and walk two minutes through Esze Tamás Street to Szent István Square.), ☏ +36 72 213719 , ✉ regeszet@jpm.hu . Apr-Oct: Tu-Su 10:00-17:30; Nov-Mar: Tu W Su 10:00-15:30, F Sa 10:00-16:30. The upper part of the two-storey building was a chapel while the lower part, decorated with murals depicting scenes from the Bible, functioned as a burial chamber. Museum shop. Guide available. Adult Ft 1700, reduced Ft 900. Entrance fee included visiting the Cella Septichora Visitor Centre (2014).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">House of Arts and Literature</hi> (Művészetek és Irodalom Háza), Pécs, Széchenyi tér 7-8, ☏ +36 72 510628 , fax: +36 72 510629 , ✉ info@pmh.hu . An exhibition hall different - mostly contemporary - exhibitions in 'Elaphat building complex' in the Hoitsy house (late Baroque, end of the 18th century), and the Piatsek house (second half of the 19th century). Events: classical chamber music, jazz, and world music presentations, chamber theater and literary programs </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Csontváry Museum</hi> (Csontváry Múzeum), Janus Pannonius u. 11. (Centre), ☏ +36 72 310544 . Tu-Su 10:00-18:00. This museum houses the largest collection of visionary painter Tivadar Kosztka Csontváry. A pharmacist by trade, Csontváry became a self-educated painter after receiving a vision at the age of 27 with a voice announcing “you will be the greatest sunway painter, greater than Raphael!” Gradually abandoning his civilian profession, he travelled the Mediterranean, North Africa and the Middle East as well as the Dual Monarchy for inspiration, and painted strange vistas of vivid colour in a unique style that has traces of post-impressionism and expressionism, but defies classification. Csontváry has been praised by Dalí as the second greatest painter of the century after himself. A must-see. Ft 1200.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ethnographic Exhibition</hi> (Néprajzi Kiállítás), Rákóczi u. 15. (East of Museum of Natural History), ☏ +36 72 315-629 . Tu-Sa 10:00-16:00. It presents the material and spiritual culture of Hungarian and ethnic minority groups of Baranya county. Here is the second largest textile collection of Hungary. Ft 500.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Gyugyi Laszlo Collection</hi> (Gyugyi-gyűjtemény), Pécs, Zsolnay Vilmos utca 37 (Next to Miner Museum), ☏ +36 72 500350, +36 20 2354722 (Mobil) , ✉ latogato@zsn.hu . Apr-Oct: Tu-Th Su 10:00-18:00, F Sa 10:00-19:00; Nov-Mar: Tu-Th Su 10:00-16:00, F Sa 10:00-17:00. Laszlo Gyugyi's private collection. It covers two period of art era is historicism and secession. There are some of the most beautiful ceramics of the 'Golden Age' of Zsolnay Factory. Guided tour available by appointment Ft 5000. Adult Ft 1400, reduced Ft 700. Photo/Video ticket Ft 500. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Modern Hungarian Gallery I</hi> (Modern Magyar Képtár I), Káptalan u. 4., ☏ +36 72 514040 . Tu-Sa 10:00-16:00. Amerigo Tot Museum. http://www.jpm.hu/index.php?m=1&amp;s=2&amp;id=44 Martin Ferenc Museum. A collection of works of Ferenc Martyn (Kaposvar, 1899 - Pécs, 1986), sculptor, painter, graphic designer, illustrator</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Modern Hungarian Gallery II</hi> (Modern Magyar Képtár II), Papnövelde u. 5. (Next to Miner Museum), ☏ +36 72 514040 , fax: +36 72 514042 , ✉ art@jpm.hu . Tu-Sa 10:00-16:00. A permanent exhibition of the Modern Hungarian Gallery presents the broadly interpreted 20th and 21st century Hungarian Art, paintings, sculptures, installations. Ft 500.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Miner Museum</hi> (Mecseki Bányászati Múzeum), Káptalan utca 3 (Old Town), ☏ +36 30 2185659, +36 99 338902 , ✉ info@kbm.hu . Tu-Sa 10:00-18:00 (winter until 16:00). The Mining Museum of Pécs located in a part of the former wine cellar storage system with several levels below where they show eliminated coal and uranium mining relics of the region. Adult 300 HUF, reduced 150 HUF.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Museum of Natural History</hi> (Természettudományi Múzeum), Szabadság u. 2. (Located on south part of the Old Town), ☏ +36 72 213419 , ✉ termtud@jpm.hu . Tu-Sa 10:00-16.:00. Adult Ft 500, reduced Ft 250.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Local History Exhibition</hi> (Várostörténeti Kiállítás), Felsőmalom u. 9. (on eastern part of the Old Town), ☏ +36 72 310165, +36 72 514040 , ✉ varostort@jpm.hu . Tu-Sa 10:00-16:00. The exhibition on the history of Pécs, between 1686 and 1948, in a former tannery house. On the first floor there are two interiors: one in biedermeier-style and a sitting-room from the turn of the 19th and 20th centuries.In the exhibition there are objects, documents, photos, interiors, models of buildings and the town. The intimate court of the tannery can add to the visitors' impressions. Gift shop. Adult Ft 700, reduced Ft 350 (2014).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pink Zsolnay Exhibition</hi> (Rózsaszín Zsolnay Kiállítás), Zsolnay Vilmos utca 37 (take bus to the Zsolnay Cultural Quarter: 2, 2/A, 20, 20/A, 21, 31, 31/A, 43, 60 - Get off at "Zsolnay Negyed" or bus 27, 40 - Get off at "Bóbita Bábszínház" or "Csillag utca"), ☏ +36 72 500350, +36 20 2354722 (mobile) , ✉ visitor@zsn.hu . Apr-Oct: Tu-Th Su 10:00-18:00, F Sa 10:00-19:00. Nov-Mar: Tu-Th Su 10:00-16:00; F Sa 10:00-17:00. The best of everyday objects for visitors. Each piece is unique. Guided tours can be ordered, available in different languages. Adult Ft 1200, reduced Ft 600 (2014).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Planetarium of Pécs</hi> (Planetárium Pécs), Zsolnay Vilmos utca 37. (See at 'Pink Zsolnay Exhibition'), ☏ +36 72 500350, +36 20 2354722 (Mobil) , ✉ latogato@zsn.hu . Th-Su: according to schedule. Offers substantial pastime for all ages. 45-person capacity. You can do time travel into the past and the future. Ft 1100/700 (2014), in foreign language: Ft 4000 per group.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Puppet Museum and Theater</hi>, Pécs, Felsővámház utca 50., ☏ +36 72 210301, +36 20 9675999 (mobile) , fax: +36 72 211791 , ✉ bobita@bobita.hu . M-F 09:00-16:00, Sa 09:00-18:00. This is an interactive Puppet Museum. Children can try out the old puppets, learn more information about the techniques of puppets. Guided tours are available Ft 400. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Renaissance Stonework</hi> (Reneszánsz Kőtár), Káptalan u. 2, ☏ +36 72 514046 . Tu-Sa 10:00-16:00. Ft 500.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">University History Collection</hi> (Klimo Collection, PTE University Library, University History Museum, Egyetemtörténeti Gyűjtemény), Szepesy Ignác utca 1-3., ☏ +36 72 501600, +36 72 22651 , fax: +36 72 325552 , ✉ tgyo@lib.pte.hu . Apr-Oct: M-F 09:00-15:00, Sa 08:00-16:00. Nov-Mar: M-F 09:00-15:00. In the University Library. Here can be seen the valuable Klimo-collection Ft 500.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Vasarely Museum</hi> (Vasarely Múzeum), Káptalan St 3 (next to Miner Museum in the Old Town), ☏ +36 30 8738129 (Mobil) . Tu-Su 10:00-18:00. Dedicated to the works of Victor Vasarely, founder of the op-art movement. Faux-threedimensional paintings, gobelins and "kinetic statues". One of the three collections of Vasarely's work besides Gordes (France) and Budapest. Ft 1200.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Zsolnay Museum</hi> (Zsolnay Múzeum), Káptalan utca 2 (Centre, north of Vasarely Museum), ☏ +36 72 514040 . An exhibit on the life, times and decorative ceramics of Vilmos Zsolnay and the Zsolnay Ceramic Factory. The lustrous eosin glaze and colourful pyrogranite developed in the 1870s has given the Manufacture its fame and a Grand Prize at the 1878 Paris World Exhibition. Eosin had gained particular significance in Hungarian Art Nouveau, and became a popular material for public and private buildings as well as art objects. Although the fortunes of the company have been uneven, with world wars, family troubles, nationalisation in 1948 and the mass production of industrial ceramics, the hand-painted charm of the brand survives. The museum collects the lustrous ceramics of the Zsolnay legacy in chronological order in addition to plans, documents and other relics of this cornerstone of the city’s industrial heritage. Ft 1200.</item>
</list>
</text>
