<text id="autogum_whow_doc572" title="Look After Your Dog" shortTile="look-dog" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-02-24" dateModified="2019-07-26" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Look-After-Your-Dog" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Look After Your Dog</head><p>If you have a dog or are thinking about getting one, you might want to read this article: it gives you a step-by-step guide on how to care for your furry friend.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Preparing For a New Dog</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be prepared for the responsibility of a dog. Think of them as your furry baby. You'll need to spend a lot of time with them, care for them, and buy them the things they need. Before you decide on a dog, do a bit of research to find the kind of dog that will be best for you. Some breeds are easier to care for than others, and some dogs will need special care for disabilities or illnesses. If you have the time and money for it, always try to get a dog like this. They are difficult to find homes for and are usually put down by shelters. <figure rend="Stop Your Dog from Barking at Strangers Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure you have everything your dog will need, such as a dog bed, dog bowls for food and water, good quality dog food, and a leash and collar before adopting or purchasing your dog. <figure rend="Look After Your Dog Step 1.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Caring For Your Dog</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Spend time with them. Dogs are very social animals, so you need to pay lots of attention to them to make them feel happy and loved. Pet them and play with them every day. Getting another dog is usually a good idea to prevent them from getting lonely, if you have the space and money for it and you have enough room. <figure rend="Look After Your Dog Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Provide somewhere suitable to sleep. When your dog is a puppy, they will need to go to bed early. Make sure you have a comfy bed for them to sleep in and that they go to bed as often as they need to. On average, dogs need about 12-14 hours of sleep, but may need more or less depending on their breed, size and age. <figure rend="Keep-Your-Dog-Looking-Clean-and-Fresh-Step-1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be sure to feed your dog at least three times a day. Provide fresh water at all times. <figure rend="Look After Your Dog Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Feed your dog the right kind of food to have a healthy diet. If your dog isn't eating, you might want to try changing the brand of food that you're giving them; however, they may be sick, and will need to see a vet if they still won't eat. <figure rend="Look After Your Dog Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure you have time to walk your dog at least once a day so that they can get exercise. If dogs aren't walked enough, they may develop heart problems, become overweight, or develop destructive tendencies. Remember not to overwork your dog: they need to build stamina the same way humans do, so you want to take it easy on them at first, especially if they're already overweight. <figure rend="Look After Your Dog Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Groom and wash your dog. Make sure you buy a quality brush that fits the needs of your dog's coat. You should also be sure to wash your dog when ever they get too dirty, but not too often, as your dog's skin may become too irritated; bathing your dog every week or every other week is too often. If they don't like bathing, be sure to reward them afterwards. If you're having trouble grooming your dog by yourself, or they have a difficult coat to look after, take them to a groomer every six to eight weeks, depending on how fast their hair and nails grow. <figure rend="Look After Your Dog Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Train carefully and consistently. When training your dog, make sure it's in a big place such as a park or a big backyard. <figure rend="Look After Your Dog Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always reward your dog, with a treat or a pet, when it has done something well during training. This will reinforce that they are doing a good thing, and will make them listen to your commands more often</item></list></item>
<item>Provide substitute care when you're gone. If you are away on vacation, make sure to leave your dog with a pet-sitter or at a kennel so that they are taken care of, even without you there. <figure rend="Look After Your Dog Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Foods to Provide and Avoid Giving Your Dog</head>
<p><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Doc:Foods_Dogs_Can_Eat,Foods_to_Avoid_Feeding_Your_Dog">Doc:Foods Dogs Can Eat,Foods to Avoid Feeding Your Dog</ref></p>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Love them.</item>
<item>Your dog will love and respect you if you play and feed him/her.</item>
<item>Be prepared. If you get a puppy, it is likely to whine and cry a lot.</item>
<item>You will need some newspaper or a puppy pad to house train your dog. A good strategy for this is to keep moving the newspaper closer and closer to the door and so that eventually your dog will learn to pee outdoors.</item>
<item>It's a good idea to keep your dog's bed close to the door, or at least downstairs so that if they need to go outside quickly to pee, they will be able to. You should also invest in a dog door.</item>
<item>Do not leave a new puppy alone for more than an hour. If you can, check on them periodically if you're nearby.</item>
<item>Train your dog to use a chew toy so that they won't chew your furniture. Buy toys that they won't eat or destroy too quickly.</item>
<item>Sometimes your dog will bond with a cat, but not always. Make sure to introduce them slowly, and make sure they like each other before leaving them in the same room together. If they don't trust or like each other, they might hurt each other.</item>
<item>Don't worry if your dog does not immediately trust you; it will take a while for him/her to warm to you. Don't force him/her to immediately be your best friend - this plan normally backfires and creates problems in your relationship.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not neglect or harm your dog in any way. It's illegal, and just a bad thing to do.</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
