<text id="autogum_interview_doc666" title="part9_Gay Talese on the state of journalism, Iraq and his life" shortTile="partgay-talese-state" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-27" dateModified="2019-01-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gay_Talese_on_the_state_of_journalism%2C_Iraq_and_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  After <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hurricane%20Katrina">Hurricane Katrina</ref> there was a lot of debate on whether we would rebuild one of our own cities as we were over in Iraq demolishing their cities.  How did you feel about that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  I was there a month after it hit.  I had a friend down there, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Julia%20Kass">Julia Kass</ref>, who I went to see.  I stayed in a hotel--there were hotels functioning.  It wasn't that <hi rend="italic">everything</hi> was destroyed; there were parts that weren't--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Yeah, the high areas; the rich areas--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  --that's right.  And this was a rich area.  It was a good hotel.  She would get in her car, Miss Julia Kass, and take me around.  And boy did I see that town...it...it...it was just like what you read.  And it's like the military:  the outside people just didn't care.  The poor blacks, as there are always those who are invaded by the forces of nature and are not protected then or later, they are the people who get sucked up into this swamp of military life or a disaster such as Katrina.  And the sense of humanity and human rights aren't there.  We have a human rights <hi rend="italic">lobby</hi> in this country.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amnesty%20International">Amnesty International</ref> is very quick to point fingers at countries who are failing, at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Darfur,%20Sudan">Darfur</ref> or the Chinese with regard to the Tibetans.  But right in our own country--New Orleans--the outrage was never equal to what should have been proper and humanely expedient.  It's still a class thing.  The country is really divided by class.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  More than it used to be?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  Well, considering that what this country's history <hi rend="italic">should</hi> be, which is a learning experiment, which is going back to the time of legally abolishing racism in schools and jobs, what came out of the civil rights struggle; all those wonderful laws like <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brown%20v.%20Board%20of%20Education">Brown v. Board of Education</ref></hi> and all.  But we are still a racial society.  And it's no less true with the schools in New York than the schools in Alabama.  I've been to Selma, Alabama every year for the last thirty or forty years.  I wrote about it when I was one of the reporters in 1965, and I have not failed to go to that town since then once every year.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Every year you go to Selma?  Why?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  To watch it.  I think it's a little town that gives a good face of America.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  There was a <hi rend="italic">Times</hi> report, I think, about Selma and they say that it is very changed.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  Bullshit!  There's always a report.  Absolute bullshit!  They go down there every March 7, John Lewis comes out of Atlanta and they go march, and there's some old crotchety group of what's left over from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bloody%20Sunday">Bloody Sunday</ref> massacre.</p>
</text>
