<text id="autogum_interview_doc163" title="part1_Canupa Gluha Mani speaks about Lakota Oyate, Lakota freedom" shortTile="partcanupa-gluha" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-01-08" dateModified="2013-03-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canupa_Gluha_Mani_speaks_about_Lakota_Oyate%2C_Lakota_freedom" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Canupa Gluha Mani also endorsed Naomi Archer, who has acted as Lakota Oyate's liaison; indeed, as the Lakota Freedom Delegation prepared its trip to Washington DC he called in Naomi Archer, who though of non-native extraction is his adopted sister and a fellow Cante Tenza member, to handle media support. "I support the understandings of what she's saying", he said, referring to a previous interview with Archer which revealed an apparent split between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russell%20Means">Russell Means</ref> and other members of the Lakota Freedom Delegation. "She as an individual has integrity." However, the previous interview missed nuances and the perceived gap between Lakota Oyate and Russell Means' Republic of Lakota is not so great. "There's no division here....it's communication, that's all. We can always get past this."</p>
<p>With regard to Russell Means, who has declared himself Chief Facilitator of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republic%20of%20Lakotah">Republic of Lakotah</ref>, he said, "I've worked with my uncle Russell Means in positive venues. And I'm still behind him, I have love for him;" He emphasized the familial bond between himelf and Means, noting that Means had adopted him as a nephew. However, "the Lakota have to be recognized." It was "genocide", he said, that of all the races of humanity, American Indians are not represented at the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Nations">United Nations</ref>.</p>
<p>On the subject of Lakota activist Alfred Bone Shirt, who organized the Lakota Oyate's first freedom celebration and information meeting on Saturday, 5 January but has since made comments attacking the legitimacy of Canupa Gluha Mani, Naomi Archer and Lakota Oyate, Canupa Gluha Mani had this to say. "I have nothing to do with Mr Bone Shirt, nothing against him". He also noted that Lakota Oyate had respected Bone Shirt's call to take down invitations for donations, but expressed a wish that Mr Bone Shirt would make the same call to any other website inviting donations to Lakotah.</p>
<p>The traditional decision making process within the Lakota, he said, was informal discussions among the women of the Lakota rather than pronouncements and declarations. Ideas like western forms of government — referencing the "Republic" — and the use of the English language were part of the reason for both the misunderstanding of the dispute between Russell Means and Canupa Gluha Mani and the Lakota's problems:  "It's hard for Indian people to adapt to this modern lifestyle....It's white teaching that cause Indian problem....leave us alone....This country has not learned a thing about its own First Nations people."</p>
<p>US governing of Lakota has led directly to the economic and social decline of the Lakotah people, he argues. Canupa Gluha Mani noted that the life expectancy for Lakota men is only 44, and that alcohol and drug use are epidemic, as are infectious diseases such as tuberculosis. But revival of the Lakota has to be not just economic to improve the circumstances of the people, but cultural too: "Our language is at stake right now" but the US government-backed institutions like the Tribal Police are just "the second coming of the white man's cavalry".</p>
</text>
