<text id="autogum_bio_doc231" title="Mushulatubbee" shortTile="mushulatubbee" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-11-26" dateModified="2019-09-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mushulatubbee" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Mushulatubbee</head><hi rend="bold">Warning:</hi> Page using <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Infobox_officeholder">Template:Infobox officeholder</ref> with unknown parameter "religion" (this message is shown only in preview).
<p><hi rend="bold">Mushulatubbee</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Choctaw_language">Choctaw</ref> <hi rend="italic"><hi lang="cho" rend="italic">AmoshuliTabi</hi></hi>, "Determined to Kill") (born c. 1750–1770, died c. 1838) was the chief of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Choctaw">Choctaw</ref> <hi rend="italic">Okla Tannap</hi> ("Lower Towns"), one of the three major Choctaw divisions during the early 19th century.  When the Principal Chief <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greenwood_LeFlore">Greenwood LeFlore</ref> stayed in Mississippi at the time of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indian_Removal_Act">removal</ref>, Mushulatubbee was elected as principal chief, leading the tribe to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indian_Territory">Indian Territory</ref>.</p>
<p>In 1812 he had led his warriors to assist General <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrew_Jackson">Andrew Jackson</ref> in the war against the Creek <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Red_Sticks">Red Sticks</ref>, known as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Creek_Wars">Creek Wars</ref>.</p>
<p>In December 1824 Mushulatubbee was one of three principal chiefs leading a Choctaw delegation to Washington to seek help against encroaching European-American settlers. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pushmataha">Pushmataha</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apuckshunubbee">Apuckshunubbee</ref> were the other chiefs; Apuckshunubbee, age 80, died before they reached Washington, and Pushmataha died of illness in the capital soon after their meeting with the government.</p>
<p>On 26 September 1830, together with the Principal Chief Greenwood LeFlore and others, Mushulatubbee signed the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treaty_of_Dancing_Rabbit_Creek">Treaty of Dancing Rabbit Creek</ref>, which ceded to the US government most of the remaining Choctaw territory in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mississippi">Mississippi</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alabama">Alabama</ref> in exchange for territory in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indian_Territory">Indian Territory</ref>.  Other spellings for his name include: <hi rend="italic">Mosholetvbbi</hi>, <hi rend="italic">AmoshuliTvbi</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Musholatubbee</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Moshaleh Tubbee</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Mushulatubba</hi>.</p>
<head>Creek Wars</head>
<p>The great Shawnee leader <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tecumseh">Tecumseh</ref> visited Mushulatubbee in 1811 when he came south to get support for his Great Confederacy, in an effort to push out the European Americans. Today it is known as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tecumseh's_Confederacy">Tecumseh's Confederacy</ref>. Tecumseh met Moshulatubbee at his village Mashulaville (located in present-day <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Noxubee_County,_Mississippi">Noxubee County, Mississippi</ref>). He was chief of <hi rend="italic">Okla Tannap</hi> (Lower Towns), the southern division of the three major geographic and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clan">clan</ref> Choctaw areas of settlement. Other major divisions were in the northeast, including part of Alabama; and the west, near Vicksburg. Mushulatubbee had sympathy for Tecumseh and his cause, but decided he was too old to do anything for the confederacy, so remained neutral.</p>
<p>In addition to fighting with Jackson and his forces against the Creek, Mushulatubbee led 52 Choctaw warriors in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_New_Orleans">Battle of New Orleans</ref> in 1814. They fought in the swamps and cypress trees, picking off many British pickets and demoralizing them.  They kept shooting down the Red Coats, as they were fighting for their homeland. When the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_New_Orleans">Battle of New Orleans</ref> was over, Moshulatubbee and his 52 warriors returned home. They left the service on January 27, 1815, from Fort Stoddard.</p>
<head>Land cessions</head>
<p>Under continuing pressure from European-American settlers and the United States government, Mushulatubbee signed the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treaty_of_the_Choctaw_Trading_House">Treaty of the Choctaw Trading House</ref> on 24 October 1816, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treaty_Ground">Treaty Ground</ref> on 18 October 1820 to cede land. The US failed to prevent settlers from continuing to encroach on Choctaw territory.</p>
<head>Journey to Washington</head>
<p>In 1824, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pushmataha">Pushmataha</ref>, Mushulatubee, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apuckshunubbee">Apuckshunubbee</ref>, the three chiefs of the Choctaw regional divisions, became concerned about the encroaching settlement of European Americans and the unwillingness of local authorities to respect Indian land titles.  They still hoped to offset the government's push for removal west of the Mississippi River and resolved to take their case to the Federal government in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Washington,_D.C.">Washington, D.C.</ref>  Pushmataha led the delegation; they sought either expulsion of white settlers from deeded lands in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arkansas">Arkansas</ref>, or compensation in land and cash for such lands.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-mhs-1">[1]</ref> The group also consisted of Talking Warrior, Red Fort, <hi rend="italic">Nittahkachee</hi>, Col. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Cole_(Choctaw)">Robert Cole</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Folsom_(Choctaw)">David Folsom</ref>, both (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mixed-race">mixed-race</ref>) Choctaw; Captain Daniel McCurtain; and Major John Pitchlynn, the U.S. Interpreter.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-choctaw_nation_earl_white-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>They planned to travel the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Natchez_Trace">Natchez Trace</ref> to Nashville, then to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lexington,_Kentucky">Lexington, Kentucky</ref>; onward to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maysville,_Kentucky">Maysville, Kentucky</ref>; across the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ohio_River">Ohio River</ref> (called the <hi rend="italic">Spaylaywitheepi</hi> by the Shawnee) northward to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chillicothe,_Ohio">Chillicothe, Ohio</ref> (former principal town of the Shawnee); then finally east over the "National Highway" to Washington City.
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-choctaw_nation_earl_white-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>While in Washington, the chief also met with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marquis_de_Lafayette">Marquis de Lafayette</ref>, who was visiting <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Washington,_D.C.">Washington, D.C.</ref> for the last time.  He hailed him as a fellow aged warrior who, though foreign, rose to high renown in the American cause.</p>
<p>You are one of our fathers that fought in the War with Gen. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Washington">George Washington</ref>. We take you here by the hand as a friend and a father. We have always walked in the white paths of peace; and in those paths we have traveled to visit you. We offer you pure hands, which have never been stained with the blood of Americans.-- We live in the south, where the sun shines hot upon us. We have been neighbors to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/France">French</ref>, neighbors to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spaniards">Spaniards</ref>, and neighbors to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/England">English</ref>: but now our only neighbors are the Americans, in the midst of whom we live as friends and brothers.</p>—Mushulatubba, <hi rend="italic">The Essex Register </hi>, 2 December 1824.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-marquis_speech-3">[3]</ref>
<head>Candidate for U.S. Congress</head>
<p>In 1830 Mushulatubbee announced his candidacy for office in Mississippi in the <hi rend="italic">Port Gibson Correspondent</hi>, as reported by the <hi rend="italic">Christian Mirror and N.H. Observer</hi> (15 July 1830).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-us_congress-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>To the voters of Mississippi. Fellow Citizens:-I have fought for you, I have been by your own act, made a citizen of your state; ... According to your laws I am an American citizen, ... I have always battled on the side of this republic ... I have been told by my white brethren, that the pen of history is impartial, and that in after years, our forlorn kindred will have justice and 'mercy too'.</p>—Mushulatubba, <hi rend="italic">Christian Mirror and N.H. Observer</hi>, July 1830.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-us_congress-4">[4]</ref>
<p>The US government forced the Choctaw to remove to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indian_Territory">Indian Territory</ref> west of the Mississippi River.  Mushulatubbee was the chief of his division during the removal and for a time after their resettlement in what became <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oklahoma">Oklahoma</ref>. The government had encouraged the Choctaw to resettle in their former clan divisions.  Relocation soon led to changes in the society in which those clan divisions became less important.</p>
<p>In 1838 Mushulatubbee died of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smallpox">smallpox</ref> in present-day <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arkansas">Arkansas</ref> and was buried near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cameron,_Oklahoma">Cameron, Oklahoma</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Le_Flore_County,_Oklahoma">Le Flore County, Oklahoma</ref>.</p>
</text>
