<text id="autogum_interview_doc032" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Paúl M. Velazco about new yellow-shouldered bat species" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-04-20" dateModified="2017-06-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Pa%C3%BAl_M._Velazco_about_new_yellow-shouldered_bat_species" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Paúl M. Velazco about new yellow-shouldered bat species</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, April 21, 2014</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Paul Velazco with a Vampyrum spectrum. Image: Marco Tschapka.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>Distribution range of species formerly ascribed to <hi rend="italic">Sturnira lilium</hi> (gray tone) and the type localities (stars) of species in the S. lilium complex. Image: Paúl M. Velazco.</caption></figure>
<p>Scientists at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Chicago">Chicago</ref>'s Field Museum and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York,_New_York">New York</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/American_Museum_of_Natural_History">American Museum of Natural History</ref> have discovered three new species of yellow-shouldered bats, <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/genus#Noun">genus</ref> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sturnira">Sturnira</ref></hi>, in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/neotropic%20ecozone">Neotropics</ref>. On Wednesday open-access journal <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ZooKeys">ZooKeys</ref></hi> published their paper on two of the new species, <hi rend="italic">Sturnira bakeri</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Sturnira burtonlimi</hi>. The two new species were previously confused with <hi rend="italic">S. ludovici</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">S. lilium</hi> and <hi rend="italic">S. luisi</hi>, respectively. With the discovery, genus <hi rend="italic">Sturnira</hi> now has the most species of any genus in family <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phyllostomidae">Phyllostomidae</ref></hi>, the leaf-nosed bats.</p>
<p>Species <hi rend="italic">S. bakeri</hi> was named after Dr. Robert J. Baker, who "has made enormous contributions to our [Authors of the ZooKey paper] understanding of bats, particularly to the evolution of Neotropical phyllostomids"; and <hi rend="italic">S. burtonlimi</hi> after Dr. Burton K. Lim, who "collected the type series of this species and has made many other important collections throughout the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neotropics">Neotropics</ref> and beyond", the authors noted in the paper.</p>
<p>Within the New World tropics, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Range%20(biology)">distribution range</ref> of the genus, the new species' known living areas are in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Costa_Rica">Costa Rica</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Panama">Panama</ref> for <hi rend="italic">S. burtonlimi</hi>, and Western <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ecuador">Ecuador</ref> for <hi rend="italic">S. bakeri</hi>. The researchers identified differences between different specimens, including those in their teeth, skull shapes, and DNA sequences.</p>
<p>Wikinews interviewed one of the <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/chiropterologist">chiropterologists</ref>, Paúl M. Velazco of the American Museum of Natural History, about the study.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  The <hi rend="italic">Sturnira</hi> genus now has 22 species, over 1.5 times larger than it was a year ago (14 species). Who contributed to this change? Did you participate throughout the entire process, or only the discovery of the last 2 species?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Paúl M. Velazco</hi>: The last Mammal Species of the World (Simmons, 2005) recognized 14 species for <hi rend="italic">Sturnira</hi>. Since then three new species have been described [<hi rend="italic">S. sorianoi</hi> Sánchez-Hernández et al., 2005; <hi rend="italic">S. koopmanhilli</hi> McCarthy et al., 2006; and <hi rend="italic">S. perla</hi> Jarrín-V. and Kunz, 2011] and one subspecies was elevated to the species level (<hi rend="italic">S. hondurensis</hi>) by Gardner (2008). This brought the number of species of <hi rend="italic">Sturnira</hi> to 18 by 2011.  Along with my coauthor Bruce Patterson, we generated the most comprehensive <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/phylogeny">phylogeny</ref> of the genus. For this we <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DNA%20Sequencing">sequenced</ref> two nuclear and three mitochondrial genes from the liver or muscle tissue that had been frozen or preserved from each bat specimen, isolating nearly 5,000 base pairs of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DNA">DNA</ref>. These sequences were obtained from specimens we have collected in the past (38) and from tissues we borrowed from different natural history collections. We published this phylogeny last year in the journal <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Molecular%20Phylogenetics%20and%20Evolution">Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</ref></hi>. Results of this study found that two subspecies of <hi rend="italic">Sturnira lilium</hi> should be recognized as valid species (<hi rend="italic">S. parvidens</hi> and <hi rend="italic">S. paulsoni</hi>). Additionally we found three new species, two of them described in the ZooKeys paper. The third one hopefully will be published later this year.</p>
</text>
