<text id="autogum_voyage_doc43" title="Alto Ribeira State Touristic Park" shortTile="alto-ribeira-state" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=132782" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Alto Ribeira State Touristic Park</head>


<p>The <hi rend="bold">Alto Ribeira State Touristic Park</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Parque Estadual Turístico do Alto Ribeiro - PETAR</hi>) is a state park in <ref target="S%C3%A3o%20Paulo%20%28state%29">São Paulo state</ref>, <ref target="Brazil">Brazil</ref>. It is a prime destination for cave exploring, containing the Gruta da Casa da Pedra cave, with the largest cave mouth in the world.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>The park has one of the largest concentrations of caverns on the planet — more than 300 — in a region of untouched Atlantic forest covering mountains and ridges. This natural heritage site is made up of paleontological, archeological, and historical sites, not to mention the extreme biodiversity and speleological richness to be found in the region.</p>

<p>The high precipitation index, coupled with its action on the limestone, is responsible for the formation of the caverns and their endless stalactites (on the ceiling), stalagmites (on the floor), columns (from ceiling to floor), and curtains. The caverns include both horizontal ones (grottoes) and vertical ones (abysses).</p>

<p>Due to its area — almost 36,000 hectares — visitation is limited to areas concentrated around four different nuclei: <hi rend="bold">Santana</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Caboclos</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Ouro Grosso</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Casa da Pedra</hi>.</p>

<p>PETAR, in conjunction with the state parks of Jacutinga, Intervales, and Carlos Botelho, and the Xitué Ecological Station, forms a large, contiguous area of Atlantic Forest with more than 200,000 hectares and an immense variety of species. The whole region has be designated a Biosphere Reserve by UNESCO.</p>

<head>History</head>

<p>Prior to the arrival of the Portuguese in 1500, the Atlantic Rainforest surrounded most of the Brazilian coast, but it has now been mostly decimated with exception of a few pockets, which now compose the Atlantic Rainforest South-East Reserves, a UNESCO World Heritage Site. The Ribeira Valley, between the states of <ref target="S%C3%A3o%20Paulo%20%28state%29">São Paulo</ref> and <ref target="Paran%C3%A1">Paraná</ref>, contains most of the remaining primary rainforest. The Alto Ribeira State Touristic Park (PETAR) was created in 1958.</p>

<head>Landscape</head>
<p>The park is spread across the Serra da Boa Vista range, part of the Serra de Paranapiacaba. Besides the exuberant rainforest covering this mountainous terrain, the most distinguishing traits of PETAR are its limestone caves - totaling 300. Of these, only 12 are open to the public. The park also contains 20 waterfalls and the towns of Iporanga and Apiaí.</p>

<head>Flora and fauna</head>
<p>The landscape is covered with virgin Atlantic Forest. <hi rend="italic">Araucária</hi> trees, Brazilwood trees, palm trees, orchids, and bromeliads are common. There are also many ficus trees, whose roots can reach many meters into the earth. The larger trees can reach 40 meters in height.</p>

<p>The larger mammals which live in this habitat include the Red Brocket (a type of small deer), the Tayra (a type of weasel), the Jaguar, the Otter, the Southern Muriqui (a type of wooly spider monkey), the Robust Capuchin Monkey, and the Howler Monkey. Birds include the Harpy Eagle, the Vinaceous-breasted Amazon (a type of parrot), the Black-fronted Piping Guan, and the Dusky-legged Guan.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<p>All visitor centres are only accessible by car. Two visitor centers - Núcleo Santana and Ouro Grosso - are located at <hi rend="bold">SP-165</hi>, between Iporanga and Apiaí. Núcleo Caboclos is at SP-250, between Apiaí and Guapiara. For those coming from <ref target="S%C3%A3o%20Paulo">São Paulo</ref>, it is better to first take the BR-116 (<hi rend="italic">Régis Bittencourt</hi>), then take the SP-193 at Jacupiranga towards Eldorado, and finally, the SP-165 towards Iporanga and Apiaí. Those coming from <ref target="Iguape">Iguape</ref> or <ref target="Ilha%20Comprida">Ilha Comprida</ref> can reach Jacupiranga through the SP-222, passing through Paiquera-Açu.</p>

<p>For those who don't have their own means of transport, an alternative is to hire a tour agency, such as:</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ipotur</hi>, Rua Diogo Ribeiro de Oliveira 67, Alto do Coqueiro - Iporanga, ☏ +55 11 98515737, +55 13 96076579 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Núcleo Terra</hi>, Rua João Evilásio Nunes, 160, Alto do Coqueiro - Iporanga, ☏ +55 15 3556-1125, +55 11 3628-2758 .</item>
</list>


<head>Fees and permits</head>
<p>Most visits to the PETAR require a licensed guide, requiring you to contact the park's main office:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">PETAR Public Use Team</hi> (Equipe Uso Público PETAR), Av. Isidoro Alpheu Santiago, 364 - Fepasa - Apiaí, ☏ +55 15 3552-1875 , ✉ petar@fflorestal.sp.gov.br . M-F 07:00-17:00.</item>
</list>

<p>Tours generally cost R$ 9; cars have an admission fee of R$ 6, and motorbikes, of R$ 4.</p>

<head>Caves</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Santana Cave</hi>, Rodovia SP-165, km 159 (Núcleo Santana), ☏ +55 15 3552-1875 . Tu-Su 09:00-15:00. The most visited cave in the park and arguably the most beautiful. It is 7-km-long, but only the first 800 meters are open to the public. Cave exploration takes about 2 hours and has low difficulty. R$ 9.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Morro Preto Cave</hi>, Rodovia SP-165, km 159 (Núcleo Santana), ☏ +55 15 3552-1875 . Tu-Su 09:00-16:00. Cave famous for its cave mouth, which is particularly beautiful when seen from inside and against the light. Exploration has medium difficulty and takes about 1 hour. R$ 9.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Couto Cave</hi>, Rodovia SP-165, km 159 (Núcleo Santana), ☏ +55 15 3552-1875 . Tu-Su 09:00-16:00. A nice cave to observe the exhuberant rainforest from inside. Exploration takes 1 hour and has low difficulty. R$ 9.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Água Suja Cave</hi>, Rodovia SP-165, km 159 (Núcleo Santana), ☏ +55 15 3552-1875 . Tu-Su 09:00-15:00. A large cave containing a river. It has 1.8 km, with 800 meters open to the public. Part of the internal trail is completely dark. Medium difficulty, 40 minutes to reach the cave + 2 hours of exploration. R$ 9.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Casa de Pedra Cave</hi>, Núcleo Casa de Pedra, ☏ +55 15 3552-1875 . Casa de Pedra has the largest cave mouth in the world, which is 173 meters high. The cave has 5.5 km of internal galleries, but unfortunately, its interior is not open to the public due to safety considerations. The stunning visual of the cave mouth is worth a visit by itself, however, and can be reached through a 4-km trail with high difficulty.</item>
</list>
</text>
