<text id="autogum_interview_doc332" title="part0_Canada&amp;apos;s St. Paul’s West (Ward 21) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-st-pauls" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-21" dateModified="2013-09-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_St._Paul%E2%80%99s_West_%28Ward_21%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Canada's St. Paul’s West (Ward 21) city council candidates speak</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday, November 3, 2006</hi></p>
<p>On November 13, Torontonians will be heading to the polls to vote for their ward's councillor and for mayor. Among Toronto's ridings is St. Paul's West (Ward 21). One candidate responded to Wikinews' requests for an interview. This ward's candidates include John Adams, Tony Corpuz, <hi rend="bold">Joe Mihevc</hi> (incumbent), and John Sewell.</p>
<p>For more information on the election, read <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toronto%20municipal%20election,%202006">Toronto municipal election, 2006</ref>.</p>
<head id="Joe_Mihevc_(incumbent)"><ref target="http://www.joemihevc.com">Joe Mihevc</ref> (incumbent)</head>
<p>54-year-old Joe Mihevc is the incumbent for Ward 21, St. Paul's West, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toronto">Toronto, Canada</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Describe the three most important issues in your campaign.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> The three most important issues are the environment, transportation and the local economy. As Toronto plans for its future, we need to increase our waste diversion and recycling programs. We need to maintain and protect our green spaces. We need to enhance sustainable energy options. We need to reduce gridlock and smog in order to improve our air quality. And, we need an efficient, affordable, reliable transit system to keep the City and local economy moving.</p>
<p>In addressing each of these issues, I am convinced that we cannot make decisions for today only; we need to have vision and hope for a brighter future. As Councillor, I have worked, and will continue to work, on each of these issues in many separate and specific projects throughout the Ward and City. For a full record of the positive results of my work on these issues, go to www.joemihevc.ca</p>
<p>All three of the issues come together in one local project – the rejeuvenation of St. Clair Ave W, which I address in the next question.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What one election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> The majority of residents have indicated to me that they want St. Clair, the Avenue at the centre of our community life in the south of Ward 21, to provide them with reliable public transit, an efficient flow of traffic, and sidewalks that draw neighbours out for a stroll or to shop locally. This is the vision towards which we are working! With streetscape and transit improvements, St. Clair West will continue to be pedestrian-friendly, and I will continue to encourage the growing patio culture for restaurants and cafes. To improve public transit, I support a dedicated lane that will allow streetcars to pass unobstructed along the street. In terms of reliability, we are getting the equivalent of an above ground subway service – the dream of so many neighbourhoods across the city! How can I not support that as the local Councillor, responsible for enhancing the Ward which I represent? Current levels of transit service are already insufficient here and will become more so as St. Clair increases in density and popularity. Improved public transit is vital to preserving the neighbourhood character of St. Clair, while moving us into the future.</p>
</text>
