<text id="autogum_whow_doc614" title="Appreciate the Uniqueness in You" shortTile="appreciate-uniqueness" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-01-04" dateModified="2018-09-25" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Appreciate-the-Uniqueness-in-You" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Appreciate the Uniqueness in You</head><p>Dear friends , the world will say 'No!' in a thousand ways . Each No! you hear has the potential to erode your confidence bit by bit until you quit all together.You have to continue to do what you are doing , if you are certain you are doing the right thing. Self esteem and self confidence are the key stones to success and happiness.Here are some steps you must follow and internalize if  you wish to raise your self worth and confidence level.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Stop comparing yourself with other people , Say and think good about yourself. Everyone makes mistakes, but it is how you react to them that makes a difference. Don't beat yourself up over a slip up; forgive yourself,  laugh it off, and learn from it. <figure rend="Appreciate the Uniqueness in You Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Associate with similar people. It is said that you are that he average of five of your closest friends. Try to surround yourself only with positive people who reflect your values and that you can learn from. Keep people near you who will encourage, motivate, and accept you as you are. Do not keep "vanity friends." Those are the people who pose as your friends but pull you down at the earliest opportunity. Having them may make you seen popular, but they are useless as actual friends. <figure rend="Appreciate the Uniqueness in You Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make a list of your positive qualities. It's okay to start with a few and add more each day. List out what you love about yourself and the qualities you want to have; work towards fostering those qualities every day. You could also write down your short-term to help motivate you to reach them <figure rend="Appreciate the Uniqueness in You Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Start doing some exercise every day. By doing this, you will feel better. Exercising releases endorphins which will lessen your stress. By exercising, your helping your body keep your hormones and feelings at the appropriate level. <figure rend="Appreciate the Uniqueness in You Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Help others reach your level. Yes, you are unique, and that deserves appreciation. Other people are unique and need appreciation as well. They may not think they deserve it or may not know how to accept themselves. Help them by building them up as you do yourself. Be generous with compliments. Thank others when they help you, and give them credit when they deserve it. <figure rend="Appreciate the Uniqueness in You Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Praise yourself but not at the expense of others. Instead of putting people down to make you seem better, praise everyone's achievements with your own. When the team wins, you don't say "I did it." Instead, you say "we did it." By praising everyone (while including yourself), you help everyone and create a personal, friendly bond with them.</item>
<item>Sometimes, just smiling at someone can give their self-esteem a boost.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not confuse high self esteem and confidence with arrogance and ego. While the former makes people happy and lets them believe they are good as anyone else, the second makes them believe they, and only they, are the best.</item></list>
</text>
