<text id="autogum_interview_doc165" title="part0_Interview with Stephanie Beaumier, City Council candidate for Wards 1 &amp; 5 in Brampton, Canada" shortTile="partinterview-stephanie" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-24" dateModified="2007-06-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Stephanie_Beaumier%2C_City_Council_candidate_for_Wards_1_%26_5_in_Brampton%2C_Canada" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Interview with Stephanie Beaumier, City Council candidate for Wards 1 &amp; 5 in Brampton, Canada</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 24, 2006</hi></p>
<p>The upcoming <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brampton%20municipal%20election,%202006">2006 Brampton municipal election</ref>, to be held November 13, features an array of candidates looking to represent their wards in city council or the council of the Peel Region.</p>
<p>Wikinews contributor Nick Moreau contacted many of the candidates, including <hi rend="bold">Stephanie Beaumier</hi>, asking them to answer common questions sent in an email. This ward's incumbent is Grant Gibson, also challenging Gibson is Malcolm Jones, Larry Lee, Jeffrey Schrik, Jagtar Shergill, and Whoston Wray.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> List the three most important issues in your campaign.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> The residents of Wards 1 and 5 have told me that traffic congestion, public safety and taxes are the most important to them.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What one election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> All of the above-mentioned are very important to myself and the residents in these wards.  The revitalization of the downtown core is also a key issue that will directly affect the residents of Wards 1 and 5.  We must carefully plan to simultaneously improve downtown Brampton while proactively controlling traffic congestion, pollution, and public safety.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What qualities or experiences do you possess, that make you more desirable than the incumbent? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> For me, it's all about people.  I have a proven track record of working for and with people.  I have worked for Goodwill Industries, The Credit Valley Hospital Foundation, The United Way and Big Brothers Big Sisters of Peel.  Working on behalf on the less fortunate has instilled in me a willingness to fight for what is right.  I will be accessible and responsive.  I will approach this position with integrity and with passion</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent your ward on council?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Representing the residents of Wards 1 and 5 is a natural progression in my career.  I feel that my experiences working with people can be brought together to make a stronger difference in this community on a larger scale.  I moved to Ward 1 in 1975 and have been living in Ward 5 for over 13 years.  I have personally witnessed the growth of Brampton and the challenges that come with it.  I will represent a City Council that is based on person-to-person communications.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> For over two years, I have worked with a team that has raised over $1 Million for children, youth and their families in Brampton.  I have initiated partnerships with service clubs and The City of Brampton for this cause.  This has been my full time occupation.  I currently volunteer with The Brampton Canadettes Girls Hockey League and organize community events to benefit various charities.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Much of Brampton's existing council is quite seasoned in the civic political process. What could you bring to the table as a "rookie", above and beyond the current roster of councilors?</p>
</text>
