<text id="autogum_interview_doc584" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Australian Paralympic skiers Toby Kane, Cameron Rahles Rahbula, and Mitchell Gourley" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-12-10" dateModified="2014-05-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_Paralympic_skiers_Toby_Kane%2C_Cameron_Rahles_Rahbula%2C_and_Mitchell_Gourley" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  So you guys like the new point system they implemented?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Cameron Rahles-Rahbula:</hi> There's always challenges, because you've got different classes, and varied conditions, so they try and adapt the times to fit, but it'll never be something that can be always right, because we've got a sport that's got different conditions, and different locations, as opposed to a swimming pool, where you know you've got fifty metres.  So that's something that'll always be a challenge, but in saying that, it has raised the bar, in terms of the standard of skiing, which is good. From an Australian perspective, not necessarily the public will be aware of that but I think from an international perspective, the skiing has moved into a more professional area, which is good, and I think that it will be the best thing for the sport moving forward.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evan%20O'Hanlon">Evan O'Hanlon</ref> at the summer games was talking about the disparity problem between able bodied athletes and athletes with disabilities in terms of sponsorship. You guys have no visibility, is that something that you guys sit there going "we should have the same sponsorship as the great Australian skiers"? </p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Mitchell Gourley:</hi> The problem in that is that in our sport we would probably be the most visible alpine skiers from Australia. The able bodied alpine team is pretty average and has been for a few years now, since a couple of guys retired after Vancouver. So we're probably, while its still very small, it's a lot less than the summer guys, even the summer Paralympics guys, were are more visible than the Australian alpine team.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Toby Kane:</hi> I think a few of us, well Cam and I and I think Mitch is along the same lines, is that we're not here for a career as an athlete. so I know I haven't actively a lot of sponsorships. I have a life away from skiing with what I'm doing at the university and I'm here because I really love to do it, and I love to compete, but I'm not overly fussed about the public recognition of it all. I'm more concerned with skiing with our able-bodied counterparts and showing them what we can do.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Do you guys get equal treatment? Your share of the same facilities, same trainers, that sort of stuff? </p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Toby Kane:</hi> We train on the same hills.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mitchell Gourley:</hi> And last week we had pretty much the same races as the able-bodied had the week before on the same hills, and what they ski on next week, and we follow on that, so we don't have to start. But with a hundred of... that's why I'm a level below world cup for able-bodied skiers, and skiing on the same hill, and running pretty comparable times, and getting a lot of comments from coaches and athletes there. And yeah that's what we all, I think, strive for. It's an awkward thing to ever try and illustrate it to the Australian public, ski racing, and let alone Paralympic ski racing, and what we're doing. So [...] we've got to accept that we're not going to get the recognition publicly probably that we may or may not deserve, and we more look towards our peers, whether they're able bodied or disabled, and if they respect us, if the best able bodied skiers in the world respect what we are doing, and think that we are doing it bloody well, then we can hold our head high and feel really good. Had one of the best <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/slalom">slalom</ref> skiers in the world walk up to me a few years ago when we were in training, and say "that's some of the best slalom skiing that I've ever seen, wow that's incredible. One-legged. I couldn't do that on one leg". That kind of thing. So that obviously makes us all feel like we're doing something that while the recognition might not be there from the public, that we feel as though we are doing a really competitive and really difficult sport, and doing it to a really high level.</p></p>
</text>
