<text id="autogum_news_doc717" title="CFPB records fewer complaints in early days of US government shutdown" shortTile="cfpb-records-fewer" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-10-08" dateModified="2013-11-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CFPB_records_fewer_complaints_in_early_days_of_US_government_shutdown" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>CFPB records fewer complaints in early days of US government shutdown</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 8, 2013</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Count of complaints by company recorded so far during the US Government shutdown Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:LauraHale">Laura Hale</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>Unlike some parts of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US">US</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/US%20Federal%20Government">Federal Government</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Consumer_Financial_Protection_Bureau">Consumer Financial Protection Bureau</ref> (CFPB) has been open during the federal government shutdown and recording a record-low number of complaints submitted by consumers against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/mortgage%20loan">mortgage</ref> companies, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/credit%20card">credit card</ref> companies, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/student%20loan">student loan</ref> providers, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/bank">banks</ref>, money transfer providers, companies who provide <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/credit%20history">credit reports</ref>, and other companies providing consumer loans.</p>
<p>With data not available for yesterday, the first four days of the shutdown had daily totals of 37, 16, 13, and 3 complaints.  With the exceptions of September 29 with 15 complaints and September 28 with 23, it is the lowest daily total since March 16 of this year when 36 total complaints were recorded and February 23 of this year with 14. The total complaints are also down from the same dates last year, when the total complaints per day for the first four days of October 2012 were 272, 298, 288, and 225.</p>
<p>Of the 69 filed complaints recorded so far this month, 27 were complaints about mortgage companies, 21 were about bank accounts and 10 were about credit card companies.  40% of credit card companies complaints, 42.9% of bank account complaints and 48.1% of mortgage complaints are currently listed as still in progress.  Most of the rest have been closed with an explanation.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bank%20of%20America">Bank of America</ref> leads all companies in terms of total complaints filed this month with 9. Bayview Loan Servicing, LLC and
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JPMorgan%20Chase">JPMorgan Chase</ref> have 7 complaints each. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ally%20Bank">Ally Bank</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sovereign%20Bank">Sovereign Bank</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wells%20Fargo">Wells Fargo</ref> have 4 each. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flagstar%20Bank">Flagstar Bank</ref>
and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Equifax">Equifax</ref> have 3 each.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Citibank">Citibank</ref>, Nationstar Mortgage, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TD%20Bank">TD Bank</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amex">Amex</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FirstMerit%20Corporation">FirstMerit Bank</ref> have 2 complaints each. 18 financial services companies have 1 complaint each filed against them.</p>
<p>During the government shutdown, some CFPB staff have voiced their opinions on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Twitter">Twitter</ref>. Dan Munz, deputy assistant director for consumer engagement at the CFPB, tweeted, "Boy, shutdown week has really created a sudden bumper crop of amateur federal management experts."; "Also, seems like <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Boehner">Boehner</ref> is singlehandedly undoing whatever progress he'd made in portraying this as a Dem [<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Democratic_Party_(US)">Democratic Party</ref>] shutdown."; and "Basically, there's now a strong incentive to fill legislation with minor symbolic things you can bargain away later to protect the core."</p>
<p>The agency has been able to stay open during the government shutdown because it is funded by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal%20Reserve">Federal Reserve</ref>.  According to Amanda Terkel at the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Huffington%20Post">Huffington Post</ref></hi>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(United_States)">Republican</ref> members of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_House_of_Representatives">United States House of Representatives</ref> have put closing the CFPB on their wish list of items in negotiating for a new debt ceiling limit. Party members have previously stalled the appointment of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard%20Cordray">Richard Cordray</ref> as the CFPB boss as a way of hindering it from engaging in oversight of financial organizations in the the US.</p>
</text>
