<text id="autogum_interview_doc684" title="part7_Sam Brownback on running for President, gay rights, the Middle East and religion" shortTile="partsam-brownback" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-12" dateModified="2014-12-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sam_Brownback_on_running_for_President%2C_gay_rights%2C_the_Middle_East_and_religion" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think it's a bad idea to have elections in countries if it's possible that an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Islamic%20fundamentalism">Islamic extremist group</ref> will win, such as happened in Palestine with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hamas">Hamas</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  No, I don't think it's necessarily a bad idea, but I also don't think elections necessarily mean that you're going to have an open, free society, as we've seen taking place in the Palestinian authority and the activities of Hamas and now them even throwing out <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Fatah">Fatah</ref> from the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gaza_Strip">Gaza Strip</ref>, and this huge conflict that's taking place there.  I think we're just gonna have to be a lot more <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/real%20politic">real politic</ref> about this in the Middle East and the Muslim region of the world, about how far you can push and how hard you can push the governmental systems without just going into the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Islamo-fascism">radical Islamic fascist</ref> regime.  One of the things I think we've gotta push a lot better, David, is to have the governments there provide services to the people, like health care and education, that are all too often being provided by these radical Islamic groups, so that people look more to the radical elements to meet their daily needs than the role that the government should be playing.  I think that's bad for us.  I think it's bad for the governments of those countries, and they need to do better about taking care of their own people.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think that things like the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gravina%20Island%20Bridge">Bridge to Nowhere</ref> are projects that shouldn't be funded?  And I'm using that popular phrase--I realize it's a little emotionally charged--but things such as that.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  Yes, I agree that they shouldn't be funded.  What I'd like to see is, again, you change the system.  You require an authorization before you can get an appropriation, so I think that'll cut down more on those projects more than anything else.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You support the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elon%20Peace%20Plan">Elon plan</ref> that would essentially allow Israel to keep the entire West Bank while taking little responsibility for its Arab residents.  The plan is against U.S., Israeli, Jordanian and Palestinian policies.  Why do you think that would advance peace in the Middle East?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  Well, at first, I didn't endorse the plan.  We put out a statement yesterday on this;  I think this is an interesting entry into a discussion that we haven't gotten very far at all with, this land-for-peace-type concept.  It has not produced peace.  I think what you're seeing in the Gaza Strip just further clarifies that.  The Palestinian authority was given full control over this--what happened, you had Hamas run Fatah out in a gun battle.  That's not a civil society. What I'm saying here is that it seems to me a good idea to look at a different model where you can get settlement of the Palestinian refugees and bring the Jordanians back into the picture on the West Bank, so you're not--you're looking more at a stable country like Jordan being involved, rather than trying to have the Palestinian authority take over when they've just shown no capacity to be able to govern.  That's why I think this is an interesting way for us to look forward.  I have not and I do not endorse the plan, but I do think we've gotta get different models on the table for discussion.</p>
</text>
