<text id="autogum_whow_doc201" title="Support Your Child&apos;s Unique Gifts in the School Environment" shortTile="support-childs-unique" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2010-12-17" dateModified="2018-03-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Support-Your-Child%27s-Unique-Gifts-in-the-School-Environment" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Support Your Child's Unique Gifts in the School Environment</head><p>So you have a child(s) that has a unique gift, and depending on your stance with views, you've decided the best way to fully support it in anyway possible. And with the even more troubling task of doing so in a school environment. This article will explain the nature, possible causation, and a way to support the gift.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Recognize the full potential of the gift. Under any circumstance, If you do not support it, your child will fail to understand why you support it, but do not see it's full potential. Every object in this world has a purpose, no matter how small, it's there to do something.</item>
<item>Let your child know you care. Depending on the age, the presence of this gift in your household (or another) is the physical representation of your child's thoughts and views of society as a whole. Their view right now is you. That's about it. If they don't know you care, their view of you will become darker with each passing day. Can't let that happen can we? With the positive response of them knowing you care, two things can happen. The first one being (if the original view of the world is above a neutral, ie. happy, joyful) that their gift will continue to grow. On the other hand that gift will either decay and cease to exist, or become as volatile as car wreck. Follow the next step to continue with the first option, for the second. And if both of these are not a problem, continue on.
<list type="unordered"><item>Loss. If you came to this step then the reason your child quit acknowledging the gift, is due to the possibility that the child's subconscious mind made a goal to gain attention from you and that the goal has been met. With you at his/her side, they are set free of doubt and misery. They know they can trust you.</item>
<item>Resentment. If you came to this step then the reason your child became so volatile is because he/she thinks you are "playing" his/her. The distrust has become more prominent, immediate action must take place at once to stop this from getting out of control. Unfortunately, this must be placed into your hands to be solved.</item></list></item>
<item>Make it known at their school. Try not to make it too known at their school. The child will be made fun of if too known, which defeats the purpose of this wikiHow. Stick to the principal and teacher(s) at their grade level.
<list type="unordered"><item>At this point you have nothing to worry about. Try to give constant support, telling them they are good at what they have, and cherishing what they give you, and never letting them feel alone.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always let them know you care.</item>
<item>Let them tell themselves about the unique gift.</item>
<item>Make sure they feel loved and supported.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Never let them feel alone.</item>
<item>Never start an argument concerning the gift.</item>
<item>If things go sour, get outside help.</item></list>
</text>
