<text id="autogum_whow_doc109" title="Monitor Internet Speed over Time on PC or Mac" shortTile="monitor-internet" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-03-30" dateModified="2019-05-16" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Monitor-Internet-Speed-over-Time-on-PC-or-Mac" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Monitor Internet Speed over Time on PC or Mac</head><p>This wikiHow teaches you how to monitor your internet speed over time on both PC and a Mac using TestMy.net or Speedcheck. Both of these tools will let you test your internet bandwidth for free and will work for both Mac and PC users. Using one of these websites, you'll be able to monitor changes to your internet speed over minutes, hours, or days, so you can keep up to date on how well your internet is performing.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Using TestMy.net to Monitor Internet Speed</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Navigate to the <ref target="https://testmy.net/auto">TestMy website</ref>. You should be on the automatic speed test page. <figure rend="Monitor Internet Speed over Time on PC or Mac Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are on the homepage just click on the AutoTest text on at the top of the page.</item></list></item>
<item>Click on the circle next to . This will test your upload and download internet speed. <figure rend="Monitor Internet Speed over Time on PC or Mac Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can test just your upload or download speed by clicking one instead.</item></list></item>
<item>Select how long you want to test your internet by clicking on . For example, you can set it to check your internet speed every 30 minutes. <figure rend="Monitor Internet Speed over Time on PC or Mac Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you set the time to less than 10 minutes the site will ask you to sign up.</item>
<item>Make sure pop-ups are not blocked or the test will be unable to refresh.</item></list></item>
<item>Select how often you want the test to repeat by clicking on . For instance, you can set it to repeat 5 times a day. <figure rend="Monitor Internet Speed over Time on PC or Mac Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on the  button to begin testing your speed. You can still browse normally on a different tab if you’d like or you can minimize the window and come back. <figure rend="Monitor Internet Speed over Time on PC or Mac Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Your information is not automatically saved unless you create an account. For longer tests,  you cannot turn off your computer even if you create an account.</item>
<item>If you plan on doing a test longer than a day it is recommended that you create an account in case of disconnection issues.</item>
<item>You can end the test early at any time by clicking the  button at the top.</item></list></item>
<item>Click on the  button to see how your internet speed changed. The graph will average out your speed and display changes over time. <figure rend="Monitor Internet Speed over Time on PC or Mac Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Testing Internet Speed Manually with Speedcheck</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Visit the <ref target="https://www.speedcheck.org/">Speedcheck website</ref>. The homepage is where you can begin the test. <figure rend="Monitor Internet Speed over Time on PC or Mac Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Decide how long and how often you want to test your net. You will need to check back in and run tests manually. You'll also need to leave your computer on or you can create an account to save your tests. <figure rend="Decidetech.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Create an account by clicking  and then  in the top-right corner of the page.</item></list></item>
<item>Click  to begin your internet speed test. Your data will be saved in your browser so leave your computer on while the tests run. <figure rend="Monitor Internet Speed over Time on PC or Mac Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you created an account you can start the test and turn off your computer after it finishes.</item></list></item>
<item>Check your results by clicking the  tab. It will be located at the top-right corner of the page. <figure rend="Monitor Internet Speed over Time on PC or Mac Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Run several tests throughout the day to calculate the average speed. Go back to the  tab whenever you want to begin another test. Having several tests throughout the day will show a better internet speed average under “History”. <figure rend="Monitor Internet Speed over Time on PC or Mac Step 11.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you wanted to test your speed over the week just run the test a few times each day over the week. In this case, creating an account would be best so you can save your results if the computer shuts off unexpectedly.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
