<text id="autogum_interview_doc742" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Christoph Bals of the NGO Germanwatch after conclusion of climate conference" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-12-24" dateModified="2009-03-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Christoph_Bals_of_the_NGO_Germanwatch_after_conclusion_of_climate_conference" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>What could cause some dynamics is that you need money for all these packages, and you can only really get that through strong reduction targets. Be it Climate charges or taxes, auctioning of emission certificates, or a sort of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tobin%20tax">Tobin tax</ref> on international emissions trading. That leads to those nations that want money out of the packages having an incentive to work for stronger reduction targets. It is to be hoped for that movement for strong emission targets as well as for the financing of technologies, forest protection and adaptation measures develops. And that a coalition of progressive industrial nations, least developed countries (the so called LDCs) and newly industrialized countries - for example <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China">China</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mexico">Mexico</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/South_Africa">South Africa</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/India">India</ref> - support this. There were first signs for such a development in Bali.</p>
<head id="Outlook_on_the_next_two_years">Outlook on the next two years</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: How do things continue after this conference? What's the course of events until the Conference in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Copenhagen">Copenhagen</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Denmark">Denmark</ref> 2009?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CB</hi>: The four packages climate protection targets, adaptation to climate change, accelerated commercial launching of the necessary technologies and financing of technology, forest protection and adaptation have to be negotiated in detail now. Next year there will be four rounds of negotiations. The final conclusion is to be reached by the end of 2009, at the climate summit in Copenhagen.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: What needs to happen in this period of time in your opinion? What do the agreements that are hopefully to be reached need to look like?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CB</hi>: The reduction of greenhouse gas emissions, so that a warming of more than 2°C (35.6 F) is averted, is central. The global average temperatures mustn't rise above 2°C in comparison with pre-industrial levels. We call this the aversion of the uncopeable, as the risks of such a warming would be simply too great.</p>
<p>To achieve this goal a reduction of greenhouse gas emissions by 50-85% by 2050 is necessary. For the middle term this means that the peak of global emissions needs to be reached in 10-15 years and that the output is cut considerably year after year from then onwards. The group of industrialized nations have to reduce their emissions by 25-40% till 2020 (compared to 1990 baselines) on average to make this possible.</p>
<p>Regarding adaptation, what we call coping with the inadvertable, the scale of funding is going to have to change. Roughly US$50 billion a year are going to be required.</p>
<hi rend="bold">We shouldn't think that the problem is just in the U.S., even if it is to be seen most clearly there. Many of us [Germans/Europeans] don't realize what the necessary emission cuts mean.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Christoph Bals</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: What do you see as (the biggest) obstacle(s) on the way to such an agreement? You've already mentioned the current U.S. administration.</hi></p>
</text>
