<text id="autogum_voyage_doc8" title="European classical music" shortTile="european-classical" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=148472" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>European classical music</head>


<p>Though many civilizations around the world have a tradition of <hi rend="bold">classical music</hi>, when used as a generic term, the phrase is usually understood as referring to the type of classical music that arose in <ref target="Europe">Europe</ref>.</p>

<head>History</head>
<p>While classical music has roots in the Middle Ages, the best-known epochs are the <hi rend="bold">Baroque period</hi> (late 16th to mid 18th century), the <hi rend="bold">Classical period</hi> (mid 18th to early 19th century) and the <hi rend="bold">Romantic period</hi> (19th to early 20th centuries). Of course, in practice the transition from one period to the next occurred gradually over a number of years, and music written during the transition periods often featured aspects of the periods they were straddling. Much classical music also continues to be written today, and contemporary classical music has at least a niche following in many parts of the world. </p>

<p>Since the late 19th century, European classical music has been greatly influenced by music from throughout the world. In particular, Impressionist composers (Claude Debussy and Maurice Ravel being the most famous) were influenced by <ref target="Java">Java</ref>nese and <ref target="Bali">Bali</ref>nese gamelan music and music from <ref target="China">China</ref>; <ref target="African-American%20history">African-American</ref> music such as ragtime, <ref target="jazz">jazz</ref> and the blues influenced numerous classical composers; and the complex polyrhythmic music of <ref target="Africa">Africa</ref> inspired many Modernist composers to use intricate rhythms and emphasize percussive sounds. In turn, colonization and cultural exchange spread the performance and composition of European-style classical music and classical music clearly influenced by both local and European traditions throughout the world. Interestingly, the main centre of classical music today is arguably shifting from Europe and North America to East Asia in the 21st century, as that part of the world has generally bucked the trend of the rising average age of classical music audiences.</p>

<head>Classical music today</head>

<p>Although classical music is somewhat a niche area in modern times, much of the music from the great classical composers of years gone buy continues to be pervade modern life, with such music often used in film scores, advertising and even quoted in modern pop music. Classical music continues to be composed today for modern film scores, with John Williams of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="Star%20Wars%20tourism">Star Wars</ref></hi> fame, Howard Shore of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="Lord%20of%20the%20Rings%20tourism">The Lord of the Rings</ref></hi> fame and Hans Zimmer being household names even to non-musically inclined people.</p>

<p>Some genres of classical music are <hi rend="bold">ballet</hi>, the <hi rend="bold">opera</hi>, the <hi rend="bold">symphony</hi>, the <hi rend="bold">concerto</hi>, <hi rend="bold">chamber music</hi>, the <hi rend="bold">sonata</hi> and <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Christianity%23Christian%20Music">liturgical music</ref></hi>.</p>

<head>Terminology</head>
<p>Music written before 1700 or so, and especially before 1600, is often called "early music", and instrumental ensembles that specialize in performing this repertoire are often called "early music" groups or, if they use instruments built in a similar style to those in use in those centuries, "original instruments" groups.</p>

<p>Music written since 1900, and especially after World War II, is often called "modern" or "contemporary" music, and ensembles specializing in the performance of these periods of classical music are often called "contemporary music" ensembles or, particularly if they concentrate on world premieres and other recently-composed music, "new music" ensembles.</p>

<p>Full-sized orchestras are often called "symphony orchestra" or "philharmonic". A symphony orchestra is one suitable for playing the standard symphonic repertoire, up to and including the symphonies of Shostakovich (for Mahler symphonies, additional personnel may need to be hired for the concert). "Philharmonic" means "love of harmony". Though these terms have different derivations, in practice, "symphony orchestra" and "philharmonic" refer to the same size of ensemble with the same complement of instruments that plays music from the same repertoire. That said, the exact composition of orchestras varies from piece to piece, and many operas and ballets require orchestras that differ significantly from the standard symphony orchestra. For example, Mozart's <hi rend="italic">Die Zauberflöte</hi> requires a glockenspiel, and most Baroque pieces and Classical period operas require a <hi rend="italic">basso continuo</hi> consisting of a harpsichord and perhaps a cello, theorbos and/or bassoons.</p>

<p>Most orchestras are composed of four instrument families, namely the string, woodwind, brass and percussion families. Despite their names, the terms "woodwind" and "brass" do not refer to the material the instrument is made of, but are instead used to classify the instruments based on how the sound is produced. For instance, the saxophone is usually made of brass, but is classified as a woodwind instrument, while the cornett and alphorn are usually made of wood, but are classified as brass instruments. The difference is that woodwind instruments require the performer to insert a reed or mouthpiece in their mouth or blow across a lip plate, whereas brass instruments require the performer to buzz their lips against a mouthpiece that is pressed against both lips.</p>

<p>Another question people newly introduced to orchestras often ask is what the difference is between the "first violins" and "second violins". The answer is that just as in a string quartet, there are two different violin parts that often play different notes and rhythms, but all these musicians are playing on violins.</p>

<p>In choral music, the four main voice types are, in descending order of pitch, the <hi rend="italic">soprano</hi>, <hi rend="italic">contralto</hi> or <hi rend="italic">alto</hi>, <hi rend="italic">tenor</hi> and <hi rend="italic">bass</hi>, with the former two usually sung by women and the latter two usually sung by men, though some church choirs and quite a few operas have boys singing the soprano and contralto parts. Soloists in operas and concert music such as oratorios also frequently include <hi rend="italic">mezzo-sopranos</hi> and <hi rend="italic">baritones</hi>, who are generally the middle voices of the women and men respectively. A <hi rend="italic">countertenor</hi> refers to a man singing in falsetto, thus allowing him to hit higher pitches. In an opera, the lead female singer is known as the <hi rend="italic">prima donna</hi>, while the lead male singer is known as the <hi rend="italic">primo uomo</hi>. In modern times, the prima donna is typically a soprano, while the primo uomo is typically a tenor, though the primo uomo roles were frequently taken by castrati (men who were castrated before puberty; their roles are usually played by countertenors or women in pants/breeches roles in modern-day revivals) during the Baroque and early Classical periods.</p>
</text>
