<text id="autogum_interview_doc222" title="part3_Wikinews interviews former New Mexico governor Gary Johnson, presidential nominee of the Libertarian Party" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-11-05" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_former_New_Mexico_governor_Gary_Johnson%2C_presidential_nominee_of_the_Libertarian_Party" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="Social_issues">Social issues</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">William S. Saturn</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Let's get into social issues now. You criticized President Obama for his stance that same-sex marriage be left to the states. With the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tenth%20Amendment%20to%20the%20United%20States%20Constitution">Tenth Amendment</ref> in mind, why should same-sex marriage be a federal issue and why should the federal government mandate that states allow same sex marriage?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Gary Johnson</hi>: Well I think that first and foremost that as president of the United States you take an oath to govern under strict adherence to the U.S. Constitution. I would espouse...I would suggest that marriage equality is a constitutionally guaranteed right of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Equal%20Protection%20Clause">Equal Protection Clause</ref> that is on par with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/African-American%20Civil%20Rights%20Movement%20(1955–1968)">Civil Rights of the sixties</ref>. It's not a states issue, that it's a federal issue and that the federal government should be involved. If you say it's a state issue where 42 states have said that marriage is between a man and a woman. Effectively what you're saying is that 'I'm not going to do anything when it comes to marriage equality', and I take the position that marriage equality is a constitutionally guaranteed right so goes the federal involvement.</p>
<head id="Libertarian_Party_and_political_future">Libertarian Party and political future</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">William S. Saturn</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Okay I'm getting to my final questions here. I want to talk about the Libertarian Party. The first nominee of the Party was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20Hospers">John Hospers</ref>, who died last year, and he was a supporter of Republican President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/George_W._Bush">George W. Bush</ref>. The next nominee <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roger%20MacBride">Roger MacBride</ref> also left the party and went to the Republican Party. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20presidential%20election,%201988">1988</ref> nominee Ron Paul, as we all know, serves in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_House_of_Representatives">House of Representatives</ref> as a member of the Republican Party, and his son [<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rand%20Paul">Rand Paul</ref>] serves in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_Senate">Senate</ref> as a member of the Republican Party. Both the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_presidential_election,_2008">2008</ref> presidential and vice-presidential nominees of the Libertarian Party: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bob_Barr">Bob Barr</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wayne%20Allyn%20Root">Wayne Allyn Root</ref> have recently rejoined the Republican Party and have both endorsed Mitt Romney for president.  In fact, until the end of last year, you too were a member of the Republican Party. So why does it seem Libertarians flock to the Republican Party?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Gary Johnson</hi>: I'm not so certain...I think that the tie-in is [libertarian] Republicans are fiscally conservative and socially accepting. That's the, I think, the heading under which most Americans are. I will just tell you that last night, although it did not happen, apparently the Democrats were going to come and protest my speaking at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University%20of%20Colorado%20at%20Boulder">University of Colorado at Boulder</ref>. I guess it was all those anti-gay, anti-immigration, pro-Drug War, pro-military interventionists that were going to show up and protest me.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">But you admit that there are some Liberty Republicans and that Republicans make up a large portion of libertarians. Is that correct?</hi></p>
</text>
