<text id="autogum_news_doc520" title="Vintage plane crashes into road during Shoreham Airshow in England" shortTile="vintage-plane-crashes" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-08-23" dateModified="2018-12-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Vintage_plane_crashes_into_road_during_Shoreham_Airshow_in_England" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Vintage plane crashes into road during Shoreham Airshow in England</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, August 23, 2015</hi></p>
<figure><caption>The crashed aircraft, pictured in 2013 during a display.Image: <ref target="https://www.flickr.com/people/65001151@N03">Alan Wilson</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>Police warn more bodies may remain to be found after yesterday's crash of a vintage jet killed at least seven people. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hawker%20Hunter">Hawker Hunter</ref> crashed into a busy road during the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Shoreham_Airshow">Shoreham Airshow</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/England">England</ref>.</p>
<p>The plane failed to pull out of a large loop at around 1:20p.m. It hit the nearby <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A27%20road">A27 road</ref>, erupting into a fireball and leaving cars burned out and heavily damaged. The scene in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/West_Sussex">West Sussex</ref> is near the town of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Shoreham">Shoreham</ref>.</p>
<p>Pilot Andy Hill is presently alive but critically injured in hospital. He has previously flown with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/British_Airways">British Airways</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Royal_Air_Force">Royal Air Force</ref>. Two of the dead are <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Worthing%20United%20FC">Worthing United FC</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Association_football">football</ref> players, Matthew Grimstone and Jacob Schilt, who were on their way to a match. </p>
<p>Also killed was Matt Jones, 24, who worked as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/personal%20trainer">personal trainer</ref>. He came from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Littlehampton">Littlehampton</ref> and was giving a friend a lift. A vintage <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daimler">Daimler</ref> wedding limousine on its way to collect a bride was also caught up in the crash, but its owner Chariot Chauffeurs say they are unclear on if the driver was a fatality.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sussex_Police">Sussex Police</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Air_Accidents_Investigation_Branch">Air Accidents Investigation Branch</ref> are investigating. Police Superintendent Jane Derrick said last night, "At this time we are continuing to search[...] It is possible that tonight and tomorrow we are going to find more bodies at the scene." She said it is believed all casualties except the pilot were road users. At least fourteen were injured. </p>
<figure><caption>A Hawker Hunter displaying at last year's show.Image: <ref target="https://www.flickr.com/people/62787780@N06">John5199</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>Assistant Chief Constable Steve Barry today said eleven people are "highly likely to have died in this tragedy", based upon "our initial work at the site" and "inquiries following calls to the emergency services from worried families and friends". He said officers currently remain at the "incredibly large" scene. There are plans to remove plane wreckage using a crane tomorrow.</p>
<p>The pilot, Hill, was experienced, with years of display flying under his belt and a military career that included flying <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harrier%20jet">Harrier jump-jets</ref>. David Wildridge, another pilot who took part yesterday, said Hill is "well-known and well-loved", "very professional", and that his Harrier experience made him "the best of the best."</p>
<p>The 1950s jet was decommissioned from military service in 1996 and sold at auction. In 2012 English entrepreneur Graham Peacock bought it for around <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/pound%20sterling">£</ref>65,000. It is a regular at airshows. </p>
<p>Tina Tilley, head of the local chamber of commerce, was at the show and said "From where we were we could see the jet came down very low and looked like it was going to scoop up — but it didn't. There were flames and we knew it was right on the A27. Everyone was horrified and there were people crying." Motorist Dom Lawson, whose car was narrowly missed, said "It was like something out of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Die%20Hard">Die Hard</ref></hi>". The road closure left thousands trapped at the scene as they could not remove their cars.</p>
<p>In a statement, Prime Minister <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/David_Cameron">David Cameron</ref> sent "his heartfelt condolences to the families of the people who were so tragically killed [...] [his] thoughts and prayers are with the families and friends of the victims." The airshow is cancelled today.</p>
<p>It is one of three deadly <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Europe">European</ref> airshow crashes in four days. On Thursday two planes carrying parachutists collided and crashed in West <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Slovakia">Slovakia</ref>. At least seven were killed. They had been practising for an airshow due to be held this weekend. Today two small planes collided during an airshow in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dittingen">Dittingen</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Switzerland">Switzerland</ref>. One of the pilots escaped but the other was killed.</p>
<p>Earlier this year a pilot was killed when his plane crashed during an aerial display at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CarFest">CarFest</ref> in England. In 2007 a Shoreham Airshow display recreating the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle%20of%20Britain">Battle of Britain</ref> ended with a pilot dead following a crash.</p>
Those concerned about relatives can call police on 01273 470101
</text>
