<text id="autogum_whow_doc108" title="Get Popular on the Internet" shortTile="popular-internet" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2009-08-23" dateModified="2019-08-22" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get-Popular-on-the-Internet" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get Popular on the Internet</head><p>You've been on the net for years. Yet, almost nobody knows about your web presence. You just want to be well known and you want people to talk about your online prowess and exploits. To become popular on the internet is possible, it'll just require a bit more effort beyond what you're doing normally.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Creating an Online Presence</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Understand why do you want to get popular. Be absolutely certain that you want to be a popular online presence. With popularity comes loss of peace, the inability to move around quietly and a need to maintain a great reputation in your chosen field of popularity. This can add up to a lot of effort, especially if you're not being paid for it and have to keep that day job up. It can also erode your humility and cause you to behave in ways that aren't entirely you and can lead to dissatisfaction. If you're okay with this, proceed with the next steps. <figure rend="Get Popular on the Internet Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Join plenty of social networking sites. Start with the well known ones, such as Twitter, Facebook and the like. Then tailor your online presence to the area for which you're keen to be known, such as graphic design, scene fashion, smoothies-maker extraordinaire, medical explanations guru, or whatever it is. Find a blog, website, portal, forum, etc., where you can make the most of your talents and start creating your presence there through adding information, interacting and being around a lot. <figure rend="Get Popular on the Internet Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Join bigger social sites. Go onto <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_a_Friendster_Layout">Friendster</ref>, start stalking some people – be sure to add a lot of friends for yourself. <figure rend="Get Popular on the Internet Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pick the sites Google likes. That way, your name has a better chance of coming back in the top first page returns when people search online for you and your talents. Google is always reworking its algorithms, so check Alexa and similar to find out which social networking sites are currently hip and happening.</item>
<item>Link to high page rank sites that are related to your site is the key.  Submit to directories such as <ref target="http://www.Addyoursitefreesubmit.com">Add Your Site Free Submit</ref> <figure rend="Get Popular on the Internet Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Post your creations, knowledge, information, comments, etc., on different sites. Work the imagination and make a site work for you. As for people who want to be popular for their style or looks, obviously, start <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Copyright_Photographs">posting your pictures</ref> all over the web. Get someone able to take quality pictures of you. <figure rend="Get Popular on the Internet Step 3.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Being the Kind of Person Others Love to Connect With</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be unique. If you're copying everyone else, there is a good chance that you're not going to be seen or heard about. Few people are keen to see the same, same. Thus, think of a new trend, or try something that nobody has done before, even if it's a common topic done very differently.</item>
<item>Be nice. And be genuinely nice, not just putting on an act.  <figure rend="Get Popular on the Internet Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you want to be known as grumpy and gruff, don't chop and change by pretending to be nice one minute, then horrible the next. Get your brand straight.</item></list></item>
<item>Join sites that have <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Stay_on_Top_of_Internet_Forums_with_Firefox">forums</ref>. Then be available and interactive, so that people can get to know you and trust in you. <figure rend="Get Popular on the Internet Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be aware that this is likely to chew up your time considerably. Be careful what discussions you get involved in; keep it light, friendly and caring.</item></list></item>
<item>Add friends. When you're on social websites, add many friends. Have a big list of them! Because the friends of your friends will start adding you, and you'll get more and more well known. <figure rend="Get Popular on the Internet Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Provide valuable updates, insights and information. People are thirsty for good content, not self-love. Give them something they're keen to watch, read or listen to. Introduce them to interesting things on a regular basis. Bring together the energies of other people whose work and updates add value to yours, so that you spread around support for others online.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>For to be-popular internet celebs, get someone to take pictures of you.And sometimes, you will have to photo shop your pics (read the tip above).</item>
<item>For to be-popular graphic designers, get a good editing program like <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Try_Adobe_Photoshop_CS4_for_Free">Adobe Photoshop.</ref></item>
<item>Do you know how the graphic designer Nineland got popular? She worked as a graphic designer for a site called Miss Bimbo.</item>
<item>Plan on stuff! For example "Today, I'm <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Convince_Your_Parents_to_Let_You_Have_a_MySpace">joining Myspace</ref> and I'm going to add 10 friends".</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't give up. You will never become popular on the internet just in a week. For some, it takes six months, for others it takes longer.</item>
<item>Don't let popularity spoil you. If you're popular, it doesn't mean that you're any better than your (internet) friends. Respect everyone.</item>
<item>Don't get into fights. This might make people dislike you. And your popularity might move down/ become lower.</item>
<item>Popularity dies easily. It's okay to be away from the internet for a week, two weeks. But when you reach five months, don't be surprised if someone has taken your place. This is how it is, people love novelty and fresh faces. Becoming popular is easy but keeping it is hard at the same time.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>A good editing program</item>
<item>Someone to take pics of you (optional)</item>
<item>Good social sites to join</item>
<item>Tutorials to help you in graphic designing (optional)</item>
<item>Someone that you will try to be like {optional)</item></list>
</text>
