<text id="autogum_academic_doc499" title="STAT3: An Emerging Therapeutic Target for Hepatocellular Carcinoma" shortTile="stat-emerging-therapeutic" author="Carol Lee, Siu  Tim Cheung" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6694/11/11/1646/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Primary liver cancer is the sixth most prevalent cancer and the second leading cause of cancer mortality worldwide. The most common primary liver cancer is hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC), which accounts for &gt;85% of all cases. HCC predominantly arises in the setting of cirrhosis associated with hepatitis B and C virus infections, alcohol abuse, non-alcoholic steatohepatitis and metabolic diseases. Early-stage HCC patients are often subjected to surgical resection and liver transplantation. However, 5-year recurrence rates after resection reach &gt;70% and the efficiency of transplantation is limited by organ shortage and technical issues. Although local ablation and transarterial chemoembolization respectively confer 5-year survival rates of 50–70% and survival benefit of &gt;6 months, they are confined to patients with single tumors or multinodular tumors with good liver reserve. Chemotherapy is not routinely used due to the chemoresistant character of HCC. For advanced HCC, sorafenib, a multi-tyrosine kinase inhibitor (MTKI), has been the only approved systemic first-line agent for over a decade, until lenvatinib, another MTKI, recently came into play. Yet, their clinical efficacy was suboptimal, with only ~3 months of prolonged survival. Second-line treatments include regorafenib and cabozantinib, also MTKIs; nivolumab and pembrolizumab, immune checkpoint inhibitors targeting programmed death-1 (PD-1); and ramucirumab, the first biomarker-driven therapeutics approved for HCC that targets the angiogenic vascular endothelial growth factor receptor (VEGFR), all of which have not been established until the past few years and require further investigations. So far, treatment outcomes for HCC are far from satisfactory, with a 5-year survival rate of only ~18%. Evidently, there is an urgent need to develop more effective therapeutic strategies in HCC. </p>

<p>Signal transducer and activator of transcription 3 (STAT3) has recently emerged as a potential therapeutic target for HCC due to its crucial roles in oncogenesis. STAT3 was initially determined to control acute-phase genes in response to interleukin-6 (IL-6) and epidermal growth factor (EGF) during inflammation. It belongs to the STAT family of cytoplasmic transcription factors that mediate signal transduction from the plasma membrane to the nucleus in various cellular activities. The STAT family comprises seven members: STAT1, 2, 3, 4, 5a, 5b and 6. Each of them consists of (i) an N-terminal domain for oligomerization, (ii) a coiled-coil domain for interaction with regulatory proteins, (iii) a DNA-binding domain for recognition of specific DNA sequences, (iv) a Src homology-2 (SH2) domain that triggers phosphorylation and dimerization after docking to phosphorylated receptors and (iv) a C-terminal transactivation domain with specific tyrosine (Y) (present in all STATs) and serine (S) residues (absent in STAT2 and 6) that are phosphorylated upon transcriptional activation.  </p>

<p>Intensive investigation has been done on STAT3 since its discovery, revealing its physiological roles in early embryonic development, growth and differentiation of various adult tissues. In addition, its pathogenic roles in cancer initiation, progression, metastasis, chemoresistance and immunoevasion have been uncovered. To date, STAT3 is widely recognized as an oncogenic factor in diverse human cancers. Therefore, targeting STAT3 might be an attractive therapeutic strategy for HCC treatment. In this review, we summarize the oncogenic roles of STAT3 in HCC and the current clinical development of STAT3-targeted therapeutics. </p>
</text>
