<text id="autogum_interview_doc830" title="part0_ACLU President Strossen on religion, drugs, guns and impeaching George Bush" shortTile="partaclu-president" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-30" dateModified="2019-02-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/ACLU_President_Strossen_on_religion%2C_drugs%2C_guns_and_impeaching_George_Bush" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>ACLU President Strossen on religion, drugs, guns and impeaching George Bush</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 30, 2007</hi>
<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Special:FilePath/Nadine_Strossen_5_by_David_Shankbone.jpg">File:Nadine Strossen 5 by David Shankbone.jpg</ref></p><figure><caption><hi rend="bold">Nadine Strossen:</hi> "People will often ask me, “Wasn’t it hard for you when the ACLU defended the rights of the Nazis to march in Skokie?” No! For me, it’s never about the Nazis, it’s about freedom of speech. It’s about the principle. So I tend to see things in a rather abstract level. For every bad piece of mail I receive, I get marriage proposals, love letters, letters of praise!"All photos: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref><hi rend="italic">(Image <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Template:Missing_image/message">missing</ref> from commons: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/File:Nadine_Strossen_5_by_David_Shankbone.jpg">image</ref>; <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Special:Log?page=Image%3ANadine+Strossen+5+by+David+Shankbone.jpg">log</ref>)</hi></caption></figure>
<p>There are few organizations in the United States that elicit a stronger emotional response than the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ACLU">American Civil Liberties Union</ref>, whose stated goal is "to defend and preserve the individual rights and liberties guaranteed to every person in this country by the Constitution and laws of the United States".  Those people include gays, Nazis, women seeking abortion, gun owners, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SPAM">SPAM</ref> mailers and drug users.  People who are often not popular with various segments of the public.  The ACLU's philosophy is not that it agrees or disagrees with any of these people and the choices that they make, but that they have personal liberties that must not be trampled upon.  </p>
<p>In <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref>'s interview with the President of the ACLU, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nadine%20Strossen">Nadine Strossen</ref>, he wanted to cover some basic ground on the ACLU's beliefs.  Perhaps the area where they are most misunderstood or have their beliefs most misrepresented is their feelings about religion in the public sphere.  The ACLU categorically does not want to see religion disappear from schools or in the public forum; but they do not want to see government advocacy of any particular religion.  Thus, former Alabama Chief Justice Roy Moore's placement of a ten ton monument to the Ten Commandments outside the courthouse is strenuously opposed; but "Lone Ranger of the Manger" Rita Warren's placement of nativity scenes in public parks is vigorously defended.  In the interview, Strossen talks about how certain politicians and televangelists purposefully misstate the law and the ACLU's work in order to raise funds for their campaigns.</p>
<p>David Shankbone's discussion with Strossen touches upon many of the ACLU's hot button issues:  religion, Second Amendment rights, drug liberalization, "partial-birth abortion" and whether or not George W. Bush should be impeached.  It may surprise the reader that many ideas people have about the most visible of America's civil libertarian organizations are not factually correct and that the ACLU often works closely with many of the organizations people think despise its existence.</p>
<head id="Strossen's_background">Strossen's background</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">David Shankbone:</hi>  Why did you want to be an attorney?</p>
</text>
