<text id="autogum_reddit_doc053" title="Who else has been overlooked because of cronyism? What was your experience and what did you do?" shortTile="overlooked-cronyism" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-05-31" dateModified="2018-05-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8nmtih" speakerList="#ForestParkRanger, #ipv_throwaway" speakerCount="2">
<head>Who else has been overlooked because of cronyism? What was your experience and what did you do?</head>
<sp who="#ipv_throwaway">
<p>I recently left my organisation for a different role which was more senior and higher paid. However, because of the ‘loyalty’ I held for my previous company, it was a very tough decision. However, that decision became far easier once I realised a level of cronyism displayed by an ex-colleague who always ‘acted’ like a friend and confidant to me. Story time: I recently applied for an internal promotion at my company. I was highly experienced having spent 6 years in that team at various team lead roles before taking a lateral move for broader experience, I had all the right qualifications, I knew and am respected by the team still after being away for a few years (just a different department). I found it very funny when I didn’t even get an interview. Even when I enquired with people I knew and had been close with they gave me a very cold or standard reply. I took it on face value assuming they didn’t want to sully the competitive recruitment process and run a fair process. Wrong. The person who got the job was an external hire, from a totally different industry, but who has flashy qualifications and positions, and to top it off, is an old and dear friend of the guy doing the recuriting, the guy who will be his boss. End story time. So yes, it happened to me and I felt very jaded. I wonder how many people it’s happened to and whether cronyism is just an inevitable part of employment. I know for me my professional respect for the people involved has gone to practically zero and if they ever asked for professional support or a role with me or my new company in the future I would go out of my way to make sure they didn’t succeed. So that makes me wonder also, is there such a thing as ‘reverse cronyism’ too? Anyways, just thought I’d start the discussion.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#ForestParkRanger">
<p>From my point of view, your lateral move away from the team may have been the mistake. Moving up in responsibility or a promotion is a good reason to leave to another internal team. Broader experience lateral move signals “I don’t want to work with you guys anymore” which makes it hard for the hiring manager to bring you back. That may not have been your intention but that’s what it looked like. I’m not saying it’s fair but appearances matter in a professional environment. When you leave a team it HAS to make sense for the people you leave behind, managers and co-workers. Otherwise it looks like you are quitting them.</p>
</sp>
</text>
