<text id="autogum_interview_doc225" title="part1_Jack Herrick, wikiHow founder interviewed by Wikinews" shortTile="partjack-herrick" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-01-31" dateModified="2010-07-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jack_Herrick%2C_wikiHow_founder_interviewed_by_Wikinews" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>'<hi rend="italic">((</hi><hi rend="italic">WN))</hi><hi rend="bold">Why did you decide to create wikiHow?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JH:</hi> I think that providing people with a practical education is one of the most empowering things you can offer a person. Imagine having detailed step-by-step instructions on how to do any activity you could imagine. How much more could you accomplish as an individual if you could learn any activity? I think that building a universal how-to manual would be a tremendous gift for the world. Knowledge is power and wikiHow has the potential to make all of us a bit more powerful.</p>
<p>I've been interested in building a comprehensive how-to manual long before I first envisioned wikiHow. My first attempt at building this resource was a website I used to run called eHow. eHow was and continues to be the largest and how to website in the world. eHow contains copyrighted content run on proprietary software. When I ran eHow, the content was professionally produced and edited. This business model worked for producing content on topics that appeal to advertisers in languages like English that have large advertising markets.  However, paying people to write and edit articles ultimately means that you have to make one of two sacrifices. You either 1) sacrifice on breadth and don't produce the topics that won't interest advertisers, or 2) you sacrifice on quality and produce content that doesn't cost much to write.  I wasn't interested in making either of these sacrifices, as I think the world's how to manual needs to be high quality AND comprehensive. So ultimately I decided that eHow's model would not build the resource I envisioned. When I discovered Wikipedia, I recognized that the wiki model had the potential to build the how-to resource the world really needs. So I decided to sell eHow and use the proceeds to build wikiHow.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why did you decide to use a Creative Commons license?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JH:</hi> We use a Creative Commons license to give our community the right to fork (<ref target="http://www.wikihow.com/wikiHow:Right-to-Fork">http://www.wikihow.com/wikiHow:Right-to-Fork</ref>). In my opinion, people should be hesitant to contribute to websites where you only have the "right to leave." If wikiHow volunteers think our site is going in the wrong direction, they can take all the content and all the software and move the project elsewhere. This is possible because we release all of our software under the Open Source GPL license and release our content under a Creative Commons license. This right to fork guarantees that wikiHow, the company, will always serve the goal of the mission and our volunteer community. I believe that offering this right to fork has been a key element of our success thus far. My hope is that over time, internet users will demand this of any site where they invest their time in a way that creates value for others.</p>
</text>
