<text id="autogum_interview_doc541" title="part14_Billy West, voice of Ren and Stimpy, Futurama, on the rough start that shaped his life" shortTile="partbilly-west-voice" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-13" dateModified="2013-06-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Billy_West%2C_voice_of_Ren_and_Stimpy%2C_Futurama%2C_on_the_rough_start_that_shaped_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  Well yeah. All I was presented with was life as it was deconstructing and disintegrating. And I had to pick up whatever pieces I had off the floor and try to put it together in a way that made sense to me. I don’t know if I’m making myself all that clear.</p>
<hi rend="bold">I really love what I do and I don’t want people to think I’m sitting here angry all the time. I’m absolutely happy and I like what my life has become. But I still will start feeling weird if somebody asks me a question and I can’t tell the truth about it. I’m just telling it like it is.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right"><hi rend="bold">—Billy West</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  No you are. </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  Yeah, I’m telling you stuff that I never said to anybody.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Well it’s good.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  You’re like the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barbara%20Walters">Barbara Walters</ref> of your generation.  And I’m not going to protect an image I don’t really have.  Nobody wants to hear what I really think about politics. I totally understand it. It’s like, every night is opening night if you’re a performer. Okay that’s done. Now what? I mean if everyone had to answer that standard in their job.  "Now what are you going to do?" Because I don’t get told what to do. I audition for everything because if you want to work you’ve got to audition. Some people call me out of the blue and say, 'We just want you,' which is very nice and I worked really hard for that status. But I still audition for everything. There’s a show coming up called Rahan and there’s a 26 episode commitment on that. I’ll be starting that soon. I can’t tell you much about it because I’ve only read the auditions, the lines I was supposed to do. And the other thing is <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Futurama">Futurama</ref></hi> is going to keep me busy for awhile even though all the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/voice-over">voice-over</ref> work is done. There’s lots of projects that are related to it. And I’m still doing the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/M&amp;M's">M&amp;Ms</ref>. I really love what I do and I don’t want people to think I’m sitting here angry all the time. I’m absolutely happy and I like what my life has become. But I still will start feeling weird if somebody asks me a question and I can’t tell the truth about it. I’m just telling it like it is.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That's perfect.  I will send you a link to the interview when it is published.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  That would be fine. I’d appreciate it. There's so much wrong on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikipedia">Wikipedia</ref>, like that I got booted off the Stern show.  I feel a lot of dehumanized lie dispensers get a hold of these things and just make it so. Believe me, there’s this very small but very active group of posters that want to keep dancing in the pet cemetery with animal corpses.</p>
</text>
