<text id="autogum_reddit_doc101" title="I keep getting rejected" shortTile="keep-getting-rejected" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-04-30" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8g42n9" speakerList="#Honeybadger193, #Keto-420" speakerCount="2">
<head>I keep getting rejected</head>
<sp who="#Honeybadger193">
<p>So, I'm 25 m I'll get that out of the way now. My last and only real relationship lasted like 4 or 5 months. I idk why I'm here really, because I'm probably just going to get the generic "just be yourself" "you'll find someone eventually" "be confident" bullshit "advice" that everyone regurgitates on these things. Like, I'm on Tinder and Hinge and Blendr. So I'll get a "someone new likes you" notification from tinder, and I'll go see who it is cuz I have tinder gold. If I think she's cute I'll match, and then I usually wait like 5 minutes before sending a message so I dont come across as desperate. The last 5 times I've got match, I go back to message them and I have no new matches. I feel like I'm always the accidental swipe. Blendr is shitty to begin with but i get ghosted almost every single time. Havent even had a match on hinge. Then a few weeks ago, I went out with some friends, and was outside having a smoke and chatting with a girl I've known for a while, kinda bar friends, we text often enough though. I decide "fuck it I'm half drunk, imma ask her out" so I ask if she wants to maybe get brunch the next day, as a date, and I get laughed at and a "omg no." Now, i know for a fact she wasn't  <hi rend="bold">that</hi>  drunk and neither was I, I was at that perfect kinda drunk where you're hella confident about everything ya dig? So at this point idk what to do; dating apps dont work, I literally get laughed at IRL, I'm at a loss. I'm in excellent shape, I work out 5 days a week...well usually (yay for mandatory 12 hr shifts for the last 6 weeks). Anyway, I'm fairly good looking I guess? Ive got a bit of a dry/sarcastic sense of humor, but I've been told I'm funny. The icing on the cake has to be the number of women that I work with who all seem surprised that I'm single. "You're nice/polite, good looking kid..." The typical stuff. Granted, I'm pretty sure there are only about 4 women in the entire manufacturing side of things within 5 years of me, the rest are much older. I just...I dont see the point in trying anymore, rejection after rejection after rejection hurts like a motherfucker. I was always told, "don't look for it'll happen" ive tried that, and it got me nowhere. I'm sorry if this sounds angry and r/niceguy kinda thing. I'm kinda drunk and just needed to vent. </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#Keto-420">
<p>I'll try to steer clear of the advice you don't want. </p>
<p>Instead, I have a few questions. </p>
<p>What do you usually message women on dating apps as a conversation starter? </p>
<p>Do you recognize if you have a specific type? Either looks or personality. </p>
<p>If so, have you ever tried to match with women that are maybe a bit outside of that type? </p>
<p>As for rejection.. Yeah, it sucks. You kind of just have to get used to it and learn to take it in stride. Better to try and get rejected, than to not try at all. </p>
<p>I once started dating a guy off of an anonymous app. We talked for a few days before exchanging pictures. This ensured that we actually liked talking to each other, and that it wasn't just based on physical attraction. </p>
<p>I've found that dating was much more free of pressure, once I stopped caring as much about looks. If someone is kind, caring and able to carry an intellectual conversation, looks just don't mean as much. That's not to say that looks don't have anything to say, as attraction is obviously necessary for a relationship. </p>
</sp>
</text>
