<text id="autogum_whow_doc532" title="Name Your Chinchilla" shortTile="name-chinchilla" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2017-08-25" dateModified="2019-09-14" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Name-Your-Chinchilla" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Name Your Chinchilla</head><p>Chinchillas are cute pets known for their thick, rich coats. As with most other types of pet, you can name your chinchilla anything you please. If you’re struggling to come up with a name for your pet, there are different places you can look for inspiration. You can name chinchillas after their physical features, the color of their coat, after one of their personality traits. If nothing seems to fit, you can just choose a human name and give it to the chinchilla.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Finding Namesakes for Your Chinchilla</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Choose a short name for easier training. If you're planning on training your chinchilla, choose a name that's not too long or complicated. Your chinchilla will probably only recognize the first 1-2 syllables, so a shorter name is always better. <figure rend="Create a Baby Name from Parent's Names Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you choose a long name, like Penelope, you could shorten it to a nickname, such as Penny.</item></list></item>
<item>Name your chinchilla after their ears. Most chinchillas have large, floppy ears that are immediately noticeable. In nature, these ears help them hear prey and escape from predators. In captivity, however, the ears can lead to funny names for your pet. Consider naming your chinchilla: <figure rend="Name Your Chinchilla Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Dumbo, from the Disney movie of the same name.</item>
<item>Gizmo, from the movie <hi rend="italic">Gremlins</hi>.</item>
<item>Despereaux, from the movie <hi rend="italic">The Tale of Despereaux</hi>.</item></list></item>
<item>Give the chinchilla the name of a famous mouse. Chinchillas are mammals in the rodent family, and as such, they share physical and behavioral traits with many other rodents. You could name your chinchilla after any famous pop-culture rodents or creatures who share the same chubby body, large ears, and cute muzzle. <figure rend="Name Your Chinchilla Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Mickey (if it’s male)</item>
<item>Minnie (if it’s female)</item>
<item>Jerry, from the <hi rend="italic">Tom and Jerry</hi> cartoon</item>
<item>Pikachu</item></list></item>
<item>Borrow a name from TV, literature, or history. Your reading and viewing preferences will put a wealth of names at your fingertips. You can name your chinchilla after your favorite character in a book or play, or a popular TV show or movie. Not only will this make the name easy to remember, but many of your friends will also know what the name refers to. <figure rend="Name Your Chinchilla Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Borrow a name from literature, like Macbeth or Ophelia.</item>
<item>If you prefer movies or TV, name your chinchilla after a famous character like Buffy, Shirley Temple, or Tinkerbell.</item>
<item>If you like history, name your chinchilla after a historical figure like Kit Carson, Napoleon, or Lincoln.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Naming the Chinchilla after Its Fur</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Name the chinchilla “Dusty.” Chinchillas take dust baths in order to maintain their coat and keep their bodies clean. Use this fact when naming your chinchilla; “Dusty” would be a suitable name for either a male or female chinchilla. <figure rend="Name Your Chinchilla Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can name your pet other words that are synonymous to dusty, like “Sandy.”</item></list></item>
<item>Create a name based on the color of its coat. Chinchillas’ standard coat color is gray. While this may not seem like the most exciting color to base a name off of, there are quite a few words that are synonymous with shades of gray that make good pet names. Consider: <figure rend="Name Your Chinchilla Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Onyx</item>
<item>Smokey</item>
<item>Olive</item>
<item>Oatmeal</item></list></item>
<item>Find a name for an uncommonly colored chinchilla. Decades of breeding practices and mild genetic mutations have led to a large variety in the colors of chinchillas’ coats. Their fur can be a variety of shades of gray, many shades of beige, black (called “ebony”), or white. <figure rend="Name Your Chinchilla Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If your chinchilla’s fur has pink or reddish tones, you could name it Rose or Rosie.</item>
<item>Many chinchillas have a slight blue tint to their fur. You could name such a chinchilla Sapphire or just Blue.</item>
<item>If your chinchilla is black, you could name it Licorice.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Naming the Chinchilla after its Personality</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Base the chinchilla’s name on its funny behavior. Chinchillas can appear comical because of their large bodies, small faces, and curious nature. Pick a name that reflects these aspects of your chinchilla, like: Furry, Floppy, or Fluffy. <figure rend="Name Your Chinchilla Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Chinchillas are also naturally acrobatic animals. You could name the pet Jumper, as you’ll often see it leaping around its cage.</item></list></item>
<item>Base your chinchilla’s name on its nocturnal habits. Like many other types of rodent pets (including hamsters), chinchillas are nocturnal. This means that your chinchilla will be active primarily at night and spend a large part of the day sleeping. Use this to give you ideas for names, including: <figure rend="Name Your Chinchilla Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Sleepy</item>
<item>Grumpy</item>
<item>Night Owl</item></list></item>
<item>Name your chinchilla “Chilly” after their preferred temperature. Chinchillas thrive as pets when they’re kept at cooler temperatures—ideally between 58 and 68°F (14.4 and 20°C). You could also change the spelling and name the chinchilla Chile. This is doubly appropriate, since chinchillas are native to the country of Chile. <figure rend="Name Your Chinchilla Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Avoid choosing an extremely long name (say, over 12 characters) for your chinchilla. At some point you’ll have to fill out paperwork for the animal (e.g. at the vet’s office) and the form may not be able to accommodate a very long name.</item>
<item>Avoid your chinchilla's name being irrelevant to their physical or internal traits because you may forget it and will have to get your chinchilla used to a new name which could slow down the process of taming and teaching new tricks to your chinchilla.</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
