<text id="autogum_academic_doc162" title="Targeted Delivery Prodigiosin to Choriocarcinoma by Peptide-Guided Dendrigraft Poly-l-lysines Nanoparticles" shortTile="targeted-delivery" author="Kai Zhao, Dan Li, Guogang Cheng, Baozhen Zhang, Jinyu Han, Jie Chen, Baobei Wang, Mengxia Li, Tianxia Xiao, Jian Zhang, Dongpo Zhou, Zheng Jin, Xiujun Fan" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1422-0067/20/21/5458/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Cancer has been a major threat to human health in recent years. In the past forty years, even though great efforts have been made, there is still much to be done before a safe therapy is achieved. Currently, chemotherapy and radiotherapy are still the main therapeutic methods for cancer. However, most of the anticancer drugs have toxic side effects. Therefore, it is critical to develop novel anticancer drugs that have no toxic side effects on other tissues or organs in vivo, and only target the lesion area. Compared with traditional chemotherapeutic drugs, the nano-anticancer drug therapy has potential application prospects in curing cancer diseases. </p>

<p>One of the major concerns about the nano-anticancer drugs is the drug-delivery vector. The ideal delivery vector should possess such characteristics as a high drug-loading capacity, low immunogenicity, low toxicity, better shelf-life, and water solubility, and it should have the potential to be further modified. Synthetic polymers, such as, chitosan, polyetherimide (PEI), poly(lactic-co-glycolic acid) (PLGA), polyamidoamine (PAMAM), and poly-l-lactic acid (PLA) have been widely used in gene- and drug-delivery systems. However, stability of sustained-release formulations in aqueous solution, long delivery times, and low delivery efficiency are only a small part of the challenges highlighted by researchers. Dendrigraft poly-l-lysines (DGL) have emerged as a new kind of synthetic polymer consisting of lysine and have been employed as drug- or gene-delivery carriers, due to their biodegradability and rich external amino groups that can encapsulate drugs by the emulsion crosslinking method or plasmid DNA through electric interactions. Besides their biodegradability, they can also be modified with targeting ligands and polyethylene glycol (PEG), thereby rendering vectors with targeting properties and long circulation. As yet, there are only a few ways available for targeted delivery of anticancer drugs. Recently, a report showed that VAR2CSA, which is exposed on the membrane of <hi rend="italic">Plasmodium falciparum</hi> infected red blood cells (iRBC), could bind to 90% of tumors, which was verified by running immunohistochemistry on a tumor-tissue array. Therefore, VAR2CSA is becoming an attractive target for anticancer drugs’ development. <hi rend="italic">P. falciparum</hi> infection during pregnancy results in the sequestration of iRBC in the placenta by adhering to a distinct type of chondroitin sulfate A (CSA) exclusively expressed on trophoblast via VAR2CSA. Short continuous regions of VAR2CSA with affinity for multiple types of CSA were defined. A 28 amino acids placenta CSA-binding peptide (plCSA-BP) from the VAR2CSA region was recently tested as a guide peptide for targeted delivery of doxorubicin to choriocarcinoma. However, whether it could be used to modify the DGL and its bioactivity after the modification was not evaluated. </p>

<p>The immunosuppressive, antimalarial, and pro-cytotoxic bacterial prodigiosin was recently described as a potent antimetastatic and anticancer agent. It can induce apoptosis in a wide range of cancer cell lines, including hematopoietic cancer, breast cancer, gastric cancer, colon cancer, lung cancer, and rat hepatocellular carcinoma cell lines, with no marked toxicity in nonmalignant cells. However, prodigiosin has not been reported for the treatment of choriocarcinoma yet. It is selective in promoting apoptosis of malignant tumor cells, rendering prodigiosin a promising anticancer agent. The antitumor mechanism of prodigiosin is still unclear, especially in regard to newly acquired prodigiosin produced by a small number of microorganisms, including <hi rend="italic">Serratia marcescens</hi> and other bacteria, such as <hi rend="italic">Streptomyces griseoviridis</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Serratia</hi> spp., <hi rend="italic">Zooshikellarubidus, Vibrio</hi> sp., <hi rend="italic">Actinomycetes</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Hahella chejuensis</hi>. Research on the mechanism of bacterial origin prodigiosin is very important for clinical application and drug development. </p>

<p>In this study, to develop a new type of targeted drug delivery carrier material and investigate the anticancer mechanism of prodigiosin, we first used plCSA-BP as a guide peptide to coat on the DGL vector for cancer-cell-targeted delivery of prodigiosin produced from <hi rend="italic">Serratia marcescens</hi> subsp. <hi rend="italic">lawsoniana</hi> HDZK-BYSB107. Then, we tested the binding ability of the newly developed DGL/CSA-PNPs and its anticancer effect in vitro on a JEG3 choriocarcinoma cell line and <hi rend="italic">in vivo</hi> on a tumor model, respectively. In addition, the mechanism responsible for the anticancer effect of targeted nano-prodigiosin was also investigated. Overall, these findings suggested that the DGL/CSA vector is an excellent cancer-specific-drug delivery carrier, which has great potential as a novel delivery system for the treatment of cancer. </p>
</text>
