<text id="autogum_news_doc430" title="Death toll from Borneo bridge collapse reaches eleven" shortTile="death-toll-borneo" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-11-28" dateModified="2011-12-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Death_toll_from_Borneo_bridge_collapse_reaches_eleven" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Death toll from Borneo bridge collapse reaches eleven</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, November 28, 2011</hi></p>
<p>The death toll from the weekend <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/suspension%20bridge">suspension bridge</ref> collapse on the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Indonesia">Indonesian</ref> island of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Borneo">Borneo</ref> has risen from four to eleven. Search and rescue teams continue to look for bodies in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahakam%20River">Mahakam River</ref>.</p>
<p>The number of wounded is currently 39 injured; reports from locals suggest 33 people remain missing at the scene in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/East%20Kalimantan">East Kalimantan</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kutai%20Kartanegara">Kutai Kartanegara</ref> district, where "Kalimantan's Golden Gate Bridge" linked the towns of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tenggarong">Tenggarong</ref> and the regional capital, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samarinda">Samarinda</ref>. A six-month-old baby is among the dead.</p>
<figure><caption>Kutai Kartanegara Bridge. Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Ezagren">Ezagren</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>Cars, motorbikes, and buses all fell into the Mahakam River when the bridge came down during repairs. Another car was left overturned and balanced upon wreckage over the water. State-owned builders PT Hutama Karya completed the bridge about a decade ago in the image of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/California">California</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golden%20Gate%20Bridge">Golden Gate Bridge</ref>. A cable on the 720-metre structure is thought to have failed as workers dealt with it; six of the repair crew were reported missing yesterday. It had been the longest suspension bridge in Borneo.</p>
<p>Eyewitnesses described heavy traffic at the time of the collapse, and one survivor said he left his truck to investigate a traffic jam. Some people were left trapped by debris as the bridge came down. "It happened so fast, only about 30 seconds," according to National Disaster Management Agency spokesman Sutopo Nugoroho.</p>
<p>National search and rescue head Daryatmo said yesterday cranes will attempt to move debris today, with new reports saying echo-sounding equipment will be used to check it is safe to begin lifting. It is believed the bodies of more victims will be found trapped in vehicles beneath the water, which is 35-40 metres deep. Visibility is poor, and one official explained authorities are still unsure how many vehicles are on the riverbed.</p>
<figure><caption>The famous Golden Gate Bridge in the USA, which the bridge in Borneo aimed to replicate. Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:RichN">Rich Niewiroski Jr.</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>"The above-water search is continuing, but underwater operations have not been carried out because we're worried that the bridge's pylons are unstable and could collapse any time," said Nugoroho today. He explained that bodies had washed onto the riverbanks overnight and were recovered today.</p>
<p>The president, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Susilo%20Bambang%20Yudhoyono">Susilo Bambang Yudhoyono</ref>, has sent three ministers to the site to investigate the accident, while Bambang Widaryatmo, head of East Kalimantan's police, promised "parties found to be negligent will be prosecuted". The government has promised a replacement ferry service. The river is closed to boats as rescue operations continue, and a 22-strong team has been dispatched from the national police, comprising six forensics experts, five disaster victim identification specialists, and eleven investigators. They are there to augment the East Kalimantan Police. Health Minister Endang Rahayu Sedyaningsih yesterday visited survivors in Parikesit Hospital and promised them medical treatment at government expense.</p>
<p>Some people swam ashore after falling, with the aftermath filled with screams.  Survivor Syakrani, 24, yesterday asserted "The authorities should have closed the bridge if it was under repair." His words were followed by a <hi rend="italic">Jakarta Globe</hi> editorial declaring the accident "unacceptable".</p>
<p>The <hi rend="italic">Globe</hi> went on to comment upon suggestions corruption may have played a role; "It is too early to point fingers and look to place blame, but if shoddy materials were used in the building of the bridge, those responsible must answer to the public." Another suggestion is coal barges striking the bridge may have weakened it. Local coal company Harum Energy lost five percent of its share value today amid fears the river blockage will hamper their ability to ship coal.</p>
<p>Samarinda's seen a population and construction boom lately. A few years have seen the population triple and the construction of a large mosque, and a sports stadium; an airport and port are set to follow. However, the Corruption Eradication Commission warns 70% of the corruption it investigates concerns government contracts and up to 40% of money earmarked for infrastructure ends up stolen.</p>
</text>
