<text id="autogum_academic_doc545" title="Research of Modal Analysis for Impeller of Reactor Coolant Pump" shortTile="research-modal-analysis" author="Jiaming Wang, Pengfei Wang, Xu Zhang, Xiaodong Ruan, Zhongbin Xu, Xin Fu" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/9/21/4551/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head><head> 4.1. Influence of Different Factors</head>
<p>
In this study, natural frequencies of a scale RCP impeller under different conditions are tested and simulated. From the comparison between Condition A and B in Table 1, it can be found that all natural frequencies are reduced by added mass by more than 10%. From the comparison between Condition A and D, it can be concluded that the effect of centrifugal force can be ignored. Condition C is related to added mass, centrifugal force and hydraulic load. Because natural frequencies under Condition C are smaller than those under Condition B, and the effect of centrifugal force can be neglected, it can be concluded that hydraulic load increases natural frequencies of the impeller. According to our data, the hydraulic load increases natural frequencies by more than 3%. </p>

<p>In summary, when an impeller rotates in water, added mass reduces natural frequencies of the impeller, the hydraulic load increases them, while the centrifugal force slightly reduces them. Therefore, among the three influencing factors, added mass and hydraulic load should be considered in modal analysis of the impeller, while the centrifugal effect can be ignored. Since added mass is related to the density of the liquid and the speed of sound, and hydraulic load is related to pressure distribution around the impeller. Changes of medium, temperature or pressure distribution will lead to variations of natural frequencies of the impeller. </p>

<head> 4.2. Theoretical Expression of Natural Frequencies of the Impeller</head>
<p>
Equation (2) is the motion differential equation of a static impeller in the air. While the underwater rotating impeller is subject to the damping of water, centrifugal force and hydraulic load. Therefore, modified from Equation (2), Equation (3) stands for the motion differential equation of the rotating impeller in water. In general, the velocity damping term can be neglected, and the system is approximately undamped. Then after solving Equation (3), the <hi rend="italic">i</hi>-th order main vibration expression of the impeller is Equation (4); therefore, natural frequencies of the wet modal rotating impeller are represented by Equation (5). Similarly, natural frequencies of the dry modal static impeller are expressed as Equation (6).

(2)

(3)

where <b><hi rend="italic">M</hi></b>, <b><hi rend="italic">Ma</hi></b>, <b><hi rend="italic">C</hi></b>, <b><hi rend="italic">G</hi></b>, <b><hi rend="italic">K</hi></b>, <b><hi rend="italic">D</hi></b> and <b><hi rend="italic">B</hi></b> respectively represent the structural mass matrix, the added mass matrix, the damping matrix, the gyro matrix, the stiffness matrix, the matrix and the rotational damping matrix. , , and <b><hi rend="italic">R</hi></b> respectively represent the acceleration vector, the velocity vector and the displacement vector.

(4)

where <hi rend="italic">αi</hi> and <hi rend="italic">φi</hi> are related to the initial state of motion. The array <b><hi rend="italic">Φ</hi></b>(<hi rend="italic">i</hi>), which is called the <hi rend="italic">i</hi>-th model, represents the relative ratio of vibration amplitudes per coordinate when the structure is in the <hi rend="italic">i</hi>-th order main vibration.

(5)

where the subscript pi represents the <hi rend="italic">i</hi>-th order. <hi rend="italic">Mpi</hi> = <b><hi rend="italic">Φ</hi></b>(i)<b><hi rend="italic">T</hi></b><b><hi rend="italic">MΦ</hi></b>(j), others are similar to <hi rend="italic">Mpi</hi>,

(6)

</p>

<p>From Equation (3), it is found that natural frequencies of the impeller are related to added mass, centrifugal force and hydraulic load. The effect of water damping is added to the mass matrix item, and the effect of centrifugal force and hydraulic load is added to the stiffness matrix item. Comparing Equation (4) with Equation (5), it is found that added mass increases natural frequencies, while the centrifugal effect and hydraulic load decrease natural frequencies. The analysis of our research in Section 4.1 follows the theoretical analysis result. However, since the effect of centrifugal force is small, it can be ignored in the natural frequencies study of the impeller. </p>

<head> 4.3. Improved Design of the RCP Impeller</head>
<p>
Due to the inconstancy of the hydraulic load around RCP impeller, natural frequencies of the impeller vary within a certain range. Therefore, in order to prevent resonance during normal operation, it is necessary to keep a large gap between the natural frequency of the impeller and the frequency of fluctuating pressure. Although redetermining the blade numbers of the impeller and vane diffuser can change both the node-diameter number of resonant mode and the excitation frequency, it may have a huge influence on the hydraulic performance of the RCP. Likewise, if the impeller hub structure is modified, other hydraulic components that cooperate with the impeller should be redesigned. </p>

<p>Natural frequencies of the impeller can be adjusted by modifying blade shape. There are several methods that can be employed, but a few of them are not recommendable for some reasons. For instance, the change of blade outlet edges affects the head, and the change of blade three-dimensional twist shape affects the efficiency. In the above chapter, there is a conclusion that hydraulic load affects natural frequencies. As can be seen from <figure>Figure 5</figure> (red circle), the pressure difference between the pressure surface and suction surface at the inlet of the blade is larger than those in other areas. Therefore, cutting the blade inlet edges might be a viable way to alter natural frequencies. Besides, this method will not significantly affect hydraulic performance. </p>
</text>
