<text id="autogum_voyage_doc454" title="Hakuba" shortTile="hakuba" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=13896" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Hakuba</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://vill.hakuba.nagano.jp/">Hakuba</ref></hi> (白馬村 <hi rend="italic">Hakuba-mura</hi>), is a skiing resort in <ref target="Nagano%20%28Prefecture%29">Nagano Prefecture</ref>, in the <ref target="Chubu">Chubu</ref> district of <ref target="Japan">Japan</ref>. The name Hakuba which means white horse was derived by the shape of a horse of snow on the mountain side during spring time. History shows traders following the famous Salt Road from the Japan Sea to Matsumoto who would stop in the Hakuba valley overnight to rest.</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>Hakuba is a stop on the <hi rend="bold">JR Oito Line</hi>.</p>

<p>From <ref target="Tokyo/Shinjuku">Shinjuku</ref> in <ref target="Tokyo">Tokyo</ref>, there is one daily <hi rend="italic">Super Azusa</hi> limited express service that runs to Hakuba. The ride takes 3 hours, 45 minutes and costs ¥8070 each way. As of November 2009, the outbound service leaves at 07:30, and the inbound service (to Shinjuku) departs from Hakuba at 14:57. There is also an additional <hi rend="italic">Azusa</hi> service on certain dates, making the run to Hakuba in about 4 hours.</p>

<p>Otherwise, you will have to take an <hi rend="italic">Azusa</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Super Azusa</hi> to <ref target="Matsumoto">Matsumoto</ref> and take one (possibly two) Oito Line local trains, increasing the journey to 4 1/2 hours.</p>

<p>The fastest route from Tokyo is by Shinkansen (bullet train) from <ref target="Tokyo%20Station">Tokyo Station</ref> to <ref target="Nagano">Nagano</ref>: 105min./8,170yen. Then by bus from <ref target="Nagano">Nagano</ref> to Hakuba 65min./1,500yen. Trains run every half hour or so, buses every hour. Note that the last bus from Nagano Station to Hakuba is 8:30PM. This whole trip takes just over 2.5 hours, 9,700yen one way.</p>

<p>These trips are useful for Japan Rail Pass holders, or else it is probably cheaper to take the bus.</p>

<head>By bus</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hakuba-Shinjuku Express</hi> (高速バス白馬・安曇野－新宿線). Every two or three hours.. Buses run from <ref target="Tokyo/Shinjuku">Shinjuku</ref> and stop at several places in the Hakuba region. The trip takes around 4 and a half hours</item>
</list>

 ¥8500 round-trip for adults, half off for children.

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Nagano-Hakuba Express</hi> (特急バス長野－白馬線). Every hour during ski season.. Buses from <ref target="Nagano">Nagano</ref> to Hakuba. The journey takes just over an hour.</item>
</list>

 ¥1400 for adults, ¥700 for children.

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Nagano Snow Shuttle</hi>, ☏ +81 261-75-5360 . Operates in the winter season.. Daily service from Narita Airport to Hakuba.</item>
</list>


<head>Get around</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Outside of the winter months, there are plenty of bike trails and walking paths to get around the area. Many hostels have bike rental which helps if you are a little bit outside of Hakuba proper.</item>
<item> If you are based around Kamishiro station, you are on the main rail line and road so a trip into Hakuba proper is only five minutes by JR or by Bus.</item>
<item> The Shuttle Bus "Genki-Go" runs from December through March in the evenings from 17:00. Three lines run throughout Hakuba for 300yen a ride.</item>
</list>


<head>During the Green Season</head>

<p>Near Hakuba, during the green season (i.e. spring, summer &amp; autumn), there are three freshwater lakes that are so clean that you can swim in them. In order from south to north, they are called Aoki-ko, Nakazuna-ko, and Kizaki-ko. The use of engines and outboard motors is banned on Aoki-ko, making it the quietest and nicest of the three. Popular activities include boating, sport fishing, and windsurfing. Nakazuna-ko is very small and only really attracts fishermen. Kizaki-ko is the most developed, and since engines are allowed, sports like wakeboarding are popular.</p>

<p>During the summer, most of the ski resorts operate some of their lifts to allow access to higher elevations. At Hakuba 47 and Aokiko (in nearby Omachi), the lifts allow access for mountain biking. Hiking or simply enjoying the views are popular at Happo, Goryu and Tsugaike. Above Happo, an easy trail extends for 40 minutes to a small pond in which the local alpine peaks are reflected. A couple of hours further up the trail lies the peak of Mt. Karamatsu on the main ridge of the North Alps. The top ski run at Goryu becomes an alpine garden in summer and another trail leads further upward to a viewpoint (around 50 minutes) or the peak of Mt. Goryu itself (around four hours). Above Tsugaike, a further ropeway takes you to a wetland that is designated as a national park. A trail from here takes you up to Mt. Shirouma, after which Hakuba is named. Shirouma and Hakuba are different readings of the kanji for "white horse". The smaller ski field of Iwatake uses its pistes to grow thousands of lilies in summer and also has a dry ski slope if you're desperate for turns.</p>

<p>Like all mountain areas in Japan, temperatures in Hakuba stay much cooler than in the cities on Japan's Pacific coast. That alone makes it worthy of a visit.</p>

<p>Hakuba, located in Nagano Prefecture, equally central to Osaka, Nagoya and Tokyo and nestled at the base of the Northern Japan Alps is towered over by the Three Peaks which provide a stunning backdrop year round. While Hakuba is world famous for it's snow and boasts more than 10 resorts, the green season offers plenty to those craving an escape from the confines of Japan in general.</p>

<head>Do</head>
<p>Whether you're a snowboarder or skier, beginner or pro, with seven ski resorts in the area you shouldn't have problems finding a run to suit your style.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hakuba 47 Winter Sports Park</hi> (Hakuba 47 ウインタースポーツパーク), 24196-47 Kamishiro, ☏ +81 261-75-3533 . Open 8.30AM to 4.30PM daily, Dec-May approx. With an annual snowfall of over 10m, Hakuba 47 offers 23 name runs, from beginner to advanced, as well as snowshoe and snowmobile tours. Private lessons for skiers or snowboarders are available in English and they rent basic equipment too.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hakuba Happo-one</hi> (白馬八方尾根スキー場), 5713 Hokujo, ☏ +81 261-72-2715 . Hakuba Happo-one is an extremely popular ski resort in Nagano Prefecture. Kick off your winter snow sports adventures in the heart of Japan. Happo-one is located in a pure natural setting in the Northern Japanese Alps where hot springs flow abundantly in this extensive mountainous region. The ski runs are varied ranging from beginner level to Olympic challenging long course and downhill runs (Nagano Olympic 1998). 13 courses and 23 lifts with the longest run 8000m. There is much to be experienced in Happo area. Not only a winter sports resort Happo runs all year round and experiences peak visitor times during the summer in July and August. Outdoor sports lovers should come to Happo to soak up the wonderful views, the fresh clean air and enjoy the local food and wine which is highly recommended. With this and Happo's friendly and polite customer service the visitor will not be disappointed. Please come and experience Happo-one! Click on our English Home Page above for further information and links.</item>
</list>


<p>There are plenty of <hi rend="italic">onsen</hi> (hot spring baths) in the Hakuba area, perfect for soaking away the aches and pains of a day on the slopes. Don't forget to wash off before you enter the water.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Juro No Yu</hi> (十郎の湯) (A ten minute walk from Kamishiro Station.), ☏ +81 261-71-8160 . Dec-Mar 24h, Apr-Nov 10AM-10PM, closed 2nd Tu each month. Enjoy the piping hot mineral waters in the inside and outside baths while looking out over the snow capped mountains. When your skin starts shrivelling up, dry off and head to the lounge to kick back on the tatami and watch TV or dig into a steaming bowl of tempura soba. Sauna, lockers provided. Adults ¥500, children ¥400.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tenjin No Yu</hi> (天神の湯) (A 15 minute walk from Hakuba Station.), ☏ +81 261-72-3450 . W-M 9AM-10PM. Recommended by locals for its healing waters, Tenjin No-Yu offers great views of the mountains from both indoor and outdoor baths. Lockers available. ¥500.</item>
</list>
</text>
