<text id="autogum_interview_doc483" title="Wikinews interviews 17-year-old author of &amp;apos;LEGO Heavy Weapons&amp;apos;" shortTile="wikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-06-12" dateModified="2014-06-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_17-year-old_author_of_%27LEGO_Heavy_Weapons%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews 17-year-old author of 'LEGO Heavy Weapons'</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, June 17, 2012</hi></p>
<p>17-year-old Jack Streat has accomplished something some people spend a lifetime reaching for: he's a published author. Streat's book, "LEGO Heavy Weapons: Build Working Replicas of Four of the World's Most Impressive Guns", was released in May by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/indie%20literature">indie</ref> publisher <hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/No%20Starch%20Press">No Starch Press</ref></hi>. The book features detailed drawings and explanations on how to build highly sophisticated working models of 4 assault weapons, including the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Desert%20Eagle">Desert Eagle</ref> handgun, among others. <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> interviewed Jack, to learn more about his passion for building.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<figure><caption>Jack Streat, with a LEGO weapon model.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> First, how old are you now and how old were you when the book was published?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JS</hi>: Seventeen at the moment, as I was when the book was published. I'll be 18 in just over a month, though.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Who is the publisher of the book?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JS</hi>: No Starch Press, who're based in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/San_Francisco">San Francisco</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> How long have you been serious about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LEGOs">LEGOs</ref>?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JS</hi>: Well I can't remember a time when I haven't been building with [LEGOs]...as to being 'serious' about it (if I haven't always been), the major turning points would probably be when, at age thirteen I posted my first gun online. Incidentally [that one is] also the first gun in the book. I started working toward the book...around October 2010.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Are there any designers/creators who've inspired you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JS</hi>: Not particularly. This may be due to the fact that most of my work was in replicating existing guns — which, of course, isn't quite the same as being inspired by someone and then designing something else from scratch.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Educationally, where are you: finished with high school? In college?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JS</hi>: Just entering my last week of A2 exams (the last exams in school) at the moment, and then after that (well, in a few months' time) I'm off to university!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> What have your parents/family thought about your passions for LEGOs?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JS</hi>: They've always encouraged it. They'd buy me LEGO for birthdays and Christmas and so on, and I always enjoyed showing them the latest thing I'd built — of course I wouldn't be anywhere near where I am now without their support, so they must be okay with it!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> With the publishing world, did you face any challenges in getting your book published? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JS</hi>: I was very lucky actually — Tyler Ortman, my editor, contacted me out of the blue (also through <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/YouTube">YouTube</ref>'s messaging system) and asked on behalf of <hi rend="italic">No Starch</hi> if I'd like to write a book of instructions for them to publish. I'd just started teaching myself how to use some <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer-aided%20design">CAD</ref> software for modelling LEGO creations, so I was all set, really.</p>
<figure><caption>Jack Streat, with a copy of his book, "LEGO Heavy Weapons".</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Are you working on another book at present?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JS</hi>: Well I still have a few mechanism/gun ideas floating around in my head, but that's simply ideas for more of the models I've been building personally. I've got to get through university before I even consider the possibility, but after that, who knows?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Have there been other activities/classes that have helped your LEGO work improve?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JS</hi>: Not really. Just time, patience, and lots and lots of bricks!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Where can our readers see videos or other forms of your work?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JS</hi>: My YouTube channel has videos of most of the guns I've built, but with very little textual description. [YouTube] and my <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/My%20Own%20Creation">MOCpages</ref> homepage has lots of information on all the guns I've built; they didn't all end up on YouTube. [At MOCpages] there's descriptive text and a set of pictures for each one.</p>
</text>
