<text id="autogum_bio_doc201" title="Abba Jifar II" shortTile="abba-jifar-ii" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-07-15" dateModified="2018-12-23" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abba_Jifar_II" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Abba Jifar II</head>
<p><hi rend="italic">Moti</hi> <hi rend="bold">Abba Jifar II</hi> was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King">King</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gibe_region">Gibe</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Jimma">Kingdom of Jimma</ref> (r. 1878–1932).</p>
<head>Reign</head>
<p>Abba Jifar II a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oromo_people">Oromo people</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> the son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abba_Gomol">Abba Gomol</ref> and Queen <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gumiti_of_Jimma">Gumiti</ref>. He had several wives: Queen Limmiti, who was the daughter of the King of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Limmu-Ennarea">Limmu-Ennarea</ref>; Queen Minjo, the daughter of the King of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Kaffa">Kaffa</ref>; and Queen Sapertiti, also from Limmu-Ennarea.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>During his reign there were <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sufism">Sufi</ref> saints who supported his rule. One of them is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sadati_Bure_(Ethiopia)">Sadati Of Bure</ref>(who later migrated to Illubabor).</p>
<p>In the 1880s, Abba Jifar II conquered a portion of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Janjero">Kingdom of Janjero</ref>, which lay east of Jimma, along the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Omo_River_(Ethiopia)">Omo River</ref>, and incorporated it into his kingdom.</p>
<p>Due to the advice of his mother Queen Gumiti, to avoid the detriments of war, he agreed to submit to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Menelik_II">Menelik II</ref>, <hi rend="italic">negus</hi> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shewa">Shewa</ref> in 1884. In 1886, Abba Jifar II paid peace offerings consisting of "slaves (including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eunuch_(court_official)">eunuchs</ref>), ivory, bamboo internodes filled with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Civet">civet</ref>, jars of honey, locally made cloth, spears, shields ornamented with silver plates, and objects of wood (including stools)."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> Because of these "shrewd politics" (Herbert S. Lewis' words), which included providing military assistance to Menelik in conquering the neighboring kingdoms of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kullo">Kullo</ref> (1889), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walamo">Walamo</ref> (1894), and Kaffa (1897), he was able to preserve the autonomy of Jimma until his death.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> On the other hand, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_Bulatovich">Alexander Bulatovich</ref> states that, when Jimma was annexed to Ethiopia, Emperor Menelik imprisoned Aba Jifar "for inspiring excessive enthusiasm in his own standing army and trying to entice Abyssinian soldiers to his own service" in Ankober for a year. "When he was freed," Bulatovich continues, "Aba Jefar again received the throne of Jimma from Menelik."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Bulatovich-web-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>Queen Gumiti also advised him to expand the cultivation of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coffee">coffee</ref> in his kingdom, which provided increased revenue for him and his subjects.</p>
<p>In January 1898, as part of a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Red_Cross">Red Cross</ref> mission to southwestern Ethiopia, Bulatovich visited Jimma, and was the guest of Abba Jifar. While in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeren">Jeren</ref>, Bulatovich treated the Queen Mother for "a little bronchitis". He left the following description of the king:</p>
<p>Aba Jefar is still a young man -- handsome, well-built, and somewhat in his prime. He has a typical face: a straight thin nose; bright, handsome eyes which shift suspiciously from side to side; a thick black beard; and black, short-cropped, curly hair. His hands are graceful. He wears large gold rings on all his fingers. Dressed in a white shirt and trousers, he has draped over his shoulders the thinnest white shamma. His feet are also very small and handsome, clad in leather sandals.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Bulatovich-web-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>Towards his later years, Abba Jifar II succumbed to senility. His grandson <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abba_Jofir">Abba Jofir</ref> attempted to take control and re-assert Jimma's independence. However, Emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haile_Selassie">Haile Selassie</ref> responded quickly and sent military forces against Abba Jofir. The soldiers brought Abba Jofir back to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Addis_Ababa">Addis Ababa</ref>, where he was imprisoned.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>In 1930, Haile Selassie removed an enfeebled Abba Jifar II from power and installed his son-in-law, <hi rend="italic">Ras</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Desta_Damtew">Desta Damtew</ref>, in his place. Desta Damtew ruled as Governor (<hi rend="italic">Shum</hi>) of Jimma, while Abba Jifar II was allowed to remain as King (<hi rend="italic">Negus</hi>) as titular head. When Abba Jifar II died in 1932, the Kingdom of Jimma was officially ruled directly by the Emperor.</p>
</text>
