<text id="autogum_interview_doc868" title="part8_Wikinews interviews World Wide Web co-inventor Robert Cailliau" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-07-22" dateModified="2014-09-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_World_Wide_Web_co-inventor_Robert_Cailliau" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Robert Cailliau</hi>: The web was hijacked by those who put something in it.  They are the people who did not make long ideological or so-called "intellectual" reasonings but who put content there.  The approach differs greatly between our European parochial little cultures.  For example on the whole French companies are pretty bad on the web:  there is a lot of aesthetical ado but you can't find the information you are looking for.  The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Switzerland">Swiss</ref> sites, even those written in French, are much more direct and informative.</p>
<p>The Dutch do better than the Belgians.  There is a large difference between the private sector and government agencies.  The sites of the French government are a model of completeness, user friendliness and usefulness, almost completely the opposite of the sites of the private companies of the same country.</p>
<p>I did not make a study of this phenomenon but it seems there are two large influences:  approach to life (Protestant/pragmatic/experimental/Germanic versus catholic/intellectual/cartesian/Latin ?) and language.</p>
<p>It's obvious that there is more available in English, say, than in Basque.  But that should not surprise anyone.  OK, so we have a language problem in Europe.  That leads to one of my favourite subjects:  language as a technology, but that's for another interview.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi>: How much has the web evolved since the 1970s? What factors are hindering further evolution?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Robert Cailliau</hi>: You probably mean the 90s unless you want to talk internet instead of web.  Looking back and from the many conversations with web and internet pioneers, I think not much has changed fundamentally.</p>
<p>There was a first explosion of internet services in the 70s (e-mail, chat, file transfer, remote login, ...) then a pause with nothing much until the web involved the public at large from 1995.  Two grand phases then: academic development followed by explosion in the public sphere.</p>
<p>We must remember two incompatible communication models:  telephony (no guaranteed contact but guaranteed bandwidth) and internet (guaranteed contact but no guaranteed bandwidth).  Circuit switching and packet switching.  Fashion dictates that we should now do everything via TCP/IP.  That's fine als long as there is no need for continuous contact (e-mail, web, download) but it is never good enough when that need is present (audio, video, TV).  Not to mention tele-surgery.  Would you like to be on the operating table knowing that the surgeon on the other side has just TCP/IP between his hand and the scalpel?  Probably not.</p>
<p>There are applications that need a guaranteed bandwidth and that's not achievable with classic TCP/IP.  Of course, the mathematician and the network geek will tell you that there is no difference if you make the bandwidth high enough.  True, but I fear that you can also always find an application that's bandwidth hungry enough that those limits need to be put higher again.
Maybe we find a combination whereby the web is used to initiated a circuit so that the best of both approaches can be had.</p>
</text>
