<text id="autogum_bio_doc209" title="Georgi Obretenov" shortTile="georgi-obretenov" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-05-06" dateModified="2017-09-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Georgi_Obretenov" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Georgi Obretenov</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Georgi Tihov Obretenov</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulgarian_language">Bulgarian</ref>: Георги Тихов Обретенов) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulgaria">Bulgarian</ref> revolutionary, best known for his participation in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/April_Uprising">April Uprising</ref> of 1876.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Georgi Obretenov, the youngest son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tonka_Obretenova">Tonka Obretenova</ref>, was born after 1849.  He studied in the class school in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rousse">Rousse</ref>, and afterwards helped his father with his business in the village of Isakcha in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Northern_Dobruja">Northern Dobruja</ref>.  In the spring of 1870 Georgi was admitted to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Junker_(Russia)">junker</ref> school in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Odessa">Odessa</ref>.</p>
<p>In order to take part in setting the ground for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stara_Zagora_uprising">Stara Zagora uprising</ref> of 1875, he returned to Rousse, and joined the preparations of a detachment's in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Veliko_Tarnovo">Veliko Tarnovo</ref>.  After the uprising's failure, he moved to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Romania">Romania</ref>.</p>
<p>The revolutionary committee in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giurgiu">Giurgiu</ref> estimated Georgi Obretenov's training and sent him to the region of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sliven">Sliven</ref> as a military instructor and as an assistant apostle to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ilarion_Dragostinov">Ilarion Dragostinov</ref>.  Along with the weapons, Obretenov brought to Sliven some revolutionary proclamations, by-laws, a flag, and the inspiring poetry of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hristo_Botev">Hristo Botev</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stefan_Stambolov">Stefan Stambolov</ref>.</p>
<p>Dragostinov and Obretenov chose different routes to Sliven.  Dragostinov travelled through <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Svishtov">Svishtov</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arbanasi,_Bulgaria">Arbanasi</ref>, in order to bid farewell to his parents and relatives.  Obretenov's route was through Rousse.  After passing the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Balkan_mountains">Balkan mountains</ref>, he stayed in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tvarditsa,_Sliven_Province">Tvarditsa</ref> at priest Stefan's, and hid the dangerous luggage in the altar of the local church.  Then, he set off to the village of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Korten,_Bulgaria">Korten</ref> to visit Georgi Kolev, the leader of the local revolutionary committee, with whose help he hid the items he carried in a wheat cart, and they both arrived in Sliven.</p>
<p>The coming of the two gave new impulse to the preparations in Sliven, though they didn't manage to reach consensus with local activists in terms of tactics.  The locals' plan was to adopt a course of preparation of detachments, who were to operate in the Balkan mountains, without exciting a revolt in town.  This viewpoint dominated, and put an imprint the overall preparatory work, and later on the range and power of the uprising throughout the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sliven_Province">Sliven region</ref>.</p>
<p>The military instructor, Georgi Obretenov, brought to Sliven modern guns, having issued directions about arms before departing from Giurgiu.  He wrote that every rebel had to possess a revolver with 200 bullets, a gun with 250 bullets, and a knife.  Furthermore, each of them was to provide two cartridge-boxes for the bullets.  Undoubtedly, Obrevenov strived for imposing those requirements on everyone in the Second Revolutionary Region.  Concerning military action, he gave oral instructions without leaving anything on paper.  There is information that the leaders of the Sliven revolutionary committee took care to supply modern guns from Romania.  They grew funds from the rebels' voluntary donations.</p>
<p>Obretenov brought to Sliven a flag sewn by his sisters Petrana and Anastasia.  Therefore, Sliven revolutionaries considered it unnecessary to prepare their own flag.</p>
<p>The leaders of the rebel group, gathered on "Kush Bunar"—Ilarion Dragostinov, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stoil_Voyvoda">Stoil Voyvoda</ref>, Georgi Obretenov, and Georgi Drazhev—decided to execute the adopted plan for touring the Balkan villages in the vicinity of Kotel and exciting a revolt, despite the small number of rebels.</p>
<p>Attempting to go back for food through <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neykovo">Neykovo</ref>, the detachment were confronted by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bashi-bazouk">bashi-bazouks</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Military_of_the_Ottoman_Empire">regular army</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cherkez">cherkez</ref> cavalry.  On their way back, they fought, and Obretenov was fatally wounded in the battle.  On 10 May 1876, realizing that, he committed suicide.</p>
</text>
