<text id="autogum_interview_doc224" title="part0_Jack Herrick, wikiHow founder interviewed by Wikinews" shortTile="partjack-herrick" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-01-31" dateModified="2010-07-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jack_Herrick%2C_wikiHow_founder_interviewed_by_Wikinews" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Jack Herrick, wikiHow founder interviewed by Wikinews</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 31, 2009</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Herrick at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RecentChangesCamp">RecentChangesCamp</ref> 2008 Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:ShakataGaNai">ShakataGaNai</ref>.</caption></figure><p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/wikiHow">wikiHow</ref> is a wiki-based site which aims to "build the world's largest, highest quality how-to manual." It recently published its 50,000th article, and to discuss what the site has achieved since its creation, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> interviewed the site's founder, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack%20Herrick">Jack Herrick</ref>.</p>
<p>In the interview, Herrick explains what wikiHow is, why he decided to create it, how he grew it in size, and why he chose to use a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Creative%20Commons">Creative Commons</ref> license for his site. Read below for more of the interview in full.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">For our readers who are unaware of your site, could you briefly explain what wikiHow is?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jack Herrick:</hi> Sure. wikiHow is a collaborative effort to build the world's largest, highest quality how-to manual. Our long term goal is to produce practical instructions on almost every topic in every language. We're quite far from our goals currently, but we take comfort in the fact that every month wikiHow gets noticeably better and larger. We currently have just under 50,000 articles [Note: The interview took place just before the 50,000 milestone was met] and over 1,000 featured articles. We hope that in time, we will have millions of articles with many of them having featured status. That said, we are realistic enough to realize that this goal will take decades to achieve. However, in terms of readership, we are probably the most popular single subject wiki after Wikipedia. We get over 14 million unique visitors per month (source:Google Analytics), which makes us the 135th most popular site according to Quantcast.  </p>
<p>Like Wikipedia, wikiHow is a wiki that runs on Mediawiki software. Our community is full of volunteers from all over the world. That said, we are quite different from Wikipedia in several respects:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>We are much smaller. The English wikiHow has only 60 admins, compared to the 1000+ on English Wikipedia. As a result, wikiHow is still at the size that every editor eventually gets to know other editors.</item>
<item>We are run as a Hybrid Organization - a for-profit company focused on achieving a social good. This has several advantages and disadvantages when compared to the non-profit structure at the Wikimedia Foundation. We show opt-out advertising to anonymous visitors rather than ask for donations. Our advertising revenue funds community meetups and has even allowed us to donate over $60,000 to charities such as the Wikimedia Foundation and Creative Commons. (<ref target="http://www.wikihow.com/wikiHow:Contributions-to-Charity">http://www.wikihow.com/wikiHow:Contributions-to-Charity</ref>). In addition, we've used our revenue on things like buying carbon offsets to become carbon neutral. (<ref target="http://www.wikihow.com/wikiHow:Carbon-Neutral">http://www.wikihow.com/wikiHow:Carbon-Neutral</ref>)</item>
<item>Our community culture is focused on wikiLove and civility. As a result some folks believe wikiHow is a more humane and enjoyable place to work than other places online.</item></list>
</text>
