<text id="autogum_voyage_doc173" title="Plockton" shortTile="plockton" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=27868" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Plockton</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.plockton.com/">Plockton</ref></hi> is a village on the coast of <ref target="Ross%20and%20Cromarty">Wester Ross</ref> in the <ref target="Scottish%20Highlands">Scottish Highlands</ref>, sheltered from the west winds and popular with yacht and dingy sailors. Plockton along with Kyle of Lochalsh was the setting for the "Hamish MacBeth" TV series, aired 1995-97.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">By train:</hi> four trains run M-Sat between <ref target="Inverness">Inverness</ref> and <ref target="Kyle%20of%20Lochalsh">Kyle of Lochalsh</ref>, one on Sunday, stopping at Dingwall, Achnasheen, Stromeferry and Plockton. Buses to Skye connect with these trains at Kyle. </p>

<p><hi rend="bold">By road</hi> Plockton is about 7 miles north of Kyle of Lochalsh, take A890 then branch west down the coast lane. Macrae Kintail Bus 712 runs just once in the morning M-F from Corran via Glenelg, Dornie and Kyle of Lochalsh to Plockton. It immediately turns round for the return, so it's no help for day trips. The long-distance coaches to Kyle and Skye don't come via Plockton.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<p>The village is small and pleasant to walk around.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Plockton Harbour:</hi> The mild climate due to the North Atlantic Drift allows palm and cabbage trees to prosper. You'll probably see seals.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Attadale Gardens</hi> are 10 miles east on A890 along Loch Carron. 20 acres of woodland, fern and Himalayan species, dotted with sculptures. They're open April-Oct daily 10:00-17:00, adult £8.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> There is plenty of opportunity for hill-walking locally.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Calums Seal Trips</hi>, Harbour Street, ☏ +44 1599 544306 . Wildlife watching trips (weather permitting) sail daily Easter to Oct, usually at 10:30, 12:00, 14:00 and 16:00. The boat <hi rend="italic">Sula Mhor</hi> takes 61, with 35 places bookable. Depending on tides it may sail from the car park pontoon or the main pier. Adult £12.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lochcarron Highland Games</hi> are held in late July at Attadale Estate, along A890. The next event is on Sat 18 July 2020.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Plockton Hotel: see Sleep listing.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Shores Restaurant</hi>, 30 Harbour St, Plockton, ☏ +44 1599 544263 . Coffee shop open year round daily, light lunches Tu-Sat. Restaurant Apr-Oct Tu-Su 11:30-14:30 &amp; 17:00-21:00.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Harbour Fish Bar</hi>, Innes Street, Plockton, ☏ +44 1599 544479 . Daily 12:30-14:30 &amp; 17:30-20:00. Traditional fish &amp; chips, chicken, Stornoway black pudding, etc. Seating outside.</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Plockton Inn</hi> also has rooms.</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> There are several B&amp;Bs (doubles from £90) and self-catering cottages.</item>
<item> Station Bunkhouse has two six-bed and two four-bed dorms. From £18 ppn; sole use £260.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Plockton Hotel</hi>, 41 Harbour St, ☏ +44 1599 544274 . Cosy two-star with public bar and restaurant. B&amp;B double £130.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Duncraig Castle</hi> (A mile east of village). Hotel in 19th C mansion <hi rend="bold">closed</hi> for renovation until spring 2020. </item>
</list>


<head>Go next</head>

<p>From <ref target="Kyle%20of%20Lochalsh">Kyle of Lochalsh</ref> cross to <ref target="Skye">Skye</ref> on the toll-free bridge. </p>
</text>
