<text id="autogum_interview_doc487" title="part3_ACLU, EFF challenging US &amp;apos;secret&amp;apos; court orders seeking Twitter data" shortTile="partaclu-eff-challenging" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-04-06" dateModified="2019-09-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/ACLU%2C_EFF_challenging_US_%27secret%27_court_orders_seeking_Twitter_data" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>"<hi rend="italic">As for traffic analysis (finding out who you are talking to rather than finding out what you are telling to whom), NSA and GCHQ are known to have access to lots of traffic (part of this is obtained via the UK-USA agreement). Even if one uses strong encryption, it is feasible for them to log the IP addresses and email addresses of all the parties you are connecting to. If necessary, they can even make routers re-route your traffic to their servers. In addition, the European Data Retention directive forces all operators to store such traffic data.</hi>"</p>
<p>"<hi rend="italic">Whether other companies would have complied with such requests: this is very hard to tell. I believe however that it is very plausible that companies such as Google, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Skype">Skype</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Facebook">Facebook</ref> would comply with such requests if they came from a government.</hi>"</p>
<p>"<hi rend="italic">In summary: unless you go through great lengths to log through to several computers in multiple countries, you work in a clean virtual machine, you use private browser settings (don't accept cookies, no plugins for Firefox, etc.) and use tools such as Tor, it is rather easy for any service provider to identify you.</hi>"</p>
<p>"<hi rend="italic">Finally: I prefer not to be quoted on any sentences in which I make statements on the capabilities or actions of any particular government.</hi>"</p>
<head id="Views_of_a_security_expert">Views of a security expert</head>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> also consulted <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">French</ref> IT security researcher Stevens Le Blond on the issues surrounding the case, and the state-of-the-art in monitoring, and analysing, communications online. Le Blond, currently presenting a research paper on attacks on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tor">Tor</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/USENIX">USENIX</ref> audiences in North America, responded via email:</p>
<p><figure><caption>Wikinews</caption></figure> Were the US Government to obtain the sought data, it would seem reasonable the NSA would handle further investigation. How would you expect them to exploit the data and expand on what they receive from Twitter?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Le Blond:</hi> My understanding is that the DOJ is requesting the following information: 1) Connection records and session times 2) IP addresses 3) e-mail addresses 4) banking info</item></list>
<p>By requesting 1) and 2) for Birgitta and other people involved with WikiLeaks (WL) since 2009, one could derive 2 main [pieces of] information.</p>
<figure><caption>Logo of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tor">Tor</ref> project.</caption></figure>
<p>First, he could tell the mobility of these people. Recent research in networking shows that you can map an IP address into a geographic location with a median error of 600 meters. So by looking at changes of IP addresses in time for a Twitter user, one could tell (or at least speculate about) where that person has been.</p>
<p>Second, by correlating locations of different people involved with WL in time, one could possibly derive their interactions and maybe even their level of involvement with WL. Whether it is possible to derive this information from 1) and 2) depends on how this people use Twitter. For example, do they log on Twitter often enough, long enough, and from enough places?</p>
</text>
