<text id="autogum_interview_doc197" title="part6_Andrea Muizelaar on fashion, anorexia, and life after &amp;apos;Top Model&amp;apos;" shortTile="partandrea-muizelaar" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-25" dateModified="2012-02-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Andrea_Muizelaar_on_fashion%2C_anorexia%2C_and_life_after_%27Top_Model%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> When your health faltered, that's when you said, "No, I can't do this anymore"?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> Correct. This as well as the fact that the industry was cold and treating me quite badly.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Do you feel that there should have been more of a fine line drawn between the money you received, between "prize" and "work," for tax purposes?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> Yes! The money was at one point on the show classified as a prize and we never even thought about taxes. This would make the prize more inconsiderable if it was called "$65,000 total prize winnings" to all the viewers.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> You discuss many horrible housing situations during your reign as Top Model. Were you not allowed to make your own decisions as far as housing was concerned?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> In the beginning, no. My parents and I were told where I would stay, and what I could and mostly could not bring. The second housing was because I refused to live in the first dwelling and again this was an arranged accommodation. After seeing how nasty this second place was (mice in my bed), I decided to make a decision and see what I could afford in terms of rent close to what I was already paying ($650) in another place in Toronto [that was] NOT in someone's house. This is where I found [the final place], the only available place for this price...a place on Parliament Street. The nasty side of town.</p>
<head id="Her_brief_modeling_career">Her brief modeling career</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Your spread in <hi rend="italic">Fashion</hi> magazine only paid $500. Is that a competitive rate for models or do you feel that you were paid less because you were under your television contract?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> That is incorrect; I was paid zero dollars for the <hi rend="italic">Fashion</hi> shoot. I was paid $500 for a wedding magazine front page and spread. This dollar amount is standard in the business for this job - apparently whether you are Canada's Next Top Model or not.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Why do you feel CityTV did not back you, as you say they were going to, during the lawsuit with your previous agency?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> The truth? We never got them to sign on their promises to my parents and I. They knew this and we were naive and didn't. Everything these days is officialized only if it is in writing. So, they claim now that they never said such things and [told us] to deal with the situation as these things happen every day.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> The Canadian website Canoe said you had alleged that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeanne%20Beker">Jeanne Beker</ref>, a judge on the show, effectively "ruined your career." Can you elaborate on what was meant by that, and do you indeed feel she ruined your career?</p>
</text>
