<text id="autogum_news_doc493" title="Seven killed, forty-eight injured in attack on London Bridge" shortTile="seven-killed-fortyeight" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-06-04" dateModified="2019-01-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Seven_killed%2C_forty-eight_injured_in_attack_on_London_Bridge" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Seven killed, forty-eight injured in attack on London Bridge</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, June 5, 2017</hi></p>
<p>Saturday night in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UK">UK</ref>, three men wearing what were later found to be fake suicide vests drove a van into crowds on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London%20Bridge">London Bridge</ref>, then exited the van at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Borough%20Market">Borough Market</ref> and began to stab people with blades, killing seven and injuring at least 48.  All three were shot and killed by police, who went on to arrest at least twelve other people. Militants from the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Islamic_State_of_Iraq_and_the_Levant">Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant</ref> claimed responsibility.</p>
<p>Prime Minister <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Theresa_May">Theresa May</ref> says that the attacks on Westminster Bridge, Manchester Arena, and now London Bridge were not connected through any known network but did attribute the attack to the "evil ideology of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Islamism">Islamist</ref> extremism". According to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BBC">BBC</ref>, a witness to the attack heard one or more of the perpetrators say "this is for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Islam">Allah</ref>."</p>
<hi rend="bold">Muslims everywhere are outraged and disgusted at these cowards [...] That this should happen in this month of Ramadan [...] only goes to show that these people respect neither life nor faith</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—Harun Khan of the Muslim Council of Britain</p>
<p>"Enough is enough," said May. "There is, to be frank, far too much tolerance of extremism in our country. So we need to become far more robust at identifying it and stamping it out [...] That will require some difficult and often embarrassing conversations. We need to live our lives not in a series of separated, segregated communities but as one truly United Kingdom."</p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Muslim_Council_of_Britain">Muslim Council of Britain</ref> condemned the attacks: "These acts of violence were truly shocking and I condemn them in the strongest terms. Muslims everywhere are outraged and disgusted at these cowards who once again have destroyed the lives of our fellow Britons. That this should happen in this month of Ramadan, when many Muslims were praying and fasting only goes to show that these people respect neither life nor faith" said the organization's Secretary General, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harun%20Khan">Harun Khan</ref>.</p>
<p>Yesterday morning there was no train service to London Bridge station.  Because the site was still cordoned off, many people had to take miles-long detours, often on foot, to get to work or else had to wait outside for long periods.  Security office Mohammed Osman told the press: "I'm not feeling worried. I'm strong enough. These enemies are trying to divide us but we have to be together."</p>
<p>While most of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Kingdom">the country</ref>'s political parties have decided to suspend campaigning temporarily, the upcoming general elections scheduled for Thursday have not been cancelled.</p>
<p>According to the <hi rend="italic">BBC</hi>, this attack differs from the one in Manchester Arena because creating a bomb requires sophisticated technical skill and operating vans and knives does not.</p>
<p>Some of the people injured in the attacks have been released from hospitals; as of yesterday, others were still reported in critical condition.</p>
<head id="Sister_projects">Sister projects</head>
<list type="unordered"><item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/June%202017%20London%20attack">June 2017 London attack</ref></hi></item></list>
</text>
