<text id="autogum_whow_doc508" title="Be Organised (for Teens)" shortTile="organised--teens" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2013-06-21" dateModified="2019-07-17" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be-Organised-%28for-Teens%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be Organised (for Teens)</head><p>Seeing a mess in your space is always a big put-off, and it's always tempting to procrastinate and typically 'leave it for later'. Hate not knowing how to navigate your own room? Read more to find out how to get rid of these annoying things.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Cleaning Your Room</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Clean that cupboard. Basically, take out your clothes drawer by drawer, folding them into neat piles according to them (shirts, tank tops, shorts etc). When your closet is completely empty, allocate clothes to each drawer/section and put them in accordingly. <figure rend="Be Organised (for Teens) Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Organize your desk. For this, this is pretty similar to cleaning your cupboard, the most efficient way is to completely empty your desk, put all your stuff in piles on your bed. In your mind make a little plan for where you'll put everything, then carefully refill your desk neatly. <figure rend="Be Organised (for Teens) Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make your bed. It's not that hard, and it'll make you feel better about your room. It won't look right if you have a perfect room except for a bed that resembles a disaster zone. <figure rend="Be Organised (for Teens) Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have a nice floor. Don't have underwear or any other things beside furniture littering your floor. If your hands get messy from cleaning, wear gloves. <figure rend="Be Organised (for Teens) Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use boxes. If you have a bit of stuff that you don't use that much, but too precious to you that you can't throw it away, allocate a box for all this stuff and guess what you do now? Fill it. When done, label your box and put it subtly in a corner. <figure rend="Be Organised (for Teens) Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Organizing School Stuff</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Organize those school books. When you take your textbooks home, it's better if you have a nice little box or magazine holder thing so you can keep your books organized, neat and easy to reach. <figure rend="Be Organised (for Teens) Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Clean out that pencil case. Empty your pencil case onto your desk or a table. Sort out your things, throw out out broken pens or other items and if you have an unnecessarily large amount of something, use only a few for school. Use elastic bands or spare hair-ties to organize if you need it. <figure rend="Be Organised (for Teens) Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have a strong and suitable school bag. A good one should be about to fit in all of your books and laptop (if you need/have one), don't let it be so small you need to carry something else to occupy your hands. <figure rend="Be Organised (for Teens) Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Preparing Ahead of Time</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Get ready every night before going to bed. Prepare your school bag every night before you go to sleep, if you take a packed lunch, you could prepare it the night before and put it in the fridge overnight to put in the next morning. <figure rend="Be Organised (for Teens) Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Prepare your uniform. Each night lay out some fresh clothes/your uniform for the next day and other things you need. <figure rend="Be Organised (for Teens) Step 10.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>When you're finished with something, make sure you put it away immediately.</item></list>
<list type="unordered"><item>When you get changed into your nightclothes, don't leave them on the floor, put them in the laundry basket straight away.</item></list>
</text>
