<text id="autogum_interview_doc822" title="part7_Satanism: An interview with Church of Satan High Priest Peter Gilmore" shortTile="partsatanism-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-04" dateModified="2018-10-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Satanism%3A_An_interview_with_Church_of_Satan_High_Priest_Peter_Gilmore" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Where do they violate Satanic principles in that conflict?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  Each have their own goals.  I would say killing people who are just innocent folks, that’s against Satanic philosophy.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terrorism">Terrorism</ref>, specifically, is against Satanism because we feel that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/justice">justice</ref> is important, and that is giving people what they deserve.  Blowing up somebody who is just wandering around is not a just approach.  That’s something against the social contract, and we would oppose people engaging in terrorism.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What about <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Same-sex_marriage">Same-sex marriage</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  Absolutely support it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Abortion?</hi></p>
<hi rend="bold">I would look at it as if I was the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/fetus">fetus</ref>, I wouldn't want to be snuffed out.</hi>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  I think people should practice <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/birth%20control">birth control</ref> rather than use abortion as an easy way out.  Again, the concept of being responsible for yourself and not to willy-nilly get pregnant unless you are really interested in carrying forth the child.  Since we have overpopulation generally speaking, I think abortion is something fine to be used, but I think it should not be used as a means of cleaning up after people’s irresponsible sexual activity.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why do you not consider it just another operation?  Some people run or exercise not realizing their limitations and pull a muscle or need an operation for that.  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  I would look at it as if I was the fetus, I wouldn't want to be snuffed out.  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So is the fetus a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sentient">sentient being</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  Not necessarily, it’s just a piece of tissue and most human life doesn't really have that much value on a grand scale.  In the universe, individual life is practically meaningless, it’s sort of like droplets in a wave that crashes against a rock.  Who cares about the droplets?  The way life works is it is making large amounts of species of whatever it is, and it keeps moving biologically.  I would just think that if it was myself as the fetus, I have a potential to become the person that I am.  I wouldn't want to be snuffed out.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When do you think life begins?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  Life is there, whether it is conscious and valuable is debatable.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You mean just on a cellular level it is functioning?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  Yeah, it is life.  Sperms and eggs are alive, they're organic, you can't say that is not life.  But what I think you’re looking for is the idea that Christians wants to say from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/conception">conception</ref>.  If people want to have abortions it really doesn't bother me, I just think they really should be more responsible.  It just makes more sense.  Contraception is easy!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  A lot of people don't like contraception.</hi></p>
</text>
