<text id="autogum_academic_doc688" title="Kuznets Environmental Curve for Ecuador: An Analysis of the Impact of Economic Growth on the Environment" shortTile="kuznets-environmental" author="Carolina Jimenez, Luis Moncada, Diego Ochoa-Jimenez, Wilman-Santiago Ochoa-Moreno" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5896/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Theory about the Kuznets Environmental Curve</head>
<p>
The ECK is considered as the relationship between economic growth and environment and is one of the most heavily debated issues within environmental economics. This curve represents a reduced form that conceals other phenomena such as technology, product composition, environmental regulations, or demands of society. In this sense, this reduced form does not allow initial identification of the effects of economic policy.  </p>

<p>To note this hypothesis, the authors applied the cross-section panel methodology, taking as variables some comparable measures of the partners, among which was air pollution in several urban areas. In the analysis of, it was observed that sulfur dioxide and smog in the air increase with the presence of lower GDP per capita. However, this contamination decreases as income increases, indicating statistical evidence of the existence of a relationship between the ECK and the two environmental quality indicators used. The inflection point or the level at which pollution indicators begin to decrease was determined in a range of GDP per capita between 4000 and 5000 dollars. On the contrary, for the specific case of sulfur dioxide and smog, a point of change was not identified; however, the relationship between pollution with these indicators and GDP per capita was perceived as a monotonous increase.  </p>

<p>In the same way, documented the intensity of toxic production for a sample of 37 manufacturing sectors in 80 countries during the 1960–1988 period. This document aimed to determine the environmental effect that manufacturing industries received and to analyze whether their contribution to pollution varied with respect to different incomes. The results obtained indicated the existence of a relationship between the ECK and the intensity of toxic elements per unit of GDP. </p>

<p>Generally, three specific explanations for the existence of ECK have been proposed: (i) the first one corresponds to the analysis that the environment can go from being a normal good to a luxury good, (ii) the second one makes a brief reference to countries going through technological life cycles when they move from primary sector economies to tertiary sector economies, and (iii) the third one emphasizes the demand for international relocation of industries.  </p>

<p>On the other hand, there is the interesting contribution of, which is the relevant review of the ECK bibliography. The logic that manages to explain the relationship between increased income and environmental degradation could be based on the following, among other things: (i) by reaching a sufficiently high standard of living, a society within a country assigns a particular increasing value to the environment. Therefore, once the income reaches a given level, the availability to pay for a cleaner environment increases in greater proportion than the income; ii) environmental degradation tends to increase when the structure of the economy changes from rural to urban or from agricultural to industrial, but it begins to decline again with another structural change, when it goes from an energy-intensive industry to services and towards an economy intensive in technology and knowledge; iii) as a rich nation can allow more resources to be devoted to research and development, technological progress is presented with economic growth, and dirty and obsolete technologies are replaced by cleaner and more advanced ones; and finally, iv) the characteristics of the political system and some cultural values play an important role in the application of public policies compatible with the environment, which are more easily adopted once the economy reaches high income. </p>

<p>For the deliberation of variables that allow for the analysis of the economic growth impact on the environment, a matrix of different variables was elaborated, which contained contributions that carried out different works and facilitated the choice of such variables. These were: economic growth or product gross domestic income per capita, CO2 emissions, energy consumption, and population (used in logarithms). It should be noted that economic growth and CO2 emissions were considered the most important variables because these are the essential elements in the relationship of the Kuznets Environmental Curve. </p>

<p>The descriptive statistics of the main variables in the research are presented below in Table 1. </p>

<head> 2.1. Economic Growth</head>
<p>
Economic growth is measured as the percentage increase in gross domestic product or gross national product (GNP) in a year. It can occur in two different ways—an economy can grow "extensively" using more resources (such as physical, human, or natural capital) or "intensively" using the same amount of resources more efficiently (more productively). When economic growth occurs using more labor, it does not result in an increase in per capita income; when it is achieved through a more productive use of all resources, including labor, it does result in an increase in per capita income and an improvement in the living standard of the population. Intensive economic growth is a condition of economic development. </p>
</text>
