<text id="autogum_news_doc692" title="U.S. Senate approves revised bailout package after controversial additions" shortTile="us-senate-approves" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-10-02" dateModified="2017-10-23" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S._Senate_approves_revised_bailout_package_after_controversial_additions" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>U.S. Senate approves revised bailout package after controversial additions</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 4, 2008</hi></p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S._Senate">U.S. Senate</ref> passed a revised <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emergency%20Economic%20Stabilization%20Act%20of%202008">bailout bill</ref> designed to help the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liquidity%20crisis%20of%20September%202008">struggling U.S. financial economy</ref>, which has measures nearly identical to the bill rejected by the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S._House_of_Representatives">U.S. House of Representatives</ref> on Monday.</p>
<p>"Senate Democrats and Republicans believe it is essential that we work quickly on this important legislation to restore confidence to our financial system and strengthen the economy," said Senate Majority Leader <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Harry_Reid">Harry Reid</ref>.</p>
<p>The new revisions include raising the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FDIC">FDIC</ref> insurance cap to $250,000, a move designed to please progressives. However, the $110 billion in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/tax%20break">tax breaks</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earmark%20(politics)">earmarks</ref> and what has been called <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/pork%20barrel">pork barrel</ref> spending is not offset by any increases in revenues and has added opposition to the bill from some Representatives in the House.</p>
<p>Earmarks added into the bailout bill included $192 million in tax rebates for the Virgin Islands rum industry, $148 million in tax cuts for the wool industry, $100 million tax cuts to the auto racing industry, and $48 million in Hollywood tax incentives. </p>
<p>Vice President of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taxpayers%20for%20Common%20Sense">Taxpayers for Common Sense</ref>, Steve Ellis, offered his explanation for the pork and earmarks added in. "People who support some of these provisions will forget about the $700 billion and concerns they may have on that, and say, 'If you give me a few million in tax breaks for my constituents, I'll go along'".</p>
<p>The tactic seems to have worked, however, managing to flip enough votes to pass the bill.</p>
<p>"The inclusion of parity, tax extenders and the FDIC increases has caused me to reconsider my position," said Representative <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jim%20Ramstad">Jim Ramstad</ref> (R Minnesota), who voted against the previous bill on Monday. "All three additions have greatly improved the bill."</p>
<p>But Representative <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcy%20Kaptur">Marcy Kaptur</ref> (D Ohio) was not changing her no vote. "I will not support this legislation because it's the wrong medicine," she said.</p>
 HAVE YOUR SAY
 Do you think the bailout bill will help the US economy, hurt it, or be a waste of money?
<ref target="//en.wikinews.org/w/index.php?title=Comments:Main_Page&amp;action=edit&amp;preload=Wikinews:Commentary_pages_on_news_events/body&amp;editintro=Template:Editintro_comments&amp;summary=create">Add or view comments</ref>
<p>The Senate took <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/H.R.%201424">H.R.1424</ref>, a bill originating in the House concerning "equity in the provision of mental health and substance-related disorder benefits under group health plans, to prohibit discrimination on the basis of genetic information with respect to health insurance and employment," and extended it with the bailout provisions.  </p>
<p>H.R.1424 was introduced on March 9, 2007, by Rep. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patrick%20J.%20Kennedy">Patrick Kennedy</ref> (RI-1) and had the support of First Lady Rosalind Carter.  It is noted on the Congressional Website that "On 10/1/2008, the Senate passed H.R.1424 as the vehicle for the economic rescue legislation. In the EAS version of the bill (Engrossed Amendment as Agreed to by the Senate), Division A (pp.1-110) is referred to as the Emergency Economic Stabilization Act of 2008; Division B (pp. 110-255) is referred to as the Energy Improvement and Extension Act of 2008; and Division C (pp. 255-441) is referred to as the Tax Extenders and Alternative Minimum Tax Relief Act of 2008."  It was not treated as an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Appropriation%20bill">appropriations bill</ref> in the House.</p>
<p>There were two votes in the Senate. The first was to amend H.R.1424, which required 3/5 to be accepted, which it was.  The second was a vote on the bill. Passage of the Bill required only a 1/2 majority. It was passed with 74 yeas and 25 nays.  Senator Kennedy did not vote. </p>
</text>
