<text id="autogum_voyage_doc507" title="Vianden" shortTile="vianden" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=37928" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Vianden</head>

<p>One of <ref target="Luxembourg">Luxembourg</ref>'s main tourist attractions, <hi rend="bold">Vianden</hi> is a delightful historic town with a stunningly restored medieval castle, spectacularly situated on a rock high above town. Think charming cobblestoned streets with typically pastel-coloured Luxembourg mansions and a gorgeous <hi rend="italic">Our</hi> valley backdrop. Vianden is a traveller's favourite and although high season will bring in some crowds, it's a most pleasant little town with a restaurant at every corner and all the fairytale atmosphere you could ask for. Coming here, you'll follow in the footsteps of countless celebrities, famously going back to Victor Hugo, who repeatedly spent time here.</p>

<head>History</head>

<p>Vianden's history goes far back, with a Gallo-Roma castellum preceding the current castle. The earliest documented mentions of the town, then called <hi rend="italic">Viennensis</hi>, date from the end of the 7th century. Building of the castle began in the 11th century and Vianden soon became the seat of the counts of Vianden, but the city gained its charter only in 1308. The town flourished in the Middle Ages, when it was known for its craftsmen, and later on for its leather works. The last leather tannery closed in the 1950s.</p>

<p>The power of the counts of Vianden was at its peak in the 13th century, and so was the grandeur of their castle. A Renaissance-style structure was added to the castle in the 17th century, but over time the state of the fort diminished with the stature of its lords. As Luxembourg fell under Dutch rule, the town became of little consequence, with earthquakes and a fire further damaging its castle. Things worsened when William I of the Netherlands, uninterested in Vianden and its castle, eventually sold the premises to a local merchant, who in turn sold off its interior piecemeal, leaving the place in ruins. There were several largely unfruitful attempts at restoration, but it was only in the late 1970s that serious repairs took place and the castle was returned to its former glory. For anyone who's interested in the town's history, a visit to the castle is a must-do, as it provides a wealth of information on the matter.</p>

<head>Vianden today</head>

<p>The revival of the castle immediately turned Vianden into a major tourist destination in the region. With its winding roads and rolling hills, the area around town is particularly popular among motorcyclists, who are welcomed by local establishments for the business they bring. On sunny summer afternoons the town can get a bit crowded and noisy because of the many motorbikes and visitors, but early risers will find a peaceful village even in high season.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tourist Information Office</hi>, 1A, rue du Vieux Marché, ☏ +352 83 42571 . Tu-F 08:00-12:00 &amp; 13:00-17:00, Sa-Su &amp; holidays 10:00-14:00. The tourist office has information on all the sights in and around Vianden, and it can arrange guided tours and make reservations for hotels or the adventure park. It can also provide information on hiking routes starting in Vianden.</item>
</list>


<head>By car or motorcycle</head>
<p>Most people come here by <hi rend="bold">car</hi> or motorcycle. It's a 50 minute drive from Luxembourg city via the <hi rend="bold">N17</hi>, with a scenic final approach. Most parking in the village is paid and has a time limit of 3 hours. Your best parking options are near the castle, or immediately left before you enter the village. Some hotels offer basement private parking for motorcycles.</p>
<p>Parking spaces are limited, so during the high season in summer, parking could be challenging.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>To get here by public transport, e.g. from <ref target="Luxembourg%20%28city%29">Luxembourg (city)</ref>, take a <hi rend="bold">train</hi> to <ref target="Ettelbruck">Ettelbruck</ref>, and then catch the <hi rend="bold">570 bus</hi> at the bus station adjoining the train station. It runs twice per hour on weekdays, but less frequently on weekends, and also stops in <ref target="Diekirch">Diekirch</ref>. The bus trip takes about 35 minutes, or 20min from Diekirch. Vianden is the second to last stop on the route – ask the driver if unsure. From Luxembourg city, the entire trip takes about an hour and costs just €4 for a return ticket including the bus.</p>

<p>There are also two buses to and from <ref target="Clervaux">Clervaux</ref> in the morning, and another two in the afternoon (<hi rend="bold">line 663</hi>, takes about half an hour). In season, a bus from the German city of <ref target="Bitburg">Bitburg</ref> runs to Vianden as well.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>The nearest major <hi rend="bold">airport</hi> is <ref target="http://www.lux-airport.lu/">Luxembourg Findel Airport</ref>. Alternatively, try <ref target="http://www.hahn-airport.de/Default.aspx%3Fmenu%3Dpassengers_visitors%26amp%3Bcc%3Den">Frankfurt-Hahn Airport</ref>, which is about 120 km from Vianden.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>The town itself is small and just <hi rend="bold">walking</hi> down the Rue Grande (which does have some vehicular traffic) is a must do. The castle is situated on a rock some 300 m above the town centre. You can drive a good part up the hill and park there, go up by foot, or walk down from the télésiège stop.</p>

<p>The <hi rend="bold">télésiège</hi> leads from the river side to a restaurant stop even higher than the castle, providing some lovely views over town. From there, it's a 15min downhill walk through the forest to the castle; the path is fairly rough and steep, so a reasonable level of fitness and appropriate footwear are required. The télésiège provides return tickets, but if you want to see the castle in one go, you will need to walk the path back up. In that case, buying a single ticket up and strolling down the hill from the castle to town is at least as convenient.</p>
<p>Alternatively, in summer, there's a little <hi rend="bold">tourist train</hi> that runs through town and up to the castle, offering a convenient way to reach the castle for elderly or less mobile visitors, or another fun activity for kids. Its ticket office is near the bridge over the <hi rend="italic">Our</hi>.</p>

<head>See</head>

<p>The town's <hi rend="italic">Grand-Rue</hi> is as much its functional main street as it is an attraction, with its cobblestoned course and centuries-old buildings on both sides. Most buildings remain in use, as hotels, restaurants of residential houses. Particularly picturesque is the <hi rend="bold">Place de la Resistance</hi>, along the main street, where you'll find the town hall and a small fountain.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Vianden Castle</hi>, ☏ +352 83-41081 . Apr-Sep 10:00-18:00; Mar,Oct 10:00-17:00; Nov-Feb 10:00-16:00. There's no way to miss the grand castle of Vianden, overlooking and dominating the little town beneath it. It was impressively restored in 1977 and has been a real visitor's magnet ever since. A route leads visitors through 20 different historic castle rooms, after passing the modern entrance and soon to be opened visitors centre. Some of the rooms (including the kitchen) have been fully refurbished, in order to give a real peek into life as it would have been in the castle in the middle ages. Others have been restored but leave more to the imagination, including the upper chapel, the impressive Knight's hall and the beautiful Byzantine Gallery. There's an arms room and a genealogy room, where the family history of the castle masters is explained. In short, take your time to wander through these ancient halls. It's a fine trip for adults and children alike. €6, student €4.50, senior €5, child (6-12y) €2, children (&lt;6y) free. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Maison Victor Hugo</hi>, 37, rue de la Gare, ☏ +352 26-874088 . Tu-Su 11:00-17:00. During his 19 years of exile from France, Victor Hugo stayed in Vianden a few times, most notably for 3 months in 1871. He left behind a painting of the castle ruins as they were at the time and reportedly got the castle architect fired as he thought his work to be insufficient. The Maison Victor Hugo is a small museum displaying some original works (manuscripts and drawings) as well as the original rooms with furniture as the famous visitor has used it. From the museum windows, there's a lovely view of the castle. Audio guides are available in English, French, Dutch and German. €4 for adults, €3.50 for young people (13-25) and €2.50 for children (6-12).</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Trinitarian church and cloister</hi>, Grand-Rue, ☏ +352 26-950566 . This old church of the Trinitarians is an excellent example of <ref target="Gothic%20architecture">Gothic architecture</ref> in the country. It was built as early as 1248, with the large choir originating in 1644. The main Rococo-style altar was created by Michel Weiler in 1758. Adjoining is a small former cloister, from the same 13th century origin. Don't miss a peek in its wonderfully tranquil <hi rend="bold">courtyard</hi>. The entrance is a simple door on the side of the building, in the alley between hotel Heintz and the church. Note the late 13th century effigy of Marie de Spanheim.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">City ramparts</hi>. In the Middle Ages, Vianden was a fully fortified town, surrounded by city walls with 24 half-round towers and five gates. Most of those ramparts are now gone, taken down by Marechal de Bouffiers in 1679. A few restored ruins and a bell tower remain, however. Take a quick detour via the small stairway between Grand Rue numbers 58 and 60. It will lead you to the 1603 belfry and some nice views over the village.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Stadtmuseum</hi> (Musée d’Histoire de la Ville de Vianden), 96-98 Grand-Rue, ☏ +352 83-4591 . Open Easter to Oct., daily 11-17, although in low season it's closed on Mondays. A charmingly small museum, housed in two adjoining buildings on the main street. One of the buildings still has its 19th century interiors, while the other serves as a bakery museum, with part of the décor of the 1950s bakery that was housed here on display. The house that now has the bakery museum, was once the home of famous poet <hi rend="bold">Edmond de la Fontaine</hi>, famous under his pen-name <hi rend="bold">Dicks</hi>. A tablet on the façade reminds of the buildings famous former inhabitant. All the text in the museum is in German, but there's an English translation text available on request. The entrance ticket also gives free access to the copper mine museum in <ref target="Stolzembourg">Stolzembourg</ref>, about 6 km out of Vianden.</item>
</list>

 €3, child €1.50.

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Vianden Pumped Storage Plant</hi>, ☏ +352 84-90311 . 10:00-16:00, Easter-Sep 10:00-20:00. If you have a taste for major industrial sights or large water basins, and would like to get away from the crowds, hike a few kilometres up along the river Our, until you reach the Pumped Storage Plant. It has two large reservoirs and was recently expanded. The total reservoir capacity is about 10,800,000m³, making it the largest hydro-electric power plant in Europe. It has a visitors' centre, which allows a peek into its underground power plant. It's a pleasant walk, along the water, but uphill. Free. </item>
</list>
</text>
