<text id="autogum_interview_doc496" title="part1_Asbestos controversy aboard Scientology ship Freewinds" shortTile="partasbestos-controversy" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-05-16" dateModified="2017-06-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Asbestos_controversy_aboard_Scientology_ship_Freewinds" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<hi rend="bold">The Freewinds regularly inspects the air quality on board and always meets or exceeds US standards.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church%20of%20Scientology">Church of Scientology</ref> spokeswoman Karin Pouw</p>
<p>Church of Scientology spokeswoman Karin Pouw responded to <hi rend="italic">Radar Online</hi> about the asbestos reports, in an email published in an article in <hi rend="italic">Radar</hi> on May 1. "The Freewinds regularly inspects the air quality on board and always meets or exceeds US standards," said Pouw. She stated that two inspections performed in April "confirmed that the air quality is safe," and asserted that the inspections revealed the <hi rend="italic">Freewinds</hi> satisfies standards set by the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Occupational%20Safety%20and%20Health%20Administration">Occupational Safety and Health Administration</ref> and the U.S. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clean%20Air%20Act">Clean Air Act</ref>. </p>
<p>Pouw told <hi rend="italic">Radar</hi> that "The Freewinds will be completing its refit on schedule." The Church of Scientology-affiliated organization <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Citizens%20Commission%20on%20Human%20Rights">Citizens Commission on Human Rights</ref> (CCHR) had been planning a cruise aboard the <hi rend="italic">Freewinds</hi> scheduled for May 8, but according to <hi rend="italic">Radar</hi> an individual who called the booking number for the cruise received a message that the cruise had been delayed due to ongoing work on the ship. Citing an article in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Netherlands%20Antilles">Netherlands Antilles</ref> newspaper <hi rend="italic">Amigoe</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Radar</hi> reported on May 6 that a team from the United States and supervised by an independent bureau from the Netherlands traveled to Curaçao in order to remove asbestos from the <hi rend="italic">Freewinds</hi>. </p>
<hi rend="bold">...if the Church of Scientology claims to have removed the blue asbestos, I just don't see how, it's everywhere. You would first have to remove all the pipes, plumbing, a/c ducts, electrical wiring etc. etc. just a maze of stuff.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Lawrence Woodcraft</p>
<p>"I stand by everything I wrote in my 2001 affidavit," said Lawrence Woodcraft in an exclusive statement given to <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi>. Woodcraft went on to state: "I would also comment that if the Church of Scientology claims to have removed the blue asbestos, I just don't see how, it's everywhere. You would first have to remove all the pipes, plumbing, a/c ducts, electrical wiring etc. etc. just a maze of stuff. Also panelling as well, basically strip the ship back to a steel hull. Also blue asbestos is sprayed onto the outer walls and then covered in paint. It's in every nook and cranny."</p>
<p>Many <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scientology%20and%20celebrities">Scientologist celebrities</ref> have spent time aboard the <hi rend="italic">Freewinds</hi>, including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tom%20Cruise">Tom Cruise</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Katie%20Holmes">Katie Holmes</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20Travolta">John Travolta</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kelly%20Preston">Kelly Preston</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chick%20Corea">Chick Corea</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lisa%20Marie%20Presley">Lisa Marie Presley</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catherine%20Bell">Catherine Bell</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kate%20Ceberano">Kate Ceberano</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juliette%20Lewis">Juliette Lewis</ref>. <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Now%20magazine">Now magazine</ref></hi> reported that Tom Cruise has been urged to seek medical attention regarding potential asbestos exposure, however a representative for Cruise stated he has "absolutely no knowledge" of the recent asbestos controversy. Cruise, Holmes, Travolta and Preston have celebrated birthdays and other events on the <hi rend="italic">Freewinds</hi>.</p>
<hi rend="bold">There is not now and never has been a situation of asbestos exposure on the Freewinds.</hi>
</text>
