<text id="autogum_whow_doc328" title="Maintain Mental Health with Exercise" shortTile="maintain-mental-health" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-11-01" dateModified="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Maintain-Mental-Health-with-Exercise" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Maintain Mental Health with Exercise</head><p>There is a lot of proof that exercise will benefit your mental health and creativity. But what are the best exercises for maintaining a healthy mind and body? Here are some tips but know that the most important thing is to stay consistent, listen to your body and know what's best for you.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Casual exercises</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Go for a walk routinely.This is the easiest way of exersising, which will not only keep your body moving but also relaxes your mind
<list type="unordered"><item>Spare around 10-60minutes each day to just wander around the block or a park nearby</item>
<item>Listen to some music or podcasts</item>
<item>Try walking meditation</item></list></item>
<item>Jogging. Light running can free your mind and achieving certain distances can boost your serotonin level, which will keep up your overall happiness
<list type="unordered"><item>Plan around 10-60minutes each day to jog around the block or in a nearby park</item>
<item>Listen to motivational music or try guided runs via apps</item>
<item>Begin small by starting to run 10minutes and increase it slowly</item>
<item>Don't push yourself to run a certain distance in a certain time</item></list></item>
<item>Cycling. Just like the previous exercises this one not only improves your stamina but also reliefs your mind from tension.
<list type="unordered"><item>Get yourself a bike. It does'nt have to be an overly expensive one</item>
<item>Plan to cycle to work, school or anywhere else</item>
<item>Start slow and organize more time for your ride than the GPS estimates. This will reduce stress.</item>
<item>Be safe. Wear a helmet and look out for car drivers, traffic lights and signs.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Gym exersises</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Extended light cardio.
<list type="unordered"><item>Go on a treadmill, stationary bike or stairmaster</item>
<item>Plan around 30minutes for your workout</item>
<item>Take it easy by setting a low speed or resistance</item>
<item>Listen to music or podcasts but don't watch a series or a movie as this will occupy your mind.</item></list></item>
<item>Follow a training plan or routine.
<list type="unordered"><item>Ask a trainer to help you with a plan perfected for your desired results. This will help you with motivation to go to the gym.</item>
<item>Use your phone only to listen to music. Don't scroll through social media while resting in between laps.</item>
<item>Focus on the exercise, not the surrounding and the people. This way your mind does't wander and you get trough your exercises more quickly.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Ultimate mental health exercises</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Yoga. As stereotypical as it seems yoga is the best way to ground yourself, improve your flexibility and boost your mental health. With elements similar to meditation it offers deep relaxation while exercising.
<list type="unordered"><item>Try out a yoga class at your gym. Most gym memberships include classes such as yoga class. Look at the schedule and visit one. You won't find scrawny models or grandmas but rather the regular people you see at the gym.</item>
<item>Try guided yoga routines at home.</item></list></item>
<item>Tai chi. Just like yoga it helps you stay connective to your body, control your movement and relax your mind.
<list type="unordered"><item>Consider tai chi classes</item>
<item>Try out a free first lesson to see if it fits you</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't push your limits and overpower your body while exercising. Be sure to rest appropriately and don't be so hard on yourself if you only lift light weights or run slowly. Your mental health is more important than what others think of you</item></list>
</text>
