<text id="autogum_academic_doc701" title="The Research on Sustainable Tourism in the Light of Its Paradigms" shortTile="research-sustainable" author="Małgorzata Kieżel, Paweł Piotrowski, Joanna Wiechoczek" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5821/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 6. Discussion</head>
<p>
Starting deliberations concerning the issues of the possibility of scientific recognition, especially research methods for identification and explanation of the problem of sustainable tourism, its nature and possibility of its development and evaluation is an important aspect in the study. This represents taking into account the ontological aspect (that inquires whether the analysis of existence should precede the analysis of recognition), as well as epistemological one (comprising the problem of appropriate path of recognition). </p>

<p>Conducting tourism activity has a very complex nature because it takes place both in geographical space (physical and anthropogenic), as well as in economic, social and cultural space. In an individual dimension, tourism also gains the psychological aspect, because it represents some symbolic and emotional value of a high level of individualization. Consequently, tourism is becoming the subject of interest of researchers who represent various fields and apply diverse methods. This multi-faceted nature of the phenomena occurring in tourism raises the need to approach tourist activity as conducted in the space linking both material and non-material aspects. </p>

<p>The case study adopts the initial ontological assumption that shows that studied aspects of sustainable tourism should be approached as a part of a higher level space (geographical, socio-economic and cultural), rather than as a separate entity. These ontological assumptions affect epistemological aspects and adoption of some assumptions concerning the methods of sustainable tourism research. However, it is assumed that it should be studied in a multi-faceted way while taking into account its specific and complex character, and also considering strong relationships with the external environment. Analysing the trends of further research it seems useful to verify how much the defined features distinguishing sustainable tourism from the higher level space, enable its measurement or description in the sphere of adopted research aspects, depending on the assumed methodological approach, i.e., quantitative, qualitative or mixed. </p>

<p>It should be stated that it is difficult to assess these two types of research and recognise one of them as better than the other. This results from the fact that each of them enables gaining another set of information, that if it is used differently, it supports solving the research problem. Consequently, this causes quantitative research to occur together with qualitative while complementing each other, or possibly it precedes qualitative research while enabling primary recognition of the formulated problem. The purpose of triangulation of research methods may be particularly useful to increase the credibility and validity of the results and gives a more detailed and balanced picture of the situation. It is an "attempt to explain more fully, the richness and complexity of human behavior by studying it from more than one standpoint. "The concept of triangulation is borrowed from navigational and land surveying techniques that determine a single point in space with the convergence of measurements taken from two other distinct points". It is an appropriate strategy of founding the credibility of qualitative analyses and it becomes an alternative to traditional criteria like reliability and validity. </p>

<p>According to Spencer’s views, development, on the one hand, consists in a growing diversification of phenomena, and on the other hand in their growing integration, ordering and balancing. For the assessment of the development of sustainable tourism, this represents the need to identify and measure the broadly perceived benefits against broadly approached costs of tourism development. An attempt to consider all or at least the majority of elements of contemporary tourist space would demand application of the research approach of a synthetic and systemic character. Such an approach would be especially important at identification and analysis of the level of tourism sustainability. </p>

<p>For the holistic approach to the issues of sustainable development, it is necessary to evaluate all tourism stakeholders in a given area. This reflects the necessity to consider the opinions of tourists, as well as residents and other entities (in visited places) directly or indirectly involved in tourism development. This results from the fact that both tourists, as well as the local community, can have diverse expectations, but they also bear consequences (positive and negative) in terms of the broadly perceived natural, socio-cultural and economic environment. </p>

<p>The specified division into more uniform sub-groups supports the performance of research on the evaluation of the level of sustainable tourism development as perceived by many groups of stakeholders. As a result, subgroups of diverse socio-demographic features, but also different reasons for travelling and related different expectations or travel frequency can be indicated within the group of tourists. On the other hand, within the local community one can distinguish tourist entrepreneurs, workers, employers hired for tourist services, representatives of public administration, representatives of social organisations associated with tourism development among others. However, people not involved in providing services to tourists or people occupationally not active that are affected by tourism development should also be included here. </p>
</text>
