<text id="autogum_reddit_doc108" title="MIL gets salty about doing the right thing" shortTile="mil-gets-salty-doing" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-04-30" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8g44i7" speakerList="#MILBitchBot, #cup_of_pencils" speakerCount="2">
<head>MIL gets salty about doing the right thing</head>
<sp who="#cup_of_pencils">
<p>SO and I have her pretty much under control, I just need to vent today. The biggest thing that is pissing me off lately is her perception of what constitutes "punishment." Some examples: -MIL, 4YO, and I were at a park. We were about to leave to get ice cream when I noticed that kiddo had left a snack wrapper on the play equipment. I told him he had to go fetch it and put it in a trash can before we could leave. He whined a little but complied. In fact, he was super proud to do a little basketball dunk in the trash can(it was seriously cute). What was MIL's reaction? She practically hissed at me once he was out of earshot. She informed me that it wasn't fair to punish him, he was just a little boy, he didn't litter on purpose, I should have just thrown it out myself if it was so important to me. I reminded her that if she questioned my parenting she would get a time out, she didn't say anything more but had a sour face for a few hours after that. -My neighbor's preschooler left a scooter in my driveway behind my car and I backed up over it. I replaced the scooter, the girl's parent's had her thank me and apologize for leaving her things laying out. When MIL heard the story she was appalled. "Why did you do that?! It was their fault! You didn't have to, you were so foolish to do that." I asked if she thought I should have risked bad blood with my neighbors over a $30 plastic scooter, and she said, "Of course! It was *their fault!*" She got that special bitchy look on her face and I warned her that if she said one word to my neighbors she would be banned from my house permanently. -Most recently I was again accused of punishing my son for enforcing responsibility. He ran up to us and happily informed me that he had spilled juice. He loves to use the carpet steamer attachment but unfortunately for him it was on the linoleum, so just a matter of paper towels. He was disappointed he didn't get to use the steamer so he moped while mopping up. MIL made a snide little "joke" about me just having kids to use as slaves, and I'd had it. I told her it was nap time and tossed her out. I'm just so tired of her bullshit. She does respond to boundaries and has experienced consequences she didn't like in the past, so she's compliant when called out. SO has an even harder spine than I do, so no problems there. She just can't seem to keep her selfishness in check. I just needed to get that off my chest. EDIT: Update: About an hour after I posted this she started texting me to see if I was mad, then called to apologize after I confirmed that I was. Apparently FIL questioned why she was back home from our place so soon and when she didn't know why she'd been kicked out told her, "You better find out how you pissed Pencils off, don't you think?" After some back and forth where she had to get told what she'd did and clarified that she was not "snarky," she was  <hi rend="bold">bitchy</hi> , we resolved it to my satisfaction and all is calm for now. Thank you all so much for your kind remarks and your sympathy. </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#MILBitchBot">
<p>Welcome to r JUSTNOMIL! </p>
<p>I'm u MilBitchBot. I stalk you in this sub and allow others to subscribe to your posts. </p>
<list type="unordered">
<item></item>
<item> </item>

</list><p>^(To be notified as soon as cup_of_pencils posts an update )<ref target="http: www.reddit.com message compose ?to=MilBitchBot&amp;subject=subscribe&amp;message=subscribe cup_of_pencils">^click ^here.</ref></p>
</sp>
</text>
