<text id="autogum_whow_doc602" title="Search for Your Inherent Qualities" shortTile="search-inherent-qualities" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-12-18" dateModified="2018-10-04" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Search-for-Your-Inherent-Qualities" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Search for Your Inherent Qualities</head><p>Everyone is naturally inclined toward having different qualities —  some people are even-tempered, some are inherently kind, and others prefer solitude to socialization. However, a number of outside influences act on everyone, shaping their behavior or personality in a way that, deep down, feels just wrong. If you feel this way, this article will show you how to get to the root of who you are.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Determining Your Qualities</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Consider what qualities you have. These could be anything from leadership and a strong intellect to being a great communicator or a healer. Most people have a range of qualities, so be sure to list everything that you consider to be a quality. Find some forms of qualities listed here (a very incomplete list):
<list type="unordered"><item>Generosity, kindness, openness</item>
<item>Joyful and happy nature</item>
<item>Truthful, trustworthy, sincere</item>
<item>Leader, manager, organizer, communicator</item>
<item>Ethical, patient, tolerant, considerate</item>
<item>Brave, courageous, fierce, assertive</item>
<item>Wise, intelligent</item>
<item>Lonesome, silent</item>
<item>Strict, unforgiving</item>
<item>Considerate, well-mannered</item>
<item>Risk taker, opportunist, entrepreneurial, inspiring</item>
<item>Idealist, creative, artistic, observer.</item></list></item>
<item>Match your qualities to the things you want to do in life. A good match means that you will find the work, hobby, study, vocation, etc., that will be more enjoyable and successful for you. Think back to what you wanted to do when you grew up. Often that gives you an idea of what you are best at and are likely to love, based on your inherent qualities.</item>
<item>Give wings to your imagination. Sketch the person you admire and want to be like. For instance, if you want to be a fashion designer, think which shoes will you use, what shapes impress you, what cuts appeal to you, what fabrics would you use, which colour combination looks vivacious in a nutshell almost everything. You will definitely be able to bring out the best in you and even beyond.</item></list>
<head>Dealing with Character Dents</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Listen to other people's criticisms or feedback about you. If someone says you are rude or shy or not studious enough, don't reply back instantly; that's your defensive self in action. Instead, decide what about their criticism might have elements of truth in it. Then, if you realize critics have a point, work hard on improving that aspect of yourself. It may require working on your communication skills, cutting down on sarcastic remarks, working harder, focusing more, saying kinder things, etc. <figure rend="Search for Your Inherent Qualities Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't put yourself down or quite because of what others say. Learn from their opinions of you, but be a cherry picker –– honestly ascertain what is right, and discard what is just mean or unhelpful.</item></list></item>
<item>Learn to communicate with greater ease. Find ways to get your own opinions, thoughts and ideas across to others in ways that provide interest and do not cause others to feel intimidated or preached at. It is also important to learn to stand up for yourself, so that your qualities are recognized and not ignored. <figure rend="Search for Your Inherent Qualities Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take challenges thrown to you seriously. When someone says you can never do something, aim to be fired up to achieve it at any cost. Use those words as a motivation to prove others wrong. Acting that way will automatically reveal some personal qualities you have, but you've never known before. <figure rend="Search for Your Inherent Qualities Step 3.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>That day will also come, the day when you will be able to show your inherent qualities to the world. Always think positive and in your mind, live life as if you are actually living the life of the kind of person you want to be.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Remember that life is not fair and sometimes merciless, so keep your cool.</item></list>
</text>
