<text id="autogum_bio_doc116" title="Maitatsine" shortTile="maitatsine" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-11-03" dateModified="2019-09-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maitatsine" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Maitatsine</head>This article is about the preacher. For the military officer, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mohammed_Buba_Marwa">Mohammed Buba Marwa</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Mohammed Marwa</hi> (died 1980), best known by his nickname <hi rend="bold">Maitatsine</hi>, was a controversial preacher in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nigeria">Nigeria</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Maitatsine</hi> is a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hausa_language">Hausa</ref> word meaning "the one who damns" and refers to his curse-laden public speeches against the Nigerian state.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-adesoji-1">[1]</ref> His militant followers are known as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yan_Tatsine">Yan Tatsine</ref>. </p>
<head>Background</head>
<p>He was originally from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maroua">Marwa</ref> in northern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cameroon">Cameroon</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Lubeck-2">[2]</ref> After his education he moved to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kano,_Nigeria">Kano, Nigeria</ref> in about 1945, where he became known for his controversial preachings on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qur'an">Qur'an</ref>. Maitatsine spoke against the use of radios, watches, bicycles, cars and the possession of more money than necessary.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-kastfelt1989-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-pham-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>The British <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colonial_Nigeria">colonial authorities</ref> sent him into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exile">exile</ref>, but he returned to Kano shortly after <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nigerian_Independence">independence</ref>. By 1972 he had a notable and increasingly militant following known as <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yan_Tatsine">Yan Tatsine</ref></hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-pham-4">[4]</ref>  In 1975 he was again arrested by Nigerian police for slander and public abuse of political authorities<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Lubeck-2">[2]</ref>  But in that period he began to receive acceptance from religious authorities, especially after making <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hajj">hajj</ref>, the Muslim pilgrimage to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mecca">Mecca</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Lubeck-2">[2]</ref> As his following increased in the 1970s, so did the number of confrontations between his adherents and the police. His preaching attracted largely a following of youths, unemployed migrants, and those who felt that mainstream Muslim teachers were not doing enough for their communities.  By December 1980, continued Yan Tatsine attacks on other religious figures and police forced the Nigerian army to become involved.  Subsequent armed clashes led to the deaths of around 5,000 people, including Maitatsine himself.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-pham-4">[4]</ref>  Maitatsine died shortly after sustaining injuries in the clashes either from his wounds or from a heart attack.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-hiskett-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>According to a 2010 article published by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sunday_Trust">Sunday Trust</ref> magazine the military cremated Maitatsine's remains, which now rest in a bottle kept at a police laboratory in Kano.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sundayTrust20101226-6">[6]</ref></p>
<head>Legacy</head>
<p>Despite Mohammed Marwa's death, Yan Tatsine riots continued into the early 1980s. In October 1982 riots erupted in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulumkuttu">Bulumkuttu</ref>, near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maidaguri">Maidaguri</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Omotosho-7">[7]</ref> and in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kaduna">Kaduna</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Omotosho-7">[7]</ref> to where many Yan Tatsine adherents had moved after 1980.  Over 3,000 people died.  Some survivors of these altercations moved to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yola,_Nigeria">Yola</ref>, and in early 1984 more violent uprisings occurred in that city.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Omotosho-7">[7]</ref>  In this round of rioting, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Musa_Makaniki">Musa Makaniki</ref>, a close disciple of Maitatsine, emerged as a leader and Marwa's successor.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-pham-4">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-hiskett-5">[5]</ref>  Ultimately more than 1,000 people died in Yola and roughly half of the city's 60,000 inhabitants were left homeless.  Makaniki fled to his hometown of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gombe,_Nigeria">Gombe</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Omotosho-7">[7]</ref> where more Yan Tatsine riots occurred in April 1985.  After the deaths of several hundred people Makaniki retreated to Cameroon, where he remained until 2004 when he was arrested in Nigeria.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-pham-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Some analysts view the terrorist group <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boko_Haram">Boko Haram</ref> as an extension of the Maitatsine riots.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cfrBackgrounder-8">[8]</ref></p>
<head>Literature</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Allan Christelow, Abdalla Uba Adamu: Art. "Mai Tatsine" in John L. Esposito (ed.): <hi rend="italic">The Oxford Encyclopedia of the Islamic World.</hi> 6 Bde. Oxford 2009. Bd. III, S. 459-462.</item></list>
</text>
