<text id="autogum_interview_doc321" title="part8_John Reed on Orwell, God, self-destruction and the future of writing" shortTile="partjohn-reed-orwell" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-18" dateModified="2015-01-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Reed_on_Orwell%2C_God%2C_self-destruction_and_the_future_of_writing" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Sure.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  And someone came screaming out: they'd had an audience with the Queen.  They were shouting that they had just met the Queen and that the Queen had given him ... a poop.  One of her poops.  And he comes running out and he's saying this, and everyone is mocking him.  He's taking it good-naturedly, as he should.  He's standing there, and the crowd kind of quiets down, and he's holding this small plastic tub--which incidentally is the one that we put the lizard in when we're cleaning the cage--he's holding this small plastic tub that has two dry, narrow poops in it, one sort of tipped on the other.  There's a silence overwhelming the crowd.  Then he pops the lid, and he lifts it to his nose to sniff it.  And he sniffs it, and he really takes it in, and he's thinking about this smell and committing it to memory.  Then, in utter silence, he just passes it to the person next to him, and that person takes the poop up to their nose and sniffs it, and then it passes through the whole crowd.</p>
<p>[<hi rend="italic">both chuckle</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  So, that dream I keep thinking about.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you do dream analysis?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  I think that dream has to do with the way things become big in culture.  I have all kinds of complaints about the literary canon.  For example, there are a lot of books that are widely remembered that I think could be forgotten--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Like Animal Farm?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Well, Animal Farm, I don't know if I would forget it, but I might forget other lesser-known books by--let's pick a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trollope">Trollope</ref> book and get rid of it, because that book is at the expense of a contemporary author.  I don't really see the genres as competing against literary authors; I see the backlist as competing against literary authors.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What's a book that every kid in high school reads that you think should be removed?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Well, I read <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Typhoon%20(novel)">Typhoon</ref> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joseph%20Conrad">Joseph Conrad</ref>, and that could definitely go.  I was not a big fan of those <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%20James%20Fenimore%20Cooper%20">James Fenimore Cooper</ref> books, which I had to read.  I thought they were just preposterous.  They could go.  There are a bunch of Trollope books that could go.  I know there are some people who love <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Balzac">Balzac</ref>, but frankly, a lot of those bore me to death, too.  I would have kids reading contemporary books.  A kid who reads a book and says, "This isn't for me.  It doesn't have anything to do with my time period; I don't know why I'm reading it.  Literature is completely removed from my experience."  They're right!  There's no reason to have that kid reading books that are removed from their experience.</p>
</text>
