<text id="autogum_interview_doc384" title="part5_Wikinews interviews Mark Bunker, producer of anti-Scientology website &amp;apos;XenuTV&amp;apos;" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-05" dateModified="2016-03-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Mark_Bunker%2C_producer_of_anti-Scientology_website_%27XenuTV%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What do you think Anonymous should do if Scientologists plant fake anons in a protest and act like idiots to show anons up?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: Scientologists pretending to be Anonymous at your pickets, that's bound to happen. That's what Hubbard ordered. Adopt a "suitable guise" and infiltrate an organization to collect intelligence. They also are logging this channel and watching every word here and anywhere else we speak about them. As for the dopey comments, I understand completely that that is the power of being Anonymous on the net. It allows you to say outrageous things with no repercussions. It happens everywhere on the net and I am not offended. People say things they would never say to your face.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Are you going to upload the old XenuTV movies (RealVideo) to Google Video or something similar?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: Will my old RealVideos be uploaded to Google? Yes. I have been working on it but I have a full time job and tons of things going one which has only gotten worse since this thing started. I was talking to Tory yesterday and she is overwhelmed by the emails she's getting. I look at them and have panic attacks that I haven't even been able to read all of mine yet let alone respond.</p>
<head id="Questions_from_IRC_users">Questions from IRC users</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DA-freakshow</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">As you know now, the Anonymous Protests was extremely huge, but we are planning a second round the 15th of March. And I — a 12-year-old WILL attend, is that a good sign that so young a person wants to be involved, or is it a bad sign?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: Well, it's good if you understand what you're getting yourself into and your parents or guardians are aware as well. Scientology is serious. They won't harm you but they don't play games either. 12-year-old kids get swept into Scientology's Cadet Org and moved into the Sea Org shortly after. That is far more dangerous to a 12-year-old than picketing fraud and abuse.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Carbonflux</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Can you put any of this in a historical context? Have you studied the history of Scientology in relation to its "parent" organizations (cults praying on the elite) in the 18th - 20th centuries ? (Many of L. Ron Hubbard's ideas were taken directly from OTO which he was a member of in his early life for example).</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: Hubbard did call Crowley his good friend but I doubt that he was seriously deep into it. I think he stumbled into a situation at Jack Parson mansion in which he could live high off the rich guys cash and steal his hot girlfriend. I think he probably enjoyed a good laugh at the satanic rituals he engaged in but it certainly informed his understanding of how to run such a group and how people can buy into any wacky belief system.</p>
</text>
