<text id="autogum_bio_doc521" title="Anna Notaras" shortTile="anna-notaras" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-08-06" dateModified="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anna_Notaras" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Anna Notaras</head><p><hi rend="bold">Anna Notaras Palaiologina</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greek_language">Greek</ref>: Ἄννα Νοταρᾶ Παλαιολογίνα; died 8 July 1507) was the daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loukas_Notaras">Loukas Notaras</ref>, the last <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Megas_doux">megas doux</ref></hi> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byzantine_Empire">Byzantine Empire</ref>. </p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Anna probably left <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constantinople">Constantinople</ref> prior to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fall_of_Constantinople">fall of Constantinople</ref> in 1453, although the passenger manifest of a Genoese ship which escaped the siege on the morning of the 29th May includes two entries for the family name Notaras.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> Her exact whereabouts before 1459 are not certain, but in that year she appeared in Italy and made claim to the Notaras family inheritance, held at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bank_of_Saint_George">Bank of St George</ref> in Genoa. The fate of this large inheritance had become a diplomatic question during the six years following the death of Loukas Notaras. She had her younger brother, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacob_Notaras">Jacob Notaras</ref>, disinherited on the grounds that he had converted to Islam while in captivity.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> She lived for a time in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rome">Rome</ref> before eventually settling in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Venice">Venice</ref>, where she became the center of the Byzantine expatriate community.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Nicol1-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>She repeatedly petitioned the Republic to allow the construction of an Orthodox church within Venice (something not granted until 1539) and when the Council of Ten prevaricated, she badgered them into a compromise, allowing her to build an oratory within her own sizable Casa and hold Orthodox services within it from 1475.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Nicol1-3">[3]</ref> In 1498, the Venetian Senate finally granted their Greek community the right to found the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scuola_dei_Greci">Scuola di San Nicolò dei Greci</ref>, a confraternity which aided members of that community. Although Anna Notaras died in 1507, prior to the completion of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Giorgio_dei_Greci">San Giorgio dei Greci</ref>, she left three of icons in her will to the church, where they remain today. </p>
<p>In 1499, the first exclusively Greek printing press in Venice began operation under the direction of Nikolaos Vlasto and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zacharias_Calliergi">Zacharias Kalliergis</ref>. The first product of the press was the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Etymologicum_Magnum">Etymologicum Magnum</ref></hi> and the dedication at the front thanks the ‘most modest lady Anna, daughter of…Loukas Notaras’ who had defrayed its cost.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Nicol1-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>In 1472 Anna began negotiations with the council of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republic_of_Siena">Siena</ref> to take possession of the old castle of Montauto and the surrounding lands in order to found a commune where Greeks could live "according to their laws and customs". In their correspondence with her, the council referred to her as the widow of the last Byzantine emperor, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constantine_XI_Palaiologos">Constantine XI Palaiologos</ref> (r.1449–1453), but this was untrue. There is no mention of such a marriage in any other contemporary source, especially in the writings of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Sphrantzes">George Sphrantzes</ref>, his chancellor. Although the legal contract was drawn up, the commune project went no further.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Nicol1-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>A friend of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basilios_Bessarion">Basilios Bessarion</ref>, Anna also recovered several Greek manuscripts from the east. In 1470 she acquired a 12th century manuscript Catena of Job written for the Grand Duke of Cyprus. On March 2, 1489, Zabeta, wife of her brother Jacob, filed a petition before the judges of the Venetian Procurator alleging that Jacob had shortly before his death in Ancona, sent to his sister Anna "a box of law books of different kinds, both on parchment and on paper" of great value. She demanded that Anna hand over these works to her, or be ordered to pay her the sum of 120 ducats. Anna acknowledged receipt of this box but contended that most of the books had actually been bought by herself and been lent to Jacob. Anna won this court case and then on 8th of May, 1490, Anna filed a petition against Zabeta, alleging that she had entered the Ca Notaras and stolen a valuable copy of Petrarch, which Anna had bought from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Palaiologos">Thomas Palaiologos</ref> in 1462, during his visit to Venice, which she valued at 51 ducats. The judge ruled in Anna's favour again.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Fictional Portrayals</head>
<head>Novels</head>
<p>Anna Notaras appears as a central character in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Dark_Angel_(Waltari_novel)">The Dark Angel</ref></hi> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mika_Waltari">Mika Waltari</ref> and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Porphyry_and_Ash">Porphyry and Ash</ref></hi> by Peter Sandham</p>
</text>
