<text id="autogum_voyage_doc92" title="Seward" shortTile="seward" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=32273" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Seward</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://seward.com/">Seward</ref></hi> ("SOO-word") is a small port city (population ~2,700) located at the head of Resurrection Bay on the <ref target="Kenai%20Peninsula">Kenai Peninsula</ref> in <ref target="Southcentral%20Alaska">Southcentral Alaska</ref>. Seward was named in honor of William H. Seward, President Abraham Lincoln's Secretary of State, who was responsible for negotiating the purchase of Alaska from Russia in 1867.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>Founded in 1903 as the ocean terminus of what is now the Alaska Railroad, Seward prides itself, not only on its natural beauty, but as Alaska's only deep-water, ice-free port with rail, highway and air transportation to Alaska's interior and major urban population centers.</p>

<p>For local events and news see <ref target="http://www.sewardcitynews.com">SewardCityNews.com</ref>, Seward's citizen journalism website.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>Seward is located 127 road miles south of <ref target="Anchorage">Anchorage</ref>. The <ref target="http://alaska.org/driving/seward-drive.htm">Seward Highway</ref> is a very scenic 2.5-hour drive from Anchorage to Seward, but can be slow in peak summer.</p>

<p>In 2017 the Alaska Department of Transportation announced a 4-year 2-phase <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.sewardhighway75to90.com/">Milepost 75-90 Rehabilitation Project</ref></hi> to make major safety improvements to a busy crash-prone section of the Seward Highway from Girdwood to beyond the Portage curve toward Turnagain Pass. In July 2015 a tour bus crash at Milepost 79 (<hi rend="italic">Portage Glacier Road</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Alaska Wildlife Conservation Center</hi>) killed one man and critically injured several others, causing a 10-hour traffic jam. During the summer months, up to 15,000 vehicles use this 15-mile stretch of Seward Highway daily. Although the project is not yet fully funded, construction on Seward Highway is scheduled to begin 2018.</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.alaskarailroad.com/">The Alaska Railroad</ref></hi> offers daily rail passage between Anchorage and Seward in the summer, May 13 to Sept 14. The trip between Anchorage and Seward -- the Coastal Classic -- is arguably its most scenic section, and you can take the train one-way. The train parallels the Seward Highway along the Turnagain Arm, but also heads up into the mountains away from the road, pass glaciers and alpine meadows you won't be able to see by car. Adventure Class (with shared access to older vista dome railcar) Round Trip/One Way fare: $119/$75 adults, $59/$38 children (2-11); GoldStar Service (New Dome Railcar) Round Trip/One Way fare: $219/$130 adults, $110/$65 children.</p>

<p>Passengers are required by TSA to check-in at the ticket window (hour before at Anchorage, 30-45 minutes before at Seward) and show a government issued photo ID (for those age 18 and older) to receive boarding passes. If you have luggage (2 pieces max), it must be checked through to your destination. At depots, boarding for trains occurs 20-30 minutes prior to the scheduled departure.</p>

<p>Southbound</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> 6:45AM - Depart Anchorage Depot - 411 West 1st Avenue</item>
<item> 11:05AM - Arrive Seward Depot - 410 Port Avenue (short walk to small boat harbor; about 1/2 mile to cruise ship dock)</item>
</list>


<p>Northbound</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> 6PM - Depart Seward Depot</item>
<item> 10:15PM - Arrive Anchorage Depot</item>
</list>


<head>By bus</head>
<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.alaskacoach.com/">The Park Connection</ref></hi>, 1-800-208-0200, offers twice daily bus service between Anchorage and Seward in the summer, mid-May to mid-September. Check in 15 minutes prior; luggage 2 pieces max. In general, the trip by bus is faster than by train, but slower than by car.</p>

<p>Southbound AM</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> 7AM - Depart Anchorage - Egan Center: $55</item>
<item> 9:45AM - Arrive Seward Small Boat Harbor</item>
</list>

<p>Southbound PM</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> 3PM - Departs Anchorage Museum: $65</item>
<item> 5:45PM - Arrive Seward Small Boat Harbor</item>
</list>


<p>Northbound AM</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> 10:30AM - Depart Seward Small Boat Harbor: $65</item>
<item> 1:30PM - Arrive Anchorage Museum</item>
</list>

<p>Northbound PM</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> 6:30PM - Depart Seward Small Boat Harbor: $55</item>
<item> 9:30PM - Arrive Anchorage Museum</item>
</list>


<head>By ship</head>

<p>The <hi rend="bold">Dale R. Lindsey Alaska Railroad Seward Intermodal Terminal</hi> ("cruise-ship dock" to locals), 913 Port Ave, is where cruise ships moor. Ships tie up directly to the dock, and no tenders are used to transport guests between the ship and shore. The Alaska Railroad uses this facility for freight.</p>

<p>From May to September, about 50 ships arrive and depart Seward's port as part of the popular 7-14 day Alaska cruises, round-the-world itineraries, and special charter cruises.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>Seward is a great place to walk around. For those needing a ride, here are some options.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Summer Shuttle Bus</hi>, +1 907-224-4020, is operated daily by the city of Seward during the summer months when the cruise ships are in town. The shuttle makes a half hour loop starting at the cruise ship dock to the Alaska SeaLife Center and back. $5 pp, good for entire day.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://tidewatertaxi.com/">Tidewater Taxi</ref></hi> +1 907-727-1929. Water taxi servicing Resurrection Bay, Kayakers Cove, Alaska State Park Cabins and elsewhere.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hertz of Seward</hi>, 907-224-4378. Rentals for a day or longer with one-way drop off in Anchorage available.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Seward Bike Shop</hi>, 411 Port Ave., 907-224-2448, sewardbikeshop.com. Rents bikes by the hour or day. There is a bike path along the water from the harbor to the front of town.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.pjstaxi.com">PJ'S Taxis</ref></hi>, 907-224-5555.</item>
</list>


<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Sealife Center</hi>, 301 Railway Ave, ☏ +1 907 224-6300 , toll-free: +1-800 224-2525 . Aquarium and research facility featuring marine life of the Gulf of Alaska. The Sealife Center is Alaska’s only public aquarium and ocean wildlife rescue center. Exhibits feature puffins, octopus, sea lions and other sealife. $20 adult, $15 student (12-17), $10 child (4-11), age 3 and under free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Exit Glacier</hi>. Exit Glacier is the only part of <ref target="Kenai%20Fjords%20National%20Park">Kenai Fjords National Park</ref> accessible by road. Here you can stroll the trails, walk very close to an active glacier or take a ranger-led walk. It is a place where you can witness up close how glaciers re-shape a landscape and learn how plant life reclaims the barren rocky land exposed by a glacier's retreat.</item>
</list>

 

<head>Do</head>

<p>Sewards highlights are the neighboring <ref target="Kenai%20Fjords%20National%20Park">Kenai Fjords National Park</ref>, sport fishing (for salmon, halibut, ling cod and salmon shark), glacier and wildlife day cruises, kayaking, sailing, hiking and mountain biking, quaint and quirky townsfolk, 4th of July celebrations and the Silver Salmon Derby.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Stoney Creek Canopy Adventures</hi>. - located in Seward</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">4th of July Mount Marathon Race</hi>. Three miles up and down, complete with cliffs, waterfalls, and loose sharp rocks, a great Alaskan event</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Seavey's Ididaride</hi>, Exit Glacier Rd. Here you can see one of the family's 3 dog yards. Go for a ride on a buggy with a team of dogs, play with puppies, and get up close and personal with Mitch's gear and sled. You get a tour guide through the property and learn about the grueling ididarod race.</item>
</list>
</text>
