<text id="autogum_interview_doc612" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Joe Schriner, Independent U.S. presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-04-16" dateModified="2019-08-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Joe_Schriner%2C_Independent_U.S._presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Joe Schriner, Independent U.S. presidential candidate</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, April 17, 2010</hi></p>
<p>Journalist, counselor, painter, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US">US</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20presidential%20election,%202012">2012 Presidential candidate</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joe%20Schriner">Joe Schriner</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cleveland,%20Ohio">Cleveland</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ohio">Ohio</ref> took some time to discuss his campaign with <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> in an interview.</p>
<p>Schriner previously ran for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/President%20of%20the%20United%20States">president</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20presidential%20election,%202000">2000</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20presidential%20election,%202004">2004</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20presidential%20election,%202008">2008</ref>, but failed to gain much traction in the races.  He announced his candidacy for the 2012 race immediately following the 2008 election. Schriner refers to himself as the "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Average%20Joe">Average Joe</ref>" candidate, and advocates a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/pro-life">pro-life</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Environmental%20movement">pro-environmentalist</ref> platform. He has been the subject of numerous newspaper articles, and has published public policy papers exploring solutions to American issues.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:William_Saturn">William Saturn‎</ref> talks with Schriner and discusses his campaign.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">William Saturn</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">I was reading the January 2009 article <ref target="http://starbeacon.com/obitcorrection/x343696723/In-the-2008-presidential-campaign-it-was-Joe-the-Plumber-In-2012-it-s-going-to-be-Joe-the-Painter">In the 2008 presidential campaign, it was Joe the Plumber. In 2012, it’s going to be Joe the Painter</ref> from the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Star%20Beacon">Star Beacon</ref></hi> , and it says that you're "a former print journalist and addictions counselor who switched to house painting when he felt guided to run for president." Why did you feel guided to run for president?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Joe Schriner</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Ok, ‘Joe the painter’… While the Star Beacon article was done quite well as a whole, the wording in this part about ‘the presidency and house painting’ is a bit too abbreviated, and a bit too disjointed.  The more accurate version is… I have a degree in journalism from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bowling%20Green%20State%20University">Bowling Green State University</ref> and have worked for several intermediate sized newspapers in Ohio. A ways into this, I changed professions and became a licensed chemical dependency counselor who started one of the first outpatient treatment programs in the Midwest for people who were raised in addictive/dysfunctional families.  (As an aside, during Campaign 2000, I told <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CBS%20News">CBS News</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monterey,%20California">Monterey</ref>, that: “To heal the country, we have to heal the family.”   After working in the chemical dependency field for about eight years, I felt a spiritual prompting – as other people at times feel spiritual promptings to do any number of things – to leave this profession and go out on the road to look for people trying to make a difference when it came to things like healing the family, saving the environment, helping the poor, creating peace ...I felt compelled to gather these stories, using my journalism background, then share them with others – with the hopes of planting “seeds of change.”  After a long, considered discernment process, I decided to go on the road and left  Cleveland, in 1990.  This was the start of an eight-year research period where I logged close to 100,000 miles.  What I learned was a lot of tremendously creative, common sense solutions to practically all the issues of our day.  Armed with this, I started to running for president in 1999, and have been doing it ever since (four successive election cycles).  In each newspaper interview, each radio show, each speech... I share parts of what I researched with the hopes people will try some of it in their own town, and who knows how far out it will ripple from there.  (I found that running for president is a great way to get a message out.  And yes, I am indeed trying to win as well. Then I could get the information out a lot quicker, and further.) Now as far as the house painting, because I'm on the road some six to eight months a year campaigning, it's logistically quite hard to hold down a counseling or journalism job. So, instead, I do some part-time house painting to make ends meet. And thus, “Joe the painter.”    Note:  As an example, in the heart of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buffalo,%20New%20York">Buffalo</ref>, I interviewed Dr. Myron Glick who felt his own 'spiritual prompting' to move his family to inner city Buffalo and start the Jericho Road Health Clinic.  He uses a minimal sliding fee scale and has seen people from at least 50 different countries (Buffalo is a port city).  Why?  Because he's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christianity">Christian</ref>, he told me, and it is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesus">Jesus Christ</ref>' edict that we help the poor.  I have shared Dr. Glick's story all over the country, with the hopes of inspiring other doctors to consider doing some version of the same.  And each time that happens, I get a component of our healthcare bill passed – and another little kid living below the poverty line gets the medical help they might have otherwise not gotten.  For more on our healthcare position paper, see  or, listen to my “<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fireside%20chats">Fireside Podcast</ref>” on healthcare, and podcasts on other pressing issues of the day, at  </p>
</text>
