<text id="autogum_academic_doc221" title="Behavioral Facilitation of a Transition to Energy Efficient and Low-Carbon Residential Buildings" shortTile="behavioral-facilitation" author="Robert  A. Enker, Gregory  M. Morrison" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2075-5309/9/11/226/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 6. Discussion</head>
<p>It is unarguable that an effective response to the challenge of climate change and its contributory GHG emissions must include an explicit policy focus on the building sector. To this end, a coherent response by governments calls for the deployment of diverse, complementary policy instruments. </p>

<p>The effective implementation of building energy policy ultimately depends on achieving an intended behavioral change by the respondent sectoral stakeholder group. These outcomes require engagement with property developers, contractors, lessees, builders, or individual consumers, depending on the market sector targeted by the policy measure in question. For example, in the residential sector, consumers and building service providers are seen to be the key target stakeholder groups. </p>

<p>This paper seeks to break new ground by examining residential building energy policy interventions using a BE approach, wherein the behavior of key stakeholders such as consumers, designers, and builders, is addressed from a socio-psychological perspective. Although BE theory is being applied to policy implementation in areas such as consumer protection, finance, and public health, its principles have yet to be applied to the key building sector in the core area of building performance (as energy efficiency). It is worth reflecting on the contribution of residential building performance, including services such as water heating, to total residential energy demand. According to a definitive study by the Australian Government, residential space conditioning and water heating accounts for over 60% of the total residential energy consumption, with the balance taken up by electrical appliances and cooking. So, policy interventions focused on improved building design and construction are particularly important for reducing residential energy consumption, as downstream interventions directed towards reducing demand during building operation will inevitably be constrained by structural factors. </p>

<p>Working from a grounding in BE theory, the paper explains how decisions made by building industry stakeholders differ substantially from those assumed by an orthodox (essentially economic) policy perspective. This divergence has significant implications for the framing of sectoral climate and energy policies. Thus, BE theory suggests that understanding and applying inferences drawn from an appreciation of the cognitive heuristics at play among stakeholders can contribute to a marked improvement in the prospects for successful policy intervention, to deliver sustained behavioral change. Conversely, failure to heed the lessons available from BE theory is likely to jeopardize prospects for successful policy deployment. </p>

<p>A high level of complementarity between key elements of BE theory—represented by cognitive heuristics—and the behavioral triggers that building energy policy seeks to influence (Table 2) has been demonstrated. So, it follows that lessons available from BE theory might make a substantial contribution to the development of the government policy instruments that are being deployed to accelerate the transition to an energy efficient, low-carbon residential building stock (see Table 4 below for examples). </p>

<p>In a series of case studies (Section 5), the operation of each major category of building energy policy intervention was examined in turn. This section of the paper clarifies and reinforces the strong relationship between the tenets of BE theory and the mechanics of building policy. More revealingly, each category of policy implementation is shown to suffer from significant flaws—deficiencies that might reasonably be attributed, at least prima facie, to a failure by policy makers to appreciate the implications of the behavioral changes expected from targeted stakeholder groups. The utilization of BE principles through the application of appropriate heuristics offers a powerful vehicle for addressing these identified policy shortcomings. </p>

<p>Reviewing these policy failures through a BE lens better explains the following:
<list>
<item>Why compliance with energy efficiency requirements mandated in building regulations may be fatally compromised as a result of indifference by both building project developers and consumers;</item>
<item>Why price-based interventions in the property market (such as through an ETS) will not necessarily prompt a rational response from consumers;</item>
<item>Why consumer information campaigns such as the EU EPC initiative fail to achieve a significant market impact, or a price premium for superior certified performance, because of weak and irrational consumer responses.</item>
</list>
</p>

<p>These findings are summarized in Table 4, together with selected references from the literature that could provide a platform for the development of more effective market interventions based on BE principles. </p>

<p>BE theory suggests that understanding and applying inferences to be drawn from an appreciation of the cognitive heuristics at play among industry stakeholders could contribute to a marked improvement in the success of policy interventions, delivering a sustained behavioral change. But failure to heed the lessons available from BE theory is likely to jeopardize prospects for successful building policy deployment. </p>

<p>Despite the strong case for a focus on energy efficient buildings in terms of a global climate response, this policy area has yet to be appreciated by government BITs. A recent OECD study into the potential application of BE principles to energy policy development concluded that areas for exploring the application of behavioral insights should specifically focus on regulatory implementation and decision making by regulatory agencies. </p>
</text>
