<text id="autogum_news_doc049" title="Egypt struggles to recover tourism, investment" shortTile="egypt-struggles-recover" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-02-03" dateModified="2015-08-30" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Egypt_struggles_to_recover_tourism%2C_investment" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Egypt struggles to recover tourism, investment</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, February 10, 2012</hi></p>
<figure><caption>The Egyptian pound is currently falling in value.Image: Mabuhelwa.</caption></figure><p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Standard%20&amp;%20Poor's">Standard &amp; Poor's</ref> downgraded <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Egypt">Egypt</ref>'s currency rating for the second time in four months based on the country's shorfall in foreign reserves and shaky political transition. It's the latest development for a nation facing mounting economic diffuclties.</p>
<p>Egypt's foreign reserves fell by over 50 percent last year to about <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_dollar">US$</ref>16 billion. Egypt has requested US$3.2 billion from the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/International_Monetary_Fund">International Monetary Fund</ref> to bolster its reserves and prevent a devalation but that could take months.</p>
<p>Experts say that <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Egypt">Egypt</ref>'s problem of attracting foreign investment and tourists, which are two sources that would increase reserves, has already caused the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Egyptian%20pound">Egyptian pound</ref> to lose 1 percent of its value and if the country doesn't solve the shortfall in foriegn currency, it could even lead to a further currency <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/devaluation">devaluation</ref> within the next two to three months.</p>
<p>The long-term solution is to restore tourism and foreign investments but both are suffering because of the continuing unrest.</p>
<head id="Tourism">Tourism</head>
<figure><caption>The Sphynx was said to guard the city of Thebes by killing anyone who couldn't  answer a riddle.Image: Schreibkraft.</caption></figure><p> Egyptian tourism suffered this past year as a result of a revolution, a transition to an elected government, and continuing signs of unrest and instability.</p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2011%20egyptian%20revolution">Egyptian Revolution</ref> began on January 25 last year and President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hosni_Mubarak">Hosni Mubarak</ref> resigned over two weeks later on February 11. The protests have continued as Egyptians grew uncomfortable with the military's control over the transition. At the start of this month, 79 people were killed at a soccer event in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Port%20Said">Port Said</ref>.</p>
<p>Tourism in Egypt accounted for US$12.5 billion in 2010 but fell 30 percent, or US$8.8 billion, in 2011, according to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mounir%20Fakhry%20Abdel%20Nour">Mounir Fakhry Abdel Nour</ref>, Egypt's tourism minister. Tourism accounts for 11.6 percent of Egypt's GDP.</p>
<figure><caption>Tourists visit The Valley of the Kings in Egypt. It holds 63 tombs and chambers for Pharaohs and nobles of the New Kingdom era. The valley is on the west bank of the Nile across from Thebes.Image: Markh.</caption></figure><p> Last week, two U.S. female tourists and their Egyptian guide were abducted in the Sinai peninsula by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bedouin">Bedouin</ref> tribesmen and released shortly afterward.</p>
<p>The kidnapping took place in broad daylight on a busy road while the tourists travelled after a visit to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint%20Catherine's%20Monastery,%20Mount%20Sinai">St. Catherine's Monastery</ref>. Masked tribesmen stopped their bus, abducted the tourists by gunpoint, and escaped into the mountains. Three other tourists of unknown nationalities were left on the bus. Local authorities organized a search which ended in negotiations with local Bedouin tribesmen. The Bedouin demanded the release of recently apprehended tribesmen, who had been detained for drug trafficking and robbery. The US hostages were released unharmed, Abdel Nour said.</p>
<p>As a location, Egypt boasts ancient <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Egyptian%20pyramids">pyramids</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nile">Nile River</ref>, Biblical sites like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mount%20Sinai">Mount Sinai</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Egyptian%20Museum">museums</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Red_Sea">Red Sea</ref> coastal resorts. Last year the number of tourists plunged from fifteen million people down to nine million, which is a 40 percent drop.</p>
<figure><caption>A camel resting between rides at the Pyramids in Egypt.Image: Crashsystems.</caption></figure><p>The low amount of tourism to Egypt has also affected tourism in other countries. Stas Misezhnikov, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Israel">Israeli</ref> tourism minister, said that Israeli tourism is down because the flow of tourism from Egypt's <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sharm_el-Sheikh">Sharm el-Sheikh</ref> resort is "almost nonexistent right now."</p>
<head id="Investment">Investment</head>
<p>Egypt's current investment climate is also severely hampered by the perception that the climate is not yet right for investment. </p>
<p>Mulyani Indrawati, managing director of the World Bank, said investors were not ready to get back into the markets of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Arab_Spring">Arab Spring</ref> countries until stability is restored but the situation has also been exacerbated by the precarious state of the regional and international economy.</p>
<p>Egypt's domestic politics is threatening one of the country's largest stable sources of foreign investment. The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref>' annual military aid to Egypt accounts for US$1.5 billion. U.S. politicians have threatened to withhold that aid package, however, because of an investigation into pro-democracy NGOs that involve 19 American citizens and more U.S. money. Senator <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Kerry">John Kerry</ref> said the Egyptian investigation is a "dangerous game that risks damaging both Egypt's democratic prospects and the U.S.-Egyptian bilateral relationship."</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Faiza%20Abou%20el-Naga">Faiza Abou el-Naga</ref>, who is the Egyptian minister who distributes Egypt's aid money, a former Mubarak loyalist who survived through the transition, and one of Egypt's most visible female politicians, claims the NGOs are meddling in her country's sovereignty. Both the Muslim parties who won the election and the generals in power are backing those hearings. Her argument that foreigners are meddling in Egypt also has a populist appeal.</p>
<p>The military government's slow transition is also stalling foreign investments. Khaled bin Mohamed al-Attiya, foreign minister of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Qatar">Qatar</ref>, said a few weeks ago his government is holding back from making US$10 billion in investments because power has not been transferred to an elected government. The other Middle Eastern countries that pledged investments, such as <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Saudi_Arabia">Saudi Arabia</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Arab_Emirates">United Arab Emirates</ref> are also waiting.</p>
<p>The Egyptian government announced this week that it was investigating Yasser el-Mallawany, an investment banker with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EFG-Hermes%20Holding%20Company">EFG Hermes</ref> based in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Cairo">Cairo</ref>, for allegedly paying soccer fans to riot at Port Said, a charge which el-Mallawany dismissed and attributed to gossip.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, investors within Egypt are looking for other investment vehicles such as real estate as they fear holding cash in a period of devaluation.</p>
<p>Florence Eid, who is an expert on Middle Eastern economies at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.K.">U.K.</ref> Arabia Monitor, said the situation throughout the Middle East could get worse. "People are frustrated because the reasons that they revolted against to begin with, are still there," Eid said. "Whoever said this was going to be smooth was naive."</p>
</text>
