<text id="autogum_interview_doc058" title="part3_Wikinews interviews painter Pricasso on his art and freedom of expression" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-10-10" dateModified="2019-08-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_painter_Pricasso_on_his_art_and_freedom_of_expression" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<figure><caption>The painting of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikipedia">Wikipedia</ref> co-founder <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jimmy_Wales">Jimmy Wales</ref>, the uploading of which Wales called "harassment". 2013. Image: <ref target="http://www.pricasso.com/">Pricasso</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You painted a portrait of Wikipedia co-founder Jimmy Wales in 2013; a picture and a video file of the making of this painting were uploaded to Wikipedia's sister site for images and media, Wikimedia Commons. Shortly thereafter, the files were <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Commons:Deletion_requests/File:Jimmy_Wales_by_Pricasso.jpg">nominated for deletion and a deletion discussion ensued</ref> — what are your thoughts on this discussion?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Pricasso</hi>: I did not think Wikipedia censored anything as on Jimmy Wales' <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Twitter">Twitter</ref> account his banner heading is: "Wikia guy. Free speech activist, entrepreneur." Either this is misleading in the very least or blatantly untrue. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> The deletion discussion at Wikimedia Commons resulted in keeping the photograph of your portrait of Jimmy Wales, but deleting the video of your making-of-the-portrait — do you consider a video of your portrait painting to be offensive?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Pricasso</hi>: Not in the least; it's pure <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/performance%20art">performance art</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> During the deletion discussion, Jimmy Wales commented <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User_talk:Jimbo_Wales?diff=prev&amp;oldid=560022997">"I encourage people to go to commons and work to explain to the community there some of the concepts behind Hostile environment sexual harrassment. I encourage everyone to seriously consider whether it is appropriate behavior to upload a clearly non-notable film of someone using his penis to paint a picture of a Wikipedia volunteer. It is harassment, it is trolling, and I am deeply disappointed to have to point this out to some people."</ref></hi> What do you think of his response to your artwork? Do you feel your paintings constitute harassment?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Pricasso</hi>: Harassment is when one continually annoys someone, over and over again; I only painted the one painting of him and it to my mind was not offensive, I consider my work as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/satire">satire</ref> just like late night TV, something that gives light relief to a serious subject. There are many examples of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/political%20cartoon">political cartoon</ref> images on Wikipedia, so why are they still up there or is it just the things Jimmy Wales doesn't like get taken down? By the way anyone who has not seen the offending Video can view it on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vimeo">Vimeo</ref> under Pricasso: http://vimeo.com/user10315938/review/68837137/893b31ca54</p>
<p>I paint about 1000 portraits a year and get paid by the sitters or a close friend of them to do so. I had a request to paint a portrait, to do [this] portrait of Jimmy Wales with a video of me painting, by <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Russavia">Russavia</ref> (who is an editor at Wikipedia), something I do all the time and I have great feedback as to how funny the videos are; I had no idea who Jimmy Wales was at the time of the request, but painted him only once so it can't be called Harassment. Is he just using his position of power to cut and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/censor">censor</ref> ... It took me a lot of effort and time to put this together so I was pretty upset. And would really like it to be republished next to the portrait as originally it was before Mr Wales had it removed.</p>
</text>
