<text id="autogum_academic_doc115" title="Quantifying the Sustainability of Products and Suppliers in Food Distribution Companies" shortTile="quantifying-sustainability" author="Marina Segura, Concepción Maroto, Baldomero Segura" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5875/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Results of Sustainable Supplier Evaluation: Comparing MAUT and PROMETHEE Approaches</head><head> 4.1. Criteria for Sustainable Supplier Evaluation of Fresh Fruits</head>
<p>
The performance of fresh food suppliers in supermarket chains depends on the quality of products provided by suppliers, in addition to other criteria needed to assess them from a sustainable perspective. In particular, the company assesses the fruit suppliers based on three main groups of criteria: logistic, commercial and “product quality”. Logistic criteria are stockout, rejections (in logistic platform), and service capability. Commercial criteria include product innovation, conflict resolution, collaboration, and administrative functions. The “product quality” that a company evaluates is a subjective assessment of product quality made by a manager, followed by withdrawal when food safety problems occur. These criteria have some weaknesses; for example, they do not consider objective measures of the quality of products, but only consider the judgements/opinions of managers about the general performance of suppliers with respect to this issue. The manager evaluations for all criteria are measured on a scale from zero to 10. The company wants to improve its procedure to assess the food safety of suppliers and this paper provides new criteria for this purpose. In addition, another shortcoming of the company procedure consists of not including environmental criteria, with the exception of environmental certification or HACCP implementation as a prerequisite. </p>

<p>Sustainability requires taking into account economic, environmental, and social factors. <figure>Figure 8</figure> presents a criteria hierarchy for sustainable supplier evaluation in fresh fruits that contributes significantly to both the literature and company management. To select the criteria, the authors have taken a literature review into account, as well as the results of a survey with managers of supermarket chains and interviews with experts. The survey included questions about the current system for evaluating fresh products and their suppliers and distinguished between criteria already applied and those that would be of interest to apply in the future. The criteria selection also considered the availability of reliable data in practice. The aggregated indicator of the quality of products provided by a supplier is the average of all product indicators from this supplier plus the standard deviation.  </p>

<p>Food safety is the most relevant criterion in food supply chain management. In general, food distribution companies qualify suppliers if they have food safety certifications. Nevertheless, from time to time crises arise due to food safety issues, which are difficult to manage by the companies affected and have great impacts from social and economic standpoints. Thus, the indicator of food safety from suppliers is measured through four sub criteria: food safety certification, withdrawal volume due to food safety issues, number of withdrawals, and withdrawals impact. If a supplier has at least one food safety certification, it receives the best value (100) in the evaluation table. When the supplier has HACCP implemented, the value is 50 and zero when it has neither of these options. HACCP implementation is necessary when the provider does not have any food safety certification. Withdrawal volume is expressed in percentage with respect to total quantity provided by the supplier. Finally, the following scale is used to assess the impact: none (100), low (75), medium (30), and high (0). </p>

<p>The model proposes as environmental criteria: environmental certification, product origin, and organic product. These criteria are qualitative, and are translated into numerical values for the multicriteria evaluation table as follows. If the supplier has environmental certification, the value assigned is 100 and is zero otherwise. The origin criterion distinguishes among local, national, or international sources (100, 75, 50). Organic products have better value than non-organic products, scoring 100 and 75, respectively. </p>

<p>The logistic criteria are the product number, product volume, stockout, rejection, and service capability. The number of varieties of yellow peach provided by a supplier is the number of products in this case study. All these data are quantitative and from databases of the company related to supplier performance in the logistic platform. Stockout and rejection criteria are measured in percentages over the quantity of product. The company monitors the degree of compliance with the day and time in order to measure the service capability of suppliers, which is the average of both percentages. </p>

<p>Finally, the commercial criteria group includes product innovation, conflict resolution, collaboration and administrative functions of suppliers. Managers of the company rate the supplier performance for these criteria using a scale from zero to ten. </p>

<p>Following the flowchart in <figure>Figure 1</figure>, the second step is to carry out the supplier evaluation taking into account the scores (indicators) of all products provided by each supplier, as well as other relevant supplier criteria for the company. <figure>Figure 8</figure> shows all criteria included in sustainable evaluation, as well as their weights, for applying MAUT and PROMETHEE.  </p>
</text>
