<text id="autogum_interview_doc310" title="part3_Interview with Sue Gardner of the Wikimedia Foundation" shortTile="partinterview-sue" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-19" dateModified="2012-01-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Sue_Gardner_of_the_Wikimedia_Foundation" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">SG:</hi>  The trouble for traditional media is, they don't own the rights to very much material. They operate inside a web of very complex agreements with multiple entities.  We used to joke at the CBC that the only thing we owned was nature documentaries. And even those didn't entirely belong to us. So they are very constrained.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Brian: For wikinews all they have to do is credit us with the story to comply with the license</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SG:</hi>  You mean, they can use your material if they credit you, yes?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Brian: Yes, a link to us would be nice too</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Matt: Yeah, as long as they state its CC-BY-2.5 and give our name, they can use it. Can users who have edited Wikinews be respected around real journalists? Will they be turned down because they have written for an online website like Wikinews, which is not particularly fond of the mainstream media, and not traditional media?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SG:</hi>  First, let me say that I don't think Wikinews and the traditional/mainstream media should consider themselves at all in opposition to each other. I think they can peacefully coexist. There are some things the mainstream media are very good at, and they are also (sometimes) happy to admit their faults. And yes, I think Wikinews writers can be respected by real journalists, because the work speaks for itself. The one major challenge to that would be the collaborative authorship issue. Because as in academia, authorship is significant for professional journalists, and so I think the idea that something was collaboratively authored is hard for traditional journalists to understand.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Matt: Although you have an account on the English wikinews (<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:SueGardner">User:SueGardner</ref>), you have never edited. One would assume that as a journalist you would use this project. Is there any main reason you don't edit here or do you just not have time?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SG:</hi>  I am just too busy. I think there are lots of people who can do as good or better a job than I could, of editing Wikinews. But I think I am the only person who is paid to be thinking about the organization as a whole all day every day - so that's what I do.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Matt: If you could interview anyone for Wikinews who would you like to interview?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SG:</hi>  Did you interview <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doris%20Lessing">Doris Lessing</ref>?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Brian: Not yet, although we reported on her though (see <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Doris_Lessing_wins_Nobel_Prize_for_Literature">Doris Lessing wins Nobel Prize for Literature</ref>)</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SG:</hi>  Okay. I read your Doris Lessing story, and I was thinking maybe someone had interviewed her later. For me personally, I would love to interview Doris Lessing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Dodge: Do you use Wikinews as a primary source for news, or do you use other mainstream sources, and then look to Wikinews?</hi></p>
</text>
