<text id="autogum_news_doc200" title="Civilians testify to Halliburton fraud, coercion" shortTile="civilians-testify" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-06-28" dateModified="2012-01-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Civilians_testify_to_Halliburton_fraud%2C_coercion" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Civilians testify to Halliburton fraud, coercion</head><p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews:2005/June/28">June 28</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews:2005">2005</ref></hi></p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Democratic%20Party">Democratic Party</ref> held a public committee, aired on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C-Span">C-SPAN 3</ref>, at which former civilian employees based in or administering operations in Iraq, testified to specific instances of waste, fraud, and other abuses and irregularities by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Halliburton">Halliburton</ref> and its subsidiary <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kellogg,%20Brown%20and%20Root">Kellogg, Brown and Root</ref> (KBR). </p>
<p>Allegations of fraud by Halliburton, specifically with regard to its operations in Iraq, have persisted since before the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraq%20War">Iraq War</ref>. The  associations between U.S. Vice President <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dick%20Cheney">Dick Cheney</ref> and Halliburton, have been the basis for repeated speculation over possible political improprieties and business <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/profiteering">profiteering</ref> from the war.</p>
<p>Among the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Senate">senators</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S.%20House%20of%20Representatives">representatives</ref> present at the hearing were <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byron%20Dorgan">Byron Dorgan</ref> (presiding), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry%20Waxman">Henry Waxman</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frank%20Lautenberg">Frank Lautenberg</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark%20Dayton">Mark Dayton</ref>. </p>
<p>Among those testifying were <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bunny%20Greenhouse">Bunny Greenhouse</ref>, former Chief Contracting Officer of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S.%20Army%20Corps%20of%20Engineers">U.S. Army Corps of Engineers</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rory%20Mayberry">Rory Mayberry</ref>, former Food Program Manager for Halliburton subsidiary, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allan%20Waller">Allan Waller</ref>, of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lloyd-Owen%20International">Lloyd-Owen International</ref> security and operations firm.</p>
<p>Greenhouse, who provided the bulk of testimony, spoke for several minutes about her involvement in the evaluation and crafting of government Army contracts, and how explaining how superiors undermined and dismissed her concerns of illegal business practices. "Ultimately my main concern  was the repeated insistence that the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/">Rio contract</ref> be awarded to KBR without competitive bidding," Greenhouse said. She testified to have been given misinformation in answer to her complaints, and being "overtly misled" by KBR managers.</p>
<p>Mayberry, still in Iraq, testified by video from questions prepared by the committee. He said that KBR routinely sold expired food rations to the Army. The interviewer asked, "Are you saying that Halliburton deliberately falsified the number of meals they prepared and then submitted false claims for reimbursement and that they did this to make up for past amounts auditors had disallowed?" Mayberry firmly answered "Yes." He said that serving expired food ration was "an everyday occurrence, sometimes every meal." He explained that Halliburton systematically overcharged for the number of meals as well, saying, "they were charging for 20,000 meals and they were only serving 10,000 meals." Dorgan later commented, "obviously there's no honor here, by a company that would serve outdated food to our troops in Iraq." </p>
<p>Mayberry also claimed would-be <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/whistleblower">whistleblowers</ref> were threatened "to be sent to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Falluja">Falluja</ref>" and other "places under fire" if they talked to media or governmental oversight officials. In 2003 and 2004, Falluja had been well known as dangerous for foreign troops and civilians. "I personally was sent to Falluja for three weeks. The manager told me that I was being sent away until the auditors were gone, because I had talked to the auditors," Mayberry said.</p>
<p>"The threat of being sent to a camp under fire was their way of keeping us quiet. The employees who talked to auditors were sent to camps under more fire than other camps, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Camp%20Anaconda">Anaconda</ref>." This report led Dorgan and others to voice considerable outrage that U.S. citizens would be personally threatened with harm for talking to oversight officials or media.</p>
<p>Allan Waller testified to specific examples of how KBR officials had conspired in blocking Lloyd-Owen fuel transports, and using other coercive means against its competitor. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/British">British</ref> Lloyd-Owen has a direct contract with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraqi%20government">Iraq government</ref> to provide <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/fuel">fuel</ref> to various parts of the country.</p>
<p>In his introductory remarks, Dorgan explained that Senate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Republican%20Party">Republicans</ref> had blocked or ignored any requests by Democrats to have a formal <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/bipartisanship">bipartisan</ref> hearing, resulting in the need for an independent committee.
</p>
</text>
