<text id="autogum_news_doc573" title="Wikinews interviews President of the International Brotherhood of Magicians" shortTile="wikinews-interviews" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-09-26" dateModified="2014-06-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_President_of_the_International_Brotherhood_of_Magicians" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews President of the International Brotherhood of Magicians</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 9, 2013</hi></p>
<figure><caption> File photo of magician David Gish displaying magic props for a young child. Image: Paul Budd.</caption></figure>
<p>October is National Magic Month in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> spoke with William Evans, president of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International%20Brotherhood%20of%20Magicians">International Brotherhood of Magicians</ref>, about the current state of magic and what its future looks like in the world of entertainment.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  For how long have you been involved in performing/studying magic?  </p>
<hi rend="bold">William Evans</hi>: Over 50 years.  I am 61 now so I really started when I was about 10 years old even though I had seen and worked with some basic tricks a few years earlier.  I remember going into Hollywood Magic and wanting that big red box with the dragons on it and I didn't even know what it did.  The magician behind the counter was wise enough not to sell it to me, but instead sold me two books which I still own today — "Scarne on Card Tricks" and "Scarne on Magic Tricks".  That started me out on books and I have amassed quite a few since then.  My major influences on performance are <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eugene%20Burger">Eugene Burger</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael%20Skinner%20(magician)">Michael Skinner</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  October is National Magic Month in the US. Do you think magic is alive as a viable form of entertainment today?  </p>
<hi rend="bold">WE</hi>: Absolutely.  There are more magicians working today than ever before.  There will always be an audience for good magicians doing good magic.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Has the internet helped or hurt magic?  </p>
<hi rend="bold">WE</hi>: Both.  I think it has helped draw younger people to magic as a hobby, but I think it has hurt the ability of young magicians to think because so many rely on the internet for everything and they aren't reading the books.  We have to have knowledge of the history of magic and what has been done before.  Moreover, seeing someone perform on the internet takes away the use of our senses, originality and imagination that reading and thinking about magic can produce.  Anyone can become a monkey; it takes serious study to become a magician.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Do you travel much in your current role?  </p>
<hi rend="bold">WE</hi>: Yes, I am traveling quite a bit.  After I was inducted as International President in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Phoenix,_Arizona">Phoenix</ref> in July, I have been to the Jeff McBride Experience in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eureka%20Springs,%20Arkansas">Eureka Springs</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Arkansas">Arkansas</ref>, Magic Live in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Las_Vegas">Las Vegas</ref>, The Midwest Magic Jubilee in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St.%20Louis">St. Louis</ref>, the TAOM in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dallas">Dallas</ref>, the British Ring Convention in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buxton">Buxton</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/England">England</ref> and the Magic Circle in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/London">London</ref>.  I am going to Las Vegas and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Los_Angeles">Los Angeles</ref> next month, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Italy">Italy</ref> in November, back to Las Vegas in December, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mexico">Mexico</ref> in January, Magi-Fest in February, the Winter Carnival of Magic in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tennessee">Tennessee</ref> in March, Eureka Springs Cavalcade of Magic in March, and the FFFF in April.  That's as of now.
</text>
