<text id="autogum_bio_doc304" title="Yeğen Osman Pasha" shortTile="yegen-osman-pasha" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-11-27" dateModified="2019-06-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ye%C4%9Fen_Osman_Pasha" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Yeğen Osman Pasha</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Yeğen Osman Pasha</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Yeğen Osman Aga</hi> was 17th-century <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman</ref> military officer of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Armenians_in_the_Ottoman_Empire">Armenian</ref> origin.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-umetnosti1950-1">[1]</ref> After being commander of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sekban">sekban</ref> (peasant mercenaries) units in Anatolia, he was appointed first to position of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sanjakbey">sanjakbey</ref> and serçeşme of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sanjak_of_Karahisar-i_Sahib">Sanjak of Karahisar-i Sahib</ref>. In 1687 for a couple of months he was also the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beylerbey">beylerbey</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rumelia_Eyalet">Rumelia Eyalet</ref>, which was the highest position he held.</p>
<head>Career</head>
<head>Reign of Mehmed IV</head>
<p>Yeğen Osman was commander of all Anatolian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sekbans">sekbans</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Somel2010-2">[2]</ref> Rivalries between the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Janissaries">janissaries</ref> and the sekbans ultimately resulted in a rebellion.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-İnalcıkQuataert1997-3">[3]</ref> After the janissaries had been defeated on the Rumelian front, they marched on Istanbul in 1687 to depose <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mehmed_IV">Mehmed IV</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-İnalcıkQuataert1997-3">[3]</ref> The latter took actıon to marry his daughter to Yeğen Osman and appointed him to hold the janissaries in check.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEStanojević197679-4">[4]</ref> In 1687 Yeğen Osman was appointed as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sanjakbey">sanjakbey</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sanjak_of_Karahisar-i_Sahib">Sanjak of Karahisar-i Sahib</ref> in exchange for providing support to the sultan with 5,000 of his men. At his insistence, he was also appointed as security chief (<hi rend="italic">serçeşme</hi>) of this province. Instead to bring his forces to the front, by the middle of May 1687 he brought around 4,000 men to Istanbul and instead to defeat forces that threaten the sultan, they actually additionally threaten him.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Murphey2006-5">[5]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Kasaba2009-6">[6]</ref> Only 1,500 of his men were sent to the front at the end of June. To satisfy appetites of ambitious Yeğen Osman and win his support the sultan made him beylerbey of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rumelia_Eyalet">Rumelia Eyalet</ref> with seat in Sofia<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTE19687-7">[7]</ref> and responsible for exceptionally important front toward <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holy_League_(1684)">Holy League</ref>. Yeğen Osman <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> remained on the position until 1689 and treated the territories he controlled as his personal fiefdom.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-İnalcıkQuataert1997-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Schmitt2009-8">[8]</ref> He increased taxes to unbearable level to earn as much money as possible for himself, though he regularly denied this when he was faced with criticism.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETomić190228-9">[9]</ref></p>
<head>Reign of Suleyman II</head>
<head>Rebellion</head>
<p>Mehmed IV to be succeeded by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suleyman_II">Suleyman II</ref> who continued the policy of his predecessor towards sekbans. Yeğen Osman, as Rumelian beylerbey, rebelled against new sultan and became the main enemy of the Ottoman government. All dissatisfied sekbans gathered around him, including many from Anatolia. The sultan offered him the position of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serasker">serasker</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Timișoara">Timișoara</ref>, but he refused. Sultan appointed him as sanjakbey of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sanjak_of_Bosnia">Sanjak of Bosnia</ref> and Yeğen's uncle as sanjakbey of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sanjak_of_Herzegovina">Sanjak of Herzegovina</ref>, but this did not satisfy his ambitions so his forces of 10,000 men continued to plunder the territories under his control, including the Ottoman Serbia and Greece.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEStanojević197681-10">[10]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEumetnosti1950391-11">[11]</ref> According to some sources, Yeğen Osman had more money than Ottoman treasury.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEumetnosti1950391-11">[11]</ref></p>
<p>In 1688 his forces, notorious because of the robbing of the population, robbed the treasury of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serbian_Patriarchate_of_Peć">Serbian Patriarchate of Peć</ref> hidden in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gračanica_monastery">Gračanica monastery</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEStanojević197696-12">[12]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESamardžić1981544-13">[13]</ref> According to one letter written by Catholic bishop <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Bogdani">Peter Bogdani</ref>, Yeğen Osman Pasha threatened to cut off the head of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serbian_Patriarch">Archbishop of Peć and Serbian Patriarch</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arsenije_III_Crnojević">Arsenije III Crnojević</ref> because he received money from Austrians to instigate anti-Ottoman rebellion of Orthodox Serbs.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTE1993507-14">[14]</ref></p>
<p>To bring Yeğen Osman to heels new sultan appointed Yeğen Osman on the position of governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Belgrade">Belgrade</ref> in 1688.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Wilson2002-15">[15]</ref> This appointment angered Yeğen Osman, because this position was subordinated to Ottoman <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serdar_(Ottoman_rank)">serdar</ref> of Hungary, Hasan Pasha. He insisted that his new position would not make him subordinated to Ottoman serdar of Hungary, nor porte itself. The struggle over position of serdar of Hungary caused deep hatred between Hasan Pasha and Yeğen Osman.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEInstitute1992115-16">[16]</ref> When Yeğen Osman went to Belgrade with his forces he forcefully deposed Hasan Pasha by capturing his camp on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vračar">Vračar</ref> hill and putting him into prison.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTE1992108-17">[17]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEInstitute1992115-16">[16]</ref></p>
<head>Siege of Belgrade 1688</head>
<figure><caption>Siege of Belgrade in 1688</caption></figure>
Main article: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siege_of_Belgrade_(1688)">Siege of Belgrade (1688)</ref>
<p>When the Holy Roman Empire forces <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siege_of_Belgrade_(1688)">besieged Belgrade</ref> in 1688, the emperor sent a letter to Yeğen Osman and offered him Wallachia to desert Ottomans and switch to their side.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTE1992108-17">[17]</ref> Since Yeğen Osman requested all of Slavonia and Bosnia, they did not make an agreement.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTERadonić1955102-18">[18]</ref> Austrians positioned ponton bridges near Ostružnica and crossed Sava with 10,000 forces. Yeğen Osman attacked them with bulk of his forces, but Austrians repelled his two attacks, captured more land on the right bank of Sava and brought additional forces.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEPaunović1968193-19">[19]</ref></p>
<p>When Yeğen Osman realized that his forces were outnumbered, he burned his camp and both Serb populated Belgrade suburbs on Sava and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Danube">Danube</ref>. He then retreated to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smederevo">Smederevo</ref> where he spent two days looting and burning it. Yeğen Osman left Smederevo and went to Niš via Smederevska Palanka.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEStanojević1976103-20">[20]</ref> From Niš he wrote to porte reports about the siege and requested military and financial support to defend Belgrade and to annihilate rebellious rayah. He explained that Belgrade will fall if his requests would not be met within ten days. Porte sent him 120 bags of gold and decided to mobilize Muslim population of Rumelia to deal with rebelled population of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Belgrade_pashalik">Belgrade pashalik</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMilić1983197-21">[21]</ref></p>
<head>Last years</head>
<p>Yeğen Osman, by then a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pasha">Pasha</ref>, then attempted to become <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grand_vizier">grand vizier</ref>.Although Yeğen Osman's ambition angered the other Ottoman statesmen they were reluctant to make an operation against Yeğen Osman for they were afraid of the  exaggerated power of Osman. However, in a war council in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edirne">Edirne</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Selim_I_Giray">Selim I Giray</ref>  the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crimean_khanate">Crimean khan</ref> and a vassal of the Ottoman Empire called the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Porte">Ottoman Porte</ref> to execute Osman <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-22">[22]</ref>
When this happened, the incumbent grand vizier outlawed the sekban corps, threatening soldiers who proved unwilling to disperse with execution, and a civil war ensued.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-İnalcıkQuataert1997-3">[3]</ref> The sekbans gained the upper hand, but a further volte-face of the Ottoman central administration saw Yeğen Osman be captured and executed. This did not end the sekban's rebellions, and while in 1698 the Sultan reached an agreement with the sekbans, extending them guarantees in return for future good behaviour, the agreement was rapidly broken, and sekban's rebellions continued throughout the 18th century.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-İnalcıkQuataert1997-3">[3]</ref></p>
</text>
