<text id="autogum_interview_doc208" title="part9_BDSM as business: Interviews with Dominatrixes" shortTile="partbdsm-business" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-28" dateModified="2008-01-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BDSM_as_business%3A_Interviews_with_Dominatrixes" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Can a person who has no experience really just jump into it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  No.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So I guess someone with some experience, because a person with no experience would probably fail utterly, right?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  Well, no.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  It depends, here.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  A lot of the time men like new fresh faces, so she’ll get picked for a session regardless of her experience level.  It’s not all about your expertise.  A lot of time they just want someone who looks a certain way.  It’s very visual for certain people.  So, if you are a black woman with a big ass and that’s what they came here for in looking for someone to dominate them.</p>
<head id="Strange_requests">Strange requests</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That was one of the things Jada and I were talking about earlier: if someone comes in and says, “Treat me like I’m a dirty Jew” or “Treat me like I’m a bad slave” is it difficult for you to bring yourself to that level?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  Yeah, I had a guy who wanted me to treat him like a slave and call him a nigger, and stuff like that.  It was difficult for me but I got over it.   I had to step back and look at it as someone’s fetish and whenever someone tries to get me to do something that is a little psychological and walks the line between being abused or not, I don’t try to judge their method for dealing with it.  I mean, that’s the way he is trying to deal with this, and there’s no research saying it is bad for him to explore that, or that it’s good.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You intellectualize it.  So you were able to treat him like a slave?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  Oh yes, I made him pick cotton off the floor…stuff like that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  I remember you telling me about that!</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  Yeah [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You made him pick cotton off the floor?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  Yeah, he was fun and he was so appreciative, and it really got me past my hang-up.  That was one psychological hurdle I overcame.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  A lot of times they know you may feel uncomfortable with it and they’ll understand.  Some of them will know you won’t like it but that you’ll try to do it anyway.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What if someone wanted to treat you that way?  If you were Jewish…</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  I can separate myself from that enough and see it as a game.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Yeah, I’d say the same thing</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  It’s not reality.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What is your ethnicity, Jada?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  I’m <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Puerto%20Rican">Puerto Rican</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So if someone wanted to treat you like a dirty <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wetback">wetback</ref>, you’d be able to go with that?</hi></p>
</text>
