<text id="autogum_academic_doc385" title="Does State-level Upgrade of High-tech Zones Promote Urban Innovation Efficiency: Evidence from China" shortTile="statelevel-upgrade" author="Qiong Wang, Ru Yang, Ruyue Zhao, Chengyuan Wang" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/6071/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Conclusions and Discussion</head>
<p>
Based on the panel data of Chinese prefecture-level cities from 2007 to 2015, taking the large-scale state-level upgrade of HIDZ in 2010 as a quasi-natural experiment, the paper uses the PSM-DID method to examine the impact of the upgraded state-level HIDZ on urban innovation efficiency and its dynamic effect. In addition, heterogeneity analysis based on the scientific research level of local higher education institutions in the cities is conducted. The conclusions are as follows: First, the upgraded state-level HIDZ has significantly promoted the urban innovation efficiency, the positive effect gradually being strengthened with the implementation of the state-level upgrade policy. Second, the higher the scientific research level of higher education institutions in the cities, the greater the positive policy effect of upgraded state-level HIDZ. </p>

<p>Urban innovation efficiency is an appropriate indicator to evaluate fulfillment of the state mission of state-level HIDZ. Compared to the born state-level HIDZ, the upgraded one faces more significant opportunities and challenges. Therefore, evaluating the policy effect of the upgraded state-level HIDZ from the perspective of urban innovation efficiency, the paper not only fills a gap left by previous studies which have focused mostly on the total or originally established state-level HIDZ, but also evaluates the state-level upgrade policy more accurately, thus providing more effective support for policy adjustment or optimization. </p>

<p>Conclusions of this paper offer two policy implications: First, the state-level upgrade policy of province-level HIDZ should be unswervingly implemented in China. Although the performance of the upgraded state-level HIDZ is weaker than the born ones due to many developmental challenges, their policy effect on urban innovation efficiency is a significant positive. Additional reasons include the following: On the one hand, the state-level upgrade is a strategic arrangement for optimizing the spatial layout of HIDZ, and it will help to speed up the development of cities with weaker growth (e.g., some resource-based cities, western cities, and other poor or border cities), thus promotes coordinated regional development. On the other hand, the state-level upgrade is also an incentive and “spur” for province-level HIDZ. Before the upgrade, the province-level HIDZ will be encouraged to make it eligible for state-level upgrading. After the upgrade, the upgraded state-level HIDZ will be spurred to grasp huge opportunities as they ensue, making good use of the latecomer’s advantages to fulfill the mission of leading innovation and promoting balanced development. </p>

<p>Second, the scientific research level of the higher education institutions in the cities should be considered in the development of the upgraded state-level HIDZ, as well as the qualification assessment of the province-level HIDZ to upgrade. On the one hand, for the existing upgraded state-level HIDZ, in addition to taking better advantage of the state-level identity based on their own characteristics, local governments should also pay attention to the cultivation of scientific research capabilities of higher education institutions in their cities. In this way, the innovative factors such as talents and achievements in scientific research will be continuously prepared for the upgraded state-level HIDZ to boost their real upgrade. On the other hand, for the province-level HIDZ who intends to apply for state-level upgrade in China, except for the economic performance and development potential, the scientific research level of the local higher education institutions should also be included in the evaluation criterion of the upgrade qualification. Thus, in order to upgrade the province-level HIDZ, the local governments would be motivated to raise the scientific research level of higher education institutions in the cities, and this will help to achieve a virtuous cycle of regional innovation and development. </p>

<p>There are also several limitations in the paper that future research can address. First, this paper’s focus is on the state-level upgrade of HIDZ in 2010, while there are more than 100 HIDZ that were upgraded in batches since 2009. Future research can further expand the sample to evaluate the policy effect comprehensively based on the data from all of the upgraded state-level HIDZ in China. Second, due to the problem of data availability, the paper does not conduct empirical examination on the mechanism of how the upgraded state-level HIDZ affects urban innovation efficiency. Future work can further optimize research design and provide empirical support for the impact mechanism. Finally, as elaborated in the report of the 19th National Congress of the Communist Party of China, it is necessary to build a coordinated pattern of regional development based on city clusters. Therefore, the policy effect of the establishment and upgrade of HIDZ can further be evaluated at the dimension of city clusters.
 </p>
</text>
