<text id="autogum_interview_doc585" title="part3_Wikinews interviews Australian Paralympic skiers Toby Kane, Cameron Rahles Rahbula, and Mitchell Gourley" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-12-10" dateModified="2014-05-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_Paralympic_skiers_Toby_Kane%2C_Cameron_Rahles_Rahbula%2C_and_Mitchell_Gourley" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  You mentioned Australia being like a country of summer sports. What attracted you to winter sport in the first place?</p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Mitchell Gourley:</hi> I think it's a better sport. (laughter)</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Cameron Rahles-Rahbula:</hi> Australians, considering we don't have many hills, Australians do love skiing, those that do it. It's a unique sport in the sense that you get to travel at high speeds, on different mountains all over the world, under your own power, going down a hill at 130 or something <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/kilometer">k's</ref> an hour, that sort of thing. You don't get... to me, running up and down a track, or...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Toby Kane:</hi> I think to me it's a fun sport. There aren't that many sports that people, a lot of people, spend <hi rend="italic">heaps</hi> of their own money to go and do, as a pastime. As something that they want to do on the holidays and with their family and all that kind of stuff. It's kind of cool that that's what we do. Like, lots of people would spend a sh-tload of money to go skiing, and that's our sport. Not many people would pay a heap of money to stare at a black line in a pool, or to run around a track against the clock.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Cameron Rahles-Rahbula:</hi> Yeah, we love it, and that's why I've done it for so many years, because I love the sport. I mean, racing's one thing but if I didn't enjoy skiing I wouldn't be here and there's not a day when... I mean you have cold days and weather and stuff, but you don't... for us to get out and get on the hill isn't a burden I don't think in the same way as other sports can be.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Toby Kane:</hi> I think the change for me — I think I can speak for Cam as well, 'cause he's been around for a while — the change between racing in so many classes to racing in so few probably kept us around, I think. It made it a lot more competitive; it made it a lot more of a challenge, that previously it wouldn't have been, and I think if we took an LW2 class right now we'd be getting similar results to what Michael got in Salt Lake City, so, the fact that it did get a lot more competitive is probably why I've been here for so long, in the challenge to keep competing and keep improving and keep performing at the highest level.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Are there any skiers that you're looking forward to racing against this week coming up? </p>
</text>
