<text id="autogum_whow_doc343" title="Prepare for Herniated Disk Surgery" shortTile="prepare-herniated" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-04-12" dateModified="2019-06-27" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Prepare-for-Herniated-Disk-Surgery" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Prepare for Herniated Disk Surgery</head><p>A herniated disk occurs when the cushion between your vertebrae begins to wear down. Instead of acting as a cushion, the vertebrae can actually press on nerves, resulting in pain. Surgery is necessary for a herniated disk if other methods to relieve the back pain do not work. Preparing for herniated disk surgery is largely a matter of knowing what to expect.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Undergo a physical exam and complete any tests deemed necessary by your doctor -- possibly a urine sample and an X-ray. You'll also need to supply your medical history. Make sure to note any allergies you have. <figure rend="Prepare for Herniated Disk Surgery Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Ask your doctor questions you have in regards to your herniated disk surgery and fully research the procedure. There are three common types of herniated disc surgery: laminectomy, corpectomy, and anterior cervical discectomy and fusion. <figure rend="Prepare for Herniated Disk Surgery Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Eat fruits and vegetables, and drink plenty of water in the days and weeks leading up to your herniated disk surgery. Adequate hydration will help your body before and after surgery, so aim for 10 glasses of water per day. <figure rend="Prepare for Herniated Disk Surgery Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take time to rest and relax prior to your herniated disk surgery. Seek help around the house with any chores so you don't re-injure your back prior to surgery. <figure rend="Prepare for Herniated Disk Surgery Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Stop smoking. Smoking can cause surgery complications and can lengthen your healing time. Some doctors recommend quitting 6 to 8 weeks prior to surgery, while others only insist on no cigarettes for 24 hours prior to surgery. Check with your doctor on this issue. <figure rend="Prepare for Herniated Disk Surgery Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Follow the pre-surgery guidelines as given to you by your doctor. Instructions may include what to eat and drink, as well as whether you're allowed to take any medications or supplements prior to surgery. <figure rend="Prepare for Herniated Disk Surgery Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Your doctor may require that you only consume clear liquids for several days prior to surgery or may restrict your diet in other ways for 12 to 24 hours prior to surgery.</item></list></item>
<item>Plan ahead for an overnight stay at the hospital. It's not required in all cases, but you make proper arrangements ahead of time just in case. <figure rend="Prepare for Herniated Disk Surgery Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Plan for your recovery at home following your herniated disk surgery. You won't be able to drive, so find a ride home from the hospital. You may also want someone around to help you at home as you recover. Total recovery time should take 6 to 8 weeks. <figure rend="Prepare for Herniated Disk Surgery Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Expect to take time off work as you recover. The amount of time will depend on how your recovery is progressing. However, you must wait about 6 weeks to do anything other than desk work. <figure rend="Prepare for Herniated Disk Surgery Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make contact with a physical therapist and set up appointments for after your surgery while you are recovering at home. <figure rend="Prepare for Herniated Disk Surgery Step 10.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Find out how much the procedure will cost and what your insurance will cover. Make sure you are pre-certified through your insurance carrier before your herniated disk procedure. You may be able to pay the surgery center over time.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Repairing a herniated disc may require more than one surgery.</item></list>
</text>
