<text id="autogum_bio_doc013" title="Lício Velloso" shortTile="licio-velloso" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2019-06-05" dateModified="2019-06-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/L%C3%ADcio_Velloso" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Lício Velloso</head><p><hi rend="bold">Licio Augusto Velloso</hi> is a Brazilian full professor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Medicine">medicine</ref> at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Campinas">University of Campinas</ref>.</p>
<head>Education</head>
<p>Lício Velloso obtained his MD degree in 1986 from the University of Campinas. He then attended <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uppsala_University">Uppsala University</ref> in Sweden from which he graduated in 1993 and then served as a postdoc at the Mario Saad Lab, University of Campinas and at the Ron Kahn Lab, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harvard_University">Harvard University</ref> in 1994 and 1995 respectively.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> He also was postdoctoral <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fellow">fellow</ref> at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joslin_Diabetes_Center">Joslin Diabetes Center</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> and is coordinator of the Obesity and Comorbidities Research Center at the University of Campinas.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-rdmag-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Research</head>
<p>In 2001 he studied type 2 diabetes along with Claudio Teodoro de Souza, a back-then Ph.D. student at the Cell Signaling Laboratory. Their study revealed that the disease reoccurs when <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pancreas">pancreas</ref> fail to supply the peripheral need for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Insulin">insulin</ref> that the body needs. According to Lício Velloso, as long as the pancreas can produce insulin to maintain this need, the blood glucose level remains stable - close to 80, 90, expected for a healthy person. But, when it does fail, the glucose rises, which makes a patient dependent on insulin. This dependency can result into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyperinsulinemic_hypoglycemia">hyperinsulinemic hypoglycemia</ref>, according to Velloso. Under Velloso's guidance, Souza had studied alpha protein and injected it with an insulin-producing cell. While the result didn't yield a major breakthrough, it opened a possibility of developing a drug that would reduce the action of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PPARGC1A">PPARGC1A</ref>. During the trials, which the duo conducted revealed that it does indeed reduces the production of alpha protein while increases insulin production. Not only did it increase insulin production, but it also decrease diabetes occurrence.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>For two years, he and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marciane_Milanski">Marciane Milanski</ref>, a nutritionist, had studied <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Obesity">obesity</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rat">rats</ref>. During the study, it was suggested that it is possible to make brain control liver in order to maintain glycemic balance. When it does happen, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hypothalamus">hypothalamus</ref> becomes the main actor of this mechanism. The research, along with his comment: "The mechanism described by this research shows that control of high glucose in fasting is done, at least in part, by the hypothalamus. This reinforces our suspicion that the development of drugs with action in the central nervous system should be interesting for the treatment of diabetes" were published in the <hi rend="italic">American Journal of Deabetes</hi> in 2012.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>From 2005 to 2007 he had studied human diet, and, according to him, the studies of various groups have shown that a diet rich in simple <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carbohydrates">carbohydrates</ref>, can also increase <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lipid">lipid</ref> levels in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blood">blood</ref> and indirectly promote <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inflammation">inflammation</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hypothalamus">hypothalamus</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-rdmag-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>In 2018 Lício Velloso studied hunger strikes and divided them in three categories: Absolute, total and partial. During the study, he suggested that people who do partial hunger strikes could have more severe consequences then those that have the absolute one. For example, in an absolute strike only <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kidney">kidneys</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heart">heart</ref> fails after 25 days of being on a strike, while strikers who preferred partial ended up with liver complications within 40 to 50 days after the strike. In conclusion, what Dr. Velloso suggests is that people who have a weak heart shouldn't take too much liquid, otherwise it can lead to heart failure and even death.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>On October 30, 2018 he appeared on an interview with Paulo Saldiva of Science and Health program of the Futura Chanel.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<head>Editorial work</head>
<p>He is a former member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Editorial_board">editorial board</ref> of <hi rend="italic">Clinical Endocrinology</hi> and current member of the editorial board of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Journal_of_Obesity">International Journal of Obesity</ref></hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
</text>
