<text id="autogum_interview_doc755" title="part1_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Progressive Conservative candidate Jim Chapman, London-Fanshawe" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-25" dateModified="2007-11-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Progressive_Conservative_candidate_Jim_Chapman%2C_London-Fanshawe" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>The continuing decline in health care delivery is number one on my list, and at the doors. People are also very concerned about job losses in the riding, and the perception that our streets are no longer safe. These, too, parallel my own priorities.</p>
<p>Improving all of them will require the same first step- we must regain control of public spending, institute strict financial controls on every ministry and require public servants to account for every penny of public money they spend.</p>
<p>With a provincial budget that has increased by a third in four years, there is plenty of money flowing through Queen's Park, The challenge is to direct it where it will do the most good for the most people.</p>
<p>Regarding my three priorities, a greatly oversimplified "to do" list would include involving front-line nurses and doctors much more actively in health care delivery reform, reducing red tape to create an environment that attracts more job-producing investment, and bringing the justice system more in line with the wishes of the people by advocating tougher treatment for crimes of violence and tighter bail for potentially dangerous offenders.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly?</hi></p>
<p>Financial reform, as outlined above.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are the property taxes in your riding at a fair level for the amount of services received in the municipality?</hi></p>
<p>No. Provincial downloading and contentious local policies have seen costs rise much faster than service levels.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How can the province lead the way in stimulating job creation?</hi></p>
<p>As above, by creating an environment that is more conducive to attracting job-creating investment. Having the highest tax rates in Canada and one of the most cumbersome economic bureaucracies is not a combination likely to bring new jobs to Ontario. That must change.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What are your views on the mixed member proportional representation (MMP) referendum?</hi></p>
<p>While I understand the concerns with the existing system that led to the referendum, any system that proposes appointing rather than electing members of the legislature does not get my support.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What role, if any, does "new media" play in your campaign, and the campaign of your party? (websites, blogs, Facebook, YouTube videos, etc) Do you view it as beneficial, or a challenge?</hi></p>
<p>Utilizing new technologies beneficially is always a challenge, but in this election they have allowed me to reach more people, more directly, through a website, YouTube videos and hundreds of e-mails back and forth with constituents.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Of the decisions made by Ontario 's 38th Legislative Assembly, which was the most beneficial to your this electoral district? To the province as a whole? Which was least beneficial, or even harmful, to your this riding? To the province as a whole?</hi></p>
</text>
