<text id="autogum_interview_doc767" title="part0_Keep your eyes peeled for cosmic debris: Andrew Westphal about Stardust@home" shortTile="partkeep-eyes-peeled" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-05-18" dateModified="2015-10-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Keep_your_eyes_peeled_for_cosmic_debris%3A_Andrew_Westphal_about_Stardust%40home" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Keep your eyes peeled for cosmic debris: Andrew Westphal about Stardust@home</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, May 28, 2006</hi></p>
<p>Stardust is a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NASA">NASA</ref> space capsule that collected samples from comet <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/81P/Wild">81P/Wild</ref> (also known as "Wild 2) in deep space and landed back on Earth on January 15, 2006. It was decided that a collaborative online review process would be used to "discover" the microscopically small samples the capsule collected. The project is called <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Stardust@home">Stardust@home</ref>. Unlike <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/distributed%20computing">distributed computing</ref> projects like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SETI@home">SETI@home</ref>, Stardust@home relies entirely on human intelligence.</p>
<p>Andrew Westphal is the director of Stardust@home. Wikinews interviewed him for May's Interview of the Month (IOTM) on May 18, 2006. As always, the interview was conducted on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IRC">IRC</ref>, with multiple people asking questions.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold"> Some may not know exactly what Stardust or Stardust@home is. Can you explain more about it for us?</hi></p>
<p>Stardust is a NASA Discovery mission that was launched in 1999. It is really two missions in one. The primary science goal of the mission was to collect a sample from a known primitive solar-system body, a comet called Wild 2 (pronounced "Vilt-two" — the discoverer was German, I believe). This is the first <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US">US</ref> "sample return" mission since <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Apollo_program">Apollo</ref>, and the first ever from beyond the moon. This gives a little context. By "sample return" of course I mean a mission that brings back extraterrestrial material. I should have said above that this is the first "solid" sample return mission — Genesis brought back a sample from the Sun almost two years ago, but Stardust is also bringing back the first solid samples from the local interstellar medium — basically this is a sample of the Galaxy. This is absolutely unprecedented, and we're obviously incredibly excited. I should mention parenthetically that there is a fantastic launch video — taken from the POV of the rocket on the JPL Stardust website — highly recommended — best I've ever seen — all the way from the launch pad, too. Basically interplanetary trajectory. Absolutely great. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Is the video available to the public?</hi></p>
<p>Yes [see <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Main_Page#External_links">below</ref>]. OK, I digress. The first challenge that we have before can do any kind of analysis of these interstellar dust particles is simply to find them. This is a big challenge because they are very small (order of micron in size) and are somewhere (we don't know where) on a HUGE collector— at least on the scale of the particle size — about a tenth of a square meter. <hi rend="italic">So</hi>...</p>
<p>We're right now using an automated microscope that we developed several years ago for nuclear astrophysics work to scan the collector in the Cosmic Dust Lab in Building 31 at Johnson Space Center. This is the ARES group that handles returned samples (Moon Rocks, Genesis chips, Meteorites, and Interplanetary Dust Particles collected by U2 in the stratosphere). The microscope collects stacks of digital images of the aerogel collectors in the array. These images are sent to us — we compress them and convert them into a format appropriate for Stardust@home. </p>
</text>
