<text id="autogum_interview_doc876" title="part1_Author Amy Scobee recounts abuse as Scientology executive" shortTile="partauthor-amy-scobee" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-10-11" dateModified="2015-12-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Author_Amy_Scobee_recounts_abuse_as_Scientology_executive" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Prior to her book's publication, Scobee was threatened with legal action, in a letter from a lawyer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bertram%20Fields">Bertram Fields</ref> representing influential Scientology member and celebrity, actor <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tom_Cruise">Tom Cruise</ref>. Separately, Scientology representative <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tommy%20Davis%20(Scientology)">Tommy Davis</ref> stated the organization was also preparing a lawsuit against her related to the publication of her book. Further news about such threatened lawsuits have not been forthcoming following these statements from Tom Cruise's lawyer and Scientology's spokesman.</p>
<p>After Scobee began to speak out critically about Scientology to the <hi rend="italic">St. Petersburg Times</hi>, the Scientology <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/propaganda">propaganda</ref> publication <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freedom%20Magazine">Freedom Magazine</ref></hi> issued a publication in which it referred to her repeatedly as "The Adulteress". Though Scobee had thought that statements she made during Scientology counseling sessions called "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Auditing%20(Scientology)">Auditing</ref>" were to be kept confidential under priest-penitent religious privilege, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BBC_News">BBC News</ref> reported that "intimate details of her sex life" were forwarded by Scientology, to the <hi rend="italic">St. Petersburg Times</hi>. BBC News reported that during an interview for the <hi rend="italic">Panorama</hi> program, Scobee was photographed by agents for Scientology along with journalist John Sweeney. These photographs were then sent by Scientology UK lawyers from the firm Carter-Ruck to the BBC, in an attempt to show "bias" of journalist Sweeney towards Scobee in his interviewing.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Scientology - Abuse at the Top</hi> received a favorable reception from reviews and media coverage. <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/All%20Headline%20News">All Headline News</ref></hi> characterized it as a "tell-all book" about Scientology. Scobee's account has also received positive reception in coverage from <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Today%20Tonight">Today Tonight</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drew%20Marshall">The Drew Marshall Show</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lateline">Lateline</ref></hi>, and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Panorama%20(TV%20series)">Panorama</ref></hi>.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> How did you first get involved with Scientology?</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Amy Scobee in 2007 Image: <ref target="http://www.scobeepublishing.com/">Amy Scobee</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amy Scobee</hi>: I was 14 years old. My parents had recently divorced and my mother took custody of me and my older brother. The three of us moved 30 miles north to the Seattle area and my mother started working as a draftsman at a company near by. My brother and I would go to school during the day and spend the evenings with our mom. We’d visit my father on the weekends. I was beginning to get used to this routine when suddenly my mother was no longer spending the evenings with us. Instead, she began attending classes after work at the local Church of Scientology.</p>
<p>One day I was home alone and the phone rang. It was a staff member from the church named Brett. I told him that my mom wasn’t home. He said that he was actually calling to talk to me. He said that he heard I was a very nice person and that I should come into the church to do an introductory service myself. I remember becoming very curious about this. I recall thinking, "Even though I’m just a kid, these guys are interested in me!" That somehow made me feel recognized and important.</p>
</text>
