<text id="autogum_interview_doc886" title="part11_Author Amy Scobee recounts abuse as Scientology executive" shortTile="partauthor-amy-scobee" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-10-11" dateModified="2015-12-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Author_Amy_Scobee_recounts_abuse_as_Scientology_executive" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">AS</hi>: I did video recorded interviews with several Scientologists – they didn't know what the interviews were for. I told them that I was doing a project, had some questions and at some point may possibly get back to them. I asked them questions about themselves, their skills, where they stood on Scientology training and counseling, etc. I then weeded out the ones that I didn't think would be appropriate for the personal staff of Tom Cruise and for those who seemed promising, I compiled their video with contact information and sent it to Shelly Miscavige. She would forward to Andrea (TC's Assistant at the time) any she thought were good. Andrea would then contact them for an interview directly. This continued until they had Scientologists selected for all of the key functions of the Cruise household (chef, nanny, Executive Housekeeper, etc.). Up to that point, several of those functions had been being done by Sea Org members (the specifics on this are covered in my book). Once they were hired by TC, they reported to him or his Assistant for their work assignments, not to the Scientology organization to my knowledge.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> After being appointed in October 1991 as the "Watchdog Committee member over the Celebrity Centre sector", you recall meeting several members of "the top Scientology celebrity public", including <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Travolta">John Travolta</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kelly%20Preston">Kelly Preston</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kirstie%20Alley">Kirstie Alley</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anne%20Archer">Anne Archer</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nancy%20Cartwright">Nancy Cartwright</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Billy%20Sheehan">Billy Sheehan</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Priscilla%20Presley">Priscilla Presley</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lisa%20Marie%20Presley">Lisa Marie Presley</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juliette%20Lewis">Juliette Lewis</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Isaac_Hayes">Isaac Hayes</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tom_Cruise">Tom Cruise</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edgar%20Winter">Edgar Winter</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jenna%20Elfman">Jenna Elfman</ref>. In what capacity did you meet these Scientology celebrities? Were they coming in for Scientology auditing, or counseling? Did they receive advice and assistance in some form with their professional careers?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS</hi>: While I was working on the project to build Celebrity Centre International in Hollywood, I was often in the President's office of the Celebrity Center where the top celebrities often would come. That's how I met most of them. They would come into Celebrity Center to attend a course, to go in for a counseling session or to bring someone new in to introduce them to Scientology. Celebrity Centre International has a "career counseling" service it does provide and some celebrities have done this service to hopefully help them to do better in their careers.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You write that you are aware of situations where members of Scientology hired by celebrities as assistants or security staff, have actually reported back to the organization through a Scientology process called "Security Checks", with revealing information about those celebrities. Did any of these celebrities ever find out such a tactic was being used to uncover information about them? If so, what was their response to this?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS</hi>: No, not to my knowledge.</p>
</text>
