<text id="autogum_interview_doc476" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Australian Paralympic wheelchair basketballer Shelley Chaplin" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-01-03" dateModified="2014-06-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_Paralympic_wheelchair_basketballer_Shelley_Chaplin" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Australian Paralympic wheelchair basketballer Shelley Chaplin</head>
 This article mentions the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Foundation">Wikimedia Foundation</ref>, one of its projects, or people related to it. <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> is a project of the Wikimedia Foundation.
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday, January 4, 2013</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Listen to this interview.</caption></figure>
<figure rend="140611 - Shelley Chaplin - 3b - 2012 Team processing.jpg"></figure> Recently, <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> spent time with with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australian">Australian</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Paralympics">Paralympic</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wheelchair_basketball">wheelchair basketballer</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Shelley_Chaplin">Shelley Chaplin</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Interview with Shelley Chaplin. First of all, what position do you play?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> Usually a point guard.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Right. And whenever I go to see the basketball in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canberra">Canberra</ref>, we pass by a glass case. In the case is a guernsey with number twelve on it, and a big sign that says that this was the guernsey worn by Shelley Chaplin...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> That's me! That's my...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  It's signed by the rest of the team, if you look — press your nose to the glass and look really close. How did that come to be there?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> It's actually the singlet that I wore in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2008_Summer_Paralympics">Beijing</ref>. Usually you get people to sign stuff. Anyway, the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australian_Institute_of_Sport">AIS</ref> just asked everybody if we would donate something [...]. I wasn't using it so, yeah, I gave them that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Oh okay.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> I don't think they have it... It's been there for a while now. It think that was a four year loan or something like that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I think it's been there for longer than that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> It's been there for longer than that. Or — it must be four years around about now. Went in just after Beijing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  So they'll return that to you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> They'll return it at some point. I mean, I like it. It's nice to have it there. It's good that they have some stuff from wheelchair basketball there, and I don't need it, so, yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How did you get into playing wheelchair basketball? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> After the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1996%20Summer%20Paralympics">Atlanta Paralympics</ref> actually. There was a welcome home parade in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Melbourne">Melbourne</ref>. So I never knew anything about wheelchair sports before that. And I went to the parade, and I used to walk around, but that day I used a wheelchair because I was really tired, and someone just approached me and said "Hey, do you know anything about wheelchair sports? You should get involved!" And, yeah, so I did! I tried everything, and I liked basketball the most.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  And you're a three point player?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> Three point five.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I'd never seen the game before. My first experience of it was when the Gliders came out on the court for that first game [in London], and I was really taken with the sport from the word go. It has a sort of grace that normal basketball lacks. But otherwise it's very similar.</p>
</text>
