<text id="autogum_news_doc097" title="China offers Africa financial aid including $10 billion in loans" shortTile="china-offers-africa" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-11-08" dateModified="2014-12-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China_offers_Africa_financial_aid_including_%2410_billion_in_loans" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>China offers Africa financial aid including $10 billion in loans</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, November 8, 2009</hi> </p><figure><caption>Members of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Forum%20on%20China-Africa%20Cooperation">FOCAC</ref>Image: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Wangyunfeng">Wangyunfeng</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China">China</ref> has offered <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Africa">Africa</ref> concessional loans worth <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_dollar">US$</ref>10 (<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Euro">€</ref>6.5) billion as part of a host of new measures aimed at improving the economy of African nations. The announcement was made at the opening of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Forum%20on%20China-Africa%20Cooperation">Forum on China-Africa Cooperation</ref> (FOCAC) in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sharm%20el-Sheikh">Sharm el-Sheikh</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Egypt">Egypt</ref>. Leaders of nearly 50 African countries are attending the two-day conference. </p>
<p>China had already stated today at the 3rd Conference of Chinese and African Entrepreneurs, held immediately before the FOCAC, that Chinese firms would be encouraged to invest in Africa, while both sides would work together to improve the tourism, telecommunications and finance industries. China also said that governments should work with businesses to ensure co-operation between China and Africa.</p>
<p>As well as the loans, made over three years, China will write off the debt of Africa's poorest countries, build 100 African green energy facilities and systematically lower import duties on 95% of all African products exported to China. Another promise is a loan of one billion dollars aimed at small and medium sized businesses in Africa. There will also be efforts to promote each other's culture and increased medical assistance to Africa. Medical assistance comes in the form of 500 million <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chinese%20yuan">yuan</ref> (US$73.2 million) of goods for the 60 hospitals and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Malaria">malaria</ref> centers China has already built, as well as 3,000 doctors and nurses. Roads will also be improved.</p>
<p>China also plans to assist with satellite weather monitoring, to help combat desertification and work within the urban environment, all aimed at reducing global warming. The new energy facilities will focus on solar, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/biogas">biogas</ref> and small-scale hydroelectrical installations. Another new measure is a promise to aid African farmers to ensure the continent is fed, increasing the number of demonstrations of agricultural technology in Africa to 20 and sending 50 teams of agricultural technology experts to the continent. Training in agricultural technology will be provided to 2,000 people. </p>
<p>"The Chinese people cherish sincere friendship toward the African people, and China's support to Africa's development is concrete and real," said co-chair Chinese Premier <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wen%20Jiabao">Wen Jiabao</ref> as the FOCAC opened up, adding "Whatever change that may take place in the world, our friendship with African people will not change." He described this friendship as 'unbreakable'. Two years ago China pledged <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_dollar">US$</ref>5 (<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Euro">€</ref>3.37) billion at the last FOCAC in Beijing and now, according to Jiabao, "China is ready to deepen practical cooperation in Africa."</p>
<hi rend="bold">We want more investment from China</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tanzania">Tanzanian</ref> President <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jakaya%20Kikwete">Jakaya Mrisho Kikwete</ref></p>
<p>China has fulfilled its 2006 pledge, investing a total of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_dollar">US$</ref>7.8 (<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Euro">€</ref>5.26) billion in Africa last year alone. 49 African countries are represented at the FOCAC, which was created in 2000, although Jiabao noted that relations between China and Africa go back fifty years. China had already forgiven or reduced the debt for thirty nations at that FOCAC summit.</p>
<p>According to Chinese state-owned paper <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/China%20Daily">China Daily</ref></hi>, trade between China and Africa increased by 45% last year, to give a total value of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_dollar">US$</ref>107 (<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Euro">€</ref>72.1) billion, a tenfold increase since 2001 and up from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_dollar">US$</ref>491 (<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Euro">€</ref>331) million in 2003. The Chinese have a 9.8% market share, the largest of any nation, according to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Commerce%20Department">U.S. Commerce Department</ref>. China has paid for schools, hospitals, malaria clinics and Chinese scholarships for African students. 50 more schools are to be built and 1,500 people trained to staff them.</p>
<p>Since 2006 Chinese energy firms have committed to spend at least <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_dollar">US$</ref>16 (<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Euro">€</ref>10.8) billion securing African oil and gas. China's Sinopec Group, an oil giant, bought up Addax Petroleum Corporation from its <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Switzerland">Swiss</ref> owners that year, gaining control of oilfields in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Nigeria">Nigeria</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Cameroon">Cameroon</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gabon">Gabon</ref>. China promised earlier this year to spend <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_dollar">US$</ref>9 (<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Euro">€</ref>6) billion on infrastructure in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Congo">Congo</ref> in exchange for mineral deposits for mining operations.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean%20Ping">Jean Ping</ref>, leader of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/African_Union">African Union</ref>, said the told those at the conference that the money is coming at an opportune time, because African growth was "totally compromised" by the global financial crisis. Ping said one of the lessons learned is that the world is paying for "the irresponsible and lax behavior" of large financial companies whose philosophy was to make short-term profits.</p>
<hi rend="bold">We thank China particularly for backing efforts by our countries to achieve peace and stability in Africa's zones of conflict</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sudan">Sudanese</ref> President <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Omar%20al-Beshir">Omar al-Beshir</ref></p>
<p>Not all Africans are happy with China's increasing involvement in their continent. Trade practices are a concern for some, with a view that China exploits Africa for raw materials before selling back finished goods. Among these are Egyptian Trade and Industry Minister Rachid Mohamed Rachid. Egypt is the richest nation in the Middle East and is discussing this perceived issue with China. Rachid told <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bloomberg">Bloomberg</ref> "What is a worry for me is if competition is unfair. That is where we are unhappy." Jiabao described the trade as being based on "win-win programmes... and transparency."</p>
<p>Others in Africa are delighted with the situation. "We want more investment from China," <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tanzania">Tanzanian</ref> President <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jakaya%20Kikwete">Jakaya Mrisho Kikwete</ref> told the forum. Egypt's own President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hosni_Mubarak">Hosni Mubarak</ref> talked of "peace, security and growth," and of "boosting cooperation between China and Africa."</p>
 HAVE YOUR SAY
 China investing in Africa: Good or bad?
<ref target="//en.wikinews.org/w/index.php?title=Comments:Main_Page&amp;action=edit&amp;preload=Wikinews:Commentary_pages_on_news_events/body&amp;editintro=Template:Editintro_comments&amp;summary=create">Add or view comments</ref>
<p>Jiabao also used his speech to respond to criticisms that China worked with nations regardless of their human rights record, such as <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sudan">Sudan</ref>, whose President <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Omar%20al-Bashir">Omar al-Beahir</ref> is wanted on a warrant issued by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International%20Criminal%20Court">International Criminal Court</ref> for war crimes. "Africa is fully capable of solving its own problems, in an African way," he said, adding that "China has never attached any political strings […] to assistance to Africa."</p>
<p>Beshir thanked China in a speech for diplomatic work in Sudan, including working to defuse the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War%20in%20Darfur">Darfur conflict</ref>, which the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Nations">United Nations</ref> says has left 300,000 dead. "We express our deep appreciation for China's efforts in backing the comprehensive peace agreement in Sudan and its peace efforts in Darfur," he said, referring to a peace deal between the northern and southern parts of his country. "We thank China particularly for backing efforts by our countries to achieve peace and stability in Africa's zones of conflict." Jiabao said China was willing to work towards "the settlement of issues of peace and security," in Africa.</p>
<p>A further criticism has been that China has brought in Chinese workers and used their own knowledge, instead of training locals. Jiabao's speech indicated an intention to co-operate better in the fields of science and technology, as well as improve training for African students on technical courses.</p>
<p>"Why do some only criticise China?" asked Jiabao. "Is this a view representing African countries, or rather the view of Western countries?"</p>
</text>
