<text id="autogum_academic_doc379" title="How the New European Union’s (Pictorial) Tobacco Health Warnings Influence Quit Attempts and Smoking Cessation: Findings from the 2016–2017 International Tobacco Control (ITC) Netherlands Surveys" shortTile="new-european-unions" author="Dirk-Jan  A. van Mourik, Math  J. J. M. Candel, Gera  E. Nagelhout, Marc  C. Willemsen, Hua-Hie Yong, Bas van den Putte, Geoffrey  T. Fong, Hein de Vries" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4260/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
This paper was the first to test the mediational pathways through which the new EU tobacco health warnings influence quit attempts and smoking cessation. We based our mediational model on the ITC conceptual model, which hypothesizes that policies influence quit attempts and smoking cessation via health warning salience as a policy specific variable and a set of eight potential psychosocial mediators. The hypothesized model fitted the data very well, thus supporting the ITC conceptual model. </p>

<p>This study’s analysis revealed three significant pathways between PHW salience and smoking cessation. The pathway from health warning salience to quit intention to quit attempts, and to smoking cessation was mediated by two psychosocial mediators between health warning salience and quit intention. First, we found positive associations between health warning salience and attitude towards quitting, and between health warning salience and health worries. A study from Thailand also found a positive association between health warning salience and such attitude, and experimental studies showed that PHWs could be effective to elicit a negative smoking attitude. Second, a positive association between health warning salience and health worries was found, in line with a previous study. This might have been caused by the distressing messages as communicated by the health warnings. The attitude and health worries were both associated with a stronger quit intention, in accordance with previous studies. The third significant pathway ran from health warning salience—perceived social norms, quit attempts, and smoking cessation. Health warning salience might have been positively associated with stronger perceived social norms due to the accompanying (THWs): “Quit now—stay alive for close family and friends”. Perceived social norms were associated with quit attempts at follow-up, as also found in a previous study, although sometimes, this association is mediated by quit intention. </p>

<p>Several pathways were not significant. First, in line with experimental studies, this study found that the efficacy messages “Quit now! Go to <ref target="http://www.ikstopnu.nl">www.ikstopnu.nl</ref>., or call the quitline at 0800–1995 (free)” (1) were not enough to change self-efficacy levels. Second, in addition to inconclusive results on the direction and size of the association between health warning salience and quit intention in previous literature, we found no direct association between both variables. Furthermore, health warning salience was associated with three psychosocial mediators that were not directly or indirectly associated with quit intention, quit attempts, or smoking cessation. First, health warning salience was associated with more knowledge about the health risks of smoking, in line with other longitudinal observational studies. The knowledge, as communicated by the current EU tobacco health warnings, may not have been enough to motivate smokers to quit smoking, contrary to another study, but sufficient research on this is lacking. Second, health warning salience was associated with increased self-reports that health warnings stopped smokers from having a cigarette when they were about to smoke one and avoiding health warnings. Similar associations were also found in experimental studies, and previous longitudinal observational studies. Forgoing did not influence quit intention or attempts, in contrast to other observational studies that showed positive associations for forgoing. These observational studies, however, showed weak associations and also included THWs without PHWs. In line with other population-based studies, avoidance of health warnings did not have negative effects on quit intention, quit attempts, or smoking cessation. </p>

<head> 4.1. Strengths and Limitations</head>
<p>
A major strength of this study is that due to the high number of respondents and the imputation of missing data, we had high statistical power. Another strength of this study is the use of a longitudinal design that is conducive for demonstrating the causality of the tested pathways between the psychosocial mediators and quit attempts and smoking cessation. However, the mediational model was partly cross-sectional, making it difficult to draw causal conclusions about the relationships between all outcomes, notably those between the policy-specific variable and the mediators, both of which were measured at the same wave. Nonetheless, since the construction of the mediational model tested in this study was based on the ITC conceptual model and behavior change theories, the results provide some support for the possible causal pathways from health warning salience to quit attempts. Relatedly, we could not examine the causal relationships between the psychosocial mediators. Our study has some limitations that should be acknowledged when interpreting the results.  </p>
</text>
