<text id="autogum_whow_doc493" title="Have Clothes Custom Made in Hong Kong" shortTile="clothes-custom-made" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-04-21" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Have-Clothes-Custom-Made-in-Hong-Kong" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Have Clothes Custom Made in Hong Kong</head><p>Custom clothes have been a traditional souvenir of visiting China since Hong Kong belonged to China the first time. If you have clothes custom made in Hong Kong, you can't expect the deeply discounted prices you'll find on the mainland, but you can come home with an exquisite suit or dress made with fine fabrics and cut exactly to fit your form.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Create some preliminary ideas or sketches before you even leave your country of origin. When getting clothes custom made in Hong Kong you should be prepared. You're very likely to spend much more than you budgeted for, and be less happy with the final result if you go without a plan or idea. <figure rend="Have Clothes Custom Made in Hong Kong Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>It can be a good idea to make your custom clothes part of your travel budget. You'll spend several hundred U.S. dollars on a quality Hong Kong tailor.</item></list></item>
<item>Talk to several tailors by phone or contact them via email to get an idea of their availability and prices. The best tailors won't be available on a drop-in basis, so you can make an appointment as your travel plans are arranged. <figure rend="Have Clothes Custom Made in Hong Kong Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can find information about tailors in Hong Kong from recently-updated guidebooks for the city. Another technique is to contact the hotel where you'll be staying. With tailored clothing being such a draw in Hong Kong tourism, the concierge is almost guaranteed to have a relationship with at least one tailor.</item></list></item>
<item>Visit the tailors you're considering early during your stay in Hong Kong. View fabric samples, talk about pricing and look at finished garments before committing to one tailor. It's best to set aside at least half a day for this research. <figure rend="Have Clothes Custom Made in Hong Kong Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Set aside another half day for your fitting and initial negotiation with your tailor. Bring sketches or photos from fashion magazines to help communicate exactly the kind of garment you want. <figure rend="Have Clothes Custom Made in Hong Kong Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you have a favorite suit, dress or other set of clothing, you can bring it to the tailor, and he will produce additional copies in different fabrics and colors.</item></list></item>
<item>Expect to pay a 50 percent deposit before your tailor will begin work. Prior to paying that deposit, get a written agreement on price and due date. Quality tailoring takes from several days to 1 week, so it's best to get to this stage early during your vacation in Hong Kong. <figure rend="Have Clothes Custom Made in Hong Kong Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pick up your garment on the due date. Check quality before you pay, and negotiate for any needed alterations. <figure rend="Have Clothes Custom Made in Hong Kong Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Avoid tailors who offer package deals. The best tailors will make your clothing exactly to order, without adding extra garments. Establishments with those package deals work to templates, trusting the fact that the tourist market doesn't represent many return customers.</item>
<item>Burlington Arcade on Nathan Road is famous for its wide selection of quality and reasonably-priced tailors.</item></list>
</text>
