<text id="autogum_whow_doc139" title="Improve Communication Within a Globally Distributed Team" shortTile="improve-communication" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-05-22" dateModified="2019-06-05" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Improve-Communication-Within-a-Globally-Distributed-Team" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Improve Communication Within a Globally Distributed Team</head><p>Communication plays an essential role in software development. In the first month of a project, developers spent over 50% of their time on group work.. When working in a globally distributed team, communication becomes more of a challenge due to the lack of face-to-face meetings. Communication in globally distributed teams has “a critical role in the success of a team” and can be “the largest source of problems.” This wikiHow will provide an overview of the best practices for communication in a globally distributed software team to help you avoid common mistakes.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Improving General Communication</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><figure rend="Measure the Effectiveness of Communication Step 9.jpg"></figure> Have teams meet in person at an early stage of the project. When starting a project, it is highly recommended to define standardized processes and establish shared knowledge. You can do this by doing a physical kick-off meeting with all teams involved at the start of a project. Studies show that this increases inter-team performance dramatically..If you are only using online tools, it may not be enough.
<list type="unordered"><item>Another advantage meeting in person provides is that it gives you a common understanding of requirements which in the long run will cut down project costs and enables your teams to better react to changes within them.</item></list></item>
<item>Proactively check the status of teams. Since your teams are operating independently, there is a risk that some of them might deviate from the initially agreed upon plan. These deviations can have a major impact on the other teams and therefore on your whole project. If you pro-actively check the status of all teams on the overall project, you can ensure all teams are always aligned.</item>
<item><figure rend="Measure the Effectiveness of Communication Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure> Assign a ‘communication manager’ responsible for the communication between the teams. In order to prevent miscommunication between the teams, you can appoint one person to coordinate the communication.  This ‘human facilitator’ has the goal of providing smooth communication and reducing conflicts. It is important that this facilitator is not biased and both teams feel comfortable communicating with this person.
<list type="unordered"><item>It can even be helpful to have a key member of one team physically located with the other team.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Measure the Effectiveness of Communication Step 10.jpg"></figure> Introduce avenues for informal communication between the teams. In addition the formal communication, there is generally also a lot of informal communication between colleagues. Think of conversations at the coffee machine. It turns out that developers spent an average of 75 minutes per day on unplanned interpersonal communication. In these small conversations, team members become aware of what is happening and what issues are being encountered within the project.
<list type="unordered"><item>The challenge is to simulate these casual encounters in a digital environment. One solution is to get all of your teams members on a video call and just let them chat away.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Measure the Effectiveness of Communication Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure> Choose the right communication tool. Communication tools can be divided into two groups: Synchronous and asynchronous.
<list type="unordered"><item>Synchronous communication requires both parties to be available at the same time, this includes video calling and live chats.</item>
<item>Asynchronous communication does not have this requirement and includes tools like e-mail.</item>
<item>Choosing which type of communication is needed depends on the goal of the communication.  Synchronous communication is preferred when reaching an agreement is the goal, since it is highly interactive. Asynchronous communication is fit for highly technical discussions that include detailed content such as source code.  The asynchronous communication allows the parties to take their time to understand the content before responding.</item>
<item>Despite the points mentioned above, it is important to allow your teams to choose their own tools without forcing anything on them. They know what is best for them.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Enhancing Communication Via Automation</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><figure rend="Measure Process Improvement Step 13.jpg"></figure> Use automation to communicate effectively. Automation not only makes the process run faster, but it is also a very effective way to communicate precisely with others to understand how the task or process should be executed. This is useful when working in distributed environments; you can make use of automation to bridge the gaps.
<list type="unordered"><item>Process automation like building software, testing, etc. eliminates human errors, configuration drifts, and communication misunderstandings, which helps people focus more on feature development.</item></list></item>
<item>Do not create a separate, siloed automation team. When working in a distributed environment, it is easy to offshore all the automation work, like test automation and infrastructure automation, to other teams or countries.
<list type="unordered"><item>Most companies follow a pattern of building features and software onsite and then moving the automation work to an offshore team. However, this does not work in practice, as only specific teams will have to knowledge of how the automation works. This causes a more bureaucratic silo and is eventually is followed by a blame-game of teams when an error is caused.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Prepare for a Coding Interview Step 2.jpg"></figure> Follow the same coding guidelines and testing guidelines for automation. You should follow specific coding guidelines and testing guidelines, because it makes sure that the right message is passed from the development team to the business.
<list type="unordered"><item>Since automation code is also production code, you need to maintain the same quality checks and standards that you use to maintain the production code, or else the testing code becomes harder to maintain in the long run; the team will eventually lose focus and interest as it is difficult to maintain automation.</item></list></item>
<item>Create a framework or set up tools to promote people to talk to each other frequently. Every team member should be able to track and review any new technical decisions or requirements changes such as build failures or refactoring. You can use tools like TFS, Github, JIRA, Slack, or Trello, which show who’s accountable for each task and help developers to have a reference to add in data where it was last completed. This ensures teams at different locations know what is going on.</item>
<item>Practice continuous integration and continuous delivery. Practicing an automated deployment pipeline ensures that teams at different locations are working towards a common goal and can work more integrated which results in better communication between distributed teams.
<list type="unordered"><item>This also reduces the time required to manually review and wait for decisions. Sharing information helps all the teams understand the objectives and aids communication and productivity.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
