<text id="autogum_voyage_doc266" title="Sfax" shortTile="sfax" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=32291" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Sfax</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Sfax</hi> is on the east coast of <ref target="Tunisia">Tunisia</ref>, approximately midway on the highway between <ref target="Tunis">Tunis</ref> and the border with <ref target="Libya">Libya</ref>.</p>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sfax-Thyna Airport</hi> ( SFA ). has two flights per week to/from Paris CDG Airport with <ref target="http://www.tunisair.com/">Tunisair</ref>. You can also reach Sfax by internal flights with Sevenair from Djerba, Tozeur, Tunis or with a <ref target="http://en.libyanairlines.aero/">Libyan Airlines</ref> flight from Tripoli. </item>
</list>


<head>By car</head>
<p>A highway connects Sfax to northern cities like Tunis and Sousse.</p>

<head>By train</head>

<p>Train connections are available from the train station in the centre of Sfax to most major Tunisian cities. The main station, is located just north of the city centre.</p>

<head>By bus</head>

<p>There are two has bus stations in Sfax. <ref target="http://www.soretras.com.tn/">Soretras</ref>, which is the regional bus company, and may not offer A/C buses, is on Rue Commondant Bejaoui, a few blocks past the central market.</p>

<ref target="http://www.sntri.com.tn/">SNTRI Bus</ref> station, which offers long distance buses, may be marked incorrectly on some travel guide maps. It is not across from the regional bus station, but is roughly 400 m to the south, over the train tracks. It is probably best to take a taxi there, especially in the summer (less than 2 DT from the Medina/Blvd Republique). The bus station is in the same building as the Tunisair office.

<head>By boat</head>

<p>Sfax is the gateway to the Kerkennah Islands, 20 kilometers off the coast. <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.sonotrak.tn">Sonotrak</ref></hi> has up to eight daily departures. The is located on 5 Ave Mohamed Hédi Khefacha.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<p>Public transport is easily available in Sfax.</p>

<p>Taxis are economical, and getting around in the downtown area should cost less than 2 DT per ride. For example, this would include from Bab Bhar (south of the Medina) to Sfax Jdiid (north of the Medina), or from the Railway station to Hotel Syphax.</p>

<p>Buses are rarely used by tourists, since they are irregular, slow and crowded. If you are going to a destination on one of the roads that radiate out of the city, a taxi might cost about 3.500 DT to kilometer 8, for example. A bus would only cost 0.510 DT. These buses depart from locations around the Medina (mostly to the north or to the east). The site www.ecfi-t.com has a useful map of bus routes, and other information about Sfax.</p>

<p>Transport between cities can be done by train or by louage.</p>
<p>Trains go south to Gabes for the Ksour district or sites where Star Wars was filmed, or north to El Djem, Sousse or Tunis. Trains have 3 classes of travel: 2nd class, 1st class and Confort. The last is recommended, especially when the train is crowded, since the inspector will move passengers out of seats where they don't belong. The Confort class is a separate section within one of the 1st class coaches, the smaller section, with about 24 seats. (Often locals do not realise this, and will sit there until moved on by the inspector, or wiser souls.)</p>

<p>The louage is a minibus of about 9 passengers. The Louage station is located beyond the western end of Avenue Bourguiba, about 1½ km from the railway station (and so is worth a taxi fare). The louage driver will wait until the bus is full, which may mean an hour or more at quiet times, or to infrequent destinations. A wait for a ride to Tunis, El Djem or Sousse should not take too long, but if you are in a hurry and there is only one or two seats left, offer to pay for an extra seat or two.</p>

<p>Bus transport between cities is also available.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Archaeological Museum of Sfax</hi> (Muséé de Sfax), 9 Ave Habib Bourguiba (Ground floor of the city hall). 8:30-1PM, 3-6PM. Hosts an impressive collection of mosaics from the region, in particular the Roman towns of Taparura (where Sfax now is) and Thaenae (now Thyna, 11 km west of Sfax). 3 DT.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kasbah</hi> (Southwest corner of the Medina). The kasbah was a military garrison before and during the French Protectorate (1881-1956). The French influence (buildings, etc.) has been removed and the Kasbah now hosts rooms of displays relating the industry for which Sfax is famous; construction, metalwork and the famous Bourj and Djenes of Sfax all have their own rooms. Additionally there is a display of religious architecture and some documents in another room, with an underground mosque area also worth a visit. Definitely a highlight is the view from the top of either of the towers that form part of the Kasbah. 3 DT.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Dar Djellouli</hi> (See map for location.). The Djellouli family has provided Sfax with a number of its governors over the years, particularly during the 1700s and 1800s. Dar Djellouli is also referred to as the Governor's Mansion, and is an example of traditional Medina architecture. It is built around a courtyard that is open to the sky, with two floors of balconies on four sides looking down on it. The rooms open onto these balconies, and house cultural items from the 1800s and even earlier. Costumes from the period can be viewed, as can examples of cooking, calligraphy, embroidery, perfume distillation and furniture. 3 DT.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Filming locations for <hi rend="italic">The English Patient</hi></hi>, Blacksmith's Souk (Souq des Forgerons) (inside the Medina, near Bab Jebli). Inside this souk is where Almasy gave Katherine a silver thimble of saffron. It no longer houses the blacksmiths, and has bern remodeled around retail. See <ref target="http://homepage.ntlworld.com/colin.kenworthy1/compare.htm">here</ref> for more Tunisian film locations.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Dar Siala</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Maison de la photographie</hi> (Dar Kammoun), cultural centres and art galleries</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>
<p>Wander around the fascinating Medina (which has an easily mastered and logical layout) where life and business go on much as they have for years and where tourists, although welcome, are few and far between.</p>

<p>Ride to Kerkenna on the ferry, with 8 trips a day costing about 800 millimes each way. In Kerkenna, get a taxi to the Hotel Cercina where you can walk the beach, or sit on their patio and enjoy tea looking over the bay. Check the times of the ferry's return, and make sure you get a taxi back in time! From the Grand Hotel you an also walk the beach, with your destination, the old Bourj, visible in the distance. About 1½ km each way, so give yourselves time to enjoy it. The Roman ruins beside the Bourj are opened to public as well.</p>
</text>
