<text id="autogum_interview_doc052" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Steve Burke, U.S. Democratic Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-12-11" dateModified="2019-08-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Steve_Burke%2C_U.S._Democratic_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Steve Burke, U.S. Democratic Party presidential candidate</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, December 13, 2015</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Steve Burke Image: Steve Burke.</caption></figure>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Macomb,%20New%20York">Macomb</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York">New York</ref> Councilman Steve Burke took some time to speak with <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> about his campaign for the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S.">U.S.</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Democratic_Party_(United_States)">Democratic Party</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_presidential_election,_2016">2016 presidential nomination</ref>.</p>
<p>Burke, an insurance adjuster and farmer, was elected councilman in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brookhaven,%20New%20York">Brookhaven</ref>, New York in 1979.  He left the town after being accused and found not guilty of bribery in the 1980s.  Since 1987 he has served as Macomb councilman off-and-on and currently holds the post.  From 1993 to 1996 and 1999 to 2002 he worked as chairman of the Democratic Party of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St.%20Lawrence%20County,%20New%20York">St. Lawrence County</ref>, New York.  Among his many political campaigns, Burke unsuccessfully sought the Democratic Party's presidential nomination in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20presidential%20election,%201992">1992</ref> and recently attempted to run for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S._Congress">U.S. Congress</ref> in 2014 but too many of his ballot petition signatures were found invalid.  Burke filed with the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Federal_Election_Commission">Federal Election Commission</ref> to run for president in the 2016 election on September 18, 2015 and has qualified for the first-in-the-nation <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20Hampshire%20Primary">New Hampshire Primary</ref>. </p>
<p>With <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:William_S._Saturn">William S. Saturn</ref>‎, Burke discusses his political background, his 2016 presidential campaign, and his policy proposals.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">William S. Saturn</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What are some of your achievements as councilman in Brookhaven, New York?</hi></item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Steve Burke</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>   The only way to answer your question is by semi story okay? I was asked once to take over the fight to save the county infirmary from closure. It housed ill and hopeless cases.  I felt it was the county's obligation to keep it open. Just as I believe we have an obligation to the mentally ill who need a hospital setting instead of the street or jail. So I took on the county and organized the seniors, relatives of the patients and went to work until the county elected officials cried uncle and kept it open.  In fact they built a brand new infirmary and I believe it is still open. I last stopped there in the 1990s to visit a man I became friends with at the infirmary. He was bed ridden after he was stabbed with a knife in the back and it severed his spine. The county infirmary is owned by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suffolk%20County,%20New%20York">Suffolk County</ref> but in the town of Brookhaven. When I was first elected to the Brookhaven council, I felt we could now start to help the people. What a shock I got and lessons no political course in school can teach. There [were] some minor patronage jobs available. One person who was a disabled vet wanted some part time work.  I spoke with my board members and they agreed to give him a bingo inspector job. About four evenings a month minor pay. On our very first meeting I looked at the agenda and his name was not there. I asked why and they told me they decided to give it to a bartender where they ate and drank. Because he made good drinks. That did not fly with me. I called them all into a room and spoke with them and the party leader by phone. The result was that day the disabled vet got the position and held it until he passed on.  So back stabbing, back biting, always looking to get even [are] the lessons I learned the hard way from my fellow elected officials. But it taught me how to get things done. Former <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_Hampshire">New Hampshire</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_Senate">U.S. Senator</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Warren%20Rudman">[Warren] Rudman</ref> said when he quit the Senate, he could not get over the hatred and back stabbing in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Washington_D.C.">Washington</ref>.   So I guess when you deal with elected egos it is the same all over. The town had a few hundred vehicles they owned and the employees drove.  Remember Brookhaven is the largest town in New York. I was assigned the public safety department.  I found the town cars were unaccounted for. No one knew where they were or who had them. Some I found in back yards of employees with parts missing, invoices of repairs not done on town cars but on personal cars and charged to the town.  I stopped all of that, put the repairs out to bid. Made a depot to pick up and drop off daily a car. Changed the color and bought smaller vehicles. I also started a repair yard with town mechanics. When the bid expired. I saved the local police/code enforcement department that they wanted to get rid of.  They took care of our parks and buildings, etc. I think I put in a resolution to push for the five cent return bottles, cans, etc., or maybe I just brought it up. I am not sure. That was before the state did it. The town <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/dog%20pound">dog pound</ref> was a problem.  I heard they were selling dogs and cats out the back door to labs and for guard dog companies.  I got the town board to go in with me one evening and seize the records. We went through them and turned them over to the district attorney.  It was not followed up.  But there [were] no more rumors of dogs or cats going out the back door. I am sure there was more but that was 30 years ago. You will have to cut it down. One builds up enemies if you do anything as an elected official. Those that last a long time are generally do nothings, no waves.</p>
</text>
