<text id="autogum_interview_doc588" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Australian Paralympic skiers Jessica Gallagher and Eric Bickerton" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-12-10" dateModified="2017-10-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_Paralympic_skiers_Jessica_Gallagher_and_Eric_Bickerton" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Gallagher:</hi> I'm surprised by that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Eric Bickerton:</hi> That's unusual, yeah.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  One of the things that was mentioned earlier, most delightful about you guys is you were racing and "we were halfway down the course and we lost communication!" How does a blind skier deal with...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Gallagher:</hi> Funny now. Was bloody scary.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What race was that?</p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Gallagher:</hi> It was the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giant%20Slalom">Giant Slalom</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2010_Winter_Paralympics">Vancouver</ref> at the Paralympics. Actually, we were talking about this before. It's one of the unique aspects of wearing headsets and being able to communicate. All the time while we were on the mountain earlier today, Eric had a stack and all he could hear as he was tumbling down was me laughing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Eric Bickerton:</hi> Yes... I wasn't feeling the love.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Gallagher:</hi> But um... what was the question please?</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I couldn't imagine anything scarier than charging down the mountain at high speed and losing that communications link. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Gallagher:</hi> The difficulty was in the Giant Slalom, it was raining, and being used to ski racing, I had never experienced skiing in the rain, and as soon as I came out of the start hut I lost all my sight, which is something that I had never experienced before. Only having 8 per cent you treasure it and to lose all of it was a huge shock. And then when I couldn't hear Eric talking I realised that our headsets had malfunctioned because they'd actually got rain into them. Which normally wouldn't happen in the mountains because it would be snow. So it was the scariest moment of my life. Going down it was about getting to the bottom in one piece, not racing to win a medal, which was pretty difficult I guess or frustrating, given that it was the Paralympics.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I asked the standing guys upstairs: who is the craziest amongst all you skiers: the ones who can't see, the ones on the mono skis, or the one-legged or no-armed guys. Who is the craziest one on the slopes?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Gallagher:</hi> I think the completely blind. If I was completely blind I wouldn't ski. Some of the sit skiers are pretty crazy as well.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  You have full control over your skis though. You have both legs and both arms. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Gallagher:</hi> True, but you've got absolutely no idea where you're going. And you have to have complete reliance on a person. Trust that they are able to give you the right directions. That you are actually going in the right direction. It's difficult with the sight that I have but I couldn't imagine doing it with no sight at all.</p>
</text>
