<text id="autogum_academic_doc446" title="Effectiveness of Chronic Wound Debridement with the Use of Larvae of Lucilia Sericata" shortTile="effectiveness-chronic" author="Dariusz Bazaliński, Maria Kózka, Magdalena Karnas, Paweł Więch" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2077-0383/8/11/1845/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. The Mechanism of Action</head>
<p>
Only <hi rend="italic">Lucilia sericata</hi> larvae from certified farms can be safely used in medicine. Complicated procedures of egg disinfection, using chloroamine, povidone-iodine and sodium hypochlorite, are intended to ensure safety during use of this product. MDT is based on three mechanisms, observed when <hi rend="italic">Lucilia sericata</hi> are introduced to the wound: the mechanical removal of necrotic tissue, bactericidal and bacteriostatic activity, and promotion of the healing process. Reports from the last decade point out that physical contact with the wound is a less important effect of the larval presence within the wound, and is probably a negative effect for the patient, who may feel a physical presence and wiggling in the wound. Chemicals secreted by larvae initiate the process of bacterial elimination and remodeling of the wound bed. </p>

<p><figure>Figure 1</figure> shows the effect of debridement on a necrotic forearm wound measuring over 200 cm². Within 72 hours, 100 free-range larvae cleansed over 70% of necrosis in the wound, revealing the damaged forearm bones. The above observations suggest the potential use of this method in cases where wounds cover full skin-thickness, with a high risk of necrosis, or an already existing infection. The selection of an appropriate method for the further wound healing process is the next stage of local action. </p>

<p>A maggot does not literally consume pieces of tissue, but it secretes and excretes digestive enzymes (digestive secretions and excretions of arginase). Digestion begins directly in the wound bed, outside the maggot’s body. Dead tissue is liquefied and can be easily absorbed by the maggot. This phenomenon can be easily observed during therapy because of the increase in the amount of exudate from the wound and its specific odor. Hobson was the first scientist to systematically present the proteolytic effects of digestive enzymes produced by the larvae of <hi rend="italic">Lucilia sericata</hi>. The movements of maggots, scratching tissue and secreting arginase, facilitate the debridement process. Other enzymes released include leucine aminopeptidase, collagenase and chymotrypsin-like proteases. These enzymes have various functions in the wound; they mainly transform dead tissue into liquid, which is either exuded from the wound or consumed by the maggots. The evacuation of necrosis and reduction in bacterial contamination promotes the regeneration process. The authors of numerous recently published papers have noted chemical substances that influence the promotion of the healing process. The migration of resident epidermal keratinocytes and dermal cells, including fibroblasts and dermal microvascular cells, from the wound margins into the wound bed, is a crucial step in wound healing. Amino acids, such as L-histidine, 3-guanidinopropionic acid and L-valinol, have been identified in larva secretions, and it has been demonstrated in vitro that these isolated components specifically increase the proliferation of human endothelial cells. </p>

<p>Collagenase speeds up the process of proteolysis by decomposing the material into smaller components, digested later by other enzymes secreted by the larvae. Once necrosis is effectively removed, the consecutive stages of healing are facilitated by the increased phagocytic activity of leukocytes and higher oxygen pressure, resulting in optimum conditions for the regeneration of damaged tissues. </p>

<p>Proteolytic digestion is the initial act of tissue repair, leading to hemostasis, thrombosis, inflammatory cell activation and the reconstruction of tissue. Several studies suggest that the beneficial effect of larvae may be due to their ability to reduce pro-inflammatory factors. The work of Pecivova et al. studied the effect of the <hi rend="italic">Lucilia sericata</hi> salivary gland extract on opsonized neutrophils, stimulated with zymogen and unstimulated neutrophils. Salivary gland extract had no effect on superoxide production and myeloperoxidase release from unstimulated neutrophils, but significantly reduced both peroxide production and MPO secretion levels in zsonogen-stimulated opsonized neutrophils. </p>

<p>Following debridement, the wound may be appropriately assessed. Consequently, it is also possible to introduce other methods that promote wound closure, or to perform a skin transplant. </p>

<p>The granulation tissue in the wound, debrided and stimulated by larval secretions, should be dressed as soon as possible with the chosen method of local treatment. The choice of method depends on several factors, such as level of tissue destruction, area, wound etiopathogenesis, and general condition of the patient. Wound management criteria should be carefully implemented based on the TIME concept. The use of negative pressure wound therapy (NPWT) is effective in shrinking the wound, reducing exudate and bacteria, and stimulating neoangigenesis, specialized dressings, in the case of superficial and penetrative lesions that do not qualify for surgery. There are clinical situations, especially in terminally ill patients, in which wounds debrided from necrotic tissue are only managed with dressings, due to the patient’s condition and poor prognosis. </p>
</text>
