<text id="autogum_news_doc175" title="Arabs react to Israeli debate on Jerusalem&apos;s Holy sites" shortTile="arabs-react-israeli" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-02-26" dateModified="2018-01-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Arabs_react_to_Israeli_debate_on_Jerusalem%27s_Holy_sites" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Arabs react to Israeli debate on Jerusalem's Holy sites</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 27, 2014</hi></p>
<figure><caption>In Jewish tradition, the rock upon which Abraham built his altar for the sacrifice of Isaac (Dome of the Rock interior). Image: OSU Special Collections &amp; Archives.</caption></figure>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Islam">Islamic</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jordan">Jordanian</ref> leaders responded yesterday to a debate conducted by the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Israel">Israeli</ref> parliament, the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Knesset">Knesset</ref>, addressing current Arab control over holy sites in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old%20City%20(Jerusalem)">Old City</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jerusalem">Jerusalem</ref> including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al-Aqsa%20Mosque">Al-Aqsa Mosque</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dome%20of%20the%20Rock">Dome of the Rock</ref>.</p>
<p>Last week, members of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parliament%20of%20Jordan">Jordanian Parliament</ref> condemned the plan for a debate in the Knesset on the issue, but yesterday after the debate in Israel almost 50 of them had petitioned the Jordanian government to stop the enforcement of the 1994 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Israel–Jordan%20peace%20treaty">Israel–Jordan peace treaty</ref>. The treaty allowed for the exchange of ambassadors and on that point, the Jordanian parliament voted on the recall of the nation's ambassador to Israel. Jordan's Prime Minister Abdullah Nsur said, in remarks to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Qatar">Qatari</ref> newspaper <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al-Watan%20(Qatar)">Al-Watan</ref></hi>, any Israeli action affecting Jordanian control of the Holy sites would violate the treaty and Jordan could review whether or not the treaty had been invalidated. Meanwhile, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Organisation%20of%20Islamic%20Cooperation">Organisation of Islamic Cooperation</ref> criticized the Knesset debate as a provocation.</p>
<p>Before the Israeli debate Tuesday, Palestinian protesters took to one of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gates%20of%20the%20Temple%20Mount">Gates of the Temple Mount</ref> in the Old City, used by <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Judaism">Jews</ref>, armed with firecrackers and rocks and were met by Israeli police.</p>
<p>On Tuesday, members of the Israeli Knesset began a debate on an issue it had never before broached. MK <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moshe%20Feiglin">Moshe Feiglin</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Likud">Likud</ref> started the debate about one of Jerusalem's holiest sites, The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Temple%20Mount">Temple Mount</ref>. Feiglin spoke to freedom of religion and the right of Israelis to pray on the site controlled by the Arabs while opponents addressed their fears the sensitive topic could harm ongoing peace talks. He said, "Any terror organization can raise its flag there, [but] there can be no trace of the Israeli flag. Only Jews are forbidden to pray at this place."</p>
<p>During the debate, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Israeli_Labor_Party">Labor</ref> MK <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eitan%20Cabel">Eitan Cabel</ref> reacted to Feiglin's motion, "Why stop at the Temple Mount? If you are the new messiah of our times, what about" — he named various specifics of the holy promise of the lands of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greater%20Israel">Greater Israel</ref> — "Why leave them behind?" A "Greater Israel" promised by God is generally considered off limits in civic discourse inside Israel. The Knesset did not vote on the issue.</p>
<p>Al-Aqsa Mosque ranks just behind <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mecca">Mecca</ref> and  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Medina">Medina</ref> as the holiest of Islamic sites. Jews consider the Temple Mount to be their holiest site. </p>
<figure></figure>
<p>The Al-Aqsa Mosque from the Western Wall Plaza. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Wilson44691">Wilson44691</ref>.</p>
<figure></figure>
<p>Southern aerial view of the Temple Mount in the Old City of Jerusalem. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Godot13">Godot13</ref>.</p>
 <figure></figure>
The portal of the Al-Aqsa Mosque from the north. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Godot13">Godot13</ref>.  <figure></figure>
Al-Fakhriyyah Minaret &amp; Islamic Museum. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Godot13">Godot13</ref>.  <figure></figure>
The Al-Aqsa Mosque in Jerusalem. Image: Jane Fresco.  <figure></figure>
The Dome of the Rock (close). Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:بلال_الدويك">بلال الدويك</ref>.  <figure></figure>
The outdoor Islamic Pulpit of the Cadi Borhan-ed-din Jerusalem Holy Land at the Al-Aqsa Mosque, Jerusalem. Image: Snapshots of The Past.  <figure></figure>
Al Aqsa Mosque from the Dome of the Rock. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:MatthiasKabel">MatthiasKabel</ref>.  <figure></figure>
 The Dome of the Chain (Arabic: قبة السلسلة, Qubbat al-Silsila) in front of The Dome of the Rock. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Godot13">Godot13</ref>.  <figure></figure>
Southern Wall of the Temple Mount in Jerusalem. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Wknight94">Wknight94</ref>.
</text>
