<text id="autogum_whow_doc315" title="Fold a Napkin" shortTile="fold-napkin" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2010-10-28" dateModified="2019-04-04" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Fold-a-Napkin" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Fold a Napkin</head><p>Add a little flair to any dinner with elegant napkin folds. Folding napkins is a time-honored tradition used in restaurants and homes alike. It's simple, classy, and easy to master. Read on for several different instructions on how to fold a napkin.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Goblet Fan</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Fold the napkin in half to form a long rectangle. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 1 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Starting at one short end, fold the napkin like an accordion all the way to the opposite end. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 2 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Holding one folded end, place it into your drinking glass. Let the napkin fan over the top of the glass. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 3 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure></item></list>
<head>Pyramid</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Lay the napkin out in front of you. If your napkin flops down easily, ironing it with a little bit of light starch should help this process. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 4 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Fold the napkin across diagonally. Turn the folded napkin so that the tip of the napkin is facing directly in front of you. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 5 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Fold the right corner down to meet the tip of the napkin. Make sure that this fold creates a clean center line in the middle of the napkin. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 6 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Fold the left corner down to meet the tip of the napkin, mirroring the last step. The napkin should now look like a diamond. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 7 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Turn the napkin over, keeping the open end of the napkin away from you. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 8 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Fold the farthest point of the diamond back over itself, creating a triangle. The tip of the triangle should be pointing down. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 9 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Fold the napkin along the center seam, right to left. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 10 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Prop it up like a tent. If your napkin is floppy and won't stay propped up, you may need a little starch. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 11 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Bishop's Hat</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Lay the napkin out in front of you. If your napkin flops down easily, ironing it with a little bit of light starch should help this process. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 12 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Fold the napkin in half by bringing the top end down. You should have a rectangle now. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 13 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Bring the top right corner down to the middle-bottom of the napkin. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 14 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Bring the bottom left corner up to the middle-top of the napkin. You should have a parallelogram now. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 15 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Flip the napkin over and rearrange it so that the top left and bottom right edges are sticking out. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 16 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Fold the bottom of the napkin up and towards the top half. The edges should all be meeting each other, except for a stray triangle at the bottom left of the napkin. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 17 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Gently bring out the flap on the right so that it forms another triangle on the bottom right. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 18 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Bring the top left corner and tuck it underneath the triangle on the right. The left triangle is now folded in half. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 19 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Flip the triangle over so that the two points are now facing up. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 20 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Fold the right edge into the left flap. The napkin should be completely symmetrical again. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 21 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Push the folds in the center of the hat down so that the base of the bishop's hat is circular. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 22 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Finished. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 23 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Basic Silverware Pouch</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Lay the napkin out in front of you. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 24 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Fold the napkin in half by bringing the top end down. You should have a rectangle now. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 25 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Fold the napkin again to create a square. Move the right end over the left end. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 26 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Turn the napkin around so that the open corner is facing top-left. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 27 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Bring the top fold of the top-left corner of the napkin down diagonally to the bottom-right. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 28 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Flip the triangle over so that the open corner is now facing top-right. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 29 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Fold the right side over about 1/3 of the way and crease the fold. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 30 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Fold the left side over about 1/3 of the way and fit it into the little fold created at the bottom right. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 31 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Flip the napkin over again and arrange any utensils inside the napkin. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 32 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Finished. <figure rend="Fold a Napkin Step 33 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
