<text id="autogum_voyage_doc109" title="Chicago/Chatham-South Shore" shortTile="chicagochathamsouth" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=7131" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Chicago/Chatham-South Shore</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Chatham-South Shore</hi> is a district at the heart of <ref target="Chicago">Chicago</ref>'s South Side, home to the <hi rend="italic">real</hi> Chicago blues, some mind-blowing BBQ, and the best soul food in town.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>This side of Chicago does not feature in many travel plans. If you ask a hotel concierge in the <ref target="Chicago/Near%20North">Near North</ref> to make arrangements for a trip here, the reaction — whether incredulous or simply bewildered — should be a sight to behold. Don't be fooled, though; Chatham and Greater Grand could be the highlight of your trip to Chicago. The best <hi rend="bold">blues clubs</hi>, the last true juke joints, are way down here.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Greater Chatham</hi> (Chatham, Avalon Park, Calumet Heights, Burnside) is a residential stronghold of middle and upper class African-American Chicagoans. No sightseeing to be done, but Chatham boasts some of the best food on the South Side (including <hi rend="italic">the ultimate Harold's</hi>), as well as one of the city's best blues clubs.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Greater Grand</hi> rivals Chatham for soul food, BBQ, and blues club supremacy. It also has the <hi rend="bold">Oak Woods Cemetery</hi>, which is beautifully laid out, and a resting place to some of the most famous residents of the South Side's past.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">South Shore</hi> is home to a lively arts scene, largely thanks to the ETA Creative Arts Foundation and the magnificent <hi rend="bold">South Shore Cultural Center</hi>. It is also home to one of the city's best and least known beaches, Rainbow Beach. Incidentally, many of Chicago's most prominent black politicians call this community home. Its main commercial strip runs alongside Metra's Electric Line on 71st St and is literally lined with kids hanging out when school's not in session.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>If you are traveling by car, it is very easy to get into the district — the two major highways on the South Side cut right through it. From the <hi rend="bold">Chicago Skyway</hi> (I-90), heading northbound, there are exits at 73rd, Stony Island Ave, 87th, and 95th (<hi rend="italic">there are no exits heading southbound from the Dan Ryan junction to 92nd St, past the tollbooth</hi>). Off the <hi rend="bold">Dan Ryan</hi> (I-94), the principal exits are at 67th, 71st, 76th, 79th, and 87th. The major relevant east-west routes within the area occur every mile, at 71st, 79th, and 87th. For north-south travel within the district, the most useful routes are Cottage Grove Ave, Stony Island Ave (by far the widest route), and to a lesser extent South Chicago Ave.</p>

<p>Parking is widely available in each neighborhood. It is a relatively poor section of the city, and is far enough away from the city center that on-street parking should be easy to find. The only main streets lacking on street parking are in South Shore, along 71st and Exchange.</p>

<head>By rail</head>
<p>Rail is not the best way to visit this section of the city, as you will need to take bus transfers wherever you want to go.</p>

<p>The one relevant CTA line, the <hi rend="bold">Red Line</hi>, passes through the western side of Greater Grand and Chatham, right in the center of the Dan Ryan.</p>

<p>The <hi rend="bold">Metra Electric Main Line</hi> runs straight from Millenium Station <ref target="Chicago/Loop">downtown</ref> through the heart of the district and, while the trains run less regularly, can be more convenient than the CTA.</p>

<p>For visiting South Shore, on the other hand, Metra is the best way to go, as the <hi rend="bold">Electric South Chicago Branch</hi> runs right on top of the main strip the entire way through the neighborhood, with a very convenient stop right by the South Shore Cultural Center.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>Bus, while certainly less convenient than driving, is the most widely used mode of transport throughout most of the district. Route #4 runs the length of Cottage Grove Ave from Chicago State University up King Drive all the way to Michigan Ave in the <ref target="Chicago/Loop">Loop</ref>. Route #4 runs the length of Cottage Grove Ave from Chicago State University through <ref target="Chicago/Hyde%20Park">Hyde Park</ref>, and all the way to Michigan Ave in the <ref target="Chicago/Loop">Loop</ref>. #6 runs express from downtown to 47th Street running through Kenwood/Hyde Park south to Jackson Park South Shore ending at 79th Street and South Shore Drive. This route provides front door access to the South Shore Cultural Center. #28 runs along Stony Island Ave from eastern Hyde Park all the way to 103rd St on the <ref target="Chicago/Far%20Southeast%20Side">Far Southeast Side</ref>. #14 runs from express Downtown to 67th Street and then South along Jeffery Boulevard to all the way to 103rd St on the <ref target="Chicago/Far%20Southeast%20Side">Far Southeast Side</ref>. #15 runs just like #14 except it is a local route running from the CTA Red Line at 47th Street then east along 51st Street/Hyde Park Boulevard and then down Lake Park Avenue/Stony Island Avenue through the Hyde Park neighborhood to Jeffrey Boulevard all the way to 103rd Street as well.</p>
<p>For traveling east-west, the routes are simple, following the main roads: #67 along 67th St, #71 along 71st St, #75 along 75th, #79 along 79th St and #87 along 87th St.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bronzeville Childrens Museum</hi>, 9301 S Stony Island Ave, ☏ +1-773-721-9301 . Tu-Sa 10AM-2PM. The only African American children's museum in the country is named after the Bronzeville neighborhood even though it is much further south. $5. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">New Regal Theater</hi> (Old Avalon Theater), 1641 E 79th St. Built in 1927 as one of the South Side's most impressive movie palaces, done up in ornate Moorish Revival style, this theater was in operation well past the riots and up into the late 1970s. Since then, the theater has served as a church, and then a performance venue, before finally shuttering its doors in 2003. In 2008, however, the building caught a glimmer of new hope with a purchase by new owners hoping to turn the building into a new cultural venue. The idea hasn't quite taken hold yet, but there is reason to feel optimistic about this Chicago Landmark's long-term future. If you are not getting in for an event in the meantime (and believe it, the interior is in fabulous shape and incredibly beautiful), check out the cool mural on the side and ponder the building's incredible musical history; the venue's performers truly include every single world class blues, jazz, rhythm &amp; blues, funk, and soul musician you can think of: John Coltrane, Count Basie, Nat King Cole, Sammy Davis Jr, Earth Wind &amp; Fire, Duke Ellington, Ella Fitzgerald, the Supremes, Gladys Knight, the Isley Brothers, Billie Holiday, Isaac Hayes, B.B. King, Miles Davis, Stevie Wonder, Marvin Gaye, and so on. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Oak Woods Cemetery</hi>, 1035 E 67th St, ☏ +1-773-288-3800 . M-F 8:30AM-4:15PM, Sa Su 8:30AM-sundown. Were it not for the somber atmosphere, Oak Woods would probably be one of Chicago's favorite parks as it is beautifully laid out and has four attractive elongated ponds. The cemetery is the final resting place of many of the South Side's most famous residents, including Olympian runner Jesse Owens, nuclear physicist Enrico Fermi, civil rights leader Ida B. Wells, Mayor William Hale Thompson (perhaps Chicago's most eccentric leader), and the first black mayor of Chicago, Harold Washington Jr. One of the more striking monuments is the memorial to the overwhelming <hi rend="italic">6,000</hi> Confederate prisoners of war who died at Camp Douglas (on the site of the present day Illinois Institute of Technology in <ref target="Chicago/Bronzeville">Bronzeville</ref>). The mayors' graves are located along the northwest shore of the largest lake (Symphony Lake). If Illinois' ugly political world interests you, you can find "Senator" Roland Burris' ostentatious monument/grave prepared in advance, with a list of his "achievements."</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">South Shore Cultural Center</hi> (SSCC), 7059 S Shore Dr, ☏ +1-773-256-0149 . Su-F 9AM-6PM, Sa 9AM-5PM. An enormous South Side landmark, which once served as the private golf clubhouse — closed to African-Americans. Times have changed. The country club went bankrupt, and the golf course and tremendous building were bought by the Chicago Park District, and then converted into a beautiful and extravagant community center with large chandeliers and floor to ceiling windows. The SSCC hosts plays, live music, and dance performances. It's no stranger to fame, having hosted the wedding receptions of countless South Side notables, including the Obamas; the exterior also served as the "Palace Hotel Ballroom" for the Blues Brothers' big gig. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">St Michael the Archangel Church</hi>, 8231 South Shore Dr, ☏ +1-773-221-0212 . Perhaps the grandest example of the Polish Cathedral style on the South Side is this towering neogothic church, built in 1909. Of course, economic-driven neighborhood change has meant the end of the Polish steelworker demographic in this parish, which is now heavily Latino. The interior is very impressive — look especially for the hand-sculpted statue of St Michael defeating Lucifer, the oak and marble communion rail, and the enormous, beautiful German-made stained glass windows. </item>
</list>
</text>
