<text id="autogum_whow_doc472" title="Grow Dandelions" shortTile="grow-dandelions" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-05-30" dateModified="2019-10-01" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Grow-Dandelions" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Grow Dandelions</head><p>Dandelions are known for their bright yellow flowers, dark green leaves, and seed-spreading puffballs that children love to blow on! While they are largely considered to be weeds, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Harvest_Dandelions">dandelions can be harvested</ref> and used in many ways, and may possibly have some health benefits. <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Eat-Dandelions">Dandelions are edible</ref> from root to flower, and people often use them in herbal medicine to treat conditions of the liver, bile ducts, and gallbladder, as well as for minor problems like bloating and indigestion. Start growing dandelions in your garden or in pots to ensure that you always have a supply of these useful plants on hand!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Planting Dandelion Seeds</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Gather or purchase some seeds. Dandelions grow wild and you can easily harvest their seeds when the plant is in the seed phase. This is when the top of the plant looks like a puffball. Each of the little feathery strands has a seed attached to it, so you can collect these in a bag or other small container and take them home for planting. If you prefer to purchase dandelion seeds, then check your local garden center or look for seeds online. <figure rend="Grow Dandelions Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Wild dandelion greens may have a bitter taste, while cultivated dandelion greens will not be as bitter.</item></list></item>
<item>Choose a sunny location to grow your dandelions. Dandelions do best when they have full sunlight for a large part of the day, so choose a sunny location in your garden or plan to place potted dandelions in a sunny window. Try going out in your yard a few times throughout the day to scope out the sunniest spot. <figure rend="Grow Dandelions Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, you could go outside at 8 am, 12 pm, and 4 pm and note where the sun is at by placing a few rocks on the edges of where the sun is shining.</item>
<item>If you will mainly be using dandelions for their leaves, then growing them in partial shade is a better option. This will help to reduce the bitterness of the leaves and the number of flowers it produces.</item></list></item>
<item>Sow the seeds for flowers or greens. The dandelion seed will need to be  apart for flowers and  apart for greens. Flowers will need more room than baby dandelion greens because they will have deeper roots. Measure the distance between your seeds to ensure that they will have plenty of room. <figure rend="Grow Dandelions Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Leave the seeds uncovered if you are planting indoors.</item>
<item>You will not need to worry about the seeds getting blown out. Dandelions do best in a shallow bed.</item>
<item>Do not plant your dandelions in an area with poor drainage or a tightly packed soil, such as clay.</item>
<item>Use a garden fork to loosen the soil before you plant if it is tightly packed. Use a loosely packed potting soil with added compost as the growing medium.</item></list></item>
<item>Water the dandelions regularly. Dandelions need a lot of water to thrive, so plan to water them regularly. However, do not water them too much. Water just enough so that the soil feels moist. Check the soil by poking your finger into it once every 2 to 3 days. If the soil feels moist, then they do not need water yet. If it feels dry, then give them some water. <figure rend="Grow Dandelions Step 4.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Harvesting Dandelions</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Cut leaves near the base of the plant. Use a sharp pair of garden shears to snip the leaves away from the base of the plant. Cut as many individual leaves as needed or cut the entire rosette of greens from the root. You may also leave the smaller leaves to continue growing if desired. <figure rend="Grow Dandelions Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can harvest the dandelion greens when they are small for the mildest flavor, or wait until they are larger if you prefer a bitter flavor.</item></list></item>
<item>Cut flowers when they have just opened. If left too long, dandelion flowers will convert to seed distributing puffballs. This means that you might end up with an infestation of dandelions rather than a controlled crop of them. To prevent this from happening, cut the dandelion flowers right after they bloom. Use a pair of sharp garden shears to cut the flowers at the base of the stem near the leaves. <figure rend="Grow Dandelions Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can cut the flower from the stem after harvesting and discard the stems.</item></list></item>
<item>Dig up roots after the flowers have bloomed. The roots of the dandelion should be large enough to harvest after the flowers have bloomed, but you can even harvest roots of dandelions that have gone to seed. To harvest the roots, insert a garden spade into the ground about  from the base of the dandelion. Dig around the dandelion to loosen the dirt and make it easier to pull up, and then pull the dandelion root out of the ground. <figure rend="Grow Dandelions Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You may be able to pull up younger dandelion roots without digging since they tend to be shallower than mature ones.</item>
<item>Dandelions are perennials in most climates. Leave the plant in place if you want to have it come back every year.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Using Dandelions</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Add fresh dandelion greens to salads, smoothies, and stir-fry dishes. Young, small dandelion greens, also known as baby dandelion greens, are mild in flavor, so they are great in salads and smoothies. However, mature dandelion greens (larger ones) will taste best if you stir-fry them with other ingredients and seasonings, because they can have a bitter flavor. <figure rend="Grow Dandelions Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try sautéing dandelion greens with onions and garlic and a little bit of olive oil for a healthy veggie side dish.</item></list></item>
<item>Use new dandelion flowers to make beer, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make-Dandelion-Wine">wine</ref>, and jelly. If you like to make your own beer or wine, look up recipes for beer or wine made with dandelions. You can also use the flowers to make a jelly that you can spread on toast. <figure rend="Grow Dandelions Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can also <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Fry-Dandelions">fry dandelion flowers</ref> for a tasty snack!</item></list></item>
<item>Dry dandelion roots and use them for tea. The roots of dandelions are often used to make tea. Dry the roots using a food dehydrator or by putting them out in the sun on a baking sheet. Then, chop the roots up into  pieces and store them in a glass jar. <figure rend="Grow Dandelions Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>To make a cup of dandelion tea, place 1 teaspoon of the dried root pieces into  of boiling water and let it steep for 3 to 5 minutes. Strain the tea and enjoy once it is cool enough to drink!</item></list></item></list>
<head>Things You’ll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Dandelion seeds</item>
<item>Potting soil</item>
<item>Pot or garden bed</item>
<item>Garden spade</item>
<item>Garden shears or scissors</item></list>
</text>
