<text id="autogum_interview_doc229" title="part1_CanadaVOTES: Libertarian John Kittridge in St. Paul&amp;apos;s" shortTile="partcanadavotes-libertarian" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-10-10" dateModified="2016-07-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CanadaVOTES%3A_Libertarian_John_Kittridge_in_St._Paul%27s" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">As you campaign around your riding, it's likely that some issues are mentioned more often by voters, than other issues. What would you say are the three hottest topics this election, in your riding? What would you and your party do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>People in St Paul's seem to be most concerned about the economy (and pensions), health care and the environment.</p>
<p><list type="ordered"><item>The economy would benefit from lower taxes, less government spending and meddling. Entrepreneurship could flourish and the economy grow. The political decision-making process cannot effectively be used to manage an economy. Libertarians would cease the pandering for votes, stop all corporate welfare, allow researchers and new business creators to benefit from their achievements (eliminating capital gains and dividend taxation among other things), dramatically simplify regulations, eliminate the restrictions on foreign investment in Canada, eliminate marketing boards, cut the civil service bureaucracy, etc. etc., etc. Short term, the concentration would be waste, dysfunctional and inappropriate programme spending and efficiency (easy targets in this environment). Longer term a broader and deeper elimination of programmes and an opening up of the market place to more options, competitors and innovators.</item>
<item>Health care, in particular will benefit from new options, competition and an arena for open innovation. There is no moral, ethical, economic or technical justification for continuing to criminalize the open provision of health care options. Too many of our vulnerable parents, children, spouses, friends and neighbours are at risk to ignore the quality of care any longer simply to ensure that all Canadians have access to the same (poor) execution.</item>
<item>The environment is somewhat different.</item></list></p>
<p>Where pollution and other environmental degradation is at issue we consider the problem in two aspects: (i) government controlled environment (crown lands, waterways, underground mineral rights, airspace, 200-mile-limit ocean waters off our coastline, etc.) and (ii) private property.</p>
<p>With respect to (i) Canadians and all other statist countries suffer the typical (and inevitable) "tragedy of the commons." (When everybody owns it nobody owns it and it is treated accordingly. If and when legislation is passed to control it, the regulations are politically designed, favour special interest groups for political gain and the associated shenanigans produce an even worse outcome than existed prior to action being taken.) Hence clear-cutting, hence goldmine tailings in beautiful rivers, hence irrigation scemes <hi rend="italic">[sic]</hi> despoiling wetlands, etc., etc.!</p>
<p>Real owners care AND are interested in the long term to cover their children's children or their corporation's future growth and success! Libertarians would sell these assets and create an ownership environment that would foster environmentalism, conservation and rational exploitation and / or enjoyment of natural resources.</p>
<p>With respect to (ii) our laws are adequate (or should be and certainly can be made to be) to protect private property from polluters and despoilers, whether individuals or corporations. Unfortunately they currently are not adequate to protect us from our own government's encroachment, its' pandering of rent seekers, or its' political decision making. Hence pig farms in your back yard, hence mineshafts sunk in your back forty, hence a high rise or monster home erected across the street, etc., etc.!</p>
</text>
