<text id="autogum_voyage_doc407" title="Severna Park" shortTile="severna-park" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=32258" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Severna Park</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Severna Park</hi> is a town in <ref target="Anne%20Arundel%20County">Anne Arundel County</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>This town is located in central Maryland, located near the Major City of Baltimore. It is a suburban town with plenty of retail resources and one of the better public school systems in the state. </p>
<head>By car</head>
<p>From the north</p>
<p>There are quite a few ways to get into Severna Park but the most commonly used route involves taking an exit off of I-97 which will bring you to Ritchie Highway road, one of the more central roads in Severna Park. </p>

<p>From the South</p>
<p>You will most likely find yourself traveling on I-95 until you pass through the Washington D.C. area, then you'll want to take the US-50 exit towards Annapolis and then the same exit leading to Ritchie Highway</p>

<head>By air</head>
<p>The Airport closest to Severna Park, is the Baltimore Washington International Airport. It is located about 25 minutes away from Severna Park, assuming there is no major traffic. Most airports will have direct flights to BWI as it is a major airport. </p>
<p>You can also fly into the Washington Dulles International Airport located near southern D.C. and close to Virginia. It is a little over an hours time away from Severna Park, but is most likely your destination if you are traveling Internationally.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<p>Because the town is so small, the best and most effective way to get around town is by car. There are also buses that circulate through the town. Also, in the summer when the weather is nice you can get most places in town by walking to them.</p>

<head>Do</head>
<p>Kinder Park - </p>

<p>This public park offers free use during the day for anyone who wants to play any type of sporting event or just spend a nice day in the park. Kinder park is also home to the local Boy Scout meeting halls and to other local events throughout the year. </p>

<p>B&amp;B Bike Trail - </p>

<p>This trail runs throughout the entire town and can be followed all the way through to Annapolis, MD. There are many stops along the way with benches if you need to rest, and the trail lets off at some of the more commercial parts of town.</p>

<head>Buy</head>

<p>Marley Station Shopping Mall 7900 Ritchie Highway - </p>

<p>Marley Station is a medium sized retail mall that can be found on the outskirts of Severna Park. It contains over 100 in-store shops, as well as a few restaurants and a movie theater. There is ample parking located all around the mall and there are three main department stores that help make up the mall. (JcPenny, Sears, Macy's). </p>

<p>Ritchie Highway Shopping Plaza - </p>

<p>This shopping plaza includes over 20 family owned businesses that offer a variety of services from shoes, to salons and boutiques, and more.</p>

<head>Eat</head>

<p>Bill Bateman's Bistro (Best Buffalo Wings in town!) 566 Gov. Ritchie Highway - </p>
<p>This family style restaurant is located in one of the towns most central shopping plazas. It offers great service, delicious food, and some of the best buffalo wings you'll probably ever have. Bateman's has won numerous awards for their Buffalo wing recipes. There is ample parking and a decently sized menu. There is also a bar in the middle of the restaurant and many television sets tuned to sports games throughout the place. </p>

<p>Kyoto Steakhouse 568 Ritchie Highway - </p>
<p>If you are a fan of Japanese cuisine with a western steakhouse mixture than this place is for you. There are two styles of seating. You can sit in an old fashioned Japanese style lounge, or you can get one of the tables that have a grill right on them. It is a great place to have a fun meal and see your food get cooked right in front of your eyes.</p>

<p>Romilos Pizzeria 478A Ritchie Highway - </p>
<p>This old fashioned Greek pizzeria has been a local favorite for over 15 years. There is a large dinning area and also a plentiful takeout menu that includes pizza, pasta, wings, and other traditional Greek dishes. It is the perfect place for Friday night dinners.</p>

<head>Sleep</head>
<p>While there are no hotels or motels in Severna Park there are plenty that are within a few minutes from the town. </p>

<p>Valencia Motel &amp; Efficiencies 10131 Washington Blvd N, Laurel, MD 20723 - </p>
<p>Offers cable TV, double sized beds, free parking, hot showers, and accepts most major credit cards.</p>
</text>
