<text id="autogum_bio_doc177" title="Soshihiro Satake" shortTile="soshihiro-satake" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-06-07" dateModified="2019-10-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soshihiro_Satake" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Soshihiro Satake</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Antonio Satake</hi>, born <hi rend="bold">Soshihiro Satake</hi>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-onzuka-2">[2]</ref> was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Japan">Japanese</ref>-born <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brazil">Brazilian</ref> martial artist and teacher.  One of the teachers of Brazilian martial artist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luiz_França">Luiz França</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> together with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geo_Omori">Geo Omori</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mitsuyo_Maeda">Mitsuyo Maeda</ref>, Satake was one of the primary founders of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brazilian_jiu-jitsu">Brazilian jiu-jitsu</ref> (BJJ).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-BJJ_Heroes-4">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-BJJ-5">[5]</ref>  He pioneered <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Judo">judo</ref> in Brazil, the United Kingdom, and other countries.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEStanlei200222-25-6">[6]</ref></p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Satake started fighting as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sumo">sumo</ref> wrestler, then he joined the Kudokan dojo academy and competed in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Judo">judo</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jujutsu">jujutsu</ref> for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kanō_Jigorō">Kanō Jigorō</ref>, the founder of judo, and for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kodokan">Kodokan</ref> institute.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-BJJ_Heroes-4">[4]</ref>  With Mitsuyo Maeda, Satake formed the head of the second generation of Kodokan judoka, which had replaced the first by the beginning of the 20th century.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEStanlei200233–34-7">[7]</ref>  Satake, at 175 centimetres (69in) and 80 kilograms (180lb), was unmatched in amateur sumo but admitted that he himself was not able to match Maeda in judo.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEStanlei200233–34-7">[7]</ref>  At that time, there were few graduated Kodokan judoka.  Maeda and Satake were the top graduated professors at Waseda University, both <hi rend="italic">sandan</hi> (3rd <hi rend="italic">dan</hi>), along with Matsuhiro Ritaro (<hi rend="italic">nidan</hi> or 2nd <hi rend="italic">dan</hi>) and six other <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shodan_(rank)">shodan</ref></hi> (1st <hi rend="italic">dan</hi>).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEStanlei200236–37-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>In 1903, a senior Kodokan instructor named <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yamashita_Yoshitsugu">Yamashita Yoshitsugu</ref> traveled to the United States at the request of the Seattle businessman <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samuel_Hill">Sam Hill</ref>.  In Washington, DC, Yamashita's students included <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theodore_Roosevelt">Theodore Roosevelt</ref> and other prominent Americans.  At Roosevelt's request, Yamashita also taught judo at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Naval_Academy">US Naval Academy</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref>  Capitalizing on the publicity, the Japanese Legation in the USA asked the Kodokan to send more judo teachers to America, providing continuity to Yamashita's work.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tsunejiro_Tomita">Tsunejiro Tomita</ref> reluctantly accepted the task; Maeda and Satake embraced the opportunity.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEStanlei200239–41-10">[10]</ref>  Tomita, Maeda, and Satake sailed from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yokohama">Yokohama</ref> on 16 November 1904, and arrived in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_York_City">New York City</ref> on 8 December 1904.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-onzuka-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-green-11">[11]</ref></p>
<p>Before traveling to Europe, Maeda and Satake went to Cuba along with Akitaro Ono and Tokugoro Ito.  All of them engaged in combats.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEStanlei200253-12">[12]</ref>  On 8 February 1907, Maeda and Satake arrived in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liverpool,_England">Liverpool, England</ref>.  Apparently they had planned to join up with Akitaro Ono, who had gone to London to wrestle for promoter William Bankier in London music halls.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-green-11">[11]</ref>  During September 1909, a Japanese calling himself 'Nobu Taka' arrived in Mexico City for the purpose of challenging Maeda for what the <hi rend="italic">Mexican Herald</hi> said would be the world jujutsu championship.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref>  After several months of public wrangling, Taka and Maeda met at the Colon Theater on November 16, 1909; Taka won.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref>  There was an immediate rematch, and four days later, Maeda was pronounced the champion.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref>  It was later revealed that Taka was, in fact, Soishiro Satake.  During 1911, Maeda and Satake were joined in Cuba by Akitaro Ono and Tokugoro Ito. The four men were known as the 'Four Kings of Cuba.'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEStanlei200253-12">[12]</ref>  The Four Kings were very popular in Cuba, and the Japanese media were proud of the reputation they were bringing to judo and Japan.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[16]</ref></p>
<p>In 1913 Maeda and Satake went to El Salvador, Costa Rica, Honduras, Panama, Colombia, Ecuador and Peru.  In El Salvador, the president was assassinated while they were there, and in Panama, the Americans tried to pay Maeda to lose, and, in response, they kept moving south.  In Peru they met Laku, a Japanese jujutsuka who taught the military, and invited him to join them.  They were then joined by Okura in Chile, and by Shimitsu in Argentina.  The troupe arrived  in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Porto_Alegre">Porto Alegre</ref> on 14 November 1914.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-green-11">[11]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEStanlei200267-17">[17]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-eros-18">[18]</ref> and then moved throughout the country for a year.  On 26 August 1915, Maeda, Satake, Okura, Shimitsu, and Laku were at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Recife">Recife</ref>, during October 1915, they were in Belém, finally arriving in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manaus">Manaus</ref> in the Brazilian state of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amazonas_(Brazilian_state)">Amazonas</ref> on 18 December 1915.  Tokugoro Ito arrived some time later.  On 20 December 1915, the first demonstration in Belém took place at the Theatro Politheama.  The <hi rend="italic">O Tempo</hi> newspaper announced the event, stating that Conde Koma would show the main <hi rend="italic">jiu-jitsu</hi> techniques, excepting the prohibited ones. He would also demonstrate self-defense techniques.  After that, the troupe would be accepting challenges from the crowd, and there would be the first <hi rend="italic">sensational</hi> match of <hi rend="italic">jiu-jitsu</hi> between Shimitsu (champion of Argentina) and Laku (Peruvian military professor).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEStanlei200269–73-19">[19]</ref>  On 22 December 1915, according to <hi rend="italic">O Tempo</hi>, <hi rend="italic">jiu-jitsu</hi> world champion Maeda, head of the Japanese troupe, and Satake, New York champion, performed an enthusiastic and sensational <hi rend="italic">jiu-jitsu</hi> match.  On the same day, Nagib Assef, an Australian Greco-Roman wrestling champion of Turkish origin, challenged Maeda.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEStanlei200269–73-19">[19]</ref></p>
<p>On 8 January 1916, Maeda, Okura, and Shimitsu boarded the SS <hi rend="italic">Antony</hi> and left for Liverpool.  Tokugoro Ito went to Los Angeles.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-20">[20]</ref>  Satake and Laku stayed in Manaus teaching, according to <hi rend="italic">O Tempo</hi>, <hi rend="italic">jiu-jitsu</hi>.  After 15 years together, Maeda and Satake had finally split up.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-green-11">[11]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEStanlei200269–73-19">[19]</ref>  Of this last trip to Europe, little is known.  Maeda went from England to Portugal, Spain, and France, coming back to Brazil in 1917 alone.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEStanlei200269–73-19">[19]</ref>  Satake would become the founder, in 1914, of the first historically registered judo academy in Brazil.  He and Maeda are considered the pioneers of judo in Brazil.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEStanlei200233–34-7">[7]</ref>  In January 1916, Satake won the first jiu-jitsu tournament in the Amazon.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-onzuka-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-BJJ-5">[5]</ref>  In Manaus Satake opened his own academy in 1916, at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atlético_Rio_Negro_Clube">Atlético Rio Negro Clube</ref>, which became the first Japanese to open a judo and jiu-jitsu academy in Brazil.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-onzuka-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-BJJ_Heroes-4">[4]</ref>  Satake became a Brazilian citizen and changed his name to Antônio Soshihiro Satake.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-BJJ_Heroes-4">[4]</ref>  On 19 September 1921, Satake, Maeda, and Okura were briefly in New York City.  They were aboard the Booth Line steamship SS <hi rend="italic">Polycarp</hi>.  All three men listed their occupations as professors of "juitso".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-21">[21]</ref>  After leaving New York, the three men went to the Caribbean, where they stayed from September to December 1921.  In Havana, Satake and Maeda took part in some contests.  Their opponents included Paul Alvarez, who wrestled as Espanol Icognito.  Alvarez defeated Satake and Yako Okura—the latter being billed as a former instructor at the Chilean Naval Academy—before being himself beaten by Maeda.  Maeda also defeated a Cuban boxer called Jose Ibarra, and a French wrestler called Fournier.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-22">[22]</ref></p>
<p>In 1922, Satake embarked to Europe and nothing was known about him after that.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-onzuka-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-BJJ-5">[5]</ref></p>
</text>
