<text id="autogum_news_doc225" title="Wikileaks cable disclosure shows Arab fears of Iranian ambitions" shortTile="wikileaks-cable-disclosure" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-11-29" dateModified="2015-10-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikileaks_cable_disclosure_shows_Arab_fears_of_Iranian_ambitions" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikileaks cable disclosure shows Arab fears of Iranian ambitions</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 30, 2010</hi></p>
<p>Sunday night's release of leaked <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> diplomatic cables shows widespread concern in the Arab world over <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iran">Iran</ref>'s ambitions to build a "Persian Empire in the 21st Century".</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikileaks">Wikileaks</ref>, so far, have released under 300 of the quarter million plus diplomatic communications posted to them on a memory stick. The small sample shows, over several months, the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Arab_Emirates">United Arab Emirates</ref> (UAE), <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kuwait">Kuwait</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bahrain">Bahrain</ref> asserting that further sanctions against Iran will likely have no effect.</p>
<figure><caption>File photo of US General David Petraeus.</caption></figure>
<p>Early November last year, General <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20Petraeus">David Petraeus</ref> discussed the situation with King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hamad%20ibn%20Isa%20Al%20Khalifa">Hamad</ref> of Bahrain, who argued for the use of force to thwart Iran's nuclear ambitions; stating: "The danger of letting it go on is greater than the danger of stopping it."</p>
<p>In that meeting concern was expressed that more Arab involvement in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iraq">Iraq</ref> was needed to frustrate Iranian plans. Petraeus was told Bahrain sought <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Egypt">Egyptians</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Saudi_Arabia">Saudis</ref> support, but talks with the latter revealed no interest in taking a leading rôle.</p>
<p>The King did welcome the prospect of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/India">India</ref> becoming involved in the region as a stabilising influence.</p>
<p>A mid-December meeting between Crown Prince <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mohammed%20bin%20Zayed%20Al%20Nahyan">Mohammed bin Zayed Al Nahyan</ref> of the UAE and US Deputy Secretary of Energy <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniel%20Poneman">Daniel Poneman</ref> saw the subject brought up again. In a discussion that touched on the two countries renewable energy plans, and reliable movement of oil through the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Strait_of_Hormuz">Strait of Hormuz</ref>, the Prince asserted Iran saw itself as spearheading a campaign for a "Persian Empire in the 21st Century." Alleging Iran has established "emirates" in Kuwait, Bahrain, Eastern Saudi Arabia, Southern Iraq, Yemen, and South <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lebanon">Lebanon</ref>, his picture of Iranian nuclear ambitions is "Al-Qaeda is not going to get a nuclear bomb; Iran is a matter of time."
<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Special:FilePath/Iran_strait_of_hormuz_2004.jpg">File:Iran strait of hormuz 2004.jpg</ref></p><figure><caption>Map of the Strait of Homuz.<hi rend="italic">(Image <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Template:Missing_image/message">missing</ref> from commons: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/File:Iran_strait_of_hormuz_2004.jpg">image</ref>; <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Special:Log?page=File%3AIran+strait+of+hormuz+2004.jpg">log</ref>)</hi></caption></figure>
<p>The Prince was keen to stress that those in power are the same people who, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iran%20hostage%20crisis">in 1979, seized the US embassy in Tehran</ref>.</p>
<p>Subsequent talks between a congressional appropriations sub-committee and UAE's Foreign Minister were the scene of equally serious predictions. The sub-committee, consisting of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nita%20Lowey">Nita Lowey</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tom%20Cole">Tom Cole</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barbara%20Lee">Barbara Lee</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Donna%20Edwards">Donna Edwards</ref>, heard from Sheikh <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abdullah%20bin%20Zayed%20Al%20Nahyan">Abdullah bin Zayed Al Nahyan</ref> that if Iran became a nuclear state the rest of the region would likely follow suit.</p>
<p>Plans to keep the fifteen-millions-plus barrels of oil passing through the Strait of Hormuz each day moving were discussed. Whilst keen to weaken Iranian ties with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China">China</ref>, Sheikh Abdullah stressed the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_dollar">US$</ref>50 billion in trade between the two; this being considered an obstacle to China backing, and enforcing, a stronger sanctions regime.</p>
<p>The sub-committee's Emirates host, like many in the region, stated progress on the Israeli peace process was a good route to de-escalation.</p>
<p>A meeting in February this year with Kuwaiti Interior Minister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jaber%20Al-Khaled%20Al%20Sabah">Jaber Al-Khaled Al Sabah</ref> was the scene of comparable warnings. Alongside discussions on travel restrictions to be enforced against former Guantanamo Bay detainees, he described Iran as the "beating heart" of Islamic Extremism.</p>
<p>Concerns over Iran's involvement in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Yemen">Yemen</ref> were discussed, with the minister saying Iran is intent on exporting its revolution; that its nuclear ambitions can only be thwarted by force.</p>
<p>Updating the US on perceived Iranian actions, he claimed they were attempting to infiltrate Egypt by recruiting the poor. And, they were becoming involved in the drugs trade, shipping narcotics into Yemen to fund militants.</p>
<p>The cable on the Kuwait meeting closes referring recipients to a wiki page: http://www.intelink.sgov.gov/wiki/Portal:Kuwait. <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> has been informed this is a page on the US intelligence community's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intellipedia">Intellipedia</ref>; an internally-maintained project, based on the same technology as <hi rend="italic">Wikipedia</hi>, and intended for use in building intelligence dossiers on countries, regions, their politicians, diplomats, plus political and terrorist groups.</p>
<p>A cable originating in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/London">London</ref> from January this year is corroborated by later U.S. news reports; hinting that the Iranian government may indeed be using tactics more reminiscent of the cold-war.</p>
<p>In the opening weeks of the year, London-based <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Voice_of_America">Voice of America</ref> commentator Ali Reza Nourizadeh was advised that Mohammed Reza Sadeqinia intended to target him for assassination, along with others. Sadeqinia was previously arrested in California, and prosecuted for attempting to hire a hit man. The target at that time was reported to be Iranian-American broadcaster Jamshid Sharmahd, one of the main figures behind Tondar — a loose collection of in-exile Iranians opposed to the current regime.</p>
<p>Tehran insists Tondar is a terrorist organisation, accusing it of being responsible for a 2008 bombing that killed 14.</p>
<p>Sadeqinia, who worked as a painter in Ann Arbour, was arrested on July 28, 2009 near Los Angeles International Airport in possession of thousands of dollars and an Iranian passport. FBI investigations into his possible Iranian government ties were still ongoing a month before his scheduled release in July this year. </p>
<p>Found guilty by Los Angeles Superior Court of attempting to hire someone to murder Sharmahd, he had been expected to spend around a year in jail. Tondar spokesman Iman Afar, in the lead up to Sedeqina's release, expressed concern for his own safety and that of others in the L.A. area.</p>
</text>
