<text id="autogum_bio_doc367" title="Mirza Ghiyas Beg" shortTile="mirza-ghiyas-beg" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-01-23" dateModified="2019-08-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mirza_Ghiyas_Beg" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Mirza Ghiyas Beg</head><hi rend="bold">Warning:</hi> Page using <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Infobox_officeholder">Template:Infobox officeholder</ref> with unknown parameter "religion" (this message is shown only in preview).
<p><hi rend="bold">Mirza Ghiyas Beg</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Urdu">Urdu</ref>: مرزا غياث بيگ), also known by his title of <hi rend="bold">I'timad-ud-Daulah</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Persian_language">Persian</ref>: اعتمادالسلطنه آگهی الدوله‎), was an important <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Persian_people">Persian</ref> official in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mughal_empire">Mughal empire</ref>, whose children served as wives, mothers, and generals of the Mughal emperors.</p>
<p>Born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tehran">Tehran</ref>, Ghiyas Beg belonged to a family of poets and high officials. Nevertheless, his fortunes fell into disfavor after the death of his father in 1576. Along with his pregnant wife Asmat Begum, and his three children, they immigrated to India. There he was received by the Mughal emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Akbar">Akbar</ref> (r. 1556-1605), and was enrolled into his service. During the latters reign, Ghiyas Beg was appointed treasurer for the province of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kabul">Kabul</ref>.</p>
<p>His fortunes further increased during the reign of Akbar's son and successor Jahangir (r. 1605-1627), who in 1611 married his daughter <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nur_Jahan">Nur Jahan</ref> and appointed Ghiyas Beg as his Prime minister. By 1615, Ghiyas Beg had risen to further prominence, when he was given the status of 6,000 men and was given a standard and drums, a prestige normally restricted for distinguished princes.</p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>Ghiyas Beg was a native of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tehran">Tehran</ref>, and was the youngest son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Khvajeh_Mohammad-Sharif">Khvajeh Mohammad-Sharif</ref>, a poet and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vizier">vizier</ref> of Mohammad Khan Tekkelu and his son Tatar Soltan, who was the governor of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Safavid_dynasty">Safavid</ref> province of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greater_Khorasan">Khorasan</ref>. Mohammad-Sharif was later listed under the service of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tahmasp_I">Shah Tahmasp I</ref> (r. 1524–1576), where he in the start served as the vizier of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yazd">Yazd</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abarkuh">Abarkuh</ref>, and Biabanak for seven years. Thereafter he was appointed as the vizier of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isfahan">Isfahan</ref>, and died there in 1576.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEShokoohy2001594–595-1">[1]</ref> Ghiyas Beg's elder brother, Mohammad-Taher Wasli, was a learned man who composed poetry under the pen name of Wasli.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBanks_Findley19939-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Immigration to India</head>
<p>After the death of Ghiyas' father, his family fell into disgrace. Hoping to improve his family’s fortunes, Ghiyas Beg chose to relocate to India where the Emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Akbar">Akbar</ref>'s court was said to be at the centre of the growing trade industry and cultural scene.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Gold148-3">[3]</ref> Half way along their route the family was attacked by robbers who took from them the remaining meager possessions they had.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Chandra4-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Left with only two mules, Ghiyas Beg, his pregnant wife, and their three children (Mohammad-Sharif, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asaf_Khan_IV">Asaf Khan</ref> and a daughter Sahlia) were forced to take turns riding on the backs of the animals for the remained of their journey. When the family arrived in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kandahar">Kandahar</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asmat_Begam">Asmat Begam</ref> gave birth to their second daughter. The family was so impoverished they feared they would be unable to take care of the newborn baby. Fortunately, the family was taken in by a caravan led by the merchant noble Malik Masud, who would later assist Ghiyas Beg in finding a job in the service of Emperor Akbar. Believing that the child had signaled a change in the family’s fate, she was named <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nur_Jahan">Mehrunnisa</ref>, meaning "sun among women".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Nath_1990_66-5">[5]</ref> Ghiyas Beg was the not the first member of his family to move to India—his cousin Asaf Khan Jafar Beg and the uncle of Asmat Begum, Mirza Ghiyasuddin Ali Asaf Khan, had been enrolled into the provincial assignments of Akbar.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBanks_Findley19938-6">[6]</ref></p>
<head>Service under the Mughal Empire</head>
<p>Ghiyas was later appointed <hi rend="italic">diwan</hi> (treasurer) for the province of Kabul. Due to his astute skills at conducting business he quickly rose through the ranks of the high administrative officials. For his excellent work he was awarded the title of ‘‘Itimad-ud-Daula‘‘ (‘Pillar of the State’) by the emperor.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Chandra4-4">[4]</ref> As a result of his work and promotions, Ghiyas Beg was able to ensure that Mehirunnisa (the future Nur Jahan) would have the best possible education. She became well versed in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arabic_language">Arabic</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Persian_language">Persian</ref>. She also became well versed in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Art">art</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Literature">literature</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Music">music</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dance">dance</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Nath_1990_66-5">[5]</ref></p>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Itmad-Ud-Daulah's_Tomb">Mirza Ghiyas Beg's tomb</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agra">Agra</ref></caption></figure>
<p>Ghiyas' daughter, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mehrunissa">Mehrunissa</ref> (Nur Jahan) married Akbar's son Jahangir in 1611, and his son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abdul_Hasan_Asaf_Khan">Abdul Hasan Asaf Khan</ref> served as a general to Jahangir.</p>
<p>Ghiyas was also the grandfather of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mumtaz_Mahal">Mumtaz Mahal</ref> (originally named Arjumand Bano, daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abdul_Hasan_Asaf_Khan">Abdul Hasan Asaf Khan</ref>), the wife of the emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shah_Jahan">Shah Jahan</ref>, responsible for the building of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taj_Mahal">Taj Mahal</ref>. Jahangir was succeeded by his son Shah Jahan, and Abdul Hasan served as one of Shah Jahan's closest advisors. Shah Jahan married Abdul Hasan's daughter <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mumtaz_Mahal">Arjumand Banu Begum</ref>, Mumtāz Mahal, who was the mother of his four sons, including his successor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aurangzeb">Aurangzeb</ref>. Shah Jahan built the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taj_Mahal">Taj Mahal</ref> to serve as Mumtaz Mahal's tomb.</p>
<head>Death and burial</head>
<p>Ghiyas Beg died near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kangra,_Himachal_Pradesh">Kangra</ref> in 1622 while the Mughal camp was moving towards its summer residence in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kashmir">Kashmir</ref>. His body was carried back to Agra, where he was buried on the right bank of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yamuna_river">Yamuna river</ref>. His burial place still stands till this day, and is known as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tomb_of_I'timād-ud-Daulah">Tomb of I'timad-ud-Daulah</ref>.</p>
</text>
