<text id="autogum_bio_doc494" title="John Jones (martyr)" shortTile="john-jones-martyr" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-12-22" dateModified="2019-04-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Jones_%28martyr%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>John Jones (martyr)</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">John Jones</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Order_of_Friars_Minor">OFM</ref> (d. 12 July 1598), also known as John Buckley, John Griffith, Godfrey Maurice, or Griffith Jones was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franciscan">Franciscan</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Friar">friar</ref>, Roman Catholic priest, and martyr. He was born at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clynnog_Fawr">Clynnog Fawr</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caernarfonshire">Caernarfonshire</ref> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gwynedd">Gwynedd</ref>), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wales">Wales</ref>, and was executed 12 July 1598 at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Southwark">Southwark</ref>, England.  He is one of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Forty_Martyrs_of_England_and_Wales">Forty Martyrs of England and Wales</ref>.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>John Jones was born at Clynnog Fawr, Caernarfonshire (Gwynedd), Wales. He came from a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Recusancy">recusant</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Welsh_people">Welsh</ref> family, who had remained faithful Roman Catholics throughout the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protestant_Reformation">Protestant Reformation</ref>. He was ordained a diocesan priest and was imprisoned in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marshalsea">Marshalsea</ref> under the name Robert Buckley from 1582 to about 1585 for administering the sacraments. By summer 1586 he was out on bond, but in 1587 confined at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wisbech_Castle">Wisbech Castle</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-rambler-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>He left England, either escaped or exiled, in 1590 and at the age of sixty joined the Conventual Franciscans at Pontoise. Afterwards he went to Rome, where he lived among the Observant Friars of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ara_Coeli">Ara Coeli</ref>. After a time he was sent back by his superiors to the English mission; and before leaving Rome he had an audience of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Clement_VIII">Pope Clement VIII</ref> who embraced him and gave him his blessing.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Jones reached <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London">London</ref> about the end of 1592, and stayed temporarily at the house which Father <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Gerard,_S.J.">John Gerard, S.J.</ref>,  had provided for missionary <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Priests">priests</ref>, which house was managed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anne_Line">Anne Line</ref>. Jones ministered to Catholics in the English countryside until his arrest in 1596.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Brown-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>In 1596 the 'priest catcher' <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Topcliffe">Richard Topcliffe</ref> was informed by a spy that Father Jones had visited two Catholics and had said <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mass_(liturgy)">Mass</ref> in their home. It was later shown that the two Catholics were actually in prison when the alleged offense took place. Regardless, Jones was arrested, severely tortured and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scourge">scourged</ref>.  Topcliffe then took Jones to his house where he was further tortured, "To him (Topcliffe) was granted the privilege, unique in the laws of England, or, perhaps, of any country, of maintaining a private rack in his own home for the more convenient examination of prisoners."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Following his torture, Jones was imprisoned for nearly two years.  During this time Jones helped sustain <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Rigby_(saint)">John Rigby</ref> in his faith, who later also became one of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Forty_Martyrs_of_England_and_Wales">Forty Martyrs of England and Wales</ref>. On 3 July 1598 Father Jones was tried on the charge of "going over the seas in the first year of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_I_of_England">Her majesty's</ref> reign (1558) and there being made a priest by the authority from Rome and then returning to England contrary to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Statute">statute</ref>". He was convicted of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/High_treason">high treason</ref> and sentenced to be <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hanged,_drawn_and_quartered">hanged, drawn and quartered</ref>.</p>
<p>A not entirely unsympathetic account of the executions of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Bodey">John Bodey</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Bodey#ade">John Slade</ref> in 1583 was written by someone with the initials "R.B.". Historian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Hungerford_Pollen_(Jesuit)">John Hungerford Pollen S.J.</ref> suggests that it was written by a Catholic and further suggests that "R.B" could be Robert Barnes, who was convicted and hung fifteen years later for harboring John Jones.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> Also arrested for allegedly sheltering priests was Mrs. Jane Wiseman, who had two sons who were Jesuits. Like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Margaret_Clitherow">Margaret Clitherow</ref>, Wiseman refused to enter a plea and was therefore condemned to the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peine_forte_et_dure">peine forte et dure</ref></hi>, although she was eventually pardoned.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-rambler-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<head>Execution</head>
<p>As by this time the people had grown tired of these butcheries, the execution was arranged for an early hour in the morning. The place was St. Thomas's Watering, a small bridge over the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neckinger">Neckinger</ref> crossing the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old_Kent_Road">Old Kent Road</ref>, at the site of the junction of the old Roman road to London with the main line of Watling Street. This marked the boundary of the City of London's authority; it was also a place of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gibbets">gibbets</ref>. The execution was delayed by about an hour because the hangman forgot to bring a rope. Jones used the time to preach to the people and answer their questions. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> When the time came to draw away the cart, the hangman whipped the horses; but they were held back by three or four fellows till Jones had finished what he was saying.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-rambler-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>John Jones' dismembered remains were fixed atop poles on roads leading to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newington,_London">Newington</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lambeth">Lambeth</ref> (now represented by Tabard Street and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lambeth_Road">Lambeth Road</ref> respectively).  His remains were later reputedly removed by at least two Catholic Englishmen, one of whom suffered a long imprisonment for this offense. One of the relics eventually reached <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pontoise">Pontoise</ref>, where Jones had taken his religious vows.</p>
<head>Veneration</head>
<p>John Jones was named Venerable by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Leo_XIII">Pope Leo XIII</ref> and beatified in 1929 by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Pius_XI">Pope Pius XI</ref> with a feast day of 12 July. He was canonized on 25 October 1970 by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Paul_VI">Pope Paul VI</ref> as one of the Forty Martyrs of England and Wales, who are commemorated on that date.</p>
</text>
