<text id="autogum_news_doc020" title="Russian Ksenia Sukhinova crowned Miss World 2008" shortTile="russian-ksenia-sukhinova" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-12-14" dateModified="2015-03-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Russian_Ksenia_Sukhinova_crowned_Miss_World_2008" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Russian Ksenia Sukhinova crowned Miss World 2008</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, December 14, 2008</hi></p>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miss%20World%202008">Miss World 2008</ref> - <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ksenia%20Sukhinova">Ksenia Sukhinova</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Russia">Russia</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ksenia%20Sukhinova">Ksenia Sukhinova</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Russia">Russia</ref>, won the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miss%20World%202008">Miss World 2008</ref> crown on Saturday, outshining 108 other international competitors. She was crowned by her predecessor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miss%20World%202007">Miss World 2007</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zhang%20Zilin">Zhang Zilin</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/People's_Republic_of_China">People's Republic of China</ref>. She pledged to "help people" and said, "I think I can help people and I want to help people and today if I walk away with this crown I will do that." </p>
<p>Sukhinova, 5' 10", said that her immediate ambitions included meeting <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/President%20of%20Russia">Russia's president</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dmitry_Medvedev">Dmitry Medvedev</ref>. She is a student of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tyumen%20State%20Oil%20and%20Gas%20University">Tyumen State Oil and Gas University</ref>, she is enrolled in the Bachelor of Science program, majoring in Engineering.</p>
<p>Sukhinova was born in 1987 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nizhnevartovsk">Nizhnevartovsk</ref>,  in the north west of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Siberia">Siberia</ref>. Sukhinova won the 2007 Miss Russia beauty contest on December 14, in Moscow, where she represented Tyumen. Ksenia surpassed 50 other contestants from all over Russia. She was unable to represent Russia at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miss%20Universe%202008">Miss Universe 2008</ref> due to her college work, so her 2nd runner-up, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vera%20Krasova">Vera Krasova</ref>, replaced her in the contest. Vera placed as the 3rd runner-up to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Venezuela">Venezuela</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dayana%20Mendoza">Dayana Mendoza</ref>.</p>
<p>Miss World 2008, the 58th Miss World was held at Sandton Convention Centre in Johannesburg, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/South_Africa">South Africa</ref> on December 13, 2008. Originally, the pageant was going to take place in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kiev">Kiev</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ukraine">Ukraine</ref>, but because of the ongoing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2008%20Georgia-Russia%20crisis">crisis between Georgia and Russia</ref> in neighboring South Ossetia, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miss%20World%20Organization">Miss World Organization</ref> decided to move the pageant away from Eastern Europe. 109 contestants from all over the world competed for the crown, marking the biggest turnout in the 58 years of the pageant, surpassing the previous record of 107 during Miss World 2004. </p>
<figure><caption>A locator map for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miss%20World">Miss World</ref> showing number of winners from each country.</caption></figure>
<p>She is the second Russian contestant to win Miss World, the first was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Julia%20Kourotchkina">Julia Kourotchkina</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miss%20World%201992">1992</ref>.</p>
<p>The first runner-up was <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/India">India</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parvathy%20Omanakuttan">Parvathy Omanakuttan</ref>, while the second runner-up was <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Trinidad_and_Tobago">Trinidad and Tobago</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gabrielle%20Walcott">Gabrielle Walcott</ref>. The other finalists were <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Angola">Angola</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brigith%20dos%20Santos">Brigith dos Santos</ref> and South Africa's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tansey%20Coetzee">Tansey Coetzee</ref>. There were 15 semi-finalists. </p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Julia%20Morley">Julia Morley</ref>, Miss World committee head, and wife of Miss World creator <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eric%20Morley">Eric Morley</ref> said that the winner has to espouse "beauty with a purpose" with charity via fund raising, being one of the main focuses of the contest. "Over the years the crown that is worn by the winner is a symbol for fundraising. Miss World herself, this year, the winner from China, she's raised over 30 million dollars in her year in office. So perhaps from anything else it does a lot of good things for needy children and old people, which I think is important too." she said.</p>
<p>It was the sixth time that South Africa hosted the pageant, more than any other country except England. The event was aired live to millions of viewers in 187 countries, who, for the first time in the pageant's history, were allowed to vote for one of the semi-finalists through the Internet. An international jury elected the winner. </p>
</text>
