<text id="autogum_voyage_doc1" title="Gruyères" shortTile="gruyres" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=13508" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Gruyères</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Gruyères</hi> is a city in <ref target="Switzerland">Switzerland</ref> and the capital of the district of Gruyère in the canton of <ref target="Fribourg">Fribourg</ref> in <ref target="Switzerland">Switzerland</ref>. Its German name is <hi rend="italic">Greyerz</hi>. This medieval town is an important tourist location in the upper valley of the Saane river, and gives its name to the well-known Gruyère cheese. While its most famous landmark (other than the cheese) is the castle, the old town is lovely as well.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>From <ref target="Lausanne">Lausanne</ref>, <ref target="Vevey">Vevey</ref>, <ref target="Fribourg">Fribourg</ref> you have to follow the highway until you reach <ref target="Bulle">Bulle</ref> and then follow the road to Gruyères.</p>

<head>By train</head>

<p>Gruyères is served by a train coming from the town of <ref target="Bulle">Bulle</ref>, which has regular services to <ref target="Fribourg">Fribourg</ref> and <ref target="Bern">Bern</ref> and thence to the rest of the Swiss railway network. From the railway station it's a 15 minutes walk uphill to the old town area. The cheese factory is just adjacent to the station.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">La Maison du Gruyère</hi>. 09:00-18:00 (19:00 in summer). A cheese factory where Gruyere cheese is made. Fr. 7.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Gruyères Castle</hi> (Château de Gruyères), Rue du Château 8 (Follow the road up through the village to the top of the hill), ☏ +41 26 921 21 02 , ✉ info@chateau-gruyeres.ch . Nov-Mar 10:00-17:00, Apr-Oct 09:00-18:00. This castle was built in the 13th century. It is known mostly for its picturesque views among the hilly landscape. Fr. 12. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">HR Giger Museum</hi>, Château St. Germain, ☏ +41 26 921 22 00 , ✉ info@hrgigermuseum.com . 10:00-18:00, reduced opening hours/days during winter. Here are famous works by the HR Giger, known for his design of the antagonists in the Alien and Species films. Make sure to also check out the HR Giger Bar opposite. Fr. 12.50.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Try ice cream made from the local dairy herds.</item>
<item> Enjoy the scenic "chemin de Gruyère" hike from Gruyères to Charmey through the spectacular Jaun gorge.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Skydive</hi> (EPCO), ☏ +41 79 213 71 38 . Take a dive from 4000 metres alone or tandem. Fr. 430 for a tandem jump.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>
<p>You will be able to eat a cheese fondue made of <hi rend="italic">Gruyère</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Vacherin</hi> in every restaurants of Gruyères. Gruyères is also famous for its double cream which is served with meringues or berries.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hostellerie Saint-Georges Restaurant</hi>, Rue du Bourg 22, ☏ +41 26 921 83 00 . Tu-Su 11:45-18:00, Sa 11:45-20:00. While the food is as ordinary as any other at this very touristy place, it has a glass wall with a very nice view on the surrounding region from the restaurant area.</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">La Fleur de Lys</hi>, Rue du Bourg 14, ☏ +41 26 921 82 82 , ✉ hotelfleurdelys@bluewin.ch . Fr. 120/160 single/double.</item>
</list>


<head>Nearby</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Maison Cailler</hi>, Rue Jules Bellet 7, 1636 Broc (Hourly connections from Bulle to Broc-Fabrique (S60).), ☏ + 41 26 921 59 60 , ✉ maisoncailler@nestle.com . 10:00-17:00 (16:00 during winter). Interactive tour through a chocolate factory and the history of chocolate. You won’t get to see much of the actual production, it’s mostly films and displays, but the chocolate tasting at the end of the tour is definitely the highlight. Fr. 12, free under 16 years when accompanied by an adult. </item>
</list>


<head>Go next</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Fribourg">Fribourg</ref> - capital of the canton of Fribourg in Switzerland</item>
</list>
</text>
