<text id="autogum_interview_doc065" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Mark Everson, U.S. Republican Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-08-18" dateModified="2015-08-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Mark_Everson%2C_U.S._Republican_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How much campaigning have you done so far?</hi></item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Everson</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I have campaigned in 26 counties across <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iowa">Iowa</ref> and also made campaign stops in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_Hampshire">New Hampshire</ref>.  I have been interviewed on radio shows across the country.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What are your thoughts on your fellow Republican presidential candidates?</hi></item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Everson</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I think it is a strong field and that the vigorous policy debate underway in the party is good for the country.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Would you ever consider running as a third party or independent candidate?</hi></item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Everson</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I am running as a Republican and am not contemplating a third party or independent candidacy.</p>
<head id="Media_blackout">Media blackout</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> covered the complaint you filed with the FEC against Fox News in your attempt to be included in the August 6 Debate. In our report, Election Law expert <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard%20Winger">Richard Winger</ref> suggested you file a lawsuit rather than an FEC complaint. Do you have an update on your FEC complaint and might you consider filing a lawsuit if you are excluded from future debates?</hi></item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Everson</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  We have received notice that the FEC has filed the complaint with Fox News, but nothing else. I have written to CNN and the Reagan Foundation requesting inclusion in their September debate. At this time I do not expect to file a lawsuit on this matter.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What is your response to Mr. Winger, who said you had a good case and may have had an opportunity to gain access to the debate if you filed a lawsuit instead of an FEC complaint?</hi>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Everson</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I did look into the possible filing of a law suit and was informed by a prominent election law expert that the chances were quite slim that the courts would intervene in a matter properly before the FEC.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Are you saying that you do not expect to litigate the Fox News matter or do you not expect to file a lawsuit to gain access to future debates? If so, why?</hi>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Everson</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I expect to pursue the FOX matter with the FEC. I will assess future legal actions as events unfold.</p></p></p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Your exclusion from National presidential polls appears to be the biggest detriment to your campaign and effort to appear in debates. Is there anything your campaign can do to include your name in polls to qualify for future debates?</hi></item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Everson</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  We have written the polling companies requesting that I be included in the polls.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Have the polling companies responded to your requests?  If so, what have they said?</hi>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Everson</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  We have not yet heard from the polling companies.</p></p></p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Are you surprised by your exclusion from presidential polls and events or did you expect this when you announced?</hi></item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Everson</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  At this still early stage of the race, I am surprised that participation has been limited to established politicians and individuals already enjoying significant name recognition. The process should be about surfacing issues of importance to the country and who can best tackle the challenges at hand.</p>
</text>
