<text id="autogum_interview_doc380" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Mark Bunker, producer of anti-Scientology website &amp;apos;XenuTV&amp;apos;" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-05" dateModified="2016-03-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Mark_Bunker%2C_producer_of_anti-Scientology_website_%27XenuTV%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How would you describe yourself in the context of religions, churches, and belief systems, and what you are seeking to accomplish?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: I think I stand outside the religious arena. I'm not interested in buying a ticket for the big game. People are free to believe anything they want but when it comes to fraud and abuse, I think it's important to object.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">There are other religions that practice things that are just as bad as Scientology. For example the Catholic Church, Scientology and Islam dislike/sin homosexuals. Why protest Scientology? The Catholic Church, in terms of atrocities, has likely committed more? Even Muslim extremism... Is Scientology really worth more to protest than those religions or any other?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: The Catholics standing outside the Boston churches, protesting the priest sex abuse scandals were heroes in my mind. Scientologists who stand up to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20Miscavige">David Miscavige</ref> and say stop disconnection, forced abortions, the RPF [<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rehabilitation%20Project%20Force">Rehabilitation Project Force</ref>, ed.</hi>] and fraud are as well.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">That was protest the crime and cover-up? Similar to your work?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: Exactly. It says nothing about the Catholic religion to say stop the priest sex abuse. Except it does make one wonder how a religion could systematically cover up such rampant abuse.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Other than your experiences with ex-members of Scientology, do you have any special qualification that would make you an expert on so-called "cults", i.e. do you have a degree in sociology, anthropology, psychiatry, psychology, theology, or any similar related subject area?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: None whatsoever. I took one course in world religions back in college. That's it. I am not a psychologist. I am not going to council people in need of therapy. I speak out against fraud and abuse. Anyone can do so. Nor have I studied Political Science but that does not prevent me from speaking out against the Bush administration.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Would that include the fields of tax law, i.e. do you have a degree in accounting, finance, law, or any similar related subject area?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: Far from it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Scientology, as many members have claimed, has saved their lives. Do you think, comparing the circumstances, the good things Scientology has done, outweighs the supposed bad things it has done?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: Well, people can feel they gain benefits from a wide range of things. I am not opposed to anyone following Scientology and auditing themselves till the time they drop their bodies. But along the way, many people are getting hurt. Fix that and people would stop protesting. Although I think they may still giggle about Xenu. We have the amazing ability to convince ourselves about anything. Our government is protecting us by wiretapping our phones and getting us into a needless war while letting the real terrorists regroup. But — hey — we were scared and went along with it. Sit in a dark room and imagine there is some scary creature about to get you and you can probably raise some goosebumps. That doesn't mean that there is actually anything in the room. We easily can be tricked and trick ourselves and lead with emotion instead of intellect. So people may feel that Scientology has saved their lives but has it? Have they not also lured them into a group which takes over an increasingly large part of their lives and income, at the same time it is stripping them of their reality to replace it with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/L.%20Ron%20Hubbard">Hubbard</ref>'s? I spoke with Billy Sheehan last weekend at the picket and he told me is an OT3 and would talk about anything about his religion. I asked him to tell me about Xenu and Body Thetans and he couldn't. He just can't. He's not allowed to.  I am free to do so. How are you becoming a better, more free individual when you have to follow such strict orders or a group that promises to teach you to "Think for yourself?"</p>
</text>
