<text id="autogum_whow_doc027" title="Create a Literary and Arts Magazine" shortTile="create-literary-arts" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-05-06" dateModified="2018-08-27" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Create-a-Literary-and-Arts-Magazine" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Create a Literary and Arts Magazine</head><p>Ever thought about creating a literary and arts magazine for your high school or college? Even just for fun? If so, this step by step process for creating a literary and arts magazine will be very useful to you.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Getting Started</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Create a website or portal for works to be submitted. Decide on content (poems, short stories, art etc).
<list type="unordered"><item>This may include hiring an IT person to help set up the site. The IT person should include procedures for authors and artists to submit their works, along with username accounts for each member of the review team. A reviewing and scoring system should also be created.</item></list></item>
<item>Get a group of people together to help create the magazine.
<list type="unordered"><item>This may be in the form of a club or actual class.</item>
<item>Make sure to assign important positions to members of the Magazine team such as Editor in Chief, Assistant Editor, etc.</item></list></item>
<item>Once a team is assembled, start promotion!
<list type="unordered"><item>Design flyers/posters to put up around your community or school campus. Also think about creating various social media accounts for the magazine such as Facebook, Instagram, and Twitter.</item>
<item>This will get the word out to possible authors and artists who are interested in submitting their work.</item>
<item>Don't forget to include a deadline for submissions and a link to the magazine's website on the flyers and social media accounts! That way potential authors and artists will know exactly where to submit their work.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Reviewing Content</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Once works are in, start reviewing! Make sure to give you and your team a couple weeks to do this.
<list type="unordered"><item>Review each piece thoroughly so that it is given proper consideration. Meet frequently with your club or class to discuss works with the highest scores. These will probably be the ones chosen for publication!</item></list></item>
<item>While reviewing works, get in touch with a graphic designer who can create the cover and template for the magazine. He or she is essential in bringing your vision for the magazine to life!
<list type="unordered"><item>Also get an idea of the cost for printing and how many copies need to be made. An experienced printing company will be needed for this.</item></list></item>
<item>Make final decisions! Choose the works that will be published in the magazine.
<list type="unordered"><item>Notify the authors and artists and possibly request brief personal biographies to be included in the magazine.</item></list></item>
<item>Have the editing team look over the chosen works for any grammatical errors.
<list type="unordered"><item>Works should be proofread multiple times by each editor to ensure little to no mistakes.</item></list></item></list>
<head>The Final Stages</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Send out final drafts of the short stories and poems, author bios, and editor's note to the graphic designer. He or she will place these into the finished magazine template.</item>
<item>Send to print! Allow 1-2 weeks for the magazine to be printed prior to publication.</item>
<item>Celebrate! This step is optional, but a nice party for the magazine team, authors, and artists is always a plus!</item></list>
</text>
