<text id="autogum_voyage_doc534" title="Kurayoshi" shortTile="kurayoshi" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=18478" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Kurayoshi</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.apionet.or.jp/kankou/f/e/index.htm">Kurayoshi</ref> </hi> (倉吉市 ) is a city in <ref target="Tottori%20prefecture">Tottori prefecture</ref>.</p>
<head>By car</head>
<p>Visitors arriving by car can park for free at the city hall, just up the hill from the scenic center of town.</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>Kurayoshi is connected on the JR Sanin Line.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Tourism information</hi></p>
<p>Tourism pamphlets and bus information can be found at Kurayoshi Hotto Plaza (［TEL］0858-26-9095) located to the west of the bus terminal at Kurayoshi Station. They are closed on Thursdays.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>Buses from <hi rend="bold">JR Kurayoshi Station</hi> run to popular tourist sites like the 20th Century Pear Museum, the Misasa Hot Springs, the Sekigane Hot Springs, Enchoen Chinese Garden, and the Shirakabe Warehouse District.</p>

<p>Parking is also available at all of these sites for tourists visiting by car.</p>

<head>See</head>
<p>Many of the old kura or storehouses in town have been restored and filled with small shops. There are many narrow canals and waterways winding through the town which is pleasant for a short walk through the Meiji era houses and store fronts.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tottori Nijisseiki Pear Museum</hi> (鳥取二十世紀梨記念館 なしっこ館), Dakyojicho 198-4 (12 min by bus from Kurayoshi station platform #2, get off at the Kurayoshi Park Square stop), ☏ +81 858-23-1174 . 8:30 to 17:30. The Tottori Nijisseiki Pear Museum celebrates the prefecture's signature product, the 20th Century Pear. This is the only pear museum in Japan. It features interactive exhibits highlighting pear production, the history of pears in Japan, a tasting area, a dessert parlor, and more. 300yen adults, 150 for children.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Chokoku-ji</hi> (長谷寺).</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Utsubuki Park</hi>, Nakano-cho (Bus to Utsubuki Koen Iriguchi), ☏ +81 858-22-1200 . Every April, Utsubuki Koen is filled with people admiring the 4,000 cherry blossom trees and 40,000 azaleas in the park. Utsubuki Koen has been designated one of the top 100 city parks in Japan, and it is also known as one of the <ref target="Japan%27s%20Top%20100%20Cherry%20Blossoms%20Spots">top 100 cherry blossom viewing sites</ref> in the country.</item>
</list>

 

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Akagawara Craft District</hi>, Shinmachi 1-chome, ☏ +81 858-23-6666 . 9AM-5PM. In the Shirakabe area, these <hi rend="bold">crafts shops</hi> offer visitors the chance to experience traditional Japanese crafts. Classes include Hakota doll painting, postcard-making, kite-making, and ceramics. Participants must reserve a spot in advance.</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>
<p>Many small craft shops and antique stores fit the retro theme of this town. Antiques can be an especially good deal here if you know what you are looking for.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Shirakabe Warehouses</hi>, Kurayoshi-shi (From JR Kurayoshi Station: 12 mins by Hinomaru or Nikko bus Shinai Line, from Shirakabe-Dozogun-Mae bus stop: immediate access.), ☏ +81 858-22-1200 . The warehouses that line this street comprise some of the oldest buildings in the area, dating back to the Edo and early Meiji periods. Shops specializing in sake, oil, rice, or soy sauce once formed a prosperous shopping district, and the old-style buildings with white plastered walls, black wall panels, and red tiled roofs give an authentic glimpse back into old Japan. Many of these buildings have since been remodeled on the inside to offer regional crafts and souvenirs. You can also try soy sauce ice cream and specialty coffees here.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Utsbuki Kouen dango</hi>. Utsubuki Kouen dango are a signature sweet of the Kurayoshi area, and they are available in many souvenir shops across the prefecture.</item>
</list>


<head>Go next</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Yurihama">Yurihama</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Misasa">Misasa</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Daisen%20%28Tottori%29">Daisen</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Kotoura">Kotoura</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Yonago">Yonago</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Sakai%20Minato">Sakai Minato</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Maniwa">Maniwa</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Tottori">Tottori</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Niimi">Niimi</ref></item>
</list>
</text>
