<text id="autogum_whow_doc097" title="Add a Computer to a Domain on PC" shortTile="add-computer-domain" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-10-02" dateModified="2019-03-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Add-a-Computer-to-a-Domain-on-PC" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Add a Computer to a Domain on PC</head><p>This wikiHow teaches you how to add a Windows 10 computer to a domain.  You can add a computer to a domain using the Control Panel or Windows Settings.  After you join your computer to a local domain, you can log in to the domain at the Windows Sign In screen.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Click the Windows Start  button.  It's the button that has the Windows logo.  By default, it can be found in the task bar in the lower-left corner.  This displays the Windows Start menu. <figure rend="Add a Computer to a Domain on PC Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Type  and press .  This displays the Control Panel in the Windows Start menu.  It's the app that has an icon that resembles a computer screen with graphs.  Click the Control Panel, or press the <hi rend="bold">Enter</hi> key to open the Control Panel. <figure rend="Add a Computer to a Domain on PC Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click .  It's the green text next to the icon that resembles a blue shield next to a planet.  This opens the System and Security Settings menu. <figure rend="Add a Computer to a Domain on PC Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click .  It's the green text next to an icon that resembles a computer screen.  This displays system information. <figure rend="Add a Computer to a Domain on PC Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click .  This is across from the computer name, domain and work group information.  This displays the System Properties menu. <figure rend="Add a Computer to a Domain on PC Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the  tab.  It's the first tab at the top of the System Properties menu. <figure rend="Add a Computer to a Domain on PC Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click .  It's the last button in the System Properties menu. <figure rend="Add a Computer to a Domain on PC Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click .  It's the first radial button at the bottom of the "Computer Name/Domain Changes".  You can select a <hi rend="bold">Domain</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Workgroup</hi>. <figure rend="Add a Computer to a Domain on PC Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Type the domain name and click .  Type the name or URL of the domain you would like to join.  If you are not sure what the domain name is, consult the network administrator. <figure rend="Add a Computer to a Domain on PC Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Type an administrator's username and password and click .  You need to have permission from a network administrator to join a domain.  Type a network administrator's username and password and click <hi rend="bold">Ok</hi> to join. <figure rend="Add a Computer to a Domain on PC Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click .  You may see a welcome prompt, and a prompt advising you to restart your computer.  Click <hi rend="bold">Ok</hi> to acknowledge. <figure rend="Add a Computer to a Domain on PC Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click .  This closes the  System Properties window.  A prompt immediately displays asking you to restart your computer. <figure rend="Add a Computer to a Domain on PC Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click .  Before you log in to the domain with your computer, it must be restarted.  If prompted, click <hi rend="bold">Restart Now</hi>.  If you are not prompted to restart your computer, use the following steps to restart. <figure rend="Add a Computer to a Domain on PC Step 13.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Click the <hi rend="bold">Windows Start</hi> button.</item>
<item>Click the icon with the circle with a line through the top.</item>
<item>Click <hi rend="bold">Restart</hi></item></list></item>
<item>Click .  After your computer restarts, you can log in to your computer locally using your Windows username and password, or click <hi rend="bold">Other User</hi> in the lower-left corner to log in to the domain. <figure rend="Add a Computer to a Domain on PC Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Type the domain name/administrator's username.  In the first bar where you would normally type your Windows username, type the domain followed by a slash (/), then followed by an administrator's username.  For example, "Company/adminstrator". <figure rend="Add a Computer to a Domain on PC Step 15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Type the administrative password and press .  Type an administrative password in the box below the bar with the domain and user name.  Press the <hi rend="bold">Enter</hi> key, or click the arrow to the side of the password bar to log in to the domain. <figure rend="Add a Computer to a Domain on PC Step 16.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
