<text id="autogum_whow_doc033" title="Increase Your Artistic Abilities" shortTile="increase-artistic" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2009-07-07" dateModified="2018-06-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Increase-Your-Artistic-Abilities" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Increase Your Artistic Abilities</head><p>Have you always wanted to be artsy but just didn't think you had any artistic ability? Think again! Art is a question mark - it can be anything, as long as it means something. Here you will learn how to discover and increase your artistic ability.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><figure rend="Artistic ability Step 1.jpg"></figure>The first thing you need to do is realize that inspiration is art. So, get inspired! Take note of things and people around you that inspire you or make you think deeply. Use these things and people as inspiration for your art.</item>
<item><figure rend="Artistic ability Step 2.jpg"></figure>Research the different types of art there are. There is an exhaustive list of things that are considered art, some mainstream, most not. Try your hand at any of them that you are interested in.</item>
<item><figure rend="Artistic ability Step 3.jpg"></figure>Figure out your "niche" in art. You could be multi-talented, and with practice anyone can become great at what they do. A lot of the time though, someone will have a "niche," one specific way of creating art that they're good with and tend to stick with. For some it's drawing, for some it's painting, for some it's sculpture, for some it's photography. Some of us do more modern takes on art like collage or even graffiti. You can figure out your niche by experimenting with different areas of art that you're interested in and finding out which ones you're naturally talented with.</item>
<item><figure rend="Artistic ability Step 4.jpg"></figure><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Visit_an_Art_Gallery">Go to art shows</ref>, museums, or even just the art rooms at your school and look at all the art that people create. Other art may inspire you, but the main point of this exercise is to get an idea of just how vast of an area the simple word "art" covers.</item>
<item><figure rend="Artistic ability Step 5.jpg"></figure>Realize that art is not relegated only to plastic arts (art in which material is used to create a tangible thing). Art can also mean the performing arts - <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Learn_to_Play_an_Instrument">music</ref>, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Dance">dance</ref>, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Act">theatre</ref>, etc. Art can even mean <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Cook">cooking</ref>, as in culinary arts! Technology is your friend. If you find you have some abilities with <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Get_Into_Graphic_Design">graphic design</ref>, that can be your art. As I said, art can be just about anything, as long as it means something. Experiment with them ALL!
<list type="unordered"><item>You can make art out of just about anything. You don't have to spend a lot of money to create good art. A pencil and a sheet of paper can yield a fantastic <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Write_a_Poem">poem</ref>, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Write_a_Short_Story">story</ref>, or <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Draw">drawing</ref>. A cheap set of watercolors and a cheap watercolor pad can make a beautiful <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Paint">painting</ref>. Opening up your mouth and singing something a cappella can lead to a wonderful song. Buy a can of spray paint and try your hand at <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Draw_Graffiti_Letters">graffiti</ref>. Print pictures off of the Internet, cut pictures out of magazines, and get a stick of glue and a piece of cardboard and try making a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_a_Collage">collage</ref>. Grab your digital camera and <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Develop_Your_Photography_Skills">snap some pictures</ref>, it may lead to a great piece of photography. Do anything, as long as you are giving it some sort of meaning.</item>
<item>The most important thing to realize when you're trying to be artistic is that art is making something tangible out of the intangible, and it is not always easy. You're trying to take yourself, your own feelings, another person, their feelings, etc., and create something that can be seen, heard, touched, smelled, tasted - something that can be experienced on a whole other level.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be happy with what you created, and always keep improving your work! Professional artists practice over and over again, until they the image that was in their head, right in front of them!</item>
<item>Not everyone will like your art. Be OK with this! Some of the best-known artists of days gone by were not appreciated in their time but they kept going anyway. The main point of art is to express yourself, not to please others!</item>
<item>This is optional, but try to develop a rule! For example, Georges-Pierre Seurat painted just using little dots.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be aware that if you decide to try art on public property (for example, graffiti), it may be illegal to do so and you could face prosecution if caught. Proceed with doing art on public property at your own risk.</item></list>
</text>
