<text id="autogum_news_doc669" title="Super Bowl 50: Denver Broncos defeat Carolina Panthers 24–10" shortTile="super-bowl--denver" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-02-08" dateModified="2017-06-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Super_Bowl_50%3A_Denver_Broncos_defeat_Carolina_Panthers_24%E2%80%9310" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Super Bowl 50: Denver Broncos defeat Carolina Panthers 24–10</head>
<figure><caption>Von Miller, the Super Bowl 50 MVP. Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Denverjeffrey">Jeffrey Beall</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 9, 2016</hi></p>
<p>On Sunday, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Denver%20Broncos">Denver Broncos</ref> defeated the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carolina%20Panthers">Carolina Panthers</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Super%20Bowl%2050">Super Bowl 50</ref> by a score of 24–10. The game, played at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Levi's%20Stadium">Levi's Stadium</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santa%20Clara,%20California">Santa Clara, California</ref> in front of 71,088 spectators, marked the Broncos' third Super Bowl victory and their first since 1999. Entering the game, the Panthers had lost only once in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2015%20NFL%20season">2015 NFL season</ref>, while the Broncos won 12 of their 16 games.</p>
<p>The Panthers kicked off to start the game, and the Broncos scored first with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brandon%20McManus">Brandon McManus</ref>' 34-yard <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/field%20goal">field goal</ref>. After both teams exchanged punts, the Broncos scored again when linebacker <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Von%20Miller">Von Miller</ref> stripped the ball from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cam%20Newton">Cam Newton</ref>, forcing him to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/fumble">fumble</ref>, and the ball was recovered by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malik%20Jackson">Malik Jackson</ref> in the endzone to result in a Denver touchdown. In the second quarter, the Panthers scored a touchdown when running back <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jonathan%20Stewart">Jonathan Stewart</ref> jumped over the goal line. The two teams punted again on their next drives. The second turnover of the game occurred when Bronco <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Darian%20Stewart">Darian Stewart</ref> forced <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mike%20Tolbert">Mike Tolbert</ref> to fumble, with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Danny%20Trevathan">Danny Trevathan</ref> recovering; however, the Broncos failed to capitalize when <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peyton%20Manning">Peyton Manning</ref> was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/interception">intercepted</ref> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kony%20Ealy">Kony Ealy</ref>. The half ended with the Broncos leading 13–7. In the second half, the Panthers had a chance to narrow the margin to three points, but kicker <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Graham%20Gano">Graham Gano</ref>'s 44-yard field goal attempt hit the goal post's right upright. Afterwards, Denver increased the score with McManus kicking a 30-yard field goal. On the next series, Newton led the Panthers' offense to the Broncos' 28-yard line, but was intercepted by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/T.%20J.%20Ward">T. J. Ward</ref>. Denver and Carolina both subsequently punted. Afterwards, Manning was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quarterback%20sack">sacked</ref> by Ealy and fumbled; Carolina took advantage with Gano's 39-yard kick to make the score 16–10. Unfortunately for the Panthers, Miller forced Newton to fumble at the Panthers' four-yard line and Ward recovered. With 3:08 left in the game, Denver's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C.%20J.%20Anderson">C. J. Anderson</ref> sealed the game with a two-yard touchdown run, followed by Manning's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/two-point%20conversion">two-point conversion</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bennie%20Fowler">Bennie Fowler</ref>.</p>
<p>Miller ended the game with six tackles, 2.5 sacks and two forced fumbles and was awarded the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Super%20Bowl%20Most%20Valuable%20Player%20Award">Super Bowl Most Valuable Player Award</ref>. Manning, who is the oldest quarterback to start a Super Bowl at the age of 39 and is rumored to have played his final game in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/National_Football_League">National Football League</ref>, completed 13 of 23 passes for 141 yards with an interception and a lost fumble. The Broncos recorded only 194 yards, the fewest by a Super Bowl winner.</p>
<p>The game's festivities featured <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lady%20Gaga">Lady Gaga</ref> performing the national anthem. After the second quarter, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coldplay">Coldplay</ref> performed the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Super%20Bowl%2050%20halftime%20show">Super Bowl 50 halftime show</ref> with former Super Bowl performers <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bruno%20Mars">Bruno Mars</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beyoncé">Beyoncé</ref>. Coldplay opened the show with "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Viva%20la%20Vida">Viva la Vida</ref>" and "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paradise%20(song)">Paradise</ref>", followed by a performance of "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uptown%20Funk">Uptown Funk</ref>" with Mars. Afterwards, Beyoncé performed her new song "Formation" and joined Coldplay and Mars on stage to end the show.</p>
</text>
