<text id="autogum_academic_doc708" title="The Impact of Government Role on High-Quality Innovation Development in Mainland China" shortTile="impact-government" author="Xuanzhi Yang, Zhaofang Zhang, Wei Luo, Zhen Tang, Xin Gao, Zhongchi Wan, Xin Zhang" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5780/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
In a world full of opportunities and challenges, it is imperative for different countries to attach supreme importance to the high quality of development. To gain a first-mover advantage in the new round of international economic competition, the majority of the world’s players have embarked on strategies for future-oriented development. The number of countries propelled by national development plans has more than doubled, from about 62 in 2006 to 134 in 2018, making over 80% of the global population subject to a national plan of one form or another. </p>

<p>Against the backdrop of intensifying global competition and novel domestic development environment, China has become a leader among emerging economies in the process of actively exploring new growth paths and development models. However, excessive energy consumption, environmental deterioration, imbalance of economic structure, and a widening income gap have become increasingly prominent. For these reasons, the path of high-quality development has become the optimal way to handle the current difficulties and achieve a leap in the future.  </p>

<p>With the reflection on the rapid economic development in the past 40 years of reform and opening-up, China’s economic development has shifted its focus from scale and speed to efficiency and quality, which also symbolizes the start of China’s high-quality development. According to the government work report 2018 of China’s State Council, a new statement on high-quality development has been made. Compared to the traditional development model, the high-quality development model in China represents high efficiency, equitable, and sustainable development, which is aimed at meeting the growing needs of the people for a better life. Additionally, how to correctly position the governments’ role in the high-quality development of mainland China has also been proposed. Following the state’s guidelines, academics have begun to conduct extensive studies revolving around three aspects: high-quality development connotations, high-quality development systems, and high-quality development paths. Although the research contents differ, they all hold that innovation has become the first driving force for high-quality development. </p>

<p>The basis of in-depth study on these three aspects is to make an objective evaluation of high-quality innovation development levels of different regions in mainland China. On this basis, exploring the government role in high-quality innovation development will promote China’s economic advance. Therefore, this paper firstly evaluates the high-quality innovation development level of 30 provinces and municipalities in mainland China; secondly, on the basis of the evaluation results, it introduces role theory to determine the role of different governments in promoting high-quality innovation development of the provinces and municipalities. </p>

<p>At present, the main methods used in evaluating the high-quality development are AHP (analytic hierarchy process), the multi-objective linear weighting method, SFA (stochastic frontier analysis), and the entropy value method. These research methods follow nearly the same research idea: firstly, establishing an evaluation system in advance; secondly, selecting different kinds of indicators; thirdly, determining the weights of them through the analytic hierarchy process, multi-objective linear weighting method, and entropy value method, etc.; and, finally, conducting a comprehensive assessment of the high-quality development of research objects. However, the above research methods have some limitations: the AHP method may be too subjective when comparing the importance of various indicators; the entropy weight method can obtain relatively objective results, but it has higher requirements on the number of data samples; and multi-objective linear weighting and SFA require a definite function to show the relationship between high-quality development efficiency and influencing factors, which is easily affected by the misspecification and, thus, leads to inaccurate results. </p>

<p>Given the limitations of the above research methods, we introduce the super-efficiency DEA model and the Tobit regression model into this study to evaluate the high-quality innovation development level in different regions of mainland China. As to the advantages of super-efficiency DEA model, it does not need to determine the index construction function relation in advance, which can avoid the influence of subjective factors on the model construction and can distinguish the efficiency value of effective and non-effective decision-making units. In addition, it can compare the decision-making units with a higher efficiency value that reaches 1. In addition, Tobit regression can analyze the real effect of exogenous variables. Thus, the research method not only has high credibility and applicability but also conforms to the research design of this paper. </p>

<p>Based on the correct evaluation of high-quality innovation development level of different regions in mainland China, how to specify the role of governments is the next core issue; particularly, the role of provincial governments remains controversial. Therefore, this paper will attempt to identify the role of government from the perspective of role theory. </p>
</text>
