<text id="autogum_academic_doc192" title="Synthesis of NdAlO3 Nanoparticles and Evaluation of the Catalytic Capacity for Biodiesel Synthesis" shortTile="synthesis-ndalo-nanoparticles" author="Mayra Dionicio-Navarrete, C.  Dinorah Arrieta-Gonzalez, Alfredo Quinto-Hernandez, Maura Casales-Diaz, Jacqueline Zuñiga-Diaz, Jesus Porcayo-Calderon, Lorenzo Martinez-Gomez" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2079-4991/9/11/1545/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Pollution caused by the use and abuse of fossil fuels has created motivation for the search for sustainable energy alternatives. In this sense, undoubtedly, biodiesel is a real alternative that can be used to reduce mineral diesel consumption. Biodiesel, although it can also be obtained from animal fat, is a derivative of vegetable oils, and therefore is a fuel friendly to the environment. Because biodiesel is non-toxic, biodegradable, free of sulfur, free of carcinogenic compounds, and contains oxygen in its molecule, it can be considered a clean fuel. </p>

<p>The use of biodiesel as an alternative fuel to fossil fuels has a direct impact on the reduction of CO2 emissions because its combustion emits the anthropogenic CO2 that plants used for their growth. In addition, during the combustion of biodiesel, the energy obtained is actually solar energy that was used by the plants to carry out their photosynthesis activities: this is an additional feature to be considered as a clean fuel that contributes to reduce the greenhouse gas emissions. </p>

<p>Biodiesel synthesis can be carried out using a process of esterification and/or transesterification of vegetable oils, depending on their content of free fatty acids, in the presence of a catalyst, where the catalytic reaction can be homogeneous or heterogeneous. </p>

<p>Most of the research has been focused on the study of the transesterification reactions of vegetable oils based on homogeneous systems due to their high yield and lower reaction time. The most commonly used homogeneous catalysts are based on methanolic solutions of NaOH and KOH, which, when mixed with the oil, form a single phase that favors the contact of the reaction mixture, minimizing the mass transfer resistance, and therefore increases the reaction rate. However, the main disadvantages of this system are: use of raw materials of high purity (no presence of moisture and low content of free fatty acids), catalyst is corrosive and non-recoverable, uses many stages of purification to obtain a high-quality biodiesel, and the purification of crude glycerol is not profitable. </p>

<p>In the case of the use of heterogeneous catalysts, the reaction mixture forms an immiscible system (oil–methanol–catalyst) that faces many mass transfer problems that cause low reaction speeds and lower biodiesel yields. However, the main advantages are: recovery and reuse of the catalyst, higher purity of the reaction products, less pollutant emissions to the environment, and lower production costs. Unlike homogeneous catalysts, heterogeneous catalysts can be considered as green catalysts due to their easy recovery and recyclability; in addition, many solid catalysts based on mixed metal oxides have shown a tolerance to the presence of free fatty acids and moisture. </p>

<p>Heterogeneous catalysis can use three types of solid catalysts, namely those of an acidic character, those of a basic character, and bifunctional ones (acid-base character), with the basic ones being the most used due to their higher reaction rate. Many studies have shown that rare earth-based oxides can be used to carry out the esterification and transesterification of vegetable oils. The excellent catalytic activity of the rare earth oxides is comparable to that of CaO, and this is determined by its crystalline structure and cation radius. However, one of its main disadvantages is the leaching of the catalyst, which reduces its stability and catalytic activity, in addition to the greater reaction time required to obtain performances comparable to those achieved in homogeneous catalysis. </p>

<p>Due to the various advantages offered by heterogeneous catalysts, and in particular those of a basic nature, the search for new catalysts for the transesterification reaction is important. Each heterogeneous catalyst behaves differently, which requires further investigation in order to determine the optimal reaction conditions to achieve the highest possible yields in the shortest reaction time, as well as in terms of the lowest temperature, and lowest use of methanol and catalyst. In this sense, perovskite-type mixed oxides, based on rare earths, have greater chemical stability than simple rare earth oxides or rare earth oxides supported on other oxides (such as α-Al2O3). Its greater chemical stability is an advantage because its leaching can be significantly reduced, and therefore, its possible loss of activity is reduced. </p>

<p>Therefore, the purpose of this study is to explore the potential use of a NdAlO3 perovskite as a catalyst to carry out the biodiesel synthesis. For this, this study considers the synthesis and characterization of the NdAlO3 nanoparticles, and the evaluation of its catalytic activity in the biodiesel synthesis from canola oil. Nanoparticles were synthesized using the sol-gel process, and its catalytic activity was determined based on the methanol:oil ratio, temperature, reaction time, and catalyst recyclability. Reaction products were analyzed using FTIR, NMR, and gas chromatography. </p>
</text>
