<text id="autogum_interview_doc823" title="part8_Satanism: An interview with Church of Satan High Priest Peter Gilmore" shortTile="partsatanism-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-04" dateModified="2018-10-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Satanism%3A_An_interview_with_Church_of_Satan_High_Priest_Peter_Gilmore" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  And a lot of people are morons and irresponsible, so—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But then doesn't responsibility come down to defining it for yourself in Satanism?  Your statements seem to come down to a baseline level of what is responsibility?  What is innocence?  Whereas you were saying earlier that a lot of these things are self-referentially defined.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  Right, right.  We allow people to make that definition for themselves, absolutely.  But for me personally, you try to deal with other people around you so that you don't make their lives miserable unless there is some real overriding reason that would have to happen.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Who are you supporting for President?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  Nobody, yet! [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>].  Right now, there is not really one candidate that speaks to me more than others.  I generally feel that so many candidates are lacking in so many ways, that it really IS the lesser of multiple evils that you are picking.  I like the old <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/H.P.%20Lovecraft">Lovecraftian</ref> t-shirt:  "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cthulu">Cthulu</ref> for President!  Why choose the <hi rend="italic">lesser</hi> of two evils?"  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  If you had a choice between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rudolph%20Giuliani">Giuliani</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hillary_Clinton">Clinton</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  I would probably go with Hillary Clinton.  Giuliani was acting like such a fascist before <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/9/11">9/11</ref>.  He was trying to use his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sensation%20exhibition#New_York">Catholicism to control art</ref> that was exhibited in this city.  It was unbelievable!  His popularity was really down.  It wasn't until 9/11 that he stepped up and did things that were required to be a leader and make people feel more comfortable that his ratings shot back up, but he was really <hi rend="italic">not</hi> somebody who was well regarded back then.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That’s talked about now more than it used to be.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  It should be now that he is running for President.  People <hi rend="italic">need</hi> to mention that!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It’s a question of how much it will penetrate the American consciousness that has mythologized him.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  That’s the thing: he really <hi rend="italic">was</hi> so mythologized at that point.  We build heroes, and so many people really do deal with idealistic portrayals and not realistic ones.  We have to examine these things all the time and be careful.</p>
<head id="Religious_and_Satanic_symbols">Religious and Satanic symbols</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Could you explain your logo?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sigil%20of%20Baphomet">Sigil of Baphomet</ref>.  Heavy metal people say “Bapho-MAY!” Because they want to take it from the French <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knights%20Templar">Templars</ref>, where it originally came from the trials of them.  But we explain it as there is a goat face in the center of a five-pointed star.  The goat face represents carnality.  In <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ancient%20Egypt">ancient Egypt</ref> goats were considered representations as god symbols of lust, and we think lust is an important factor of biology that keeps humanity going so we value that.  The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pentagram">five-pointed star</ref> really comes from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pythagoreans">Pythagoreans</ref>.  That is the one figure in which every element is within the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golden%20ratio">golden mean</ref> of each other.  It’s this wonderful mathematical symbol of perfection, organic perfection specifically.  Since we are organic life and enjoy the idea of perfecting ourselves, that star is right for us in there and it perfectly fits the goat head inside.  Now around it are two circles, one at the tip of the points of the star and one outside.  In that are Hebrew characters starting at the bottom and going counter-clockwise spelling <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leviathan">Leviathan</ref>.  In Hebrew mythology, Leviathan was the great dragon of the abyss, this powerful Earth figure that even Yahweh was afraid of.  So all these things taken together creates a symbol that Anton LaVey identified with Satanism specifically.  When he started the Church of Satan, usually <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cross%20of%20St.%20Peter">upside down crosses</ref> were considered Satanic, and he saw that these different elements and felt this was a <hi rend="italic">positive</hi> symbol you could tie to the Satanism he was creating.</p>
</text>
