<text id="autogum_whow_doc215" title="Pick a Family Reunion Location" shortTile="pick-family-reunion" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-05-13" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Pick-a-Family-Reunion-Location" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Pick a Family Reunion Location</head><p>Choosing a location for a family reunion can difficult when each person has their mind set on a different meeting place. Another challenge can be taking into account where everyone is traveling from to get to the reunion, and how much money you are willing to spend on the event. By calculating a budget, considering local attractions, and calling for a family vote, you can initiate a fun and memorable family reunion.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Calculating Your Budget</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Come up with a per-head expenditure. This should include shared, group expenses rather than individual expenses. Coming up with an idea of per-head spending will help you to set a budget that suits everyone. This will help you to more easily choose a location that suits your needs. <figure rend="Pick a Family Reunion Location Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Choose one family member, or elect a finance committee, to calculate these costs. They will be responsible for budgeting and planning for expenses of the family reunion. They will also collect monetary contributions from the rest of the family.</item>
<item>Costs to keep in mind include food, transportation, lodging, venue rentals, and means of entertainment.</item></list></item>
<item>Consider the cost of food when choosing location. No family reunion is complete without a feast of some sort. Whether you want to have a cook-out, order in, or go to a restaurant, you will have to account for the cost of food during your reunion. <figure rend="Pick a Family Reunion Location Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take transportation into account. Some family members may be traveling from far locations for the reunion event. Be considerate of their budgetary needs and financial situation. If you are splitting the cost of the event between several families, first ask them for a range of what they would be willing to spend on the event altogether, including their own transportation costs. <figure rend="Pick a Family Reunion Location Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Weigh lodging costs. While you may want to stay at a nearby relative’s house to cut back on costs, some families may want to stay in a hotel room or motel. Use these costs to determine the best location for your reunion. <figure rend="Pick a Family Reunion Location Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you’re looking for a cheaper option, you may want to consider a local campground, taking time of year and forecasted weather into account. Many campgrounds provide excellent activities for children, such as fishing, pools, and paddle boat riding.</item></list></item>
<item>Factor in venue costs to narrow down options. If you are renting a function or banquet hall for the reunion, there will be a fee. Call ahead of time to ask about the cost for a per-day rental. This will help eliminate some of the pricier location options. <figure rend="Pick a Family Reunion Location Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Some venues offer additional options, such as decorations or a photographer that you can use during your event for an additional fee.</item></list></item>
<item>Budget for costs of entertainment at each location. Whether you are choosing to bring games and activities with you or participate in nearby attractions, such as horse riding, these costs can add up. Be sure to account for everything offered at each of your potential event locations.    <figure rend="Pick a Family Reunion Location Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Exploring Location Options</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Choose family-appropriate venues as options. Consider the ages of the youngest members of your extended family, and choose a location that would interest them as well. While your uncle may think that a bar is a good place to meet, this location wouldn’t work for your cousin’s five-year-old daughter, for example. <figure rend="Pick a Family Reunion Location Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Age-appropriate venues can include a state park, a campground, a bowling alley, or a country club.</item></list></item>
<item>Look for locations that offer lodging. If some members of your family are traveling far distances for the reunion, they will need somewhere to stay. Be sure that you take each family member’s needs and budget into account during this process. <figure rend="Pick a Family Reunion Location Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Choose a lodging location that is within each family member’s individual budget. Also, be sure that the lodging is located a reasonable distance from the main event venue and any additional activities. Nobody wants to spend the entire reunion driving from location to location.</item></list></item>
<item>Ask for recommendations from friends. Local friends may have hosted their own family reunions, so do not hesitate to ask them for ideas. Your friends may even have connections or know of ongoing discounts in your area. <figure rend="Pick a Family Reunion Location Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Allow each family member to come up with a location. If everyone gets a chance to offer their ideas, then they will feel more included in the planning process and will be more excited about the overall event. Tell them to email you or call you with their ideas, and conduct a family vote once all have been collected. <figure rend="Pick a Family Reunion Location Step 10.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Choosing a Reunion Venue</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Give fair consideration to all suggested locations. As it is a family reunion, it would be great if every suggested place by each member is considered at least once. This will avoid conflicts later. <figure rend="Pick a Family Reunion Location Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Check the amenities at each venue option. Be sure that there are accessible restrooms for your family to use. You may want to consider a venue with a kitchen if you intent to do some cooking at the event itself. Ask whether the venue allows alcohol on its premises if you want to bring booze to your event. <figure rend="Pick a Family Reunion Location Step 12.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you have a disabled family member, check that the facility offers amenities for disabled people, such as a ramp and a wheelchair-accessible bathroom.</item></list></item>
<item>Go through the travelogues of the shortlisted places. Check each place to see whether or not it has a minimum of two things of interest for each age group. If you would rather book a place that does not offer its own attractions, come up with games or activities that you could bring to the event in order to keep everyone entertained. <figure rend="Pick a Family Reunion Location Step 13.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Look for places that offer exciting things to do, such as boat rides or fishing. If you plan on bringing your own activities, try to find a place that has plenty of space for you to set these games up, whether it's a volleyball net or a water balloon toss.</item></list></item>
<item>Conduct a family vote to choose the location. Have each family member email their selections to a chosen Vote Counter. This vote will eliminate places that more than a few family members are disinterested in pursuing. <figure rend="Pick a Family Reunion Location Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make reservations early. Venues can book up quickly, especially during the summer months, so be sure to call and make a reservation as soon as you can. Ask about any cancellation fees or security deposits, so that you have all of your bases covered. <figure rend="Pick a Family Reunion Location Step 15.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
</text>
