<text id="autogum_academic_doc235" title="Cabinet of Curiosities: The Interesting Geometry of the Angle β = arccos ((3ϕ − 1)/4)" shortTile="cabinet-curiosities" author="Fang Fang, Klee Irwin, Julio Kovacs, Garrett Sadler" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2504-3110/3/4/48/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Curiosities</head>
<p>
We have seen the construction of several aggregates of tetrahedra. Each of these structures contains tetrahedra with coincident faces, offset angularly by  or a closely related angle (). We will now explore some of the interesting features of these structures. As already noted, it is interesting that  appears in the face junctions of structures generated by “closing” gaps between tetrahedral aggregates. It is additionally interesting that when this angle is employed in the construction of a helical chain of tetrahedra, a periodic structure emerges (whereas the canonical BC helix has no non-trivial translational or rotational symmetries). </p>

<p>The features we will highlight in this section involve the reduction of the overall number of “plane classes” and the linear displacements between facial centers in a face function. Here, we say that two planes belong to the same plane class if and only if their normal vectors are parallel. The number of plane classes for a collection of tetrahedra, then, is defined as the number of distinct plane classes comprising the collection’s two-dimensional faces. By rotating tetrahedra so as to bring faces into contact (as in Section 2.1 and Section 2.2), or rotating tetrahedra to obtain periodicity (as in Section 2.3), the overall number of plane classes for an aggregate is reduced. Clearly, as the values of , , and  are such that they bring faces of adjacent tetrahedra into contact, we would expect to see a reduction in the number of plane classes in the corresponding aggregations of tetrahedra featured in Section 2.1 and Section 2.2. It is interesting, however, that rotation of the tetrahedra in a BC helix by  (observed in the face junctions of <figure>Figure 1</figure>c, <figure>Figure 2</figure>c and <figure>Figure 3</figure>c) obtains a reduction from an arbitrarily large number of plane classes (, where <hi rend="italic">n</hi> is the number of tetrahedra in the helix) to relatively small numbers: 9 plane classes in the case of the 3-BC helix, 10 plane classes in the case of the 5-BC helix. Table 1 provides the numbers of plane classes for the tetrahedral aggregates described in Section 2 before and after their transformations. </p>

<p>Finally, an appealing feature is observed in the face junction projections of the tetrahedral aggregates discussed in this paper. <figure>Figure 7</figure> provides a side-by-side comparison of these face junctions. As the angular displacement between tetrahedra in all face junctions is related to , we can see that translation of a tetrahedron in one junction can produce any of the other junctions. Let the displacement between tetrahedra in the face junction of 5 tetrahedra about a common edge be denoted by , where <hi rend="italic">a</hi> is the tetrahedron edge length. Starting from the face junction of a 3- or 5-BC helix, the remaining face junctions corresponding to 20 tetrahedra about a vertex, 5 tetrahedra about an edge, and 3 tetrahedra about an edge may be obtained by translating a tetrahedron of the junction by , , and , respectively. </p>
</text>
