<text id="autogum_whow_doc034" title="Get Better at Drawing or Painting" shortTile="better-drawing-painting" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-12-11" dateModified="2018-06-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get-Better-at-Drawing-or-Painting" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get Better at Drawing or Painting</head><p>Being artistic is a respectable talent, but it doesn't come naturally to everyone. Some of us are born to be the next Vincent van Gogh, and some of us are still working on stick figures. This article is here to help you improve your artistic skills - no matter where on the talent spectrum you are.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Expose yourself to art. As you learn more about different styles and art principles, you will be able to incorporate them into your own art. Go to art museums and get art books from your local library. Learn about art in all of its forms. Make sure to do your research before you begin.</item>
<item>Practice your skills. Draw or paint every day. You can buy a notebook that you fill completely with doodles- just to get your creativity flowing. It's okay if you just do one stroke a day - just make sure to do that one stroke with an artistic flair.</item>
<item>Experiment freely. If you like the flow of the sky in "Starry Night", try to replicate it in a painting of your own. Try out any technique or style that intrigues you. You might find that you're a natural at a style you never tried before. If not, that doesn't mean it's not for you. Keep trying. Mix styles. See what works and what doesn't. Slowly you will begin to develop a style of your own.</item>
<item>Don't fall into autopilot. It has been said that anything you do without thinking will not be your best work. Concentrate on your art. Think about what you're doing from beginning to end.</item>
<item>Take it slow. Some people fly through a painting in half an hour and are frustrated by the subpar results. Don't rush; even if you're incredibly talented, trying to squeeze art into a tiny span of time will never go well. Leave the piece for later if you need a break.</item>
<item>Get your own supplies. It's good to have them on hand instead of going to a community center or similar public place. That way you'll have more opportunities to create art.
<list type="unordered"><item>For painting, you should have canvases; normal paper shrinks and becomes malformed under paint. Have a paint palette, a water bowl to clean your brushes, a few different types of brushes, and red, yellow, blue, white paint at least. To darken a mixture, it's best not to use pure black, so find a variation of black as well.</item>
<item>For drawing, have plenty of paper- printer paper works, but go for a drawing pad/sketchbook if you want to. Have a good eraser and a variety of pencils: 4H, 2H, HB, 2B, 4B, and 6B, primarily. This will give you a greater variety of potential shades to use.</item>
<item>If you're on a tight budget, buy your supplies over time.</item></list></item>
<item>Take proper care of your supplies. They will be no use to you otherwise. Wash all the paint out of your brushes after use and then dry them. Keep your pencils in a place where they will not be broken.</item>
<item>Practice shading and highlights to bring depth to your art.</item>
<item>Show your work to family and friends and ask for suggestions. Use the suggestions to your advantage - improve what you aren't doing well.</item>
<item>Take an art class... or two... or three. Learn tips and tricks from people who are paid to teach them.</item>
<item>Most importantly, don't throw away your creativity. It's there, and it's the best tool you'll ever have. Let it run wild, no matter how silly you feel.</item></list>
</text>
