<text id="autogum_bio_doc049" title="Fred Bass" shortTile="fred-bass" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-10-07" dateModified="2019-10-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fred_Bass" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Fred Bass</head>For the owner of Strand Bookstore, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fred_Bass_(businessman)">Fred Bass (businessman)</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Fred Bass</hi> is a former <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vancouver_City_Council">city councillor</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Environmentalist">environmentalist</ref> and a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Preventive_medicine">preventive medicine</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Physician">physician</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vancouver">Vancouver, British Columbia</ref>, Canada.</p>
<head>Background</head>
<p>Bass was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_York_City">New York City</ref>, attended <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antioch_College">Antioch College</ref>, Case-Western Reserve <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Medical_School">Medical School</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harvard">Harvard</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johns_Hopkins">Johns Hopkins</ref>. He served as a preventive medicine officer in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/US_Army">US Army</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/7th_Infantry_Division_(United_States)">7th Infantry Division</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Korea">Korea</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fort_Monmouth">Fort Monmouth</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Jersey">New Jersey</ref>. After his military service, he was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tuberculosis">tuberculosis</ref> control officer for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Jersey_Department_of_Health">New Jersey Department of Health</ref> and unit medical health officer. He earned a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Master's_degree">master's degree</ref> in epidemiology at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harvard_School_of_Public_Health">Harvard School of Public Health</ref> and a Doctor of Science at Johns Hopkins, writing a thesis on medical care use attributable to cigarette smoking. He taught at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Pennsylvania">University of Pennsylvania</ref> and came to the Vancouver Health Department in 1975. There, in 1982, he became director of health promotion.</p>
<p>In 1989, he founded the BC Doctors Stop-Smoking Program to help doctors help their patients stop smoking. He helped to form the Society for Clinical Preventive Care in 1997, which has a mission to implement proven clinical preventive measures. In 2001 he was awarded a Senior (life) Membership in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canadian_Medical_Association">Canadian Medical Association</ref> for his extensive work in tobacco control. He continues in 2007 to serve as the medical director of the Society for Clinical Preventive Health Care.</p>
<head>Early involvement with Vancouver politics</head>
<p>In 1989–90, Bass served on Vancouver's Clouds of Change Task Force which addressed the issues of global climate change. Bass, concerned about global warming, entered electoral politics in 1996 as a candidate for Vancouver's civic <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Green_Party_of_British_Columbia">Green Party</ref> under the leadership of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stuart_Parker_(politician)">Stuart Parker</ref> but was defeated by a wide margin. However, the increased share of the vote won by the Greens and of a new populist party called VOICE resulted in a total rout for the city's leftist forces in which every single candidate who was not a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Non-Partisan_Association">Non-Partisan Association</ref> was defeated. Despite being the Greens' second-best vote-getter in the 1996 election (second only to the party's provincial leader <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stuart_Parker_(politician)">Stuart Parker</ref>), Bass was defeated when he sought renomination by the Greens in 1999. With the support of the Greens' executive and provincial leadership, he sought and won the nomination of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coalition_of_Progressive_Electors">Coalition of Progressive Electors</ref> (COPE), the party with which the Greens had just inked a coalition agreement.</p>
<head>Elected city councillor</head>
<p>Bass was first elected to city council in 1999 as a member of COPE, and topped the polls when re-elected in 2002 with 70,525 votes. His political priorities were action on the environment and transit. Bass was outspoken in his opposition to the expansion of gambling and to excessive expenditures for rapid transit by a faction of his party under the leadership of Mayor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Larry_Campbell">Larry Campbell</ref>.</p>
<p>In 2003–2005, three COPE councillors and the mayor split from the party to form <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vision_Vancouver">Vision Vancouver</ref>. Bass and councillors <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tim_Louis_(British_Columbia_politician)">Tim Louis</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Cadman">David Cadman</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anne_Roberts">Anne Roberts</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ellen_Woodsworth">Ellen Woodsworth</ref> remained in COPE. Bass was not re-elected in the 2005 election, finishing 12th overall with 48,248 votes.</p>
<p>Bass introduced a controversial motion in 2005 to widen the sidewalks on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burrard_Bridge">Burrard Bridge</ref> to encourage cyclists and pedestrians, but first do a minimal-cost trial of using one lane in each direction for bicycles, reserving the existing sidewalk for pedestrians, despite the failure of a similar experiment in 1996. The sidewalk-widening was slated to cost $13 million if the $2 million trial failed. Some cyclists applauded the move, though other users of the current bridge sidewalks questioned whether any changes were necessary. Concerns about motorist rage did not deter Bass, who stated "Motorists called for my head long ago and my head is still on my neck."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> Heritage advocates strongly supported the bicycle trial, since the sidewalk-widening would impair the heritage value of this landmark, art deco bridge. Bass was the council lead on the Vancouver Area Transit Plan, which planned six new bus routes and a number of transit-friendly changes.</p>
<head>Intentions to run for mayor</head>
<p>In late 2006 he announced his aspiration to run for mayor in the next Vancouver civic election because of his concerns for respect, global warming, homelessness and lack of affordable housing. In August 2007, he announced that he no longer intended to participate in the mayoral race.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
</text>
