<text id="autogum_academic_doc729" title="A CBR–AHP Hybrid Method to Support the Decision-Making Process in the Selection of Environmental Management Actions" shortTile="cbrahp-hybrid-method" author="Fernando Ramos-Quintana, Efraín Tovar-Sánchez, Hugo Saldarriaga-Noreña, Héctor Sotelo-Nava, Juan  Paulo Sánchez-Hernández, María-Luisa Castrejón-Godínez" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5649/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Conclusions</head>
<p>
The selection of a set of adequate EMAs to reduce the risky trends of the current environmental state of a region represents an important decision-making challenge. In addition, the selection of a set of inadequate EMAs already implemented put at risk a sustainable performance of an EMS. Such selection becomes more critical when decision makers should assign an order of priority to several candidate EMAs. In order to address this problem, we have proposed the integration of the CBR and AHP methods to select a set of adequate EMAs, thus supporting the sustainable performance of the EMS. </p>

<p>We have argued that the interactions—represented by cause–affect relationships in this work—between the involved variables that affect the environment make the complex task of selecting a suitable set of EMAs to improve the environmental-state quality difficult. We have also emphasized that the knowledge of the relationships between drivers and stressors that exert effects on the environmental state is basic to understanding important processes taking place in the environment which, in turn, will allow us to assess the environmental state to support decision makers in the selection of more-adequate EMAs. </p>

<p>The selection of a set of adequate EMAs should satisfy relevant aspects related to certain criteria determined by experts, who should know very well the environmental context of the region under study. The alternatives represented by EMAs should satisfy the criteria for selection, the set of EMAs should be ordered by priorities by formally checking the consistency of the given order, and the assessments of the current environmental state should reflect a general environmental context, instead of partial views associated with isolated environmental variables. </p>

<p>We have found that selection criteria based only on the assessments of current values of independent variables is not significant enough to reflect an acceptable environmental context. Therefore, we have proposed assessments of KEPs, because the behavior of the trend values of KEVs over time is due to a sequence of cause–effect relationships between drivers and stressors that converge into them. This is the reason why we use trend values of KEPs in the construction of situation–solution pairs or cases to be stored in the MC. In addition, through the use of KEPs, we are able to identify what relationships are causing the most, or the least, damage to the global environmental state. Finally, we point out that a KEP is always associated with a KEV. </p>

<p>Despite the advantages of the CBR method to reason about experiences or cases stored in the MC to solve new problems, this method is sensitive to inconsistent data without having the capacity to establish an order of priority of the involved variables, which is required in two important processes of the CBR method. The first process is during the calculation of the similarity value to retrieve similar cases to current situations. In this case, KEPs should be weighted to calculate the similarity value. The second process is during the adaptation process to obtain the solution by combining several candidate EMAs to build a solution. In this case, EMAs or alternatives should be weighted and ordered according to priority. Due to these disadvantages, the CBR method alone does not guarantee a selection of a set of adequate EMAs, and, consequently, the sustainable performance of the environmental management system can be affected. This disadvantage is an advantage in the AHP method. Thus, the advantages related to both methods were integrated to reinforce the decision-making process to select adequate EMAs. </p>

<p>The criteria and alternatives determined to select the EMAs to be implemented depend on the needs and the context of the region under study. This dependence is multifactorial, where socioeconomic, sociopolitical, and technological factors play a very important role in the decision-making processes. For example, the highest priorities assigned to EMAs may be water availability or loss of vegetation cover for certain regions of developing countries, such as Mexico. Instead, the reduction of CO2 emissions may be the highest priority for European countries. These aspects make the task of selecting adequate EMAs in the decision-making processes even more difficult. The hybrid method proposed aims to support decision makers in this complex task. </p>

<p>The results obtained provided significant insights into the capacity of the hybrid CBR–AHP method to support the decision-making process in the selection of adequate EMAs to reduce the risky trends of an environmental state in a region. Such results also suggest expanding the number of KEPs and EMAs to test the capacity of the CBR–AHP method in more-complex scenarios and verify the limits of the consistency-checking method as criteria and alternatives increase. For future study, this CBR method could be replicated and applied to other environmental issues. Another important issue for future study is to enrich the MC by providing cases with information related to hints about the effort necessary to implement EMAs and about the expected results derived from an eventual implementation of EMAs.
 </p>
</text>
