<text id="autogum_voyage_doc88" title="Nisyros" shortTile="nisyros" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=24658" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Nisyros</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.nisyros.com">Nisyros</ref></hi> is a small island of the <ref target="Dodecanese">Dodecanese</ref> group, a few miles south of <ref target="Kos">Kos</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Nisyros, with fewer than 1,000 permanent inhabitants, is famous for having the only 'active' <hi rend="bold">volcano</hi> in Greece together with Santorini (Thyra). The island is essentially a volcanic cone with a large collapsed caldera in the center. It is possible to walk into the volcanic crater and view the smoking fumaroles at close hand.</p>

<p>There are two main villages on the island: <hi rend="bold">Mandraki</hi> in the north-west (where the ferries dock) and <hi rend="bold">Nikea</hi>, up on the edge of the volcanic rim to the south.</p>

<p>During the summer month the island is frequented daily by hundreds day-trip visitors from Kos that arrive on multiple boats in the morning, visit the crater, spend some time in <hi rend="italic">Mandraki</hi> and leave in the afternoon. Afterwards the island returns to its calm and relaxing atmosphere in which some traditional greek life can be enjoyed, therefore it's worth to stay for a night.</p>

<head>By sea</head>
<p>Nisyros is a popular day-trip destination from <ref target="Kos">Kos</ref> island. During the summer month, boats leave from Kos (Kardameina port) at 9:30 to <hi rend="italic">Mandraki</hi> and return at 15:30. Prices for a one-way boat-trip range from 5-8.5€.</p>

<p>Nisyros is also one of the stops for ferries that run between <ref target="Piraeus">Piraeus</ref> (on the Greek mainland) and <ref target="Rhodes">Rhodes</ref>, with other nearby stops being at <ref target="Kos">Kos</ref>, <ref target="Tilos">Tilos</ref> and <ref target="Symi">Symi</ref>.</p>
<p>Schedules for these can be found online.</p>
<p>Sailings are not to a regular daily schedule and become less frequent in the winter months.</p>

<p>In addition, a fast catamaran service runs to Rhodes on some days (via Tilos).</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>The villages on the island are small enough to stroll around on foot.</p>

<p>To travel between them, two there is an occasional bus service, the schedule can be found on http://www.nisyros.gr.</p>
<p>There are also about two taxis on the island. Given that there’s essentially only one road, hitchhiking is also an easy option.</p>

<p>There is a car and motorcycle rental based on the main port. Manos tel 2242031029.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Eagle's Nest Car &amp; Bike Rental</hi> (Pali Harbour), ☏ +30 6932732906 . Mike and his American wife Marilyn give very friendly service and very good tour advice. The office is next to the church in Pali Harbour. Mike is also a mechanic and the go to man for assistance.</item>
</list>


<p>Alternatively, it is a half day's hike between the two villages, via the volcanic crater.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The walk-in volcanic crater.</hi>. A path leads down to the yellow sulphur stained floor where you can walk up to and view the steaming vents. Try to avoid being here when the day-trip visitors come (~11:00). There’s a small café with shaded seats after the entrance. 3€ (free if you hiked there).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Nikia</hi>. A mountain-village at the ridge of the crater. The village is pretty, painted in blue and white. There’s one square with 2 restaurants. There’s a view-point to see down into the crater valley.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<p>Hiking between <hi rend="italic">Mandraki</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Nikia</hi> via the volcanic crater is a great day-trip. Beware of the elevation and the sun and pack enough water. The island’s peak can also be climbed, apparently one could sleep there with a sleeping bag (unverified).</p>
<p>There are multiple hiking paths between and Mandraki and the volcanic crater. The one east of the mountain is hard to find for the last part until it hits the paved street leading to the crater.</p>
<p>OpenStreepMap maps have good coverage of the trails. Most hotels on the island also have free maps available for anyone interested in walks around the island.</p>

<head>Eat</head>
<p><hi rend="italic">Mandraki</hi> has many restaurants. If you go with a group, try to avoid the places where the tour guide sends you to eat. Some tour guides get a commission from the restaurants, which means it will be expensive. Look around and try to avoid the main tourist pathways.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Nikia</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Emborios</hi> have just 1-2 restaurants, the <hi rend="italic">tavern</hi> in Emborios has a great view of the crater valley.</p>

<head>Drink</head>
<p><hi rend="italic">Mandraki</hi> has a few bars and lots of restaurants inviting for a drink.</p>

<head>Sleep</head>
<p>There’s very few hotels on the island. On some days all may be booked out. Book in advance and make sure to check with the hotel in case you’re arriving late.</p>

<p>Most hotels in <hi rend="italic">Mandraki</hi> are in the port area.</p>

<head>Budget</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Miramare</hi>, Mandraki, ☏ +30 22420 31100, +30 22420 31254 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ta Liotrida</hi>, Mandraki, ☏ +30 22420 31580 , ✉ info@nisyros-taliotridia.gr .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tria Aderfia</hi> (Three Brothers), Mandraki, ☏ +30 22420 31344 . Simple rooms, very friendly owner. Right next to the port. double-room from 32€.</item>
</list>


<head>Mid-range</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hotel Porfyris</hi>, Mandraki (400m from the sea). 2-star hotel with 38 rooms.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Haritos</hi>, Mandraki, ☏ +30 22420 31322 . 11 rooms</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">White Beach</hi>, Pali, ☏ +30 22420 31497 , fax: +30 22420 31389 . 2-star hotel with 47 rooms.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Polyvotis</hi>, ☏ +30-22420-31011 . 3-star hotel with 20 rooms.</item>
</list>
</text>
