<text id="autogum_voyage_doc185" title="Arad (Israel)" shortTile="arad-israel" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=1424" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Arad (Israel)</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.arad.muni.il/">Arad</ref></hi> (<hi rend="italic">Hebrew</hi>, &#1506;&#1512;&#1491;) is a small city in <ref target="Israel">Israel</ref> that lies on the border between the <ref target="Negev">Negev</ref> desert and the <ref target="Judaean%20Desert">Judaean Desert</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p><hi rend="italic">Tel Arad</hi>, the site of the ancient city of Arad, is located some 10 km west of the modern city centre. Arad is a great centre for hiking and exploring the northeastern part of the <ref target="Negev">Negev</ref> desert.</p>

<p>Modern Arad was founded in 1962 by young Israelis, most of them ex-kibbutzniks and ex-moshavniks, who were seeking an environment free of the urban ills of overcrowding, traffic, noise and pollution. Although not noted for its great beauty, the town's growth has closely followed a well-designed master plan. Arad's present population is approximately 28,000 (2003 estimate) and reflects the broad spectrum of Israeli society with a special emphasis on recent immigrants.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>Take a bus from <ref target="Beer%20Sheva">Beer Sheva</ref>. There are also less frequent buses from Tel Aviv, Jerusalem and other cities. Check the schedule for those ahead of time.</p>

<head>From Beer Sheva</head>
<p>From the Beer Sheva central bus station, line 386 (express), 387 (direct) and line 388 (higher frequency, but more intermediate stops) run to Arad. The price is ₪8.70.</p>

<head>From Tel Aviv</head>
<p>From <ref target="Tel%20Aviv">Tel Aviv</ref> (Arlozorov terminal only), lines 389 and 421 run to Arad. Each line has only 2-3 trips per day each direction. Line 421 continues to the Dead Sea.</p>

<p>In addition, line 550 runs from Bnei Brak to Arad, approximately 9 times per day.</p>

<head>From Jerusalem</head>
<p>From <ref target="Jerusalem">Jerusalem</ref>, lines 554 and 555 run to Arad. These lines are oriented to the Haredi sector, so they start in Haredi neighborhoods rather than the central bus station. Together these lines have about 9 trips per day in each direction.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>There are 5 local bus lines (Lines 1, 2, 3, 11 and 12) that serve all parts of the city. These lines are operated by Metropoline.</p>

<p>Having said that, Arad can easily be explored on foot.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tel Arad National Park</hi> (At the Tel Arad junction on Route 31 (Arad-Shoket junction) turn north on Route 2808 - the park is 2 miles north of the junction.), ☏ +972 7 776-2170, +972 8-9957 690 , fax: +972 7 995-5866 . Open April-September 8am-5pm, October-March 8am-4pm. The site of the ancient city, well worth a visit from an archaeological point of view. The site consists of two parts, the lower city (from the Bronze Age) and the upper city (an Israelite settlement). ₪<date when="2007-12-14">14/12/7</date> adult/student/child&amp;senior. </item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">"Eshet Lot" – The artists' quarter</hi>. An exclusive quarter with its own brand of desert atmosphere, combining creativity and artistry is in the heart of the industrial zone, on the road leading down to the Dead Sea. The artists, who are all inhabitants of Arad, united together to create a productive community with an enhanced sensitivity towards the environment.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Arad Visitors Centre</hi> (downtown Arad, close to the mall and community centre), ☏ +972 07 995-4409 . April-September 8am-5pm, October-March 8am-4pm. The Israel Nature and National Parks Protection Authority's visitors centre introduces visitors to the geology and history of the Judaean Desert. Its audiovisual program uses water and a 3D model of the Judaean Desert to demonstrate why this desert is so prone to flooding. Artifacts from Tel Arad and models of Canaanite Arad and the Israelite-period fortress are on display in the section devoted to history. A multi-screen video presentation brings the visitor back to the present and the modern city of Arad. The Visitors Centre has information on hiking trails, events and areas of interest in the Judaean Desert. Visitors can purchase maps, sheets with suggested hiking routes and related literature. adults ₪23, children ₪12.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Yatir Forest</hi>. One of the biggest forests in Israel and popular in summer for hiking and biking. The <ref target="Israel%20National%20Trail">Israel National Trail</ref> runs through the forest and by Tel Arad.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Moav Lookout</hi>. Here the Israeli artist Yigal Tumarkin created a big outdoor sculpture in 1968.</item>
<item> Camel herds, owned by the local Bedouins, can be spotted along the main road before and after the .</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>
<p>There are some <hi rend="bold">hiking</hi> destinations east. Align with the local tourist information.</p>

<p>The following lookouts are used as hiking or biking destinations from Arad: and .</p>

<head>Buy</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> The biggest shopping mall, , is located in the centre of the city</item>
<item> The is famous for its weekly market on Mondays</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>
<p>There are apparently many private rooms available for rent here – try the usual suspects.</p>

<head>Budget</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Arad Tandem</hi>, Gilad St 21, ☏ +972 8-9952207, +972 54-5439980 , ✉ Saltroomarad@gmail.com . This is the secret in town. Offers a great apartment with 3 rooms (including private) and all necessities. Book through their website or just call ahead, they are not so firm with online bookings, but you want to make sure it is not fully booked. Don't mind the dog when walking up to their house - there is no sign, you have to walk up on the left side and knock. From ₪95 for a bed in a 4 bed room (supposedly $34 during high season, but the website doesn't say something like it).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Dead Sea Adventure Hostel</hi>, Odem St 68 (Rotem), ☏ +972 58 4960748 , ✉ Deadseaadventurehostel@gmail.com . Also offers tours into the surrounding area. Dorms from ₪85.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Desert Bird Hostel</hi>, 28 Bareket St. (Rotem), ☏ +972 72-3902195 , ✉ desertbird2015@gmail.com . Another budget option. Member of ILH. Dorm bed from ₪100.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Israel YHA Hostel Arad</hi> (Blau-Weiss Hostel), ☏ +972 8-9957150 , ✉ arad@iyha.org.il . Book ahead, not to get an expensive private room offered if you arrive late. Dorm bed from ₪145.</item>
</list>


<head>Mid range / Splurge</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Inbar Hotel</hi>, 38 Yehuda Street, ☏ +972 8-997-3303 .</item>
</list>


<head>Go next</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Masada">Masada</ref></hi> – A former Roman fortress on top of a mountain. The only road access to the west side of Masada is through Arad. This route is popular for those arriving early for sunsets.</item>
</list>


<p>Besides that, Arad is a great location for trips to all directions including:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Dead%20Sea%20%28Israel%20and%20the%20West%20Bank%29">Dead Sea</ref> – One of the most famous things to see/do in Israel and <ref target="Jordan">Jordan</ref>.</item>
<item> <ref target="Judaean%20Desert">Judaean Desert</ref> – Visit its various attractions, next to the Dead Sea.</item>
<item> <ref target="Beer%20Sheva">Beer Sheva</ref> – University town, but does not much cater for tourists and especially backpackers.</item>
<item> <ref target="Mitzpe%20Ramon">Mitzpe Ramon</ref> – Great site, hikes and views on the edge of a giant crater.</item>
<item> <ref target="Eilat">Eilat</ref> – Holiday town in the far south with border crossings to <ref target="Jordan">Jordan</ref> and <ref target="Egypt">Egypt</ref>.</item>
</list>
</text>
