<text id="autogum_interview_doc194" title="part3_Andrea Muizelaar on fashion, anorexia, and life after &amp;apos;Top Model&amp;apos;" shortTile="partandrea-muizelaar" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-25" dateModified="2012-02-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Andrea_Muizelaar_on_fashion%2C_anorexia%2C_and_life_after_%27Top_Model%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> After the Pantene photo shoot, at panel, all the judges criticized your weight, specifically that you didn't weigh enough, and you later became defensive and said you ate well. This was interspersed with an interview from Alanna who said she never saw you eat a full meal the entire time you were in the house. The mantra quickly became "Andrea, you need to eat!" Now my question is, do you feel that they truly cared about whether you ate or not, and do you think that mantra was just an excuse to go, "Well, I did say she needed to eat..."?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> They obviously did not care as I ended up winning the show and only ate dinner with everybody once.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> What would you hypothesize is the reason for the disconnect between the fashion industry's definitions of "health," "attractiveness," and "beauty," and what most people, completely unrelated to the fashion industry, would see as healthy, attractive and beautiful?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> I have no idea why the image of beauty is so distorted and why the industry went wrong in the first place.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Twiggy">Twiggy</ref> herself has noted that models were more full-figured and traditionally "beautiful" before she came along, and that she thinks she may be a trend-setter in that regard. If you believe that's true, then do you think that she should be telling other potential models how to fit in "the mold," since she was the one who broke it in the first place?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> I personally do not believe that she had such impact on the whole industry.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> In your opinion, who do you think had the bigger impact? Is it one model? A series of models?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> Personally, that is well before my time and I'm unsure as to how exactly it changed.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> But you don't feel it's correct for Twiggy to "claim ownership" of today's "model look," as it were?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> No way!  No one in that industry has that much impact!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Do you feel that there are certain good qualities that the fashion industry has, and if so, what are they?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> No, because the clothes the average person wears are not even remotely close to high fashion modelling.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Alanna was bigger than you were, but still rather average in terms of everyday women. If she had won and not you, do you think she would have had a tougher time breaking into high fashion?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> For all I know - maybe she would be the one to break the mold of being skinny!  Ha, ha!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Alanna was a very strong competitor. Do you feel the final two was a good choice, or should someone else have taken Alanna's place?</p>
</text>
