<text id="autogum_interview_doc824" title="part9_Satanism: An interview with Church of Satan High Priest Peter Gilmore" shortTile="partsatanism-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-04" dateModified="2018-10-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Satanism%3A_An_interview_with_Church_of_Satan_High_Priest_Peter_Gilmore" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So much of the symbology references a lot of myths and superstitions, yet you’re antithetical to that.  How do you explain how those two notions comport?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  We have this approach that we take the dualities and find a third side to it, a way of integrating.  You might find that even in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marxism">Marxist theory</ref>, a way of finding opposites and coming with a new synthesis of the different thesis and antithesis.  So ritual is natural to people, because humans have a conceptual consciousness.  Symbols let us hold much more information in conscious focus, more so than just keeping them separately.  So symbols are something we function with.  It’s part of our nature.  So using ritual activities that are symbolic and have deep meaning to us is common to our species if you look at our history from cave paintings up to every civilization currently existing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It’s almost difficult to come up with a symbol that <hi rend="italic">doesn't</hi> reference a superstition in some way.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  Absolutely!  So we feel that since they are often used to support a fiction, why not let it be used to explore the inner part of our nature.  For us, when we do ritual—which we call greater magic—we call it an intellectual decompression chamber.  It’s a place where we release our emotions, any emotions that are hindering us, and we use the symbolism we find most stimulating.  We leave it in the ritual chamber. You enjoy the self-transformational psychodrama in the ritual where you release any emotions that are hindering yourself and then you go outside and basically pursue your life, being rational and doing what you need to do to make your life as rich as it can be.</p>
<head id="The_Iraq_War:_A_Satanic_perspective">The Iraq War: A Satanic perspective</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think our pursuing the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iraq_War">War in Iraq</ref> is an example of killing innocent people?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  Oh, of course <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Innocence">innocent</ref> people are being killed in almost any war.  It doesn't matter if it is just Iraq, because there are civilian populations who are caught between these people with agendas, and those civilians just want to live their lives.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Who are the innocents?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  Not being involved in the particular conflict.  If you are just living your life and doing what you need to do to survive, have a job, bringing in food for your family; that’s being an innocent person.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How has the war in Iraq affected your worldview?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  It hasn't changed it in the least.  I see it as human behavior as usual.  History is full of aggressors.  Iraq to me is an interesting place where there was a totalitarian holding in check religious factions, and now that cap has been removed, the religious factions want to destroy each other.  I think it’s a lesson for most people to say look at how these religions were important to people who are always looking above themselves to be regulated, and they found an Earthly regulator in Saddam Hussein, and now that that regulator who actually existed is gone, they are each looking to their own interpretations of their own deities and wanting to slaughter each other.  It just shows how poisonous fundamentalist fanaticism can be, which to me is the most dangerous thing in all of human society.</p>
</text>
