<text id="autogum_voyage_doc302" title="Seville" shortTile="seville" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=32267" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Seville</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.turismosevilla.org/ing-index.html">Seville</ref></hi> (<ref target="Spanish%20phrasebook">Spanish</ref>: <hi rend="italic">Sevilla</hi>) <ref target="Andalucia">Andalucia</ref>'s capital. With more than 700,000 inhabitants, and 1.6 million in the metropolitan area, it is Spain's fourth city, dominating southern Spain. With heritage from the Arabs and from the Age of Discovery, as well as the <hi rend="italic">flamenco</hi> scene, Seville is a diverse destination.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>The smooth, slow Guadalquivir River flows through Seville, known as <hi rend="italic">Betis</hi> by the Romans and as <hi rend="italic">Betik Wahd-Al-Khabir</hi> by the Arabs. Since it is hard to navigate upstream from Seville, the cereal-producing region starts here, and Seville has been a busy port from Roman times, under Muslim rule, and exploding during the Age of Discovery. As the monopoly was broken and <ref target="C%C3%A1diz">Cádiz</ref> largely took Seville's place, the city entered a period of relative decline.</p>

<p>In the 19th century Seville gained a reputation for its architecture and culture and was a stop along the Romantic "<ref target="Grand%20Tour">Grand Tour</ref>" of Europe. Seville has built on its tourism industry since, playing host to the International Exposition in 1992, which spurred the construction of a new airport, a new train station, a bullet train link to Madrid, new bridges and improvements to the main boulevards. Tourist facilities are top-notch and the city is buzzing with festivals, color and a thriving nightlife scene.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sevilla International Airport</hi> ( SVQ ) is about 25 minutes drive from the city center.</p>

<p>A bus service <ref target="http://www.tussam.es/index.php%3Fid%3D432">"Especial Aeropuerto (EA)"</ref> runs about every 30 minutes from just outside the "Arrivals" hall during most of the day (though with longer gaps from 13:00-16:00) and costs €4.00. Taxis are always available next to the bus stop and run on a fixed fare to Seville center, €22 during the day and €25 after 22:00 and on weekends/holidays. Much controversy has been stirred by some taxi drivers trying to overcharge tourists, so be careful to pay no more than this if you are traveling into the city. Other destinations outside Seville obviously cost more and are metered. Tips are <hi rend="italic">not</hi> necessary, though €1-2 for polite, helpful service is appreciated. Speed limits seem to be considered as kind of minimum speed by most taxi drivers.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">La Parra International Airport</hi> ( XRY ) is 10 km from <ref target="Jerez%20de%20la%20Frontera">Jerez de la Frontera</ref>, on the way to Seville.</p>

<p>This airport is in a nearby city, and is used by discount airlines such as Ryanair (from Frankfurt-Hahn London-Stansted). The communication between Jerez de la Frontera and Seville is good, as it is connected by bus and train. It is also possible to go by taxi or rent car.</p>

<p>Ryanair also flies to Sevilla International Airport, from more destinations than Jerez.</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>High-speed <ref target="http://www.renfe.com/EN/viajeros/larga_distancia/productos/index.html"><hi rend="bold">AVE</hi></ref> trains are great if time is of the essence, less than an hour from the wonderful city of <ref target="C%C3%B3rdoba%20%28city%2C%20Spain%29">Córdoba</ref>, less than three hours run from <ref target="Madrid">Madrid</ref> to Seville. However, slower <ref target="http://www.renfe.com/EN/viajeros/index.html"><hi rend="bold">RENFE</hi></ref> trains remain a bargain, and there is an overnight train that runs from <ref target="Barcelona">Barcelona</ref> to Seville in under 11 hours.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Estación de Sevilla-Santa Justa</hi> (Sevilla Santa Justa Station), Avda Kansas City, ☏ +34 902 432 343 . M-F 04:30-00:30, Sa Su and holidays 05:15-00:30. On the eastern edge of Seville city centre. Completed in 1991, the station is the southern terminus of the Spanish high-speed AVE train service. Has luggage lockers, cafés, and a tourist information centre.Santa Justa also serves many of the principal stations in Andalucia, including 'Media Distancia' trains to <ref target="Cadiz">Cadiz</ref>, <ref target="Ja%C3%A9n%20%28city%2C%20Spain%29">Jaén</ref>, and <ref target="Malaga">Malaga</ref>.</item>
</list>

 

<head>By car</head>
<p>Driving is also always an option for long distance travel in Spain, but isn't as convenient or as useful once in town. Public transportation works fine in the city, and most of the main tourist points are located in a walk distance, so it is recommended finding a lodging with a garage or else researching the area for parking places before the trip.</p>

<p>Driving in the old city is tricky but possible. There is a 45-minute limit on cars entering the old city M-Sa 08:00 and 22:00. It is enforced by license plate scanners placed at entrances to the old city. There is a €200 fine for exceeding this limit. Your rental company will be sure to tack on its €50 processing charge, not to mention the late fees that will accumulate due to the time it till take to receive the citation in your home country. </p>

<p>There is very cheap parking available across the street from Av. de Málaga, 12. The lot is unguarded and if there is not agent in the booth then the entrance to the lot is free of charge. Do not give money to the panhandlers loitering outside pretending they are lot attendants. If they have not receipt to give you then its a scam. Be sure leave absolutely nothing in the car. Seville in general is known for car break-ins. </p>

<p>Another very common option is using carpooling such as BlaBlaCar, a safe transportation method used by many locals.</p>

<head>By bus</head>

<p>The Spanish bus service is amazingly punctual and comfortable with most having air-con and a toilet. Getting to Seville from other cities in Spain can sometimes be only minimally longer than train (but much cheaper). Check out your options first with the helpful Information desk you will find inside any terminal. The buses run regularly to/from most major cities, departing either from the near the river, or the near the University/Santa Cruz. Sometimes the queue for buying ticket from the ticket office on a busy day might take up to 20 minutes or more.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> El Rocio - Sevilla M-F 10:15, Sa 10:45, daily 15:15, daily 18:15</item>
<item> Sevilla - El Rocio Sa 08:00, Su 08:15, M-F 09:30, Sa Su 11:00, daily 15:00, M-F 17:00</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> Jerez - Sevilla daily 08:30 13:00 14:30 22:45 23:30 (M-Sa there is an extra bus at 08:40)</item>
<item> Sevilla - Jerez daily 08:00 08:30 13:00 16:00 20:00 21:30 23:00</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> Alicante - Sevilla daily at 00:00</item>
<item> Sevilla - Alicante daily at 22:00</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> Cordoba - Sevilla daily at 05:15, 08:35, 11:00, 11:45, 16:30, 18:45, 20:00</item>
<item> Sevilla - Cordoba daily at 08:00, 09:00, 13:45, 15:00, 16:15, 18:30, 22:01</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> Granada - Sevilla Daily at 03:00, 07:00, 08:00, 12:00, 14:00, 15:30, 16:30, 20:30</item>
<item> Sevilla - Granada Daily at 07:45, 09:30, 11:15, 12:00, 16:00, 17:15, 20:00, 23:00</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> Malaga- Sevilla Daily at 12:00, 15:00, 17:30, 18:00, 20:30 also M-F 09:00, Sa Su and holiday 09:15</item>
<item> Sevilla - Malaga Daily at 07:00, 08:00, 12:00, 15:00, 18:00, 20:30</item>
</list>
</text>
