<text id="autogum_interview_doc036" title="part1_Wikinews interviews India&amp;apos;s first female Paralympic medalist Deepa Malik" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-09-13" dateModified="2018-01-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_India%27s_first_female_Paralympic_medalist_Deepa_Malik" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What message should other Indian women take away from your participation and result in Rio?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DM</hi>:  This is going to be the first female medal that India would have ever won in Paralympics and as it is I'm working aggressively towards transforming this entire concept of empowerment for the women, especially the women in disabilities in my country. So I'm really happy that this medal give my voice more value, more strength, and I'll be able to impact even more, though on the ninth of September the Prime Minister's jury has awarded me with the award of Women Transforming India, I'm so happy that within three days of getting that award, I have added another feather to it and proved that yes this journey of ability beyond disability. And not just disability, this is a universal message that if women put their minds to their dreams they can balance it; age, gender, disability, is all a state of mind. If you put your passion and hard work, you can get it, and in the Indian scenario were they say infrastructure is a challenge, women participation that are taboo, religiously and psychologically, disabilities taken as a curse, dependability[?] increases because of lack of infrastructure, well, time to get rid of the excuses. We have to start erasing the excuses and believe your own self and that's the message I'm carrying with all the activities that I do whether it is car rallying, motorbiking or swimming across a river, every record or every unique activity that I've undertaken and just below paralysis has been aimed at changing the stereotypical image of a women and also a women in disability.  </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Will you and your daughter both be trying to represent India at the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2020_Summer_Paralympics">2020 Games</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tokyo">Tokyo</ref>?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DM</hi>:  I'm very sure about myself, but my daughter, though, she's a Paralympian, yes, which again was considered a huge taboo in my society that oh my god both the mother and the daughter both have a physical disability, what is going to happen to these two, but we did good and she is working as a youth council representative in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Commonwealth%20of%20Nations">Commonwealth</ref> countries, for the Paralympics specially, and her work though her foundation called Wheeling Happiness has earned her the young leader award from the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Elizabeth_II">Queen of England</ref>, so I guess her focus is now shifting to more on community service and empowering others and not just herself. And she is leaving on first of October to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loughborough%20University">Loughborough</ref> to do her PhD doctorate programme in disability sports psychology, I'm very sure Loughborough is going to give her a huge amount of sports [inaudible] but how much time she going to decide to devote to sports and studies is her decision entirely. That's her dream, her journey. </p>
</text>
