<text id="autogum_academic_doc492" title="Current Therapeutic Strategies in Diabetic Foot Ulcers" shortTile="current-therapeutic" author="Aurelio Perez-Favila, Margarita  L Martinez-Fierro, Jessica  G Rodriguez-Lazalde, Miguel  A Cid-Baez, Michelle  de J Zamudio-Osuna, Ma.  del Rosario Martinez-Blanco, Fabiana  E Mollinedo-Montaño, Iram  P Rodriguez-Sanchez, Rodrigo Castañeda-Miranda, Idalia Garza-Veloz" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1010-660X/55/11/714/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Treatments for Diabetic Foot Ulcers</head>
<p>
One strategy for the management of patients with a DFU is to introduce a multidisciplinary approach and address the multifactorial processes involved in DFUs. The use of multi-disciplinary teams (MDTs) that include all relevant specialties (i.e., nursing, orthopedics, plastic surgery, vascular surgery, nutrition, and endocrinology departments) has shown an effect of decreasing the risks associated with DFUs and amputation by 50–85%, lowering costs, and leading to a better quality of life for patients with DFUs. </p>

<p>Management of DFUs requires the correct classification of stage and severity. Adequate care for DFUs should include a focus on DM control as well as on wound care, proper infection control, relieving pressure, and optimizing blood flow. The basic care for the control and treatment of DFUs is focused on the management of adequate perfusion, pressure mitigation, control of infection, and debridement. With technological advancement, other series of therapies for DFUs have been implemented, such as the development of skin substitutes, negative pressure wound therapy, hyperbaric oxygen, the creation of new wound dressings that include growth factors, and the use of tissues from bioengineering. In this way, treatments for DPN, PAD, and infections have provided encouraging results. </p>

<head> 4.1. Treatments for Diabetic Peripheral Neuropathy</head>
<p>
DPN is a factor that increases the risk of the appearance of a DFU, owing to the loss of sensation in the limb, making patients vulnerable to trauma. Tight glycemic control is the primary step and a main feature of DPN management. Normoglycemia is more effectively restored by a pancreas transplant. Several studies have demonstrated improvement of motor and sensory neuropathy in patients with DPN after they were treated with a pancreas transplant. However, discrepancies exist in the time of response. </p>

<p>Pharmacological treatment is used for painful DPN manifested as numbness, burning, stabbing, or excruciating or intractable pain; only three treatments are approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration for the pain associated with DPN, namely, pregabalin, tapentadol, and duloxetine. </p>

<p>Another pharmacological therapy includes analgesics, such as tramadol, acetaminophen, and some opioids such as oxycodone, which have constipation and nausea as side effects, and must be taken with care because they can be misused. Therapy with antidepressants such as amitriptyline, nortriptyline, and venlafaxine, among others, has shown an efficacy in neuropathic pain management. It has an effect on the recapture of noradrenaline and serotonin, as well as on muscarinic effects. In spite of this, there are limited studies evaluating these drugs because their doses in clinical trials are not entirely reproducible in clinical practice. </p>

<p>Alpha-lipoic acid (ALA) has been suggested as a potential therapeutic agent in treating DPN; its antioxidant capacity seems to delay or reverse damages to peripheral nerves. Several human randomized controlled trials (RCTs) have investigated the effects of ALA in the development of diabetic nephropathy. A meta-analysis of four RCTs (n = 653) showed that, compared with placebo, intravenous ALA (600 mg per day) decreased symptoms of neuropathy when administered for three weeks, but symptom improvement with oral ALA (&gt;600 mg per day for 3–5 weeks) was not clinically significant. There is no evidence evaluating long-term treatment. </p>

<p>Currently, treatments based on the use of mesenchymal stem cells (MSC) derived from adipose tissue have been considered as a potential treatment against DPN. These therapies promote the production of pro-angiogenic, neuroprotective, and anti-inflammatory factors, which have a positive impact on the clinical manifestations of the disease. </p>

<p>On the other hand, the use of biological therapy with low doses of IL-6 has been demonstrated to promote improvement of blood flow, decrease chronic inflammation, and regenerate peripheral nerve fibers. Accordingly, IL-6 may prove to be an effective treatment for the protection and/or restoration of peripheral nerve function in DPN; see Table 1. </p>

<head> 4.2. Treatments for Peripheral Arterial Disease (Ischemia)</head>
<p>
Ischemia presenting in diabetic patients due to a reduction in blood flow that occurs in both small vessels (microvascular, such as capillaries) and large vessels (macrovascular, such as arteries and veins), or due to a decrease of angiogenesis, can be treated through revascularization of at least one of the foot arteries to try to restore blood flow in patients with a DFU whose toe pressure is &lt;30 mmHg or transcutaneous oxygen pressure (TcPO2) &lt;25 mmHg, as well as in those who have a DFU that does not heal with pressure on the ankle of &lt;50 mmHg or ankle-brachial index (ABI) &lt;0.5. </p>
</text>
