<text id="autogum_academic_doc680" title="The Role of Regional Determinants in the Deployment of Renewable Energy in Farms. The Case of Spain" shortTile="role-regional-determinants" author="María  J. Ruiz-Fuensanta, María-Jesús Gutiérrez-Pedrero, Miguel-Ángel Tarancón" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5937/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Results</head>
<p>
One of the requirements for applying the multilevel analysis technique is that the between-groups variance of the dependent variable is significant. To verify this, a variance decomposition model will be used with a single factor coinciding with the grouping variable, in this case the region, in which explanatory variables are not included. Due to its basic character, this model is known in the literature as <hi rend="italic">null model or empty model</hi>. The first column of Table 5 shows the results of the estimation of this model. </p>

<p>The inter-region variance is estimated at 0.26 with a standard error of 0.19. The likelihood ratio test has a value of 7.56 with an associated p-value of less than 0.01. This result confirms the existence of a non-zero inter-region variance, and therefore, justifies the application of the multilevel analysis technique. From these values it is possible to calculate the intra-class correlation (ICC) as a representative measure of the variation percentage of the dependent variable which is attributable to differences between the regions. </p>

<p>In this case, it is observed that most of the variation in the dependent variable has its origin in the differences between farms, while 7.3% of this said variance, based on the CCI value, can be attributed to differences in regional factors.  </p>

<p>Although it may seem like an influence of reduced magnitude, it is a logical value, since the intra-class correlation tends to be smaller the larger the theoretical dimension of the group, its value oscillating between 0.05 and 0.85%, for example, when the group identifies with the region. </p>

<p>Regarding the selection of explanatory variables, we follow a stepwise strategy. Thus, in the first model (Model 1) only variables at the farm level are entered, so that it is possible to establish comparisons with previous studies. Then, in a second estimate, the model is expanded to incorporate the regional level variables (Model 2). The inclusion of the regional characteristics results in a slight improvement of the Akaike Information Criterion (AIC) (from a value of 457.45 to a value of 457.15), while the goodness of fit measures considered (pseudo-R2) exhibit an appreciable increase. In Model 3, we intend to isolate the effect of the contextual variables related to the action of regional authorities (CAPACITY and R&amp;D). As shown in Table 5, this most parsimonious model gives rise to an improvement of the Akaike Information Criterion (AIC), as compared to Model 2. </p>

<p>As for explanatory variables pertaining to the farm dimension, the results point to four statistically significant variables. Three of them, PROFES, PERMANENT and SIZE, which have a relevant and positive effect on the probability that the farm will invest in renewable energies, refer to the characteristics of the farm, while the fourth, EDUCATION, corresponds to a characteristic of the person in charge. With regard to, firstly, the characteristics of the farm, as expected, the dimension (SIZE) is an element that determines the willingness to invest in renewable energy. It is well known that business size is an indicator that serves as a proxy for the set of financial and human resources of a company. In this sense, it is logical that the larger the farm size, the greater the probability of embarking on new projects other than the main activity. This result, together with the positive effect of the PROFES and PERMANENT variables that represent, respectively, their legal status and workforce stability, demonstrate that management professionalization and the solidity of the farm are elements that work in favor of investment in a renewable infrastructure. This could be in line with the opinion of authors who believe that this type of investment is favored by the farm’s orientation towards obtaining an economic profit, which would be achieved through a strategy of production diversification. On the other hand, other variables referring to the farm characteristics do not have statistically significant coefficients. Thus, PROPERTY, which includes the fact that most of the surface of the farm is owned by the person in charge, has a positive parameter associated, consistent with literature, which points to the fact that the ownership of the farm favors investment in renewables; although in this case this relationship is not statistically significant. The same applies to ECO, which indicates whether the holding is dedicated to organic farming, which in the opinion of several authors favors investment in renewables. The positive sign of the coefficient is consistent with this opinion, although the estimated relationship is not statistically significant. </p>
</text>
