<text id="autogum_interview_doc110" title="part1_Wikinews interviews specialists on South Korea military parade" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-10-02" dateModified="2015-01-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_specialists_on_South_Korea_military_parade" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<figure><caption> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/President%20of%20South%20Korea">South Korean President</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Park%20Geun-Hye">Park Geun-Hye</ref> with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/America">United States</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/President_of_the_United_States">President</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref>. Image: White House.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Kosal</hi>: The "display" was multi-functional. It shows the modern, indigenous conventional military capabilities of the South Korean forces. It was also to credibly communicate — literally show to the North — possession of an adequate deterrent force, a force that is both capable and credible. The underlying capacity supports the newly announced bilateral tailored deterrence strategy between South Korea and the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref>. The military parade served to transparently show, in a largely passive/non-offensive/non-reactionary  way, the capacity to follow through on that strategy that is directed at North Korea's offensive <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Nuclear_weapons">nuclear weapons</ref>, offensive <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Chemical_weapons">chemical weapons</ref>, and offensive <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Biological_weapons">biological weapons</ref> programs rather than a more general deterrence strategy. There is much more to a tailored deterrence strategy, but that is one part of it. The specific declaratory policy highlights South Korea's responsibility to "continue to build reliable inter-operable response capabilities and to develop the Korean Air and Missile Defense system."  These are largely passive defense measures to minimize the effects of a North Korean offensive attack and to reduce vulnerability of South Korean forces and civilians. It's part of the overall strategic defense posture.</p>
<p>While not commonly observed in the US, parades like this are not atypical for East Asia, particularly in conjunction with significant anniversaries. In this case, the parade also marked the 65th anniversary of the Republic of Korea [South Korea] Armed Forces. In addition to the international visibility, it also serves South Korean domestic politics and advances South Korean President <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Park%20Geun-hye">Park Geun-hye</ref>'s own strong national security policies.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ledyard</hi>: It could very well be, but I have no knowledge regarding it. It has long been routine for both Koreas to compete in the headlines.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Terry</hi>: President Park is trying to make it clear to the North that this time, under her watch, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Seoul">Seoul</ref> is now serious about responding to future provocations by the North.  South Korea's display of its missiles is meant to deter the North, to show the North that any provocation in the future would be met with strong retaliation.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chi</hi>: The institution of the military parade has been a regular feature of the Armed Forces’ Day celebration in South Korea. Yet the display of the cruise missiles in the recent parade is designed to achieve specific purposes. One is obviously targeting at the North Korean regime as a warning for possible pre-emptive strikes on their conventional and nuclear missile sites. The other target is South Korean citizens who have been increasingly agitated about the possession of WMDs by its Northern counterpart and want to see some guarantee from their own government. Hence the parade is not only for displaying its military capabilities to its enemies but it is also playing a psychological game with its own people. Yet, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyunmoo-3">Hyunmoo-3c</ref>, one of the cruise missiles displayed in the event, signals that the South Korean government’s perspective is no longer limited to the Korean peninsula. Hyunmoo-3c’s range of 1,500<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/kilometer">km</ref> indicates that the Korean military oversees the entire Northeast Asian region as its strategic theatre. Such a wide strategic thinking is also behind the planned construction of the naval base in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeju%20Island">Jeju Island</ref>.</p>
</text>
