<text id="autogum_news_doc424" title="Paralympic highlights: September 7, 2008" shortTile="paralympic-highlights" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-09-07" dateModified="2017-10-19" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Paralympic_highlights%3A_September_7%2C_2008" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Paralympic highlights: September 7, 2008</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, September 7, 2008</hi></p>
<p>September 7, 2008 is the 1st major day of the 2008 Paralympic games, the below article summarises all the world records and medals.</p>
<head id="World_Records">World Records</head>
<head id="Swimming">Swimming</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>In the S13 class, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dzmitry%20Salei">Dzmitry Salei</ref> from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Belarus">Belarus</ref> set a new world record in the final of the men's 100m butterfly with his time of 58.89 seconds.</item>
<item>In the S4 class, Patricia Valle from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mexico">Mexico</ref> set a new world record in Heat 1 of the women's 100m freestyle event with her time of 2:03.82 minutes.</item>
<item>In the SM7 class, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/USA">American swimmer</ref> Rudy Garcia Tolson  set a new world record in heat two of the men's 200m individual medley with his time of 2:37.80 minutes.</item>
<item>In the S8 class, Peter Leek from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia">Australia</ref> set a new world record in the first heat of the men's 100m butterfly with his time of 1 minute and 1.01 seconds .</item>
<item>In the S8 class, Amanda Everlove from the United States set a new world record in the second heat of the women's 100m butterfly with her time of 1 minute and 11.64 seconds .</item>
<item>In the S9 class, Tamas Sors from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hungary">Hungary</ref> set a new world record in the first heat of the men's 100m butterfly with his time of 59.38 seconds.</item>
<item>With a time of 4:45.43, Russian Dmitry Kokarev set a new world record in the S2 class of the men's 200m freestyle.</item>
<item>With a time of 1:35.21, Chinese Du Jianping set a new world record in the S3 class of the men's 100m freestyle.</item>
<item>With a time of 1:11.05, Brazilian Daniel Dias set a new world record in the S5 class of the men's 100m freestyle.</item>
<item>With a time of 1:16.65, Spanish Maria Teresa Perales set a new world record in the S5 class of the women's 100m freestyle.</item>
<item>With a time of 3:13.05, American Miranda Uhl set a new world record in the SM6 class of the women's 200m individual medley.</item>
<item>With a time of 2:54.61, American Erin Popovich set a new world record in the SM7 class of the women's 200m individual medley.</item></list>
<head id="Cycling">Cycling</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>In the CP3 class, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UK">British cyclist</ref> Darren Kenny set a new world record in the qualifying stage of the men's individual pursuit with his time of 3:36.875 minutes.</item>
<item>With a time of 4:18.961, Australians Kieran Modra and Tyson Lawrence set a new world in the B&amp;VI 1-3 class of the men's individual pursuit.</item>
<item>With a time of 1:14.936, British Simon Richardson set a new world in the LC 3-4 class of the men's 1km time trial.</item>
<item>With a time of 1:21.157, Britons Ellen Hunter and Aileen McGlynn set a new world in the B&amp;VI 1-3 class of the women's 1km time trial.</item></list>
<head id="Shooting">Shooting</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>With a score of 578, Russian Valeriy Ponomarenko set a new world in the SH1 class of the men's P1-10m air pistol.</item></list>
<head id="Gold_medals">Gold medals</head>
<head id="Track_Cycling">Track Cycling</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Christopher Scott of Australia won the gold medal in the CP4 class of the men's individual pursuit.</item>
<item>Darren Kenny of Great Britain won the gold medal in the CP3 class of the men's individual pursuit.</item>
<item>Kieran Modra and Tyson Lawrence of Australia won the gold medal in the B&amp;VI 1-3 class of the men's individual pursuit.</item>
<item>Simon Richardson of Great Britain won the gold medal in the LC 3-4 class of the men's 1km time trial.</item>
<item>Aileen McGlynn and Ellen Hunter of Great Britain won the gold medal in the B&amp;VI 1-3 class of the women's 1km time trial.</item></list>
<head id="Judo">Judo</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Huaping Guo of China won the gold medal in the -48 kg class Judo.</item></list>
<head id="Shooting_2">Shooting</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Valeriy Pomomarenko of Russia won the gold medal in the SH1 class of the men's P1-10m air pistol.</item>
<item>Veronika Vadovicova of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Slovakia">Slovakia</ref> won the gold medal in the SH1 class of the women's R2-10m air rifle standing.</item></list>
<head id="Swimming_2">Swimming</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Du Jianping of China won the gold medal in the S3 class of the men's 100m freestyle.</item>
<item>David Smetanine of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">France</ref> won the gold medal in the S4 class of the men's 100m freestyle.</item>
<item>Daniel Dias of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brazil">Brazil</ref> won the gold medal in the S5 class of the men's 100m freestyle.</item>
<item>Dmitry Kokarev of Russia won the gold medal in the S2 class of the men's 200m freestyle.</item>
<item>Dzmitry Salei of Russia won the gold medal in the S13 class of the men's 100m butterfly.</item>
<item>Sascha Kindred of Great Britain won the gold medal in the S13 class of the men's 200m individual medley.</item>
<item>Nely Miranda of Mexico won the gold medal in the S4 class of the women's 100m freestyle.</item>
<item>Maria Teresa Perales of Spain won the gold medal in the S5 class of the women's 100m freestyle.</item>
<item>Valerie Grand Maison of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada">Canada</ref> won the gold medal in the S13 class of the women's 100m butterfly.</item>
<item>Miranda Uhl of the United States won the gold medal in the SM6 class of the women's 200m individual medley.</item>
<item>Erin Popovixh of the United States won the gold medal in the SM7 class of the women's 200m individual medley.</item></list>
<head id="Medal_Table">Medal Table</head>
<hi rend="bold">2008 Paralympics - Beijing, China     </hi>
Flag
Country
G
S
B
TOT
Rank
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/China%20at%20the%202008%20Summer%20Olympics">China</ref>
8
10
10
28
1
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/USA%20at%20the%202008%20Summer%20Olympics">USA</ref>
8
4
5
17
2
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great%20Britain%20at%20the%202008%20Summer%20Olympics">Great Britain</ref>
7
5
3
15
3
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Australia%20at%20the%202008%20Summer%20Olympics">Australia</ref>
6
5
10
21
4
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South%20Africa%20at%20the%202008%20Summer%20Olympics">South Africa</ref>
4
0
0
4
5
<p>Source: <ref target="http://results.beijing2008.cn/WRMP/ENG/INF/GL/95A/GL0000000.shtml">Official Medal Count</ref> (<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Template:2008_Beijing_Paralympic_medal_count">update</ref>)
</p>
</text>
