<text id="autogum_fiction_doc442" title="Twenty Years After" shortTile="twentyyears" author="Dumas, Alexandre" type="fiction" dateCollected="2019-10-22" sourceURL="http://gutenberg.readingroo.ms/1/2/5/1259/1259-0.txt">
<head>CONTENTS</head>

<p>1. The Shade of Cardinal Richelieu. 2. A Nightly Patrol. 3. Dead Animosities. 4. Anne of Austria at the Age of Forty-six. 5. The Gascon and the Italian. 6. D’Artagnan in his Fortieth Year. 7. Touches upon the Strange Effects a Half-pistole may have. 8. D’Artagnan, Going to a Distance to discover Aramis. 9. The Abbe D’Herblay. 10. Monsieur Porthos du Vallon de Bracieux de Pierrefonds. 11. Wealth does not necessarily produce Happiness. 12. Porthos was Discontented with his Condition. 13. Two Angelic Faces. 14. The Castle of Bragelonne. 15. Athos as a Diplomatist. 16. The Duc de Beaufort. 17. Duc de Beaufort amused his Leisure Hours in the Donjon of Vincennes. 18. Grimaud begins his Functions. 19. Pates made by the Successor of Father Marteau are described. 20. One of Marie Michon’s Adventures. 21. The Abbe Scarron. 22. Saint Denis. 23. One of the Forty Methods of Escape of the Duc de Beaufort. 24. The timely Arrival of D’Artagnan in Paris. 25. An Adventure on the High Road. 26. The Rencontre. 27. The four old Friends prepare to meet again. 28. The Place Royale. 29. The Ferry across the Oise. 30. Skirmishing. 31. The Monk. 32. The Absolution. 33. Grimaud Speaks. 34. On the Eve of Battle. 35. A Dinner in the Old Style. 36. A Letter from Charles the First. 37. Cromwell’s Letter. 38. Henrietta Maria and Mazarin. 39. How, sometimes, the Unhappy mistake Chance for Providence. 40. Uncle and Nephew. 41. Paternal Affection. 42. Another Queen in Want of Help. 43. In which it is proved that first Impulses are oftentimes the best. 44. Te Deum for the Victory of Lens. 45. The Beggar of St. Eustache. 46. The Tower of St. Jacques de la Boucherie. 47. The Riot. 48. The Riot becomes a Revolution. 49. Misfortune refreshes the Memory. 50. The Interview. 51. The Flight. 52. The Carriage of Monsieur le Coadjuteur. 53. How D’Artagnan and Porthos earned by selling Straw. 54. In which we hear Tidings of Aramis. 55. The Scotchman. 56. The Avenger. 57. Oliver Cromwell. 58. Jesus Seigneur. 59. Noble Natures never lose Courage, nor good Stomachs their Appetites. 60. Respect to Fallen Majesty. 61. D’Artagnan hits on a Plan. 62. London. 63. The Trial. 64. Whitehall. 65. The Workmen. 66. Remember! 67. The Man in the Mask. 68. Cromwell’s House. 69. Conversational. 70. The Skiff “Lightning.” 71. Port Wine. 72. End of the Port Wine Mystery. 73. Fatality. 74. How Mousqueton had a Narrow Escape of being eaten. 75. The Return. 76. The Ambassadors. 77. The three Lieutenants of the Generalissimo. 78. The Battle of Charenton. 79. The Road to Picardy. 80. The Gratitude of Anne of Austria. 81. Cardinal Mazarin as King. 82. Precautions. 83. Strength and Sagacity. 84. Strength and Sagacity--Continued. 85. The Oubliettes of Cardinal Mazarin. 86. Conferences. 87. Thinking that Porthos will be at last a Baron, and D’Artagnan a Captain. 88. Shows how with Threat and Pen more is effected than by the Sword. 89. Difficult for Kings to return to the Capitals of their Kingdoms. 90. Conclusion.</p>

<p>1. The Shade of Cardinal Richelieu.</p>

<p>In a splendid chamber of the Palais Royal, formerly styled the Palais Cardinal, a man was sitting in deep reverie, his head supported on his hands, leaning over a gilt and inlaid table which was covered with letters and papers. Behind this figure glowed a vast fireplace alive with leaping flames; great logs of oak blazed and crackled on the polished brass andirons whose flicker shone upon the superb habiliments of the lonely tenant of the room, which was illumined grandly by twin candelabra rich with wax-lights.</p>

<p>Any one who happened at that moment to contemplate that red simar--the gorgeous robe of office--and the rich lace, or who gazed on that pale brow, bent in anxious meditation, might, in the solitude of that apartment, combined with the silence of the ante-chambers and the measured paces of the guards upon the landing-place, have fancied that the shade of Cardinal Richelieu lingered still in his accustomed haunt.</p>

<p>It was, alas! the ghost of former greatness. France enfeebled, the authority of her sovereign contemned, her nobles returning to their former turbulence and insolence, her enemies within her frontiers--all proved the great Richelieu no longer in existence.</p>

<p>In truth, that the red simar which occupied the wonted place was his no longer, was still more strikingly obvious from the isolation which seemed, as we have observed, more appropriate to a phantom than a living creature--from the corridors deserted by courtiers, and courts crowded with guards--from that spirit of bitter ridicule, which, arising from the streets below, penetrated through the very casements of the room, which resounded with the murmurs of a whole city leagued against the minister; as well as from the distant and incessant sounds of guns firing--let off, happily, without other end or aim, except to show to the guards, the Swiss troops and the military who surrounded the Palais Royal, that the people were possessed of arms.</p>
</text>
