<text id="autogum_reddit_doc011" title="FF:DOO and Monetization" shortTile="ffdoo-monetization" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-05-31" dateModified="2018-05-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8njz9h" speakerList="#RobertAWing, #TastedCorn" speakerCount="2">
<head>FF:DOO and Monetization</head>
<sp who="#RobertAWing">
<p>Hi there, Like many, I've been playing the game since GL launch, and have honestly been having a great time. I tried RK and BE, and couldn't really get into them for a myriad of reasons. This game, however, has hit the proverbial spot as a longtime fan of the franchise. I've had a QoL gripes over the course of my time playing, but most of them have been handled, and they were honestly small things to begin with. My only major gripe is the game's monetization model. I should preface the rest of this post by saying that I'm someone who does have access to expendable income, and does enjoy supporting F2P games I frequent. This is to say, I definitely do not mind spending money as a means of saying thanks to SE, and helping to ensure the longevity of the title. That out of the way, FF:DOO's monetization approach is one of the most oddly punishing approaches I've ever encountered. Short version as to why: 1. Pricing - Without sales, pricing for pulls is bonkers, especially in a game like this where, if you're not rolling 5 star weapons, you're essentially just lighting your money on fire. In other titles, suboptimal equipment can sometimes serve a purpose, but in this game they're just slightly better leveling mats, even for the F2P community. 2. Gems - I literally cannot spend money on anything other than gems, and for reasons listed above, spending money on gems just legitimately feels awful. When I do spend money on them, it's only ever during sales, and it legitimately comes from a place of 'I want to support the game, and the community, I accept my god awful Cyan 15CP katana as punishments'. I know that additional systems (skins, additional content, other cosmetics, et cetera) take time to add, and I'm not suggesting they just magically appear overnight, but I would personally love to see that sort of optional stuff appear at some point so that folks in my position who can spend money have more fruitful avenues to spend money. Again, I'd like to state that the game feels awesome most of the time, from content itself to pacing, and as much as I megalothe the monetization approach, the game does a great job of taking care of players with an amazing amount of free gems/tickets, so it's not as if the monetization hamstrings the community. I'd just personally love to see better incentives /to/ invest money and help support the community while also maybe getting an Advent Children Cloud skin. Thanks for reading, and keep up the awesome work, SE folks. (this post may have been motivated by not pulling Lightning's 35 CP &gt;:() </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#TastedCorn">
<p>Actually... What about pay only rolls which allow guaranteed top prize once per banner. Can probably cost the same as 5k gems but guarantees the top prize on the first time. </p>
<p>I guess it could be a little over powered since then EX weapons will not be so rare as a result though. Maybe 2nd best prize guaranteed? </p>
</sp>
</text>
