<text id="autogum_voyage_doc372" title="Blue Lake Provincial Park" shortTile="blue-lake-provincial" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=162770" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Blue Lake Provincial Park</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.ontarioparks.com/park/bluelake">Blue Lake Provincial Park</ref></hi> is a 2314-ha recreational park in <ref target="Northern%20Ontario">Northern Ontario</ref>, <ref target="Canada">Canada</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>The park is open mid-May to Mid-September.</p>

<p>Barrier-free access is available at both comfort stations. There is also a wheelchair ramp at the day-use area. </p>

<p>Each of the park’s campgrounds has a comfort station with showers and flush toilets.</p>

<p>The 1-km beach at Blue Lake is a popular day-use area. This sandy beach has buoyed swimming areas and shady areas with picnic tables, water taps and hibachis.</p>

<p>Flush toilets are found in various locations throughout the campground and day-use area.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>Take Highway 17 (the <ref target="Trans-Canada%20Highway">Trans-Canada Highway</ref>) to Vermilion Bay (west of <ref target="Dryden">Dryden</ref>), then turn north onto Highway 647 (Blue Lake Rd) and travel 10 km.</p>

<head>Fees and permits</head>
<p>Daily vehicle permit:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Regular $11-20</item>
<item> Ontario Senior $9.00-16</item>
<item> Ontarian with Disabilities $5.50-10</item>
</list>


<head>See</head>
<p>The Visitor Centre, in an old log cabin at the south end of the beach, has displays of plant, rock and wildlife specimens. The cabin is one of the original cottages from the early days of Blue Lake campers.</p>

<head>Hiking</head>
<p>There are hiking trails ranging from easy, interpretive trails to longer day hikes.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Boulder Ridge Trail</hi> – 1 km, easy, 30 minutes. Walk through a forest created by fire, onto a ridge made by ice and over sands carried by rivers now dry.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Goblin Lake Trail</hi> – 11 km, moderate, full day. It follows the edge of Goblin Lake and explores the wilds of Northern Ontario the way pioneers would have.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Rock Point Trail</hi> – 4 km, moderate. This trail takes you through a variety of environments from cedar groves to Jack Pine ridges. Varying terrain: be sure to wear appropriate foot wear. It starts at the beaver pond and loops back to the campground near M road.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Spruce Fen Boardwalk Trail</hi> - 1 km, easy, barrier-free, 30 minutes</item>
</list>

<p>In a fen, land floats on water, plants eat animals and creatures of the water fly. The Spruce Fen Trail takes you through a Black Spruce fen and a beaver pond environment. Interpretive signs help describe these environments along the trail. To protect the fen, the trail is a boardwalk and is also wheelchair accessible.</p>

<head>Canoeing</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Route 12 Blue Lake</hi> – 97 km loop, partially in the park, moderate, 5-7 days. This route features varied scenery, wildlife and sandy beaches. In the past, portages were used as trading routes to the Hudson Bay Post on Eagle Lake. There is also an abandoned Mica mine site on Cobble Lake. Detailed maps and more canoe route information is available at the Blue Lake Park Office.</item>
</list>


<p>Canoes and kayaks are available for rent. Personal Floatation Devices (life jackets) are also available on loan with a $25 refundable deposit.</p>

<head>Birding</head>
<p>The boreal forest is home to a variety of bird species. Often the Common Loon fills the evening sky with its mournful song as Chimney Swifts fly high above, snagging insects out of the air. Bald Eagles are common place as well as many forest dwelling song birds. Bird checklists are available at the Visitor Centre.</p>

<head>Boating</head>
<p>Power boats are allowed on all lakes within the park. Be aware of non-motorized canoes, kayaks and sailboats. There is a boat launch at the north end of the beach and a dock is available.</p>

<head>Buy</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> There is a <hi rend="bold">Park Store</hi> in the main entry station that sells basic camper needs and Ontario Parks’ merchandise. The store features clothing items, souvenirs, books and ice cream.</item>
<item> Thrre are coin-operated washers and dryers in both of Blue Lakes’ comfort stations.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat and drink</head>
<p>Ice and groceries are available outside of the park in Vermilion Bay, nine km south of the park on Highway 17.</p>

<head>Lodging</head>
<p>There is a travel trailer available with dinette, couch slide, screened-in add-a-room, cook stove, fridge, air conditioner, heater, shower and two sinks with potable water. There is no toilet, but a vault toilet is available nearby. Reserve <ref target="https://reservations.ontarioparks.com/Mobile/">online</ref>.</p>

<head>Camping</head>
<p>There is a range of car camping opportunities from private tent pads to pull through sites with parking areas. Half of the campsites offer electrical hook-up. Amenities such as water taps, comfort stations and laundry facilities are close by. Swimming, boating and the Visitor Centre are only a short distance away.</p>

<p>Two campsites are reserved for campers who require barrier-free access.</p>

<p>2018 rates per night per camping site: $41-51 for electrical sites ($33-41 for Ontario seniors, $21-26 for Ontarians with disabilities; $36-45 for non-electrical sites ($29-36 for Ontario seniors, $18-23 for Ontarians with disabilities).</p>
</text>
