<text id="autogum_interview_doc403" title="part1_Bat for Lashes plays the Bowery Ballroom: an Interview with Natasha Khan" shortTile="partbat-lashes-plays" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-27" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bat_for_Lashes_plays_the_Bowery_Ballroom%3A_an_Interview_with_Natasha_Khan" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you notice a difference between playing in front of British and American audiences?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NK:</hi>  The U.S. audiences are much more full of expression and noises and jubilation.  They are like, "Welcome to New York, <hi rend="italic">Baby</hi>!" "You're <hi rend="italic">Awesome</hi>!" and stuff like that.  Whereas in England they tend to be a lot more reserved.  Well, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English%20people">English</ref> are, but it is such a diverse culture you will get the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spanish%20people">Spanish</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Italian%20people">Italian</ref> gay guys at the front who are going crazy.  I definitely think in America they are much more open and there is more excitement, which is really cool.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How many instruments do you play and, please, include the glockenspiel in that number.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NK:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>] I think the number is limitless, hopefully.  I try my hand at anything I can contribute; I only just picked up the bass, really—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  --I have a great photo of you playing the bass.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NK:</hi>  I don't think I'm very good...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You look cool with it!</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NK:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  Fine.  The glockenspiel...piano, mainly, and also the harp.  Guitar, I like playing percussion and drumming.  I usually speak with all my drummers so that I write my songs with them in mind, and we'll have bass sounds, choir sounds, and then you can multi-task with all these orchestral sounds.  Through the magic medium of technology I can play all kinds of sounds, double bass and stuff.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you design your own clothes?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NK:</hi>  All four of us girls love vintage shopping and charity shops.  We don't have a stylist who tells us what to wear, it's all very much our own natural styles coming through.  And for me, personally, I like to wear jewelery.  On the night of the New York show that top I was wearing was made especially for me as a gift by these New York designers called <hi rend="italic">Pepper + Pistol</hi>.  And there's also my boyfriend, who is an amazing musician—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  —that's Will Lemon from Moon and Moon, right?  There is such good buzz about them here in New York.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NK:</hi>  Yes!  They have an album coming out in February and it will fucking <hi rend="italic">blow</hi> your mind!  I think you would love it, it's an incredible masterpiece.  It's really exciting, I'm hoping we can do a crazy double unfolding caravan show, the Bat for Lashes album and the new Moon and Moon album: that would be really theatrical and amazing!  Will prints a lot of my T-shirts because he does amazing tapestries and silkscreen printing on clothes.  When we play there's a velvety kind of tapestry on the keyboard table that he made.  So I wear a lot of his things, thrift store stuff, old bits of jewelry and antique pieces.</p>
</text>
