<text id="autogum_interview_doc825" title="part10_Satanism: An interview with Church of Satan High Priest Peter Gilmore" shortTile="partsatanism-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-04" dateModified="2018-10-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Satanism%3A_An_interview_with_Church_of_Satan_High_Priest_Peter_Gilmore" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That is what you consider the greatest threat to humanity?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  Yes, any fundamentalist fanaticism is a vast threat.  I’m looking for humanity to have a secular, pluralistic culture.  People should be able to follow whatever fantasies or religions they want, as long as they don't impose them on other people and force other people into doing things based upon whatever kind of holy writ they have.  So the biggest threat to that are these fundamentalists who want to force people into their belief systems.  They want to destroy people who have sexual activity they don't think is appropriate according to their texts.  It will be interesting to see in the future if people will wake up to this threat and decide to somehow corral that kind of behavior, defang people like that who are basically on a jihad, whether they be Christians or Muslims or any other religion, because we’ve seen in the past the Catholics were torturing people to death in the Inquisition, then the Reformation happened and different denominations and sects were killing each other.  Heretics were being slaughtered.  So this is not something just one religion is guilty of.</p>
<head id="On_New_York_City">On New York City</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How do you feel about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hell's%20Kitchen,%20Manhattan">Hell's Kitchen</ref>, where you live, being called Clinton?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  I despise that.  It should stick to what it really is, and it’s Hell’s Kitchen.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When you see how New York is changing around you—I’ve lived here for close to seven years, and even when I moved here it was very different.  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  I like the sleaze, I like the history, I like to see New York being this amazing range of the highest and the lowest and I don't think New York should be cleaned up and Disneyfied.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But it is.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  It’s getting there.  I did a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black%20Mass">Black Mass</ref> for the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/British_Broadcasting_Corporation">BBC</ref> in the old Hellfire Club, and that’s gone and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apple%20Store">Apple</ref> is putting up a store in that neighborhood. [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  Everybody just feels safe walking around all the time now.  There’s still some parts of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chinatown,%20Manhattan">Chinatown</ref> that are still pretty rough.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Where do you think the culture is going to go?  Is the sanitized version here to stay?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  No, because if you look at anything that at one point is sleazy, at one it was new and spiffy and wonderful.  So, at this point, New York is Manhattanland, it's for tourists and we’ve made this almost Las Vegas simulacrum of the whole thing.  But it will change.  As soon as the money isn't worth pumping into it to keep up the façade, all of the roughness around the edges will creep back in.  It’s still here, it just hides in the daytime.  There’s still all kinds of weird crime going on in the city when you watch the news.</p>
</text>
