<text id="autogum_interview_doc731" title="part3_Wikinews interviews Brian Moore, Socialist Party USA presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-30" dateModified="2016-07-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Brian_Moore%2C_Socialist_Party_USA_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Why do you believe socialism or even democratic socialism has never really "taken off" in America?</hi></item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">Moore:</hi> Socialism had taken off in America.  It is just that the <ref target='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/"Red%20Scare"'>"Red Scare"</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Espionage%20Act">Espionage Act</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sedition%20Act">Sedition Act</ref> between 1917 and 1924 by the U.S. government, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stalinism">Stalinism</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/McCarthyism">McCarthyism</ref> from 1945 to 1955; and the Cold War in the second half of the 20th century all undermined a wonderful and rich heritage of our country that thrived from 1900 thru 1925 and beyond. There were 1200 officeholders in America who were registered and public candidates as Socialists in America around 1920. Close to one million Americans voted for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eugene%20Debs">Eugene Debs</ref> in 1912 and 1920, gaining 9% and 11% of the popular vote. Remember, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Teddy%20Roosevelt">Teddy Roosevelt</ref> ran in 1912 as a third party candidate and garnered the second highest vote totals (20%) and still Gene Debs also gained around 11%. Can you imagine if Teddy Roosevelt had not been a candidate in that election! Secondly, the Socialists were against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World%20World%20I">World World I</ref>, plus there was a split in the party with over half going to Communism, thus both suffering the consequences of Woodrow Wilson's Sedition Act and Red Scare tactics accusing them of being traitors.</p>
<p>Membership in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socialist%20Party%20of%20America">Socialist Party of America</ref> grew from 13,000 to 118,000 by 1912, and circulation of its journal, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Appeal%20to%20Reason">Appeal to Reason</ref></hi>, reached a circulation of over 760,000.</p>
<p>Keep in mind supporters of Socialism then and into the 1930's and 1940's, in addition to Eugene V. Debs were <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Upton%20Sinclair">Upton Sinclair</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Helen%20Keller">Helen Keller</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albert%20Einstein">Einstein</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sinclair%20Lewis">Sinclair Lewis</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A.%20Philip%20Randolph">A. Philip Randolph</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter%20Reuther">Walter Reuther</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Margaret%20Sanger">Margaret Sanger</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack%20London">Jack London</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William%20DuBois">William DuBois</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kate%20Richards%20O'Hare">Kate Richards O'Hare</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frank%20Zeidler">Frank Zeidler</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rose%20Pastor%20Stokes">Rose Pastor Stokes</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Victor%20Berger">Victor Berger</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bayard%20Rustin">Bayard Rustin</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael%20Harrington">Michael Harrington</ref>.</p>
<p>The growth of the left worried President <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Woodrow%20Wilson">Woodrow Wilson</ref> and his administration so much that America entered what became known as the "Red Scare" period.  In 1919, U.S. Attorney General <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander%20Mitchell%20Palmer">Alexander Mitchell Palmer</ref>, at the order of President Wilson, arrested over 10,000 suspected communists and anarchists. These people were  charged with "advocating force, violence and unlawful means to overthrow the Government." <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/J.%20Edgar%20Hoover">J. Edgar Hoover</ref> was part of the effort at that time.  Large number of these "suspects" were held without trial for a long time, and some were expelled to Russia. The Socialist party took a terrible hit and its membership suffered a severe drop due to the governmental intimidation and false claims against it.</p>
<p>One of my jobs is to re-educate America about this rich and radical heritage, and how its vision is positive and beneficial to the country. My other function will be to point out how capitalism is failing America and that it is acceptable to think in terms of radical change and alternative economic systems that will preserve and insure our country's  survival and bring more fairness and justice to more Americans and to the world.</p>
</text>
