<text id="autogum_news_doc331" title="Signalling issues and stalled train disrupt service on Singapore&apos;s Mass Rapid Transit lines" shortTile="signalling-issues" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-11-02" dateModified="2016-11-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Signalling_issues_and_stalled_train_disrupt_service_on_Singapore%27s_Mass_Rapid_Transit_lines" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Signalling issues and stalled train disrupt service on Singapore's Mass Rapid Transit lines</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 3, 2016</hi></p>
<p>Train services on two of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Singapore">Singapore's</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mass%20Rapid%20Transit%20(Singapore)">Mass Rapid Transit</ref> system lines, both operated by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SMRT%20Corporation">SMRT Corporation</ref>, were disrupted at separate times yesterday in two incidents.  </p>
<p>During the morning rush hour, six stations of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Circle%20MRT%20Line">Circle MRT Line</ref> (CCL) were without train service in both directions during the morning rush hour following what SMRT described as "intermittent signal interference". The company first announced the signalling fault on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Twitter">Twitter</ref> at 7:37 am, advising commuters to anticipate 10 additional minutes of travel time in the commute between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pasir%20Panjang%20MRT%20Station">Pasir Panjang</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/one-north%20MRT%20Station">one-north</ref> stations. The fault was announced rectified two minutes later by another tweet from SMRT, though delays were still expected in the direction of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dhoby%20Ghaut%20MRT%20Station">Dhoby Ghaut</ref> station due to congestion at stations and on trains.</p>
<figure><caption>File photo of HarbourFront station, 2006.  Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Sengkang">Sengkang</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>SMRT issued another tweet at 8:09 am, alerting commuters to another signalling fault affecting the CCL, on the stretch between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Botanic%20Gardens%20MRT%20Station">Botanic Gardens</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HarbourFront%20MRT%20Station">HarbourFront</ref> stations.</p>
<p>Initially informing commuters that the issue would add 10 minutes of travel time along the affected stretch, the company later revised this to 20, and finally, 30 minutes in subsequent tweets, attributing the delays to "intermittent signalling faults".</p>
<p>The company later announced via Twitter service unavailable between Botanic Gardens and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marymount%20MRT%20station">Marymount</ref> stations at 9:06 am, whilst offering free bus services along the length of the CCL. SMRT later amended the announcement in another tweet to encompass the stretch between Botanic Gardens and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serangoon%20MRT%20Station">Serangoon</ref> stations. Train service was restored along the affected stretch by about 10:27 am.</p>
<p>SMRT had previously experienced disruptions in service on the CCL for five consecutive days in September, also attributable to signalling issues, leading to authorities briefly switching off mobile signals at four CCL stations for two hours on September 2 during investigations. Most of the disruptions took place during peak hours, leading to suspicion the telecommunications network could be interfering with the train signalling system. After tests proved inconclusive following the lack of a disruption that day, the decision was made to turn off telecommunications signals in the event of another disruption.</p>
<p>“It's very frustrating", commented a commuter, 41-year-old Joseph Lim.  "The trains are sometimes moving and sometimes getting stuck. I don't know whether to stay on board. The communication has been insufficient".</p>
<p>Another commuter, 29-year-old Alice Pan, stated, "I am now stuck at the station with no way to get to work. I can't get on any <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SBS%20Transit">SBS</ref> buses because they are full and there's no free shuttle bus in sight. I can't get any cabs either". Pan was stranded in a train for an hour at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lorong%20Chuan">Lorong Chuan</ref> station.</p>
<p>36-year-old Sean Chew, said of his experience during the incident, "I was stuck at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buona%20Vista%20MRT%20Station">Buona Vista</ref> for more than one hour. I didn't want to take the bus because it was very crowded. So no choice, had to wait [...] Luckily I just finished work."</p>
<p>However, following the morning incidents, a stalled train on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/East%20West%20MRT%20Line">East West MRT Line</ref> led to a half-hour disruption during the evening peak hour on the same day. SMRT informed commuters of the disruption, between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queenstown%20MRT%20Station">Queenstown</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Outram%20Park%20MRT%20Station">Outram Park</ref> stations in the direction of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pasir%20Ris%20MRT%20Station">Pasir Ris</ref> station, on Twitter at 5:48 pm, attributing it to a "train fault" at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tiong%20Bahru%20MRT%20Station">Tiong Bahru</ref> station. In the same tweet, SMRT estimated that the issue would be resolved around 6:10 pm. Due to the disruption, the company offered free bus services along the affected stretch in a subsequent tweet.</p>
<p>At 6:20 pm, SMRT announced on Twitter that it had cleared the disruption by removing the stalled train, and that trains were "progressively return[ing] to normal speed". The company continued to offer free bus services until 7 pm, when it announced the termination of the service on Twitter. </p>
<p>In the wake of yesterday's incidents, commuters criticized SMRT's handling of the matter on social media, citing SMRT's failure to provide sufficient information or sufficient buses for commuters, and uploading photos of the congestion.</p>
</text>
