<text id="autogum_academic_doc294" title="An Energy Efficient and Formally Secured Certificate-Based Signcryption for Wireless Body Area Networks with the Internet of Things" shortTile="energy-efficient" author="Insaf Ullah, Abdullah Alomari, Noor Ul Amin, Muhammad  Asghar Khan, Hizbullah Khattak" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2079-9292/8/10/1171/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
In the current era, the Internet of things (IoT) is one of the most debatable topics among the research community of information technology. The IoT includes all those devices, which have the capacity of computing, communication, and connection with the Internet. The IoT has so many applications in our daily lives, i.e., it is used in smart cities, smart homes, and e-health, etc.. By providing faster access to the treatment of patients, the wireless body area networks (WBAN) integrate with the Internet of things (IoT) and play an important role in the patient health care system, because this ecosystem, enables all the users and devices to access the patient’s psychological data from anywhere and anytime in the world by utilizing the Internet. However, due to the open nature of the Internet, authenticity and data security are the two major concerns in the IoT based WBAN.  </p>

<p>The authenticity of IoT is ensured through digital signature, and data security is met by using the encryption method, although the IoT has a resource hungry nature and cannot afford these two different algorithms separately, i.e., signature and then encryption at the same time. In 1997, Zheng was the pioneer to merge these two processes in one algorithm, called signcryption. This scheme is based on the concept of old public key cryptography (PKC), which is suffering from certificate overheads, renewing, and revocation problems. Shamir was the first to propose an alternate concept of PKC, called identity-based cryptography (IBC). This technique removed the limitations of PKC and used the identity in place of a certificate. Later, in 2002, Malone-Lee, for the first time merged the concept of IBC with the signcryption technique, namely, identity-based signcryption (IBS). The IBS includes three entities, for example, a sender (signcrypter), a receiver (unsigncrypter), and the private key generation center (PKGC), respectively. In this setup, the users (signcrypter and unsigncrypter) generate their identities and after that, send it to the PKGC. Then, the PKGC produces and delivers the private keys for all the participating users, by using the secured networks. Unfortunately, IBS suffers from the key escrow issue (KEI), because the private key is generated by the PKGC and one can easily use this key for forging the digital signature and decrypting the ciphertext.  </p>

<p>To eliminate the above problem in IBS, in 2008, Barbosa and Farshim, put forward the concept of a certificateless signcryption (CL-SC) scheme. The CL-SC mechanism almost works the same as IBS, but the main difference is that the private key is generated by the users themselves. The central authority known as a key generation center (KGC) only provides the partial private key to the users by using an open link. Although it removes the issue of key escrow in IBS and certificate management in PKC-based signcryption, it still suffers from the needs of the partial private key distribution problem. Another strategy, named heterogeneous signcryption was proposed by Sun. This strategy contains two sub-methods, the first one works under the condition in which the sender belongs to the conventional PKC and the receiver belongs to the IBC, while in the second one, a sender uses the concept of IBC and receiver based on the PKC. Since, these two types (PKC and IBC) of the public key are suffering from some crucial problem, i.e., certificate overheads, renewing, certificate revocation, and KEI, respectively, these types of problems are not suitable for the IoT environment. To cater to this particular issue, heterogeneous signcryption was coined by Li et al., in which the signcryption part belongs to the certificateless cryptosystem (CLC) and the unsigncryption side is based on the functionality of PKC, however, the scheme is affected by the secrete key distributions and certificate management issues. To remove the certificate management at the receiver side, Omala et al., contributed a new heterogeneous signcryption scheme, in which the signcryption part belongs to the CLC and the unsigncryption part works under the notion of IBC. This method is also affected by the key escrow and the secret key distribution problem. A new type of cryptosystem was introduced by Gentry in 2003, namely, certificate-based cryptography (CBC), in which one can use the functionality of old PKC in a better manner. The CBC enables each participant in the network to generate his public and private keys and give their public key to the certifier’s authority (CsA). Later, by using the concept of IBC encryption, based on the participants’ public key which serves its identity, CsA generates a certificate for each participant while using an open link. Noteably, this certificate acts as a partial private key and also uses a decryption key on the receiver side. In 2008, Li et al., provided a new scheme, which is used to merge the concept of CBC with signcryption, called certificate-based signcryption. In 2019, Braeken proposed pairing free certificate-based signcryption schemes using ECQV implicit certificates. However, the proposed approach is based on a hyper-elliptic curve, i.e., it suffers from high computational cost. Moreover, the proposed scheme is not validated through any formal security tool. </p>
</text>
