<text id="autogum_academic_doc371" title="Utility of Digital Technologies for the Sustainability of Intangible Cultural Heritage (ICH) in Korea †" shortTile="utility-digital-technologies" author="Seulah Kim, Dong-uk Im, Jongoh Lee, Heejae Choi" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/6117/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Discussion</head>
<p>Systematic evaluation is necessary to improve the quality of VR programme as this kind of programme has not yet been realised widely. Feedback from the holders and successors as well as engineers are mandatory. Holders and successors are at the very core of this whole transmission system, which authorises them to evaluate whether the programme is effective in educating and training the general public, contributing towards making the ICH more authentic and sustainable. The engineers and technicians are to try the programme themselves so that they can see whether the technologies are rightly used to enhance the presence and immersion within the programme. They are the ones who understand what needs to be improved and how it can be improved. Feedback from the general public who have tried out the programme is also essential. Questionnaires can be useful to get the opinions on how the people felt and thought about the programme on the basis of the grades and descriptive answers they give to each question. The questionnaire is intended to evaluate the programme regarding (1) educational effects, (2) technical effects, and (3) inducing effects. The tentative list of questions with regard to the Jultagi programme follows: </p>

<p>
<list>
<item>(1) Questions on “educational effects” are to see whether the programme is effective in teaching the general public by giving relevant information about Jultagi and ICH in general.

<p>(1-1) Do you think the programme rightly included explanations on what Jultagi and ICH in general are?</p>

<p>(1-2) Do you think now you know more about Jultagi and about ICH in general after trying the programme?</p>

<p>(1-3) Did the programme explain the importance of preserving ICH in detail?</p>

<p>(1-4) Do you agree with the importance of preserving ICH as explained in the programme?</p>

<p>(1-5) Would you recommend your friend to try this programme in order to learn about Jultagi and ICH in general?</p></item>

<item>(2) Questions on “technical effects” are to see whether technologies are properly applied on the programme and are helpful to enhance its educational effect.

<p>(2-1) Was VR technology helpful in understanding what Jultagi and ICH in general are?</p>

<p>(2-2) Did the technologies encourage you to get interested and involved in Jultagi and ICH in general?</p>

<p>(2-3) Do you think the VR programme on Jultagi is helpful if you actually try Jultagi in reality?</p>

<p>(2-4) Do you think the technologies were properly used to make the virtual environment feel like reality?</p>

<p>(2-5) What are the strengths and weaknesses of the VR programme on Jultagi when compared to the actual Jultagi training led by living human treasure in reality?</p></item>

<item>(3) Questions on “inducing effects” are to see whether this pre-level participatory programme encourages actual education of transmission run by living human treasure in reality.

<p>(3-1) Do you think this programme give people a taste of what Jultagi and ICH is?</p>

<p>(3-2) Do you think this programme would encourage people to get more interested in Jultagi and ICH in general?</p>

<p>(3-3) Are you more interested in exploring ICH yourself now compared to before?</p>

<p>(3-4) Do you have plans to participate in experiential programme run by the living human treasure?</p>

<p>(3-5) Do you have plans to get actual transmission training to be a successor?</p></item>
</list>
</p>
</text>
