<text id="autogum_interview_doc787" title="part2_Eurovision &amp;apos;73 winner Anne Marie David discusses her four-decade career and the Contest, past and present" shortTile="parteurovision--winner" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-02-15" dateModified="2012-02-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eurovision_%2773_winner_Anne_Marie_David_discusses_her_four-decade_career_and_the_Contest%2C_past_and_present" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="Eurovision_'73_and_initial_mainstream_success">Eurovision '73 and initial mainstream success</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> When you competed for Luxembourg, one country winning twice in a row was still rare. Was there a lot of pressure for you to win the grand prize for Luxembourg? Did you also feel pressure to succeed from yourself?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AMD</hi>: There was no need to win the grand <hi rend="italic">prize</hi> except in <hi rend="italic">my head</hi>. I felt sure that an opportunity like that one was <hi rend="italic">unique</hi> and that I would not have it a second time... I was incorrect... I got it twice! What I mean to say is that Eurovision remains for me a musical contest before all else, although of course a good song is worth nothing without a good [singer]. Thus the need to have both!</p>
<p>I've always had a taste for challenges... Eurovision is one. And among the challenges I like the competition, so when challenge and competition are combined, I think only of victory. I think it would be ridiculous and useless to go to Eurovision without wanting to win! I never participate in a contest, or anywhere for that matter, when it consists of singing with a tourist view of it. I prioritize my work and the result of my work. This has not allowed me to visit many things in all the countries where I have been in competition, but this allowed me to never find myself poorly ranked or last. One must know whether one wants victory or tourism...and I think it's a lack of respect to all those who count on us, and all those who spend a lot [of time] (production, television, etc...) to not take every chance to rank better or not put every chance of winning on our side.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You ended up in a three-way dead heat between Mocedades from Spain and Cliff Richard from the United Kingdom, who both performed songs some fans also consider worthy of the grand prize. What were your opinions of those songs? If, hypothetically, your song didn't win, do you think either of them were strong enough to be winner material?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AMD</hi>: 1973 was a year very rich in quality candidates... the proof: victory came to me with just a very few points ahead. The ranking of that year's other candidates was what I dreaded most. Mocedades was a pure moment of happiness and of a formidable effectiveness; Cliff Richard benefited from an exceptional notoriety and a mastery of the scene that I was far from having; so I needed to play everything I had... but I told you that I'd chosen <hi rend="italic">victory</hi>, not tourism!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> During the mid-1970s, you did many tours of Turkey and the Middle East, and won reporters' music awards there. What was the best thing you liked about being in Turkey? What experiences did you have that really stand out in your mind even today?</hi></p>
</text>
