<text id="autogum_interview_doc649" title="part7_Popular soap opera &amp;apos;The Young and the Restless&amp;apos; celebrates 35 years on the air" shortTile="partpopular-soap" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-25" dateModified="2014-04-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Popular_soap_opera_%27The_Young_and_the_Restless%27_celebrates_35_years_on_the_air" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="Questions_asked_to_Tricia_Cast">Questions asked to Tricia Cast</head>
<figure><caption>Tricia Cast on her character's reputation as the "beleaguered heroine": "I think that's fair. No one wants every character to be 'together'."</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi>: In terms of writing and depth of character, where do you think Nina was at her strongest throughout her time in Genoa City? And what was her weakest point?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tricia Cast</hi>: Her strongest point was just before she moved away. She had evolved into a talented and independent woman. Weakest? Perhaps when she temporarily lost control of her faculties. [editor's note: reference to Nina's suicide attempt in 1997.]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi>: Nina's best friend on the show was Christine, and in many respects, Christine's personality served as a contrast to Nina's. Why do you think those two kept a strong friendship as long as they did?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tricia Cast</hi>: Who else but the kind, responsible Cricket was going to haul Nina out of the messes she got herself into?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi>: Over the last couple of years, history was rewritten so that Philip, Nina's first husband, wasn't really Jill's son at all. What does that say to you as far as Nina ever coming back to the show? Do you find it disheartening that the show's history was rewritten to that degree?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tricia Cast</hi>: What? What did you say? Who told you that? Jill? <hi rend="italic">Why that...</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi>: You won one Emmy Award, for the bulk of your storyline involving David Kimble. What were some pros and cons in acting that emotional story?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tricia Cast</hi>: Con: All that crying. Pro: I got to shoot him.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi>: Many fans would deem the character of Nina as the "beleaguered heroine." Do you think that assessment is on the mark, or were there other facets to her character that you feel were integral to your portrayal of her that deserve note?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tricia Cast</hi>: I think that's fair. No one wants every character to be "together."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi>: For a time while you were on the show, you (and Nina) gained some weight. In the storyline, Ryan had left Nina for Tricia [Dennison, played by Sabryn Genet], and she became convinced she was unattractive and unloved. Was that a difficult storyline to act out? Also, what kind of fan reaction did you receive while playing that sort of storyline, as it related to female viewers and their own self-image concerns?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tricia Cast</hi>: It was tough because it was so close to home. I struggled with my weight off camera and that wasn't fun. I got both supportive reaction and a measure of cruelty come my way over it. Some people love you no matter what and some people just don't like their TV personalities to be less than perfect.</p>
</text>
