<text id="autogum_whow_doc272" title="How to cook Karen &quot;Ta Ka Phaw&quot; dish" shortTile="cook-karen-ta-ka" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-09-22" dateModified="2019-10-17" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/How-to-cook-Karen-%22Ta-Ka-Phaw%22-dish" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>How to cook Karen "Ta Ka Phaw" dish</head><p>This hot and spicy Karen traditional "Ta Ka Phaw" will give you the feeling of warm in during the cold season. People might not often see this Karen dish in shops because it is special and if you cannot cook well the dish will not turn out well. By following the following steps carefully, tough, you will be able to accomplish it.</p>
<head>Ingredients</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Five raw bamboo shoots</item>
<item>Fresh basil leaves</item>
<item>Drumstick leaves</item>
<item>1 kg fish or chicken</item>
<item>2 djenkol beans</item>
<item>2 tbsp of fish pate</item>
<item>Black pepper</item>
<item>Five to ten green chili peppers</item>
<item>Salt</item>
<item>Soaked pounded rice powder</item></list>
<p><hi rend="italic">Serves two people</hi></p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Slice five bamboo shoots into small pieces.</item>
<item>Mix with some salt and boil it for 30 minutes. Pour its liquid to another pot.
<list type="unordered"><item>Your bamboo shoot must be raw to be able to test good. Your raw slide bamboo shoot needs some salt to add when boiling it because salt will make it tastier.</item>
<item>However, you must be careful with adding salt because you will have to add one more time during you cook.</item></list></item>
<item>Cut the fish or chicken into small pieces and put it in the liquid.
<list type="unordered"><item>If needed put more some water until it boils. You should not put the whole body of the fish or all of the chicken without adding something.</item>
<item>To be able you dish smell good, both fish and chicken have to be roast before boiling with bamboo shoot liquid.</item></list></item>
<item>Put some two table spoon of fish pate, some slat again and slide djenkol bean into the boiling water and keep boiling it until 15 minutes.
<list type="unordered"><item>In this step you are going to add salt again. So, if you add a lot of salt for the first time your dish will be salty. Too much fish pate will cover the smell of the fish or chicken roast. So, I recommend not to put more than two table spoon of fish pate. Djenkol bean must test good, after you cook, but if you are allergic with djenkil bean, you will not include it in your ingredient. Especially, for the pregnant women.</item></list></item>
<item>Put basil leaves first, follow by drumstick leaves, and powder black pepper keep boiling it more for 3 minutes and wait until it boils again.
<list type="unordered"><item>That 3 minutes will mix the leaves with ingredient. To put chili pepper into the pot is your choice. If you like spicy, you can include chilly, but if not up to you. My recommendation is when you are cooking this dish in cold season make this spicy otherwise the test will not be delicious. Hot and spicy will help you to get warm.</item></list></item>
<item>Add pounded rice that you had sink into water when it boils again after 3 minutes for the lest step.
<list type="unordered"><item>There are two ways we can make the rice powder. The first way we can get it by sink rice we need and pound it.</item>
<item>The second way is we toasted the rice. These two ways have different result. The sink rice when we pound it, it sticks inside mortar and take more time. It does not give us good smell when we cook it. Toasted rice are better but it takes little bit of time when we toasted it. However, it going well when we pound and give us good smell when we cook. If you like good smell and delicious dish, use toasted rice.</item>
<item>Keep boiling it and it up to you. If you want to eat with some liquid or not. After this step you are ready to have Karen "Ta Ka Phaw" dish.</item></list></item>
<item>Hope you find way easy to cook Karen "Ta Ka Phaw" dish by using these steps and enjoy your "Ta ka Phaw."</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>This Karen dish is easy to make and cheap. It includes meat and vegetables which good for your health and diet plan.</item>
<item>Toasted rice is the best choose to use for this dish. It gives us better smell and delicious test.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be careful when you add salt because you have to add it twice. The first time you have to add with slide bamboo shoot and second time you have to add with fish pate and djenkol bean again. If you add a lot, you will end up with salty dish.</item>
<item>Djenkol bean is not good for pregnant women to eat because it can course problem to embryo. So, if someone in your family is pregnant, you are not going to add djenkol bean into this dish.</item></list>
</text>
