<text id="autogum_academic_doc277" title="Analysis of Energy Consumption and Optimization Techniques for Writing Energy-Efficient Code" shortTile="analysis-energy-consumption" author="Javier Corral-García, Felipe Lemus-Prieto, José-Luis González-Sánchez, Miguel-Ángel Pérez-Toledano" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2079-9292/8/10/1192/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Related Work</head>
<p>
In we provided a detailed review of the existing literature, specially focused on improving source code optimization to achieve better execution times. The lack of proposals dedicated to writing efficient code for IoT devices was especially noteworthy. Diverse approaches to optimize C and C++ code for other operating systems and architectures were found instead. Descriptions of all of them can be consulted in the aforementioned previous work. </p>

<p>Nevertheless, it is important to highlight that IoT may benefit from the existing literature on the usage of low-power arm processors for high-performance computing (HPC) where energy efficiency has become a key challenge to address Exascale needs, highlighting the importance of the relationship between performance and energy consumption in the development of HPC systems. A survey which includes a list of articles mainly focused on the use of Arm processors to reduce the energy consumption of HPC infrastructure can be found in. For instance, the role played by hardware factors and by some software aspects in the energy-performance landscape of real-life HPC applications is analyzed in detail in, and a combination of both architecture and software improvements to optimize performance and energy consumption on arm-based platforms by using dynamic voltage and frequency scaling (DVFS) techniques, multithreading and vectorization is proposed in. </p>

<p>With regard to Raspberry Pi energy consumption, its efficiency has been evaluated in several works with the objective of providing software developers and users with indicators for understanding how much energy the device is consuming while running a software application [35,36]. For instance, a research about how Raspberry Pi power drain is affected by the key functionalities that could be performed by end-users on the platform can be found in. This is compared against other types of common personal computers, and techniques and practices that could reduce energy consumption are recommended. In, the energy efficiency issue of an SBC-based cluster is addressed in the context of big data applications. They correlate energy utilization for the execution time of several benchmarks using workloads of different sizes. </p>

<p>Next, other proposals related to the scope of our research are described: an approach for power and energy usage for scientific calculation with and without General-Purpose Unit (GPU) acceleration on RPi devices can be found in; energy and execution time of several wearable and mobile devices, including RPi Zero, are compared in with a benchmark to discuss offloading techniques to use for increasing quality of service (QoS) in IoT applications; a preliminary analysis and modeling of energy consumption of evolutionary algorithms in different devices, including RPi, is introduced in [41]; an estimation of energy consumption in transferring data using an IoT protocol over different QoS levels is presented in; a linear IoT model to deploy processes and data to devices and servers in IoT (considering a RPi as a fog node) reducing the total energy consumption of nodes is introduced in [43]; a study about the service distribution in multi-layer IoT architecture to minimize the total energy consumption is presented in; the evolution of the energy consumption of several RPi models is compared to alternative platforms in. </p>

<p>However, the above-mentioned proposals are focused on analyzing and optimizing the energy consumption of IoT and RPi devices, rather than on the energy saving that can be achieved when writing energy-efficient code for RPi boards. Thus, the current manuscript aims to demonstrate the effectiveness of 25 proposed techniques and confirm that, in many cases, the percentage of energy-saving obtained by applying these techniques manually is much higher than those achieved with the automatic optimizations offered by compilers such as GCC. </p>
</text>
