<text id="autogum_academic_doc113" title="The ‘Lunar Side’ of the Story: Exploring the Sustainability of Curricular Internships in Higher Education" shortTile="lunar-side-story" author="Betina Lopes, Patrícia Silva, Ana  I. Melo, Elisabeth Brito, Gonçalo Paiva Dias, Marco Costa" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5879/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Methods</head>
<p>The study reported in this paper was conducted within a broader sequential mixed method study focused on linking data from two separate, but interlinked stages. The first stage (quantitative approach) included the inventory of nearly 200 FCD and sought to understand the impact of internships on graduates′ employment (access to work) while controlling for other institutional and contextual variables. This stage of research informed the second stage, namely regarding the selection of cases, as well as the within-case analysis strategy. It preceded the in-depth study of some cases that digged deeper into the processes of organizing and managing internships, including its associated liabilities and tensions. </p>

<p>In order to ensure the comparability of the data to be collected from each case, it was decided to confine the FCD to interrelated areas. The areas chosen were Marketing and Management and Accounting since these FCD revealed to be the ones where internships are more common. Four HEIs were chosen based on the effort in maintaining some diversity regarding: </p>

<list>
<item>(i) the type of institution, namely university vs. polytechnic. While polytechnic institutions tend to provide a more practical and professionally oriented training—hence, theoretically, more prone to the establishment of internships, the university system tends to be associated with a stronger theoretical basis and tends to be more research oriented. This once sharp distinction seems, however, to have become increasingly blurred over time.</item>
<item>(ii) the geographical localization (costal vs. inland), since Portugal′s inland is characterized by depopulation, stagnation, and delay, being the levels of social and economic maladjustment difficult to reverse, thus contributing to lower levels of development.</item>
<item>(iii) nature (mandatory vs. facultative) of internships, since previous research indicated that compulsory internships significantly impact on graduate employment.</item>
</list>

<p>Overall, this sequential combination of a mixed methods approach derived from the abundant research on the potential variables impacting on graduates′ employment, though the independent impact of internships had been scarcely demonstrated. </p>

<p>This article presents a within-case analysis, reporting the use of internships in seven FCD offered by four Portuguese HEIs. A focus group was conducted in each institution in 2014, in a context when Portugal was embarking on a narrative of austerity, implementing wide-ranging fiscal consolidation measures to reduce public spending. The economic downturn amplified the demand for local public services in the face of high unemployment, a pressure to which HEIs were surely not immune to. </p>

<p>The first case (CASE A) corresponds to a polytechnic school and involved stakeholders from the ‘Marketing Degree’. The second case (CASE B), corresponds to a public university and involved stakeholders from two FCD: ‘Management’ and ‘Accounting’. The third and fourth cases (CASE C and CASE D), correspond to two polytechnic schools. Concerning CASE C, three degrees were considered: ‘Management’, ‘Marketing’, and ‘Tourism’. To note, that the inclusion of the Tourism degree resulted from the suggestion of the participants. Once explained the research main goals, the Head of Department, asked if it would be possible to include supervisors and students from Tourism. He argued it would be an excellent opportunity for collaborative reflection, and institutional innovation. Considering that the researchers’ aim is also to inform institutional practices (‘applied research’) it was decided to include these participants also.) CASE D involved the ‘Management Degree’. Table 1 presents a brief outline of the institutional policy regarding internships in each of the involved institutions. As depicted, the diversity of cases, along with the wide spectrum of internship strategies used by each institution, enables a deep understanding of the organization and functioning of internships in Portuguese HEIs, thus enhancing the accuracy of the findings. The geographical localization of each HEI is also identified. </p>

<p>As stated above, data gathering of the qualitative study included focus-group with different stakeholders in each institution (deans, departmental directors, degree directors, and former students) to access a truly pluralist perspective. It was assumed that the use of mixed groups enhanced the emergence of different and even opposite perspectives while increasing the opportunity of a broader understanding of institutional internship policies. This strategy allowed for circumventing the traditional single interview format, with classical questions that could elicit politically correct answers or rehearsed speeches. Extensive literature review on curricular internships did not reveal any study where stakeholders from the same institution, and therefore sharing the same or similar internship experiences, talked to each other about internships. In fact, the majority of studies tend to be single voiced. Furthermore, the opportunity to give voice to all participants involved converges to institutional sustainability (<figure>Figure 1</figure>), enhancing the aspects of equity and justice. Table 2 resumes the four focus-groups that were conducted, with a total of 21 participants from seven degrees, as aforementioned. </p>

<p>The focus groups were structured in three main moments: </p>
</text>
