<text id="autogum_interview_doc790" title="part5_Eurovision &amp;apos;73 winner Anne Marie David discusses her four-decade career and the Contest, past and present" shortTile="parteurovision--winner" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-02-15" dateModified="2012-02-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eurovision_%2773_winner_Anne_Marie_David_discusses_her_four-decade_career_and_the_Contest%2C_past_and_present" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> In the late 1980s, you retired from music completely. Was this a difficult decision for you to make? What things did you want out of your life which required you to leave music? Where did you go, and what did you do in retirement?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AMD</hi>: Nothing is ever difficult when we accept to assume our choice. Those years were very disco, we were entering terrains I wasn't ready to tread, and I had been spoiled by my artist's life by going ever farther and farther from home. The French media ignored me after my victory for Luxembourg. Everyone wanted a second "Tu te reconnaîtras" and that is impossible. </p>
<p>And so I went where the public awaited me, by changing countries nearly daily, and this tired me. I told myself that my life was not made <hi rend="italic">only</hi> of songs and glory, and that I was passionate [about] many other things. I would have had to sacrifice far too many things and people to recover a place in France, like going to live in France, living a life of popularity, etc... I told myself that I had already been spoiled, so I said <hi rend="italic">stop!</hi> in 1987 after the [Song] Festival in Chile. I participated in [many] great projects [revolving] around the Lusitanian horses and the fighting bulls which I raised with passion and love, but [my] life [eventually] did not follow those paths... maybe because <hi rend="italic">my</hi> life is the stage and <hi rend="italic">life</hi> took charge [and reminded] me of that...</p>
<head id="Return_to_music">Return to music</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You came out of retirement five years ago. How often did you think about returning to music while in retirement? Was music something you felt you couldn't just "let go"?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AMD</hi>: When I decide to do something, I do it. When I decide to stop something, I do that too. But that isn't taking into account that there are things which we want to do, and those which life decides for us! In 1987, I vowed never to return to the stage, but as I said, life sometimes serves you dishes that you didn't choose, and in 2003 it's chance that made me return to the stage, and it's my fans whom I never imagined [I had] in such numbers and whom, so many years later, had conserved their love, which made me stay. I owe them a lot and will never forget that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Tell us about the CDs you have released since coming out of retirement. Are you experimenting with any new musical styles? I read you had a lot of input into your CD "Federico"; describe the direction you wanted to pursue with that disc.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AMD</hi>: It's thanks to the fans from my fan club that I could create a live CD, which I titled "Live à Charleroi" (Live at Charleroi). They sent me money via my fan club to allow me to be at the concert, and they bought my CD in advance even before it existed. [All of this was] just to help me, just to show me how much they wanted to find me [on stage] again [for that moment], in the space of 14 songs with a simple piano. </p>
</text>
