<text id="autogum_interview_doc559" title="part11_Ingrid Newkirk, co-founder of PETA, on animal rights and the film about her life" shortTile="partingrid-newkirk" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-20" dateModified="2018-02-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ingrid_Newkirk%2C_co-founder_of_PETA%2C_on_animal_rights_and_the_film_about_her_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Where do you draw your strength from?  What’s behind that question is when I was in law school I did a Chihuahua rescue and helped to save perhaps 15 to 20 dogs.  I thought it would be a great fulfilling thing, and it would be easy to do to host these animals while I read my law books.  Instead, it was grueling.  It ended up tearing me apart—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  It does.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  --watching your film I thought, “I would be a terrible investigator.  I would be like the guy in the movie who simply couldn’t do it.”  I saw a 14-pound dog that was raped by a man and her insides were torn up; I had a dog who almost died on me because it had been so severely starved and beaten, and the only thing I could do to get it to survive was to take a syringe full of blended dog food liquidated with heavy cream and feed it while it bit my fingers.  It took its toll on me and it was one of the things that made me very down on humanity—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  You’re a good man.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But it was hurtful.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  Yeah, it’s very painful!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Where do you draw your strength to continue on and to not hate humanity?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  I definitely don’t hate humanity, because I am one.  I think we’re weak.  I think our species loves to think of itself as all important and knowing and clever; and we’re not.  Fundamentally, we like a chocolate soda and stay in bed late.  We like some rubbish on TV.  It’s just the way we are.  If everyone could come to America from all over I think they would so they could all get fat and rich and do almost nothing, and collect unemployment.  Anyway, whatever.  Substitute something there. [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  Anthropologists have said that it is only human conceit that has separated us from the other apes; for starters the apes.  Really, there is no such thing as a hominid.  They say there are <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/hominids">hominids</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/pongids">pongids</ref>, and we’re probably all in it together and that we are probably all the same taxa.  I see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/chimpanzees">chimpanzees</ref> are very much like human beings, and they are very aggressive.  The males will go out together and hunt, and they’ll take apart a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black-and-white%20colobus">Colobus monkey</ref> just for the fun of it, like a gang on the street.  The males will beat their chest and are full of testosterone, and they’ll gang-bang the females, which happens every day if you read the newspaper.  And they are lazy.  If you put them in captivity they’ll throw their feces at you, but they don’t mean it!  That’s just their <hi rend="italic">nature</hi>; it’s not as if they sat there thinking this up.  It’s their nature.</p>
</text>
