<text id="autogum_bio_doc024" title="Heather Anderson (economist)" shortTile="heather-anderson" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2019-04-19" dateModified="2019-08-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heather_Anderson_%28economist%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Heather Anderson (economist)</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Heather Margot Anderson</hi> is an Australian Maureen Brunt Chair and Professor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Economics">economics</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Econometrics">econometrics</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monash_University">Monash University</ref> and a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fellow">Fellow</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy_of_the_Social_Sciences_in_Australia">Academy of the Social Sciences in Australia</ref> (2005).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Education</head>
<p>Anderson had obtained her BS in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mathematics">mathematics</ref> from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_New_England_(Australia)">University of New England</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_South_Wales">New South Wales</ref> in 1978. In 1987 she got her <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Graduate_diploma">graduate diploma</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Economics">economics</ref> from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Australian_National_University">Australian National University</ref> and two years later flew to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> where she got hers Master's and Ph.D. from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_California,_San_Diego">University of California, San Diego</ref>, in 1989 and 1992 respectively.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cv-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Career</head>
<p>From 1976 to 1977, Anderson was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tutor">tutor</ref> at the Department of Mathematics, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_New_England_(Australia)">University of New England</ref> and from 1978 to 1979 worked as a Statistical Officer for the Central Planning Bureau on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cook_Islands">Cook Islands</ref>. In 1981, she relocated to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Zealand">New Zealand</ref> where she worked at its Bureau of Statistics as Statistical Officer. She kept the same position when she returned to Cook Islands, to continue her work at CPB at which she remained until 1983. From 1984 to 1987, Margot served as a senior tutor at the Department of Economics of the Australian National University, after which she relocated to the United States. From 1987 to 1992, while residing in the United States, she worked as teaching and research assistant at the Department of Economics of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_California,_San_Diego">University of California, San Diego</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cv-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Eventually, Anderson decided to become an Assistant Professor and, for that to happen, she needed to move to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Texas">Texas</ref>. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Texas_at_Austin">University of Texas at Austin</ref> was the place that gave her the opportunity to get this position and she worked for them from 1992 to 1995. Following the success at the Department of Economics of the Austin's Texas University, she was invited to the Department of Economics of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Texas_A&amp;M_University">Texas A&amp;M University</ref> where she held the same position until 1998.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cv-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>She returned to her homeland in 1999 and became first a senior lecturer and then as associate professor at the Department of Econometrics and Business Statistics of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monash_University">Monash University</ref>. The position with the university had ended in 2003, and in 2004 she became a Professor of Econometrics at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Australian_National_University">Australian National University</ref>. A year later, Margot became co-director, specializing in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Macroeconomic_model">macroeconomic models</ref> and its methods at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Centre_for_Applied_Macroeconomic_Analysis">Centre for Applied Macroeconomic Analysis</ref>, a department of the ANU. From May to July of 2011 she became Hallsworth Visiting Professor at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Manchester">University of Manchester</ref> in Manchester, England. Since 2010, Margot is a Professor at the Department of Econometrics and Business Statistics, a department of the Monash Business School and between 2016 and 2018 worked as its head.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cv-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Editorial work</head>
<p>As editor, Margot had served as an Associate Editor of the <hi rend="italic">Studies in Nonlinear Dynamics and Econometrics</hi> and was a co-editor of <hi rend="italic">Empirical Economics</hi> at which she served from 2006 to 2015. From 2003 to present, she serves on an Editorial Board of the <hi rend="italic">Economic Record</hi> and is serving a one-year term as its guest editor, which suppose to expire by 2020. Anderson also used to be a guest editor of the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Journal_of_Econometrics">Journal of Econometrics</ref></hi>, which span from 2002 to 2006 and from 2017 to present. Since 2001, Margot is serving on editorial board of the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Journal_of_Applied_Econometrics">Journal of Applied Econometrics</ref></hi> and since 2019 became one of its main editors.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cv-2">[2]</ref></p>
</text>
