<text id="autogum_reddit_doc096" title="Scenario: The Threat Has Been Dealt With, and Peace has Returned to the World... except now your family’s wondering what the hell you’ve been doing for the past 2 or so years. Pick 3 of your Servants to introduce to your family as you try to explain what exactly Chaldea’s about." shortTile="scenario-threat-dealt" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-04-30" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8g3zeo" speakerList="#LegoSpacenaut, #NixAvernal, #Rudrahp72, #StupidlyLucky, #WeeabooCreamKing" speakerCount="5">
<head>Scenario: The Threat Has Been Dealt With, and Peace has Returned to the World... except now your family’s wondering what the hell you’ve been doing for the past 2 or so years. Pick 3 of your Servants to introduce to your family as you try to explain what exactly Chaldea’s about.</head>
<sp who="#StupidlyLucky">
<p>I’m looking forward to reading the replies when I get back from work~ </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#LegoSpacenaut">
<p>Mash is the only one I'd really want to bring, I think. About time she met actual parents and saw what a family was like.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#NixAvernal">
<p>So hey dad, mom... Yeah it’s been what? Three years? Since I left. Don’t worry, everything’s fine with my new job. Though... remember those reports about blizzards and the mass amnesia event? Yeah... I might have something to do with that. </p>
<p>BUT First! I want to introduce to you guys to some of my... I guess you can call them coworkers? </p>
<p>1. This is Asagami Fujino, and she’s my girlfriend. We met a while back at work and kinda hit it off afterwards. She’s also legally blind, but that doesn’t stop her at all. Also, she can bend things with her mind. No, it’s not a magic trick - she’s broken enough bridges to prove otherwise. </p>
<p>2. The girl that’s hiding away in the corner? That’s Osakabehime. My partner charge back at work. She’s a very talented artist - it’s just that she doesn’t like people. Or the sun. Or table lights. I’ve been trying to get her to interact with people but it’s a slow process. A  <hi rend="bold">very</hi>  slow one. </p>
<p>3. Last but no least - Lavinia, my adopted daughter. I found her in Salem, where she and her best friend Abigail were being trailed for something that they had no part in. Everything’s fine now - Abigail’s with us now! But I had to adopt her - she’s just too cute. And if someone who looks like a cross between an octopus and a plate of spaghetti left out in the sun for too long comes to you, tell him that he had one chance with my daughter and he blew it. </p>
<list type="unordered">
<item></item>
<item>Bonus Round!</item>
<item> </item>

</list><p>Gudako: So... Hi dad, hi mom... </p>
<p><ref target="#smile">...</ref><ref target="#busted">…</ref> </p>
<p>Gudako: Haha... ^surprise?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#WeeabooCreamKing">
<p>I'd bring Waver since he has knowledge on Grail Wars and is generally a smart dude. </p>
<p>I'd bring Hans because he's smart and would probably be able to explain Chaldea and Rayshifting and stuff, but would also probably be an asshole and he has a man's voice but is also a child, so maybe Hans wouldn't be so good. </p>
<p>And I'd bring Iskandar because if my family freaks out he can sing my praises as a tactician and leader of an army to try and make me seem competent.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#Rudrahp72">
<p>Honestly, I'd just bring along Waver and Mash. Those to should be able to do a better job of explaining everything..... </p>
<p>Now, introducing them to Musashi is where it would get awkward, especially now that the danger is over and the other Servants would NOT be happy about not being picked.... </p>
<p>~~My punishment for my time as a HaremLord. OzymanDIO save me~~</p>
</sp>
</text>
