<text id="autogum_voyage_doc94" title="Diving in Durban" shortTile="diving-durban" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=9610" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Diving in Durban</head>

<p>This article is intended to provide the already qualified Scuba diver with information which will help to plan dives in the waters of <ref target="Durban">Durban</ref>, <ref target="South%20Africa">South Africa</ref>, whether as a local resident or a visitor. Information is provided without prejudice, and is not guaranteed accurate or complete. Use it at your own risk.</p>

<head>Climate, weather and sea conditions</head>
<p>Diving off Durban is affected by prevailing winds and the run off from the Umgeni river, the Harbour mouth and the Umlass Cutting on the Bluff which can affect visibility in the rainy season (spring: Sept – Dec).</p>

<p>With the damming of the Umgeni River at Inanda, reducing the run off considerably, the visibility directly off central Durban on the Number One Reef system has steadily improved over the years. However, the run off from the harbour entrance and Umlaas canal do still affect visibility in the immediate vicinity of their mouths and careful monitoring of prevailing weather conditions is required to make the best choice of dive site on the day.</p>

<p>The south westerly wind is generally associated with cold fronts off Durban. However this wind is directly responsible for bringing in the clear waters of the warm Mozambique current. The low rainfall and prevailing south westerlies make winter the best time to dive Durban (March though to July).</p>

<p>Check out <ref target="http://www.windfinder.com/forecastdurban">Windfinder forecast for Durban</ref> in order to get up to the hour weather forecasts for Durban.</p>

<head>Get help</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Emergency services</hi></p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> . Police.</item>
<item> . Ambulance service</item>
<item> . Sea rescue</item>
<item> . Recompression chamber</item>
<item> . DAN hotline</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Durban Undersea Club</item>
</list>
<head>Service details</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Durban Undersea Club</hi> (DUC), Vetch's Pier, Point 4069, Durban (Follow Mahatma Gandhi Drive (Point Rd) from Durban central towards the harbour and Ushaka Marine World. Turn left into Browns Rd which leads straight to the club gate), ☏ +27 31 368-1199 , fax: +27 86 637-4301 , ✉ paul@duc.co.za . Boat dives R200 non members from Fontao wreck south to Coopers Light wreck. Scuba diving club. Equipment rental for non members diving with the club, air and Nitrox fills for members and public. PADI diver training (Open water, Advanced and Rescue), Club dives.</item>
</list>


<head>Understand:</head>
<p>This vessel has definitely been subjected to depth-charging as she is in several pieces and the evidence of explosions is obvious.</p>
<p>She has only been visited twice by divers and it is hoped that in the future a more detailed history will emerge.</p>
<head>See</head>
<p>Vetchie’s has one of the highest concentrations and varieties of Moray eels of any reef off Durban – which can be a bit unnerving for first timers to the reef. Potentially more dangerous are the numerous scorpion fish that stay put even when one is about to touch them inadvertently. In spring and early summer, the rubble of the inside of Vetch's serves as a nursery ground for hordes of fishes.</p>

<head>Other</head>
<p>There are three or four different sites where there are shipping containers to visit</p>
</text>
