<text id="autogum_interview_doc245" title="part3_Dr. Joseph Merlino on sexuality, insanity, Freud, fetishes and apathy" shortTile="partdr-joseph-merlino" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-04" dateModified="2013-09-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dr._Joseph_Merlino_on_sexuality%2C_insanity%2C_Freud%2C_fetishes_and_apathy" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="Sigmund_Freud">Sigmund Freud</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Did Judeo-Christian outlook infuse any of Freud's thinking, like it did <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michel%20Foucault">Michel Foucalt</ref> in the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20History%20of%20Sexuality">The History of Sexuality</ref></hi>?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi> Freud was somewhat of a maverick in that regard, because his position really went against what a lot of other people were saying.  Freud maintained that bisexuality was a normal part of development. That all of us went through a period of bisexuality and that, in the end, most of us came out heterosexual but that the bisexual phase we traversed remained on some unconscious level, and was dealt with in other ways.  For instance, friendship, chumships, and 'greater glory of the love of mankind' kinds of sentiments.  Freud felt these had their basis in this constitutional bisexuality that all individuals had.  He did not consider it something that should be criminalized, or penalized—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  —but treated?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  —treated if it presented a problem for the individual.  Freud felt there were a number of homosexuals he encountered who did not have a variety of complex problems that homosexuality was a part of.  He found people who were totally normal in every other regard except in terms of their sexual preference.  In fact, he saw many of them as having higher intellects, higher aesthetic sensibilities, higher morals; those kinds of things.  He did not see it as something to criminalize or penalize, or to keep from psychoanalytic training.  A lot of the psychoanalytic institutes felt if you were homosexual you should not be accepted; that was not Freud's position.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How did he discern whether a person's homosexuality was a problem with the person internally, or whether it was an external problem brought about by societal reaction to the individual?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi> Freud would use the technique of analysis to figure that out, and work with that individual to explore the cause.  In his later theories he would look at whether this is an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oedipus%20complex">oedipal</ref> issue, whether he wanted to be with the mother and couldn't have the mother so he then wanted to have men,  so that men could would like him, and then he would get the affection of the mother object.  He would explore the issues that way.  He would not start from the bias that this is the individual's problem that needed to be fixed.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is his model of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/psychosexual%20development">psychosexual development</ref> model outdated as to be useless, or is it still functioning?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  I think you used the operative word.  It's a model.  What we try to do as therapists is come up with a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/hypothesis">hypothesis</ref> that works for the individual that he can use to help him or herself, as opposed to having my theory inflicted upon you.  If you can use a psychosexual development kind of model in helping to understand what the situation is, it can be a language that the two of us can speak.  Most therapists are focusing less on even using that as language.  It's more of a concept to structure something.</p>
</text>
