<text id="autogum_interview_doc444" title="Wikinews interviews Richard H. Clark, independent candidate for US President" shortTile="wikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-19" dateModified="2014-12-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Richard_H._Clark%2C_independent_candidate_for_US_President" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Richard H. Clark, independent candidate for US President</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 19, 2008</hi></p>
<p>While nearly all cover of the 2008 Presidential election has focused on the Democratic and Republican candidates, the race for the White House also includes independents and third party candidates. These parties represent a variety of views that may not be acknowledged by the major party platforms.</p>
<p>As a non-partisan news source, Wikinews has impartially reached out to these candidates, throughout the campaign. The most recent of our interviews is Gaithersburg, Maryland's <hi rend="bold">Richard H. Clark</hi> (b. 1960), a senior software engineer and member of MENSA.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why do you want to be President?</hi></p>
<p>It's not a matter of wanting to be. I don't want to. There is a need. The corruption in the administration has become astronomical. The government must be brought back to the people. I can do that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Have you ever run for political office before?</hi></p>
<p>No, I have not.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Have you ever been a member of a political party, other than the one you're currently in?</hi></p>
<p>No, I have not. I have always been a registered Independent.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Have you ever campaigned for another political candidate?</hi></p>
<p>No, I have not. But I've become fond of the involvement now. I will campaign for candidates in the future.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What is your current job?</hi></p>
<p>I'm a Technical Team Lead at a small software company. We do real-time embedded Linux work, re-assembling protocols for data analysis and critical information leakage. We are the undisputed leaders in our field, in no small part due to my contributions.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What skills or ideas do you bring from this position, or previous positions, that will benefit  the Oval Office?</hi></p>
<p>I have an open mind. I do not suffer from NIH (Not-Invented-Here). What I bring is the ability to unify and use the best that everyone on my team has to offer. I am a problem solver who knows that the best way to solve problems is to work with and listen to everyone involved. Being a member of MENSA helps as well.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Obviously, the next American President and his or her administration will face many diverse issues. But if you were to narrow identify the three most important issues, what would they be? How will you address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>Only three? 1000 words? That's difficult...</p>
<p>Priority #1 - Free Trade. This is the primary cause of our loss of jobs, our dwindling paychecks, our loss of health care, and so many other problems. We simply cannot compete directly with third world labor at a dollar a day. Our losses in the manufacturing sector will eventually bring down the economy. The loss of generated revenue causes problems everywhere, for everyone.</p>
<p>Priority #2 - Corruption. Almost none of our elected representatives actually works for us any more. Lobbyists and special interests run the country. Short-term greed rules the day. This is no way to run a country. I will clamp down hard on lobbyists and special interests. I will change the election laws to affect permanent solutions to the underlying causes of corruption.</p>
<p>Priority #3 - Illegal Immigration and Foreign Policy. First order of business is to remove our troops from the Middle East, and place them along our southern border to shut down Illegal Immigration. Second order is to establish non-oil economic ties with the Middle East to help build their economies. This puts a damper on Terrorism, in that people who are not starving to death, who are educated, do not feed terrorism.</p>
<p>There are so many issues. They will all be addressed. One thing to remember, is that it is not just me. My staff will be addressing numerous issues simultaneously. Having intelligent, dedicated staff is crucial to a good presidency. This, the staff-building, is being done as I write. I have contact with many great, highly-qualifed people.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Campaigning for the American presidency is one of the most expensive exercises in the world. How do you deal with the cost and fundraising?</hi></p>
<p>Internet. Networking with other candidates. Organizing special events. Relationship building. There is no way I can win this election alone. None of us can. We all know that. I have been in contact with numerous other candidates, and we are working to get the attention of the press. Once we have their attention, it is my belief that Americans are starving for a viable alternative to the GOP/DEM parties. The momentum should build on its own.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Do you have a running mate yet? Who are they? What are you looking for in a running mate?</hi></p>
<p>No running mate as yet. What I'm looking for is intelligence, honesty dedication, and the kahoonas to kick me in the butt if I start to stray.</p>
<p>And, quite frankly, after talking to quite a number of Third Party and Independent candidates, there is a lot of that out there! The choice will actually be rather difficult. There are a lot of great VPs out there. That's part of the problem. There are too many good candidates, and we need to narrow the field down a little and all get behind just a few.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Can you win the 2008 Presidential election?</hi></p>
<p>Me win? Perhaps. Although not for not being perfect for the job and a great representative of the people. Rather, my social and presentation skills are a littly "iffy". I'm working on it though, and am not ready to give up just yet. I'm persistent if anything.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Can any third party or independent candidate ever win?</hi></p>
<p>I'm working on it, doing the best I can to make sure that happens. So, yes. I believe so. I hope so. America is doomed to become a second-rate has-been of a country if we don't topple the GOP/DEM corruption machine very soon.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">If you can't make it into the Oval Office, who would you prefer seeing taking the presidency?</hi></p>
<p>Any of the Independent or Third Party candidates. Anyone not associated with the GOP/DEM power structure.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What should the American people keep in mind, when heading to the polls this November?</hi></p>
<p>Don't waste your vote on the GOP/DEM parties. Do your homework and find an Independent or Third Party candidate that you can support. Voting GOP or DEM is simply a green light for them, to continue screwing the country for every penny they can squeeze out of us. Please, vote Independent or Third Party.</p>
</text>
