<text id="autogum_whow_doc209" title="Help the Elderly" shortTile="help-elderly" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2016-02-25" dateModified="2018-10-12" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Help-the-Elderly" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Help the Elderly</head><p>You may have parents or grandparents who are old or maybe you work for a charity that specialises in it. Helping old people can be an absolute joy and there are many ways which can bring more enjoyment to it. This article aims at sharing some.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be polite. Politeness goes a long way when talking to the elderly because it aids in creating good communication between you. As well as this it shows that you are not disrespectful of them.</item>
<item>Have humility. These people have lived for a very long time and as such have many experiences that you have not had. As such to assume that you have more life experience could be a very arrogant thing to do and severe all communications with them.</item>
<item>Think of what you can learn from them. Many older people enjoy sharing stories of their life and often have a great amount of wisdom due to the sheer amount of experience they have. Pay attention to some of their stories and see what you can learn from their life. Also ask them for advice on matters you are uncertain of. They know how human beings change over time and so often lend a great ear in telling you how to get the most out of life.</item>
<item>If you have some spare time be good company for them. This may sound silly to people with active social lives but the elderly often get very lonely in Today’s society due to social Isolation and not seeing their family members very often. – There are various charities available that are specifically designed to help lonely elderly people that might be worth looking into.</item>
<item>Offer to do a chore for them. Sometimes age can catch up to them and they do not have the same capacity to do things as they did in their youth. It seldom goes unappreciated to either offer to do a chore for them or just do it without asking. Little things such as their shopping, ironing, dishes, tidying, housework, or bins can make them very grateful of you.</item>
<item>Bring them fruit and flowers. This is a very simple gesture and not very costly but this shows them that they are appreciated and that you think about them even when you are not there. Every-time they look at the flowers they will be reminded that they are not alone and that somebody cares.</item>
<item>Talk to them and treat them with dignity. A lot of the time people have the tendency to treat and talk to old people like they are children or incapable of things. It can be very hurtful to them to feel so incompetent in this way. Especially with a whole life of experience. The sad fact about this is that it is often done simply out of a wrong view of them and nothing else.</item>
<item>Offer them some music. Not many things can reawaken the spirit like music, there are many ways to go about this. First you can put on some music that brings them back to their time. Secondly you can introduce them to some of your music (avoid things with swearing and cursing), thirdly you can play them some live music if you know how to play an instrument. This can be very dignifying and shows that you care.</item>
<item>Cook them something nice. Meals can sometimes be difficult for older people, cooking them a nice meal shows that they are. If you cook a lot yourself, consider wrapping a portion and bringing it to them, this can show that you are thinking about them</item>
<item>Tell them jokes. They say that you cannot teach an old dog new tricks, but the exception is jokes because new jokes are coming out all of the time. They might even teach you some really funny old jokes.</item>
<item>Look to understand them. Try to see beyond superficial un-pleasantness. Often due to their such long lived lives they can come across as a little unpleasant when they do not mean to be – perhaps they are lonely or afraid. Looking to understand them can stop you from reacting angrily when you do not need to. This often creates a mutual respect.</item></list>
</text>
