<text id="autogum_interview_doc629" title="part1_CanadaVOTES: NDP incumbent Wayne Marston running in Hamilton East—Stoney Creek" shortTile="partcanadavotes-ndp" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-09-25" dateModified="2016-07-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CanadaVOTES%3A_NDP_incumbent_Wayne_Marston_running_in_Hamilton_East%E2%80%94Stoney_Creek" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>In 2006, I didn't run to become the typical politician who leaves for Ottawa and forgets about the people and organizations that elected them; or the politician who uses this position for their own gain; that's not what this community needs or deserves.</p>
<p>As an MP, I will continue to fight for the issues that are important to Canadian families, to ensure that my neighbours are getting the help they need from their government.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are you satisfied with your time as MP? What would be the biggest highlights of the roughly two years since the last election?</hi></p>
<p>I am proud of the issues that I have been able to address in the House of Commons and in my community.  I seconded Jack Layton's Environmental Protection Bill which tackles climate change and sets measurable targets to reduce carbon emissions every year.  I introduced a bill on Amateur Sport Financing to give athletes a helping hand and worked on the Subcommittee on International Human Rights to address abuses such as the case of Omar Khadr, Huseyincan Celil and Japanese Comfort Women.</p>
<p>In Hamilton, I have worked to help families with CPP, EI, Immigration and Revenue Canada issues, had funding restored to local youth programmes through Canada Summer Jobs, helped eligible constituents collect over $750,000 through the Disability Tax Credit and hosted seminars to help people apply, co-hosted a public forum to raise awareness for Turtle Ponds, the environmentally sensitive wetlands, started a petition and postcard campaign in support of Billy Mason's family and demanded that the Conservative Government establish a National DNA Databank for Missing Persons, ensured that the entire Pakistan Team could attend the 2008 World Kabaddi Tournament held in Hamilton this August</p>
<p>The biggest disappointment? It is difficult to be in opposition and watch the Conservative Government and the supporting Liberal Opposition push through legislation that actively works against ordinary Canadians.  People elect a representative to help them, not hurt them.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">As you campaign around your riding, it's likely that some issues are mentioned more often by voters, than other issues. What would you say are the three hottest topics this election, in your riding? What would you and your party do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>I have heard from a lot of people that their big concerns are the economy, health care and the environment.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Is there any misconceptions about you, your leader, or your party and platform?</hi></p>
<p>I think the biggest wall the NDP comes up against is that people are disenfranchised from politics because Conservatives and Liberals claim "The NDP has no chance of forming a government, so don't waste your vote on them."  However, in the last two elections, 1.5 million more Canadians voted NDP - more than doubling the NDP's representation in the House of Commons. Liberals on the other hand, have lost almost 800,000 votes and over 40% of their caucus. A vote for the NDP elects an NDP MP.  People said the NDP could never win in a Liberal stronghold in Montreal, but in September 2007, that's exactly what we did with Thomas Mulcair in Outremont.</p>
</text>
