<text id="autogum_voyage_doc508" title="West Bank" shortTile="west-bank" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=38851" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>West Bank</head>


<p>The <hi rend="bold">West Bank</hi> is an area located between in the <ref target="Middle%20East">Middle East</ref> between <ref target="Israel">Israel</ref> and <ref target="Jordan">Jordan</ref>, to the north of the <ref target="Dead%20Sea%20%28Israel%20and%20the%20West%20Bank%29">Dead Sea</ref>. It forms the larger half of the semi-autonomous <ref target="Palestinian%20Territories">Palestinian Territories</ref>, the smaller being the <ref target="Gaza%20Strip">Gaza Strip</ref>. De facto control on the ground tends to be Israeli, Palestinian (Fatah since the Hamas takeover of Gaza) or some degree of joint sovereignty. Be prepared for that to affect your travels and to come upon checkpoints and signs barring Israeli citizens from entering certain areas.</p>

<head>Cities</head>
<p>In each group, cities are listed from north to south:</p>
<head>Mixed</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> (الخليل/חברון) In the southern West Bank, a holy city due to the presence of the Cave of the Patriarchs. There is a large Palestinian majority, with a few hundred Jews living in the city center, and a few thousand more in the suburb/settlement of Kiryat Arba.</item>
</list>


<head>Palestinian</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> (جنين /ג'נין) – the West Bank's northernmost city, only 26km from Nazareth. Its name's meaning is The spring of gardens.</item>
<item> (طولكرم/טולכרם)</item>
<item> (نابلس/ שׁכם) – considered the commercial capital of the West Bank, and known for its old city, its furniture trade and the delicious <hi rend="italic">kunafa/kenafeh</hi></item>
<item> (قلقيلية/קלקיליה)</item>
<item> (رام الله/רמאללה) – the administrative capital of the West Bank and temporary host to the PNA, Ramallah is a magnet for Palestinians seeking work as well as foreign activists</item>
<item> (أريحا/יריחו) – the "Oldest City in the World", around 400m below sea level and great starting point for the Dead Sea</item>
<item> (بيت لحم/בית לחם) – an ancient city much like many others in the West Bank, Bethlehem is also the site of Christian holy places such as the Church of the Nativity and a Jewish holy site as the City of David; it is a <ref target="UNESCO%20World%20Heritage%20Site">UNESCO World Heritage Site</ref></item>
</list>


<head>Major Israeli settlements</head>
<p>The following settlements are of interest for tourists:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> (اريئيل/אריאל)</item>
<item> </item>
<item> (معاليه أدوميم/מעלה אדומים)</item>
<item> (جوش عتصيون/גוש עציון) including <hi rend="bold">Efrat</hi></item>
</list>

<p>Large settlements of zero interest to tourists include <hi rend="italic">Modiin Ilit</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Beitar Ilit</hi>.</p>

<head>Other destinations</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> – the lowest place on earth, with natural and historic sites as well as beaches and resorts.</item>
<item> – great for hiking and nature</item>
</list>


<head>Understand</head>

<p>This area is known as the West Bank because it lies on the western bank of the Jordan River. This part of the world is steeped in biblical history and contains many sites of religious and archaeological significance. It has been under Israeli administration since 1967 with future status uncertain and still to be resolved, between Israel and the Palestinian National Authority (PNA). Historically and among some parts of Israeli society, especially those to the right politically the area has also been known as Judaea/Samaria.</p>

<p>About 2.5 million Palestinians and 400,000 Israelis live in the West Bank (not including East Jerusalem). As far as the traveller is concerned, Jewish and Arab sites in the West Bank are essentially separate travel destinations, since Jews and Arabs have separate bus networks, and rental cars can generally be used in either Arab cities or Jewish settlements but not both.</p>

<p>The West Bank did not exist as a concept before 1949. Its border is the cease-fire line between Israeli and Jordanian troops in 1949. Even though both sides specified at the time that it was not a permanent border, nevertheless, nowadays much of the world assumes that the border between Israel and a future Palestinian state will be based on this line.</p>

<p>In 1967, due to the Six-Day War, the West Bank came under Israeli control. Israel did not annex the West Bank (except for East Jerusalem) due to its large Palestinian population, but Israelis did establish civilian settlements in the West Bank. West Bank Palestinians have often resisted the Israeli occupation, most notably in the First Intifada of the late 1980s, which however also had aspects of a civil war, targeting Palestinians seen as too pro-Israel almost as much as Israelis. The Oslo Accords in 1993 began the "peace process" and established Palestinian autonomy in parts of the West Bank. This autonomy was extended in several steps in the 1990s, but in 2000 the Second Intifada broke out and negotiations halted. Since then, there have been some attempts at negotiations, but no more concrete progress towards an agreement. Around 2002, Israel reentered the autonomous West Bank cities in order to wipe out terror cells that were carrying out bombings in Israel. In 2005 Israel withdrew its troops and settlers from the Gaza Strip, but they remain in the West Bank. A year after the Israeli withdrawal from Gaza, Hamas won the Palestinian elections and subsequently took de facto control of the Gaza strip, while Fatah continues to control the west bank. In Israeli political discourse the example of the Gaza withdrawal is often brought up as an argument against concessions or withdrawal, especially if done unilaterally.</p>

<p>The West Bank is divided into three noncontiguous areas based on the Oslo Accords:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Area A</hi> (18% of land) - Full Palestinian military and civil control, but Israel sometimes launches raids here to capture suspected terrorists. This includes most Palestinian cities.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Area B</hi> (21% of land) - Israeli military control, Palestinian civil control. This includes most Palestinian villages and the farmland between them.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Area C</hi> (61% of land) - Full Israeli control. This includes uninhabited areas, all Israeli settlements, and most major roads. Just 4% of West Bank Palestinians live in Area C.</item>
</list>


<p>There are no fences or other physical boundaries between areas A, B, and C. However, the Israeli military has put checkpoints on many roads, generally at crossings between Area C and areas A or B. Because areas A and B are noncontiguous, Palestinians going from place to place often have to transverse these checkpoints. Israel's West Bank barrier (physically a wall and a fence depending on where you are, and labeled by either term depending on political sympathies) is entirely within Area C.</p>

<head>Climate</head>
<p>Temperate; temperature and precipitation vary with altitude, warm to hot summers, cool to mild winters.</p>

<head>Terrain</head>
<p>Mostly rugged dissected upland, very hilly and mountainous, heavy vegetation is common in many places.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="italic">lowest point:</hi> Dead Sea -408 m</item>
<item> <hi rend="italic">highest point:</hi> Tall Asur 1,022 m</item>
</list>
</text>
