<text id="autogum_interview_doc300" title="part6_Shimon Peres discusses the future of Israel" shortTile="partshimon-peres" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-01-06" dateModified="2013-08-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Shimon_Peres_discusses_the_future_of_Israel" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<figure><caption>During lunch Yitzhak Apeloig, the President of Israel's renowned <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Technion">Technion</ref>, told David Shankbone that he noticed the quality of Hebrew spoken by the students at the Israeli <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/M.I.T.">M.I.T.</ref> had decreased, and that "some professors have difficulty understanding their students."  Peres waived such concerns aside:  "They think everything is being ruined and is decaying.  It’s different!  They would like that we shall still dance a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hora">hora</ref>."Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref>.</caption></figure><figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eytan%20Fox">Eytan Fox</ref>'s 2006 film <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Bubble%20(2006)">The Bubble</ref></hi>, so-named because of the mentality and sometime apathy of the peace of mind that exists in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tel%20Aviv">Tel Aviv</ref>, amid a tumultuous region.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: When you speak of language, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hebrew">Hebrew</ref> is very unique.  At a time when <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Extinct%20language">languages are disappearing</ref>, Hebrew is the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Revival%20of%20the%20Hebrew%20language">only example that I know of a language revived successfully</ref>.  Although I don’t speak Hebrew, I understand that the quality of Hebrew spoken by the younger generations has decreased.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: Don’t listen to the old generation.  They think everything is being ruined and is decaying.  It’s different!  They would like that we shall still dance a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hora">hora</ref>.  And the boys and the girls want to have all the jumping stuff:  They want to jump, let them jump, my God!  They still want that they should sing Slavic melodies and they complain the dresses are becoming shorter.  What do you care?  Let them have their own taste.  And by the way: they can have it!  Why are the girls wearing such short skirts?  Because they are not afraid to show their legs; they take care of themselves.  In previous generations, the women were not as up to develop the lady, so she couldn’t show her legs.  Today, on the contrary.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: You used to not want to see the legs. [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: They didn’t show because you didn’t want to see! [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  So every generation handles it, they have new advantages, they have new problems, and the older want that we shall obey older traditions, and that children will behave like their parents.  But the children have their own culture so they say they are deteriorating.  They are not deteriorating!  They are stronger, they are better informed, they are full of energy, they have a strategy.  They are ready-made persons at an early age—14, 15, 16—physically and mentally and we don’t give them a role in our society.  So they go off on drugs.  It’s crazy! Let them play a role.  Let them introduce themselves in the new hierarchies of our life.  I believe that an inventor, a researcher can be the age of 15, 16, 17.  We spoke about languages.  What is the best time to learn a language?  At the age of 2, 3, then you are becoming tired.  Maybe at the age of 15 or 16 you have talents which are disappearing.  Let them work.  In the past generations they would not let the children work because it was a physical effort.  Today, to work is to think.  Let them think; don’t send them to drugs.  Let them have their own challenges, their own curiosities</p>
</text>
