<text id="autogum_academic_doc536" title="A Miniaturized Butler Matrix Based Switched Beamforming Antenna System in a Two-Layer Hybrid Stackup Substrate for 5G Applications" shortTile="miniaturized-butler" author="Soyeon Kim, Seongjo Yoon, Yongho Lee, Hyunchol Shin" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2079-9292/8/11/1232/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The fifth-generation (5G) millimeter-wave (mm-Wave) frequency range, also referred to as the frequency range 2 (FR2), includes the band between 24.25 and 52.6 GHz. For the 5G mm-Wave wireless applications, beamforming antenna system is essentially needed to cope with high free-space path loss, severe multi-path fading, and possible interference management for improving signal-to-noise ratio. Two approaches are possible for the beamforming system realization. The first approach is phased-array beamforming system. It can provide continuously any-directional beam-steering capability, but requires sophisticated beamforming circuitry comprising precise phase shifters, variable gain blocks, and switches, thus it inevitably elevates the system implementation cost and complexity. On the other hand, switched beamforming antenna system can provide discontinuous discrete-directional beam-steering capability, but with much less hardware complexity and easier producibility. Thus, the switched beamforming antenna system is more preferred when precise and continuous beam steering function is not necessarily required, whereas implementation cost and producibility are of more importance. Passive beamforming matrices such as Blass matrix, Nolen matrix, and Butler matrix are generally adopted for the switched beamforming antenna system. Among them, the Butler matrix is more widely used due to its wideband characteristic and simple structure. </p>

<p>When realizing a Butler matrix based switched beamforming antenna system, the Butler matrix usually occupies a much larger area than the antenna array elements. Thus, minimizing the Butler matrix size is more critical for the overall form factor minimization. Many previous works have been reported focusing on the miniaturization of the Butler matrix. The previous techniques can be categorized into a single-layer substrate based design and a multi-layer substrate based design. For the single-layer substrate designs, several techniques, such as a higher characteristic impedance transmission line based design, a directional coupler employing lumped components, and an artificial transmission line employing quasi-lumped elements and discontinuities structure, were effective for the miniaturization. Nevertheless, since the Butler matrix and the antenna elements were put on the same plane, the spurious radiation leaking from the Butler matrix toward the antenna was a serious issue because it adversely affected the total radiation pattern.  </p>

<p>The multi-layer substrate design approach can alleviate the spurious radiation issue more effectively because the Butler matrix and the antenna elements are placed in different layers. In addition, such previous multi-layer designs have employed further miniaturization techniques, such as the suspended stripline, dual transmission line structure in a multi-layer structure, forward-wave directional coupler, modularized multi-folded structure, slot-directional hybrid coupler, and dual-layer substrate integrated waveguide (SIW) based crossover elimination structure. Yet, it should be noted that those miniaturization techniques inevitably lead to higher implementation cost and less producibility. It is also interesting to note, that those previous works have utilized only the same-property homogenous substrates for the multiple layers. </p>

<p>In this work, we propose to adopt a two-layer hybrid stackup substrate for realizing a 28-GHz band Butler matrix based switched beamforming antenna system. The hybrid two-layer stackup substrate is composed of two dissimilar layers with each layer having optimal electrical properties for the Butler matrix and the antenna elements. Such hybrid stackup substrate based design approach was also found to be effective for performance and reliability improvement in the high-frequency serial-link applications. This work is carried out to achieve the overall size miniaturization and the spurious radiation reduction in a Butler matrix based switched beamforming antenna system for 28-GHz mm-Wave 5G radio applications. </p>
</text>
