<text id="autogum_news_doc279" title="George Bush arrives in Middle East" shortTile="george-bush-arrives" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-01-09" dateModified="2014-03-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/George_Bush_arrives_in_Middle_East" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>George Bush arrives in Middle East</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 9, 2008</hi>
US President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/George_W._Bush">George W. Bush</ref> has arrived in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Israel">Israel</ref> - the first stop on a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Middle_East">Middle East</ref> journey designed to bolster the Israeli-<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Palestine">Palestinian</ref> peace process and foster unity on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iran">Iran</ref>.</p>
<p>Israel's leaders were waiting at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ben%20Gurion%20Airport">Ben Gurion Airport</ref>, as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Air%20Force%20One">Air Force One</ref> taxied to a stop.</p>
<p>They formed a long welcoming line as George W. Bush set foot on Israeli soil for the first time in his presidency.</p>
<hi rend="bold">If there needs to be a little pressure then you know I will provide it.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—George W. Bush</p>
<p>Following a discussion with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ehud_Olmert">Ehud Olmert</ref>, the Israeli Prime Minister, George Bush said he would provide pressure if necessary. He made this clear by saying "If there needs to be a little pressure then you know I will provide it," after the talks.</p>
<p>He spoke of the strong ties between the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> and Israel. He says the source of that strength is a shared belief in the power of human freedom.</p>
<p>"We will do more than defend ourselves. We will seek lasting peace. We see a new opportunity for peace here in the Holy Land and for freedom across the region," said Mr. Bush.</p>
<p>Like President Bush, Israeli Prime Minister Ehud Olmert kept his comments at the arrival ceremony broad in nature, avoiding any direct reference to issues related to the peace process.</p>
<p>"From the very beginning, your policies have reflected a basic understanding of the challenges facing Israel in this troubled region and a solid commitment to our national security," he said.</p>
<p>It fell to Israeli President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Shimon_Peres">Shimon Peres</ref>, who is considered by some to be largely ceremonial, to offer some tougher talk. He said President Bush is right to urge the world to pay attention to the threat posed by Iran.</p>
<p>"We take your advice not to underestimate the Iranian threat. Iran should not underestimate our resolve for self-defense," said President Bush.</p>
<p>President Bush, Prime Minister Olmert and President Peres wasted no time getting down to business - launching talks shortly after the arrival ceremony.</p>
<p>Thursday, President Bush will travel from Jerusalem on to Ramallah, the West Bank headquarters of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palestinian%20Authority">Palestinian Authority</ref>, to meet separately with Palestinian President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mahmoud_Abbas">Mahmoud Abbas</ref>.</p>
<p>At a meeting in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jerusalem">Jerusalem</ref>, Tuesday, Prime Minister Olmert and President Abbas agreed to begin negotiations on the thorniest issues blocking a peace agreement. Among them: the borders of a future Palestinian state, competing claims to Jerusalem, and the status of Palestinian refugees.</p>
<p>Concerns about rocket attacks into Israel from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gaza">Gaza</ref> and Israeli settlement activity have created tensions since the American-led <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Annapolis%20Conference">Annapolis Mideast conference</ref> in November. President Bush is expected to use his trip to encourage both sides to look at the big picture and keep focused on the need for peace.</p>
<p>During the flight to Israel, White House National Security Advisor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen%20Hadley">Stephen Hadley</ref> told reporters traveling with the president that Mr. Bush is not coming to the Middle East to interject himself into the negotiations. He said, instead, the president wants both sides to stay focused, and look beyond what he called "a lot of distractions."</p>
<p>Hadley also talked about the recent incident involving Iranian vessels and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Navy">U.S. Navy</ref> ships in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Persian%20Gulf">Persian Gulf</ref>. He said Iran must be careful and realize there will be consequences to bear if they again menace American boats in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/international%20waters">international waters</ref>.</p>
</text>
