<text id="autogum_interview_doc162" title="part0_Canupa Gluha Mani speaks about Lakota Oyate, Lakota freedom" shortTile="partcanupa-gluha" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-01-08" dateModified="2013-03-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canupa_Gluha_Mani_speaks_about_Lakota_Oyate%2C_Lakota_freedom" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Canupa Gluha Mani speaks about Lakota Oyate, Lakota freedom</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 9, 2008</hi></p>
<p>It's now been three weeks since the four-person <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republic%20of%20Lakotah">Lakota Freedom Delegation</ref> declared that the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lakota%20people">Lakota people</ref> were withdrawing from their treaties with the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> and, though small, the movement still proves controversial: two U.S.-recognized Lakota tribal governments have rejected the Delegation's authority outright with at least one tribe stating it will consider the Delegation's, now Lakota Oyate's, proposal. The rest of the tribes have remained silent.</p>
<p>The central figure the movement has been Canupa Gluha Mani, a longtime activist whose tactics have led repeatedly to his arrest and imprisonment — most recently in June 2007, when Canupa Gluha Mani was one of six arrested who participated in blockading a road in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Nebraska">Nebraska</ref> to keep outside alcohol from entering his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dry%20county">dry reservation</ref> where it is banned. <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> talked to Canupa Gluha Mani about the movement and Lakota Oyate in an exclusive interview.
<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Special:FilePath/Canupa_Gluha_Mani_sings.jpg">File:Canupa Gluha Mani sings.jpg</ref></p><figure><caption>Canupa Gluha Mani (left) at the Lakota Freedom Delegation's December press conference in Washington. Russell Means is in the background. Image: Naomi Archer.<hi rend="italic">(Image <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Template:Missing_image/message">missing</ref> from commons: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/File:Canupa_Gluha_Mani_sings.jpg">image</ref>; <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Special:Log?page=Image%3ACanupa+Gluha+Mani+sings.jpg">log</ref>)</hi></caption></figure>
<p>Also called Duane Martin Sr, Canupa Gluha Mani prefers to be referred to as just that, "Canupa Gluha Mani"; it means "He walks as he protects the pipe", though much of the meaning is lost in translation between English and the delicately-nuanced Lakota language. Canupa Gluha Mani prefers to speak in this, his native tongue — he "hates" that the English language has become the everyday language of the Lakota, and decries the extinction of many indigenous American languages — but uses English fluently and earthily.</p>
<p>Canupa Gluha Mani talked about the Cante Tenza, the Strong Heart Warrior Society, which he heads and which forms the paramilitary force of Lakotah. The society, an <hi rend="italic">okolakiciye</hi> or warrior society, originated in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black%20Hills">Black Hills</ref>. He told the following story: Four warriors in the hills ran across a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/coyote">coyote</ref> and gave it chase. And as the coyote ran he turned into a Lakota man, and in his changing the man left four objects: a rattle, a drum, a lance, and a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/tomahawk">tomahawk</ref> with which the Lakota people could be defended. Canupa Gluha Mani is a warrior leader, and his position with relation to the treaty council which traditionally governs the Lakota is "whip-man", loosely "sergeant at arms" — that is, he enforces order and decorum when passions grow heated during tribal discussions.</p>
<p>The authority of the Lakota Freedom Delegation, he says, comes not from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bureau%20of%20Indian%20Affairs">BIA</ref>-recognized governments but rather from the "people who understand treaties", i.e. the treaty council, from among the Seven Sister Bands of the Lakota. This traditional government is based on the idea of "staying quiet and listening to the people who have answers", the "itacans" or expert headmen.</p>
</text>
