<text id="autogum_voyage_doc477" title="Fiordland National Park" shortTile="fiordland-national" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=11628" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Fiordland National Park</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.doc.govt.nz/parks-and-recreation/places-to-go/fiordland/places/fiordland-national-park/">Fiordland National Park</ref></hi>, covering over 1.2 million hectares, is <ref target="New%20Zealand">New Zealand</ref>'s largest national park and one of the largest in the world. The park, together with the adjoining <ref target="Mount%20Aspiring%20National%20Park">Mount Aspiring National Park</ref>, occupies the south west corner of the <ref target="South%20Island">South Island</ref> and is listed as a <ref target="UNESCO_World_Heritage_List%23New_Zealand">UNESCO World Heritage site</ref>. The park was one of the film sets for the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="Lord%20of%20the%20Rings%20tourism">Lord of the Rings</ref></hi> film trilogy.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>Fiordland, as the name suggests, is home to several fiords — steep-sided inlets carved by glaciers during the last ice age, then later drowned by the rising sea. Its rugged landscape remains one of the least explored areas of New Zealand. Although the park has about 500 km of formed walking tracks, these are mostly confined to eastern and northern parts of the park.</p>

<p>Like all of New Zealand's national parks, it is managed by the <hi rend="bold">Department of Conservation</hi> (DOC). The department aims to allow the public to enjoy the park, while also preserving the environment. There are relatively few restrictions on access by individual visitors, though commercial activity is carefully (some might say strictly) controlled.</p>

<p>The main visitor information centre is in the township of <ref target="Te%20Anau">Te Anau</ref>. There are park ranger outposts at major visitor locations. Visitors intending to stay in the park overnight are advised to inform the park rangers of their intentions. In the event of an emergency, these intentions will be used as part of any search and rescue operation.</p>

<head>Flora and fauna</head>
<p>The area is so remote and unexplored that some speculate that species thought extinct in New Zealand may still live in the park. The <hi rend="bold">takahe</hi>, a flightless bird previously thought extinct, was discovered in a remote part of the park in 1948.</p>

<p>The <hi rend="bold">kakapo</hi>, the world's only flightless parrot, survived in Fiordland longer than any other place on New Zealand's two main islands, although even here it died out by the 1980s. A recovery project has been started on offshore islands free of the predators that threatened its survival on the mainland.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Sandflies</hi> are an obvious (and annoying) demonstration of the insect life that inhabits the area.</p>

<head>Climate</head>
<p>The weather in the park can change dramatically over the space of a few hours and over a few kilometres. Visitors should always be prepared for rain, which can be heavy and prolonged. The park has over 200 rain days per year, though different parts of the park receive widely different rainfalls. Te Anau, with 1200 mm (40 inches) annual rainfall is almost as dry as much of the eastern South Island, while Milford Sound, with 8000 mm (320 inches) annual rainfall, is truly rainforest and waterfall territory.</p>

<head>Aircraft</head>

<p>Aircraft are part of the Fiordland National Park scene. DOC uses them to carry out its duties in the park, including pest control. Aircraft service the walking track and remove every bit of waste, including toilet waste. As there are no roads, all lodge, track maintenance and building is enabled by aircraft and all supplies to the lodges are flown in. If you injure yourself so you can't continue or you go missing, aircraft are the only practical method to carry out search and rescue. For many people the only way they can access the park is by aircraft either because of lack of time, age or infirmity. The other important consideration is that aircraft make the least real environmental impact of any of the users of the park.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">State Highway 94</hi>. Drive or bus in to <ref target="Te%20Anau">Te Anau</ref>, the park's "gateway", from <ref target="Queenstown%20%28New%20Zealand%29">Queenstown</ref> or <ref target="Invercargill">Invercargill</ref>. You can also fly into Milford or Doubtful Sounds from Queenstown, Glenorchy or Te Anau.</item>
<item> Manapouri (15 min drive from Te Anau) is another place to start exploring Fiordland. Daily departures to Doubtful Sound (also within Fiordland National Park).</item>
</list>


<head>Get around</head>
<p>Fly, bus, walk or boat</p>

<head>Destinations</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Milford%20Sound">Milford Sound</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Te%20Anau">Te Anau</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Manapouri">Manapouri</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Doubtful%20Sound">Doubtful Sound</ref></item>
</list>


<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Homer Tunnel</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hollyford Valley</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lake Te Anau</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Te Ana-au cave</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lake Manapouri</hi>, especially the <hi rend="bold">West Arm</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Manapouri Power Station</hi>. Take a bus trip over the <hi rend="bold">Wilmot Pass</hi> to <hi rend="bold">Deep Cove</hi>. The power station, one of New Zealand's largest, has been carved out of solid rock below the lake and two tailrace tunnels take the water that passes through the power station to Deep Cove, 10 km away. The only evidence that there is a power station nearby is the power lines that disappear into the ground!</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Walk</hi>. Take a trip through the amazing wilderness on either a day trip or overnight. The Department of Conservation maintains and, part of the year, staffs the park's tracks. The tracks get busy at certain times of the year and can require bookings for the huts, so its a good option to inquire at an information center before setting off.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hollyford Track</hi>. Guided walks are available.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hump Ridge Track</hi>. Guided walks are available.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Kepler%20Track">Kepler Track</ref></hi>. Walk the Manapouri end of the track for a nice day hike, or dive all the way into the backcountry for an overnight.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Milford%20Track">Milford Track</ref></hi>. One of the DOC's "Great Walks" and considered by many to be one of the best walks in the world. Guided walks are available. A four-day, three-night 53.5-km track that starts at the head of Lake Te Anau and ends at Milford Sound. Bookings essential.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Routeburn</hi>. Take the Routeburn for a overnight trip and cross into the neighboring <ref target="Mount%20Aspiring%20National%20Park">Mount Aspiring National Park</ref>. Guided walks are available.</item>
<item> The <hi rend="bold">Dusky</hi> track. A harder, longer tramp joins Lake Hauroko to Lake Manapouri.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hunting</hi> for the introduced species of red deer, wapiti and possums is permitted and a permit can be obtained from the Fiordland National Park Visitor Centre. These introduced species are considered pests and there is an ongoing eradication programme to control these animal populations and eventually eliminate them. The moose was introduced here but is thought to have died out.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fishing</hi> for brown and rainbow trout requires a licence and compliance with regulations.</item>
</list>
</text>
