<text id="autogum_academic_doc317" title="Compact Differential-Fed Planar Filtering Antennas" shortTile="compact-differentialfed" author="Emadeldeen Hassan, Denys Martynenko, Eddie Wadbro, Gunter Fischer, Martin Berggren" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2079-9292/8/11/1241/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Wireless communication and sensing systems are continuously raising new demands not only on performance of components, but also on their miniaturization, integration with on-chip devices, environmental effects, and costs. Planar components are easy to fabricate, result in low-profile circuits, and are therefore cost-efficient. The current design of planar circuits still, however, follows a conventional approach that relies on assemblage of basic building blocks, such as filters, hybrid couplers, and antennas. The design of each component is accomplished in a separate design step and typically relies on simple structures inspired from circuit and transmission line theories. Although this design methodology is beneficial for design reuse, it results in large circuit footprints and high insertion losses. </p>

<p>Filtering antennas are components designed to offer antennas with specified filtering responses to decrease interference with surrounding wireless systems. The design of filtering antennas is currently accomplished by following one of two approaches. The first is to use a separate filtering structure that precedes the antenna. This approach has the drawback of increasing both the insertion loss and the footprint of the whole circuit. The second approach uses parasitic elements inside/near the antenna structure. This approach is suitable for narrow band antennas, such as microstrip antennas; however, it typically requires a redesign of the antenna to account for the presence of the parasitic objects. Moreover, this latter strategy is typically time-consuming and may result in structures that are complex to fabricate. In a recent work, Liu et al. proposed to suppress the out-of-band radiation of a filtering patch antenna by using dissipative resistors. The use of dissipative resistors has the advantage of decreasing the energy reflected back to the amplifier. However, the dissipated energy increases the risk of heating up the circuit. </p>

<p>In the literature, most of the previously published filtering antennas rely on structures inspired from circuit and transmission line theories. Following a different approach, this work uses topology optimization techniques to design planar differential-fed filtering antennas. Topology optimization techniques, initially proposed for structural optimization, have been employed to design various electromagnetic components, such as antennas, filters, and waveguide transitions. In topology optimization, each pixel (2D) or voxel (3D) inside the design domain is subject to design. Hence, topology optimization techniques are sometimes referred to as being parameter-free methods. Typically, these optimization techniques rely on sensitivity analysis and gradient-based optimization methods to seek designs (shapes) that satisfy the design objectives. Because of the vast degrees of freedom handled by these algorithms, they can reveal new conceptual designs. Moreover, recent designs obtained by these techniques have proven their ability not only to offer novel devices, but also to provide designs that satisfy manufacturing constraints. </p>

<p>The main interest of the current work is to optimize the antenna of a positioning system that operates over the frequency band 6.0–8.5 GHz. One essential operational requirement for such system is to possess a stable coverage over a wide beamwidth. Moreover, this positioning system is intended for use in sites where other wireless communication systems operating at the 5.8 GHz WiFi frequency band could be sources of mutual interference. Therefore, we propose to design differential-fed planar antennas that combine requirements on a wide impedance bandwidth, a stable directivity, and a filtering of the out-of-band frequencies. We aim to exploit the vast degrees of freedom offered by topology optimization to design such antennas. We formulate the problem of the antenna design as a mathematical topology optimization problem, in which all design requirements are embedded a priori as objective functions or constraints. That is, using a very large space of feasible designs, the algorithm seeks structures that accomplish multiple objectives. Using manual design procedures, it can be very difficult to manage a large design space and multiple objectives. The choice of differential lines to feed the antennas makes them suitable for use with differential RF amplifiers. Moreover, this type of feeding typically results in very low cross-polarization levels. </p>
</text>
