<text id="autogum_whow_doc314" title="Use a Napkin with Proper Table Etiquette" shortTile="use-napkin-proper" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2013-12-29" dateModified="2019-09-10" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Use-a-Napkin-with-Proper-Table-Etiquette" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Use a Napkin with Proper Table Etiquette</head><p>The practice of good dining decorum involves a vast array of elements to consider. You may already know the proper ways to use various utensils and how to eat diverse styles of dishes. But one component that is constant throughout the dining experience is the use of the napkin. Follow the steps below to use your napkin in such an elegant deportment that all your fellow guests will notice your neat civility.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Put your napkin on your lap, right away. Once you have been seated by the host, the first and foremost thing you should do is pick up your napkin and without flicking it violently, unfold it and place it comfortably on your lap. This is its home until either you need to go to the restroom, or the meal has finished. <figure rend="Use a Napkin with Proper Table Etiquette Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wipe your mouth with care. During the meal, it will be customary that you will need to wipe your mouth at certain promptings. To wipe your mouth, gently dab your mouth and allow the napkin to soak residue from the area. It is also vital that you use your napkin before sipping your wine or other beverage, so you don’t leave any greasy mouth excess on the lip of the glass. <figure rend="Use a Napkin with Proper Table Etiquette Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do not use it as a handkerchief. At no stage during the meal should you use your napkin like a tissue as a means to blow your nose. Simply excuse yourself from the table if you need to, and visit the bathroom instead. <figure rend="Use a Napkin with Proper Table Etiquette Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be careful when you get up. If you do need to take a trip to the restroom during the meal, excuse yourself from the table and place your napkin neatly on the lap of your seat (not the arm or the top) until you return. Never place it back onto the table during the meal. <figure rend="Use a Napkin with Proper Table Etiquette Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Never wear your napkin like a cravat. Toddlers wear bibs, not adults. <figure rend="Use a Napkin with Proper Table Etiquette Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wrap up at the end of the meal. The host should signal that you have reached the end of the meal by placing his or her napkin on the table beside the plate (never on it). It is fine for you to mimic this gesture and at the same time thank them for a wonderful meal if you can. <figure rend="Use a Napkin with Proper Table Etiquette Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you drop your napkin, kindly ask the host for a fresh one and avoid disturbing other diners by trying to pick it up. Simply leave it until the end of the meal and place it up on the table afterwards.</item>
<item>Avoid using the napkin excessively. Prior to taking a sip of your drink, the use of your napkin need not be lengthy.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Avoid using your napkin on other guests at the table within your vicinity. It's childish and unmannerly.</item></list>
</text>
