<text id="autogum_interview_doc301" title="part7_Shimon Peres discusses the future of Israel" shortTile="partshimon-peres" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-01-06" dateModified="2013-08-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Shimon_Peres_discusses_the_future_of_Israel" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: What informs the question I asked about Hebrew is that it seems to build such a cohesive society here in Israel.  It’s one of the binding forces...</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: You said culture as justifying history, because I don’t suggest to forget the language.  No.  I am also for having individuality for nations.  That can be cultural.  But otherwise, I mean, let science run, let values stay permanent.  I’ll give you just one example.  Take away the land, okay.  Take away a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunam">dunam</ref> of land.  But in our culture, the yield per dunam is 25 times higher than it used to be.  So maybe you lost one dunam but you won 25 yields.  On the other hand, take away the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ten%20Commandments">Ten Commandments</ref> and the world becomes all of a sudden poor.  You don’t have anything to replace these 169 words.  So that’s what I mean, the permanence of the values and the mobility of the assets.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: One value used to be military service.  20 years ago it was anathema to not serve in the military and that was another binding cohesive force in Israeli society and now it’s quite common....</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: Go over to sport, fight without killing, what’s wrong?  Go over to chess, go over to competition or a creativeness to sing, to create.  I would like to see the democracy not just a matter of real expression but a matter of self-expression.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: Do you think Israel’s security is at a point where it can move from being concerned with military service to being unconcerned and moving more towards competition in sports or the creative elements?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: The minute we shall be free of danger, yes.  Right now, no.  as long as we have dangers, we must be prepared to face them.  You cannot become all of a sudden a philosopher instead of a soldier.  It doesn’t make sense.  But you see there are two things which are really fascinating.  What makes Israel greater than our size?  And that is the size of our enemies.  We are forced to organize our defense, which means our agenda, not with the size of the land but with the size of the enemies of the land.  So all the time we have to be more tense, more alert, more developed.  The minute this will disappear, we will have to compete with the world to find our way. I think there is something in Judaism, by the way, which makes us inclined to do so.  The greatest thing about Judaism--you can take it as a joke, you can take it seriously--is that introduced to life is dissatisfaction.  A Jewish person cannot be satisfied, cannot be satisfied.  The minute he is satisfied he begins to be non-Jewish.  Dissatisfaction is the source of creation.  All the time, because we were oppressed, we were small, we couldn’t sit down and have a glass of wine.  All through time we have had to try and struggle and invest and renew.  That is the reason why the Jewish people, in a way,  are the permanent revolutionaries of history.</p>
</text>
