<text id="autogum_news_doc807" title="2005 World Social Forum-Brazil coverage" shortTile="-world-social-forumbrazil" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-01-28" dateModified="2019-02-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2005_World_Social_Forum-Brazil_coverage" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>2005 World Social Forum-Brazil coverage</head><head id="The_first_day_of_the_World_Social_Forum_wraps_up">The first day of the World Social Forum wraps up</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 27, 2005</hi></p>
<p>Brazilian president <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luiz%20Inácio%20Lula%20da%20Silva">Luiz Inácio Lula da Silva</ref> has defended himself before over 15 000 activists at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World%20Social%20Forum">World Social Forum</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Porto%20Alegre">Porto Alegre</ref>. He interrupted his speech to respond to hecklers by saying "Those of you that aren't from here, don't be afraid. These people that don't want to listen are sons and daughters of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Partido%20dos%20Trabalhadores">PT</ref> <hi rend="italic">(Partido dos Trabalhadores, "Worker's Party")</hi>  that rebelled. That's typical of youth and one day they are going to mature and we'll be here with open arms to welcome them back". Supporters also drowned out the hecklers by chanting "Lula" the president's name.</p>
<p>The President also used his speech to help launch an ambitious campaign by 1,000 non-governmental organizations to halve world poverty within ten years. "For the first time, the Forum takes upon itself the task of making a priority of an issue such as poverty," Lula said.</p>
<head id="Second_day">Second day</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday, January 28, 2005</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Nearly 500 activists from the Campaign Against the Free Trade Area of the Americas (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FTAA">FTAA</ref>) participated in a  meeting to discuss the future of the movement which appeared for the first time in the 2002 WSF. They celebrated the current impasse in the negotiations involving the Free Trade Area of the Americas. João Pedro Stédile, leader of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Landless%20Workers'%20Movement">Landless Workers Movement (MST)</ref> and the Vila Campesina movement said that the campaign has been victorious so far.</item></list>
<list type="unordered"><item>Social movements proposed a mobilization against the poverty and hunger for next September 10. According to Cândido Grzybowski, they planning on mobilizations right around the world. The date, September 10, was chosen because it is near 14 September when there will be a meeting of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20Nations">United Nations</ref>. The date is also the day before the forth anniversary of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/September%2011,%202001%20attacks">September 11, 2001 attacks</ref> and they wish to protest against the pecieved unilateralism with which the USA reacted to those attacks. </item></list>
<list type="unordered"><item>Feminists discussed strategies for the legalization of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/abortion">abortion</ref> in Brazil.</item></list>
<list type="unordered"><item>There was a march called "March Against the Lies and the War of Bush" in protest against the American President <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George%20W.%20Bush">George W. Bush</ref>. </item></list>
<list type="unordered"><item>The Portuguese writer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/José%20Saramago">José Saramago</ref> suggested a more propositive WSF. </item></list>
<head id="Third_day">Third day</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 29, 2005</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>The Brazilian writer and former Catholic priest Leornado Boff identified what he termed the "Three Wounds" of Brazilian society: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/colonialism">colonialism</ref>, the past of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/slavery">slavery</ref> and the transformation of the country by great multinational companies.</item></list>
According to Boff, the Catholic Church does not have the right to talk about dignity because it is seated in the blood of millions. He still defended that the first right is the right to the life and that other freedoms must come later, including the rights of freedom of movement and freedom of thought.
Finally Boff considered three criteria to judge the religious traditions that exist: "All tradition that implies in suffering of any person should be abolished; all religion that violates the  human rights must be abandoned; and everything which means the breaking of the land, the water and the environment must be abolished."
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South%20America">South America</ref> is the absolute priority of the Brazilian external politics according to the special assessor of external politics of the Presidency of the Republic, Marco Aurélio Garcia. (<ref target="http://www.radiobras.gov.br/especiais/forumsocialmundial_2005/audios/29-01-2005-%20marco%20aurelio.mp3"><hi rend="bold">audio</hi>)</ref> </item></list>
<list type="unordered"><item>Activists promoted a campaign against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coca-Cola">Coca-Cola</ref>. According to them the Coca-Cola Company is responsible for contamination and crisis of the water supply, unemployment and deaths. </item></list>
<list type="unordered"><item>Conference with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/José%20Saramago">José Saramago</ref>, Eduardo Galeano and Ignácio Ramonet. </item></list>
<list type="unordered"><item>Conference with the Brazilian Minister of Culture <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gilberto%20Gil">Gilberto Gil</ref> about Free Software.</item></list>
<head id="Fourth_day">Fourth day</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, January 30, 2005</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Professor Laurindo Leal, from School of Communication of the University of São Paulo (USP) defended the control of content in the broadcasting network. He cited the USA, France, Germany, Canada, England as good examples how a broadcasting network model should work. </item></list>
<list type="unordered"><item>The President of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Venezuela">Venezuela</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hugo%20Chavez">Hugo Chavez</ref>, arrived. Chavez said it is impossible to solve the severe problems of poverty in the world in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capitalism">Capitalism</ref>. "Neither [by] Statism -- Capitalism of the State -- which would be the same Soviet perversion that was the cause of its destruction. But another <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socialism">Socialism</ref> which can put the man and not the machine [of State] at the first plan."</item></list>
President Chavez also criticized the President of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/USA">USA</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/George_W._Bush">George W. Bush</ref>. He said Bush promises to be the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Superman">Superman</ref> fighting for the justice. "However, we have the red kryptonite", Chavez said.
<list type="unordered"><item>Chavez defended the control over the media by the State. "The children cannot see this violence and the media cannot transmit calls to the terrorism", he added. </item></list>
<list type="unordered"><item>Chavez met with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Landless%20Workers'%20Movement">Landless Workers' Movement (MST)</ref>. The Brazilian Minister of Agrarian Development, Miguel Rossetto, said that the presence of the president of Venezuela, Hugo Chávez, is a homage to the people who try to construct Brazil in a different form.</item></list>
Miguel Rossetto signed, with Chávez, a protocol of intentions for the interchange and reproduction of native seeds for the Brazilian and Venezuelan agriculturists. The Minister and the President also signed a document that initiates the discussion about the creation of the Latin American School of AgroEcology in Brazil, following the model executed in Venezuela.
<head id="Fifth_day:_The_closing_of_the_World_Social_Forum_2005">Fifth day: The closing of the World Social Forum 2005</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, January 31, 2005</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Venezuelan President Hugo Chavez said that the WSF is of paramount political importance. He participated of a conference with the Brazilian Minister of the Cities Olívio Dutra, the governor of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paraná">Paraná</ref> Robert Requião, the President of the CUT labour union Marine Luiz, and the managing director of the monthly periodical <hi rend="italic">Le Monde Diplomatique Ignacio Ramonet</hi>. </item></list>
<list type="unordered"><item>Activists protested against US President George W. Bush.</item></list>
<list type="unordered"><item>There was a farewell show, with musical presentations and of dance. </item></list>
</text>
