<text id="autogum_bio_doc305" title="Savatije Ljubibratić" shortTile="savatije-ljubibratic" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-07-23" dateModified="2019-09-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Savatije_Ljubibrati%C4%87" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Savatije Ljubibratić</head>Not to be confused with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Savatije_Sokolović">Savatije Sokolović</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Savatije Ljubibratić</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serbian_Cyrillic_alphabet">Serbian Cyrillic</ref>: Саватије Љубибратић; fl. Piva, c. 1660—Topla, January, 1716) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serbian_Orthodox">Serbian Orthodox</ref> bishop and metropolitan, and the caretaker of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dragović_monastery">Dragović monastery</ref>.</p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>Ljubibratić was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Piva,_Montenegro">Piva</ref>, and belonged to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ruđić">Ruđić</ref> brotherhood,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEVeselinović196678-1">[1]</ref> at a time when the region was part of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman Empire</ref>. Ljubibratić, as many of his relatives, took monastic vows and later became a bishop.</p>
<head>Bishop of Herzegovina</head>
<p>Since 1687, he was a notable participant in the struggle <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman–Venetian_Wars">against the Ottomans, in Venetian support</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEVeselinović196678-1">[1]</ref> On 10 December 1687, he was present at Tvrdoš when priest and vojvoda Vukašin Gavrilović with his people came from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nikšić">Nikšić</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMihić1975112-2">[2]</ref> In 1690, he and the Tvrdoš brotherhood (including his brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stefan_Ljubibratić">Stefan</ref>) left <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trebinje">Trebinje</ref> for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herceg_Novi">Herceg Novi</ref>, fleeing the Ottomans, where they renovated the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Savina_Monastery,_Montenegro">Savina Monastery</ref>.</p>
<p>The Republic of Venice recognized Savatije's episcopal rule as Metropolitan (<hi rend="italic">vladika</hi>) of Zahumlje in Novi in 1695.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEKomar2001-3">[3]</ref> His ecclesiastical province stretched over "newly conquered areas".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEKomar2001-3">[3]</ref> The Serbian Church made the first steps to establish an independent Serb municipality in the region of old <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dračevica_(župa)">Dračevica</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEKomar2001-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Bishop of Dalmatia</head>
<p>Metropolitan Nikodim Busović, the bishop "of all Orthodox Serbs on the Dalmatian continent", was banished from Dalmatia in early 1705. On the demand of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Krka_monastery">Krka monastery</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Krupa_monastery">Krupa monastery</ref>, Ljubibratić was appointed Nikodim's office by the Venetian government.  Ljubibratić had taken this office in spite of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Melentije_Tipaldi">Melentije Tipaldi</ref> (1658–1730), the Greek-Catholic bishop who was a driving force of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uniatism">Uniatism</ref>; and continued the struggle against the Uniatism of Serbs in Dalmatia.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Radojcic-4">[4]</ref> Tipaldi greatly undermined against Ljubibratić, so far that the Church Synod in Constantinople condemned Tipaldi and excluded him from the Orthodox Church as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Traitor">traitor</ref>; with this support, Ljubibratić was able to continue his service.</p>
<p>In July 1705 Metropolitan Savatije Ljubibratić came back from the pilgrimage from Palestine and from the time his vessel entered the quarantine station called <hi rend="italic">lazaretto</hi>, he was subjected to the sanitary procedure by the staff of lazaretto in Herceg Novi as every other traveler aboard. After a lapse of 15 days he was released. There he proceeded to build a bridge, churches and restore others. Savatije is credited for restoring <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Savina_Monastery,_Montenegro">Savina Monastery, Montenegro</ref>.</p>
<p>Savatije and his brother Stevan became friends with colonel Mihailo Miloradović,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMihić1975112-2">[2]</ref> who had along with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metropolitan_Danilo_I_Petrović-Njegoš">Metropolitan Danilo I Petrović-Njegoš</ref> been recruited by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_I_of_Russia">Peter I of Russia</ref> to incite rebellion in Herzegovina against the Ottomans in 1710–11 (during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pruth_River_Campaign">Pruth River Campaign</ref>).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>Ljubibratić successfully opposed the orders of the Catholic <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Curia">curia</ref></hi> against the Orthodox believers in Dalmatia.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Radojcic-4">[4]</ref> Savatije declined Venetian official <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ivan_Burović">Ivan Burović</ref>'s offers to begin Uniatism, Burović having sent the Catholic bishop of Kotor and his relative <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vićentije_Zmajević">Vićentije Zmajević</ref> from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Perast">Perast</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEKomar2001-3">[3]</ref> He strengthened ties with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serbian_Patriarchate_of_Peć">Serbian Patriarchate of Peć</ref>, and as a result of that, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serbian_Patriarch_Mojsije_I">Serbian Patriarch Mojsije I</ref> visited Dalmatia in 1714, after Ljubibratić's request; this visit proved important for the preservation of Orthodoxy and somewhat paused pressure on the Orthodox church in Dalmatia.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Radojcic-4">[4]</ref> Savatije Ljubibratić died in January 1716, in the village of Topla, near Herceg Novi.</p>
<p>His successor was his brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stevan_Ljubibratić">Stevan Ljubibratić</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEKomar2001-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Legacy</head>
<p>He was one of the more successful Serb national leaders of the 18th century.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEKomar2001-3">[3]</ref></p>
</text>
