<text id="autogum_reddit_doc012" title="GTA V - From Game install to Account Suspension" shortTile="gta-v--game-install" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-05-31" dateModified="2018-05-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8nk9x7" speakerList="#Medic017" speakerCount="1">
<head>GTA V - From Game install to Account Suspension</head>
<sp who="#Medic017">
<p>Let me explain a little about myself. I am a 50 year old retired firefighter/paramedic. I retired 2 years ago and moved from the Northeast US to the Southwest Florida to help an elderly parent. GTA filled a lot of my "down time", in between caring for my father. It is not like he needs 100&#37; assistance, he needs pretty much takes care of himself, outside of cooking and maintaining the household. So that provides me with A LOT of time for gaming and such. My story started 2 years ago when I moved. I had GTA installed on my old gaming laptop, but did not do a lot in the way of playing, especially online, due to my work schedule. (between 4 jobs, I worked on average of 80-90 hrs per week.) So when I retired I decided to get back into GTA V and Online, especially since I enjoyed all of the past titles from GTA III on up. Well I was a Lvl 79 online, from August 2016 to April 2018 I increased that Lvl to 879. I had Garages, Executive Office, with the 3 garages, a Bunker, a Hangar, a Facility, a Motorcycle Clubhouse with all 5 businesses, 5 warehouses, a yacht and all the cars, boats, planes, helicopters, and motorcycles I needed. I also have 167 million in GTA$. (Yes I did buy Sharkcards. I roughly spent about $400-$450 in Sharkcards.) Well low and behold, on April 19, 2018, while I was AFK taking care of something in my household, I returned to see that my account, Medic017, was suspended for 30 days. The only event of note was I was "hot lapping" a track, Greenwich Meantime, practicing with a recent car that I purchased, Flash GT. I dropped into a public lobby. Within a few minutes of being in this lobby another player, lvl 100\~ decided it would be a good idea to try and kill me with his weaponized tampa. I drove away tryin to put some distance between us. He chased me. I then used a sticky bomb and blew him up. Not thinking much about it at the time, he spawned a Hunter Helicopter (he was in the area between the scrap yard and Maze Arena, wish I had that session recorded), and tried to blow me up with barrage missiles. I hid under a bridge and he missed me repeatedly, striking the bridge and not me. Well because he had bad aim, he accused me of modding. I told him that I was not, his aim sucked. I was able to destroy his helicopter with explosive rounds from my MK II Heavy Sniper, he then spawed a Khanjali tank. I fled to the Maze Tower, went to the roof, requested my Akula Helicopter. Then parachuted to the spawn point in the LS River. Once flying I found him, and then blew him up with the Akula, and went into stealth mode. I he then started talk crap in the in game text, I told him that I was legit Lvl 879 with over 4900 hrs of game play time over the last 1-1/2 especially. He kept calling me a modder. He then commented "good luck connecting", I then killed him one more time and left the session. Within two hours of that event was when the first suspension hit. Well no worries, or so I thought. I had a second account set up in the meantime. I am part of a "somewhat serious race crew", FNFR, and we get together on Friday Nights (EST) for our Fun Runs. Definitely not serious racing, just a group of people that enjoy racing, chatting up a storm while doing so, and enjoying our favorite beverages. So I raced with the second account. I did do a previous <ref target="https://reddit.com/">Reddit.com</ref> post to try and let the information out that innocent people are being suspended/banned by Rockstar. I was chastised by some members of the community because I offered no proof, and those members contended that I was a modder and that was the only reason I would be banned. (I used to think the same thing, until this happened to me). Saturday morning I woke, logged on and was suspended on my second account, an hour after I logged off the night before. I was clueless. I am not a GTA Modder. I looked into it back in the Summer of 2016, when I started back on GTA, and found that it was frowned upon. So I played legit. Wanting to play the game, I purchased another CD Key from a known, and legit site. I purchased with an 8 million Megladon Shark Card. I did the prolog, started Online and was banned within two hours. At this time, and after talking to some friends I made online through my crew, I then did a Windows 10 Reset, wiping all my files and reformatting both my hard drives. Getting another new CD Key with another Megladon Sharkcard (the wesite had them discounted), I tried again. This account a played a little longer. I managed to play for about 4 hours before I was suspeneded. So I spent the remaining time playing Storymode and trying to achieve 100&#37; completion. After trying different suggestions, including a VPN, I tried again and again. Both were suspended. Now my original 30 day suspension on the first 3 accounts ended. My first account, where I had all the money spent in Sharkcards started with 47.7 million after the suspension, the second account had no money, and the third had 8 million because of the Megladon Card. I logged in with the account with no money, on my old computer. Figured I give that a try. Well low and behold, Permanently Banned! Contact Rockstar Support through Chat, after a lengthy conversation with him, I was assured that Rockstar only bans accounts, not IP Addresses, or HWIDs. He advised me to perform a clean GTA install and that would resolve the issue. Sent me the Rockstar Article, how to perform a clean install, and what directories I needed to ensure were deleted before the reinstall. Being helpful he offered to walk me through the process. I declined and thanked him. I then deleted the installation with Windows. Ensure the listed directories were deleted, made sure there was nothing in my Recycle Bin. And then downloaded and reinstalled GTA. After the total time of 4 hours I was back up and running. I logged in with the first account with 8 million that came off suspension. I played for over 11 hours between two days with not even a hiccup. That was when I decided to try my luck with my "primary account" Medic017 and the 47.7 million. (I wanted to take advantage of some of the discounts and sales in the in games stores). I logged in. Started at lvl 1, worked my way up to lvl 7, was finally able to purchase in game properties. I purchased my Maze Tower Office with garages, the Farmhouse Bunker, and a Fort Zancudo Hangar. I was about two hours into game play when I received the notification that this account was Permanently Banned! I contacted Rockstar Support through Chat again. All they could assure me was that it was a "legit ban", but for security reasons they could not tell me the specifics. AND I lost all the GTA$ that I had on this character. I tried logging in to the previous character, MistaVe, and found that that account was also Permanently Banned, at the same time! It was not even online. Rockstar Support Agent, also assured me that Rockstar does not ban IP Addresses, or Computer HWIDs, but only accounts. I implored him to find out what the is actual problem. How can I fix an issue on my end, if I do not know what to fix, right? Again, he could not tell me because of Rockstar's Security Policy. SMH. I told him that I was going to perform a full system reinstall, he told me that was not necessary that all I had to do was perform a full reinstall of GTA. When I told him that I already did, and I copied the GTA V folder to save game progress, he suggested that I did not do it "properly" stating that I should have only copied the GTA V\\Profiles folder for that. Ok, so I admitted that I may have done an "incorrect" reinstall of the game. After more discussion with my friends online that have more computer knowledge then I do. It was suggested to perform a little experiment. so.... This week I conducted a little experiment. I did a full system wipe of my gaming laptop. I repartitioned the hard drives, reinstalled Windows 10 from a USB drive. I went as so fast as to update the computer BIOS and create a new Outlook E-mail Account so my old gaming laptop, and this computer were not logging in from the same account. After I installed Windows 10, I then began streaming on Twitch. Here is a link to the saved videos on my Twitch Channel: <ref target="https://www.twitch.tv/medic017/videos/all">https://www.twitch.tv/medic017/videos/all</ref>. The only thing that I'm mission was my last hours of game play after I joined the public session. I did not realize that the streams stopped for some reason. As I am new to streaming I had some difficulty setting it up in the beginning, I apologize. It is definitely not professional. However, it clearly shows that the only thing I did was play the game. I worked my character up from Lvl 1 to lvl 40 by doing Racing, Missions, the new Dispatch Missions with friends, Survivals, Daily Objectives, and helping a friend do sales in a public lobby (that one of the last things I did, with the exception of finish my last Daily Objective with a friend). Of the time that I spend online I did 95&#37; of my time in an Invite Only Session. Rockstar Support does not offer that. The agent would not answer my questions directly, kept citing Rockstar Security Policy. I am at a loss. Rockstar, a multi-million dollar corporation, with another game title getting ready to be released is having issues with this online game. They seem to be not admitting they have an issue with the game, or their detection system. They keep hiding behind the generic e-mails, advising you that you can be banned for a list of reasons, but will not be specific as to which one. They refuse to provide any customer support on this issue, dancing around the issue with preprogrammed responses. I am at a loss.</p>
</sp>
</text>
