<text id="autogum_academic_doc123" title="The Changing Role of CO2 in the Transition to a Circular Economy: Review of Carbon Sequestration Projects" shortTile="changing-role-co" author="Pavel Tcvetkov, Alexey Cherepovitsyn, Sergey Fedoseev" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5834/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Literature Review</head><head> 2.1. Analysis of CO2 Sequestration Options</head>
<p>
There are various studies devoted to the analysis of the considered sequestration options. Singh et al. analyzed different power generation options (coal and natural gas) with and without CCS. The results showed that despite the reduction in CO2 emissions, fossil-fuel-based energy generation is associated with other negative environmental impacts that must be taken into account. Significant reduction in CO2 emission was confirmed by Akash et al.; however, this study also showed that the use of CCS in power generation affects construction expenditure, and consequently, the cost of electricity caused by the lack of additional economic effects. Odenberger et al. showed that various CCS options (offshore and onshore storage) could have a significant impact on the development of energy in Europe in the coming decades. However, it is noted that CCS has serious competition from alternative low carbon energy generation options. Moreover, Pihkola et al. concluded that CO2 utilization may become a more attractive option for industry, despite the potential for CCS to take a certain position in the energy strategy of Finland. </p>

<p>An analysis of the current CCUS-enhanced oil recovery (EOR) status in China was carried out by Zhen and Lijiao. It was concluded that CCUS-EOR is the optimal CO2 sequestration option for China; however, its further development requires careful state regulation. The economic assessment of CCUS-enhanced coalbed methane (ECBM) technology was carried out by Yu et al.. The authors identified key factors that have the most significant impact on the economic efficiency of such projects. An approach to assessing the technical and economic efficiency of CCUS-ECBM projects is proposed by Kim et al.. The results showed that coalbed methane can become a serious competitor to a natural gas. An assessment of the efficiency of geothermal energy production (GEP) using CCUS was carried out by Buscheck et al.. However, because of the early stage of CCUS-GEP development, further research in this area is required to confirm the economic value of such projects. </p>

<p>Different CCU options were evaluated by Schlögl et al.. A visible emphasis is placed on the need to improve the regulation system of CO2-based industries, which is also confirmed by other studies. The business model for power-to-methanol (combined CCU and renewable energy technologies) projects was proposed by González-Aparicio et al.. Economic assessment showed that this combination may become a so-called “win-win” solution, which could be competitive in the energy market. The study by Muthuraj and Mekonnen showed the results of a technology readiness level assessment for CO2-based co-polymers and polymers blend (CCU) manufacturing. The authors noted that these technologies are at an early stage of development; however, in the near future they could be used in many areas, including the processing of plastic wastes. Chauvy et al. also described the assessment of various CCU technology readiness levels and a novel method for selecting optimal short- and medium-term CCU options. </p>

<p>Cuéllar-Franca and Azapagic analyzed 27 studies related to CCS, CCUS, and CCU to compare the environmental impact of each option. The authors concluded that the positive global warming mitigation potential of CCU is much higher than CCS and CCUS. At the same time, the negative environmental impacts of CCS and CCUS (acidification, eutrophication, toxicity potential) are much higher compared to most CCU technologies. Zhang et al. proposed a roadmap for the implementation of various CO2 sequestration options in China. The authors concluded that the most effective options for the Chinese economy are CCUS-EOR and onshore saline aquifers. The study by Li et al. was also devoted to China and showed that large-scale deployment of sequestration technologies will require significant improvements in regulatory frameworks. </p>

<p>Viebahn et al. described an ecological and economic assessment of CCS (offshore and onshore) and CCUS-ECBM development potential. The results showed that the success of sequestration projects significantly depends on the successful experience of developed countries in this area. There are also a number of constraints, such as the high cost of technology, competition from renewable energy, and the long-term implementation period. Another study by the same authors was based on the same methodology but aimed at China, and also included CCUS-EGR and CCUS-EOR. Key factors for the successful deployment of such projects are the presence of state support, as well as improvement of the methodology for assessing CO2 storage potential. The relevance of such studies was also noted by Peck et al., who showed a number of decision points that help to determine optimal methods of CO2-EOR storage capacity estimation. The valuation of CCS and CCUS was carried out by Wilberforce et al.. The results showed that despite the significant pace of development, as well as government support, such projects still have limited competitiveness in the energy market. </p>
</text>
