<text id="autogum_bio_doc227" title="Francis Barrett (occultist)" shortTile="francis-barrett-occultist" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2004-12-27" dateModified="2019-04-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_Barrett_%28occultist%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Francis Barrett (occultist)</head><p><hi rend="bold">Francis Barrett</hi> (born probably in London around 1770–1780) was an English <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Occultist">occultist</ref>.</p>
<head>Background</head>
<p>Barrett, an Englishman, claimed himself to be a student of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chemistry">chemistry</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metaphysics">metaphysics</ref> and natural occult <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philosophy">philosophy</ref>. He was known to be an extreme <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eccentricity_(behavior)">eccentric</ref> who gave lessons in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magic_(paranormal)">magical</ref> arts in his apartment and fastidiously translated <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kabbalah">Kabbalistic</ref> and other ancient texts into English, such as von Welling's work, <hi rend="italic">Philosophy of The Universe</hi> circa 1735, from German (1801). According to his biographer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_X._King">Francis X. King</ref>, Barrett's parents were humble folk married in the parish of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Martin's_in_the_Fields">St. Martin's in the Fields</ref> on September 29, 1772.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head><hi rend="italic">The Magus</hi></head>
Main article: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Magus_(Barrett_book)">The Magus (Barrett book)</ref>
<p>Barrett was enthusiastic about reviving interest in the occult arts, and published a magical textbook called <hi rend="italic">The Magus</hi>. It was a compilation,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> almost entirely consisting of selections from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heinrich_Cornelius_Agrippa">Cornelius Agrippa</ref>'s <hi rend="italic">Three Books of Occult Philosophy</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Fourth Book of Occult Philosophy</hi> attributed to Agrippa, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Turner_(writer)">Robert Turner</ref>'s 1655 translation of the <hi rend="italic">Heptameron of Peter of Abano</hi>. Barrett made modifications and modernized spelling and syntax. Possibly influencing the novelist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Bulwer-Lytton">Edward Bulwer-Lytton</ref>, the book gained little other notice until it influenced <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eliphas_Levi">Eliphas Levi</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The Magus</hi> dealt with the natural magic of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herbs">herbs</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rock_(geology)">stones</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magnetism">magnetism</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amulet">talismanic magic</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alchemy">alchemy</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Numerology">numerology</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Classical_element">elements</ref>, and biographies of famous <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adept">adepts</ref> from history.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The Magus</hi> also served as an advertising tool. In it Barrett sought interested people wanting to help form his magic circle. An advertisement in <hi rend="italic">The Magus</hi> (Vol. 2, p.140) refers to an otherwise unknown school founded by Barrett.</p>
<p>According to the advertisement:</p>
<p>The Author of this Work respectfully informs those that are curious in the studies of Art and Nature, especially of Natural and Occult Philosophy, Chemistry, Astrology, etc., etc., that, having been indefatigable in his researches in those sublime Sciences; of which he has treated at large in this book, that he gives private instructions and lectures upon any of the above-mentioned Sciences; in the course of which he will discover many curious and rare experiments.</p>
<p>Those who become Students will be initiated into the choicest operations of Natural Philosophy, Natural Magic, the Cabbala, Chemistry, the Talismanic Arts, Hermetic Philosophy, Astrology, Physiognomy, etc., etc. Likewise they will acquire the knowledge of the Rites, Mysteries, Ceremonies and Principles of the ancient Philosophers, Magi, Cabbalists, and Adepts, etc.</p>
<p>The Purpose of this school (which will consist of no greater number than Twelve Students) being to investigate the hidden treasures of Nature; to bring the Mind to a contemplation of the Eternal Wisdom; to promote the discovery of whatever may conduce to the perfection of Man; the alleviating the miseries and calamities of this life, both in respect of ourselves and others; the study of morality and religion here, in order to secure to ourselves felicity hereafter; and, finally, the promulgation of whatever may conduce to the general happiness and welfare of mankind.</p>
<head>Views</head>
<p>When writing about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Witchcraft">witches</ref> Barrett stated that he did not believe that their power to torment or kill by enchantment, touch or by using a wax <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Effigy">effigy</ref> came from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Satan">Satan</ref>. He claimed if <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Devil">the Devil</ref> wanted to kill a man guilty of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seven_deadly_sins">deadly sin</ref>, he did not need a witch as an intermediary.</p>
<p>Barrett's belief in magical power might be summed up this way:</p>
<p>The magical power is in the inward or inner man. A certain proportion of the inner man longs for the external in all things. When the person is in the appropriate disposition an appropriate connection between man and object can be attained.</p>
</text>
