<text id="autogum_academic_doc125" title="An Environmental Health Typology as a Contributor to Sustainable Regional Urban Planning: The Case of the Metropolitan Region of São Paulo (MRSP)" shortTile="environmental-health" author="Natasha Ceretti Maria, Antônio Ralph Medeiros-Sousa, Anne Dorothée Slovic" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5800/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Material and Methods</head><head> Selection and Construction of Indicators</head>
<p>
Secondary data was obtained from documentary research in public institutions and bibliographical reviews about the theme. Indicators were selected from governmental open-access databases such as the Brazilian Institute of Geography and Statistics (IBGE), the Department of the Brazilian Unified Health System (DATASUS), and the São Paulo State Foundation of Data Analysis (SEADE). </p>

<p>The framework for selection and arrangement of the indicators was based on the matrix of environmental health indicators developed in partnership with the United Nations Environment Program (UNEP), the World Health Organization (WHO), and the USA Environment Program (USEPA), known as the DPSEEA framework. The matrix establishes a demand flow and pressure for natural resources and changes in the ecosystem, enabling a broad observation of the factors that influence human health and well-being. Its multiple dimensions allow the analysis of the driving forces (D), the environmental pressure (P) that influence the state/situation of the environment (S), modulating the exposures (E) to diseases, which are considered the effect (EF) in the cycle. Thus, this systemic and ranked set of indicators focuses on health and environmental issues, bringing options for different and strategic actions (A) that can be executed at different levels and in different ways of prevention and control. </p>

<p>According to the environmental indicators, the manual of the Brazilian Ministry of Health, the model proposed by the WHO, appeared to be suitable for the rational basis exhibited in an integrated matrix of indicators conjoining socioenvironmental and health issues (<figure>Figure 2</figure>). </p>

<p>For this project, four categories of indicators were selected: sanitation, land use, air quality, and forest coverage. These categories were chosen based on human pressure and their influence on urban environmental quality such as infrastructure, air and water quality, solid waste management, and prevalence of areas covered by natural vegetation. Each selected indicator expresses different socioenvironmental conditions in MRSP that aim at specific demands when quality and sustainability were considered. </p>

<p>In addition to the DPSEEA Matrix, for the selection of relevant indicators that fit the MRSP metropolitan context, the priority metropolitan themes expressed in the MRSP IUDP (Integrated Urban Development Plan) were considered. The Plan considers metropolitan issues that go beyond municipal boundaries. Examples are the use of water resources considering the possibilities of integrating the production systems and the projections of demand, availability of electricity, infrastructure barriers to serve the population and support economic activity. With regard to sanitation and the environment, issues such as sanitary sewage, macrodrainage, solid waste disposal, and environmental damage were highlighted. </p>

<p>The DPSEEA approach, adopted by World Health Organization, has been applied in Brazil by the General Coordination of Environmental Health Surveillance of the Health Surveillance Secretariat of the Ministry of Health (CGVAM / SVS / MS) since the late 1990s. The construction of indicators that point to the interrelationships of environmental changes and health situation are at the origin of the process of institutionalization of environmental health surveillance within the Health Sector, from the 20th to the 21st century, initially by Decree No. 3.450/2000 of the Presidency of the Republic, establishing in the former National Center for Epidemiology (Cenepi) the management of the national system of epidemiological and environmental surveillance and, subsequently, through Normative Instruction SVS No. 1 of 2005, which regulated the National Environmental Health Surveillance Subsystem (SINVSA).Brazil was a pioneer in adapting this conceptual framework and in the systematic and validated use of indicators that help manage environmental health problems. </p>

<p>Table 1 presents a set of indicators used by environmental health, organized according to the DPSEEA model: </p>

<p>This model allows the integrated analysis of environmental health within an economic and social context and can be applied to subsidize the monitoring of sustainability conditions at the regional and municipal levels. Stauber et al. 2018 points out that applying the DPSEEA matrix structure can allow to make more focused decisions around key socioenvironmental issues by identifying areas for intervention. Thus, achieving improvements in the health and well-being of the cities requires better tracking and understanding of the role of indicators, especially in urban environments. Inserted in the logic presented, the application of the DPSEEA matrix was the basis of this study to select indicators that operationalize the concept of environmental health. </p>

<p>According to Sobral and Freitas (2010), it is important to highlight that the DPSEEA model of indicators should be used as an auxiliary tool of the social determination model of health, because although it allows an integrated view of the indicators, by itself it cannot contemplate all the complexity of interrelations of the dimensions that determine the process of social production of health-disease and its inequalities between social groups. </p>
</text>
