<text id="autogum_academic_doc710" title="Doing Good Better: Impure Altruism in Green Apparel Advertising" shortTile="doing-good-better" author="So  Young Song, Youn-Kyung Kim" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5762/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Literature Review</head><head> 2.1. Green Advertising Appeal Type</head>
<p>
Green advertising is advertising that discourses on the impact of a green product on the biophysical environment, promotes a green lifestyle, or shows corporate social responsibility. To meet these criteria, firms can uniquely position advertising messages to elicit consumers’ favorable perceptions of the benefit of a green product and its brand. In this study, we use two categories of green appeals to explain the complex mechanism of why an individual engages in sustainable purchases and to illustrate the conception of impure altruism: the message orientation (altercentric versus egocentric) and the beneficiary type (earth versus human).  </p>

<head> 2.1.1. Message Orientation: Altercentric Versus Egocentric</head>
<p>
The first ad category is a message orientation. It consists of altercentric versus egocentric message appeal types. Altercentric appeals focus on how others benefit from prosocial behavior. The sentiments such as “we can help others” and “we can prevent abuse to others” would be examples of ad messages. Generally, altercentric appeals are effective at promoting honorable or benevolent behavior among individuals with altruistic motives. In comparison, egocentric appeals focus on how the behavior benefits individuals propelled by receiving recognition or feeling good about themselves, for example, “our product will make you feel good about yourself.” Research suggests that egocentric appeals can be viewed as more valuable among individuals with self-oriented motives than altercentric appeals. We therefore postulate that the types of perceived benefits change according to the altercentric or egocentric orientation of the advertising appeal.  </p>

<head> 2.1.2. Beneficiary Type: Human Versus Earth</head>
<p>
Research in altruism shows that the norm of reciprocity in which an individual can expect to receive reciprocal benefits from his or her altruistic act can motivate prosocial behavior. Literature in sustainable behavior further suggests that consumers perceive a greater benefit from acts that help people compared to acts that help the environment. This difference can be interpreted as in-group favoritism toward humans. As a result, advertising messages about human beneficiaries (e.g., “when you buy our product, you support children’s education”) can facilitate a more positive evaluation and higher reciprocal value positioning than messages about the planet or environmental beneficiaries (e.g., keeping the environment clean). Thus, we propose that green advertising can be more effective when advertisements emphasize humans over the earth.  </p>

<head> 2.2. Altruistic and Egoistic Motivation</head>
<p>
Motivation can be described as the reason for the behavior behind consumers’ product choices to meet their needs. Motivations for behaving sustainably can be categorized into two psychological states: altruism and egoism. Altruism describes “true” philanthropic motivation, in which one responds with empathic concern for others without seeking a personal benefit. Batson defines altruism as “a motivational state with the ultimate goal of increasing another’s welfare” (p. 20). Thus, an individual who purchases green products only to enhance the wellbeing of others falls into the altruistic category. By contrast, egoism is “a motivational state with the ultimate goal of increasing one’s own welfare”. As such, egoism is achieved when one pursues actions that benefit oneself or that offer personal rewards. Many psychological theories have asserted that all human motivation is inherently selfish. Reflecting this egoistic view in sustainable behavior, when an individual seeks to attain self-gratification through serving his or her self-interests and welfare through purchasing green products (e.g., seeking aesthetic uniqueness of Fair Trade products, choosing organic children’s wear and natural food for health and safety reasons), this individual falls into the egoistic category.  </p>

<p>An argument over whether self-interest or other interests motivates altruistic behavior has been ongoing for the last two decades. Scholars disagree about the existence of true altruism because others’ welfare is not easily one’s ultimate goal without expectations of reciprocity. For example, Batson argues: “Even if it were possible for a person to be motivated to increase another’s welfare, such a person would be interested in attaining this desired goal and would experience pleasure in doing so” (p. 21). Cialdini et al. counter that “the conditions that lead to empathic concern also lead to a greater sense of self–other overlap, raising the possibility that helping under these conditions is not selfless but is also directed toward the self” (p. 481). To explain this mixed category of altruistic and egoistic motivations, we borrow Andreoni’s theory of warm-glow giving and explore impure altruism as a psychological phenomenon that connects altruism to egoistic good feelings. </p>
</text>
