<text id="autogum_interview_doc570" title="part1_Interview with Mathew Njenga, City Council candidate for Wards 2 &amp; 6 in Brampton, Canada" shortTile="partinterview-mathew" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-05" dateModified="2008-10-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Mathew_Njenga%2C_City_Council_candidate_for_Wards_2_%26_6_in_Brampton%2C_Canada" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Much of Brampton's existing council is quite seasoned in the civic political process. What could you bring to the table as a "rookie", above and beyond the current roster of councillors?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> The one thing that I would do differently from the incumbent is to make sure that I involve the community in the decision making process and educate them about municipal services. Wards 2 and 6 where I am a candidate have the biggest influx of immigrants in Brampton. I had a chance to meet most of them over the summer and they know very little about the city they live in. Therefore, they presume that all is fine and that everything will fall in place. As a councilor in wards 2 and 6, my role would be to educate the community so that they can become more pro-active in helping us deliver the services that are most suitable for them. Most people were also quick to point out that it was the first time anyone from the municipal government had actually knocked at their door. If elected, I would make sure to close that gap which currently exists between the majority of the residence of wards 2 and 6 and there councilor. I believe to closing this gap requires a fresh pair of eyes and that is what I intend to bring to the table as an elected councilor.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> The Rose Theatre recently launched. What are your thoughts on this facility? Have you had a chance to tour it yet? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> The Rose Theatre is a magnificent building and it's a step in the right direction. Brampton Downtown needs several other projects that would attract business and improve the general profile of the city. So often, residents of Brampton have to commute to Toronto if they want to catch a good show and have a relaxing evening. If we can offer that right here in Brampton, then we can keep the dollars within the local economy creating Jobs.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> The province has strongly encouraged the development of high-density residences near the downtown. Do these buildings fit in with your vision of the downtown? How much say should other levels of government have in urban planning? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> All levels of government have to work together as the same taxpayer funds them all. I believe that high-density residents in the downtown location make sense given the proximity to the transit routes planned for the future. This would also bring more business in an area that really needs rejuvenation.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How do you feel about Brampton's rate of expansion? Council recently capped the annual amount of new development; do you agree completely with this decision, would you have slowed development even further, or not have imposed a cap at all? </p>
</text>
