<text id="autogum_reddit_doc080" title="I wanted to share something I have been writing the past year for my brother Nick" shortTile="wanted-share-something" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-04-30" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8g4011" speakerList="#peaceandlove5, #throwaway921987" speakerCount="2">
<head>I wanted to share something I have been writing the past year for my brother Nick</head>
<sp who="#peaceandlove5">
<p>I just celebrated the life of my older brother Nick and grieved this past year without him on Saturday . It’s been a very confusing and difficult ride the past year but I wanted to share something I wrote and I encourage anybody going through a loss as great as I experienced to write out your feelings. On April 28th, 2017 I received a phone call from my dad while I was at work. I received a phone call that I had spent a good majority of my adult life preparing for. But the thing that took my breath away and knocked me down the stairwell into a pile of cardboard was why he had died. My brother Nick, my big brother. My fellow blue eyed buddy had taken his own life. I have never known sorrow so deep as I did when I lost Nick. Your spelling was atrocious but your heart...your heart was bigger than I think even your understanding. In your mind you always tried to do the right thing, but sometimes in reality it wasn’t always right. You fought my first bully and got me through my last breakup and so much in between. I always wanted to be like you. You were fiercely and i reiterate FIERCELY loyal. You stuck up for yourself and for your family. Everyone knew your name. I thought you were just the coolest. For whatever reason that I will never get an answer to, you thought this world was better off without you. I disagree. Living with you in my life was exponentially better than this past year without you. I think about you every day. Whether it’s your picture greeting me in the car in the morning or going to work and reminding myself why I chose to change careers and how much I have accomplished since your passing. Because of you, I have pushed myself to be a better person. I have put myself outside my comfort zone so I can finally start living. Your death brought me a new life. </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#throwaway921987">
<p>This brought me to tears... the mere thought of losing my brother, the person whom I love the most on this earth is too much. But then by the end, I was smiling. This is beautiful. Thank you for sharing and for spreading a little bit of hope and joy. Your strength is amazing. Wishing you all the best.</p>
</sp>
</text>
