<text id="autogum_news_doc646" title="Adele and David Bowie each win five Grammys" shortTile="adele-david-bowie" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-02-14" dateModified="2019-10-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Adele_and_David_Bowie_each_win_five_Grammys" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Adele and David Bowie each win five Grammys</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 15, 2017</hi></p>
<p>On Sunday, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UK">British</ref> singer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adele">Adele</ref> won five <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grammy%20Award">Grammy Awards</ref> at the 59th Grammy Awards event in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Los_Angeles">Los Angeles</ref>. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20Bowie">David Bowie</ref> posthumously won five Grammys.</p>
<p>Adele won Song of the Year, Best Pop Solo and Record of the Year for her song <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hello%20(Adele%20song)">Hello</ref></hi>, and Album of the Year for her album <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/25%20(Adele%20album)">25</ref></hi>, becoming the first singer to win the Song of the Year, Record of the Year, and Album of the Year twice.</p>
<p>David Bowie was nominated in five categories — three for his album <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blackstar%20(album)">Blackstar</ref></hi> in Best Alternative Music Album, Best Engineered Album, Non-Classical, and Best Rock Performance; and two for his song <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blackstar%20(song)">Blackstar</ref></hi>, Best Rock Song and Best Rock Performance. Days after releasing his 25th album, <hi rend="italic">Blackstar</hi>, Bowie passed away in January 2016, due to cancer. Before <hi rend="italic">Blackstar</hi>, Bowie won a Grammy for his music video <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jazzin'%20for%20Blue%20Jean">Jazzin' for Blue Jean</ref></hi>, and Lifetime Achievement Award in 2006, never winning the award in a major category before.</p>
<p>In the event, singer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bruno%20Mars">Bruno Mars</ref> paid tribute to music icon <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prince%20(musician)">Prince</ref>, replicating style, costumes, and guitar of Prince's. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minneapolis">Minneapolis</ref>-based funk band <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Time%20(band)">The Time</ref>, who had performed with Prince, paid tribute to the singer who passed away in April at the age of 57. Adele, in her performance, paid tribute to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/George_Michael">George Michael</ref>. While performing, Adele stopped, swore, and restarted. She later apologised, saying "I am sorry for swearing and I am sorry for starting again, I can't mess this up for him[...] I am sorry, I can't."  British pop singer George Michael died on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Christmas_Day">Christmas Day</ref> of heart failure at the age of 53.</p>
<p>Adele was in tears while receiving Grammy for the Album of the Year. In her acceptance speech, she said, "But I can't possibly accept this award. And I'm very humbled and I'm very grateful and gracious. But my artist of my life is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beyoncé">Beyoncé</ref>. And this album to me, the '<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lemonade%20(Beyoncé%20album)">Lemonade</ref>' album, is just so monumental. Beyoncé, it's so monumental. And so well thought out, and so beautiful and soul-baring and we all got to see another side to you that you don't always let us see. And we appreciate that. And all us artists here, we fucking adore you. You are our light. And the way that you make me and my friends feel, the way you make my black friends feel, is empowering. And you make them stand up for themselves. And I love you." Other albums in the pool, besides <hi rend="italic">25</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Lemonade</hi>, were <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Justin_Bieber">Justin Bieber</ref>'s <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Purpose%20(Justin%20Bieber%20album)">Purpose</ref></hi>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drake%20(musician)">Drake</ref>'s <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Views%20(album)">Views</ref></hi>, and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A%20Sailor's%20Guide%20To%20Earth">A Sailor's Guide To Earth</ref></hi> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sturgill%20Simpson">Sturgill Simpson</ref>.</p>
<p>Earlier, while receiving award for the Record of the Year, Adele said, "My dream and my idol is Queen Bee [Beyoncé], and I adore you and you move my soul every single day and you have done for nearly seventeen years". Other songs nominated in the category were Beyoncé's <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Formation%20(song)">Formation</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Work%20(Rihanna%20song)">Work</ref></hi> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rihanna">Rihanna</ref>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/7%20Years%20(Lukas%20Graham%20song)">7 Years</ref></hi> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lukas%20Graham">Lukas Graham</ref>, and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stressed%20Out">Stressed Out</ref></hi> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TWENTY%20ØNE%20PILØTS">TWENTY ØNE PILØTS</ref>.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beyoncé">Beyoncé</ref> received the largest number of nominations for the event — nine — but she won only two. Her album <hi rend="italic">Lemonade</hi> won Best Urban Contemporary Album and her song Formation won Best Music Video.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chance%20The%20Rapper">Chance The Rapper</ref> won Best New Artist, and claimed Best Rap Performance for <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/No%20Problem%20(Chance%20the%20Rapper%20song)">No Problem</ref></hi> and Best Rap Album for <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coloring%20Book%20(mixtape)">Coloring Book</ref></hi>. Chance's songs were never sold, and were available for free on streaming services.</p>
<p>The new host <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James%20Corden">James Corden</ref> took a <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/pratfall">pratfall</ref> on the stairs while entering. The duo TWENTY ØNE PILØTS won Best Pop Duo/Group Performance for their song <hi rend="italic">Stressed Out</hi>. Upon announcement, they removed their pants to accept the award. Sharing an incident of watching Grammys before the duo was famous, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tyler%20Joseph">Tyler Joseph</ref> said <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Josh%20Dun">Josh Dun</ref> proposed if they were to receive a Grammy, they would receive it in their underpants as they were in underpants watching the award ceremony at the time. In his acceptance speech, he said, "I want everyone who's watching at home to know that you could be next. So watch out, because anyone from anywhere can do anything."</p>
</text>
