<text id="autogum_reddit_doc124" title="Out of 74 mounts only 4 can be earned in game? 95% of mounts you must pay for?" shortTile="out--mounts--earned" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-04-30" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8g1b9a" speakerList="#LordWolfs, #gorbash212" speakerCount="2">
<head>Out of 74 mounts only 4 can be earned in game? 95% of mounts you must pay for?</head>
<sp who="#LordWolfs">
<p>I was wondering are there any other mounts you can earn in game or are the 4 horses all you can get? Currently the majority of mounts released are all through Crown Crate. Look at the <ref target="https://www.reddit.com/r/elderscrollsonline/comments/8dasjl/crown_crate_statistical_analysis_how_much_do/">percentages</ref> they are absolutely dreadful. This is not a F2P game. You have to buy the game and the many expansions that go with it. I am totally fine with an in game Shop but at least be fair to us. Really feels like they don't care at all and just want to nickle and dime us as much as possible. When crown crates first came out you could easily get 400 Gems with 15 or so crates maybe 20. Now you are lucky to get 100 gems out of 15 crates. To the people saying the game needs to make money. I am not asking for the Store to be taken away just for them to treat us fairly. We do purchase the game and expansions so this is not a f2p game there is no reason we should be treated like its a f2p game. I don't mind having a store at all it is actually nice for quite a few things but there should be some methods to earn things in game as well. The mounts are just one example of many. Since 2014 the only mounts you can purchase in game are the same 4 from when the game was released. Also with recent rulings in other countries I imagine crown crates would be deemed gambling in those countries. Which it obviously is. I consider SWTOR to be one of the worst F2P models in the history of gaming yet somehow ESO is much worse in some ways. At least with SWTOR you can purchase the items from crates on the auction house from other people. On top of all this ESO is not a F2P game. Just because its been around a while does not mean we should not be able to talk about it. I respect peoples argument and defense of the Crown Crate system. But please realize we are allowed to critique it just as much as the people defending it.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#gorbash212">
<p>&gt; Really feels like they don't care at all and just want to nickle and dime us as much as possible. </p>
<p>You're saying this like zenimax have a problem with this. Obviously they sleep very well at night doing what they do. </p>
<p>Its far better to accept it is how it is and just tune out to what you don't like (or even 'thats not for me' like with player housing). Trying to chosen one anything zenimax holds makes you like it less. Simple fact.</p>
</sp>
</text>
