<text id="autogum_interview_doc626" title="part0_Adela Lupșe, outburst TV presenter, gives her side" shortTile="partadela-lupse-outburst" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-02-21" dateModified="2014-05-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Adela_Lup%C8%99e%2C_outburst_TV_presenter%2C_gives_her_side" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Adela Lupșe, outburst TV presenter, gives her side</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, February 22, 2009</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Adela Lupșe Image: Adela Lupșe.</caption></figure>
<p>The call-in quiz show is a staple of cheap programming throughout <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Europe">Europe</ref>. The format is simple: a question is displayed on screen, and callers phone in with their guesses – paying a premium rate to do so. The programs are often repetitive, the average question simple, the average prize small.</p>
<p>Once in a while, though, something unusual does happen.</p>
<p>On December 6 2008, Adela Lupșe, presenting the call-in quiz <hi rend="italic">Telepremii</hi> on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Naţional%20TV">Național TV</ref> on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Television%20in%20Romania">Romanian television</ref>, had what <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Daily%20Telegraph">The Daily Telegraph</ref></hi> described as a "tantrum on air". As the final prize became available, Ms Lupșe's show had no callers. Already excited, she began to shout. Throwing the telephone down on the studio floor and stomping on it, she admonished her viewers, "I want the telephone to ring now. Now. Call me now!"</p>
<p>Various reports in the English-speaking press went on to state that Ms Lupșe had been fired, or fired and re-hired, that the show had been fined heavily, forced to move to a late-evening time slot, or given an adults-only rating.</p>
<p>After presenting the broadcasts of this morning's call-in programs, including the same one she was supposedly fired from in January, Ms Lupșe spoke to Wikinews from her television studio in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Budapest">Budapest</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hungary">Hungary</ref> to give her first full-length English interview and talk about her work and her version of events.</p>
<p>Adela Lupșe was born in 1988 to a miner's family in the village of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poiana#Transylvania">Poiana</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bihor%20County">Bihor</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transylvania">Transylvania</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Romania">Romania</ref>. A member of Romania's first post-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicolae%20Ceaușescu">Ceaușescu</ref> generation, she grasped the power of television at a young age: "I think television is the most interesting phenomenon that the modern day has given us....for my type of personality, I find it impressive, the power that television has worldwide....We dress like the people that television promotes. We want to look like the celebrities that television launches."</p>
<hi rend="bold">I wanted to get some attention and get people to know my face.</hi>
<p>Knowing television was the career for her, Lupșe moved to the city of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oradea">Oradea</ref> to study journalism, and began a job at a local television station as a health reporter. Using that position as a launching board, she found her way onto the national reality program <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ro:Noră%20pentru%20mama">Noră pentru mama 1</ref></hi> (<hi rend="italic">Daughter-in-law for Mom</hi>) on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kanal%20D">Kanal D</ref>, a show in which mothers of single sons attempted to matchmake for their children. Lupșe unabashedly admits she took part in the show only for exposure: "Actually my goal from the start was not to win this thing or to find someone. I wanted to get some attention and get people to know my face. I want this attention because I'm aware of the fact that it is not easy to enter this world! And I was doing all this in order to increase my chances to get my dream job in television." That dream: to host a nationally-broadcast talk show.</p>
</text>
