<text id="autogum_voyage_doc47" title="Video recording" shortTile="video-recording" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=144680" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Video recording</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Video recording</hi> devices have evolved quickly during the 21st century. Today it is easier and more affordable than ever to take a video of your travels. There are however still concerns about lighting, battery life, and data storage.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>Motion pictures are great to <ref target="wildlife%20photography">capture animals</ref>, artistic performances and <ref target="Spectator%20sports">sport contests</ref> (if and where allowed – some theaters and stadium authorities have rather strict policies and do enforce them), or other interesting events. Overall if you want to <hi rend="bold">capture the ambiance</hi> of a place you are at, a video clip is much better than just photos as it includes movement and sound. Video also allows you to record a, say, 360° view much easier than if you have a normal camera. </p>

<p>Half a century ago, it was possible to make amateur films on Super 8 reels which lasted a couple of minutes. The cost per minute was high, the film had to be developed before it could be shown on a projector and there was often no sound at all. By the 1980s, camcorders emerged on the market and video recording became more convenient. Video and sound was recorded on a tape; just connect the camera to a TV and push play to enjoy your recordings. </p>

<p>In the 21st century digital video became the norm and prices for the devices dropped quickly, and phones, tablets and other devices also got video recording capability. Digital video clips can easily be moved to other devices, freeing space on memory cards for new recordings, so the battery level is pretty much the only thing present day video enthusiasts have to keep an eye on. In addition, compared to analog recordings, it's much easier and affordable to edit digital videos. Even an amateur traveller can now make a professional-looking travel documentary.</p>

<head>Camera types</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Smartphone">Smartphone</ref>:</hi> Easy to carry, and high resolution with the latest models. Zooming, lighting and sound qualities are however inferior. Sensitive to damage from shocks and water. Battery time and storage space are limited, though this can be alleviated somewhat if you are willing to use data to offload videos and carry around external power banks. Could be used as backup for a more advanced camera.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Digital still camera:</hi> Most of the basic automated point-and-click digital cameras now have some motion video capability, but at a lower resolution than their <ref target="travel%20photography">still photographs</ref>. A few can do HDTV reasonably well, although the audio is rudimentary at best. There is no photoflash in 'moving video' mode, so the photographer will need some other source of illumination. A tripod is also useful to eliminate camera shake.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">System camera:</hi> Good for zooming, and use together with a <ref target="telephoto%20lens">telephoto lens</ref>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Action camera:</hi> Small and durable cameras particularly usable for extreme sports and stunts. Can often be fastened e.g. on the performers helmet and are often waterproof or come with optional waterproof casing. Many models often have poor built in microphones.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Camcorder:</hi> Real video cameras are still available in many sizes and shapes from the huge things that professional crews use to pocket sized things. Traditional consumer camcorders often support changing optical zoom quietly while recording.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">360 Camera:</hi> Also known as a omnidirectional camera. These cameras capture all angles at once, creating a video that can be viewed from any angle desired. This is ideal for sharing your travel experiences in Virtual Reality or for capturing a panoramic shot with lots of action in all directions. However this type of camera is inferior for most normal uses, as it can't actually zoom in on a subject and uses a great amount of storage. Thus these make better secondary cameras then primary cameras.</item>
</list>


<head>Camera accessories</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Drones</hi> are becoming more and more affordable to the general public and are often equipped with, or are possible to equip with video recorders. They allow you to take photos and videos from perspectives that regular photographers previously could only dream of. In addition to the regulations mentioned below considering photography, there are often additional regulations — varying from country to country — considering the drones themselves. To avoid problems with the authorities, do inform yourself about regulations considering drones (maximum flight altitudes. permits and such) in the country where you intend to use them.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Gimbals</hi> are devices that work to keep camera movement stable during movement, and are especially useful while shooting video from a vehicle or on the go. 2 axis gimbals tend to be cheaper and use less energy then 3 axis gimbals, but provide less stabilization. Gimbals come in a variety of different formfactors from Smartphone focused models, to models integrated in a drone.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">UV filters</hi> can be attached to some camcorders. While they don't provide a real benefit to digital cameras as they did with film, they do act as protection for your lens, and can potentially save your lens from direct damage if your destination is particularly dirty.</item>
</list>


<head>Record</head>

<p>When recording video, keep the camera steady and move the camera slowly, otherwise it may be impossible to watch what you've recorded afterwards.</p>

<p>Remember that a minute is a very long time when watching video. Plan well before shooting unless you are going to do extensive editing – which is quite arduous. Also, if you will not be able to <hi rend="bold">recharge your battery</hi> before leaving the area (say, you're on a day trip to a national park) you should be careful with how much you use your camera. It's extremely frustrating if you can't record that stunning sunset over a canyon that you may not return to anytime soon just because of an empty battery. Bring a (charged) spare if you have one; best to recharge all batteries immediately before use, as some hold their charge poorly if left on the shelf for months. </p>

<p>If you are away from a steady source of electricity for a longer time, solar chargers and "power packs" with a lot of pre-charged ampere-hours <hi rend="italic">might</hi> be an option but <hi rend="italic">will</hi> weigh you down. If you know you will be filming for extended periods without being able to recharge, you should buy a camera operating on AA batteries, as opposed to cameras with a battery for that camera type only. Single-use versions of such batteries are available all over the world, and rechargeable AA batteries are also widely available and comparatively cheap. Also, keep in mind that if a custom-made/integrated battery breaks, it may mean a major hassle finding a new one (in particular if the camera is of an old/obscure type) and unless you find one, your camera will be useless.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Storage media</hi> isn't such a problem as it used to be when video cameras were analog; for instance a small 16 GB SD-memory card can usually hold one or two hours of high quality video (naturally, this varies a lot from camera to camera) and much more if you're recording in inferior quality. It's also easy to remove videos you don't need to free up space. However, the fact that memory cards are so small also means they are easy to lose if you're careless. If you've filled a memory card and need to replace it to continue recording, pack it away at some secure place and/or make a backup copy of the video files if you can.</p>
</text>
