<text id="autogum_academic_doc144" title="Relationship between Corporate Sustainability and Compliance with State-Owned Enterprises in Central-Europe: A Case Study from Hungary" shortTile="relationship-between" author="Anita Boros, Csaba Fogarassy" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5653/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Key Aspects of Corporate Compliance </head>
<p>Compliance is a very complex definition or concept, as it includes financial, economic, tax, business, legal, ethical, sustainability, and proprietary compliance. In fact, when examining the suitability of an organization, we are looking for the answer to whether its operating mechanisms can be subordinated to all the rules, objectives, and expectations of the organization. In the narrower sense, compliance means compliance with and the enforcement of the legal regulations applicable to a business association, including the decisions of the owner. In the broader sense, when compared to positions, it means much more:
<list>
<item>the objectives pursued in setting up the business in question;</item>
<item>ownership, sometimes at the governmental level, together with regulators at the policy (sector) level;</item>
<item>compliance with standards;</item>
<item>meeting the expectations of the public service users;</item>
<item>compliance with the organization’s short-, medium- and long-term strategic objectives;</item>
<item>it also represents compliance with corporate values for managers and employees.</item>
</list>
</p>

<p>In the context of compliance regulation, the International Standards of Supreme Audit Institutions (ISSAI) should be highlighted. The audit principles applicable to all types of audits are outlined in the General Principles of Public Sector Auditing. </p>

<p>In this system, financial control is a control activity designed to determine whether the audited entity presents its financial information in accordance with the applicable financial reporting and regulatory framework. It has a special role in relation to public sector organizations, as it can also create public confidence in the state, an organization performing public tasks. The purpose of performance audits, on the other hand, is to determine whether the operation of the organization, its operating principles and procedures can be subordinated to the principles of economy, efficiency and effectiveness. Finally, the standard emphasizes preventive mechanisms in the context of compliance auditing and states that such auditing should be aimed at examining whether a particular management decision, measure, or regulator within an organization meets predefined compliance criteria—that is, to what extent it is possible to minimize the compliance risks already mentioned. </p>

<p>A separate standard has also been adopted to regulate this control function. This standard emphasizes that compliance control is basically divided into two parts: first, compliance with the criteria established by regularity (compliance with formal criteria such as legal regulations, ownership decisions, or agreements) and other compliance (with criteria for sound financial management and ethical conduct. It has to be emphasized here that, in itself, one of the risk factors of sustainability and thus of compliance may be that these regulations have been changing frequently. </p>
</text>
