<text id="autogum_bio_doc483" title="Levina Teerlinc" shortTile="levina-teerlinc" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-11-08" dateModified="2019-09-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Levina_Teerlinc" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Levina Teerlinc</head><figure><caption><hi rend="italic">An Elizabethan <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maundy_money">Maundy</ref></hi>, miniature by Levina Teerlinc, c. 1560</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Levina Teerlinc</hi> (1510s – 23 June 1576) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flemings">Flemish</ref> Renaissance miniaturist who served as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Artists_of_the_Tudor_court">painter to the English court</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VIII">Henry VIII</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_VI">Edward VI</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary_I">Mary I</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_I">Elizabeth I</ref>. She was the most important <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portrait_miniature">miniaturist</ref> at the English court between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hans_Holbein_the_Younger">Hans Holbein the Younger</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_Hilliard">Nicholas Hilliard</ref>. Her father, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simon_Bening">Simon Bening</ref> was a renowned book <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Illuminated_manuscript">illuminator</ref> and miniature painter of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ghent-Bruges_school">Ghent-Bruges school</ref> and probably trained her as a manuscript painter. She may have worked in her father's workshop before her marriage.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Teerlinc was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bruges">Bruges</ref>, Flanders (which is now a part of Belgium) in the 1510s, one of five daughters of renowned miniaturist Simon Bening and granddaughter of Catherine van der Goes (closely related to Hugo van der Goes) and Alexander Bening.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:3-3">[3]</ref> After marrying George Teerlinc of Blanckenberge in 1545, Teerlinc left for England, and is documented there by 1546, when she became court painter to the Tudor court, serving <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VIII">Henry VIII</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_VI">Edward VI</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary_I">Mary I</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_I">Elizabeth I</ref>. She received an annual salary of £40 from 1546 until her death in 1576, as granted by Henry VIII<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:2-4">[4]</ref> and recorded by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lodovico_Guicciardini">Lodovico Guicciardini</ref> (1567),<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:2-4">[4]</ref> which was more than was provided to Holbein.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Strong:52-5">[5]</ref>  She was the only female painter in the court of Henry VIII.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref>  In 1559 Teerlinc was appointed tutor in painting to the King's daughter at the Spanish Court.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:1-7">[7]</ref> She and her husband had one son, Marcus.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> She died in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stepney,_London">Stepney, London</ref> on 23 June 1576.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<head>Works</head>
<figure><caption>Portrait of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_I_of_England">Elizabeth I</ref> by Levina Teerlinc, c. 1565</caption></figure>
<p>No extant works by Teerlinc are currently identified.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:0-10">[10]</ref> Yet she was one of the most well-documented artists at court in miniature painting, providing various portraits of Elizabeth I in the years 1559, 1562, 1563, 1564, 1567 ("a full-length portrait"), 1568 ("with Knights of the Order"), 1575 ("with other personages"), and 1576.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:3-3">[3]</ref> She also painted for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary_I_of_England">Mary I</ref> in 1556 "as a New Year gift a small picture of the "trynitie."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:2-4">[4]</ref> Teerlinc is best known for her pivotal position in the rise of the portrait miniature. She might have trained <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_Hilliard">Nicholas Hilliard</ref>, by training a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goldsmith">goldsmith</ref>, in the methods of miniature portraiture.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref></p>
<p>Attributing Teerlinc's works is challenging because she did not always sign them. However, there are a few existing paintings that are suspected to be Teerlinc's due to the fact she was the only active miniaturist of prominence in English court between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hans_Holbein_the_Younger">Hans Holbein the Younger</ref> in 1543 and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_Hilliard">Nicholas Hilliard</ref> in the 1570s.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref> Some scholars also speculate that many of the miniatures were lost in the fire at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palace_of_Whitehall">Whitehall</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref></p>
<p>A 1983 exhibition at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Victoria_and_Albert_Museum">Victoria and Albert Museum</ref> represented "the first occasion when a group of miniatures has been assembled which can be attributed to Levina Teerlinc".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Strong:52-5">[5]</ref>  Since the exhibition also performed the same function for her predecessor as court miniaturist, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lucas_Hornebolte">Lucas Hornebolte</ref>, it was especially useful in developing consensus on attributions. Five miniatures and two illuminated manuscript sheets were in the group, including a miniature of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lady_Katherine_Grey">Lady Katherine Grey</ref> from the V&amp;A, and others from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yale_Center_for_British_Art">Yale Center for British Art</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_Collection">Royal Collection</ref> (both of these possibly of the young Elizabeth I, and private collections).  Strong considered there was "a convincing group of miniatures that emerge as the work of a single hand, one whose draughtsmanship is weak, whose paint is thin and transparent and whose brushwork loose".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Strong:52-5">[5]</ref>  She also probably designed the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Seal_of_England">Great Seal of England</ref> for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary_I_of_England">Mary I</ref> and the earliest one used by Elizabeth (in the 1540s).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:1-7">[7]</ref></p>
<head>Partial list of works</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Levina Teerlinc, <hi rend="italic">Portrait of Lady Katherine Grey</hi>, About 1555–60, Victoria and Albert Museum, Museum no. P.10-1979<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref></item>
<item>Levina Teerlinc, <hi rend="italic">Portrait of a Young Woman</hi>, 1566, Victoria and Albert Museum, Museum no. P.21-1954<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref></item>
<item>Levina Teerlinc, <hi rend="italic">Portrait of Mary Dudley, Lady Sidney</hi>, ca.1575, Victoria and Albert Museum, Museum no. E.1170-1988<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[16]</ref></item>
<item>Levina Teerlinc?, <hi rend="italic">Portrait of Queen Mary I</hi>, Collection of the Duke of Buccleuch</item>
<item>Levina Teerlinc?, <hi rend="italic">Portrait of a Young Woman</hi>, Collection of H.M. the Queen, Windsor Castle</item>
<item>Levina Teerlinc?, <hi rend="italic">Portrait of Elizabeth I in State Robes</hi>, Collection of Welbeck Abbey</item></list>
</text>
