<text id="autogum_interview_doc252" title="Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Family Coalition Party candidate Joel Kidd, Beaches-East York" shortTile="ontario-votes--interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-02" dateModified="2010-06-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Family_Coalition_Party_candidate_Joel_Kidd%2C_Beaches-East_York" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Family Coalition Party candidate Joel Kidd, Beaches-East York</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 2, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Joel Kidd</hi> is running for the Family Coalition Party in the Ontario provincial election, in the Beaches-East York riding. Wikinews' Nick Moreau interviewed him regarding his values, his experience, and his campaign.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>I care about the future of my homeland, Ontario, and I believe Ontario badly needs leaders of moral integrity, who stand on principle for what they believe.  I am running to give the voters of Beaches-East York a candidate to vote for who sands for moral integrity, accountability, justice, defending the family, defending life, and fiscal responsibility.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?</hi></p>
<p>There is no other candidate running to represent the need for historic moral principles and ethical integrity to government, who will defend life and defend the family.  These issues of justice matter far more than issues of finances and budgets, but no other party has the courage to say so and stand on a principled moral foundation.  In short, only the Family Coalition Party has what that Ontario needs.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>Government's number one priority is justice, and there is a glaring, tragic injustice happening in Ontario: abortion.  It's our Darfur, our hidden genocide. Learn the truth here: <ref target="http://www.silentnomore.ca/">http://www.silentnomore.ca/</ref>  The Family Coalition Party will compassionately seek to provide ways to end this tragedy for unborn babies it kills, and for the men and women it hurts.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How can the province lead the way in stimulating job creation?</hi></p>
<p>By reducing the red tape and tax burdens, wherever possible, and encouraging innovation.  When it comes to the government, less is more -- less is better.  This is a lot of non-essential spending that needs to be eliminated to reduce the burden on taxpayers.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What are your views on the mixed member proportional representation (MMP) referendum?</hi></p>
<p>There is no question that our current electoral and parliamentary system is dysfunctional.  Ontario needs electoral reform! I have weighed the pros and cons to MMP, and I believe it will lead to a healthier political environment in Canada.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What role, if any, does "new media" play in your campaign, and the campaign of your party? (websites, blogs, Facebook, YouTube videos, etc) Do you view it as beneficial, or a challenge?</hi></p>
<p>Alternate media is a benefit because it de-centralizes the control of media, it gives freedom to the flow of ideas, a necessary ingredient of a healthy society.  Alternate media means the decentralization of idealogical and political power.</p>
<head id="Missed_questions">Missed questions</head>
<p>Note that Joel did not reply to these five questions:</p>
<p>"What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?"</p>
<p>"Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why?"</p>
<p>"What should be the first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly?"</p>
<p>"Are the property taxes in your riding at a fair level for the amount of services received in the municipality?"</p>
<p>"Of the decisions made by Ontario's 38th Legislative Assembly, which was the most beneficial to your electoral district? To the province as a whole? Which was least beneficial, or even harmful, to your riding? To the province as a whole?"</p>
</text>
