<text id="autogum_reddit_doc126" title="I watched Gone With the Wind (1939). Jesus." shortTile="watched-gone-wind" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-04-30" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8fzway" speakerList="#Iggapoo, #dillonsrule" speakerCount="2">
<head>I watched Gone With the Wind (1939). Jesus.</head>
<sp who="#dillonsrule">
<p>I saw that this was posted about 2 months ago, but I think I had a very different take on it than the other person. I understand that the movie was made almost 80 years ago, but jesus, the racism and depictions of black people was really jarring to me. Believe me, I'm no SJW, but even for me, this was over the top. I am absolutely amazed that this is still so highly regarded, as it really is a glorification of the pre-war, slave holding south. The Yankees/Notherners are absolute villains, thieves and murderers with seemingly no redeeming qualities. I understand something like "Birth of a Nation" is still talked about because of its historical significance from a filmmaking perspective, but people still seem to regard Gone with the Wind as one of the all-time great stories/movies all together. The Southerns are cast as fucking gallant knights fighting for a glorious civilization. Fuck me man! It was way too long and Scarlett was the most insufferable character I've seen in a very long time. I thought she would learn and grow significantly by the end. She does a little bit, but she is still petulant and manipulative as ever by the end of it. Maybe she has a revelation in the last 5 mins of a 4 hour movie, but that just isn't enough for a satisfying ending. There were some twists that I was not expecting towards the end, but even that isn't really given enough emotional weight or impact to make much difference by the end it seemed to me. I can understand why this was a great movie when it came out and why people would have loved it so much, but I cannot for the life of me understand why it would still be so well regarded today. </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#Iggapoo">
<p>I'd like to offer an alternate perspective on it. I've always seen Gone With the Wind as a tragedy, and at the heart of it you have Scarlett, an anti-hero. </p>
<p>She looks like a hero: she's beautiful, rich, part of this veneer of respectability and culture, but like everything else that the South was built on, it runs only skin deep. </p>
<p>One prime character trait for Scarlett is how doggedly she pursues her individual goals. It's the reason for all her successes. How she survives the war, keeps Tara, all that. But it's also the reason for all her failures. She refuses to look at herself and decide whether a particular goal she has is even something she wants. Take Ashley. She convinces herself that she wants to marry him and she pursues that goal even after meeting Rhett and the obvious chemistry they shared. Through her scheming she even gets him, but that success is ultimately a failure. She didn't really want him, and he dies anyway before her deluded fairytale life can begin. </p>
<p>Same with Rhett. She thinks at the end of the film that she can get him back after everything. Why would she even want him? He clearly doesn't want her. Her determination won't allow her to stop despite her own failures. </p>
<p>And the Tomorrow is another day is a very southern idea. This ability to brush unpleasant truths under the rug if they don't conform to her delusion. I think it makes her a tragic figure. </p>
<p>And while the portrayals of black people in the film are simultaneously from their time (1930s) and from their period (civil war south), I think it's important to note that, unlike films like  <hi rend="bold">Birth of a Nation</hi> , the South of GWtW is not preserved. They lose everything. Those portrayals are not rewarded with success.</p>
</sp>
</text>
