<text id="autogum_voyage_doc353" title="Ramla" shortTile="ramla" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=29156" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ramla</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.ramla.muni.il/">Ramla</ref></hi> is a city in central <ref target="Israel">Israel</ref>, between <ref target="Jerusalem">Jerusalem</ref> and <ref target="Tel%20Aviv">Tel Aviv</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Ramla was the only new city to be founded within the current boundaries of Israel during about 1,200 years of Muslim rule; in all other cases, they were built on top of preexisting cities. Today it has a mixed Arab and Jewish population of 66,000 people.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>Buses run frequently from <ref target="Jerusalem">Jerusalem</ref>, <ref target="Tel%20Aviv">Tel Aviv</ref>, <ref target="Modiin">Modiin</ref>, and other cities in central Israel, as well as <ref target="Beer%20Sheva">Beer Sheva</ref>.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ramla Central Bus station</hi>.</item>
</list>
<head>By train</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ramla train station</hi>. Trains run once an hour to Tel Aviv, Beit Shemesh, and Jerusalem. The station sits on the site of a 19th century stop along the original line but has seen significant renovation and new construction int the 21st century </item>
</list>


<head>Get around</head>
<p>All sites of interest to tourists are within a 15-minute walk of the central bus station.</p>

<p>Inside Ramla, Kavim operates four local bus lines (4, 5, 7, 8), and three lines to <ref target="Lod">Lod</ref> (<date when="2015-11-13">11, 13, 15</date>). Bus line 25 can be also used for local service inside Ramla.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tower of Ramla</hi> (the White Tower). was built in the 13th century. It served as the minaret of the White Mosque (al-Masjid al-Abyad) erected by Caliph Suleiman in the 8th century CE, of which only remnants remain today. The tower is six stories high, with a spiral staircase of 119 steps. You may be able to walk up to the top, where there are great views of the Tel Aviv area. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Arches Pool</hi>. An underground water reservoir with impressive arches holding up its roof. Built in the 8th century. You can get in a rowboat and paddle underground between the arches. Highly recommended, especially on hot days, as the pool remains cool. ₪14. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Great Mosque</hi> (Al-Omri Mosque), ☏ +972 8 922-5081 . Built as a Crusader church, this building was converted into a mosque by the Mameluks, and is still used as a mosque today. The building is quite impressive. Call ahead of time to arrange a visit. ₪7. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ramla Museum</hi>. Describes Ramla's history. The building, from 1922, incorporates elements of Arab architecture such as arched windows and patterned tiled floors, and is the former municipal headquarters of the British Mandatory authorities.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The old city</hi> next to the market is an abandoned area of old buildings dating to the Ottoman period and earlier.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">British military cemetery</hi>. Best known for the grave of a soldier named Harry Potter, who was killed in the Arab revolt against the British in 1939. The grave reportedly receives many visitors each year on July 31, which is the birthday of the fictional Harry Potter. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Truck and Transport Museum</hi>, HaHazon 2, Industrial Area B. An outdoor museum housing a large variety of old trucks (lorries). Lots of fun for kids. Open every day, free entry. Go to the lobby of the Taavurah company offices, ask the guard for the museum key. Unshaded, so it might not be good for a hot day. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Hospice of St. Nicodemus and St. Joseph of Arimathea</hi> (Franciscan Church). On Ramla's main boulevard, Herzl Street, is easily recognized by its clock-faced, square tower. It belongs to the Franciscan church. Napoleon used the hospice as his headquarters during his Palestine campaign in 1799. The church houses Israel's only painting by Tizian. </item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ramla's market</hi>, Jabotinsky street.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ramla Mall</hi>, 1 David Raziel street, ☏ +972 8-6701111 , fax: +972 8-9106170 . The mall is also known as Azrieli Ramla Mall. Su Th 09:30-22:00,F 09:00-15:30,Sa 20:00-23:00.</item>
</list>


<head>Go next</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Lod">Lod</ref> - Next to Ramla, it is quite similar as a place to live, but has fewer attractions for visitors.</item>
<item> <ref target="Rishon%20LeZion">Rishon LeZion</ref> - the major city between Ramla and <ref target="Tel%20Aviv">Tel Aviv</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Modi%27in">Modi'in</ref> - the major city between Ramla and <ref target="Jerusalem">Jerusalem</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Jaffa">Jaffa</ref> - The southeastern part of Tel aviv, and close atmosphere to Ramla</item>
</list>
</text>
