<text id="autogum_voyage_doc336" title="Sulphur (Oklahoma)" shortTile="sulphur-oklahoma" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=144686" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Sulphur (Oklahoma)</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Sulphur</hi> is in the <ref target="Chickasaw%20Country">Chickasaw Country</ref> Region of <ref target="Oklahoma">Oklahoma</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Sulphur, OK has a history dating back before Oklahoma's statehood in 1907. The town was formed largely due to the popularity of the healing Sulphur Springs in the <ref target="Chickasaw%20National%20Recreation%20Area">Chickasaw National Recreation Area</ref>, formerly Platt National Park.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>Sulphur is easily accessible from I-35. From I-35, take Exit 55 east toward <ref target="Davis_%28Oklahoma%29">Davis</ref> and continue through Davis on Highway 7 until you reach Sulphur.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>Sulphur is mostly a car town, but you can grab a bike at the bike share at the Chickasaw Visitor Center at Hwy 177 and Hwy 7.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lake of the Arbuckles</hi> (Located in the Chickasaw National Recreation Area). This lake also serves as a reservoir for Murray County. Fishing is available for varieties of catfish, perch, bass and crappie. Located within the Chickasaw National Recreation Area, there are several camping grounds and RV camps available to rent. Facilities include campgrounds, trailer spaces, picnic areas, shelters, tables, public restrooms, drinking water, boat docks and boat ramps. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Vendome Well</hi> (Located just off Highway 7 near downtown Sulphur in the Chickasaw National Recreation Area). A symbol of the namesake of Sulphur, Oklahoma, the Vendome Well is a mineral spring that always runs. Visitors once came from everywhere to drink the mineral waters from the well. There is a spigot where you can still drink the water (if you can get over the egg smell).</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Chickasaw Cultural Center</hi>, 867 Cooper Memorial Dr., ☏ +1 580 622-7130 . </item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Chickasaw%20National%20Recreation%20Area">Chickasaw National Recreation Area</ref> </hi>. Mineral springs, streams, lakes and waterfalls attract visitors from all over the world. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Chickasaw Visitor Center</hi>, 901 W 1st Street, ☏ +1 580-622-8050 . 9:00 a.m. - 6:00 p.m.. The Chickasaw Visitor Center stands at the entrance to the Chickasaw National Recreation Area and houses the National Park Service. The center offers public restrooms, free refreshments, a bike share program and plenty of travel information and maps for the area if you need ideas on where to go and what to do. The small gift shop has a nice selection of souvenirs, including Chickasaw Country products, Native American jewelry and gifts. The Chickasaw Visitor Center hosts regular cultural demonstrations as well as a rotating featured artist with art on display and available for purchase.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Artesian Arts Festival</hi>, downtown Sulphur, ☏ +1 580-272-5520 . This annual arts festival takes place every Memorial Day weekend in downtown Sulphur. Artwork is available from Native and Southwestern artists from across the country. Live music from local and traveling artists takes place all day along with a variety of food and retail vendors throughout the festival. Art activities and classes are available throughout the day for visitors. Free entry.</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Third and Broadway</hi> (Downtown). A small boutique with unique "country" gifts and clothing.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Spice and Tea Exchange of Sulphur</hi>, 8 West Muskogee Ave, ☏ +1 580-622-3770 , ✉ sulphur@spiceandtea.com . Sunday 11:00 - 5:00 Monday - Thursday, 11:00 - 6:00 Friday &amp; Saturday, 11:00 - 7:00. A local franchise of a larger chain, Spice and Tea Exchange has a wide variety of unique spices including salts, sugars, peppers, spice blends and teas. They also have a small selection of cooking tools available.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Luxe at the Artesian</hi>, 1600 Division (Located on the east side of the Artesian Hotel), ☏ +1 580-622-8908 . Sun – Thurs: 9 a.m. – 9 p.m.; Fri – Sat: 9 a.m. – 11 p.m.. This boutique shop carries several high-end designers and has a nice variety of clothing and fashion accessories for men and women.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Mix Mercantile</hi>, 300 West Muskogee, ☏ +1 580-232-2260 ext 1 . Tues - Sat: 10 am - 5:30 pm. Family-owned boutique in the downtown district that sells apparel, jewelry, accessories, home décor and gourmet food items.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Flower Bluff Mansion Steakhouse</hi>, 329 W Muskogee Ave (Downtown), ☏ +1 580 622-4005 . Wednesday through Saturday 5-9pm. High-end dining. The classy atmosphere provides an intimate dining experience. Reservations recommended, walk-ins welcome.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Springs at the Artesian</hi> (Springs), 1001 W. 1st Street (Located inside The Artesian Hotel), ☏ +1 580-622-8106 . Sun - Thurs: 7 a.m. – 10 p.m. Fri - Sat: 7 a.m. – 11 p.m.. This restaurant offers southern comfort food in a fine dining setting. Dishes include items like chicken-fried steak, fried green tomatoes, and catfish. Reservations are recommended due to high-volume traffic on weekends.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bedré Cafe</hi>, 14 West Muskogee (Located on the south side of the Artesian Hotel), ☏ +1 580-622-8020 . Daily: 6:00 a.m. – 8:00 p.m.. This diner-themed café offers deli sandwiches, soups, salads and desserts. They also carry the full line of Bedré Fine Chocolate and have a wide range of ice cream products.</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Rusty Nail Winery</hi>, 218 W Muskogee Ave, ☏ +1 580 622-8466 . Tuesday - Saturday: 12 - 8 p.m., Closed Sunday and Monday. The Rusty Nail is a family-owned boutique winery and gift shop. The name comes from the former resident at the same location, which was a hardware store. They don't grow their own grapes, but instead ferment their wine from juice blends and offer sweet and dry wines as well as white, blush and red. There is a small food menu available.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Fountain Club</hi> (Inside The Artesian Hotel), ☏ +1 580-622-8107 . Sunday through Thursday: 3 p.m. – 12 a.m. Friday through Saturday: 12 p.m. – 1:30 a.m.. Beer, wine and classic cocktails with live entertainment every Friday night. They also have a limited food menu available.</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Artesian Hotel, Casino &amp; Spa</hi> (The Artesian), 1001 W. 1st Street, ☏ +1-855-455-5255 . Check-in: 4 p.m., check-out: 12 p.m.. This hotel is a revival of an iconic historic hotel destroyed in the 1960s by fire. Rebuilt and reopened by the Chickasaw Nation in 2013, the hotel's architecture mimics that of the original hotel. Amenities include an on-site spa, restaurant, bar, casino, fitness center, two pools, a bath house and a wide variety of boutique shopping options. Rooms start at $139. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Chickasaw Retreat and Conference Center</hi>, 4205 Goddard Youth Camp Road, ☏ +1-855-899-8260 . Located just outside the Chickasaw National Recreation Area, this hotel offers excellent views of the surrounding Arbuckle Mountains. Amenities include fitness center, swimming pool and bar. The center provides several offerings for business and family groups. Prices start at $129.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Echo Canyon</hi>, 350 Lawton Avenue, ☏ +1 580-421-5076 . Locally owned spa resort.</item>
</list>
</text>
