<text id="autogum_interview_doc775" title="part2_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Family Coalition Party candidate Ray Scott, Algoma-Manitoulin" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-01" dateModified="2010-06-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Family_Coalition_Party_candidate_Ray_Scott%2C_Algoma-Manitoulin" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">How can the province lead the way in stimulating job creation?</hi></p>
<p>We can wait. The shortage of workers is so severe, even if we do nothing, unemployment will come close to zero. In the meantime, the FCP believes that only in a free-enterprise economy does the creation of wealth take place and productivity is best achieved. The FCP supports the long-term removal of all measures that insulate industries, businesses, financial institutions, professions and trade unions from domestic and foreign competition. Government intervention should be limited to work safety and protection of the environment issues. Finally, governments cannot create wealth, but can create the conditions in which small businesses and corporations can create wealth. The forces that contribute to the creation of wealth and jobs are need, ingenuity, labour, production, provision of services and the like. The FCP will help the private sector to create jobs by reducing taxes to stimulate investment and increase the buying power of the average citizen.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What are your views on the mixed member proportional representation (MMP) referendum?</hi></p>
<p>I support it and my party supports it. Our current system is out-dated (1792). Under our current system 60%+ of the population is routinely not represented. Under the MMP system, the legislature will reflect true voting patterns. The burden of representation would decrease, on average, by 18,000 people for each legislator. Further, “list members” under the new system would be better caretakers of the whole province, rather than thinking in solely regional terms. The citizen’s assembly worked on the MMP proposal for 8 months, and voted for it by a majority of 94 to 8. Lastly, in countries with an MMP-like system, voter turnout has increase by an average of 10%, which is a good thing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What role, if any, does “new media” play in your campaign, and the campaign of your party? (websites, blogs, Facebook, YouTube videos, etc) Do you view it as beneficial, or a challenge?</hi></p>
<p>It would be a lot more beneficial to my campaign if I wasn’t on dial-up! I use email and websites, but technology is underutilized in my campaign. The only disadvantage to “new media” is that it may not be effective in reaching some demographic groups (e.g., low-income, some seniors).</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Of the decisions made by Ontario's 38th Legislative Assembly, which was the most beneficial to your this electoral district? To the province as a whole? Which was least beneficial, or even harmful, to your this riding? To the province as a whole?</hi></p>
<p>Some investments in infrastructure was beneficial. The province will benefit as a whole if MMP passes. The persistent efforts to maintain an unsustainable healthcare system structure are the most damaging policies to the province, and the riding. 1 million people in Ontario still don’t have access to a family doctor, and this shortage is even more acute in the North. Life saving surgeries continue to be cancelled due to over-crowded emergency rooms, and the challenges in long term care are huge. The longer we wait to implement Medical Savings Accounts, the more difficult it will be to manage the healthcare crisis.</p>
</text>
