<text id="autogum_interview_doc216" title="part0_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green candidate Martin Hyde, Ottawa West-Nepean" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-24" dateModified="2016-07-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Green_candidate_Martin_Hyde%2C_Ottawa_West-Nepean" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green candidate Martin Hyde, Ottawa West-Nepean</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, September 24, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Martin Hyde</hi> is running for the Green Party of Ontario in the Ontario provincial election, in the Ottawa West-Nepean riding. Wikinews' Nick Moreau interviewed him regarding his values, his experience, and his campaign.</p>
<p>Note that he did not answer the question "Of the decisions made by Ontario's 38th Legislative Assembly, which was the most beneficial to your electoral district? To the province as a whole? Which was least beneficial, or even harmful, to this riding? To the province as a whole?"</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>Environmental issues are core to our long term social, physical and economic health, both globally and locally. Globally there is no law — only agreements that participants sometimes choose to honour. In Canada law is made at the federal, provincial, and municipal levels. I attended my riding Green Party candidate nomination meeting because I wished to participate in the nomination process for the provincial election, and found that no one was contending for the position. I'm running because I believe it’s important for people who are concerned about environmental issues to have a Green Party candidate to vote for so that the larger parties will be forced to recognise their concerns.</p>
<p>Currently in Ontario, because we are not able to vote directly for a party, but are only able to do so by voting for a local candidate, it's crucial that a party runs a candidate in every riding so that people can make themselves heard. I believe the Multi Member Proportional system of voting will help solve this problem if we choose it in the Referendum on October 10.</p>
<p>I'm running in this riding because it's where I live.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>I have no prior political experience.</p>
<p>I have been a teacher for many years in Ontario public schools, and international schools overseas, which has broadened my understanding of people and issues from many perspectives. I've often promoted environmental issues when teaching, through such things as partnered community cleanups, introducing recycling programs, and organizing Earth Days.</p>
<p>As a graduate student I studied democratic participation and education.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why? What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?</hi></p>
</text>
