<text id="autogum_reddit_doc158" title="Worth to grind O-HO?" shortTile="worth-grind-oho" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-03-31" dateModified="2018-03-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/88mqfd" speakerList="#Rodtek, #TelemichusRhade, #TollhouseFrank" speakerCount="3">
<head>Worth to grind O-HO?</head>
<sp who="#Rodtek">
<p>I faced this situation very few times. It is interesting to see how every tank play, but this thing is surprisingly horrific to me. I started the line with O-I, nice tank. O-NI have been fun, with some decent battles. This tier 8 is.. Let's say bad. Tried the 15cm and the 10cm guns. I feel always out of position. And as having no Armour. Maybe for the gold spam? And those 2 useless turrets in the front.. Can't use the 10 degrees of gun depression. So, I have some free xp... And in 2 weeks we should have some discounts, for the 7th anniversary. Maybe I free xp to the Type 4? Or better to grind, patiently, and save xp for something else? As I enjoy the Vk100, I find this super heavy tier 8 annoying to play. </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#TelemichusRhade">
<p>O-Ho is certainly a more painful grind than the O-Ni but you do still get the odd battle that's fine. I don't think its bad enough to waste free xp on tbh. Just angle right and pick your spots and you can still have a decent impact on the game. But yeah the gun depression with those two turrets... provokes a bit of rage now and again. </p>
<p>I mean, there are a lot worse tier8 heavy tanks, try playing the Tiger II. </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#TollhouseFrank">
<p>When I was grinding it, I found the O-Ho a lot more enjoyable than the O-Ni. In fact, I think the O-Ni is the only tank in the line I didn't like (and this was pre-buff to the Type 4 Type 5). </p>
<p>The derp gun + vert stabs = you never need to aim a snap shot anymore. Insta 300+ damage to every tank you hit. Add in gun rammer, vents, BIA, and make sure you also have the Snap Shot skill on your gunner (helps reduce bloom a bit on turret rotation, which in turn also helps with the vert stabs) and you have this monstrosity: </p>
<p>3,889 DPM (yes, probably closer to 1,944 due to non-pens, but trust me, you will get pens on thin skinned targets to help with this) </p>
<p>14.04 second reload. </p>
<p>If you are one of the people who doesn't mind the credit hit for adding food, then that gets you to the following stats: </p>
<p>4,058 DPM (slightly over 2k with non-pens of the HE, but again, you will get some pens on thin skinned targets) </p>
<p>13.45 second reload. </p>
<p>All on a 152mm howitzer. </p>
<p>Oh, did I forget to mention that if you learn which tanks you can easily overmatch turret roofs on, then you can easily pen many of the heavies you will face in their turret roofs with AP rounds. It makes IS-3's sad when they lose 700HP every 14 seconds to an AP round through the roof.</p>
</sp>
</text>
