<text id="autogum_academic_doc380" title="Optimizing Transport Scheme of High Value-Added Shipments in Regions without Express Train Services" shortTile="optimizing-transport" author="Boliang Lin, Xingkui Li, Zexi Zhang, Yinan Zhao" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/6108/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
In a railway freight system, commodities can be divided into two categories: bulk commodities (e.g., coal, ore, oil, etc.) and high value-added commodities (e.g., electronics, foods, etc.). The transportation of bulk commodities is generally less sensitive to shipping time but concerned more with shipping costs, while that of high value-added shipments is usually concerned with shipping time and punctuality. </p>

<p>In recent years, with the government control of carbon emissions, some goods, mostly high value-added shipments, have been shifted from roads to railways. According to statistics released by the China Railway, from 2015 to 2018, the total amount of freight transported by railway first decreased and then increased, while the number of high value-added shipments continually increased. The growth rates of high value-added shipments transported by rail were 18.7%, 25%, 9.3% and 2.3% from 2015 to 2018, respectively. </p>

<p>High value-added shipments are strict about the delivery time. At present, express scheduled freight trains are mainly formed between the distribution centers with large freight flows, such as the China Railway Express and the Yangtze River Express. However, it is not economical to provide express trains for scattered high value-added shipments. Therefore, how to deliver these scattered shipments quickly is an urgent problem to be solved. This paper proposes a new transportation pattern approach, namely the method of reserving axle loads (here, the “method of reserving axle loads” means that a train makes room at the departing station, so that the train can pick up some wagons at other stations), which can improve the delivery speed of high value-added shipments in regions without express train services as well as attract more high value-added shipments to the railway. </p>

<p>The main work and innovation points of this paper are as follows: </p>

<p>(i) A method using long-distance direct trains to reserve axle loads for high value-added shipments in the regions without express train service is proposed. </p>

<p>(ii) The accumulation cost of freight cars in reclassification yards is analyzed and deduced in detail by using the method of reserving axle loads. </p>

<p>(iii) Compared to the traditional method, the whole process and costs of railway transportation for high value-added shipments using the method of reserving axle loads are analyzed. </p>

<p>(iv) Aiming at minimizing the total cost of the whole process of transportation, a mathematical model for the high value-added shipments in regions without express train services is constructed. The model can be solved in four scenarios: reserving axle loads for departing; reserving axle loads for arriving; reserving axle loads for both departing and arriving; and not reserving axle loads. The practicability of the model was tested by two numerical examples. </p>

<p>The remainder of this paper is organized as follows. Section 2 summarizes the literature related to car-to-block, block-to-train and car-to-train problems. Section 3 introduces the delivery methods of general trains and express trains and puts forward the method of using the long-distance direct train to transport the high value-added shipments in the area without express train services. Section 4 analyzes the car-hours saved for the accumulation process of freight cars in a classification yard under the approach of reserving axle loads. In Section 5, a mathematical model for high value-added shipments in regions without express train services according to the method of reserving axle loads is proposed. The results of two numerical examples are presented in Section 6. Finally, concluding remarks and future research directions are given in Section 7. </p>
</text>
