<text id="autogum_bio_doc423" title="William Finch (merchant)" shortTile="william-finch-merchant" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-06-23" dateModified="2019-08-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Finch_%28merchant%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>William Finch (merchant)</head>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">William Finch</hi> (died 1613) was an English merchant in the service of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/East_India_Company">East India Company</ref> (EIC). He travelled to India along with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Captain_Hawkins">Captain Hawkins</ref> during the reign of the Mughal emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jehangir">Jehangir</ref>. The two of them attended on the emperor at the Mughal court and established trade relations between England and India. Finch subsequently explored various cities in India and left a valuable account of them in his journal, which was subsequently published.</p>
<head>Career</head>
<p>Finch was a native of London. He was agent to an expedition sent by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/East_India_Company">East India Company</ref>, under Captains <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sir_William_Hawkins">Hawkins</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Keeling">Keeling</ref>, in 1607 to treat with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Mogul">Great Mogul</ref>. Hawkins and Finch landed at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Surat">Surat</ref> on 24 August 1608. They were violently opposed by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portugal">Portuguese</ref>. Finch, however, obtained permission from the governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cambay">Cambay</ref> to dispose of the goods in their vessels. Incited by the Portuguese, who seized two of the English ships, the natives refused to have dealings with the company's representatives. During these squabbles Finch fell ill, and Hawkins, proceeding to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agra">Agra</ref> alone, obtained favourable notice from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emperor">Emperor</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jehangir">Jehangir</ref>. Finch recovered, and joined Hawkins at Agra on 14 April 1610. The two remained at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mughal_Empire">mogul</ref>'s court for about a year and a half. Finch refused tempting offers to attach himself permanently to the service of Jehangir. </p>
<p>Hawkins returned to England, but Finch delayed his departure in order to make further explorations, visiting Byana and Lahore among other places. Finch made careful observations on the commerce and natural products of the districts visited. In 1612 the Moghul emperor confirmed and extended the privileges he had promised to Finch and Hawkins, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/East_India_Company">East India Company</ref> in that year set up their first little <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Factory_(trading_post)">factory</ref> at Surat.</p>
<head>Exploration</head>
<p>Finch explored various cities in India, including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Delhi">Delhi</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ambala">Ambala</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sultanpur,_Uttar_Pradesh">Sultanpur</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ayodhya">Ayodhya</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lahore">Lahore</ref>, and left valuable accounts of these places in his diary. He intended to return to Europe overland, but died <hi rend="italic">en route</hi> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baghdad">Baghdad</ref> in 1612 probably due to infected water. His belongings were saved and returned to the East India Company. Reverend Samuel Purchas found Finch's journal in the archives of the Company and published an abridged version of it as a chapter in his "<hi rend="italic">Pilgrimes</hi>".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEKunal,_Ayodhya_Revisited2016133–-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In Ayodhya, Finch was an early witness to the location of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ram_Janmabhoomi">Ram Janmabhoomi</ref> (the birth place of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rama">Rama</ref>), the source of the present day <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ayodhya_dispute">Ayodhya dispute</ref>. Finch did not mention the birthplace or a mosque (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Babri_Masjid">Babri Masjid</ref>, believed to have been constructed by a general of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Babur">Babur</ref>). He did mention ruins, which were apparently believed to be Rama's castle and houses. Scholar <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hans_T._Bakker">Hans T. Bakker</ref>, who made a detailed study of Ayodhya, takes Finch's account to be an authentic record of the state of the Ramkot area at that time.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTELayton_&amp;_Thomas,_Destruction_and_Conservation_of_Cultural_Property20038-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBakker,_Ayodhya,_Part_I1984136–137-3">[3]</ref></p>
</text>
