<text id="autogum_academic_doc423" title="Quantitative Research of Photobioreactor Performance Based on an Improved Surface Fitting Method" shortTile="quantitative-research" author="Qihang Jin, Zhenzong He, Huijie Ma" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/21/4089/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>With the development of the economy and improvements in quality of life, the demand for energy is increasing. Meanwhile, the exploitation and utilization of irreproducible fossil fuels worldwide has made energy crises, environmental pollution, and global warming increasingly prominent. Thus, there is an urgent need to seek a renewable and clean energy source as an alternative. To date, hydrogen energy has been regarded as an ideal alternative energy source because of the clean byproduct (i.e., water vapor) produced from its reaction with oxygen and the varieties of production methods. Among the various production methods, the photobiological hydrogen production of microorganisms is considered to be an important potential method, since hydrogen production processes are operated at ambient temperatures and pressures. </p>

<p>The photobiological hydrogen production processes of microorganisms can be classified as follows:
<list>
<item>Photolysis of water using algae and cyanobacteria. For green algae, the electrons are derived from water under the light and used to reduce protons, to produce a hydrogen molecule with hydrogenase enzymes in a hydrogen production process. However, for cyanobacteria and blue-green algae, the electrons from the photolysis process of water are first converted into organic molecules. Then, these organic molecules are degraded and the electrons are used by the hydrogenase and/or nitrogenase enzymes to produce hydrogen.</item>
<item>Photodecomposition of organic compounds by photosynthetic bacteria. For hydrogen production of photosynthetic bacteria, the electrons are derived from external organic medium of photosynthetic bacteria in photo-fermentation and are used by nitrogenase to generate H2.</item>
</list>
</p>

<p>In the processes of photobiological hydrogen production of cyanobacteria, levels of around 30% O2 in the mixed gases with H2 is dangerous for the system. In addition, the processes of hydrogen production of photosynthetic bacteria cause water pollution and CO2 emissions. In photobiological H2 production system of green algae, hydrogenase is particularly sensitive to O2. Melis et al. showed that pure hydrogen production can be achieved by Chlamydomonas reinhardtii under sulfur deprivation. This means that the oxygen inhibition of hydrogenase and the danger of gases mixed with H2 and O2 can be avoided. In fact, the photobiological H2 production process of C. reinhardtii can generally be divided into three phases. In the first phase, C. reinhardtii grows through ordinary photosynthesis. In the second phase, C. reinhardtii is cultured in a sulfur-deprived medium, and O2 production is slowed down. In the third phase, the anaerobic state of cells is achieved by sulfur deprivation, and cells produce pure hydrogen. Until now, the Chlamydomonas reinhardtii has been regarded as a potential best candidate for photobiological hydrogen production, because of its abilities to absorb CO2 and large photosynthetic efficiency, which are larger than higher plants (e.g., tree or sugar cane). Moreover, the hydrogen production of C. reinhardtii has been studied extensively, and this means that mass data experimental data, radiation characteristics and characteristic parameters of the photobiological H2 production model can be used as a reference. Therefore, the investigation of C. reinhardtii CC125, commonly used in H2 production, was chosen to theoretically study the photobiological hydrogen production process of the photobioreactors in the present work. </p>

<p>Photobioreactors (PBR) are enclosures used to cultivate microorganisms that utilize light as their energy source for their growth and subsequent product formation. Recently, numerous numerical simulations of the H2 production process in the PBR have been studied extensively for optimizing the design, operation, and performance of the PBRs. Aiba simulated the distribution and absorptance of light intensity of a one-dimensional plane-parallel photobioreactor with microalgae Rhodopseudomonas spheroides. Berberoglu and Pilon investigated the effect of a mixed culture with C. reinhardtii CC125 and R. sphearoides ATCC 49419 on the conversion efficiency of solar energy to hydrogen energy and hydrogen productivity in plane-parallel PBR. Murphy and Berberoglu calculated the productivity of a C. reinhardtii wild strain and transformant tla1 in plane-parallel PBRs coupling the light transfer model with photosynthetic rate model. In addition, the local specific and total oxygen production as a function of optical thickness at different incident irradiances was calculated in plane-parallel PBRs. Wheaton and Krishnamoorthy simulated light transfer coupled with fluid hydrodynamics in an air-lift tubular photobioreactor illuminated from inside by fluorescent lamps. Slegers et al. simulated outdoor vertical flat-plate PBRs containing Phaeodactylum tricornutum or Thalassiosira pseudonana of continuous culture. Moreover, the effect of PBR thickness and biomass concentration on the volumetric productivity has been studied. Pruvost et al. simulated outdoor inclined rectangular PBR illuminated by solar irradiance with cyanobacterium Arthrospira platensis of continuous cultivation, and the calculation of the areal biomass productivity per unit surface area is based on light transfer model and growth kinetics model. Lee et al. demonstrated that it is necessary to optimize light intensity, cell density, and the optical thickness of the PBR for maximizing microalgal productivity for a given microalgae species in the process of design and operation of PBR. Moreover, they obtained qualitative guidelines from experimental studies. Zhang et al. investigated the effect of solar irradiation, microalgae concentration and bubbles scattering on photobiological hydrogen production in the close plane-parallel PBRs. </p>
</text>
