<text id="autogum_bio_doc039" title="David Paulides" shortTile="david-paulides" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-08-13" dateModified="2019-10-30" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Paulides" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>David Paulides</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">David Paulides</hi> is a former police detective who is now an investigator and writer known primarily for his self-published books, one dedicated to proving the reality of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bigfoot">Bigfoot</ref>, and his <hi rend="italic">Missing 411</hi> series of books, in which he documents the disappearance of people in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_park">national parks</ref> and elsewhere. Paulides attributes mysterious, unspecified causes to these disappearances, while data analysis suggests that these disappearances are not statistically mysterious or unexpected.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-SI-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Polich-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Early life and career</head>
<p>In his online biography page, Paulides states that he received his undergraduate and graduate degrees from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_San_Francisco">University of San Francisco</ref>, and in 1977 he began a 20-year career in law enforcement, transferring in 1980 to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Jose_Police_Department">San Jose Police Department</ref>, working in the patrol division on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SWAT">SWAT Team</ref>, patrol, and Street Crimes Unit, and a variety of assignments in the detective division.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> In 2011, Paulides received approval for a deferred vesting status totaling 16.5 years of service for his time with the San Jose Police Department.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Investigations</head>
<p>After leaving the police force, Paulides wrote books on the topic of Bigfoot, as well as on the disappearances of people in national parks and elsewhere which he attributes to unspecified, unknown causes.</p>
<head>Bigfoot or Sasquatch</head>
Main article: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bigfoot">Bigfoot</ref>
<p>In his pursuit of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bigfoot">Bigfoot</ref>, Paulides <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Self-publishing">self-published</ref> two Bigfoot-related books<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Hoopa-5">[5]</ref> and created the research group<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> called "North America Bigfoot Search"<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> for which he serves as director.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-CFI-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>Paulides has said North America Bigfoot Search was instrumental in the genesis of a paper published in 2013, which claimed that Bigfoot was real: "The world needs to understand that North America Bigfoot Search was the organizer of the study. We orchestrated the search that led to picking Dr. Ketchum to conduct a study of bigfoot DNA."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> The resulting paper documented the analysis of 111 samples of hypothesized Bigfoot <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DNA">DNA</ref> and was written by eleven different authors.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-CFI-8">[8]</ref> On November 24, 2012, DNA Diagnostics, a veterinary laboratory headed by Ketchum, issued a press release prior to peer review claiming that their DNA sequencing study confirmed the existence of a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hominini">hominin</ref> hybrid cross between modern humans with an unknown primate.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-CFI-8">[8]</ref> Shortly after publication two months later in the inaugural issue of <hi rend="italic">DeNovo: Journal of Science</hi>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-CFI-8">[8]</ref> the paper was analyzed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sharon_A._Hill">Sharon Hill</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sharon_A._Hill#Doubtfull_News">Doubtful News</ref> for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Committee_for_Skeptical_Inquiry">Committee for Skeptical Inquiry</ref>. Hill's report concluded that the paper was of poor quality, stating that "The few experienced geneticists who viewed the paper reported a dismal opinion of it, noting it made little sense."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-CFI-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Scientist_(magazine)">The Scientist</ref></hi> magazine also analyzed the paper, reporting that the analyses and data fail to support the claims of existence of a human-primate hybrid, but rather, "analyses either come back as 100 percent human, or fail in ways that suggest technical artifacts."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-thescientist-10">[10]</ref> The website for the DeNovo Journal of Science was setup[<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sic">sic</ref></hi>] on February 4, and there is no indication that Ketchum's work, the only study it has published, was peer reviewed.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-thescientist-10">[10]</ref> The paper failed to influence the scientific consensus that Bigfoot is a combination of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Folklore">folklore</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hoax">hoax</ref>, and misidentification of animals, particularly <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_black_bear">black bears</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-SI_Nickell-11">[11]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref></p>

<head><hi rend="italic">Missing 411</hi></head>
<p>Following his work on Bigfoot, Paulides' next project was <hi rend="italic">Missing 411</hi>, a series of self-published books and a documentary, documenting unsolved cases of people who have gone missing in national parks and elsewhere.</p>
<p>According to Paulides, his work on this subject began when he was doing research in a national park and an off-duty <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Park_ranger">park ranger</ref> found him and expressed concern about the questionable nature of some of the missing person cases which occurred in the parks. The ranger knew Paulides' background and requested for him to research the issue.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref> Paulides obliged, and asserts that he uncovered multiple lines of evidence suggesting negligence on the part of the park service in failing to locate the missing people.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref> He broadened his investigation to include missing people from across the world, and this led to his belief that he has uncovered a mysterious series of worldwide disappearances, which defied logical and conventional explanations.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[16]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-17">[17]</ref></p>
<p>As of 2018, Paulides has written eight books on this topic. According to <hi rend="italic">A Sobering Coincidence</hi>, he does not yet have a theory on what is causing the disappearances, although he indicates that the "field of suspects is narrowing." Paulides advised  his readers to go outside of their normal <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comfort_zone">comfort zone</ref> to determine who (or what) is the culprit.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-18">[18]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-19">[19]</ref></p>
<p>The interest in the book series prompted the creation of a documentary based on the <hi rend="italic">Missing 411</hi> books; this film was released in 2017.</p>
<p>Kyle Polich, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_scientist">data scientist</ref> and host of the <hi rend="italic">Data Skeptic</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Podcast">podcast</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DS-20">[20]</ref> documented his analysis of Paulides' claims in the article "Missing411"<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-21">[21]</ref> and presented his analysis to a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SkeptiCamp">SkeptiCamp</ref> held in 2017 by the Monterey County Skeptics.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-22">[22]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-SI-1">[1]</ref> He concluded that the allegedly unusual disappearances represent nothing unusual at all, and are instead best explained by non-mysterious causes such as falling or sudden health crises leading to a lone person becoming immobilized off-trail, drowning, bear (or other animal) attack, environmental exposure, or even deliberate disappearance. After analyzing the missing person data, Polich concluded that these cases are not "outside the frequency that one would expect, or that there is anything unexplainable that I was able to identify."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-23">[23]</ref> This presentation was discussed in a February 2017 article in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Skeptical_Inquirer">Skeptical Inquirer</ref></hi>, a publication of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Committee_for_Skeptical_Inquiry">CSI</ref>. In the article, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Susan_Gerbic">Susan Gerbic</ref> reported "Paulides ... gave no reason for these disappearances but finds odd <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Correlation_and_dependence">correlations</ref> for them. For example, two women missing in different years both had names starting with an "A" with three-letters, Amy and Ann.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-SI-1">[1]</ref> Polich concluded in his analysis: "I've exhausted my exploration for anything genuinely unusual. After careful review, to me, not a single case stands out nor do the frequencies involved seem outside of expectations."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Polich-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Books</head>
<head>Bigfoot</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">Hoopa Project: Bigfoot Encounters (2008)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Hoopa-5">[5]</ref></hi></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Tribal Bigfoot</hi> (2009)</item></list>
<head>Missing 411 Series</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">Missing 411 — Eastern United States: Unexplained Disappearances of North Americans That Have Never Been Solved</hi> (2012)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-MEast-24">[24]</ref></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Missing 411 — Western United States &amp; Canada: Unexplained Disappearances of North Americans that have never been solved</hi> (2012)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Missing 411 — North America and Beyond</hi> (2013)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Missing 411 — The Devil's in the Details</hi> (2014)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Missing 411 — A Sobering Coincidence</hi> (2015)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Missing 411 — Hunters</hi> (2016)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Missing 411 — Off the Grid</hi> (2017)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Missing 411 — Law</hi> (2018)</item></list>
<head>Documentaries</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">Missing 411</hi> (2017)</item></list>
</text>
