<text id="autogum_bio_doc283" title="Abgar Ali Akbar Armani" shortTile="abgar-ali-akbar-armani" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2019-05-10" dateModified="2019-05-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abgar_Ali_Akbar_Armani" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Abgar Ali Akbar Armani</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Abgar</hi> was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Armenians">Armenian</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Safavid_dynasty">Safavid Empire</ref> who lived during the reign of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shah">Shah</ref> (King) <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suleiman_of_Persia">Suleiman I</ref> (r.1666-1694). Originally a merchant, he later converted from Christianity to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shia_Islam">Shia Islam</ref> and took the name <hi rend="bold">Abgar Ali Akbar Armani</hi>. Over time, he became estranged from the Armenian community, and increasingly associated with members of the Safavid clergy and later married into their families. He wrote a conversion narrative in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Persian_language">Persian</ref>, the <hi rend="italic">Eterāfnāme</hi> ("Confession Book"), which was conceived perhaps as a missionary tool, and for circulation among Armenian Christians. According to Alberto Tibrucio, this work "fills an important gap as a rare example of a testimony narrated from the perspective of a convert and portraying a voluntary conversion".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETiburcio2018258-259-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>What little is known about his life is largely drawn from his work, the <hi rend="italic">Eterāfnāme</hi> ("Confession Book"). Born Abgar, possibly in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Julfa">New Julfa</ref>, the Armenian quarter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isfahan">Isfahan</ref>, he spent the early part of his life as a merchant. He may have been a member of either the renowned Velijanian (or Veligianian) merchant family of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Venice">Venice</ref> or the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sceriman_family">Sceriman (Shahremanian) family</ref>, although the latter is considered less likely. Around 1673, during the reign of Safavid Shah (King) Suleiman I, he converted from Christianity to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shia_Islam">Shia Islam</ref>, a decision which, according to his writings, was inspired by a scriptural evidence as well as a series of visions and dreams. At the time of his conversion, he had been in contact with the Armenian mayor (<hi rend="italic">kalāntar</hi>) of New Julfa, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hajji_Piri">Hajji Piri</ref>, who was also a convert.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETiburcio2018256-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Armani reportedly became estranged from his family after being branded an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apostate">apostate</ref>. His subsequent trip to Venice resulted in his imprisonment "in retaliation for allegations of mistreatment of Christians in Iran", but he was later released through the intervention of his brother. After his release, he journeyed to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman cities</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constantinople">Constantinople</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Belgrade">Belgrade</ref> before returning to Isfahan via the Safavid cities of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yerevan">Erivan</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tabriz">Tabriz</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mashhad">Mashhad</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETiburcio2018256-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>He is known to have married on numerous occasions and sired a number of children with his various wives.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETiburcio2018256-2">[2]</ref> After his conversion, he increasingly associated with members of the Safavid <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulama">ulama</ref></hi>, and would marry into their families.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETiburcio2018257-3">[3]</ref> His first wife, whom he met her during his journey, was the daughter of a judge and hailed from Constantinople.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETiburcio2018256-2">[2]</ref> According to Alberto Tiburcio, he was persecuted in Constantinople "for his assumed Shi'i allegiance as an Iranian".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETiburcio2018256-2">[2]</ref> However, it appears that at the time Armani was not yet an adherent of Shia Islam, at least not initially, but had developed a Shi'ite identity through the course of his journey.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETiburcio2018256-2">[2]</ref> In later life, his relations with the Armenian community would deteriorate to the point that he became a target of their persecution. Tiburcio wrote that, in retaliation, Armani "claims to have engaged in a quasi-ritual cursing of Armenian priests, leading to the death of the latter".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETiburcio2018257-3">[3]</ref>. Armani died sometime after 27 January 1708, possibly in Isfahan.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETiburcio2018256-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Work</head>
<p>Armani's work, the <hi rend="italic">Eterāfnāme</hi>, was completed on 27 January 1708 and was written entirely in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Persian_language">Persian</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETiburcio2018258-4">[4]</ref> Only one manuscript of this conversion narrative, consisting of 73 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Folio">folios</ref>, is extant and is stored in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Tehran">University of Tehran</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETiburcio2018258-4">[4]</ref> According to Tiburcio, the <hi rend="italic">Eterāfnāme</hi>, though written in Persian, was probably conceived as a missionary tool and for circulation among Armenian Christians "as far as the surviving evidence suggests".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETiburcio2018258-4">[4]</ref> Its prose is simple, yet "rich in symbolism", and describes Armani's conversion and travels.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETiburcio2018258-4">[4]</ref> His use of "oneiric elements" in his work to describe his "spiritual journey into Islam" has led Tiburcio to suggest that he had access to conversion narratives stemming from other milieus.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETiburcio2018258-4">[4]</ref> The work also includes the "standard" biblical reference to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paraclete">Paraclete</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gospel_of_John">Gospel of John</ref>, an example of inter-religious <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polemic">polemic</ref> often used in conversion narratives to express "proof" for Islam from the Bible.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETiburcio2018258-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Though the Persian chronicles, European travelogues and correspondences between Christian missionaries reveal that many converted from Christianity to Islam during the Safavid period, they only depict instances where the converts were either forced to convert or did so out of convenience.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETiburcio2018258-259-1">[1]</ref> Such accounts generally do not provide insights into the personal views of the converts.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETiburcio2018258-259-1">[1]</ref> According to Tiburcio, the <hi rend="italic">Eterāfnāme</hi> "fills an important gap as a rare example of a testimony narrated from the perspective of a convert and portraying a voluntary conversion".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETiburcio2018258-259-1">[1]</ref></p>
</text>
