<text id="autogum_interview_doc709" title="part5_Canada&amp;apos;s Beaches—East York (Ward 32) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-beacheseast" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-21" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Beaches%E2%80%94East_York_%28Ward_32%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="Luca_Mele"><ref target="http://www.etparty.com/">Luca Mele</ref></head>
<p>22-year-old <hi rend="bold">Luca Mele</hi> is the leader of the "<ref target="http://www.etparty.com/">Ecumenical Tribune Party</ref>" and recording artist/singer of signed band No Assembly Required.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Describe the three most important issues in your campaign.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> My main three points are crime, pollution and corruption. Crime and Pollution are a result of Corruption, and both corruption and pollution are crimes in my political party's platform.</p>
<p>I will enforce a 100% change of laws that are currently in support of the crime and pollution in the city of Toronto.</p>
<p>It is time we assemble groups to go out AT LEAST a few times a week to clean up our neighborhoods so that our crime and pollution reduces, 20 minutes to clean a day can make a huge difference when everyone is involved and working together to be the change.</p>
<p>Have members of each neigborhood come to the city hall council chamber meetings as often as possible and host weekly meetings in the ward for those who do not show up to city hall for the updates and info of what is being taking place at city hall.</p>
<p>Not enough people in the city are personally involved with the desicisons that are made for them and their community and I will cause that to change dramtically.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What one election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> All issues are relevant, however not for too much longer. The current structure is too unstable to generate issues of that level without a collapse.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> The best way to get things done is to do it yourself. Nobody has been able to make a change in politics, ever. The Political world is an immature joke, and it will learn to grow up soon.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent this particular ward on
council?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I feel ward 32 is one of the most beatiful water fronts of Ontario, and I want to improve on that by reducing the pollution and crime.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I belong to the G13 Mission of God, Church of the Universe, which started up in 1969 and now have a chapter of this church in the beaches neigborhood. Our work there is the same outside of the church and that is to help people by healing them with sacrements, meditations, cyrstals, and other forms of prayer.</p>
<p>I'm also releaseing a CD in stores across North America through Spinerazor and Universal records with my band 'No Assembly Required'. The CD is titled 'The Great Tribulation' and it is in relations to what you and everyone else are witnessing within this election and the events to come. We have toured around North America and have been playing in Toronto for over 7 years. Going to sell over 10,000 records in that time,</p>
</text>
