<text id="autogum_interview_doc537" title="part10_Billy West, voice of Ren and Stimpy, Futurama, on the rough start that shaped his life" shortTile="partbilly-west-voice" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-13" dateModified="2013-06-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Billy_West%2C_voice_of_Ren_and_Stimpy%2C_Futurama%2C_on_the_rough_start_that_shaped_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you believe in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Higher%20Power">higher power</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  Yes I do. I don’t know what it is. I just think its some higher form of energy and some sort of being, but I can’t embody it in my mind. But I know I have a one to one, kind of a spiritual connection to whatever that is. See I was raised, I had <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catholicism">Catholicism</ref> shoved down my throat. I was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/altar%20boy">altar boy</ref>. I knew the mass in Latin.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Me too.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  Really?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I didn’t know the mass in Latin, but I was an altar boy and I had Catholicism shoved down my face, but I’m 33, so <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second%20Vatican%20Council">Vatican II</ref> had happened.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  Yeah, and then you get "Father PreCum" trying to give you a massage and shit like that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  The priest at my church got a nun pregnant and my mother, who was the president of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parent-Teacher%20Association">PTA</ref> at my Catholic grade school, helped deliver the baby and keep the whole thing hidden.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  Really?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Yeah. And he’s still the priest.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  I think it’s probably a guy masquerading as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/nun">nun</ref>, if you’re talking about priests.</p>
<head id="West_on_his_career">West on his career</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Where do you see yourself now in your career?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  Exactly where I want to be. You know, I feel bad for kids who want to be <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Voice%20actor">voice-overs</ref>. They will always be needed. I always encourage them. They’re always going to need what you offer. And you can make a living if you’re really good. But there’s only so far you can go now. Before, the sky was the limit. There wasn’t these rigged fights standing in your way. 'Cause right now, it’s like a rigged fight. You can still audition and get great satisfaction on the job as a voiceover. And that’s all I ever really wanted to be.</p>
<p>But I did aspire to do animations that required voice work. And I’ve done some of it and then this trend set in. And believe me we don’t get the kind of money those people get for doing voices. It’s rather odd to me. At some point I realized many years ago—I was a teenager in the sixties, protesting with the long hair, running around with the hippies—I realized when I looked at all the guys we were supposed to hate so much and resent, I kind of analyzed what <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/complacency">complacency</ref> was, and they seemed complacent to me. They reached a point in their lives where they felt good about themselves and just cause a bunch of kids come along that were popping drugs and accusing you of this and that and being the man and everything, you think your feelings states are never going to change. And I used to say they’re complacent. But the thing is that everybody that’s born pretty much has to reach that point where they’re looking down the barrel of their own complacency. You gotta like do a little gear shifting.</p>
</text>
