<text id="autogum_interview_doc918" title="part3_Scientology protest group celebrates founder&amp;apos;s birthday worldwide" shortTile="partscientology-protest" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-05" dateModified="2019-02-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scientology_protest_group_celebrates_founder%27s_birthday_worldwide" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Anonymous distributed flyers and informed passers-by about Scientology. In a speech, they called for a dialogue with Scientology members, and said they were concerned for the parishioners' well-being:</p>
“
To the Scientologists who fear us: You have nothing to fear from our peaceful protests. We are here because we care about you. We demonstrate only against the abuses of the Church management and we stand by your individual freedom of religion.
”
<p><hi rend="italic">Operation: Party Hard - expect us, with cake</hi> was closed off with a birthday cake for the protesters.</p>
<p>Belgian media were in attendance with a film crew from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RTBF">RTBF</ref> interviewing several of the protesters and capturing their banners on tape. The slogans were mostly in English, ranging from "<hi rend="italic">Religion is free, Scientology isn't</hi>" to "<hi rend="italic">One billion years of servitude = super powers</hi>" — the latter a reference to the contracts that Scientologists sign when they become involved with the church's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sea%20Org">Sea Org</ref>.</p>
<p>The police presence was low-key with only one senior officer and a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Belgian%20State%20Security%20Service">Belgian intelligence services</ref> who took photographs.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Brussels Gallery</hi></p>
<list type="unordered">
<item style="width: 155px;">The protesters arrive at the Stock Exchange and start folding flyers.</item>
<item style="width: 155px;"><hi rend="italic">Anonymous</hi> members, wearing the black uniform with red tie, discuss Scientology with passers-by.</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">A volunteer speaks to a group of youngsters.</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">Pedestrians were given flyers about Scientology and its practices.</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">Protester with sign saying: <hi rend="italic">Tom Cruise can't fly, you guys</hi></item>
<item style="width: 155px;">A protester shows his banner to the press.</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">The group brings the global speech.</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">Anonymous sings a birthday song for L. Ron Hubbard, Scientology's founder...</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">...followed by birthday cake for the protesters.</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">We get offered cake, decorated with a card that criticises Scientology.</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">Protesters eating cake.</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">By the end of the demonstration, the police asks Anonymous to leave.</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">At Scientology's headquarters, an alleged 'open door day' celebrates the declaration of human rights.</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">A Scientologist waiting to hand out flyers.</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">Scientology's headquarter is located in Law Street no. 91, in the political heart of Brussels.</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">An exposition inside the Scientology building proudly displays the IRS ruling over Scientology's tax-exempt status under the header "U.S government recognition". The second panel is devoted to international recognition.</item>
</list>
<head id="London,_England"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/London">London</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/England">England</ref></head>
<p><hi rend="italic">Correspondents: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Adambro">Adambro</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Skenmy">Skenmy</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:JamesHarrison">JamesHarrison</ref></hi></p>
<p>Once more, protests took place outside of both the Queen Victoria Scientology Headquarters and the Tottenham Court Road Dianetics centre. The additional time available for protesters in the aftermath of a rushed February 10th protest allowed the many of Anonymous to expand their protest to include even more outreach towards members of the public, with Anonymous members handing out free cake, sweets and other confectionery along with leaflets and stickers to passers-by.</p>
<p>Signage was loud and varied, proclaiming a variety of messages to the public and Scientologists. Many of the signs declared amusing yet pointed comments, with others making more serious jabs at the Church of Scientology.</p>
</text>
