<text id="autogum_whow_doc293" title="Tell if Something Is Gum" shortTile="tell-something-gum" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2010-04-12" dateModified="2018-02-18" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Tell-if-Something-Is-Gum" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Tell if Something Is Gum</head><p>Often, people everywhere find themselves faced with a deceptively simple question: is this gum? It is a question that can arise anywhere, whether it be on the bottom of your shoe, the handle of your locker at school, or even in your hair while you lie in bed at night. These steps will provide you with all you need to know about how to tell if something is gum.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Don't make assumptions. Arrogance has been the downfall of many otherwise intelligent people--don't get yourself into trouble by assuming something is or isn't gum. But use your common sense. Only if something has the general appearance of gum do these instructions become necessary. Before taking any risky action yourself, ask a friend or relative to help determine whether what you're dealing with is gum. If no one is available, try getting a pet to eat the substance and see how your pet reacts. If you've tried these and you still can't tell, proceed to Step Two. <figure rend="Tell if Something Is Gum Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Smell it. Usually, the aroma of a substance can tell you whether or not something is gum. If it smells minty, sweet, or, even sometimes fruity, it is quite possible that it is gum. However, this is not a definitive test. While most things that are not gum do not smell like gum, it is quite possible that the smell has simply faded. In fact, if gum is particularly old, it could have no smell at all. Do not be ashamed if your nose is insufficient for performing this test; John Quincy Adams had no sense of smell at all. He was rarely photographed from the waist down for this very reason. With such a great leader for an example, there is no reason your inability to smell should make you feel inadequate. This is when Step Three comes into play. <figure rend="Tell if Something Is Gum Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Feel it. If the substance is soft and malleable, yet slightly sticky,the chances of it being gum will greatly increase. But be careful! Remember our mantra from Step One: guessing makes an ass out of you and me. Sometimes, Silly Putty will have these same properties, yet it is still not gum. If you are still unsure, proceed to the last step. It is said that Harrison Ford used this test on the set of his classic movie "Air Force One" in a particularly trying conundrum of whether or not something was gum. <figure rend="Tell if Something Is Gum Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Taste it. Truly, this is the final test of whether or not something is gum. There is no denying the unmistakable flavor of this precious sap bestowed upon us by the red-skinned savages of early America (the scientific name of the tree being Manilkara zapota). This satisfying and occasionally delicious trial will put to rest all apprehensions, rumors, and myths surrounding whether or not something is gum. <figure rend="Tell if Something Is Gum Step 4.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
