<text id="autogum_academic_doc184" title="Diffusion of Resveratrol in Silica Alcogels" shortTile="diffusion-resveratrol" author="Yuxiang Wang, Zeyu Kao, Ting Zhang, Yujun Zhang, Lili Qin, Zhihua Zhang, Bin Zhou, Guangming Wu, Jun Shen, Ai Du" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1420-3049/24/21/3931/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Academic editor: Alejandro Sosnik </p>

<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>Drug-delivery systems are difficult to design as there exist various mechanisms that are involved in the release processes of drug. Various factors need to be considered for drug delivery, such as the degree of absorption or the diffusion limitations of the drug in the medium. In recent years, the use of porous silica materials in drug delivery has attracted a lot of interest due to its potential for the development of systems that are site-specific and that offer time-dependent controlled delivery. Given in particular their non-toxic properties, silica aerogels are a special kind of porous silica materials consisting of highly mesoporous nanostructures. The porous structure make the aerogels have many special properties, such as low density (1000 kg/m3 to about 1 kg/m3), high porosity (~99%) and inner surface area (1000 m2/g), which is necessary for efficient drug loading. In addition, silica aerogels can be grafted with various groups by surface modification, which could deliver the drug to targeted regions. </p>

<p>Trans-resveratrol (RSV), whose full name is non-flavonoid phytoalexin trans-resveratrol, has many biological functions by virtue of its antibacterial, anti-inflammatory, anticancer, anti-thrombosis, anti-hyperlipidemia and anti-lipid peroxidation characteristics. These functions determined resveratrol has many supplementations in treatment of cancer, diabetes, skin disorders and so on. In this paper, silica aerogel and RSV was chosen as a carrier and a model drug, respectively. Drug-delivery vehicles based on aerogels can be prepared by different methods, such as the addition of the drug during the conventional sol–gel process or during the post treatment of the synthesized aerogels. We added the drug during the aging process in this work. The alcogel was brought into contactwith an aging solution which contains the RSV, and then the drug diffused into the alcogel pores from the aging solution. The diffusion rate depends on many factors, such as the size of the molecules and pores, and the initial concentration of the aging solution. It must be emphasized that the role of ethanol was simply to dissolve the drug and allow it to diffuse into the alcogel. </p>

<p>Most research focuses only on the total drug loading content, but ignores the drug distribution and load mode in the carrier. Moreover, drug-loading behaviors are commonly studied using adsorption isotherms and adsorption kinetic equations. However, diffusion also play an important role in the drug-loading process, and we should consider both the effects of diffusion and adsorption/desorption. So in this work, based on previous study, we have established a fundamental model to study the distribution of a drug in the alcogel and the interaction of diffusion and adsorption/desorption. </p>

<p>In this paper, RSV-loaded silica aerogel (RLSA) was prepared by freeze-drying. The reason we used freeze drying instead of supercritical drying is that the RSV will lose ethanol during the slow replacement process in supercritical drying. A series of characterizations were carried to compare the differences of silica aerogel and RLSA, and better understand the loading mode of the drug in silica aerogel. Furthermore, by establishing different boundary conditions and using Fick’s second law to fit the apparent diffusion coefficient (the apparent diffusion coefficients are all marked as “diffusion coefficient” in the manuscript hereafter for simplicity), three kinds of diffusion processes were studied. This facilitates the precise design of the drug-loading and -release system. </p>

<head> 2. Results and Discussion</head>
<head> 2.1. The Characterization of Silica Aerogel and Trans-Resveratrol (RSV)-Loaded Silica Aerogel (RLSA)</head>
<p><figure>Figure 1</figure>a shows the appearance of silica aerogel and RLSA after freeze drying. The mass of both is 200 mg. We can see that the volume of the RLSA is larger than silica aerogel, and the color becomes more opaque. A transmission electron microscope (TEM) image of silica aerogel shows that it is a dense structure formed by the accumulation of spherical particles, which is consistent with a scanning electron microscope (SEM) image. Compared with the silica aerogel after supercritical drying, its skeleton structure is denser and the density is larger. However, the pore size is smaller and most of it consists of micropores. The structure of RSV has a long rod shape with the size on the order of micrometers shown in <figure>Figure 1</figure>e. It can be seen from <figure>Figure 1</figure>c,f that the recrystallized RSV with a micron-sized long rod shape is integrated with the dense silica network skeleton. This is may be due to the RSV dissolving into small molecules in an ethanol solution, which can diffuse into the pores of silica alcogel. However, RSV precipitates due to minimal solubility in water during solvent replacement. After freeze drying, the solvent evaporates and the RSV recrystallizes. </p>
</text>
