<text id="autogum_interview_doc210" title="part11_BDSM as business: Interviews with Dominatrixes" shortTile="partbdsm-business" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-28" dateModified="2008-01-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BDSM_as_business%3A_Interviews_with_Dominatrixes" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That seems cliché.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  Yeah, it’s cliché.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  If people come in with post-traumatic stress disorder, are there special considerations?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  Yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Yes, I think we’ve dealt with a lot of people who have those issues.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  I can’t say I have had anyone who wanted to re-enact an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abu%20Ghraib">Abu Ghraib</ref> experience, though.</p>
<head id="Boundaries">Boundaries</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are there places you just won’t go?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  Psychological?  No.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What about physically?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  Yes, I have my boundaries, but I prefer not to define them.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  I think everyone does.  It would always depend, it would be difficult to state what would be my boundary.  One minute it can be one thing, and another client might come in and say, “Can you do this, this and that,” and the answer is no.  [Laughs]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Have you ever had a session where you felt threatened?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  No.  I feel quite safe here, because they know we outnumber them.  Okay, in terms of boundaries, if I’m a sub and the man is a dom, I don’t let him blindfold me AND put a gag in my mouth, because then there is no way to tell what he is going to do and alert anyone.  There are certain safe words that you use, and if people don’t respect those boundaries then you remind them of the boundaries or else you can end the session.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Have you had to end a session?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  Yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Can you tell me about a time?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  One time somebody was really forceful about wanting to see my panties.  It was a trampling session, where you step on his face.    He wanted me to step on his face, but he <hi rend="italic">didn't</hi> want me to step on his face, he wanted to look up my skirt.  So I ended the session and I told him I knew that he was doing that, because every time I tried to step on his face he would move it and try to look up my skirt.  So I ended it.  He was an asshole.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Will you do full nudity?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  No.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  No.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Topless?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  Yeah, it’s pretty common that we are topless.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is full nudity uncommon?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  No, I don’t think so.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why do you prefer not to do it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  I just don’t feel comfortable, and if I don’t feel comfortable I just don’t do it.  And I think a lot of people will do that because they want to please the customer and have them come back, but ultimately I don’t think that is good for you psychologically.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Yes, if you are not 100% with everything you do, then it’s going to affect you.</p>
</text>
