<text id="autogum_voyage_doc262" title="Laos" shortTile="laos" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=19089" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Laos</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.tourismlaos.org/">Laos</ref></hi> (ສປປ ລາວ), officially known as the <hi rend="bold">Lao People's Democratic Republic</hi> (ສາທາລະນະລັດ ປະຊາທິປະໄຕ ປະຊາຊົນລາວ) (<hi rend="bold">Lao PDR</hi>), is a nation in <ref target="Southeast%20Asia">Southeast Asia</ref>, known for its mountainous terrain, French colonial architecture, hill tribe settlements, and Buddhist monasteries. A mountainous and landlocked country, Laos shares borders with <ref target="Vietnam">Vietnam</ref> to the east, <ref target="Cambodia">Cambodia</ref> to the south, <ref target="Thailand">Thailand</ref> to the west, and <ref target="Myanmar">Myanmar</ref> and <ref target="China">China</ref> to the north.</p>
<head>Cities</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> — the still sleepy capital on the banks of the Mekong River</item>
<item> — in the north, on the Mekong and the border with Thailand</item>
<item> — capital of the north, known for its trekking</item>
<item> — a UNESCO World Heritage City known for its numerous temples, colonial era architecture, and vibrant night market</item>
<item> — also known as Oudomxay, the capital of the multi-ethnic province of Oudomxay</item>
<item> — halfway point on the overnight slow boat between Huay Xai and Luang Prabang</item>
<item> — gateway to the Wat Phu ruins and the "four thousand islands" (Si Phan Don)</item>
<item> — in the south on the Mekong, connected by bridge to Mukdahan in Thailand</item>
<item> — a popular base for exploring Phou Hin Boun National Park including the famous Konglor Cave</item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> — a two-day ecotourism trek in the north of Laos</item>
<item> — highland with waterfalls, jungles and farmland</item>
<item> — Wat Phu is a UNESCO World Heritage Site with Angkor-style Khmer temples</item>
<item> — beautiful karst cliffs where you can discover hilltribe villages, kayak, bike ride or just hang out</item>
<item> — Iron Age cemetery sites near Phonsavan; also one of the main locations to learn about the "Secret War".</item>
<item> — the "four thousand islands" are nestled within the Mekong near the Cambodian border</item>
<item> — backpacker hangout for exploring limestone caves and tubing on the Nam Song river</item>
<item> — remote cultural oasis and symbolic cradle of Marxism; see the caves where the Pathet Lao leaders ran their operations in defiance of the West</item>
</list>


<head>Understand</head>
 

<p>Laos is the only landlocked country in Southeasia Asia and the most sparsely populated. Unlike most countries an Asia, the country has not undergone a major industrialisation and modernisation period; as result, lifestyle remains mostly rural and true large cities are absent. An adjective often applied to Laos is "forgotten", but contrary to what advertised by travel agencies, it is hard to say this applies to tourism as well: Laos gets a number of international visitors only 20% lesser than the <ref target="Philippines">Philippines</ref>, which has a population 15 times bigger than Laos.</p>

<p>Therefore, travellers lured by the prospect of visiting an untouched "Shangri-la" are likely to be disappointed; in fact, cities like <ref target="Luang%20Prabang">Luang Prabang</ref>, <ref target="Nong%20Khiaw">Nong Khiaw</ref> and <ref target="Vang%20Vieng">Vang Vieng</ref> are heavily tourist-oriented. On the other hand, Laos can be extremely rewarding for those who are instead drawn by the laid-back lifestyle and the opportunity to knock back a few cold Beerlao while watching the sunsets on the Mekong. Perhaps one of the biggest attractions of Laos is the famous "Lao PDR" - <hi rend="italic">Lao-Please Don't Rush</hi>.</p>

<head>History</head>

<p>Laos is squeezed between vastly larger neighbours. First created as an entity in 1353, when warlord Fa Ngum declared himself the king of <hi rend="bold">Lane Xang</hi> ("Million Elephants"), the kingdom was initially a <ref target="Cambodia">Khmer</ref> vassal state. After a succession dispute, the kingdom split in three in 1694 and was eventually devoured piece by piece by the Siamese, the last fragments agreeing to Siamese protection in 1885.</p>

<p>The area east of the Mekong, however, was soon wrenched back from Siam by the French, who wanted a buffer state to protect Vietnam, and set up Laos as a unified territory in 1907. Briefly occupied by Japan in 1945, a three-decade-long conflict was triggered when France wanted to retake its colony. Granted full independence in 1953, the war continued between a bewildering variety of factions, with the Communist and North Vietnam-allied <hi rend="bold">Pathet Lao</hi> struggling to overthrow the French-leaning monarchy. During the Vietnam War (1964-1973), this alliance led the United States to dump 1.9 million tonnes of bombs on Laos, mostly in the northeast stronghold of the Pathet Lao: as a comparison 2.2 million tonnes were dropped on Europe by all sides during World War II.</p>

<p>In 1975, after the fall of Saigon, the Communist Pathet Lao took control of Vientiane and ended a six-century-old monarchy. Initial closer ties to Vietnam and socialization were replaced with a gradual return to private enterprise, an easing of foreign investment laws and admission into ASEAN in 1997.</p>

<p>Despite being just one hour by air from the hustle and bustle of <ref target="Bangkok">Bangkok</ref>, life in Laos has continued in much the same way it has for hundreds of years, although things are now slowly beginning to change. In the mid-1990s the government reversed its stance on tourism, and then declared 1998 "Visit Laos Year". Since then, tourists in Laos have been rising every year.</p>

<p>In 2017, Laos and <ref target="China">China</ref> started the construction of a high speed rail linking <ref target="Kunming">Kunming</ref> to <ref target="Vientiane">Vientiane</ref>. When (and if) complete, the rail connection is expected to have a dramatical impact on the country; Kunming itself has a population 8 times bigger than Vientiane, and in fact, comparable to the entire population of Laos, while only the province of <ref target="Yunnan">Yunnan</ref> has a population about 7 times bigger than the population of Laos. It is likely that the face of tourism in the country will drastically change, and the word "forgotten" used to describe Laos will become a forgotten memory itself</p>

<head>Culture</head>
<p>Despite its small population, Laos has 49 ethnic groups, or tribes, from which Lao, Khmou and Hmong constitute approximately three-quarters of the population. Most tribes are small, with some having just a few hundred members. The ethnic groups are divided into four linguistic branches: Lao-Tai language represented by 8 tribes, Mone-Khmer language with 32 tribes, Hmoung-Loumien language with 2 tribes, and Tibeto-Chinese language represented by 7 tribes.</p>

<p>Laos is officially Buddhist, and the national symbol, the gilded stupa of <ref target="Vientiane%23See">Pha That Luang</ref>, has replaced the hammer and sickle even on the state seal. Still, there is a good deal of animism mixed in, particularly in the <hi rend="bold">baci</hi> (also <hi rend="italic">baasi</hi>) ceremony conducted to bind the 32 guardian spirits to the participant's body before a long journey, after serious illness, the birth of a baby, or other significant events.</p>

<p>Lao custom dictates that women must wear the distinctive <hi rend="italic">phaa sin</hi>, a long sarong available in many regional patterns; however, many ethnic minorities have their own clothing styles. The conical Vietnamese-style hat is also a common sight. These days men dress Western-style and only don the <hi rend="italic">phaa biang</hi> sash on ceremonial occasions. Nowadays women often wear Western-style clothing, though the "phaa sin" is still the mandatory attire in government offices, not only for those who work there but also for Lao women who are visiting.</p>
</text>
