<text id="autogum_interview_doc820" title="part5_Satanism: An interview with Church of Satan High Priest Peter Gilmore" shortTile="partsatanism-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-04" dateModified="2018-10-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Satanism%3A_An_interview_with_Church_of_Satan_High_Priest_Peter_Gilmore" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Capital punishment is not antithetical to Satanism.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  Not necessarily, but essentially we would rather shrink from the government having the power to take you and murder you, because we don't have a lot of confidence in people being rational, or being truthful, and we have seen so often—especially with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DNA%20testing">DNA testing</ref>—that a lot of people have been jailed and accused of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/murder">murder</ref> and they were wrong.  That’s wrongful.  So it’s not this broad, “We accept capital punishment and it’s fine!”</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  “Slaughter them all!” [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  Right!  But there are certain situations where it would be appropriate.  Say, when <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colin%20Ferguson%20(mass%20murderer)">Colin Ferguson</ref> shot all those people.  There should be absolutely no time wasted on that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But should it be the government doing it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  I think the government can have the ability but under control.  There needs to be <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/checks%20and%20balances">checks and balances</ref>.  That whole idea in the United States that has come from so many other past forms of government is something we feel is necessary.  We don't want any form of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/megalomaniacal">megalomaniacal</ref> government with absolute power that can do anything willy-nilly to its citizens.  Satanists are generally <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Libertarian">Libertarians</ref>.  They may choose their specific political alliances because it might better whatever they are trying to do in their lives, but essentially most of us are fairly libertarian people.  We would like to have government as minimal as possible.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you have a 10 Commandments?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  We have the 9 Satanic Statements, but we don't have commandments that are laws that are like sins.  We have eleven sins that are kind of behaviors that we don't want to be doing.  For us, we try to create a situation where we have some social interaction with people that can be beneficial for ourselves.  But we don't set up these kinds of laws that somebody is going to punish you for.  So with Satanism they are things where you kick yourself and say, “Why did I do something stupid? I shouldn't do that next time.”  It's better for you.  It doesn't matter about anybody else on that level: you’ve got to not be an ass.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are there certain sites or places that are important to the Church of Satan?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  No, we don't really have any holy ground or anything like that.  For the Satanist, if there is any kind of architecture you like, or a place you like to visit—some people like places with devil themes or where there is historical interest.  But there is nothing particularly Satanic about any location.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  No place with a natural significance?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  Well, it’s the universe.  We look at it like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carl%20Sagan">Carl Sagan</ref> and we are star stuff, we are made of the stuff of exploding stars.  We Satanists look at the universe in this wonderful context of that’s what we are part of and that’s really exciting.  We don't need to single out any special part of it unless you find a place you really enjoy.  The place you were born, perhaps, or the place you grew up.  Some people are interested in a historical figure and say the place where a castle was built or a particular battle was fought, or some individual took a last stand.</p>
</text>
