<text id="autogum_interview_doc311" title="part4_Interview with Sue Gardner of the Wikimedia Foundation" shortTile="partinterview-sue" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-19" dateModified="2012-01-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Sue_Gardner_of_the_Wikimedia_Foundation" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">SG:</hi>  I use a lot of different sources. I think it would be difficult to rely solely—or even primarily—on Wikinews, because I don't think it is yet particularly comprehensive; I don't know if it ever will be. I'd be interested to know what you think of that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Brian: Wikinews may become comprehensive but it will be a difficult process in my opinion.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Matt: Do you think the reason for this is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/wikigroaning">wikigroaning</ref>, such as more topics are written in focused areas rather than things of interest to the most people?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SG:</hi>  I agree. And I'm not sure whether or not it should be a goal of the organization. Can I talk for just a second about one of the ways I think news is changing?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Brian: It is a "faster" project than Wikipedia.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SG:</hi>  I have never heard of wikigroaning, what an interesting word. But it makes sense to me that Wikinews would reflect the interests of the people who edit it, which I imagine is one of the reasons it (and the other WMF projects) are successful. (Again, the relevance-to-audience issue.) But regarding news... I think it used to be the case that there was X amount of shelf space for news—like, 40 pages of newsprint daily, or 22 minutes of television time. So whether it was a busy news day or a slow news day, that was the amount of news that got created. And professional journalism is still pretty much constructed that way. So if a media outlet has a reporter in Johannesburg, they get a lot of news out of South Africa, whether or not anything particularly interested is happening there. You have x shelf space and x resources. What I think changes—theoretically—with Wikinews, is that you are freed of both those constraints. You have limitless shelf space and very flexible resources. Which means, in theory, that you can cover lots of stories when there are lots of stories to cover, and do very little, when there isn't much going on. So I think this is very interesting. And I think it has implications for the future of news. People should consume news when there's something interesting to read about. And I think Wikinews has enormous potential on big stories. I am very interested to see how that plays out.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Matt: You may be interested in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews:NOT#What_Wikinews_is_not">What Wikinews is not</ref>, the first point, Wikinews is not Paper</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SG:</hi>  Yes, precisely. And when there is a big story, lots of people come here to help, I assume.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Brian: We got great cooperation on some big stories like the UK attacks, did big media notice? (<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Major_explosions_at_UK_oil_depot">Major explosions at UK oil depot</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Coordinated_terrorist_attack_hits_London">Coordinated terrorist attack hits London</ref>)</hi></p>
</text>
