<text id="autogum_interview_doc550" title="part2_Ingrid Newkirk, co-founder of PETA, on animal rights and the film about her life" shortTile="partingrid-newkirk" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-20" dateModified="2018-02-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ingrid_Newkirk%2C_co-founder_of_PETA%2C_on_animal_rights_and_the_film_about_her_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  That’s like saying to an organization set up to help the homeless, “Is it true you are more concerned with the homeless than people with mansions?”  Yes.  Obviously we are set up to help the non-humans who don’t have anybody speaking for them because there are countless organizations set up to help humans.  Humans can often invariably help themselves.  They may have <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minimum%20wage">lower wages</ref> than they should or be disrespected; they may have all sorts of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Human%20suffering">hardships</ref>, but they are not labeled <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pork%20chops">chops</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chicken%20nuggets">nuggets</ref> and doomed from the moment they are born to be cut up without anesthesia or used as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Test%20tubes">test tubes</ref>.  Once in a while you find the military used people against their will, and in the old days orphans were used in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tuberculosis">Tuberculosis</ref> experiments here in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20York%20State">New York</ref>.  But it doesn’t happen as a matter of being born getting a label as something you can cut up and deprive of life just for a fleeting pleasure.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Jim Young, one of the lab people with the really red ears—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  Oh, yeah, that was great!  It was fascinating, something like a science experiment!  Like radioactive ears.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Everyone was looking at them.  One of the things he had said was that you want to completely disassociate animals with humans.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  No, I want to more <hi rend="italic">closely</hi> associate humans with the <hi rend="italic">other</hi> animals, because if we took Biology 101 we know we are all animals.  It’s just that we decide we’re gods, they’re trash.  That’s just invalid, wrong from every point of perspective: scientific, moral and everything else.  I want people to <hi rend="italic">relate</hi> to the other animals.  It’s a matter of discrimination and prejudice to make us decide in the past that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Americans%20with%20Disabilities%20Act">disabled people</ref> aren’t as important as we are, or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Racial%20discrimination">somebody’s skin color</ref> was different and we could  exploit them.  Now it’s that we aren’t the same species so we can treat them like dirt.  It’s not logical that we do that, because we are all flesh and blood and feel pain, suffering, joy, love and all those things.  I think we have to come to terms with the fact that we are all in this life, on this Earth, with lots of other different individuals.  What was that, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Restaurant%20at%20the%20End%20of%20the%20Universe">The Restaurant at the End of the Universe</ref>?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Douglas%20Adams">Douglas Adams</ref>’ <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hitchhiker’s%20Guide%20to%20the%20Galaxy">Hitchhiker’s Guide to the Galaxy</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  Yes!  We go into space and we look for other species and we say we come in peace on the side of the space capsule...a bunch of hooey!  If we find them and they are vulnerable, we’ll experiment on them; we’ll taste them and make things out of them.  We’ll haul them back here as trinkets and trophies just as we do in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List%20of%20extinct%20animals%20of%20Africa">Africa</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fauna%20of%20India">India</ref> where we find bears and monkeys we put in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/zoo">zoo</ref>.  Animals we want to use for decoration.  We have to come to grips with the fact that we are behaving peculiarly towards the others and they are part of life itself, with us.  I don’t want to separate them.  I want to bring us together!</p>
</text>
