<text id="autogum_reddit_doc146" title="What are the justifications for banning rifle sales to people who are between 18-21 years of age?" shortTile="justifications-banning" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-03-30" dateModified="2018-03-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/887oz1" speakerList="#RomanNumeralVI, #rbalabama" speakerCount="2">
<head>What are the justifications for banning rifle sales to people who are between 18-21 years of age?</head>
<sp who="#RomanNumeralVI">
<p>The Parkland shooting was by a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stoneman_Douglas_High_School_shooting#Nikolas_Cruz">nineteen year old</ref>. Walmart will no longer sell rifles to to those younger than age 21 <ref target="https://www.ajc.com/news/national/walmart-raising-age-buy-guns-after-florida-high-school-shooting/saZakVUhxG73DCxJJDc9rI/">in the "*light of recent events*".</ref> What are the justifications to deny those between the ages of 18-21 the right to purchase a rifle? A number of thoughtful reviews <ref target="https://www.washingtonexaminer.com/is-trumps-push-for-an-ar-15-age-limit-constitutional">like this one</ref> do not offer any justification for such a ban, they just discuss  <hi rend="bold">if this ban is legal</hi> . What is the  <hi rend="bold">justification</hi>  for denying them this right? Federal law includes several different age limits for gun purchases. <ref target="http://www.latimes.com/politics/la-na-pol-trump-guns-20180225-story.html">Licensed gun dealers cannot sell a handgun to a person younger than 21, but can sell a rifle to anyone 18 or older. Unlicensed sellers, such as those at gun shows, can sell handguns to those 18 or older and rifles regardless of age.</ref>\</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#rbalabama">
<p>“Twenty-four shootings — nearly one in six — occurred after a confrontation or verbal argument intensified, because of the presence of a gun.” </p>
<p>https: everytownresearch.org reports analysis-of-school-shootings </p>
<p>That's one answer to your question. </p>
<p>Maybe an angry 18 year old shouldn't have easy access to a semi-automatic weapon of any kind. We haven't been able to intelligently discuss this because our government wasn’t allowed to fund a study of the question you asked. I believe that is of significant interest to us if we are going to seriously have this discussion. The very reason we are justified is that the people with money in the game were paying those making those decisions. It's always about the money. </p>
<p>Instead this posting will be bombarded by platitudes from both sides. Is there justification? Kids are getting killed with a greater frequency than I am comfortable with. I've heard various stats... </p>
<p>“We were informed, for example, that since 2013 there has been an average of one school shooting a week in the U.S., and 18 since the beginning of this year. While these statistics were not exactly lies or fake news, they involved stretching the definition of a school shooting well beyond the limits of most people’s imagination.” </p>
<p>https: www.usatoday.com story opinion 2018 02 19 parkland-school-shootings-not-new-normal-despite-statistics-stretching-truth-fox-column 349380002 </p>
<p>How many attacks does it take to justify an independent investigation? We know we can’t have congress do that - absolutely no one will believe their side lost fairly. The corporations will volunteer but blue states wouldn't like that just as much as if we wanted the deep state to do that. You might recall that is what they were set up to do. Our own government is no longer trusted to produce an analysis of the issue. Who would you trust to decide if semi-automatic weapons should be sold to 18 year olds?</p>
</sp>
</text>
