<text id="autogum_academic_doc620" title="Role of Wild Boar in the Spread of Classical Swine Fever in Japan" shortTile="role-wild-boar-spread" author="Satoshi Ito, Cristina Jurado, Jaime Bosch, Mitsugi Ito, José  Manuel Sánchez-Vizcaíno, Norikazu Isoda, Yoshihiro Sakoda" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-0817/8/4/206/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Discussion</head>
<p>
From 2018 until August 2019, all notifications of CSF outbreaks in Japan have been made in Gifu Prefecture as well as in the surrounding four prefectures. A total of 1110 notifications had been reported so far, with 1071 affecting wild boar and 39 affecting domestic pig farms. The continuous notification of CSF in the area might have been attributed to wide spread of the virus within wild boar populations favored by free animal movements, as well as to the emergence of epidemiologically related domestic pig farms. To prevent the disease spreading in wild boar, control measures including (i) fencing to restrict animal movements, (ii) hunting activities for active monitoring and to reduce susceptible populations, and (iii) disseminating baits for oral immunization, were implemented. However, the efficacy of these strategies has not been confirmed. Therefore, we conducted a spatio-temporal analysis to obtain epidemiological information of the spread of CSF in Gifu Prefecture. Results from this analysis could help to increase our understanding of the current CSF epidemic and to contribute strategies for the containment of the disease in domestic pigs and wild boar.  </p>

<p>Japan is an island country that has achieved the status of freedom from several contagious animal diseases by implementing adequate control measures that take advantage of the country’s geography. Nevertheless, Japan has imported outbreaks of contagious animal diseases from neighboring countries. In 2010, there was an outbreak of foot-and-mouth disease (FMD) in Miyazaki Prefecture in the southern part of Japan, which caused extensive losses in animal husbandry. According to the high degree of sequence homology between an original virus isolated in Japan and viruses that were circulating widely in East Asia, it was suspected that the FMD virus might have been introduced via movement of people or commodities from East Asia. The high homology of genetic sequences between the CSF virus isolated in Japan and viruses prevailing in China suggests that the infectious CSF virus may have been introduced from China. Potential factors that could have contributed to disease introduction include easy access from the international airport to the affected area, which has regular and direct flights from China, and the relatively high population density of Chinese people in the affected area.  </p>

<p>In the present study, standard deviational ellipse analysis was conducted to measure the standard distance of CSF notifications. Shifting the centroids of identified ellipses indicated that the disease notification has spread in a northeast direction. Overlaying the three identified ellipses with a map of snowfall area in Gifu Prefecture revealed that the disease spread along the border of the snowfall area. In the south of Gifu Prefecture, there is a widespread area of flat land with field crops or animal farms, residential areas, and forests surrounded by mountains to the north. As suggested by other authors, wild boar do not move to the snowfall or high mountain areas. Therefore, mountains could have acted as an effective geographical barrier to limit wild boar movements and guide the direction of the spread of CSF.  </p>

<p>Another concern regarding the spread of the disease is the potential for it to jump to remote areas. During the epidemic, CSFV infections were confirmed on seven farms that were geographically distant from, but epidemiologically linked, to the farms affected by CSFV (i.e., run by the same owner, supported by the same husbandry company, etc.). Given the potential for transmission of the virus between pigs on any farms or from wild boar near that farm, the epidemiologically related farms may further expand the spread of disease. This “disordered” spread of disease could affect the accuracy of spatio-temporal analysis by overestimating the maximum distance of significant spatial association between notifications. During the FMD epidemic in Miyazaki, the disease was confirmed 70 km away from the zone of movement restriction, which could have been caused by vehicle transportation. Unexpected occurrences of disease in epidemiologically related farms would require reviewing farm biosecurity measures, as well as disease monitoring protocols.  </p>

<p>In the present study, the results of the multi-distance spatial cluster analysis revealed that the maximum distance of relationship between CSF notifications was 23 km. Because of the small number of CSF outbreaks on domestic pig farms, we estimated the maximum distance of the relationship between notifications of domestic pigs and wild boar. This assumption could have influenced our estimated distance resulting in overestimation due to long distance spread observed on domestic pig farms. Nevertheless, similar approaches have studied another transboundary animal disease, African swine fever (ASF), which shares hosts and most of the transmission mechanisms with CSF. When comparing our results with other studies, the estimated distance (23 km) was similar to that obtained for notifications of ASF in domestic pigs (15 km) and wild boar (25 km) in Sardinia. This finding may be useful for setting the range of effective surveillance and control zones in the affected area. </p>
</text>
