<text id="autogum_interview_doc259" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Aurélien Miralles about Sirenoscincus mobydick species discovery" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-01-21" dateModified="2013-04-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Aur%C3%A9lien_Miralles_about_Sirenoscincus_mobydick_species_discovery" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<figure><caption> Illustration from an early edition of Moby-Dick. Image: A. Burnham Shute.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How deep underground do the lizards live?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM</hi>: Hard to answer this question because nothing is known on the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ecology">ecology</ref> of this species. But more reasonably, we can hypothesize, by comparison to similar species of skinks, that it is probably living just under the sand surface, [a] few centimeters deep, probably no more, or below [a] rock, leaf litter, or piece of dead wood.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What do the lizards eat?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM</hi>: Again, by analogy, I would say most likely small invertebrates (insects, larvae, worms etc...).</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What equipment was used during the research?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM</hi>: Classic equipment (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/microscope">microscope</ref>) and also a state-of-the-art device: a micro <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CT-scan">CT-scan</ref>. It is a big device producing [a] 3D picture of the internal structure without damaging the specimen. It is actually very similar to the scanner used in human medicine, but this one is specially designed for small specimens. Otherwise, I am currently studying the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DNA">DNA</ref> of this species and closely related species in order to determine its <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/phylogenetics">phylogenetic</ref> position compared to other species with legs, in order to learn more about the evolutionary phenomena leading to limb loss.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  There are several news sources that have a photo of the species. Is it a photo as seen in a CT-scan?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM</hi>: No, this picture showing a whitish specimen on a black background is not a CT-scan. It is a normal photograph of the collection specimen preserved in alcohol (the one that was in the jar). You can see the complete of picture (including CT-scan 3D radiography, drawing...) in the original scientific publication.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Do you know when the newly discovered mermaid skink species was put into the jar? Do you have its photo (of the jar)?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM</hi>: No, I have no picture of the jar. The specimen has been collected in November 2004.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What were the roles of the people involved in the research? What activity was most time-consuming?</p>
<figure><caption>Miguel Vences in the field in Madagascar, in 2006. Image: Miguel Vences.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM</hi>: As first investigator, I did most of the work...and the longest part of the work was to examine closely related species in order to do comparisons...and also to check the complete bibliography related to this topic and to write the paper.</p>
<p>Mrs Anjeriniaina is the student who [...] collected the specimen a couple of years ago.</p>
<p>Mrs Hipsley and Mr Müller learnt me how to use the CT-scan, and helped me concerning some point relative to internal <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/morphology%20(biology)">morphology</ref>. Mr Vences helped me as supervisors. Additionally, all of them have corrected the article, and gave me many relevant advices and corrections, thus improving the quality and the reliability of the paper.</p>
<figure><caption>A picture from the field area where <hi rend="italic">Sirenoscincus mobydick</hi> has been collected. Image: Mrs Andolalao Rakotoarison.</caption></figure>
</text>
