<text id="autogum_interview_doc679" title="part2_Sam Brownback on running for President, gay rights, the Middle East and religion" shortTile="partsam-brownback" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-12" dateModified="2014-12-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sam_Brownback_on_running_for_President%2C_gay_rights%2C_the_Middle_East_and_religion" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  If he's looking for any of those issues to be addressed by the Democrats, they're not going to be.  And I would hope he could also see that we've got two people on the Supreme Court now that are, we hope, pro-life votes to overturn <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roe%20vs.%20Wade">Roe versus Wade</ref>, that he will see that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/pro-life">pro-life</ref> legislation was passed, that taxes were cut. And what I would also say to him is that I think we also have to see that the system is built to spend.  I hear from Republicans and Independents alike that the biggest thing they've been upset about, if you set aside opinions on the war, has been spending.  And the system's just built to spend.  Whether Republicans or Democrats are in control, you just constantly get that.  I've said many times—I’ve represented Kansas since 1995--I have yet to have a single constituent come in my office and say, "Hey, we're getting too much Federal money; would you please cut it?"  I get all the time people saying, "Look, I'm a conservative, but we need this bridge, we need this subsidy, we need this hospital.”  And the system's just built to spend.  That's why you've gotta change the system, and I've been pushing aggressively, taking the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Base%20Realignment%20and%20Closure,%202005">BRAC military base closing commission</ref> process they'll use for military bases and applying it to the rest of government.  So you've got an actual culling process that you're regularly requiring Congress to vote on.  Because you've just got to change the system of its spending proclivities.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When you think about dropping out of the race, what emotions do you feel?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  Well, that presumes I'm taking that step, and what we're--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You've discussed it, and I'm just wondering when it's a thought that occurs to you-- not an inevitability---just when you think about it as a possibility, how do you feel when you reflect upon it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  You know, what I've said is that if we don't finish fourth or better in Iowa that we'll pull out. And I think you just--if you look at it in that context, and I do, and this is a fabulous country, it's a great honor to be running for President, sharing big ideas with the country, and what a great place, that a guy can grow up on a farm in Eastern <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kansas">Kansas</ref> and run for President of the United States.  I love a country like that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you feel sad when you think about possibly leaving?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  No, I feel the great honor of putting ideas out there, and we continue to do it.  We're giving a big speech on Sunday in Boston, and we're going to talk there about the expansion of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/pro-life">pro-life</ref> agenda, the need for racial reconciliation and an official apology for slavery and segregation....continuous talk about big ideas.</p>
</text>
