<text id="autogum_interview_doc801" title="part4_Antje Duvekot on life as a folk singer, her family and her music" shortTile="partantje-duvekot" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-11" dateModified="2014-03-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Antje_Duvekot_on_life_as_a_folk_singer%2C_her_family_and_her_music" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What is a new goal?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  Balance.  Trying to grow my career enough to make sure it doesn’t consume me.  It’s hard to balance a touring career because there is no structure to your life.  I’m trying to take this dream and make it work as a job.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How challenging is it to obtain that in the folk world?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  There’s not a lot of money in the folk world.  In generally right now I think people’s numbers are down and only a few people can make a living at it.  It’s pretty competitive.  I’m doing okay, but there’s no huge riches in it so I’m trying to think of my future and maintain a balance in it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think of doing something less folk-oriented to give your career a push?</hi></p>
<p>Not really, I’ve done that a little bit by trying to approach the major labels, but that was when the major labels were dying so I came in at a bad time for that.  I found that when it comes to do it yourself, the folk world is the best place to make money because as soon as you go major you are paying a band.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  More money more problems.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  More money, more investing.  It’s a hard question.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What things did you encounter doing a studio album that you had not foreseen?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  Giving up control is hard when you have a producer.  His vision, sometimes, is something you can’t understand and have to trust sometimes.  See how it comes out.  That was hard for me, because up until now I have been such a do it yourself, writing my own songs, recording them myself.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What is your most treasured possession?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  I’d like to say my guitar, but I’m still looking for a good one.  I have this little latex glove.  [Laughs]  It’s a long story—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Please!  Do tell!</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  When I was in college I had a romantic friend named David, he was kind of my first love.  We were young and found this latex glove in a parking lot.  We though, “Oh, this is a nice glove, we’ll name him Duncan.”</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You found a latex glove in a parking lot and you decided to take it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  Yeah [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>].  He became the symbol of our friendship.  He’s disgusting at this point, he’s falling apart.  But David and I are still friends and we’ll pass him back and forth to each other every three years or so when we’ve forgotten his existence.   David surprised me at a show in Philly.  He gave Duncan to the sound man who brought it back stage, and now I have Duncan.  So he’s kind of special to me.</p>
</text>
