<text id="autogum_whow_doc146" title="Be a Better Facilitator" shortTile="better-facilitator" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2009-07-25" dateModified="2019-11-04" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be-a-Better-Facilitator" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be a Better Facilitator</head><p>A “facilitator” is someone who acts as a 'lubricant' by helping a team with issues such as communications or problem solving but, typically, does not contribute to the actual content or management of a team's project (which is a team leader's function). Effective facilitation can help your organization maximize its resources by getting the most from the people who work with you. While there are a number of seminars, trainings and workshops to learn how to effectively facilitate or become certified as a facilitator, if you do not have the resources to hire a facilitator or become one, here are some tips to help get you started. Following are some tips for effective facilitation.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Add_a_Funny_Quiz_to_a_Course_to_Engage_Learners">Establish a comfortable learning environment.</ref> <figure rend="Be a Better Facilitator Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Establish <hi rend="italic">ground rules</hi> to encourage positive group interaction.  Start with a few of your own and ask the group to for any others they would like to include. Some examples of ground rules: <figure rend="Be a Better Facilitator Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Confidentiality. What is said in this room, stays in this room</item>
<item>Speak from your experience. Use “I” instead of “you” or “we”</item>
<item>There are no right or wrong answers. Our responses are based on our unique experience</item>
<item>Practice respect for myself and others</item>
<item>Listen actively. Respect others when they are talking.</item></list></item>
<item>Keep the focus of the conversation on the situation or issue. <figure rend="Be a Better Facilitator Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Build_Self_Confidence">Maintain the confidence and esteem of all participants.</ref> <figure rend="Be a Better Facilitator Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_a_Good_Listener">Listen actively.</ref> <figure rend="Be a Better Facilitator Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Have_a_Witty_Conversation">Use humor when appropriate.</ref> <figure rend="Be a Better Facilitator Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Control distractions, including distracting participants. <figure rend="Be a Better Facilitator Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Develop participation. <figure rend="Be a Better Facilitator Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>As a facilitator, your talk time should be less than 40%</item>
<item>Ask open-ended questions</item>
<item>Be comfortable with silence – it may be a time of thought.  Wait a full 10 seconds after asking a question.</item>
<item>Address people by name.</item>
<item>Use your personal experience as an example when appropriate.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be clear.</item>
<item>Speak clearly, at a moderate pace and an appropriate volume.</item>
<item>Transition smoothly from one activity or discussion to another.</item>
<item>Use visual aids to enhance and reinforce.</item>
<item>Ask for questions in an open manner – “What questions do you have?”</item>
<item>Use simple, straightforward words and sentences.</item>
<item>Enjoy the experience!  If you are confident and have a good time, others will too!</item>
<item>Be prepared. Have an outline or a curriculum. Know what you want to achieve and be able to clearly articulate the desired outcome.  Practice what you want to say, how you will say it.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Manage over-participation.</item>
<item>Stay relaxed and un-defensive.</item>
<item>Handle aggressive behavior.</item>
<item>Avoid asking closed-ended questions.</item>
<item>Allow the other person to “save face”. Acknowledge the value of the person’s concerns.</item>
<item>Acknowledge that you hear and understand by paraphrasing.</item>
<item>Refer to the ground rules.</item>
<item>To get the group back on topic, ask participants to link the conversation to the issue you are discussing.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Markers and flip charts/white board</item>
<item>Outline or curriculum</item>
<item>Visual aids</item>
<item>Pens and paper for participants</item></list>
</text>
