<text id="autogum_interview_doc377" title="part4_Wikinews interviews Australian Statistician Brian Pink" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-19" dateModified="2008-04-30" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_Statistician_Brian_Pink" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : So have any of the new politicians come in and say "We'd like our numbers to looks a little bit better for us than they did for the previous lot"?</p>
<hi rend="bold">There are only two people I trust, God and the Commonwealth Statistician.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—Billy Hughes, </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BP</hi>: No, no, you don't get that sort of ... I think one of the wonderful things in the tradition of the ABS and its predecessor the Commonwealth Bureau of Census and Statistics has been that the independence of the institution is valued by all participants in parliament, current and past, and there's a wonderful quote from a previous - this is going back some time now - but from a previous <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Billy%20Hughes">Prime Minister</ref> who was quoted as saying "There are only two people that I believe in this world - one's God and the other one's the Commonwealth Statistician".</p>
<head id="Indigenous_statistics">Indigenous statistics</head>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Also, earlier this year <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kevin%20Rudd">Kevin Rudd</ref> apologised to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stolen%20Generations">Stolen Generations</ref>, and this was on the basis of the "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bringing%20Them%20Home">Bringing Them Home</ref>" report which incorporated some of the ABS' National Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander surveys. To what extent does the ABS actually collect Indigenous statistics?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BP</hi>: We actually have an Indigenous Statistics Group within the ABS. That was formed quite a number of years ago, and its role is to understand and provide insights into the statistical needs, both of the Indigenous communities and of society more generally in trying the understand the circumstances of our Indigenous communities. The Census of course is a fundamentally important part of our understanding of our Indigenous people, but we have a number of major statistical initiatives that have been undertaken in areas of health and in, for instance, the work that we've been doing with our colleagues in the state administrations in particular to get better Indigenous identifiers in a number of the administrative systems, including over the years seeing substantial improvements in the identification of Indigeneity in Births and Deaths records, working to see better information identifiers in health and education records, for instance. It's not perfect, but the Indigenous unit within the ABS and other parts of the ABS have been working to improve the information base that we have in the society and that the Indigenous people themselves have, that provide us with better information about their circumstances.</p>
<p>I think that's one of the significant initiatives that's been taken, and as it happens next year in 2009 we'll be running the major National Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Social Survey - it's been run before, we're running it again in 2009 and it'll provide quite a rich range of contemporary information about various aspects of Indigenous households and families, so there's a lot going on and with the initiatives that the previous government and the current government are taking and the commitments that are there to improve the circumstances of our Indigenous population, we have an important role to play to provide information that allows people to shape policies, and then information that allows people to understand how those policies, and the outcomes those policies are meant to be delivering, we help measure whether those outcomes are being achieved. So we've got a really important role to play in this space.</p>
</text>
