<text id="autogum_academic_doc190" title="Species-Specific Antioxidant Power and Bioactive Properties of the Extracts Obtained from Wild Mediterranean Calendula Spp. (Asteraceae)" shortTile="speciesspecific-antioxidant" author="Concetta  Maria Messina, Angelo Troia, Rosaria Arena, Simona Manuguerra, Theodora Ioannou, Eleonora Curcuraci, Giuseppe Renda, Claire Hellio, Andrea Santulli" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/9/21/4627/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The genus <hi rend="italic">Calendula</hi> (Asteraceae) includes several species (known commonly as “Marigolds”) that have been reported since antiquity for their therapeutic properties and/or use as ingredients in food preparation. There is no agreement on the number of species within the genus, owing to the high number of taxa differently considered by different authors, but recently, this number has been proposed to be 15, with several infraspecific taxa. </p>

<p>The most studied species within the genus is <hi rend="italic">Calendula officinalis</hi> L., an ornamental and medicinal plant, of unknown origin, usually cultivated but sometimes escaped and/or naturalized in several regions. <hi rend="italic">C. officinalis</hi> extract and pure compounds isolated from different organs possess multiple pharmacological activity, including anti-inflammatory, antioedematous, antioxidant, immunostimulant, lymphocyte and wound healing, hepatoprotective, antimicrobial, antibacterial and antifungal, anti-HIV, spasmolytic and spasmogenic, genotoxic and antigenotoxic, antiviral, and anticancer. These properties are due to the presence of secondary metabolites, such as carotenoids, polyphenols, and flavonoids. </p>

<p>In particular, polyphenols represent a family of organic molecules widely distributed in the plant kingdom. Their chemical structures are characterized by the presence of different phenolic groups, which can be associated with more or less complex groups of chemicals, generally of high molecular weight. The growing interest in polyphenols comes from their antioxidant potential, which is involved in health benefits such as inflammation and cancer prevention, cardiovascular dysregulation, and neurodegenerative diseases. Due the mechanisms involved in the production, recently, this class was also recognized as a useful biomarker to reveal the resistance of plants and algae to environmental conditions. </p>

<p>Despite a long tradition of use of some species, the genus has not been explored properly, and few species (apart from <hi rend="italic">C. officinalis</hi>) have been studied for their phytochemistry and ethnopharmacological aspects. </p>

<p>In our work, we focused on the leaves of untapped wild Mediterranean species, potentially useful as source of important molecules for potential biotechnological applications. Thus, three species and one hybrid were investigated: <hi rend="italic">Calendula maritima</hi> Guss. (CM), <hi rend="italic">Calendula suffruticosa</hi> subsp<hi rend="italic">. fulgida</hi> (Raf.) Guadagno (CF), <hi rend="italic">Calendula arvensis</hi> (Vaill.) L. (CA) and hybrid (CI) between the CM and CF. CM, perennial, is endemic to Western Sicily, where it grows along the coast lines; it is one of the most endangered species on a global scale. The risk of extinction is due to direct or indirect human actions. CF, perennial, can be found throughout Sicily, Malta, in parts of southern mainland Italy and Tuscany, and also in Morocco. Present in various habitats (including disturbed areas such as fallow fields and road cuts), it is not endangered, but it is supposed to threaten the populations of CM through the formation of hybrids. CA, annual, native all around the Mediterranean area from Macaronesia to SW Asia (and introduced in other parts of the globe such as Australia and California), it grows in fields, vineyards, and waste grounds. </p>

<p>This species has also many uses since ancient times: CA and CM had high antioxidant activity, whereas only few data are available regarding antioxidant potency and chemical composition of CF and CI. In any case, regardless of the species considered, the antioxidant activity could be responsible for the effects reported, both from the phytotherapeutic traditional usages and the scarce available literature about the bioactivity of the plants of this family (anti-inflammatory, healing, antispasmodic). </p>

<p>The taxa here investigated occur in different habitats: the rare endemic CM is linked to peculiar coastal areas, the more opportunistic CF is able to colonize several different environments, the hybrid CI testifies to special evolutionary events when CM and CF come into contact, and the widespread CA is common in cultivated or disturbed areas. Ecological characteristics of a species can often explain its different properties in terms of the production of bioactive molecules as a defence strategy against specific, changing, or extreme environmental conditions. This is why we wanted to draw attention to antioxidants which are some of the key molecules involved in the ability of animals and plants to adapt to environmental and climate change. Our aim was to verify whether, in the different <hi rend="italic">Calendula</hi> species analysed, collected in different areas and at the same time of the year, there was a different ability to produce antioxidant compounds. Nowadays, the search for antioxidants is at the forefront of research in science not only for industrial application related to health and food but also focusing on organisms defences strategies toward environmental changes. For example, antioxidants represent a promising solution in microbiology fields in order to fight against bacterial resistance and appearance of new pathogen microorganisms and diseases. </p>
</text>
