<text id="autogum_voyage_doc280" title="Teaching English" shortTile="teaching-english" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=35486" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Teaching English</head>

<p>One way to travel — or to pay for your travels — is to get a job overseas teaching English. If you want to spend several years in a destination, this is a popular way to earn a living.</p>

<p>Jobs worth considering as a long-term prospect — or even as a career — are widely available. They generally require qualifications and experience; see <ref target="%23Certificates">Certificates</ref> below. In many such positions, the benefits include airfare and housing, though there is great variation from country to country and by type of institution.</p>

<p>Other jobs might do to supplement a backpacker's income, or even let you live somewhere interesting for a year. For some of these jobs, especially in remote areas, anyone who looks foreign and speaks some English can get work. Again, details vary greatly.</p>

<p>Speaking the local language is not generally required for the job itself, though it may be quite useful in beginner classes and will make your stay far easier and more pleasant in other ways.</p>

<head>Jargon</head>

<p>The students are learning <hi rend="bold">ESL</hi> (English as a Second Language) or <hi rend="bold">EFL</hi> (English as a Foreign Language) or <hi rend="bold">ESOL</hi> (English for Speakers of Other Languages). Some people make much of the distinction between ESL (in a English-speaking country so TV, shops and so on all help you learn) and EFL (English is almost never used except in class), but others treat the terms as interchangeable. For the teacher, add a T for Teaching to get <hi rend="bold">TESL</hi>, <hi rend="bold">TEFL</hi> or <hi rend="bold">TESOL</hi>, or just call the field <hi rend="bold">ELT</hi> (English Language Teaching).</p>

<p>A trend in the last few decades is to do a lot of <hi rend="bold">ESP</hi> (English for Specific Purposes), designing custom courses depending on what the learners need to use the language for. One branch of this is <hi rend="bold">EAP</hi> (English for Academic Purposes), preparing students for study abroad.</p>

<p>A major part of the ESP approach is <hi rend="bold">needs analysis</hi>, figuring out how your students will use the language. Consider a company somewhere that exports products to English-speaking countries. The engineers might just need to read manuals and product specifications in English; they might never hear, speak or write it. Marketers might need to read the quite different language of orders and contracts, and to both read and write emails in much less formal language. Some of them might also need to talk with customers. Executives might need to handle complex negotiations in English — a task that requires not only excellent spoken English but also business skills and an awareness of cultural differences. Ideally, each of these groups would get an almost completely different English course.</p>

<p>In some situations, needs analysis is a formal process and courses are written to order for specific groups. Often, however, the teacher just does an informal analysis and finds or invents exercises to suit a class.</p>

<head>Tests</head>

<p>A good score on an English test is almost always required for students whose native language is not English to <ref target="Studying%20abroad">study</ref> at a university that uses English (sometimes even when the university has a different primary language). Tests may also be required for visas in some countries or for some jobs. The widely-used tests have their own acronyms:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.ets.org/toefl">TOEFL</ref></hi>, for admission to US universities</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.ielts.org">IELTS</ref></hi>, for British, Irish, Canadian, Australian and NZ universities</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.ets.org/toeic">TOEIC</ref></hi>, a business English test from the TOEFL people</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.bulats.org/">BULATS</ref></hi>, a business English test from the IELTS people</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.cambridgeenglish.org/exams-and-tests/business-preliminary/">BEC</ref></hi>, business English Certificates from Cambridge (three exams at different levels)</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.cambridgeenglish.org/exams/proficiency/">CPE</ref></hi>, also from Cambridge: their highest level exam.</item>
</list>


<p><hi rend="bold">Teachers abroad may supplement their income by serving as examiners or markers</hi> for these tests, though both the demand and the pay rates for this vary considerably from place to place, and they are different for each test. In China a typical teacher can roughly double his or her income by working as an IELTS examiner a few weekends a month. Requirements are stiff, though — IELTS 9 (native speaker level) English, a <ref target="%23Certificates">TEFL certificate</ref> (CELTA or Trinity OK, anything else subject to discussion) and three years <hi rend="italic">classroom</hi> teaching experience <hi rend="italic">with adult students</hi> (neither teaching kids nor online teaching counts). That gets you into examiner training; there is a fee for the course and any travel involved is at your expense. You then need to pass a stiff test, and re-take it every two years, to actually get the work.</p>

<p>Some ESL students may also need or want to take other tests to get into foreign universities; these are not ESL tests, but admission tests designed for native English speakers. The main ones are:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.collegeboard.com/student/testing/sat/about.html">SAT</ref></hi> and <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.act.org/">ACT</ref></hi> for undergraduate admissions</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.ets.org/gre/">GRE</ref></hi> for most graduate programs, with both a general test and specific tests for different fields.</item>
</list>


<p>For more on these tests and discussion of others, see <ref target="Studying_abroad%23Admission_tests">Studying abroad</ref>.</p>

<head>The work</head>
<p>Teaching ESL (or any other language) has much in common with any other teaching, but also has its own unique challenges. Among other things, it needs some understanding of how language works, quite a bit of patience, and considerable showmanship since non-verbal techniques such as gesture and facial expressions are often needed to scaffold the weaker linguistic understanding of the learner.</p>

<p>Teaching English <hi rend="italic">as a second language</hi> is significantly different than teaching English literature and composition to a class of (mostly) native speakers, though of course there is overlap as well. For one thing, an ESL teacher has to deal with a wider range of problems, notably pronunciation difficulties and spoken usage questions, such as when "How are you?" is more appropriate than "How do you do?" Also, in any language even intelligent adult second language learners make grammar errors on things any eight-year-old native speaker gets 100% right; an ESL teacher has to teach and correct those. Also, you have to monitor and adjust your own English, speaking slowly and clearly, avoiding slang (or emphasizing it, depending on a needs analysis), sometimes explaining terms, and so on.</p>

<p>At any level, the teaching needs to be highly interactive. Too much talk by the teacher is fatal; you cannot teach language-using skills either by lecturing or (except in tiny groups) with a series of one-on-one interactions between the teacher and different students. You must set up situations for students to actually use the language. Often this means introducing some vocabulary and/or grammatical structures on the board or in a listening or reading exercise, then setting up some sort of pairs or group task where students can try it out. Various sorts of discussion, role-playing or game activities are often used.</p>

<p>A whole range of props are often used — maps to practice giving directions, newspaper clippings for reading comprehension or summary-writing practice, menus for a restaurant role-play, pictures for parts-of-the-body or parts-of-a-car, cartoons to provoke discussion, and so on. Sometimes the teacher must find or invent these; sometimes the school has a stock, as in the picture, or they can be borrowed from other teachers. It is fairly common for teachers working overseas to ask friends at home to mail them posters and other props, or to collect props themselves on visits home. If you are going abroad to teach, bring props or mail yourself a batch before leaving home.</p>
</text>
