<text id="autogum_interview_doc024" title="part2_Wikinews attends ComicCon in Bangalore, India" shortTile="partwikinews-attends" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-12-03" dateModified="2019-08-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_attends_ComicCon_in_Bangalore%2C_India" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Who is your inspiration?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">SG</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  When it comes to webcomics, my inspiration has to be Shen from <hi rend="italic">Blue Chair</hi>, and it is also called Shen Comics now. Then, <hi rend="italic">The Awkward Yeti</hi> — Nick Seluk, then Sarah Andersen's comics — <hi rend="italic">Sarah's Scribbles</hi>. Yeah, those are pretty much it. I only read the mainstream ones before I decided to start making my own, So I don't have a long list. [Laughs]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Where did you upload your first comic?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">SG</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Facebook">Facebook</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Are you self-taught?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">SG</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Yes! For the most part, yeah. I mean, I am studying animation design, but when it comes to drawing, I completely just taught myself.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Do you discuss your ideas before penning them down?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">SG</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  With some people. I have a couple of friends, I talk to sometimes, but for most ideas, no. I just go for it. Yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What tools do you use to create your comics?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">SG</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I draw in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adobe%20Inc.">Adobe</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Photoshop">Photoshop</ref>, and I use a Wiacom tablet.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I wanted to know what is your official website.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">SG</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I don't have an official website but it is all over on Facebook or Instagram and even on Webtoons, but I don't have a website yet, but I am planning to start one soon.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What are some of your hobbies?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">SG</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Oh, it is just drawing, animating. I play <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Soccer">football</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Basketball">basketball</ref>, but mostly just drawing and animating.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  There is one character in your comic, which is called as[...] Kabeer. Why did you name him Kabeer?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">SG</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  So Kabeer is a religiously ambiguous name. Kabeer isn't overly seen as a Hindu or a Muslim or anything. So it is a middle point and I wanted to keep a character that everyone can relate to, not just someone who belongs to a certain religion. So for that ambiguity, that is why I came up with the name, plus I really like the name. That was actually, probably the main reason.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  There is this comic which you have titled "Folow my dreams, son", which was about a boy who wanted to become a footballer, but ends up getting a degree from FFS College of Engineering. So were there some challenges with your...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">SG</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Absolutely not! My parents have been super supportive from the start. Like they actually told me to leave studies and go for art because I was so passionate about art and design. So I have had a very very smooth sailing so far. No parental pressure at all. It has been amazing, yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  If you had something to tell to your younger self, about your webcomics, what would you tell?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">SG</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Read more. Right now I am reading a lot of different kinds of comics so I can look at different ways of story telling. If I had done that earlier, maybe I could have, maybe, I don't know, some stories could have turned out better. When I look at some of my older comics, I feel like, 'Okay this could have been done a little better' sometimes. So, that's it. Otherwise nothing. Like I said, I had a smooth life, I don't give a f...</p>
</text>
