<text id="autogum_whow_doc289" title="Substitute for Mustard Seed" shortTile="substitute-mustard" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2017-09-06" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Substitute-for-Mustard-Seed" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Substitute for Mustard Seed</head><p>Mustard seeds can be hard to find, which can be frustrating when you need them for a certain recipe. Don’t worry, there are several things you can use in place of mustard seeds, like horseradish, mayonnaise, and wasabi. You can also substitute one kind of mustard seed for another, or use dry or prepared mustard in place of seeds.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Substituting with Other Ingredients</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Use prepared horseradish to add spice. Prepared horseradish is made by combining ground horseradish with vinegar, and sometimes other spices, to form a sauce. You can get it from your local supermarket. In place of mustard seed, use the same amount of prepared horseradish to add spice and complexity to your recipe. <figure rend="Substitute for Mustard Seed Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Add mayonnaise to achieve the same consistency. Mustard seeds are often used to thicken soups or other dishes. If you need mustard seeds to change the consistency of a dish, substitute the seeds for the same amount of mayonnaise. <figure rend="Substitute for Mustard Seed Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Substitute wasabi to increase the heat. Wasabi is a spicy green paste used in many Asian dishes. If you don’t have mustard seed, substitute it with a smaller amount of wasabi to add heat to your dish. <figure rend="Substitute for Mustard Seed Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use caraway seeds for a similar flavor. Substitute the same quantity of caraway seeds for mustard seeds in your recipe. The flavors are similar and using one kind of seed in place of another ensures you don’t have to alter your recipe any further. <figure rend="Substitute for Mustard Seed Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Add turmeric to increase the nutritional value. Turmeric reduces inflammation, relieves pain, and boosts immunity. Substitute ground turmeric for mustard seed using a 1 to 1 ratio for added health benefits.</item></list>
<head>Using Different Kinds of Mustard</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Substitute the same amount of dry mustard for mustard seeds. If your recipe calls for 1 Tbsp (14.3 g) of mustard seeds, simply substitute it for 1 Tbsp (14.3 g) of dry mustard. <figure rend="Substitute for Mustard Seed Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use 1 tsp of prepared mustard instead of 1 Tbsp of mustard seeds. If possible, decrease the amount of liquid in the recipe by 1 tsp (5 mL) to compensate for this substitution. For other quantities, use one-third of the amount of prepared mustard in place of mustard seed. <figure rend="Substitute for Mustard Seed Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Replace white mustard seeds with fewer brown or black mustard seeds. Brown and black mustard seeds are more potent than white (also called yellow) mustard seeds. If your recipe calls for white mustard seeds, try using half the amount of brown or a quarter of the amount of black mustard seeds. <figure rend="Substitute for Mustard Seed Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use more yellow mustard seeds, or fewer black, in place of brown. Brown mustard seeds are more flavorful than yellow but less intense than black mustard seeds. Use twice as many yellow mustard seeds or half as many black mustard seeds. <figure rend="Substitute for Mustard Seed Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Add more yellow or brown mustard seeds instead of using black. Black mustard seeds are the most flavorful and spicy. If you can’t find them, use four times as many white mustard seeds or twice as many brown mustard seeds in their place. <figure rend="Substitute for Mustard Seed Step 10.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Start with a small amount of the substitution and taste the recipe. Then, adjust the amount of the substitution as needed.</item></list>
</text>
