<text id="autogum_interview_doc610" title="part2_Wikinews interviews spokesman for Greek far-left party Xekinima" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-05-03" dateModified="2013-05-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_spokesman_for_Greek_far-left_party_Xekinima" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Tourism is the main industry in Greece because there is little cost needed in investments, and it doesn’t need a very big infrastructure.</p>
<p>Any infrastructure that was needed has been left to abandonment by both [the last two] governments, the Panhellenic Socialist Movement and New Democracy. A visitor can see and understand this by the shape ships and ferries are in and the way facilities are lacking.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">IM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> How do you respond to the assertion that 'democracy is the least-worst of all the political systems tried'? Would the Greek communists accept a multi-party system where some parties would be stridently advocating free-market economics?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">PT</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> One of the difficulties people face when seeking answers about a better political system is the black-and-white approach of ideas and names. True, democracy is a necessary principle, but there are vast differences between e.g. a bourgeoise democracy and a socialist democracy...</p>
<p>Also especially in Greece, the term "communist" is used by many in the left, it's almost a synonym. The majority of the left would strongly disagree with a one-party model. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stalinism">Stalinist</ref> leaderships - what erroneously most people call "communists" - would probably desire such a system, but no-one would advocate such a demand today. The only political forces that everyone in the left agrees should be banned are those of the ultra-right, with racist and fascist agendas, and this because they stand against the principles of democracy in any case... As we can see however throughout Europe and in history the capitalist system needs such "allies" especially in times of crisis. In Greece for instance the ultra-right populist La.O.S [<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Popular%20Orthodox%20Rally">Popular Orthodox Rally</ref>] party has proven itself an invaluable ally of PaSoK [Panhellenic Socialist Movement] in supporting the most vicious anti-labour measures, suppression of workers' rights, even a "no-questions-asked" policy of currency depositing that would favor money-laundering for illegal trades such as narcotics or human trafficking. In the mean time it tries to put the blame for the crisis caused by the financial system on scapegoats such as the immigrant and refugee populations.</p>
<p>If people had a fair and unbiased view of what a planned economy under democratic control could offer I believe that free-market advocates would be marginalized by the working class internationally, with no call for suppression which can lead to dangerous paths!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">IM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You mentioned in your email to me that the KKE does not co-operate with the rest of the nation’s left-wing community. Why is this? Does this split confuse potential voters about who to support?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">PT</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Unfortunately the un-democratic Stalinist traditions and practices of the KKE are deeply-rooted in the Greek CP [Communist party] - one has only to read the analysis of their last congress to see this. Therefore the KKE cannot stand in coalitions as an equal to other opinions. The current leadership of the KKE not only refuses to collaborate with the rest of the left but treats it as a class enemy, on the pretext that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Synaspismos">Synaspismos</ref> (the largest faction in the SYRIZA coalition) voted for the "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maastricht%20Treaty">Maastricht Treaty</ref>". This became more obvious during the December 2008 uprising where it denounced the youth as "agent provocateurs that seak to destabilize the country manipulating the masses to violence" and that SyRizA was "harboring vandals and criminal elements", earning shameful congratulations from the government and the far-right. Also the KKE through its union front P.A.ME. refuses to collaborate with other unions in industrial action except general strikes, and then always with separate demonstrations and rallies. This behaviour however has not gone unnoticed by the rank-and-file members, and there is sizable discontent with this hardline approach. The only thing that holds them is traditional strict party discipline and the occasional weaknesses of SyRIzA in terms of less militant, and more reformist positions projected by Synaspismos. In both cases, we expect to see developments that will answer to the indeed-confused public that does not give mass support to the left mostly because of disappointment over sectarianism, lack of militancy and larger demands rather than disagreement on principles.</p>
</text>
