<text id="autogum_academic_doc232" title="From Undesired Flaws to Esthetic Assets: A Digital Framework Enabling Artistic Explorations of Erroneous Geometric Features of Robotically Formed Molds" shortTile="undesired-flaws-esthetic" author="Malgorzata  A. Zboinska" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2227-7080/7/4/78/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Discussion</head><head> 5.1. Research Results in a Broader Context</head>
<p>
Today, the scarce number of research publications on architectural SPIF indicates that knowledge of this promising fabrication method is still limited and should be expanded further. Therefore, considering SPIF research in a broader context of the engineering disciplines can provide, to a certain extent, a background for discussing the significance of our study and its role in the development of the current approaches to handling the errors in fabrication. </p>

<p>The key discipline researching SPIF is manufacturing engineering, in which a number of methods have been developed to deal with the geometrical inaccuracies introduced by this forming method. Many of these methods embrace alterations of the geometrical input for the process, just as our method does. For instance, they advocate the creation of addendum surfaces and extracurricular support structures, input geometry splitting and varying toolpath designs to enable multi-pass forming, as well as input geometry alteration. However, what makes all those methods fundamentally different from our approach is their goal. In engineering research, forming inaccuracies are perceived as a problem and the main aim is to develop methods that eliminate them. In our case, we invert inaccuracies from being problematic to being generative. In addition, in the manufacturing engineering methods, the geometry alteration is a straightforward and deterministic one and is often preceded by computational analyses of material stresses and precise digital simulation of the forming conditions. For us, the process of geometry alteration is iterative, explorative, and with an uncertain outcome. Such a process is, in our case, based on approximate, qualitative ocular examinations and not computational calculations. </p>

<head> 5.2. Advantages of the Approach</head>
<p>
In contrast to the engineering approaches described above, the framework resulting from this study embodies an alternative, bottom-up approach to erroneous feature handling. Although the framework is supported by digital and computational means, which by definition are precise, an advantage is that it also offers several entry points for ambiguous explorations that may be preferred by some designers, especially those with an artistic orientation. The framework’s construction and implementation workflow also ensure that geometric feature explorations take place in a gradual, iterative manner. The benefit of this is that each iteration opens up several potential avenues for further explorations, all originating from one initial design. </p>

<p>Importantly, we also believe that an advantage of our method is its capacity to be combined with conventional, precision-oriented fabrication. This is important for a wider application of our process in non-standard building element manufacturing. Practical applications at the scale of an actual building will necessitate that some parts of the formed molds, such as edges that connect with other building elements, maintain high levels of geometrical precision, while the middle zones of the geometry can be treated in a less strict and more explorative manner. Further research is needed to find out how to make such a combined approach effective from an industrial application standpoint. </p>

<p>Another advantage of our method pertains to a novel mode of operation that it offers, in which the material is allowed to shape and compose itself partially on its own, with the human designer and the fabrication machine only to a certain extent guiding the process instead of controlling it entirely. The conventional mode of material crafting and processing, in which the material is merely formed, transformed, and reshaped, either by the designer’s hand or by the machine tool, is therefore expanded in our framework. This can be considered beneficial from an esthetic standpoint, as the material accumulations caused by the intentionally tweaked mold errors emphasize the intricate esthetic attributes of the material cast into the mold, offering an opportunity for unusual, bottom-up design feature generation. </p>

<p>Our framework therefore mediates a novel approach to design, in which designers can work very closely with material behaviors and react to these behaviors in an artistic, intuitive, and ambiguous way. Influencing these behaviors in an indirect manner creates a possibility to shape the expressive attributes of the design through the medium of the material, instead of mere drawing. This seems unique in light of the conventional design methods that often operate in a top-down manner. We hope that our research can play a part in the emergence of an alternative strand of architectural design methods, featuring material agency as an enriching design medium, existing side-by-side with the conventional design means. </p>
</text>
