<text id="autogum_interview_doc576" title="part1_Interview with Brazilian blogger Ricardo Serran Lobo" shortTile="partinterview-brazilian" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-01-13" dateModified="2012-05-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Brazilian_blogger_Ricardo_Serran_Lobo" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
Wikinews:  Is this your first international interview? What newspapers or magazines have been in contact with you?
<p>Ricardo Lobo:  Actually this is the second international interview. At the beginning of the blog,  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bloomberg%20Television">Bloomberg Channel</ref> from  New York interviewed me too. In Brazil, I have been interviewed by the main vehicles for communication. Only the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rede%20Globo">Rede Globo</ref> didn't interview me because of the denouncements that I have made against it: the 2.8 billions reals loan from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BNDES">BNDES</ref> [Brazilian Development Bank] and its daily manipulation of information.</p>
Wikinews:  Did you expect that your blog would become so famous?
<p>Ricardo Lobo: I wasn't expecting fame. Besides, I was expecting anything. I have laughed a  lot because of all the repercussion caused by the blog, however the main subject, as I see, it was the changes in the behaviours of the main personages of this crisis which were caused by the blog. In the media and in the parlamentarians.</p>
Wikinews: Do you receive a lot of emails?
<p>Ricardo Lobo:  I've already received many, about 300 emails per day at the peak of the crisis and popularity of the blog. In July, I could sleep only 3 hours by night. I answered everyone. At present time, there are usually 20 emails by day. I love that. (laughs)</p>
<head id="Journalism">Journalism</head>
Wikinews: Do you know about citizen journalism in Portuguese?
<p>Ricardo Lobo:   No. This practice is not common in my country. The blog <hi rend="italic">Vizinho do Jefferson</hi> (Jefferson's neighbor) opened a great discussion about this subject, since journalistic occupation is reserved to the ones who have a diploma of journalism. The first unofficial and "outlaw" vehicle [of communication] which really worked with citizen journalism was my blog. It is called "independent press" here.</p>
Wikinews: Is there any threat of working as an "independent press" since you do not have a journalist diploma?
<p>Ricardo Lobo: Yes, the journalist union can sue me anytime. However I am not taking any job.</p>
Wikinews:  You said that your blog caused some repercussions among some people. Can you cite some cases ?
<p>Ricardo Lobo:  About this subject, I would like to say too that the journalism elite likes my work and finds it of great importance. Only minor journalists are criticizing me and trying to disturb my work.</p>
Wikinews: Have you read the Portuguese-language Wikinews coverage about the scandal? What do you think about it?
<p>Ricardo Lobo: Unfortunately not. Excuse me, but I have to work on my blog 24 hours by day, getting and checking the information; some other histories are investigative.</p>
Wikinews: You are invited to follow the Wikinews coverture about the crisis. A lot of articles have already been written.
Wikinews: Do you think that the internet has changed something in the relationship between Brazilian people and the press?
</text>
