<text id="autogum_interview_doc381" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Mark Bunker, producer of anti-Scientology website &amp;apos;XenuTV&amp;apos;" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-05" dateModified="2016-03-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Mark_Bunker%2C_producer_of_anti-Scientology_website_%27XenuTV%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What will it take to get Congressional Hearings to review the Church of Scientology? Specifically, their tax-exempt status.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: It is going to take a groundswell of media interest into the abuses (of the Church) before it happens.  There's a lot of work that needs to be done. On public knowledge versus Scientologist knowledge, that is troubling for me. We on the outside know what is in store for the people moving onto the bridge. I think it is bait and switch to not tell them that their real problems are they are covered with BT's [<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Body%20Thetans">Body Thetans</ref>, ed.</hi>]. That's a major case of fraud in my mind.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What, if any, changes or improvements have been made in Church policy and structure since Hubbard died, and more recently too, that might have already addressed, at least partially, issues such as Snow White, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lisa%20McPherson">Lisa McPherson</ref>, disconnection, unrealistic promises of Scientology benefits, etc? On what do you base your answer to this question?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: The only major policy change I've seen from David Miscaviage is the introduction of the Lisa Clause.  What Scientology learned from the tragic death of Lisa McPherson is to have all their members sign a form to say they grant Scientology the right to treat them as they did Lisa and to promise not to sue.  Otherwise the group seems to be as militant as when Hubbard was still around which is astonishing in a way.  A cult usually dies with its founder.  I believe Scientology is a cult yet it lurches on with the help of its richest members and the ability to bleed dry the rank and file.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">I assume you mean "Lisa Clause"?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: Yes. Lisa Clause. As to Scientologists who say that I don't know what I'm talking about, why do I have documents to back up my claims and they have shore stories?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How do you think most Church members feel about your protests? What would you say to those who would criticize your protests as misguided or the information you post and expose as untrue?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: We are seeing some indications that the Scientologists inside the group are responding to the protests. There was one insider who got a message of support out. Clearly, when materials like the Tom Cruise tape are being leaked, there are people inside who are concerned about how the group is behaving.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">We have a somewhat difficult question to put next...Is R2-45 Auditing a joke within Scientology, or is it actually real?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: I think it was probably a sick joke by Hubbard but he did actually put it in some orders. It's not anything I ever discuss. There is so much sensational material about Scientology.  People find it hard to believe the actual truth. I have no knowledge of anyone being shot by Scientology and wouldn't claim otherwise. That said, I find it unbelievably odd that DM's mother-in-law supposedly committed suicide by shooting herself with a shotgun...three times. That's weird. But I won't say it's murder.</p>
</text>
