<text id="autogum_interview_doc355" title="part1_Creator of website satirizing Glenn Beck on winning domain name case" shortTile="partcreator-website" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-11-09" dateModified="2019-02-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Creator_of_website_satirizing_Glenn_Beck_on_winning_domain_name_case" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Randazza argued in the response filed on behalf of Eiland-Hall that Beck attempted to use the process of the WIPO court to infringe the free speech rights of his client; "Beck is attempting to use this transnational body to circumvent and subvert the Respondent's [web site owner] constitutional rights [to freedom of speech]," he wrote. Randazza cited the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Supreme%20Court%20of%20the%20United%20States">U.S. Supreme Court</ref> case, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hustler%20Magazine%20v.%20Falwell">Hustler Magazine v. Falwell</ref></hi>, in arguing that Beck's attorneys advised him against filing legal action in a U.S. court because the website would likely be seen as a form of parody and due to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First%20Amendment%20to%20the%20United%20States%20Constitution">First Amendment to the U.S. Constitution</ref>, such legal action would not be successful.</p>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World%20Intellectual%20Property%20Organization">WIPO</ref> headquarters in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geneva">Geneva</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Switzerland">Switzerland</ref> (2004) Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/user:Metatron">Metatron</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>On September 29, Randazza sent a request to Beck's representatives, asking that their client agree to stipulate to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Constitution">United States Constitution</ref>, and especially to the First Amendment, during the case before the WIPO. In the request, Randazza quoted a statement from Beck himself about the usage of international law by United States citizens, Beck said, "[o]nce we sign our rights over to international law, the Constitution is officially dead." In an October 19 interview with <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi>, Randazza stated that Beck had not replied to his request to stipulate to the U.S. Constitution and the First Amendment in the WIPO case. On Monday, Ed Brayton of <hi rend="italic">ScienceBlogs</hi> noted, "Ironically, Beck never did respond to Marc Randazza's motion for a stipulation that the panel would have to apply American law in deciding the case..."</p>
<p>On October 20, Randazza filed a surreply – a response document to an October 13 supplementary filing made by Beck in the case. Attorneys for Beck asserted in the supplementary filing that the joke made by the website is difficult to comprehend, and therefore the domain name is confusing. In Beck's supplementary filing, his lawyers argued, "While there is absolutely nothing humorous or amusing about the statement made by Respondent in his domain name that 'Glenn Beck Raped and Murdered a Young Girl in 1990,' the average Internet user finding the domain name GlennBeckRapedAndMurderedAYoungGirlin1990.com ("Disputed Domain Name") in a search would have no reason not to believe that they will be directed to a website providing factual information (as opposed to protected criticism or similar protected speech) about Mr. Beck." </p>
<p>Randazza's surreply asserted, "An average Internet user might not 'get the joke'. In fact, the average Internet user does not understand any internet memes. That's the fun of a meme - it is an esoteric inside joke that will leave most people scratching their heads." In Randazza's conclusion to the Eiland-Hall surreply, he called Beck "the butt" of a joke he apparently does not understand. Randazza wrote that Beck "should be deeply ashamed" for devaluing the First Amendment to the U.S. Constitution.</p>
</text>
