<text id="autogum_reddit_doc010" title="Timmy -&gt; Mughals first WC attempt" shortTile="timmy-mughals-first" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-05-31" dateModified="2018-05-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8nkf6t" speakerList="#Sevuhrow, #TiltSchweiger" speakerCount="2">
<head>Timmy -&gt; Mughals first WC attempt</head>
<sp who="#TiltSchweiger">
<p>Hello guys, I'm asking for advice on how to WC from this point on. <ref target="https://preview.redd.it/o04el48l28111.png?width=1921&amp;format=png&amp;auto=webp&amp;s=0c6e9e21ae2650f7692d2b6a28cf5788d6311804">Political Map</ref> I currently have 4,5k dev, Ottos (2k dev) are allies with 100 trust which means i can drag them into any reasonable wars. Capital is still Delhi since i didnt quite figure out on where to set my home trade node. I want to put it in Europe, preferably Constantinople, to finally get these juicy Trade Companies (works only if your capital is in continental Europe, right?), but this wont happen anytime soon. <ref target="https://preview.redd.it/744ob75t28111.png?width=1919&amp;format=png&amp;auto=webp&amp;s=7c6a50675b1029929c2559aa8eaafc1d744274dc">Trade &amp; Economy</ref> I'm currently triggering Court &amp; Country and have absolutism maxed at 70/70. I still have some years left until the disaster ends (around 7yrs). Since I only recently learned how to trigger C&amp;C, i dont quite know whether i should stop declaring wars until it finishes or just keep on declaring. Suggestions? My war path as of now are either Sweden, Russia, Naples and Ming. The african minors are all at truce and acquirable within years. Everything east of me is either Ming or a tributary of theirs, except Japan, Malacca and the indie-Nations, which are out of reach. Where should I expand next? i dont consider conquering Ming until Imperialism Cb. They are at 0 Mandate already and i think I can manage conquering Ming quite fast due to the amount of Tributaries they have. Also, I feel like i'd be wasting too much time micro managing my troops conquering Ming this early (no free forced march, low on manpower, weak economy atm). Thoughts? My Ideas are Inf -&gt; Adm -&gt; Human -&gt; Off -&gt; Dip. Im planing on going Innovative next mainly due the off-innovative policy which gives me 1 leader siege pip + 10&#37; siege ability. also, tech cost reduction, advisor cost reduction paired with estates advisors, +1 leader and war exhaustion reduction are phenomenal imo. after innovative I'd go aristocratic mainly for the extra +1 leader siege pip. reduced army tradition decay is good aswell since im constantly at war and the +33&#37; national manpower is much needed as of now. Thoughts? should i swap innovative with aristocratic since manpower is an issue ? Any advice is much appreciated! Btw, how do I handle the HRE if everything is conquered except those pesky princes?</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#Sevuhrow">
<p>Caucasian provinces can count as Europe. You can move your capital there, which allows you to do Trade Companies. </p>
<p>EDIT: <ref target="https: www.youtube.com watch?v=_Oi9DkyqoPA&amp;t=365s">This helps a lot with absolutism and C&amp;C</ref>. TL;DR, the C&amp;C disaster is a lot more psychological than anything. It's a very tame disaster and you can focus on wars after a few years of it starting.</p>
</sp>
</text>
