<text id="autogum_interview_doc280" title="part2_2008-09 Wikipedia for Schools goes online" shortTile="part-wikipedia-schools" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-10-22" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2008-09_Wikipedia_for_Schools_goes_online" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">AC:</hi></hi> It was a pleasant surprise. I don't think we had realised what the barriers schools faced in using the main Wikipedia were. It isn't just pupils posting material about teachers or meeting strangers: the "Random Article" button on every page could potentially deliver an article on hardcore porn. We had already started when discussion broke on banning Wikipedia from classrooms and I am sure we benefited from it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Can you give an outline of the selection and vetting process? Is it primarily Wikipedians working on this, or are people from the educational establishment brought in?</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">AC:</hi></hi> It was a long and painful process, even with a really good database system. Articles were taken into the proposal funnel from three main sources: direct proposals for inclusion from Wikipedians, lists which came from the Release Version team and proposals drawn up from working through National Curriculum subjects by SOS volunteers. In a few cases where we felt articles were missing we asked the community to write them (e.g. Portal:Early Modern Britain, which is a curriculum subject, was kindly written just for us): These "proposals" 
were then looked at by mainly SOS volunteers (some onwiki, some offline). Our offices are in the middle of Cambridge and we get high quality volunteers, who skim read each article and then compared two versions from the article history by credible WP editors a significant period apart (this picks up most graffiti vandalism which runs at about 3% of articles). Once they had identified a "best" version they marked any sections or text strings for deletion (sections which were just a list of links to other articles not included, empty sections, sex scandals etc). A substantial sample of each volunteers work was then doubled checked for quality by one of two office staff (of whom I was one). We then have a script which does some automated removals and clean ups. Once we had a selection we posted it to relevant wikiprojects and a few "experts" and got any extra steers.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Will you be making use of BitTorrent for distribution again this year? Was it a success in 2007?</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">AC:</hi></hi> BitTorrent was a bit disappointing in that it got us the only substantial criticisms we received online. A lot of people find it too much effort to use. However for the period we offered a straight <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/http">http</ref>: download we had huge problems with spiders eating vast bandwidth (the file is 3.5G: a few thousand rogue spider downloads and it starts to hurt). As per last year therefore our main two channels will be free download by BitTorrent and mailing the DVDs free all over the world. At a pinch we will (as before) put straight copies up for individuals who cannot get it any other way, and we have some copies on memory sticks for on distributors.</p>
</text>
