<text id="autogum_voyage_doc36" title="Hajj" shortTile="hajj" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=13887" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Hajj</head>

<p>The traditional annual <ref target="Muslim">Muslim</ref> pilgrimage to <ref target="Mecca">Mecca</ref>, the <hi rend="bold">Hajj</hi> is a mandatory religious duty for Muslims and is the largest annual gathering of people in the world. It occurs between the 8th and 12th of the last month of the Islamic calendar, Dhu al-Hijjah. Hajj is that symbolic pilgrimage when millions of Muslims from around the world belonging to different ethnic groups, socioeconomic strata and cultures travel to Mecca together and praise to Allah and ask for forgiveness of their sins.</p>

<p>The five day spiritual Hajj, which dates back to the 7th century of the Christian calendar, is designed to promote the bonds and affection between Muslim communities and shows that everyone is equal in the eyes of Allah by wearing simple white garment Ihram. Pilgrims spend days worshiping in and around the holy city of Mecca and perform rituals that make up the Hajj.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>The Hajj is one of the five pillars of <ref target="Islam">Islam</ref>; every adult Muslim is supposed to do it at some time in his or her life if health and finances permit. In poorer areas it is not uncommon for whole families or even whole villages to chip in to send one person.</p>

<p>It is an exceedingly cosmopolitan affair. Predominantly Muslim areas include most of <ref target="North%20Africa">North Africa</ref>, the <ref target="Middle%20East">Middle East</ref> and <ref target="Central%20Asia">Central Asia</ref>, plus South and Southeast Asian countries such as <ref target="Pakistan">Pakistan</ref>, <ref target="Bangladesh">Bangladesh</ref>, <ref target="Malaysia">Malaysia</ref> and <ref target="Indonesia">Indonesia</ref> and several countries in <ref target="West%20Africa">West Africa</ref>. Several other areas have large Muslim minorities and there are some Muslims nearly everywhere. The pilgrimage brings Muslims from all these places together.</p>

<p>It is also one of the largest human migrations. Every year <hi rend="bold">over two million people</hi> visit <ref target="Saudi%20Arabia">Saudi Arabia</ref> for this pilgrimage. Since they all arrive at roughly the same time and visit the same places in the same order, and since a large number of Saudis go as well, this is a <hi rend="italic">major</hi> logistical problem. The Saudi government has a <ref target="http://www.haj.gov.sa/">ministry</ref> to manage it.</p>

<p>The Hajj can only be completed during the Islamic month of Dhu al-Hijjah. A pilgrimage to Mecca at any other time is known as <hi rend="bold">Umrah</hi> (عمرة), and while not compulsory is strongly recommended.</p>
<head>History</head>
<p>The early history of Hajj can be traced back to the time of Abraham, around 2000 BCE. According to Islamic tradition, Abraham was ordered by Allah to leave his wife Hagar and his son Ishmael alone in the uninhabited desert with little food and water, where Mecca stands today. When the food and water were gone, Hagar, in search of water for her baby Ishmael, desperately ran seven times between the two hills of Safa and Marwah but found nothing. Returning in despair to Ishmael, she saw him scratching the ground with his leg and a water fountain underneath. Later, the uninhabited desert area started to attract inhabitants due to availability of water and tribes started to settle in Mecca. When Ishmael grew up, he was married into a tribe in Mecca. At some point, Abraham was commanded by Allah to construct a building believed to be the Kaaba, which he did with the help of Ishmael. Abraham was commanded by Allah to invite people to perform pilgrimage in Mecca around the Kaaba.</p>

<p>In pre-Islamic Arabia, Meccans were idol worshippers and the Kaaba was surrounded by pagan idols. During the annual pilgrimage season, people would visit the Kaaba to perform rituals some of which were introduced by Arabs of that time. It is believed some pilgrims would perform tawaf around Kaaba in a naked state. During the initial years of Muhammad's prophethood, the pilgrimage season offered Muhammad the occasion to preach Islam to the foreign people who came to Mecca for pilgrimage. In 630 CE, after Mecca was conquered by Muhammad, he led his followers from Medina to Mecca, cleansed the Kaaba by destroying all the pagan idols, and then reconsecrated the building to Allah. In 631 CE, at the direction of Muhammad, Abu Bakr led some 300 Muslims to the pilgrimage in Mecca where Ali delivered a sermon stipulating the new rites of Hajj and abrogating the pagan rites. He especially declared that no unbeliever, pagan, or naked man would be allowed to circumambulate the Kaaba from the next year. In 632 CE, Muhammad performed his only pilgrimage with a large number of followers, and instructed them on the rites of Hajj and the manners of performing them. From then, Hajj became one of the five pillars of Islam.</p>

<p>In medieval times, pilgrims would gather in the big cities of Syria, Egypt, and Iraq to go to Mecca in groups and caravans comprising tens of thousands of pilgrims, often under state patronage. Some Hajj caravans were guarded by soldiers because there were risks of robbery or attack or natural hazards. Muslim travelers like Ibn Jubayr and Ibn Battuta have recorded detailed accounts of Hajj travels in medieval times. The University of California Berkeley has a good <ref target="http://orias.berkeley.edu/resources-teachers/travels-ibn-battuta">online account</ref> of Ibn Battuta's travels including several visits to Mecca, the first in 1326 CE. Despite it being illegal for non-Muslims, a few Western explorers have managed the journey — most notably, Sir Richard Burton made the Hajj in 1853 and wrote an <ref target="http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/4657">account of the trip</ref>.</p>

<head>Prepare</head>

<p>Unless you are a citizen of Saudi Arabia you will need a visa, obtained in advance from a Saudi embassy. Visas are allocated on a quota system, based on the number of Muslims in a country. You may need to provide evidence that you are Muslim, such as a letter from your local mosque.</p>

<p>Women under 45 are required to travel with a <hi rend="italic">mahram,</hi> a related adult male who is the head of her family (usually a husband or father), and proof of the relationship is required. Women over 45 may travel without a mahram if they're in an organized group and each has a letter of permission from the man who would be her mahram.</p>

<p>Proof of vaccination for meningitis (specifically the ACYW135 vaccine) between three years before and ten days before your entry into Saudi Arabia is required. <ref target="Yellow%20fever">Yellow fever</ref> vaccination is required if you arrive from any country with known yellow fever infections, and polio vaccinations are required for children up to 15. As millions of people from all over the world gather for Hajj and therefore you will be exposed to many diseases, you may want to discuss other vaccinations and preventative measures with your doctor.</p>

<p>Throughout Hajj you are expected to remove signs of wealth or class distinctions by replacing your clothing with simple white garments. These pieces are called ‘<ref target="https://www.modestrove.com/blog/the-ultimate-guide-to-hajj-what-to-pack-for-hajj/">ihram clothing</ref>’, and for women comprise of a white abaya, scarf or shawl and socks. The ihram clothing of Hajj is a signifier of equality: all pilgrims are presented as equals in the eyes of God. The white clothing also symbolises purity, and the state of absolute devotion that the pilgrims are in.</p>
</text>
