<text id="autogum_academic_doc267" title="Spatial Resolutions of On-Axis and Off-Axis Transmission Kikuchi Diffraction Methods" shortTile="spatial-resolutions" author="Yitian Shen, Jingchao Xu, Yongsheng Zhang, Yongzhe Wang, Jimei Zhang, Baojun Yu, Yi Zeng, Hong Miao" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/9/21/4478/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Results and Discussion</head><head> 3.1. Quantitative Evaluation of the Spatial Resolution</head>
<p>
In this study, the digital image correlation (DIC) technique was used to investigate the effects of the accelerating voltage and specimen thickness. The DIC method can be used to quantitatively evaluate small variations between patterns by calculating their correlation coefficient. As the electron beam is scanned close to a grain boundary, the interaction volumes of both sides overlap, which leads to overlapping Kikuchi patterns, and thus to a decreased correlation coefficient. Therefore, this method can be used to determine the spatial resolution. It has been extensively used to evaluate the physical resolutions of the EBSD and off-axis TKD methods. The correlation coefficient can be expressed as , where  and  denote the grey scale of the reference and sampling pattern at each position (<hi rend="italic">i</hi>,<hi rend="italic">j</hi>), respectively. </p>

<p>The middle part of the on-axis and off-axis Kikuchi patterns have good qualities; however, the boundaries of the patterns contain considerable noise. Moreover, a bright spot is generated by the transmitted beam in the center of the on-axis Kikuchi pattern. The size and shape of the bright spot can change during the scanning. Thus, if the whole pattern (640 × 480 pixels) is considered, the correlation coefficient would deviate and the results would be inaccurate. Therefore, regions of interest (ROIs) have to be selected to increase the precision. Wang et al. used this method to determine the resolution of the off-axis TKD. In this study, we have used a similar approach. Circular ROIs were chosen for the off-axis TKD, which contained the overlapping region, as shown in <figure>Figure 1</figure>C. On the other hand, annular ROIs were selected in the on-axis TKD to ensure that the boundaries and bright spots were eliminated while retaining the overlapping regions (<figure>Figure 1</figure>B). In addition, the chosen ROIs should be as large as possible to ensure representativity. </p>

<p>The calculated correlation coefficients at a voltage of 30 kV and specimen thickness of 91 nm are presented in <figure>Figure 2</figure>. Chen et al. and Shih et al. applied a fast Fourier transform (FFT) filter to reduce the noise, while FFT followed by inverse FFT were applied by Wang et al. to obtain smooth curves. FFT is commonly used for filtering in the frequency domain; if a smooth profile is needed, the peak may be broadened. Therefore, an average filtering algorithm is introduced to avoid the deviation in the correlation coefficient, which can smooth profiles in the spatial domain. As it does not affect the profile width, it is commonly used to filter out Gaussian noise. In <figure>Figure 2</figure>B, the low-frequency noise was removed and the whole curve became smoother after filtering. The smooth profiles of the correlation coefficients were summed and normalized. The procedure is presented in previous reports. With this approach, we can obtain the sum of the normalized correlation coefficients as a function of the distance (<figure>Figure 2</figure>C) and the full width at half maximum can be easily calculated, which is defined as the PSR. </p>

<head> 3.2. Difference in Spatial Resolution between the On-Axis and Off-Axis TKD Methods</head>
<p>
By using the above method, the spatial resolutions of the on-axis and off-axis TKD methods were measured in the same SEM at the same sample position. The data obtained at different voltages and sample thicknesses are presented in <figure>Figure 3</figure>. The intensity and contrast of the pattern for the 169-nm-thick sample were too low to identify at the same parameters used for the other two samples. Therefore, results are presented only for the two samples.  </p>

<p>The spatial resolution of the on-axis TKD was better than that of the off-axis TKD at the same accelerating voltage and thickness; the largest gap was 8 nm. The only difference between the two configurations was the intersection angle between the phosphor screen and incident beam (α). In the off-axis TKD, the intersection angle had a magnitude of only a few degrees, which led to a high gnomonic distortion and low diffraction intensity. On the contrary, no pattern distortion and high diffraction intensity were observed in the on-axis TKD because the angle α was close to 90°. Consequently, in the off-axis TKD, the probe current and/or exposure time have to be increased to produce an equivalent pattern quality. In this study, we increased both current and exposure time. Nonetheless, the increase in current leads to larger probe size and interaction volume, which inevitably increase the spatial resolution. Therefore, at their optimal parameters, the beam current used in the off-axis TKD method should be higher than that in the on-axis TKD method, which leads to a larger spatial resolution. Similarly, if we set equal parameters for both TKD methods, the pattern quality in the off-axis TKD method would be worse owing to its lower intensity. Therefore, the spatial resolution of the off-axis TKD would still be worse than that of the on-axis TKD. </p>
</text>
