<text id="autogum_academic_doc395" title="Exploring Readiness for Change: Knowledge and Attitudes towards Family Violence among Community Members and Service Providers Engaged in Primary Prevention in Regional Australia" shortTile="exploring-readiness" author="Monica Puccetti, Heath Greville, Margie Robinson, Daphne White, Lennelle Papertalk, Sandra  C. Thompson" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4215/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
The community readiness model aims to assess how ready a community is for change to occur; this group of highly engaged participants provides insight into overall community readiness. This is because the readiness for change in this group of early adopters will necessarily be higher than the overall community due to their previous engagement; thus, their views can inform prevention efforts at all levels of the community. Focus group participants who were further from the locus of planning around prevention efforts tended to align more closely with the lower ends of community readiness. Participants acknowledged FV as a serious problem and as common in the community, but in terms of conscious change, only a few had a comprehensive knowledge of prevention theory and efforts to address it. In these early stages, leaders and community members believe that FV is an issue for the community, but there is no immediate intent to act, and the decisional balance is tipped towards the negatives. This tilted decisional balance is seen in the plethora of perceived barriers to implementation that were mentioned in the focus groups, such as organizations being too small/too big, having too much hierarchy, an inability to make policy changes, not enough time, external management, difficulties in understanding the prevention efforts, worries about backlash, macho workplace values, and a lack of workplace buy-in. Of note, Kelly and colleagues have stated that identifying barriers is an important stage in that it indicates thinking about the need to raise awareness and develop concrete ideas to address the problem. </p>

<p>Certain key organizational stakeholders were more progressed, at or beyond the planning phase, recognizing a strong impetus for change but impeded by limited resources and without detailed and focused plans or efforts to address FV. Participants understood the difficulty of the task and many of the specific challenges. They also had important suggestions around strategy implementation and evaluation, including increasing the participation of men, reducing silence and shame about the subject of FV, and bringing the experiences of victim/survivors and perpetrators into the conversation.  </p>

<p>Overall, community attitudes in this subpopulation are positive and pro-change, but the knowledge of causal pathways of FV is lacking. While all participants agreed that FV is a problem in the community, many do not see gender inequality as the main driver of FV. Participants often had trouble understanding what a community that prevents FV would look like due to a lack of knowledge about what primary prevention entails. Participants were clear about ‘changing the conversation’ as a metaphor for preventing FV, and they had suggestions about who should be involved, what ‘the conversation’ should include and how prevention efforts could be evaluated. However, the conceptual link between increasing gender equality and preventing FV is not well understood, possibly due to the CRE Plan’s lack of focus on this driver of FV. Continued education at all levels of the community is necessary to help service providers and leaders conceptualize what prevention would look like, to engage community members in a conversation that takes FV beyond the simplistic victim/perpetrator dichotomy, and to change the story for regional women.  </p>

<p>The most common misunderstanding around the primary cause of FV revolves around alcohol and drugs. The main argument against alcohol and drug use as a primary cause of FV is that it cannot explain the highly gendered patterns of violence perpetration and victimization. Identifying alcohol and drug use as a primary cause of FV can also work to excuse violence, thus reinforcing the culture which condones it.  </p>

<p>The rates of harm from alcohol are considerably higher in rural than metropolitan areas, with rural residents more likely to engage in alcohol consumption that exceeds thresholds for short-term harm and long-term harm. With both high rates of FV and high rates of alcohol misuse, it is not surprising there is considerable overlap. Unfortunately, the misunderstanding that alcohol and drugs “cause” FV has proven to be difficult to change. One study found that the percentage of people believing that alcohol consumption is the single largest predictor of FV actually increased following training that did not advocate this view. This may be due to the phenomenon described by cognitive science, that when facts are presented in a manner than is incongruent with a person’s values, the facts will be rejected, not the values framework within which the person is functioning. This model recognizes that communication is not a purely rational endeavor; rather it theorizes that the frameworks of values and norms that each individual functions within have a large impact on their understanding and acceptance of facts. For someone to accept new facts, they must be presented in a way that is not incongruent with their values systems. This points to a key challenge of a primary prevention strategy that aims to change a deeply ingrained value system. Only by understanding resistance to change can we determine how best to engage the population and refocus the conversation on primary prevention.  </p>
</text>
