<text id="autogum_bio_doc077" title="Eli Y. Adashi" shortTile="eli-y-adashi" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-07-18" dateModified="2019-10-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eli_Y._Adashi" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Eli Y. Adashi</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Eli Y. Adashi</hi> is an American physician-scientist-executive who served as the Fifth Dean of Medicine and Biological Sciences at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brown_University">Brown University</ref>. Adashi  is a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Academy_of_Medicine">National Academy of Medicine</ref> [NAM; formerly the Institute of Medicine (IOM) of the National Academy of Sciences], the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Association_of_American_Physicians">Association of American Physicians</ref> (AAP), and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Association_for_the_Advancement_of_Science">American Association for the Advancement of Science</ref> (AAAS).</p>
<head>Early life and education</head>
<p>Adashi was born and raised in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haifa">Haifa, Israel</ref> (British Mandate Palestine) in 1945, the only child of German-speaking professionals who departed Europe in the mid-1930s. A member of the first graduating class of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sackler_Faculty_of_Medicine">Sackler School of Medicine</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tel_Aviv_University">Tel Aviv University</ref>, Adashi received his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Medical_degree">Medical degree</ref> in 1973.  Following a Rotating Internship at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meir_Hospital">Meir Hospital</ref>, Adashi relocated to the United States for Residency Training in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Obstetrics_and_gynaecology">Obstetrics and Gynecology</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tufts_University_School_of_Medicine">Tufts University</ref> under the leadership of George W. Mitchell Jr., MD (1974–77).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref>  Adashi pursued Fellowship Training in the subspecialty of Reproductive Endocrinology and Postdoctoral Training in Reproductive Biology at Johns Hopkins University and at the University of California at San Diego, respectively (1977–81).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:0-2">[2]</ref> Leading mentors included but were not limited to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Georgeanna_Seegar_Jones">Georgeanna Seegar Jones, MD</ref> (1912-2005), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Howard_W._Jones">Howard W. Jones Jr., MD</ref> (1910-2015), <ref target="https://biox.stanford.edu/about/people/affiliated-faculty/aaron-hsueh-professor-obstetrics-and-gynecology-reproductive-and">Aaron J.W. Hsueh, PhD</ref> (1946-), and Samuel S.C. Yen, MD, DSc (1927-2007).</p>
<head>Appointments</head>
<p>Adashi's first faculty appointment was as an Associate Professor with the Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Maryland,_Baltimore">University of Maryland</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> under the leadership of Marion Carlyle Crenshaw Jr., MD, where he directed the Division of Reproductive Endocrinology (1981-1996). In 1996, Adashi became the John A. Dixon Endowed Presidential Professor and Chair of the Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Utah_School_of_Medicine">University of Utah Health Sciences Center</ref> where he founded and led the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ovarian_cancer">Ovarian Cancer</ref> Program of the Huntsman Cancer Research Institute (1999-2004). In 2004, Adashi was appointed Dean of Medicine and Biological Sciences at Brown University.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> Adashi led the renaming of the Medical School (after Mr. Warren Alpert) and the initial planning of its new home,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> opened up the student body to pre-med matriculants, initiated a new and integrated pre-clinical curriculum, expanded the divisional faculty roster, established the Brown Chapter of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alpha_Omega_Alpha">Alpha Omega Alpha Honor Medical Society</ref>, and launched the Scholarly Concentration Program.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>Elected to the Institute of Medicine (IOM) in 1999, Adashi has served as a member of the Committees on Clinical Applications of Mifepristone (RU 486) and Other Antiprogestins: Assessing the Science and Recommending a Research Agenda (1993),<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> Understanding Premature Birth and Assuring Health Outcomes (2005-2006),<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> Human Embryonic Stem Cell Research (2006-2009),<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> and Women's Health Research: Progress, Pitfalls, and Promise (2008-2010).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref> In addition, Adashi served as co-chair of the Committee on Reducing Childbirth Mortality in Indonesia: Saving Lives, Saving the Future (2012-2013).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref> Adashi also served twice as a member of the Board on Health Sciences Policy.</p>
<p>A former Franklin fellow and Senior Adviser on Global Women's Health to the Secretary of State Office of Global Women's Issues (1st term of the Obama Administration),<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref> Adashi is a member of the Advisory Council of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Hastings_Center">The Hastings Center</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref> a member of the Board of Governors of Tel Aviv University,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref> and the chair of the Medical Executive Committee and the Medical Advisory Council of the Jones Foundation for Reproductive Medicine.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[16]</ref> Adashi is a former member of the Board of Directors of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Physicians_for_Human_Rights">Physicians for Human Rights</ref> and of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Council_on_Foreign_Relations">Council on Foreign Relations</ref>, the Global Agenda Council on Population Growth of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World_Economic_Forum">World Economic Forum</ref> and the Medicare Evidence Development &amp; Coverage Advisory Committee (MEDCAC) of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Centers_for_Medicare_and_Medicaid_Services">Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services</ref> (CMS). Adashi is also a former advisor to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Committee_for_Quality_Assurance">National Committee for Quality Assurance</ref> (NCQA), the WHO, the World Bank, the Rockefeller Foundation, and the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:0-2">[2]</ref> A former Examiner and Director of the Division of Reproductive Endocrinology of the <hi rend="italic">American Board of Obstetrics and Gynecology</hi> (ABOG), Adashi has served as President of the Society for Reproductive Endocrinology and Infertility (SREI; 1998-1999), the Society for Gynecologic Investigation (SGI; 1999-2000),<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-17">[17]</ref> and the American Gynecological and Obstetrical Society (AGOS; 2002-2003).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-18">[18]</ref></p>
<head>Research contributions</head>
<p>Adashi was the recipient of continuous National Institute of Health (NIH) funding from 1985 to 2005 inclusive of a Research Career Development Award. Mentor to over 50 postdoctoral trainees and the author or co-author of over 350 PubMed indexed peer-reviewed publications.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-19">[19]</ref> Adashi edited or co-edited 15 books in the general area of Reproductive Medicine with an emphasis on Ovarian Biology.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-vivo.brown.edu-20">[20]</ref> Adashi's service with the NIH included membership with the National Council of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_institute_of_child_health_and_human_development">National institute of child health and human development</ref> (1997-2001), the Reproductive Endocrinology Study Section (1988-1992), and the Selection Committee of the Reproductive Scientist Development Program (1988-2005). Adashi is the former Editor-In- Chief of <hi rend="italic">Seminars in Reproductive Medicine</hi> and a former Associate Editor of <hi rend="italic">Endocrinology</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Society for Gynecologic Investigation</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Reproductive Medicine Review</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Seminars in Reproductive Endocrinology</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Reproductive Medicine Review</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Reviews in Endocrine and Metabolic Disorders</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-vivo.brown.edu-20">[20]</ref></p>
<p>Adashi's research focused on the biology of the ovary and the role of growth factors and cytokines in this context. Ongoing scholarly contributions to medical education and to the discipline of reproductive medicine are equally noteworthy. Since 2008, Adashi has undertaken to focus on matters of policy at the nexus of medicine, law, ethics, and social justice.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-21">[21]</ref></p>
<head>Awards and recognition</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>USPHS Research Career Development Award (RCDA), NICHD, NIH (1986-1991)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-22">[22]</ref></item>
<item>The President's Achievement Award, Society for Gynecologic Investigation (1989)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sri-online.org-23">[23]</ref></item>
<item>Annual Research Award, Society for the Study of Reproduction (SSR) (1989)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-24">[24]</ref></item>
<item>Franklin Fellow, US Department of State, Office of Global Women's Issues (2009-2010)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-25">[25]</ref></item>
<item>W.W. Keen Award for Outstanding Contributions to Medicine, Brown University (2010)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-26">[26]</ref></item>
<item>SRI-Pardi Distinguished Scientist Award, The Society for Reproductive Investigation (2015)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sri-online.org-23">[23]</ref></item>
<item>Doctor Honoris Causa, The Poznan University of Medical Sciences, Poznan, Poland (2016)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-27">[27]</ref></item>
<item>Doctor Honoris Causa, The University of Ottawa, Ottawa, Canada (2018)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-28">[28]</ref></item>
<item>Lifetime Achievement Award, The American Society for Reproductive Medicine (2018)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-29">[29]</ref></item>
<item>Honorary Member, European Society of Human Reproduction and Embryology (2019)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-30">[30]</ref></item></list>
<head>Personal life</head>
<p>Adashi is married to Toni Sach-Silberman. a professional actress, a poetry recitalist, and a former member of the Habima National Theater in Tel Aviv, Israel. Their only son, Judah E. Adashi, a Yale undergraduate, is the holder of Master's and Doctoral degrees from the Johns Hopkins Peabody Institute wherein he is a composer and a member of the faculty.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-31">[31]</ref> Dr. Judah E. Adashi is also the founder and director of <ref target="http://www.judahadashi.com/about/">The Evolution Contemporary Music Series</ref>.</p>
</text>
