<text id="autogum_academic_doc422" title="Inconsistent Relationships of Primary Consumer N Stable Isotope Values to Gradients of Sheep/Beef Farming Intensity and Flow Reduction in Streams" shortTile="inconsistent-relationships" author="Katharina Lange, Colin  R. Townsend, Christoph  D. Matthaei" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4441/11/11/2239/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Most ecosystems are exposed to multiple environmental stressors acting simultaneously and combined multiple-stressor effects can be difficult to predict because they can be larger or smaller than expected based on the effects of the individual stressors involved. Stable isotope values have long been considered indicators of anthropogenic disturbance. In aquatic environments, the use of δ15N (a measure of the abundance of the heavier isotope 15N relative to the lighter isotope 14N) as potential indicators of land-use intensification and nitrogen enrichment has been suggested for streams and rivers, ponds and lakes, estuaries and coastal waters. Agricultural land use can impose a variety of stressors on stream ecosystems, including nutrient enrichment, increased sediment load, higher light availability and augmented water temperatures due to removal of riparian vegetation. Another important stressor is water diversion for irrigation, which commonly reduces stream discharge and flow velocity and changes sediment and temperature regimes. Any of these stressors may alter stream nitrogen dynamics, for example by flow reduction intensifying in-stream nitrogen transformation processes such as denitrification by increasing water retention times, respiration rates and occurrence of anoxic conditions. However, the combined effects of multiple agricultural stressors on stable isotope values in stream ecosystems still need to be investigated. </p>

<p>Delta 15N values differ between nitrogen sourced from precipitation, fertilizer and sewage, and also due to subsequent fractionation during assimilation by plants and other nitrogen transformation processes. Fractionation is the enrichment of one isotope relative to another through biogeochemical processes that discriminate against the heavier isotope. Further, gaseous nitrogen losses through denitrification and ammonia volatilisation can lead to even more elevated δ15N values of the nitrogen initially derived from both inorganic fertilizer and manure. Catchment land-use intensity has been positively related to δ15N values of stream water, sediment, aquatic plants, consumers and fish. </p>

<p>Among stream consumers, invertebrate grazers represent an important link for nutrient and energy transfer from primary producers to higher trophic levels. Moreover, they have been used as bioindicators because they are widely distributed in running waters and generally reflect the isotopic values of their periphyton food sources (after taking into account enrichment through trophic fractionation). Compared to the high spatiotemporal variation of periphyton stable isotope values, grazers provide a more time-integrated and habitat-integrated measure of nitrogen sources and transformation processes. </p>

<p>Most of the existing stream studies have reported positive linear relationships between δ15N values and catchment land-use intensity, although Larson et al. reported a saturation curve for δ15N values along a wide gradient of % agriculture. To our knowledge, no studies have investigated the combined effects of multiple, simultaneously operating agricultural stressors on consumer stable isotope ratios, even though non-additive effects such as antagonisms and synergisms have been documented from experiments assessing changes in diversity and ecosystem processes in freshwater ecosystems. Nor have previous studies focused on multiple primary consumers: most have investigated the relationship between a single primary consumer taxon or calculated δ15N values from several taxa combined where the focal consumer taxon was not present at all sites. Whether different primary consumer taxa show similar relationships along gradients of anthropogenic disturbance remains to be investigated. </p>

<p>Against this background, we studied consumer stable isotope values at 43 stream sites spanning wide gradients of land-use intensity (sheep/beef farming intensity and streamflow reduction) within an agricultural river catchment, to test the following hypotheses:<list>
<item>δ15N values of common primary consumers (grazers) will show similar patterns along the gradients of catchment land-use intensity because they all feed on one resource (periphyton) and are therefore ingesting food with the same isotopic composition;</item>
<item>δ15N values are positively related to catchment land-use intensities because higher farming intensity and greater flow reduction increase the input of heavy isotopes from fertilisation and increase the intensity of nitrogen transformation processes; and</item>
<item>δ15N values follow antagonistic response patterns along the gradients of land-use intensity and flow reduction because both stressors have strong individual effects and their joint effects cannot exceed 100%.</item>
</list>
 </p>
</text>
