<text id="autogum_academic_doc146" title="Relative Income and Life Satisfaction among Chinese Adults" shortTile="relative-income-life" author="Chenghua Guan, Yingjie Qiu, Ruopeng An" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5651/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Literature Review</head>
<p>
Existing definitions of happiness, subjective well-being, life satisfaction, and quality of life suggest a conceptual overlap between these constructs. However, a related study showed that high positive correlations between happiness, subjective well-being, psychological, and health domains of quality of life, life satisfaction, and positive affect. Actually, subjective well-being refers to an individual’s overall assessment of the quality of life from his or her own perspective. Conventional measures for subjective well-being primarily focused on the tangible aspects of living conditions, such as housing and employment, whereas more recent research starts to explore the less tangible parts of subjective well-being, namely what people think and feel about their lives, such as the quality of their relationships, their emotions and resilience, and their overall life satisfaction. As a key component of subjective well-being, life satisfaction is one’s evaluation of life as a whole, rather than the feelings and emotions that are experienced in the moment.  </p>

<p>Early studies on life satisfaction were conducted within the domains of psychology and philosophy and focused on the individual-level determinants of life satisfaction, such as genes, personalities, and value systems. Human health is increasingly recognized as “a state of complete physical, mental, and social well-being and not merely the absence of disease or infirmity”. Subsequently, life satisfaction, as an important dimension of human well-being, has attracted attention from a variety of research disciplines including public health, economics, sociology, education, and policy. An extensive set of demographic and socioeconomic factors, such as employment, religion, health status, educational attainment, social network, and income, were documented to be associated with life satisfaction. </p>

<p>The relationship between income and life satisfaction could be complex. Conventional economic theory predicts an increase in life satisfaction (also known as “utility” in economics terminology) attributable to people’s ability to purchase and consume more goods given a higher disposable income. Indeed, empirical evidence from less developed nations documented higher life satisfaction in response to economic growth, but such a positive relationship between income and life satisfaction was not replicated in the wealthy nations. These contradicting observations led to the Easterlin Paradox—an increase in personal income can significantly increase happiness and life satisfaction; when income level is low, happiness or life satisfaction is initially positively influenced by income both across and within nations, whereas life satisfaction is simply less dependent income as one’s wealth increases. </p>

<p>The relative income hypothesis posits that the satisfaction or utility a person derives from a given income depends on its relative magnitude in the society rather than its absolute amount. This hypothesis might hold the potential to explain, at least in part, the Easterlin Paradox—as people’s living condition continues to improve, relative income could play a more essential role in determining life satisfaction relative to absolute income. A handful of recent studies assessed the influence of relative income on people’s life satisfaction, independent of their absolute income level. The majority reported a positive relationship between relative income and life satisfaction. However, these studies defined relative income in a single dimension. </p>

<p>Measures on relative income can be largely classified into two major categories: (1) an objective measure, such as absolute income level relative to the median or average income of an individual’s community, city, state/province, or country of residence, or of an individual’s gender, age, or education group, and (2) a subjective measure, such as self-perceived relative income level in comparison to a reference group. This study adopted a subjective relative income measure and further refined it by making a contrast with four different dimensions of one’s social network. </p>

<p>There is not much direct evidence to date about those whom people really compare themselves to. Most of the time, the evidence for comparison is indirect. This is because surveys usually do not contain direct questions about the composition of reference groups. Previous studies have usually defined reference groups based on geographical location or demographic characteristics. However, other social reference groups that have frequent social contact with individuals, such as relatives and friends, may be more prominent. In addition, previous studies have not systematically studied which geographic aggregation level has the greatest influence on life satisfaction. Residents of the same community or city may be a particularly important reference groups. </p>

<p>Some papers have defined the reference group as the inhabitants of the geographical area where the respondent lives. Certain authors defined reference groups as being composed of people with whom one has daily interactions, such as friends and colleagues. Only a few studies have identified different social dimensions of relative income at the same time. None of the above studies assessed the potential mediating and/or moderating effect from certain personal characteristics, most prominently, gender and health status. The relative importance attached to a specific reference group may differ between men and women in income comparisons, partially due to the historical and enduring division of labor between genders. As for the less healthy individuals, they could be more concerned about their health status than other things. </p>
</text>
