<text id="autogum_news_doc614" title="US director James Gunn fired from Marvel Studios for decade-old offensive tweets" shortTile="director-james-gunn" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2018-07-21" dateModified="2019-07-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_director_James_Gunn_fired_from_Marvel_Studios_for_decade-old_offensive_tweets" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>US director James Gunn fired from Marvel Studios for decade-old offensive tweets</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, July 23, 2018</hi></p>
<p>On Friday, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">US</ref> director and screenwriter <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James%20Gunn">James Gunn</ref> was fired from work on <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guardians%20of%20the%20Galaxy%20Vol.%203">Guardians of the Galaxy Vol. 3</ref></hi> for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marvel%20Studios">Marvel Studios</ref> reportedly for his offensive <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Twitter">tweets</ref> from 2008 to 2011 about, amongst other things, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Rape">rape</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/paedophilia">paedophilia</ref>.</p>
<figure><caption>File photo of James Gunn, 2014. Image: <ref target="https://www.flickr.com/photos/minglemediatv">Mingle Media TV</ref> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/flickr">flickr</ref>) (<ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/deed.en">CC BY 2.0</ref>).</caption></figure>
<p>In a statement, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Walt_Disney_Company">Walt Disney</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walt%20Disney%20Studios%20(division)">Studios</ref>' Chairman <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alan%20Horn">Alan Horn</ref> said, "The offensive attitudes and statements discovered on James' Twitter feed are indefensible and inconsistent with our studio's values, and we have severed our business relationship with him".</p>
<p>The Walt Disney Company owns Marvel Studios. James Gunn wrote the screenplay and directed Marvel movies <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guardians%20of%20the%20Galaxy%20(film)">Guardians of the Galaxy</ref></hi>, released in 2014, and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guardians%20of%20the%20Galaxy%20Vol.%202">Guardians of the Galaxy Vol. 2</ref></hi>, released in 2017. Based on the comic book characters in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marvel%20Comics">Marvel Comics</ref>, the movie franchise featured <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chris%20Pratt">Chris Pratt</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zoe%20Saldana">Zoe Saldana</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dave%20Bautista">Dave Bautista</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karen%20Gillian">Karen Gillian</ref>  as well as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bradley%20Cooper">Bradley Cooper</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vin%20Diesel">Vin Diesel</ref> as voice cast for CGI characters. The two movies earned a worldwide box office revenue of about <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/USD">USD</ref> 773 million and USD 864 million per <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Box%20Office%20Mojo">Box Office Mojo</ref>'s statistics. Gunn had been writing the third movie in the franchise reportedly to be released in 2020.</p>
<p>Responding to his firing, James Gunn said, "My words of nearly a decade ago were, at the time, totally failed and unfortunate efforts to be provocative. I have regretted them for many years since — not just because they were stupid, not at all funny, wildly insensitive, and certainly not provocative like I had hoped, but also because they don't reflect the person I am today or have been for some time. Regardless of how much time has passed, I understand and accept the business decisions taken today. Even these many years later, I take full responsibility for the way I conducted myself then."</p>
<p>In one of the old tweets, Gunn wrote, "The best thing about being raped is when you're done being raped and it's like 'whew this feels great, not being raped!'"</p>
<p>Dave Bautista, who portrays Drax the Destroyer in Gunn's Marvel movies, tweeted about Gunn's dismissal saying, "James Gunn is one of the most loving, caring, good natured people I have ever met. He's gentle and kind and cares deeply for people and animals. He's made mistakes. We all have. I'm NOT ok with what's happening to him".</p>
<p>After Gunn was fired, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20Dastmalchian">David Dastmalchian</ref>, an actor in the latest Marvel Studios movie <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ant-Man%20and%20the%20Wasp">Ant-Man and the Wasp</ref></hi> wrote on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Instagram">Instagram</ref>, "i've been saying this FOR YEARS! @jamesgunn is one of the most amazing people I've ever known - both professionally &amp; personally. there are so many people in our lives that we would never have known without the incredible magnet of talent &amp; goodness that is James [...] thanks for making us a part of your family, buddy."</p>
</text>
