<text id="autogum_academic_doc108" title="The Impact of the Quality of Interpersonal Relationships between Employees on Counterproductive Work Behavior: A Study of Employees in Poland" shortTile="impact-quality-interpersonal" author="Dawid Szostek" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5916/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The quality of interpersonal work relationships determines the behaviors that employees engage in both at work and in their private lives. As a rule, high quality relationships translate beneficially into, among others: commitment, performance, motivation, innovation, error detection, OHS, employee green behaviors (EGB), teamwork, helping others, internal and external organizational communication, absenteeism, conflict and resilience to negative events. Conversely, low quality relationships between employees have a detrimental impact on these aspects of an organization’s operation.  </p>

<p>Therefore, counterproductive work behaviors (CWB) must also be influenced by the quality of interpersonal relationships at work. This is because these behaviors are influenced by the group and are a behavioral (adaptive) response to certain workplace conditions. </p>

<p>This interrelationship is quite apparent, so, if these relationships are of a high quality, employees will tend less towards CWB. By the same reasoning, if relationship quality is low, counterproductive behaviors will be engaged in more often. In practice, however, there are many paradoxes, which is to say that negative relationships can have beneficial effects, while positive relationships can have detrimental effects (for the organization and its stakeholders). One such example is the case in which high-quality work relationships increase the propensity for counterproductive behavior directed against a person. This can be explained by the fact that such relationships are characterized by more frequent interaction and higher trust, which provides more opportunities for abuse. The research issue is thus very complex and is strongly influenced by situational conditions and the features of the employees themselves. </p>

<p>Thus far, the understanding of this relationship has tended to be based on intuition, and on research results that are scant at best, and that have been later cited by other authors as empirically confirmed paradigms. The empirical studies on this topic are not comprehensive and focus on selected aspects of the impact of QIRW on CWB. For example: Skarlicki and Folger investigated the impact of relationship quality on employee retaliation; Brass et al. analyzed the impact of relationship quality on conspiracy; and Roberts focused on the importance of relationship quality on, among others, work avoidance, the defensive behavior of personnel or the tendency to recognize one’s own mistakes and to accept criticism. In turn, based on a meta-analysis of 161 articles, Chiaburu and Harrison concluded that antagonisms between employees correlate negatively with job satisfaction, commitment and performance, and positively with absenteeism, the desire to leave work, staff turnover and CWB. Ragins and Verbos also indicated a positive relationship between low relationship quality (understood as the exploitation of one party by another) and dysfunctional behaviors. </p>

<p>It is significant that researchers are more keen to examine the beneficial aspects of the quality of work relationships and the significance of this quality for organizational citizenship behavior (OCB), also in the field of sustainability (see, e.g.,). It is therefore no surprise that Colbert et al. indicate the need to describe the effects of negative relationships at work. In turn, Bowler and Brass recommend expanding our knowledge on how these relationships influence counterproductive behavior. </p>

<p>There is even sparser research on how CWB’s relationship with QIRW is moderated by such key demographic features as employee sex, age, education, length of service and type of work. In essence, the research refers only to the last of these variables. For example, Ikola-Norrbacka found that white collar workers are less likely to engage in CWB than blue collar workers. </p>

<p>However, the topic is very important, because counterproductive behavior has multiple detrimental consequences and generates significant costs, and not only for the organization itself, but also for its surroundings (the natural environment, society, etc.). These costs can be divided into economic costs (quantifiable) and non-economic costs (non-quantifiable or difficult-to-quantify, e.g., hospitalization, earlier retirement benefits, lower professional activity, loss of reputation, lower employee morale, increased environmental pollution, wasting of limited natural resources). The economic costs in the US alone are estimated at USD 6 to 200 billion per year. Violence at work costs USD 4.2 billion, and cybercrime USD 7.1 billion per year.  </p>

<p>Counterproductive behaviors and their effects therefore conflict with the principle of sustainable development in the sense of “development that meets the needs of the present generation without compromising the ability of future generations to meet theirs” (p. 41). This applies not only to environmental factors (e.g., increased pollution, increased waste material), but also to economic (e.g., increased costs, increased consumption of raw materials) and social factors (e.g., deterioration of working conditions, threats to employee psychophysical health, unequal treatment, damage to the sense of community). These unsustainable behaviors are often a consequence of inappropriate interpersonal relationships at work. They can be a form of revenge on an organization or other people in the organization (e.g., if the manager does not treat employees fairly, they may deliberately carry out their tasks incorrectly or steal in the workplace). A solid understanding of this is essential at all stages of sustainable human resource management. Consequently, the knowledge of how to limit CWB (including those that impede sustainability) through traditional HR practices (e.g., employee selection) is limited.  </p>
</text>
