<text id="autogum_interview_doc392" title="part5_The Raveonettes on love, death, desire and war" shortTile="partthe-raveonettes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-16" dateModified="2010-12-23" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Raveonettes_on_love%2C_death%2C_desire_and_war" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  Were you?  I would probably be...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  No, at that point my body just gave out, I was completely relaxed and I was just like...that's it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Sharin, did you ever have a moment where you confronted your own death?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  When I was nine years old I was definitely close, but I wasn't aware of how dangerous it was.  When I think of it now I'm like, "Wow! That could have been it."</p>
<figure><caption>"I get much more affected not so much by war itself but when I hear about civilians involved in war. But I was much more affected by stuff that happens in Chechnya, for instance. I used to read a lot about that, and that is a forgotten war that really people don't give a shit about."photo: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref></caption></figure><figure><caption>"The extreme within the religion here in the U.S., that can be a little terrifying, I think.  But religion can also add a lot of purpose to people, and when they have purpose they can be more balanced and open-minded."photo: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref></caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What was it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  I was living in the countryside and there was a well with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Urine">urine</ref> from the cows, and it was open, and I fell into it.  My neighbor caught my hand, so I was hanging in the well with my feet in the urine.  And then afterwards, my parents were freaked out.  It was really lucky that my neighbor was right there and he caught me, because I would have died immediately.  You fall into that urine in a well, that's it! [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>] That's it!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  That would have made a great end to the interview!  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  I like that! [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What's your favorite curse word?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  Curse word?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fuck">Fuck</ref>.  I use that all the time.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  Yeah, that's probably the only one I use.  In <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Danish">Danish</ref>...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  We use the same word!  "Fuck."  We use it all the time.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  Sune definitely uses it all the time.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Chuckles</hi>]</p>
<head id="On_war">On war</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do you think is the greatest depth of human misery?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  I...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Sighs</hi>]  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Famine">Famine</ref>?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Famine?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  Maybe.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Starving to death?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  Yeah.  It just seems so...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Slow.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  Yeah, and it just seems so <hi rend="italic">unnecessary</hi>.  Know what I mean?  Just seems so...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  Obviously, war.  Being in a war.  Being in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Darfur%20conflict">Darfur</ref> right now, for instance.  That's one of the extremes of human misery, when you are so completely <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Innocence">innocent</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And seemingly so few people are paying attention.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  Yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Has the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraq%20War">Iraq War</ref> affected either of you as artists at all?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  No.</p>
</text>
