<text id="autogum_news_doc466" title="Football: Atlético Madrid beats Marseille 3-0 to win third Europa League title" shortTile="football-atletico" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2018-05-16" dateModified="2018-05-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Football%3A_Atl%C3%A9tico_Madrid_beats_Marseille_3-0_to_win_third_Europa_League_title" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Football: Atlético Madrid beats Marseille 3-0 to win third Europa League title</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 19, 2018</hi></p>
<p>On Wednesday, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Spain">Spanish</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Madrid">capital</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Soccer">football</ref> club <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Atlético_Madrid">Atlético Madrid</ref> defeated <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">French</ref> team <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Olympique%20de%20Marseille">Olympique de Marseille</ref> 3–0 to win the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UEFA%20Europa%20League">UEFA Europa League</ref> Final at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parc%20Olympique%20Lyonnais">Stade de Lyon</ref>, in France. French striker <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Antoine_Griezmann">Antoine Griezmann</ref> scored a brace (two goals in one game), one goal in each half, and Atlético's captain <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gabriel%20Fernández%20Arenas">Gabi</ref> netted the third goal a few minutes before the final whistle as Atlético won the UEFA Europa League for the third time. This was Marseille's third defeat in three Europa League or <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UEFA_Cup">UEFA Cup</ref> finals, never netting a single goal in the final.</p>
<figure><caption>File photo of Antoine Griezmann who scored twice and won Man of the Match Image: <ref target="https://www.flickr.com/photos/dsanchez17/">DSanchez17</ref>. (<ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/deed.en">CC BY 2.0</ref>)</caption></figure>
<p>Marseille had greater ball possession and better passing accuracy. Marseille were awarded three free-kicks in the first ten minutes of the match. The French side created several chances in the first half but failed to convert any into a goal. Around the 20th minute, Marseille's André Zambo Anguissa lost the ball, as Madrid's captain Gabi assisted Griezmann who opened the scoring with his left foot. A couple of minutes later, a referee made the first booking of the match. Atlético's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Šime%20Vrsaljko">Šime Vrsaljko</ref> received a yellow card for a bad foul. Just after the half-hour mark, Marseille's midfielder <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dimitri%20Payet">Dimitri Payet</ref> was injured and replaced by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maxime%20Lopez">Maxime Lopez</ref>. Payet has provided 22 assists in all competitions this season. The first half ended in a 1–0 lead for the Spanish side. Marseille's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jordan%20Amavi">Jordan Amavi</ref> was the second player to receive a yellow card.</p>
<p>At the beginning of the second half, Vrsaljko was replaced by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juanfran">Juanfran</ref> due to injury. Less than five minutes into the second half, Frenchman Griezman doubled the lead, scoring another left-footed goal, assisted by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jorge%20Koke">Koke</ref>. Koke also assisted Gabi in the 89th minute, who scored his first goal for Atlético since August 2015. 34-year-old Gabi became the oldest player to score a goal in a Europa final. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Fernando_Torres">Fernando Torres</ref> was substituted for Griezmann in the 90th minute. Marseille committed eighteen fouls in the match, twice as many as their opponents. Madrid's goalkeeper <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jan%20Oblak">Jan Oblak</ref> acheived his seventh clean sheet in this season's European competitions — UEFA Champions League and Europa League.</p>
<p>Griezmann was awarded the Man of the Match award. After winning the match, Griezmann said, "I've been working to experience such a moment for many years". Marseille's defender Adil Rami said, "The final step was too far for us but we fought for everything. We lacked experience. Against a team like this you shouldn't try to play football. You need to knock it long and high and win second balls. When you try to play and lose the ball against them, that's when you're in trouble. The opening goal we conceded was the turning point. Up until then we had troubled their defence."</p>
<p>Previously, Atlético won the Europa League in 2010 and 2012. This was the second Europa league victory for the <hi rend="italic">Rojiblancos</hi> under Diego Simeone's management. Atlético has also reached two UEFA Champions League finals under Simeone's management — in 2014 and 2016 — losing both to their city rivals <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Real_Madrid">Real Madrid</ref>.</p>
May 16, 2018circa 20:45 local time (1845 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UTC">UTC</ref>)
<hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Olympique%20de%20Marseille">Olympique de Marseille</ref></hi>
<hi rend="bold">0–3</hi>
<hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Atlético_Madrid">Atlético Madrid</ref></hi>
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parc%20Olympique%20Lyonnais">Stade de Lyon</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lyon">Lyon</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">France</ref> Attendance: 55,768 Referee:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Björn%20Kuipers">Björn Kuipers</ref> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Koninklijke%20Nederlandse%20Voetbalbond">Netherlands</ref>)
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jordan%20Amavi">Jordan Amavi</ref>  38'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luiz%20Gustavo">Luiz Gustavo</ref>  75'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clinton%20N'Jie">Clinton N'Jie</ref>  78'
(0–1) <hi rend="bold">HT</hi>
<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Antoine_Griezmann">Antoine Griezmann</ref>  21'Antione Griezmann  49'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gabriel%20Fernández%20Arenas">Gabi</ref>  89' <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Šime%20Vrsaljko">Šime Vrsaljko</ref>  23'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lucas%20Hernández">Lucas Hernández</ref>  78'
</text>
