<text id="autogum_bio_doc426" title="John Watts (merchant)" shortTile="john-watts-merchant" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-02-11" dateModified="2019-10-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Watts_%28merchant%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>John Watts (merchant)</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">Sir John Watts</hi> (1554 ca - 1616) was an English merchant and shipowner, active in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/East_India_Company">East India Company</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virginia_Company">Virginia Company</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Mayor_of_London">Lord Mayor of London</ref> in 1606.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>The son of Thomas Watts of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buntingford">Buntingford</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hertfordshire">Hertfordshire</ref>, he was owner of the <hi rend="italic">Margaret</hi> and <hi rend="italic">John</hi>, one of the ships paid by the city of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London">London</ref> in 1588 to sail against the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spanish_armada">Spanish armada</ref>. Watts himself served in her as a volunteer, and saw action. In 1590 the same ship was one of a fleet of merchantmen coming home from the Mediterranean, which successfully <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_the_Strait_of_Gibraltar_(1590)">fought and repelled the Spanish galleys</ref> near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cadiz">Cadiz</ref>. Although Watts was not on board, throughout the war he equipped and financed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Privateer">privateers</ref> led by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Geare">Michael Geare</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Lane_(died_1618)">William Lane</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Newport">Christopher Newport</ref>. A few of his notable successes include his financed and organised <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Watts'_West_Indies_and_Virginia_expedition">expedition to the Spanish main</ref> in 1590, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blockade_of_Western_Cuba">expedition to Cuba</ref> the following year and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Lancaster">James Lancaster</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capture_of_Recife_(1595)">expedition to Recife</ref> in April 1595. Watt's received significant prize money from the success of these expeditions. Another in July 1601 took into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plymouth">Plymouth</ref> a prize coming from the Indies laden with China silks, satins and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taffeta">taffetas</ref>. At this time he was an alderman of London (Tower ward), and had been suspected of being a supporter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Devereux,_2nd_Earl_of_Essex">Robert Devereux, 2nd Earl of Essex</ref>.</p>
<p>He was one of the founders of the East India Company, and on 11April 1601 was elected its governor, during the imprisonment of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Smythe">Sir Thomas Smythe</ref>. He served as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sheriff_of_the_City_of_London">Sheriff of the City of London</ref> in 1597. On the accession of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_I">James I</ref> he was knighted on 26July 1603, becoming <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Mayor_of_London">Lord Mayor of London</ref> in 1606–1607, at which time he was described in a letter to the king of Spain as "the greatest pirate that has ever been in this kingdom".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Bicheno-1">[1]</ref> During the following years he was an active member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virginia_Company">Virginia Company</ref>. In the city of London, Watts was a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clothworkers'_Company">Clothworkers' Company</ref>.</p>
<p>Watts died at his seat in Hertfordshire in September 1616, and was buried on the 7th of the month at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ware,_Hertfordshire">Ware</ref>.</p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>By his wife Margaret, daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sir_James_Hawes">Sir James Hawes</ref>, knt. (lord mayor in 1574), he left four sons and four daughters. The eldest son, John, served in the Cadiz expedition and was knighted for his good service in 1625; he subsequently served under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Villiers,_1st_Duke_of_Buckingham">George Villiers, 1st Duke of Buckingham</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhé">Rhé</ref> expedition, and under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Count_Mansfeldt">Count Mansfeldt</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electorate_of_the_Palatinate">Electorate of the Palatinate</ref>; he married Mary, daughter of Thomas Bayning, and aunt of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Bayning,_1st_Viscount_Bayning">Paul Bayning, 1st Viscount Bayning</ref>, and left numerous issue. His eldest son (grandson of the lord mayor), who also became Sir John Watts, served an apprenticeship in arms under his father. He was knighted in 1642, and received a commission to raise a troop of arms for the king. Having been expelled from the governorship of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chirk_Castle">Chirk Castle</ref>, he attached himself to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arthur_Capell,_1st_Baron_Capell_of_Hadham">Arthur Capell, 1st Baron Capell of Hadham</ref>, and was one of the defenders of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colchester_Castle">Colchester Castle</ref> (August 1648). He compounded for delinquency by paying a fine, and was discharged on 11May 1649; however, he was forced to sell to Sir John Buck his manor of Mardocks in Ware. After the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Restoration_(1660)">Restoration</ref> he was made receiver for Essex and Hertfordshire. He died about 1680, and was buried in the church of Hertingfordbury.</p>
</text>
