<text id="autogum_academic_doc168" title="Multi-Level Modeling Methodology for Optimal Design of Electric Machines Based on Multi-Disciplinary Design Optimization" shortTile="multilevel-modeling" author="Zehua Dai, Li Wang, Lexuan Meng, Shanshui Yang, Ling Mao" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/21/4173/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Electrified transportation reveals significant benefits in terms of increased reliability, improved energy efficiency, reduced emissions, and enhanced passenger comfort. With the breakthrough of power electronics, the adoption of the More Electric Aircraft (MEA) and electric propulsion aircraft concepts have become a major trend in the air industry. As a result, many hydraulic and pneumatic power-driven systems are being replaced by their electrical counterparts in existing MEAs, e.g., Boeing 787 and Airbus 380. Moreover, the hybrid/all-electric propulsion electric grid is now being investigated. In electrified aircraft, the electric machine is the key equipment to realize the conversion and transformation of multi-physical energies; therefore, the sizing of the machine has become one of the leading topics in the study of transport electrification. </p>

<p>In addition, with the development of artificial intelligence and information technologies, model-based system engineering (MBSE) and optimization-assisted design have become the focus of researchers, becoming increasingly mature, and will be particularly powerful for the design of aircraft power systems. In this context, models of the electrical environment control system (ECS), electromagnetic actuators (EMAs), and electro-hydraulic actuators (EHAs) were established to support the trade-offs between the weight and power loss of More-electric systems. To implement these analyses, machine models for optimal designs have been widely investigated. The magnetic equivalent circuit (MEC) model has been used in the electromagnetic design of machines, given the multiple flux barrier and the variables (permeance, potential, etc.). However, the model requires external structural and thermal designs to gain better performance. The finite element model (FEM) can illustrate comprehensive characteristics of multi-physical fields of machines accurately. Nevertheless, it is highly complicated and computationally expensive to extract performance indexes, leading to difficult trade-offs. Therefore, it has mainly been applied to the detailed design phase of machines. Multi-physics models present the electromagnetic, geometrical, and thermal characteristics so that couplings of multi-physics can be evaluated to help assess the More-electric degree of aircraft. However, the multi-physics model of the permanent magnet synchronous generator (PMSG) developed in has 238 inputs and 941 outputs, which indicates that it results in high computational costs, and is not suitable for system-level studies. In contrast, the multi-physics model in has relatively low complexity. However, only the iron loss was considered the model, and couplings among components were not explicitly defined. In addition, although the multi-physics model has been simplified based on physical energetical equivalence, the eight-dimensional design space leads to the limited application to studies of More-electric systems. The use of scaling law (SL) has the advantage of requiring only a reference machine for a complete estimation of a product range, which provides the designer with parameters needed for integration. However, the method is project-specific and ignores the multi-physics couplings of machines. On the other hand, the law can be broken due to some limits, e.g., with an increase of power, a cooling method may be required to satisfy the permissible temperature rise. In power grid applications, machine models are usually built as polynomial functions of power, illustrating the influences of the energy allocation on the cost at a system level. Nevertheless, they are statistical results of particular products, and not yet applicable for aircraft applications. </p>

<p>In summary, although the sizing of machines is widely investigated, an efficient modeling system of machines for the design of aircraft power systems is still lacking. To meet the demand for aircraft electrification, a machine model for the design should satisfy both the descriptions of multi-physics couplings and ease of use, which requires a trade-off between accuracy and speed. </p>

<p>In this context, multi-disciplinary design optimization (MDO) allows for contending with the strong couplings of high-complex design problems by applying technologies of model approximation, sensitivity analysis, system problem decomposition, and coordination strategies, which inspires our work. Moreover, MDO applications in power systems have been proved to be attractive in the literature. The design problem of the ECS is decomposed into the optimization of different subsystems, e.g., the filter, inverter, and machine, by the collaborative optimization method in. According to different disciplines, the design of the permanent magnet synchronous motor is divided into problems of structure, manufacture, and multi-physics. However, the MDO method has not been applied to machine modeling in existing studies. </p>

<p>Accordingly, the main contribution of this study is to propose a novel model exchange process based on MDO to satisfy multi-level design requirements of electric machines in the aircraft power system, e.g., consistency, simplicity, and accuracy. The work is based on the improvement of the existing multi-physics model in. </p>
</text>
