<text id="autogum_academic_doc574" title="A Mixed Uncertainty Power Flow Algorithm-Based Centralized Photovoltaic (PV) Cluster" shortTile="mixed-uncertainty" author="Hao Wu, Lin Zhou, Yihao Wan, Qiang Liu, Siyu Zhou" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/20/4008/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
With the increasingly severe global energy crisis, developing renewable energy has become the consensus of the whole human society. The development of renewable energy is also an inevitable trend in future power systems. As a widely utilized renewable energy, solar energy has been developing rapidly in the world, especially in China in recent years. According to national energy-related data, by the end of 2018, China had added 44 GW of PV installations, with a total installed capacity of 174 GW, including 124 GW of centralized PV clusters.  </p>

<p>Power flow analysis is one of the most fundamental and heavily used tools in power engineering, such as reactive power optimization, state estimation, and fault diagnosis. It allows power system analysts to determine the steady state or operating conditions of a power system for a specified set of values, such as load and generation levels. Power flow calculation is the basis of power flow analysis. On the one hand, power flow calculation can provide the basis for the selection of electrical equipment and the optimization of power supply schemes for power system planning; on the other hand, it can provide the analysis of static security and adjust operation mode for the power system, as well as provide the initial data for fault calculation and stability calculation of the power system. However, due to the fluctuation of PV cells, the original deterministic power flow calculation model is no longer applicable. As centralized PV clusters undertake more and more power transmission tasks in the power grid, its stable operation is crucial to the stability of the entire power grid. In order to ensure the safe, stable, and reliable operation of power systems, it is particularly important to study the uncertain power flow algorithm of centralized PV clusters. </p>

<p>At present, there are three main calculation methods for uncertain power flow: (1) The fuzzy mathematical method; (2) the probability power flow method, which mainly includes the analytical method, the approximation method and the simulation method; and (3) interval analysis. When the first and second kinds of methods are adopted, the probability density function or membership function of uncertain parameters needs to be known; due to the randomness of data, these functions are difficult to be determined in practice and usually rely on presetting. Considering the above limitations, the third type, the interval analysis method, is considered to be an effective method to solve the problem of uncertain power flow because it only needs to determine the range of variables, which is simple to model. In addition, interval analysis can avoid the interference of human factors, which has been paid close attention by researchers. Based on the existing research results, the calculation methods of interval power flow are mainly divided into the affine optimization method, the direct optimization method, and the iterative method. In, an affine-based interval power flow analysis method was proposed. By solving a power flow equation and two linear programming problems, the upper and lower bounds of the power flow solutions that restrain interval extension were obtained. In, Taylor expansion of intervals was carried out according to affine ideas, and interval power flow equations in the Cartesian coordinate system were expanded into three deterministic power flow equations for solution, which avoids interval iteration process. However, as with, the complexity of the calculation is increased by Taylor expansion. In, an interval optimization framework was proposed. Upper and lower bounds of power flow solutions were obtained respectively by solving two deterministic optimization problems. Reference proposed a new optimization scenario method, which regarded the uncertainty of the interval as bounded variables and solved these unknown variables using the two methods of minimum programming model and maximum programming model, which determined the range of interval power flow problem. In, the Ybus Gaussian iterative interval power flow equation in complex affine form was established considering the uncertainty of the operation of distributed power supply. The iterative process was simplified and the accuracy and efficiency of interval power flow calculation were improved by using the method of noise element merging. In, the Krawczyk-Moore operator was used to combine interval and affine to achieve the requirement of overcoming interval conservatism. </p>
</text>
