<text id="autogum_academic_doc515" title="Actigraphic Sleep and Dietary Macronutrient Intake in Children Aged 6–9 Years Old: A Pilot Study" shortTile="actigraphic-sleep" author="Silvia Coronado Ferrer, Isabel Peraita-Costa, Agustín Llopis-Morales, Yolanda Picó, José  Miguel Soriano, F.  Javier Nieto, Agustín Llopis-González, María Morales-Suarez-Varela" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6643/11/11/2568/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Adequate nutrition during childhood is es−sential to promote correct growth and development. It is vital that children are provided with a diet containing adequate quantities of energy, macro- and micronutrients to allow them reach their growth and development potential. Diet is one of the numerous factors that have been associated with childhood weight status, which, when grouped together, are known as the obesogenic environment. Another obesogenic factor that has been associated to the increase of child overweight and obesity is sleep. </p>

<p>Studies have observed that sleep deprivation might be one of the modifiable factors that promote inadequate nutritional intake and contribute to unhealthy food consumption behavior and excess weight gain. In the last decade, the increased prevalence of obesity has been associated with sleep curtailment. Previous cross-sectional and prospective studies have identified a relationship between shorter sleep duration and increased obesity in children, even after covariate adjustment including important obesity-related behaviors. A recent meta-analysis identified that reduced sleep was consistently related to a greater risk of being overweight or obese and its effect was even more pronounced in children. In addition, recent studies have shown that not only sleep duration contributes to obesity, but also timing, quality and sleep disturbances could play an important role.  </p>

<p>Numerous findings suggested that reduced and poor sleep were linked to increased snacking and preference for poorer food choices, including energy-dense foods and snacks with higher fat and refined sugar content. With respect to macronutrient composition, sleeping less is associated with an intake of a higher proportion of calories from fats, however, the mechanisms underlying this relationship remain unclear.  </p>

<p>Some hypotheses have proposed that the relationship between reduced sleep and excess food intake is based on social, behavioral and hedonic reasons. In an environment that offers free access to ultra-palatable foods or caloric snacks, delayed bedtime or reduced sleep increases the potential time available to eat while engaging in sedentary activities. On the other hand, delayed bedtime favors later wake up times and sleep disturbances induce daytime sleepiness and tiredness, which stimulates food intake. These factors influence the decrease of physical activity during the day and therefore, energy expenditure is reduced. In summary, short sleep duration would favor excess food intake by reducing opportunities for physical activity and enhancing opportunities to overeat.  </p>

<p>Given the possibility that children may be susceptible to sleep alterations that may favor the risk of excess food intake and that sleep is a modifiable factor, it is important to continue with research that aims to explain the influence and determine the importance of adequate sleep so that policies and interventions for nutrition management programs can be developed. Previous studies have demonstrated that sleep interventions are effective for child obesity prevention. Accelerometers have been used in sleep research for over 20 years and have been validated for use in pediatric populations. Actigraphy allows for a more objective recording of sleep parameters, such as sleep duration, efficiency, and variability, than traditional parent-report and is less intrusive than polysomnography.  </p>

<p>The purpose of the current study was to analyze the relationship between objectively measured sleep duration, efficiency and variability in sleep duration with energy and macronutrient intake in children between 6 and 9 years old. </p>
</text>
