<text id="autogum_interview_doc408" title="Canada&amp;apos;s Davenport (Ward 17) city council candidates speak" shortTile="canadas-davenport" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-11-04" dateModified="2009-04-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Davenport_%28Ward_17%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Canada's Davenport (Ward 17) city council candidates speak</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 4, 2006</hi></p>
<p>On November 13, Torontoians will be heading to the polls to vote for their ward's councillor and for mayor. Among Toronto's ridings is Davenport (Ward 17). One candidates responded to Wikinews' requests for an interview. This ward's candidates include Wilson Basantes Espinoza, Alejandra Bravo, Fred Dominelli, David Faria, Cesar Palacio (incumbent), Cinzia Scalabrini, and <hi rend="bold">Gustavo Valdez</hi>.</p>
<p>For more information on the election, read <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toronto%20municipal%20election,%202006">Toronto municipal election, 2006</ref>.</p>
<head id="Gustavo_Valdez">Gustavo Valdez</head>
<p>48-year-old <hi rend="bold">Gustavo Valdez</hi> is the publisher of a small magazine and "actor, character, artist".</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Describe the three most important issues in your campaign.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> a) Community Safety and crime prevention b) Fair property taxes and improved city services c) Cleaner and Greener neighborhoods</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What one election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Saint Clair Street Car right of way. Even the neighborhoods oppose to it, I believe we have to do Saint Clair 22 century, however I will follow what the community wishes</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> For the tax problem then the community  me his offered  its support</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent this particular ward on council?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Because its the ward were I live</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Trough my artistic side, singing and writing for them in my small publication. Performing also my poetry. I can not involve directly right know in the community local issues due I am a father of 2 children. I care personally for them.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Which council decision (since the 2003 election) do you feel the city/your ward should be most proud of, and which was least desirable?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> In keeping going and growing, the least desirable is the growing homeless community</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> If you were elected as a "rookie" councillor, What would you bring to the table beyond the incumbent?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> The municipal government need to provide incentives and motivate entrepreneurship through tax cutting, low operating and administrative system of work. It we'll create jobs, revenue and wealth. But we need to motivate the community. We need more parks health centers, shelters and food banks.</p>
<p>Affordable housing at ward 17 and the entire city is essential.</p>
<p>Taxes on property should be cut of and utilities lowered.</p>
<p>Special attention should be put on low child care facilities to ease parents and allow them to work for the welfare of their families.</p>
<p>The family is the center of the society.</p>
<p>We look forward to defeat poverty.</p>
<p>More creational activities are necessary for the social isolated and disabled and people with special necessities.</p>
<p>Of woman is part of our agenda. They need always attention.</p>
<p>We need to incentive the working class: They are the ones who construct the city, produce and keep the economy going.</p>
<p>Special attention for the working class is necessary.</p>
<p>I care for the environment,therefore we have to work for the greenhouse-gas emission problem and Kyoto Protocol.</p>
<p>Toronto is one of the most polluted cities in North America and we have to work on the air we breath free.</p>
<p>In building a great communities we build a great country. And we have to prepare the country for the years to come to face the challenges of the future.</p>
<p>So education is important. If we educate citizens we dot have to worry about crime and to spent money in unnecessary security and control,instead more education more safe city,happy families therefore neighborhoods.</p>
<p>Let's be prepare with vision for the future.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What does Toronto mean to you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> It's the city were I risen my kids, therefore I am interested in the city for the good will of the community and my family itself</p>
</text>
