<text id="autogum_news_doc496" title="Simulations show planet orbiting Proxima Centauri could have liquid water" shortTile="simulations-show" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-05-17" dateModified="2017-05-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Simulations_show_planet_orbiting_Proxima_Centauri_could_have_liquid_water" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Simulations show planet orbiting Proxima Centauri could have liquid water</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 18, 2017</hi></p>
<p>In findings published Tuesday in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Astronomy%20and%20Astrophysics">Astronomy and Astrophysics</ref></hi>, a team of scientists led by Ian Boutle at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University%20of%20Exeter">University of Exeter</ref> have created successful simulations of two possible atmospheres of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Proxima%20B">Proxima B</ref>, an <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Exoplanet">exoplanet</ref> orbiting <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Proxima%20Centauri">Proxima Centauri</ref>, one a simple atmosphere of nitrogen tinged with carbon dioxide and another an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atmosphere%20of%20Earth">Earth-like mix of gases</ref>.  They found it possible that liquid water, a prerequisite for life as we know it, might exist on parts of the planet.</p>
<figure><caption>Artist's representation of Proxima B as an arid but not waterless rocky exoplanet.Image: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/European%20Southern%20Observatory">European Southern Observatory</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>The University of Exeter's lead exoplanet modeller, Dr. Nathan Mayne, in remarks to <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wired">Wired</ref></hi>, said, "If, and it is a huge if, the composition of the atmosphere was Earth-like then we showed the planet could indeed support temperatures which would allow liquid water on the surface". In another statement, he emphasized researchers could also "exploit this to hopefully improve our understanding of how our own climate has and will evolve".</p>
<p>Proxima B is believed roughly Earth-sized and in its solar system's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/habitable%20zone">habitable zone</ref>, meaning it would have similar gravity to Earth and at least the possibility of liquid water.  The exoplanet was discovered in August 2016 about 4.2 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/light%20year">light year</ref>s from Earth. Last year, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NASA">NASA</ref> put out a statement expressing doubt that the planet could have an atmosphere in the sense that most of us understand it: "Considering the host star's age and the planet's proximity to its host star, the scientists expect that Proxima B is subjected to torrents of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/X-ray">X-ray</ref> and extreme <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ultraviolet">ultraviolet</ref> radiation from superflares occurring roughly every two hours."</p>
<p>Co-author Dr. James Manners said, "One of the main features that distinguishes this planet from Earth is that the light from its star is mostly in the near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/infra-red">infra-red</ref>[...] These frequencies of light interact much more strongly with water vapour and carbon dioxide in the atmosphere which affects the climate that emerges in our model."</p>
<p>This new model allowed scientists to evaluate the effects of Proxima B's possible orbits and likely exposure to radiation and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/solar%20flares">solar flares</ref> from its <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/red%20dwarf">red dwarf</ref> sun on two types of atmospheres. The specifics of Proxima B's orbit are not yet established.  It might rotate around its axis quickly the way Earth does or it might be <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/tidally%20locked">tidally locked</ref> to its sun, with one side of the planet always lit and the other always dark.  It might have a near-circular orbit or an elliptical one.  All these variations would have different effects on the flow of any gases over its surface.  The models described in this paper review two possible orbits: one tidally locked and one modeled after <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mercury_(planet)">Mercury's</ref>, with a slow-rotating three days per year.</p>
<p>The team used the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Met%20Office">Met Office</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unified%20Model">Unified Model</ref> to produce the simulations.</p>
</text>
