<text id="autogum_interview_doc817" title="part2_Satanism: An interview with Church of Satan High Priest Peter Gilmore" shortTile="partsatanism-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-04" dateModified="2018-10-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Satanism%3A_An_interview_with_Church_of_Satan_High_Priest_Peter_Gilmore" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="Church_of_Satan_101">Church of Satan 101</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">David Shankbone:  How would you define the word <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Satan">Satan</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Peter Gilmore:</hi>  Satan is a model or a mode of behavior.  Satan in Hebrew means "adversary" or "opposer"; one who questions.  Since we generally are skeptical atheists, we question all spirituality.  We believe that carnality is all that exists and the spiritual dimensions are fictional.  So we stand against eastern and western religions that promote fictions, according to our perspectives.  So we are adversaries.  Satan to us is an exemplar.  When we look at how he is portrayed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark%20Twain">Mark Twain</ref> in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Letters%20from%20the%20Earth">Letters from the Earth</ref></hi>, or Byron, or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20Milton">Milton</ref>'s <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paradise%20Lost">Paradise Lost</ref></hi>, he ends up being an inspirational symbol to us.  We say we would like to be more like that.  We will not bow our heads; we will be independent.  We will constantly question.</p>
<hi rend="bold">You can't be praying to a God or blaming a devil, or anyone else, for that matter, for what happens to you.  It’s on your own head.  That’s a challenge for most people.</hi>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What is the Church of Satan?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  Satanism begins with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Atheism">atheism</ref>.  We begin with the universe and say, “It’s indifferent.  There’s no God, there’s no Devil.  No one cares!”  So you then have to make a decision that places yourself at the center of your own subjective universe, because of course we can’t have any kind of objective contact with everything that exists.  That’s rather arrogant and delusional, people who try to put things that way.  So by making yourself the primary value in your life, you’re your own God.  By being your own God, you are comfortable about making your own decisions about what to value.  What’s positive to you, is good.  What harms you, is evil.  You extend it to things that you cherish and the people that you cherish.  So it’s actually very easy to see that it’s a self-centered philosophy.</p>
<p>But it also requires responsibility, since you are taking on for yourself the complete onus for your personal success or failure.  You can't be praying to a God or blaming a devil, or anyone else, for that matter, for what happens to you.  It’s on your own head.  That’s a challenge for most people.  Most people tend to really feel that they want some kind of external support, that they are outward looking and might want some sort of supernatural parental figure, or even some sort of existing governmental authority, existing in their life.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why do you think people are like that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  I think there are actually two kinds of people.  There are the kind of people who need that, and the kind that don't.  The kind that don't are the smaller percentage of our species.  It’s as simple as that.</p>
</text>
