<text id="autogum_academic_doc145" title="Nonuniform Woven Solar Shading Screens: Shading, Mechanical, and Daylighting Performance" shortTile="nonuniform-woven" author="Yao Lu, Hankun Lin, Siwei Liu, Yiqiang Xiao" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5652/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Optimized building skins can significantly reduce energy consumption for space heating, cooling, and electric lighting. Using solar shading systems for natural cooling and daylighting control is an extensively researched topic in the area of energy-efficient building design. Specifically, solar shading systems contribute significantly to controlling glare, regulating solar radiation, homogenizing illuminance levels, and protecting privacy. On the basis of spatial positions, solar shading devices can be divided into three categories, namely, external intermediate and intermediate shading systems. Many studies have demonstrated that external shading presents a better solar shading performance than internal and intermediate shading. Regarding the operable and geometrical property, current solar shading systems consist of the fixed solar shading screen, fixed overhang, grating, operable solar shading screen, Venetian blinds, shutters, and roller blinds. As one of the most commonly used external shading devices, a solar screen can efficiently scatter and redirect daylight. Numerous studies have been conducted on improving the shading performance of solar screens by optimizing their geometrical dimensions, perforation percentages, and textures. Moreover, much research has been conducted on using solar screens more effectively by adjusting their application methods on the basis of the facade orientation and shading periods. Conventional research on the performance evaluation of shading devices has primarily focused on standard solar transmission (e.g., solar heat gain coefficient) and visible daylight transmittance. At present, concerns regarding the overall daylight quality of the indoor environment in a room with different shading devices have been increasing, and the research methods have been expanded to a wider range of simulations, regarding daylight, visual comfort, and energy demand, by using climate-based computer-aided dynamic simulation tools. On the basis of the methods above, the performance of various kinds of materials for solar screens has been investigated, including metal mesh grids, perforated metal screens, and wooden screens. The distinctive light performance of a woven fabric was demonstrated by Thomas in 1967. He demonstrated that the daylight transmission process of the woven fabric includes transmission through the holes, reflection by the fibers, and diffraction. Likewise, mats woven of fine strips (e.g., rattan mats, bamboo mats) have a similar daylight transmission mechanism as fabric materials, which allows them to be developed into daylighting/shading devices. These mats can provide a preferable daylight transmission performance and combine aesthetics and functionality by delivering a striking visual appeal, safety, and energy savings. </p>

<p>However, as is shown in <figure>Figure 1</figure>a, traditional uniform woven mats show relatively weak shading performance because their thin warp and weft strips cannot significantly reduce direct solar radiation. In contrast, as shown in <figure>Figure 1</figure>b, conventional thick perforated panels effectively block the direct solar beam but limit the access of diffuse daylight. The weaknesses of the aforementioned panel types necessitate the search for an alternative material for solar screens. To address this problem, this paper proposed a nonuniform woven panel woven from strips of different thicknesses. The thick strips function as the main component to obstruct direct solar beams, whereas the side openings formed by curved thin strips allow almost exclusively diffuse daylight to penetrate. In this study, bamboo was used as a demonstration material for the screen. Due to the toughness and tensile strength of bamboo, fine strips can be easily curved and woven into mats with different patterns in the same way as fabrics. In terms of the raw material itself, the ecology potentials of bamboo as an environmentally friendly resource have been an increasingly considered option in the field of renewable building materials. Bamboo is widely planted and utilized as industrial or building material in Southern and Southeast Asia. This material has a number of eco-features, such as rapid growth, a short vegetative cycle, and low-cost cultivation. For example, Phyllostachys pubescen can grow to a height of 18 m in only 59 days after felling. Bamboo products have lower eco-costs than tropical hardwood alternatives. In addition, varied woven patterns endow mats with special aesthetic appearances for the envelope components. Thus, the distinctive characteristics of bamboo warrant an investigation of the nonuniform solar shading screen that simultaneously takes into account the daylighting performance and eco-features of bamboo. To the best of our knowledge, this panel has not been used as an external shading device, and no quantitative analysis has been conducted on its shading, daylighting, and mechanical performance. </p>
</text>
