<text id="autogum_interview_doc303" title="part9_Shimon Peres discusses the future of Israel" shortTile="partshimon-peres" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-01-06" dateModified="2013-08-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Shimon_Peres_discusses_the_future_of_Israel" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: And you feel it would be a mistake for Israel to act unilaterally, or not?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: Yes.  I don’t think Israel should say it; I don’t think Israel should talk about it.  The minute we shall talk about it we shall be left alone.  Israel is the only country that has never had a foreign army to defend it.  All the European countries had foreign armies, most of the Asian countries.  We don’t.  And…</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: You don’t feel America plays that role with Israel?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: America helps us a great deal.  We are grateful.  But we have never asked for American soldiers to defend Israel.  And one of the popularities of Israel in the United States is that American mothers know that their children don’t face danger here.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: Although they face it quite often in Iraq and Afghanistan.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: But here we defend it ourselves.  Even in the early times when the United States recognized us, they didn’t give us rifles to defend our lives.  It’s only later that they gave us arms and we are very grateful.  But with Iran, we shall do what we have to do in our own way.  We don’t want to bother anybody because it’s a world problem.  Until now, the problem was will the world stand on the side of Israel.  Today, the question is will the world stand on the side of the world?  Iran is a world danger.</p>
<head id="The_2006_Lebanon_War">The 2006 Lebanon War</head>
<figure><caption>'The Iron Dome':  The Anti-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kassam%20rocket">Kassam rocket</ref> system, to be built by Israeli defense experts <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RAFAEL">RAFAEL</ref>, is slated to be able to take its first battery in 2012.  The missile shield is designed to prevent the problems encountered in Haifa during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2006%20Lebanon%20War">war</ref>, when the city, including its oil refinery, came under heavy shelling from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hezbollah">Hezbollah</ref> in Lebanon, just on the other side of the mountains (<hi rend="italic">photo, above</hi>).  The Dome is not without its questions and controversies, including whether the $207 million (£104 million) system will work.Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: How did the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2006%20Lebanon%20War">Lebanese War</ref> help Israel’s security?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: Look, Israel is almost 60 years old next year.  In the 60 years we went through seven wars, two <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intifada">intifadas</ref>, all of them outgunned, outmanned, outnumbered.  We didn’t lose a single one.  So there were wars that were more successful, less successful, never a failure.  Now about Lebanon, it became a question of did we do rightly or wrongly.  But clearly it not wind up better for Hamas, not better for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hezbollah">Hezbollah</ref> winning.  They don’t know to answer, “Why did they go to the war?” Today, everybody recognizes that Hezbollah is a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2006–2007%20Lebanese%20political%20protests">danger to Lebanon</ref> more than to Israel.  Today when you speak to a Frenchman or to the United States, they are <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hezbollah%20military%20activities">worried more about Lebanon and Hezbollah</ref> than about Hezbollah and Israel.  So, we have learned our lessons too, and but I think by and large, some people say we could have saved the lives of 30 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zar'it-Shtula%20incident">soldiers</ref>.  Maybe.</p>
</text>
