<text id="autogum_interview_doc712" title="part2_Canada&amp;apos;s Don Valley East (Ward 33) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-don-valley" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-17" dateModified="2009-04-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Don_Valley_East_%28Ward_33%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What <hi rend="bold">one</hi> election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> 1) child poverty at 33% in ward 33, above TO's average of 30%</p>
<p>2) Transit and traffic chaos - Simply adding more buses on roads is an insufficient long-term solution.</p>
<p>To meet the rapid transportation reforms, public transit and public policing must be PRIVATIZED. It is the only means to rapidly build subway/RT capacity on a GTA large scale, and require a $10 billion dollar plan.</p>
<p>3) Affordable housing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I engage politics for a few reasons:</p>
<p>1) I lack of confidence in politicians all too willing to compromise for the sack of money.</p>
<p>2) I bring the legal authority to execute rapidly upon the demands I make upon three levels of government.</p>
<p>3) I bring the integrity, accountability, and resolve to see my demands through.</p>
<p>4) I stand up and defend those who cannot defend themselves - our youths</p>
<p>5) I fight for equality, justice, democracy at every level, and defend those who cannot defend themselves</p>
<p>6) I fight for our city, province, and nation, when no politician, lawyer, journalist, nor media network is willing to do so for political reasons. I do not believe in politics, but my life will be an example of the greatness of our city, province, and nation, when we our minds and resources to clear objectives.</p>
<p>My heart lies in the political and judicial realm, as I have been fighting 3 levels of government the past 5 years on the most fundamental of reforms. Only by threats of impeachment have I achieved rapid results in meeting the demands of our dynamic, multicultural society.</p>
<p>Not one politician, nor lawyer, nor journalist for that matter, would even attempt to do the things I have done the past 5 years. Though the successes are great, the personal cost mirrors this. Though I could have settled the expanding legal issues long ago, and compromised my position for money. Instead I choose the long hard grinding road of INTEGRITY, ACCOUNTABILITY, AND RESOLVE. The people of Toronto, Ontario, and Canada, will come to appreciate my efforts.</p>
<p>It is not the unions, nor councillors, nor mayor, nor realty firms that run this city. It is the free democratic societies right to remove officials that refuse to stand up for justice, who aid and abate fraud, conspiracies, and obstructions on a scale as unproven till now. I am no politician, nor officially a lawyer, but I run with equivalent knowledge and experiences in making the fair, equitable, and just decisions that city council lacks in judgement. I will continue to resolve the challenges that face our city, province, and nation in the twenty-second century - wether [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] or not I am elected.</p>
</text>
