<text id="autogum_academic_doc119" title="The Determinants of Income of Rural Women in Bangladesh" shortTile="determinants-income" author="Md.Shajahan Kabir, Mirjana Radović Marković, Dejan Radulović" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5842/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 9. Conclusions</head>
<p>Agricultural production is a source of employment opportunity for mostly unemployed and unpaid rural women, and can also increase the income of women, which may result in the better use of household resources and improved livelihood. When women can add income to their family, they can participate in decision-making of their family. That is a way they may be empowered. </p>

<p>Migration of the male members from rural to urban, the role of rural women is changing from unpaid family labor to farm managers, a phenomenon termed “Feminization of agriculture”. </p>

<p>Rural women are now actively involved in these activities by taking a small-scale of agricultural loan from GOs and NGOs, and these rural women now act as agricultural entrepreneurs. When a rural woman works outside, she can contribute to the family income, which has a great impact in improving their livelihood status. In fact, this change can help them to also take part in family decisions, which indicates the empowerment of rural women. Although, the contribution of rural women cannot be marked as much as should be needed. </p>

<p>The research results from different dimensions depict that the overall position of the selected women ranged between low to medium. Conclusions drawn based on findings of this study are as presented below:
<list>
<item>Various factors such as unavailability of enough credit, insufficient capital, inadequate training facilities, shortage of helping hand problem, and high price of inputs are faced by women in this area. These problems make women’s work harder in livestock production.</item>
<item>The study detected that lack of financial resources had a consequential, negative relationship with the problems confronted by female farmers.</item>
<item>Rural women’s income of selected households is strongly affected by their education, farm size, farming experience, and the training they have received.</item>
<item>This study accepted the fact that after economical participation of women in small-scale farming, most of the respondents enjoyed a relatively better position in the household and increased social prestige, which ultimately provides a peaceful life.</item>
<item>After all, economically active contribution of the respondents in the research area gives them the opportunity to improve their empowerment status in their household.</item>
<item>Necessary attentions are required from the respective authorities to solve these problems.</item>
</list>
</p>

<p>It is expected that our research will help the administrative and policy-makers of both GOs and NGOs, who are concerned with the different development programs, particularly in relation to women’s development. In addition, our findings agree with similar research on the same issues linked to Bangladesh. Namely, it can be noted that women′s decision to work in agriculture is directly related to the distance of the agricultural field from the home, the number of available technologies to use, and the number of available male adults within the family. </p>
</text>
