<text id="autogum_whow_doc345" title="Get a Second Opinion Before Major Surgery" shortTile="second-opinion-before" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2016-01-09" dateModified="2019-04-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get-a-Second-Opinion-Before-Major-Surgery" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get a Second Opinion Before Major Surgery</head><p>If your primary care physician (PCP) has referred you to a specialist, and that doctor has recommended a major surgical procedure, it would be wise to get a "second opinion" before proceeding. Doing so means you seek additional experience and perspective at an important moment in your life. It typically involves a reinforced commitment to the original diagnosis and treatment plan suggested by your doctor. It can give you confidence in the proposed surgery. It can fine-tune the suggested course of action. It could even postpone or radically change the plan. Patients have a right to a second (and third) opinion and are well advised to seek them. You want all the help you can get at a critical time. Major surgery is disruptive and expensive. You want to be sure it's necessary before you agree to it. There are sometimes acceptable alternatives to major surgery. Be an educated consumer when it comes to your health and well being, just as you would in any other area of life. Different physicians take different approaches to health care, some more aggressive than others. A second opinion may suggest a better option for you than the first one suggested. Here's how to go about this.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Ask around. Surgery is normally considered the last line of treatment. Doctors usually try to avoid it when possible, because it's invasive, complicated and even dangerous. Nonetheless, it may be urgently required, and it may be considered the patient's best option. Seek confirmation from another doctor (or doctors) that the proposed surgery is indeed your best option. Find such doctors by searching physician-locator sites online or by asking for references from area clinics, hospitals and HMOs.</item>
<item>Do not fear a second opinion. Don't worry about offending your PCP. A good doctor will encourage you to seek a second opinion. S/he may well seek a second opinion, too. In this age of high medical costs, insurance companies often encourage doctors to avoid expensive surgeries, so your doctor will probably want a confirming opinion before ordering surgery.
<list type="unordered"><item>Some patients may worry that a second opinion may confuse them and prevent from taking the right decision. In fact, quite the opposite is true. The better informed you are, the better decision you can make.</item></list></item>
<item>Do your own research. Inform yourself about your situation by conducting research online or in medical texts. If you do this before conferring with a specialist, it will help you understand what the doctor tells you as you work toward a decision.
<list type="unordered"><item>According to the American Journal of Medicine, a recent assessment of more than 6,000 patients showed that second opinions do have a positive impact on diagnoses, treatment plans and surgical outcomes. Specifically, within the assessed patients second opinions resulted in changed diagnoses 15% of the time, changed treatment plans 37% of the time, and both changed diagnoses and changed treatment 10% of the time.</item></list></item>
<item>Get the correct diagnosis. A second opinion will confirm your original diagnosis and treatment plan, or it will modify them. In either case it may save you time, money, and unnecessary treatment. Before going for a second opinion, research the physician. Get the second opinion from a specialist known to be skilled and experienced in treating patients with your condition. Not all physicians are absolutely up-to-date on new studies, treatments, procedures and diagnoses. So a second opinion from a specialist is especially valuable.</item>
<item>Get a second opinion before elective surgery.  When you have time to consider other treatment options, finding other opinions is especially appropriate. In the case of emergency surgery, you may not have that luxury. Remember that seeking a second opinion does not mean you're choosing alternate treatment; it just means you're being careful. A second opinion will help you in the following situations:
<list type="unordered"><item>You want to make sure that surgery is the only appropriate option left for you.</item>
<item>You are not satisfied with the answers given by the first doctor.</item>
<item>You are not able to make a decision.</item>
<item>You want to explore other treatment options.</item>
<item>You want help from a specialist in deciding.</item>
<item>You want more information about your condition.</item>
<item>You want to confirm that the first diagnosis and treatment plan is right.</item>
<item>You want to know more about possible risks and complications.</item></list></item>
<item>Consider seeking a third opinion. If the second opinion confirms the first, you will probably be satisfied that you're on the right course. If you're still not satisfied, however, or if the second opinion contradicts the first, you should look for a third opinion. Also take into consideration your own feelings and opinions, your lifestyle, and the fact that you're the one who has to live with the final decision. Just don't let simple fear overrule the experience the doctors bring to bear on your situation. They're staking their reputations on the decisions they make.</item></list>
</text>
