<text id="autogum_interview_doc883" title="part8_Author Amy Scobee recounts abuse as Scientology executive" shortTile="partauthor-amy-scobee" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-10-11" dateModified="2015-12-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Author_Amy_Scobee_recounts_abuse_as_Scientology_executive" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">AS</hi>: The control and handling of personnel within the Sea Org was very unpredictable. There were always huge demands and needs for people on various projects or positions that had to be filled "at once". So one could expect rapid changes. It was also considered that after one messes up, they can be corrected using the "ethics technology" of Scientology and confessionals so they can carry on after their level of ethics are once again acceptable.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> What was the highest-ranking position you held within Scientology? Who did you report to in this position? What responsibilities did you have, and how many other people and sub-entities did you oversee?</hi></p>
<hi rend="bold">I was in the Watchdog Committee (WDC) which is the highest ecclesiastical body in Scientology ... I was in WDC for about a decade and held about six different sectors over the years</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Amy Scobee</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS</hi>: I was in the Watchdog Committee (WDC) which is the highest ecclesiastical body in Scientology, with a WDC member appointed over each of the numerous "sectors" or areas of Scientology to see to their proper management. My boss as a WDC member is the WDC Chairman. This is the highest management position in the organization. I was in WDC for about a decade and held about six different sectors over the years, including the Association for Better Living and Education (ABLE) sector, which is responsible for the secular aspects of the organization – drug rehabilitation, criminal reform, Applied Scholastics study technology and The Way To Happiness Foundation – and the Celebrity Center sector. Anything that goes on inside your sector or sphere of responsibility as a WDC member, is your responsibility and you're held accountable. This could be very stressful, particularly when the current head of Scientology – David Miscavige – is so abusive. For example, Miscavige learned that the Tampa Scientology organization was not paying their rent in 2003. As I had previously been the WDC member for all Scientology churches (approx 175 of them around the world) and should have noticed and handled it then, Miscavige demanded that I personally pay the rent of $5,000 (which I did not have). This order was enforced by his personal staff – I had to borrow the money from several other staff members and turn it into the Finance Office, who then wrote a check to the Tampa organization to pay their back rent as a "gift" to them from management.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> In chapter 4 of <hi rend="italic">Scientology - Abuse at the Top</hi>, you cite the book <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Combating%20Cult%20Mind%20Control">Combating Cult Mind Control</ref></hi> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/cult">cult</ref> researcher <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steven%20Hassan">Steven Hassan</ref>, who explains that, "Members are made to feel part of an elite corps of mankind." At what point in time did you read this book? Are there other books which helped you understand and put your experiences within Scientology into a greater context?</hi></p>
</text>
