<text id="autogum_bio_doc275" title="Abraham Dob Bär Lebensohn" shortTile="abraham-dob-bar-lebensohn" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-12-30" dateModified="2018-10-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abraham_Dob_B%C3%A4r_Lebensohn" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Abraham Dob Bär Lebensohn</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Abraham Dob Bär Lebensohn</hi> (Traditional Jewish Lithuanian pronunciation: <hi rend="bold">Avrohom Dov Beyr Leybenzon</hi>) (born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vilnius">Vilnius</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russian_Empire">Russian Empire</ref> c. 1789/1794; died there November 19, 1878) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lithuanian_Jews">Lithuanian Jewish</ref> Hebraist, poet, and grammarian.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Like all Jewish boys of that time in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russian_Empire">Russian</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lithuania">Lithuania</ref> he was educated as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talmud">Talmudist</ref>, but became interested in Hebrew grammar and punctuation when, at the age of eleven, he was instructed in reading in public the weekly portions of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Torah">Law</ref>. He was married, according to the custom of those times, as soon as he had celebrated his <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bar_mitzvah">bar mitzvah</ref></hi> / <hi rend="italic">Bar Mistvo</hi> ; and he spent the following eight years with his wife's parents in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michališki">Michailishki</ref>, in the government of Vilna. This gave him the surname "Michailishker," by which he was popularly known; and it also accounts for the last letter in his pen-name "Adam" (formed from the initials of Abraham Dob Michailishker), while the family name "Lebensohn," which he adopted, is a literal translation of "ben Ḥayyim." / "Beyn Cayim" . He afterward lived about four years in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ashmyany">Oshmiany</ref>, in the government of Vilna, where he attempted to establish himself as a merchant. He was now an accomplished <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rabbinic">rabbinic</ref> scholar; but he devoted most of his leisure time to the study of Hebrew poetical and grammatical works. On returning to his native city, where he remained for the rest of his life, he engaged in teaching, a profession which he followed until his old age, except for about fifteen years in which he was engaged in the business of a broker.</p>
<head>As poet</head>
<p>His first poetical work to be published was the <hi rend="italic">Shir Ḥabibim</hi> / <hi rend="italic">Shir Chovivim</hi> (Vilnius, 1822), in honor of the marriage of Count <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tyszkiewicz">Tyszkiewicz</ref>, one of the most powerful noblemen of Lithuania. It was followed by <hi rend="italic">Ebel Kabed</hi> / <hi rend="italic">Eyvel Koveyd</hi> (ib. 1825), an elegy on the death of R. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saul_Katzenellenbogen">Saul Katzenellenbogen</ref>; this established the author's reputation as a Hebrew poet. The publication of the first volume of his poetry, entitled <hi rend="italic">Shire Sefat Ḳodesh</hi>  / <hi rend="italic">Shirey Sfas Kodesh</hi> (Leipzig, 1842; 2d ed. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vilnius">Vilnius</ref>, 1863), marks the beginning of a new epoch in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neo-Hebrew">Neo-Hebrew</ref> literature in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lithuania">Lithuania</ref>. It is the first poetical work of the rejuvenated literature that can be favorably compared with the works of that nature which were produced in western European countries. It was received with unbounded enthusiasm. Thousands of young men in sympathy with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haskalah">Haskalah</ref> movement, of which Lebensohn became the leading exponent in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lithuania">Lithuania</ref>, learned to recite the songs of <hi rend="italic">Shire Sefat Ḳodesh</hi> / <hi rend="italic">Shirey Sfas Kodesh</hi> by heart; and the fame of the author spread to all centers of Hebrew learning.</p>
<p>When Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moses_Montefiore">Moses Montefiore</ref> visited <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vilnius">Vilnius</ref> in 1846, Lebensohn prepared for his perusal an article on the condition of the Jews in Russia and the means by which it was to be improved. This interesting document, embodying the views held by the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maskilim">Maskilim</ref></hi> of that period, summarized the evils from which the Jews suffered and boldly stated that they were themselves to blame for their troubles. Lack of education and of skill in handicrafts, too early marriages, the ignorance of the rabbis and teachers, and extravagance were described as the four <hi rend="italic">abot neziḳin</hi>  / <hi rend="italic">Ayveys Nezikin</hi> or chief faults; and relief was proposed, as was customary in those times, through governmental intervention (see I. M. Dick, <hi rend="italic">Ha-Oraḥ,</hi> and Lebensohn, <hi rend="italic">Yeter Shire Adam</hi>  / <hi rend="italic">Yeser Shirey Oydom</hi> pp.67 et seq.).</p>
<head>As commentator</head>
<p>In 1848, Lebensohn was made one of the principal teachers in the newly established rabbinical school of Vilna, a position which he creditably filled for nearly twenty years, until he was forced by age and impaired eyesight to relinquish it. He was succeeded by his son-in-law <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joshua_Steinberg">Joshua Steinberg</ref>. Also in 1848, he began, conjointly with the bibliographer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benjacob">Benjacob</ref> / <hi rend="italic">Yitschok Beyn-Yaynkov</hi>, the publication of a new edition of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bible">Bible</ref>, with a German translation, himself adding valuable glosses to the <hi rend="italic">bi'ur</hi> / <hi rend="italic">Biyuyr</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Miḳra'e Ḳodesh,</hi> / <hi rend="italic">Mikroyey Kodesh</hi>,  Vilna, 1848–53). Some of his commentaries on the Bible were later printed separately as a supplement to that edition (<hi rend="italic">Bi'urim Ḥadashim,</hi> / <hi rend="italic">Biyuyrim Chadoshim</hi>, ib. 1858). A second volume of <hi rend="italic">Shire Sefat Ḳodesh</hi> / <hi rend="italic">Shirey Sfas Kodesh</hi> appeared in Vilna in 1856 (2d ed., ib. 1869); and in 1869 was published <hi rend="italic">Yeter Shire Adam</hi> / <hi rend="italic">Yeser Shirey Oydom</hi> the third volume of the same work, containing also poems written by his son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Micah_Joseph_Lebensohn">Micah Joseph Lebensohn</ref> / <hi rend="italic">Micho Yeyseyf Leybenzon</hi> . The most important of his later works are the allegorical drama <hi rend="italic">Emet we-Emunah</hi> / <hi rend="italic">Eymes VeYeymuno</hi> (ib. 1867; 2d ed., ib. 1870), which has for its theme the harmonization of science and religion; and <hi rend="italic">Yitron le-Adam</hi>  / <hi rend="italic">Yisreyn LeYoydom</hi> (ib. 1874), a commentary on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ben-Ze'eb">Ben-Ze'eb</ref>'s (Traditional Jewish Lithuanian pronunciation:<hi rend="italic">Beyn-Zyeyv</hi>) well-known Hebrew grammar, <hi rend="italic">Talmud Leshon 'Ibri</hi> / <hi rend="italic">Talmud Lesheyn Iyvri</hi> with which it has been often reprinted. A new edition of the three volumes of <hi rend="italic">Shire Sefat Ḳodesh</hi> / <hi rend="italic">Shirey Sfas Kodesh</hi> appeared in Vilna in 1895.</p>
<p>Lebensohn was the author of several other, unimportant, works and of numerous articles in the periodicals. He exercised almost as much influence by his powerful personality as by his literary efforts, and was recognized in his later years as the pioneer of <hi rend="italic">haskalah</hi> in northwestern Russia. The <hi rend="italic">Maskilim</hi> of Vilna considered themselves as his pupils, while the fanatics saw in him the embodiment of all the objectionable features of the progressivist movement.</p>
<p>He had two sons, Micah Joseph Lebensohn, cited above, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aryeh_Löb_Lebensohn">Aryeh Löb Lebensohn</ref> (Traditional Lithuanian Jewish pronunciation: <hi rend="italic">Ayryey Leyb Leybenzon</hi>), who was a prominent businessman in Vilna.</p>
</text>
