<text id="autogum_whow_doc159" title="Prepare a Strategic Plan for a School" shortTile="prepare-strategic" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-07-14" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Prepare-a-Strategic-Plan-for-a-School" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Prepare a Strategic Plan for a School</head><p>Developing a strategic plan for a school begins with the alignment of the district strategic plan. For example, one of the goals in the district strategic plan may be to improve student attendance. Taking that goal for the school may be to improve school attendance by 2 percent over 2 years. Usually, strategic plans are for a five year period, so the goals can reflect that as well. Each goal that is selected for the school's strategic plan must align with the district's strategic plan. The school may have fewer goals (usually no more than three can be reached in one year), and each goal should have activities to support the goal as well as a budget to support the activities. Each goal must be developed in a "shared experience" with all stakeholders (teachers, parents, students if high school, and staff).  Listed in a step by step method is the process one would use to develop one of the goals in the strategic plan.  After each goal activity is completed, then the information is compiled into a comprehensive strategic plan for the school year which includes a spending plan that is aligned to the school's total budget.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Determine current percent of attendance.  Most elementary schools are around 95% attendance with middle schools around 92%, and high schools around 90%.  Each school is provided a report of attendance reporting on a monthly basis by the District Office. <figure rend="Prepare a Strategic Plan for a School Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Discuss with stakeholders the current attendance rate and the need for improvement.  Discuss a 1% increase per year for the next two years, which is aligned to the District goal.  Provide stakeholders with historic attendance reporting and indicate which months are "problematic". Provide stakeholders with number of students needed to make a 1% increase. <figure rend="Prepare a Strategic Plan for a School Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Develop with stakeholders activities to meet the attendance goal of improvement by 1%.  Examples of possible activities include monthly award assemblies for perfect attendance (usually elementary school  students), privilege certificates (such as no homework for a day) for middle and high school students, attendance clerk to monitor student attendance, and make friendly home phone calls daily for absent students, Vice Principal or other administrator may make home visits for students who have missed 3 days or more before December to determine if any interventions may be appropriate, and end-of-year trips may be tied to attendance. These are just a few activities that schools use. Be sure to discuss them thoroughly with all stakeholders. <figure rend="Prepare a Strategic Plan for a School Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Determine the cost of each activity and add this into the school's budget. Additional personnel costs may need to be approved by the district budgeting department. <figure rend="Prepare a Strategic Plan for a School Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Share the final comprehensive goal with all stakeholders in a variety of venues. For parents and community, include the goal on the school's website and show the results as well as activities.  <figure rend="Prepare a Strategic Plan for a School Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If there is a monthly newsletter, share the goal and activities in the newsletter.  </item>
<item>Send positive notes to students who have improved upon their attendance, and make personal telephone calls to families, thanking them for their child's improved attendance.</item>
<item>During back-to-school night activities, be sure to have teaching staff discuss the importance of good attendance to student learning, and provide handouts to parents discussing the goal, the activities to reach the goal, the budget, and scientific research supporting good school attendance.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always include all stakeholders in the process of developing the strategic plan.</item>
<item>Keep the planning process to a manageable level. Stakeholders will be unable to attend many of the meetings.</item>
<item>Administrators must do their homework. Be sure to get all the data together before beginning the process.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Remember that there will always be folks against the process. Keep a positive attitude.  Go back to the research on attendance and its importance in learning.</item>
<item>Educate your teachers in the planning process. They will be your most positive supporters if they are engaged from the very beginning.</item></list>
</text>
