<text id="autogum_interview_doc379" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Mark Bunker, producer of anti-Scientology website &amp;apos;XenuTV&amp;apos;" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-05" dateModified="2016-03-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Mark_Bunker%2C_producer_of_anti-Scientology_website_%27XenuTV%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Mark Bunker, producer of anti-Scientology website 'XenuTV'</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, February 18, 2008</hi></p>
<p>Television producer and owner of the anti-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scientology">Scientology</ref> website www.xenutv.com (XenuTV), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark%20Bunker">Mark Bunker</ref>, also known as <hi rend="italic">Wise Beard Man</hi>, chatted online with <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> for nearly three hours. More than 120 people followed the interview live (many from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Project%20Chanology">Project Chanology</ref>), which makes this exclusive <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> interview our most attended <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet%20Relay%20Chat">IRC</ref> interview to date.</p>
<p>Bunker started XenuTV in 1999 and began to make videos that he provided for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lisa%20McPherson%20Trust">Lisa McPherson Trust</ref>. Bunker has been a critic of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church%20of%20Scientology">Church of Scientology</ref> since 1997.</p>
<p>In 2006, he won a  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emmy%20Award#Regional_Emmys">Regional Emmy Award</ref> after he and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/KUSI-TV">KUSI-TV</ref> news reporter Lena Lewis produced a documentary news video on the issues with the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> - <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mexico">Mexico</ref> border with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San%20Diego,%20California">San Diego</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/California">California</ref>.</p>
<head id="The_Interview">The Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why don't you start by telling us about yourself and what you do.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mark Bunker</hi>: I work in TV news in San Diego and have been speaking out about Scientology's fraud and abuse since 1998.  I worked "anonymously" for a year before showing my face and starting my website XENU TV.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Tell us about your history with criticism of Scientology?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: In 1998 I was living in a house in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hollywood%20Hills">Hollywood Hills</ref>.  The woman who lived there prior to me was a Scientologist.  Probably at the Celebrity Center because I would get her issues of Celebrity magazine and other Scientology periodicals.  Reading them left me bewildered.  They have their own language in many ways.  I was intrigued and visited the Celebrity Center at one point to check the place out with a friend -- as a skeptic, mind you.  I took the personality test, played with an e-meter and got my own personal screening of Orientation before sitting down with the head of the CC. I had seen the 60 Minutes reports in the eighties but didn't have a lot of knowledge at my fingertips. I wish I knew then what I know now so I could have asked pointed questions.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Such as?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: I did ask things like, "Do I have to buy all these books?  Don't you have a library?" Of course, they want you to buy everything. After 45 minutes, I broke it to him that I wasn't interested. I went home, did a quick search on the net and found out about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Xenu">Xenu</ref>. Then I discovered <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operation%20Snow%20White">Operation Snow White</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operation%20Freakout">Operation Freakout</ref> and other crimes committed by Scientology. This was more than some silly little group. I was amazed that this whole different world existed inside the U.S. and no one really paid attention to it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Has the Church ever been convicted of any crimes?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">M.B.</hi>: It has been convicted in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada">Canada</ref> for some of the same espionage tactics they used here in Operation Snow White. There have been more but I don't have them at the tip of my fingers. That's the nice thing about the net. You can now quickly research anytime, anywhere.</p>
</text>
