<text id="autogum_voyage_doc373" title="West Bali National Park" shortTile="west-bali-national" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=38849" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>West Bali National Park</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">West Bali National Park</hi> is the only national park on the island of <ref target="Bali">Bali</ref> in <ref target="Indonesia">Indonesia</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>West Bali National Park (<hi rend="italic">Taman Nasional Bali Barat</hi> in Bahasa Indonesia) is the most north-westerly point of Bali. It includes the whole of the Prapat Agung Peninsula, and large swathes of land around the towns of Gilimanuk, <hi rend="bold">Cekik</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Banyuwedang</hi>. The official area inside the park boundaries is 190 km², with a further 580 km² of protected reserve in the highlands to the east. In total this accounts for some ten percent of Bali's total land area.</p>

<head>History</head>
<p>The park was first recognised as an area of importance in 1917 when the council of Bali rulers designated it as a <hi rend="italic">nature park</hi>. It was established as an Indonesian National Park in 1941.</p>

<head>Landscape</head>
<p>The habitat is very varied with rainforest, dry savanna, acacia scrub and lowland forests, as well as more montane forests in the higher centre. There are also some pockets of dense mangrove forest.</p>

<p>In the north of the park there is an obvious north jutting peninsula called Prapat Agung. Around this peninsula there are long stretches of protected beach and offshore coral reef as well, as a small offshore island called Menjangan. The latter is a very popular diving destination.</p>

<p>There are several long extinct volcanoes in the protected reserve area to the east, with Mount Patas (1,412 metres) and Mount Merbuk (1,388 metres) being the highest points. These peaks are dominant visual landscape features from within every area of the park.</p>

<head>Flora and fauna</head>
<p>160 species of bird have been recorded in the park, including the near extinct Bali Starling, Bali's only endemic vertebrate species, and a key reason why this national park was created in the first place. By 2001, as few as six individuals were thought to survive in the wild, all of them in this park. Since then captive breeding and re-introduction efforts have continued apace, but poaching pressures are a large problem. With that in mind, a second re-introduction programme was started in remote regions of <ref target="Nusa%20Penida">Nusa Penida</ref> in 2004. Keen birdwatchers can find <ref target="http://www.birdlist.org/sas/indonesia/bali.htm">a checklist</ref> of likely species and their status here.</p>

<p>Mammals found inside the park include Banteng, a species of wild cattle from which the familiar Bali cows are descended. Java Rusa and Indian Muntjac deer are quite widespread, and Menjangan Island is in fact named after these (Menjangan means deer in Bahasa Indonesia). Wild Boar and Leopard Cats are both quite common but seldom encountered.</p>

<p>A Bali Tiger (a full sub-species of Tiger) was shot here in 1937, and despite rumours to the contrary, that is the last ever confirmed sighting of an animal considered extinct since that moment.</p>

<head>Climate</head>
<p>Not noticeably different from the rest of <ref target="Bali">Bali</ref> or eastern <ref target="Java">Java</ref>, but it may feel a little hotter and drier in the dry season here than in southern parts of Bali.</p>

<p>Bali is always warm, humid and tropical, remaining around 30-35°C (85-95°F) all year round. The April–October dry season and November–March rainy seasons are only relative, with plenty of rainfall around the year, but the Balinese winter is cloudier, more humid and with a higher chance of thunderstorms.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bali Barat National Park Office HQ</hi>, Jl Raya Cekik-Gilimanuk, Jembrana, Bali 82253, ☏ +62 365 61060 , fax: +62 365 61479 , ✉ tnbb@telkom.net . 7:30AM-5PM.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bali Barat National Park Vistor's Centre</hi>, Labuhan Lalang, ✉ tnbb@telkom.net . 7:30AM-5PM.</item>
</list>


<head>Get in</head>
<p>Most visitors to the park arrive along the north coast road from <ref target="Lovina">Lovina</ref> (about 90 minutes) or <ref target="Pemuteran">Pemuteran</ref> (about 15 minutes). Others come from the south via <ref target="Gilimanuk">Gilimanuk</ref> (about 15 minutes)</p>

<p>All visitors should check in at one of the two park offices (<hi rend="italic">PHPA</hi>) for information, and to purchase permits and arrange guides. The headquarters is at the village of Cekik just south of the Gilimanuk in the west. The other is at Labuan Lalang on the north coast from where boats to Menjangan Island depart. The main ranger station is on the road between the two offices at Sumber Klampok.</p>

<p>The park staff are welcoming, helpful and will arrange guided tours for you.</p>

<head>Fees and permits</head>
<p>Permits and obligatory guides are available at the park headquarters at Cekik and the office at Labuhan Lalang. The official permit charge is Rp 25,000 per person. The cost of a guide is negotiable. Use your common sense and do not be tight. A sensible range would be about Rp 50,000 to 100,000 for a half to full day.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>Only a small portion of the park is open to visitors, and this rule must be respected. There are two key ways to explore the park: either hiking the trails or concentrating on marine aspects.</p>

<p>Walking the trails must be done with an official guide from one of the national park offices (most normally the one at Cekik). Boat trips to Menjangan and around Gilimanuk Bay can be organised in advance (ask at your hotel), or by charter on the day you arrive.</p>

<head>See and do</head>
<p>The official park trails should be explored with a guide recommended by the national park office. This is actually a rule but it is sometimes 'quietly' ignored. Please do not do this nor encourage the practice, despite the very irresponsible advice given in some printed travel guides to do so.</p>

<p>The <hi rend="bold">Tegal Blunder Trail</hi> is most popular with birdwatchers, and it is an easy two-hour walk. The ranger checkpoint is at the village of Slumber Klampok about 20 minutes west of Cekik. From the same checkpoint you can take the more strenuous <hi rend="bold">Gunung Klatakan Trail</hi> to the south east. This is tougher walking for about five hours, but it takes you through some memorable rainforest. There are other trails and opportunities for interesting hikes, but these are the two most popular and the easiest. Ask guides about other opportunities at the time, particularly those involving hiking deeper into the Prapat Agung Peninsula.</p>

<p>The uninhabited <hi rend="bold">Menjangan Island</hi> is a must-do for any visitor to Bali interested in marine life, snorkelling or diving. Boats leave from the beach at Labuan Lalang at the northern edge of Teluk Terima bay, and can chartered on the day. Groups of tourists often club together at Labuan Lalang in the mornings for that very purpose. Any boat charter must be accompanied by a guide, and you must purchase a permit (Rp 25,000 per person) from the national park office in the main Labuhan Lalang car park. Many of Bali's dive operators based in the southern tourist regions offer dive excursions specifically to Menjangan. The snorkelling here is probably the best on Bali with good clear water and calm seas.</p>

<p>There is a notable temple on Menjangan called <hi rend="bold">Puri Gili Kencana</hi> which is certainly worth a visit. You can walk around the whole of Menjangan in about 1 hour and 15 minutes. If you take it slower though there is plenty of natural coastal beauty to absorb.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Gilimanuk Bay</hi> snakes into the south western tip of the Prapat Agung peninsula, and the park office can arrange a guided boat trip for you in a traditional outrigger. Expect to pay about Rp 300,000 per hour including guide fees. The bay is quiet and supports a rich diverstity of marine life. There are some notable areas of mangrove forest fringing the bay, and these act as a natural nursery for the diverse fish life in the area.</p>
</text>
