<text id="autogum_interview_doc907" title="part6_Interview with Reggie Bibbs on his life with neurofibromatosis" shortTile="partinterview-reggie" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-28" dateModified="2010-04-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Reggie_Bibbs_on_his_life_with_neurofibromatosis" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: Tell me about your T-shirt, what's on the front?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: The front is my image, and the back is 'Just Ask', with my website.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: Could you stand up and show me?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: Sure. On the front is my image, and on the back is the word 'Just Ask' with my website [<hi rend="italic">zooming in, reggiebibbs.com</hi>]. I have a blog where we meet and talk with others that have NF, or just others that just want to know about it, they may have family members, just let them know what were doing with the Just Ask campaign, let them know what I'm doing at the events, and we share stories, and photos, and everything like that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: How important is that blog to people with NF?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: That blog is very important to a lot of people, because it's a way of connecting with others that have NF. It's a way of connecting with moms and dads that need support from other parents and from others that just can say words of encouragement.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: Do you think there's other people like you who don't want to go out in the public, and this is their link to people?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: I really do, I really believe. You know, I chat with a lot of others that have NF and that don't go anywhere and this is the way we communicate. We try to encourage others to do just that, to go out with a friend and let people see you and give them a chance to know who you are. And let them see you having fun. I guarantee you, if they see you smiling and enjoying yourself, that will encourage them.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: Do you think by you going out and taking pictures and putting them on your blog, that you've made other people wanna do that too?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: I really believe that and that's what my goal is, to let others that have NF see me doing this. I want to encourage them to do the same thing, they can do the same thing. Give people a chance, smile at them, let them know that you're happy and you're not bitter. I would encourage you to find a friend and go places, just go to as many places as you can think of, and let people see that you're having fun.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: Is there anything else you're doing on your website that we should know about?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: Yes, right know I'm selling T-shirts to help raise awareness and research for neurofibromatosis and to search for a cure.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: How has it been going?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: It's been going great, and I hope it continues to go great.</p>
</text>
