<text id="autogum_bio_doc316" title="Jakob Greber" shortTile="jakob-greber" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-06-19" dateModified="2019-05-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jakob_Greber" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Jakob Greber</head><p><hi rend="bold">Johann Jakob Greber</hi> (? – buried 5 July 1731) was a German <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baroque_music">Baroque</ref> composer and musician. His first name sometimes appeared in its Italianized version, <hi rend="bold">Giacomo</hi>, especially during the years he spent in London (1702 – 1705). Greber composed solo <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cantata">cantatas</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sonata">sonatas</ref>, and stage works, including the opera <hi lang="it" rend="italic">Gli amori di Ergasto</hi> which opened London's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Her_Majesty's_Theatre">Queen's Theatre</ref> in 1705. He died in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mannheim">Mannheim</ref>, where for many years he was <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kapellmeister">Kapellmeister</ref></hi> of the court orchestra of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_III_Philip,_Elector_Palatine">Charles III Philip, Elector Palatine</ref>.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Margherita_de_L'Epine">Margherita de L'Epine</ref>, Greber's mistress during his London years</caption></figure>
<p>Greber's date and place of birth are unknown, although the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neue_Deutsche_Biographie">Neue Deutsche Biographie</ref></hi> proposes an approximate date of 1673.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-NDB-1">[1]</ref> He is presumed to have studied in Italy and arrived in London from there in 1702, accompanied by his mistress, the opera singer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Margherita_de_L'Epine">Margherita de L'Epine</ref>. He was to remain in London for the next three years composing incidental music for plays and arias for L'Epine. In 1703, Greber composed the incidental music for the premiere of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_Rowe_(writer)">Nicholas Rowe</ref>'s play <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Fair_Penitent">The Fair Penitent</ref></hi>, including four arias sung by L'Epine during the interlude. It was during this time that Rowe dubbed L'Epine "Greber's Peg", a name by which she was known for several years. Although L'Epine left Greber in 1703 to live with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniel_Finch,_2nd_Earl_of_Nottingham">Daniel Finch, 2nd Earl of Nottingham</ref>, she returned to him in 1704, and they took up residence on Suffolk Street in London. He continued composing arias for her and accompanying her in concerts and theatrical interludes at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lincoln's_Inn_Fields">Lincoln's Inn Fields</ref> and other venues.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-AZ-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-CBM-3">[3]</ref> The London newspaper <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Post_Man">The Post Man</ref></hi> noted their appearance together at the spa town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tunbridge_Wells">Tunbridge Wells</ref> in August 1703:</p>
<p>They write from Tunbridge Wells that there is arrived there that famous Italian Lady, Signiora Francesca Margaretta de L'Epine that gives every week entertainments of musick, all compos'd by that great Master Signior Jacomo Greber, perform'd to the content and great satisfaction of all the nobility and gentry.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Her_Majesty's_Theatre">Queen's Theatre</ref> London, where Greber's <hi rend="italic">Gli amori di Ergasto</hi> premiered in 1705</caption></figure>
<p>On 9 April 1705, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Her_Majesty's_Theatre">Queen's Theatre</ref> in London was officially opened with Greber's opera <hi rend="italic">Gli amori di Ergasto</hi> (<hi rend="italic">The Loves of Ergasto</hi>). It was the first opera sung entirely in Italian by Italian singers to be performed in London.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> The printed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Libretto">libretto</ref> also contained an English translation by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Anthony_Motteux">Peter Anthony Motteux</ref>, and on the opening night the performance included a prologue by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samuel_Garth">Samuel Garth</ref> and an epilogue by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Congreve">William Congreve</ref>, both read by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anne_Bracegirdle">Anne Bracegirdle</ref>.  The opera itself, a <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pastoral">pastorale</ref></hi> largely consisting of arias and duets between shepherds and nymphs, proved a dismal failure and was only performed a few times.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Lowerre-6">[6]</ref> Shortly after the premiere of <hi rend="italic">Gli amori di Ergasto</hi>, Greber left London (without Margherita de L'Epine).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-AZ-2">[2]</ref></p>
<figure><caption>Greber's patron <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_III_Philip,_Elector_Palatine">Charles Philip</ref></caption></figure>
<p>A baptismal certificate in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Düsseldorf">Düsseldorf</ref>, dated 23 June 1705 describes Greber as a <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kapellmeister">Kapellmeister</ref></hi> (music director) in the service of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_III_Philip,_Elector_Palatine">Charles Philip</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-NDB-1">[1]</ref> who at the time was the governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_Tyrol">Tyrol</ref> with a court in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Innsbruck">Innsbruck</ref>. In 1708 Greber married Katharina Elisabeth <hi rend="italic">née</hi> von Douven who was probably a relative of Johann Franz von Douven, one of Charles Philip's treasury officials. The couple had at least four children.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-NDB-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> Greber remained in the service of Charles Philip for the rest of his career, working closely on operas and other court entertainments with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Augustin_Reinhard_Stricker">Augustin Stricker</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Hugo_von_Wilderer">Johann Hugo von Wilderer</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gottfried_Finger">Gottfried Finger</ref> (whom he had known from his London days).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-CBM-3">[3]</ref> When Charles Philip succeeded his brother, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Wilhelm,_Elector_Palatine">Johann Wilhelm</ref>, as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electoral_Palatinate">Elector Palatine</ref> in 1716, he combined his brother's court in Düsseldorf with his own court in Innsbruck. The new court was moved first to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neuburg_an_der_Donau">Neuburg</ref>, then to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heidelberg">Heidelberg</ref>, and finally to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mannheim">Mannheim</ref>. The Düsseldorf court orchestra was dissolved in the process, but in 1718, many of its musicians were reinstated in the Innsbruck court orchestra headed by Greber. In 1723, after Charles Philip moved his court to Mannheim, Johann von Wilderer was appointed to serve jointly with Greber as <hi rend="italic">Kapellmeister</hi>. Wilderer died in 1724. Greber lived on for another seven years, dying in Mannheim in July 1731. The orchestra he led there later became famous as the orchestra of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mannheim_school">Mannheim school</ref>.</p>
<head>Works</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Opera and oratorio</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi lang="it" rend="italic">Gli amori di Ergasto</hi> (<hi rend="italic">The Loves of Ergasto</hi>) – pastoral opera in 2 acts; first performed 9 April 1705, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Her_Majesty's_Theatre">Queen's Theatre</ref>, London; revised version performed 1711, Vienna; only the score of the Vienna version survives</item>
<item><hi lang="it" rend="italic">L'allegrezza dell'Eno</hi> (<hi rend="italic">The Joy of Eno</hi>) – <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Festa_teatrale">festa teatrale</ref>; libretto by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giovanni_Domenico_Pallavicini">Giovanni Domenico Pallavicini</ref>, overture by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gottfried_Finger">Gottfried Finger</ref>; first performed May 1708, Innsbruck to celebrate the visit of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elisabeth_Christine_of_Brunswick-Wolfenbüttel">Elisabeth Christine of Brunswick-Wolfenbüttel</ref>; score lost</item>
<item><hi lang="it" rend="italic">Enea in Cartagine</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Aeneas in Carthage</hi>)  – opera; first performed 1711, Komödienhaus, Innsbruck; score lost</item>
<item><hi lang="it" rend="italic">La morte di Cristo</hi> (<hi rend="italic">The Death of Christ</hi>) – <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oratorio">oratorio</ref>; first performed 1713, Innsbruck</item>
<item><hi lang="it" rend="italic">Crudelta consuma amore</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Cruelty Consumes Love</hi>) – pastoral opera in three acts; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pasticcio">pastiche</ref> with acts 1 and 3 by composed by Greber, act 2 by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Augustin_Reinhard_Stricker">Augustin Stricker</ref>, and the overture by Gottfried Finger; first performed 1717, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neuburg_an_der_Donau">Neuberg</ref> to celebrate the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Name_day">name day</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anna_Maria_Luisa_de'_Medici">Anna Maria Luisa de' Medici</ref>; score lost</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">Cantatas</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">Tu parti idolo mio</hi> - alto singer, flute,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> two violins, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basso_continuo">basso continuo</ref></item>
<item><hi rend="italic"> Quando lungi e il mio fileno</hi> - two singers (soprano and alto), two violins and basso continuo</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Filli, tra il gelo e'l foco</hi> - soprano singer, two flutes and basso continuo</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Fuori di sua capanna</hi> - alto singer, flute and basso continuo</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chamber music</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sonata">Sonata</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C_major">C major</ref> for flute and basso continuo</item>
<item>Sonata in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C_minor">C minor</ref> for two flutes and basso continuo</item></list>
<head>Notes and references</head>
</text>
