<text id="autogum_academic_doc257" title="A Long-Term Cost-Oriented Cloudlet Planning Method in Wireless Metropolitan Area Networks" shortTile="longterm-costoriented" author="Xinjie Guan, Xili Wan, Tianjing Wang, Yifeng Li" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2079-9292/8/11/1213/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Along with the booming of mobile applications and the Internet of Things (IoT), a momentously increasing number of mobile devices and applications are widely used at the network edge. Based on a report from Cisco, it is predicted that around 850 ZB data will be generated at the network edge by 2021, which significantly exceeds the traffic in global data centers. Besides handling tremendous data, popular mobile applications and services, e.g., video surveillance, interactive gaming, and voice assistants, require intensive computational resources. In particular, with the proliferation of artificial intelligence (AI) supported smart applications, mobile and IoT devices face big challenges due to their limited computational capacities, as well as constrained power. </p>

<p>One of the conventional ways to deal with this issue is to offload the computation-intensive work and service data from mobile devices to remote cloud data centers. However, moving from the network edge to remote cloud data centers via wide area networks (WAN) results in prohibitively high transmission latency and monetary cost, which is nontrivial especially for latency-sensitive applications. Another major concern of processing data on remote clouds is the privacy leakage issue. </p>

<p>To fulfill the requirements of latency-sensitive and resource-intensive applications, the novel paradigm Multi-access Edge Computing (MEC) is proposed and promptly ascends to the spotlight. By pushing computation tasks and data to small-sized cloudlets near mobile users, MEC reduces the transmission delay, alleviates the congestion in the network core, and saves the communication cost compared with remote cloud data centers. As an essential component in the MEC paradigm, a cloudlet, which consists of trusted computers with rich resources, serves the last mile of the Internet as a complement to centralized remote clouds. </p>

<p>Despite the benefits of sinking the data and computation to the network edge, new concerns on the placement and capacity planning of cloudlets have risen. It is not a trivial problem to balance the service performance and the infrastructure providers’ (ISP) costs while additionally considering user mobility, cloudlets’ coverage, and the large scale of Wireless Metropolitan Area Network (WMAN). Specifically, deploying more cloudlets closer to mobile users could reduce transmission delay and communication costs. However, this will definitely add more costs of purchasing and operating physical servers. Furthermore, to cope with user mobility, service migration has to be performed when a mobile user moves from the service region of one cloudlet to another. Service migration ensures that users could seamlessly access network services, yet it poses additional migration costs and may suffer from handover failure. Therefore, to deploy latency-sensitive and resource-intensive mobile services at network edge, one of the vital yet essential issues is to plan the cloudlets, including where to permanently place the cloudlets, what is the service region of each cloudlet, and how many physical resources should be assigned to each cloudlet considering the ISPs’ cost and performance requirements by mobile users. <figure>Figure 1</figure> demonstrates an example of a cloudlet planning in a WMAN with multiple access point (AP) cells. As shown in <figure>Figure 1</figure>, each AP is covered by exactly one cloudlet and each cloudlet is co-existed with one AP in its service region. </p>

<p>However, most existing studies are limited to improving the Quality of Service (QoS) of mobile applications or services by properly offloading tasks to physically deployed cloudlets, e.g.,. These studies focus on how the tasks or virtual services should be embedded in cloudlets that are equipped with virtualization techniques. Obviously, the computational resources that could be assigned to each task or virtual service are bounded by the maximum available physical resources in each cloudlet. In contrast, the planning of each cloudlet’s physical location, capacity, and service region coverage has been ignored. </p>

<p>In our previous work, we noticed the impact of the cloudlet planning and started with an initial step of carefully partitioning the entire WMAN into disjoint service regions. However, in only the minimization of service handover costs is discussed, while the cloudlet construction costs and operation costs are ignored. Therefore, in the proposed solution, we only suggested the way to determine the service regions without the planning of cloudlets’ physical placement and capacities. </p>
</text>
