<text id="autogum_academic_doc523" title="Combined Supplementation with Glycine and Tryptophan Reduces Purine-Induced Serum Uric Acid Elevation by Accelerating Urinary Uric Acid Excretion: A Randomized, Single-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Crossover Study" shortTile="combined-supplementation" author="Shunji Oshima, Sachie Shiiya, Yasunori Nakamura" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6643/11/11/2562/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
This study examined whether the combined administration of 6.0 g of glycine and 0.4 g of tryptophan suppressed the elevation in serum uric acid levels induced by purine ingestion and increased urinary uric acid excretion. The amino acid doses used for single ingestion were based on those used in continual supplementation. Both glycine and tryptophan are present in dietary proteins that are ingested in normal daily living. However, glycine at doses of up to 90 g per day administered over several weeks were reported no serious adverse effects. The oral administration of up to 5.0 g of l-tryptophan per day did not lead to any adverse effects in young adult females. Therefore, no adverse effects were attributed to the combined administration of glycine and tryptophan in the current trial. This study confirmed the safety of combined glycine and tryptophan supplementation. </p>

<p>The current study demonstrated that the combined administration of glycine and tryptophan significantly suppressed the elevation in the serum uric acid levels caused by purine ingestion in healthy subjects. The effect of the combined amino acid administration was stronger than that of the same glycine dose alone, indicating that a small amount of tryptophan provides an additional benefit to glycine alone in reducing the elevation in the serum uric acid levels after the ingestion of dietary purines. </p>

<p>In agreement with previous reports, glycine increased urinary uric acid excretion and enhanced urate clearance in the current study. The authors previously reported that continual supplementation with glycine and tryptophan led to an increase in urinary pH. Glycine exhibits a buffering action and it is often used as an antacid. The water solubility of uric acid increases with increasing pH levels and uric acid excretion is more favorable in alkaline urine than in acidic urine. Therefore, it is possible that the elevation in urinary pH caused by glycine and tryptophan supplementation enhanced the solubility of urinary uric acid, thereby elevating urinary uric acid excretion and urate clearance. Previous studies provide physiological, physicochemical and clinical validation for the use of citrate salt in the treatment of some types of lithiasis. Citrate salts treatment substantially increased urinary pH in patients with uric acid lithiasis, however, there was no significant change in the amount of urinary uric acid. The mixture of amino acids might be superior to citrate salts in the prevention or treatment of hyperuricemia. Herein, although the elevation of urinary pH induced by the ingestion of glycine alone was not significant compared with the effects of placebo, glycine administration enhanced uric acid excretion and urate clearance, raising the possibility of other mechanisms. Urate transporter 1 (URAT1), a primary reabsorptive urate transporter that is targeted by pyrazinamide, reportedly disables glycine-induced uricosuria. Pyrazinamide may reflect the enhanced urate reabsorption following the exchange of its active metabolite. Thus, glycine may inhibit the reabsorptive action of uric acid, which is induced by URAT1. Further studies are needed to elucidate the action of glycine on URAT1. </p>

<p>In the current study, the supplementation with tryptophan alone had no influence on urinary pH, urinary uric acid excretion or urate clearance. As the effect of tryptophan on URAT1 might be structurally difficult, tryptophan might have exerted an indirect action against uric acid elevation via its influence on the action of glycine. Specifically, tryptophan might promote the direct action of glycine against uric acid elevation. The maximum serum levels of glycine and tryptophan are achieved within an hour of ingestion, which is followed by rapid decreases as the amino acids are metabolized. Glycine metabolizes various end-products, namely glutathione, nucleic acid bases, heme, creatine and bile acids. The increases in urinary creatinine excretion and creatinine clearance following the glycine challenge suggest that glycine might be partially absorbed back and metabolized to creatinine through creatine. Conversely, these urinary parameters did not change in response to the simultaneous supplementation with glycine and tryptophan, suggesting the suppression of the conversion of glycine to creatinine by tryptophan. In fact, the increases in the serum glycine/creatinine ratio and urinary glycine excretion were more pronounced in response to supplementation with glycine and tryptophan than with glycine alone. Further studies are required to clarify the mechanism underlying the contribution of tryptophan to the effects of glycine on uric acid excretion. </p>

<p>Among the limitations in the current clinical study, the modest sample size (<hi rend="italic">n</hi> = 16) might have reduced the statistical power and increased the risk of type II error, particularly regarding the statistical differences in multiple comparisons between the glycine and glycine + tryptophan groups. Furthermore, the current study included only male subjects because of the known effects of sex differences on serum uric acid levels. Further studies are therefore needed, although our preliminary findings suggested that there were no effective differences between males and females in response to glycine and tryptophan supplementation (data not shown). </p>
</text>
