<text id="autogum_academic_doc532" title="Oscillating U-Shaped Body for Underwater Piezoelectric Energy Harvester Power Optimization" shortTile="oscillating-ushaped" author="Iñigo Aramendia, Aitor Saenz-Aguirre, Ana Boyano, Unai Fernandez-Gamiz, Ekaitz Zulueta" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-666X/10/11/737/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Due to industrial development and the improved quality of human life, the economic and social demand for energy is growing. In recent years, the problems arising from the use of coal, petroleum, and other energy resources with high carbon content are becoming almost unbearable. The trend of annual average of atmospheric CO2 concentration has been increasing non-stop in the last decades. The global average surface temperature was reported to be approximately 1 °C higher than that of the preindustrial period. The transition to an energy system that relies primarily on renewable energy sources has become one of the greatest challenges for alleviating climate change. Clean energy sources such as wind, solar, geothermal, biomass, biofuels, waves, tidal, and hydropower can replace fossil fuels. With that in mind, water value is due not only to its agricultural and domestic use, but also to the possibility of being a source of energy, such as hydropower, ocean energy, or the energy obtained from its distribution network, for instance. </p>

<p>In this context, collecting small amounts of energy from the ambient in order to supply power to wireless devices has been investigated for the last decades. Moreover, in some cases where batteries are impractical, such as inaccessible remote systems, health monitoring, or body sensors, energy harvesting technology is very promising. In fact, the power supply is one of the biggest challenges regarding the wireless sensor network applications. Frequently, the lifetime is confined to a battery supply, which is awkward. Several environmental resources that offer enough power can be studied such as vibration, solar irradiation, thermal differences, and hybrid energy sources. Vibration energy harvesting (VeH) transforms mechanical energy obtained from ambient sources to electricity in order to power remote sensors. VeH technologies have been widely studied over the past decade. Izadgoshasb et al. proposed a new double pendulum-based piezoelectric system to harvest energy from human movements. They found a high increase in maximum output voltage in comparison to the conventional system and to an analogous system with only one pendulum. Furthermore, they stated that the double pendulum design could be further improved by varying some design parameters regarding dimensions or material. In a more recent work, Izadgoshasb et al. proposed a multi-resonant harvester that consists of a cantilever beam with two triangular branches. They performed a parametric study using the finite element method (FEM) for the design optimization in order to get close resonances at low-frequency spectrum. Experimental results showed that the proposed harvester can harvest broadband energy from ambient vibration sources and is better than analogous piezoelectric energy harvesters with cantilever beams. </p>

<p>Energy harvesting from flow-induced vibrations has also attracted attention in the past years, and energy obtained from fluid–structure interaction (FSI) in different fluids, air, or liquid have been investigated by Elahi et al.. Under flow loads, a structure can suffer different effects, such as limit cycle oscillations, chaotic movements, or internal resonances. From the point of view of aerodynamics, vortex-induced vibrations or vibrations caused by flutter or galloping can occur. Using piezoelectric devices placed in a flow field can convert large oscillations into electrical energy. An airfoil section placed on the end of cantilever piezoelectric beam can be used as a flutter energy harvester. Flutter speed is a critical value, from which the aerodynamic system becomes unstable. The self-excited oscillations that appear on the aeroelastic system once the critical value is overpassed are quite beneficial from the dynamic point of view; see Abdelkefi et al.. Elahi et al. modeled a nonlinear piezoelectric aeroelastic energy harvester that works on a postcritical aerolastic regime. An analytical model was developed taking into account the fluid–structure interaction and electromechanical performance. They concluded that higher electromechanical factor gives better harvesting. Wang et al. conducted a study on a galloping-based piezoelectric energy harvester using isosceles triangle sectioned bluff bodies and applying computational fluid dynamics (CFD) to simulate the aerodynamic forces. They performed a parametric study in order to get the optimum vertex angle of the triangle and provided a guideline for efficient design. They determined that an angle of 130 degrees was the most adequate within the specific electromechanical coupling of their prototype. Dai et al. investigated energy harvesting obtained from wind flow-induced vibrations. They compared experimentally four different test cases of piezoelectric energy harvesters, and based on the results they concluded which was the best orientation of the bluff body to design efficient devices. Jia et al. presented an upright piezoelectric energy harvester (UPEH) that has a cylinder extension along its length. In the case with low speed wind, energy is obtained by vortex-induced vibrations (VIVs) that produce bending deformation. The UPEH can generate energy from low-speed wind by bending deformation produced by vortex-induced vibrations (VIVs). Zulueta et al. developed a new control law for a contactless piezoelectric wind energy harvester, and afterwards, Bouzelata et al. improved this wind energy harvester as a battery charger The simulation results proved that the device could power the battery when the wind speed is v = 2.7 m/s, taking into account that usually the moderate wind speed is considered to be 4 m/s. </p>
</text>
