<text id="autogum_bio_doc548" title="Niccolò dell&apos;Arca" shortTile="niccolo-dellarca" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-06-02" dateModified="2016-11-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niccol%C3%B2_dell%27Arca" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Niccolò dell'Arca</head><figure><caption>Arca di San Domenico.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption><hi rend="italic">San Floriano</hi> (Arca di San Domenico).</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Niccolò dell’Arca</hi> (c. 1435-1440 – 2 March 1494)  was an Italian Early Renaissance sculptor. He is also known under the names Niccolò da Ragusa, Niccolò da Bari and Niccolò d'Antonio d'Apulia. The surname “dell’Arca” refers to his contribution to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arca_di_San_Domenico">Arca di San Domenico</ref>.</p>
<p>The place and the year of his birth are not certain. He was probably born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apulia">Apulia</ref>, perhaps in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bari">Bari</ref>, and then most likely lived for some time in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dalmatia">Dalmatia</ref>. According to C. Gnudi (see ref.) he received training there by the Dalmatian sculptor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giorgio_da_Sebenico">Giorgio da Sebenico</ref>. </p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burgundy_(region)">Burgundian</ref> elements in his sculpture are attributed by some art historians to his presumed participation in the triumphal arch of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Castel_Nuovo">Castel Nuovo</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Naples">Naples</ref> during the 1450s (where he would have known the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catalonia">Catalan</ref> sculptor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guillem_Sagrera">Guillem Sagrera</ref> and would be influenced by his style).</p>
<p>Others, rejecting his training in Naples, contend instead that he travelled to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/France">France</ref> in the late 1460s. According to them, his further training then allegedly took place in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siena">Siena</ref>, influenced by the works of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacopo_della_Quercia">Jacopo della Quercia</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Donatello">Donatello</ref>.</p>
<p>He was mentioned for the first time in September 1462 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bologna">Bologna</ref> as <hi rend="italic">Maestro Nicolò da Puglia</hi>, a “master of terracotta figures”. This probably refers to the “Compianto sul Cristo morto”, terracotta group in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sanctuary_of_Santa_Maria_della_Vita">Sanctuary of Santa Maria della Vita</ref> in Bologna (also mentioned in a Bull of 1464 by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Paul_II">Pope Paul II</ref>). A life-size group of six separate figures stand lamenting in a semicircle around the dead Christ in a lying posture. The dramatic pathos, the expressions of grief and torment of the figures is intensified by the realism of their dramatic facial details. However the date of this innovative  contribution to Renaissance sculpture is uncertain. Instead of c. 1460, some date it between 1485 and 1490.</p>
<p>In 1469 he got the commission of an ambitious new addition on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arca_di_San_Domenico">Arca di San Domenico</ref>: a spiral superstructure and several free-standing figures on top of the sarcophagus. This <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sarcophagus">sarcophagus</ref> with the remains of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint_Dominic">Saint Dominic</ref> had been sculpted two centuries before by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicola_Pisano">Nicola Pisano</ref> and his workshop (between 1265 and 1267). It had been completed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lapo">lapo</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arnolfo_di_Cambio">Arnolfo di Cambio</ref> and fra <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guglielmo_Agnelli">Guglielmo Agnelli</ref>. Niccolò dell’Arca added an elaborate spire with an impressive statue of “God the Father” on top of a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Candelabrum">candelabrum</ref>, held by two <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Putti">putti</ref> and four dolphins, all covered with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Festoon">festoons</ref> with fruit. On the cornice at its base is in the middle a small <hi rend="italic">Pietà</hi>, flanked by two angels, while on the four corners stand the four Evangelists in oriental dress. The lower part of the superstructure is surrounded by free-standing figures: the Patron Saints of Bologna (Saint <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_of_Assisi">Francis of Assisi</ref>), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Petronio">San Petronio</ref> (began by Niccolò but finished by young <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michelangelo">Michelangelo</ref> in 1494), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint_Dominic">Saint Dominic</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint_Florian">Saint Florian</ref>. On the back stand St Anne, St John the Baptist (sculpted by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Girolamo_Cortellini">Girolamo Cortellini</ref> in 1539), San Procolo and San Vitale. Niccolò also added the <hi rend="italic">Candlestick-holding Angel</hi> on the left side of the altar slab (the one on the right side is by Michelangelo).</p>
<p>Niccolò dell’Arca worked on this masterpiece between 1469 and 1473, leaving it unfinished. He probably continued intermittently at it until his death. Art critics see in this masterpiece a blend of influences: Burgundian, Florentine and non-Tuscan (such as details in clothing). The way these statuettes express their emotions and the patterns in their dresses and hair evoke the style of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacopo_della_Quercia">Jacopo della Quercia</ref>.</p>
<p>Some other important works include the terracotta bust of Saint Dominic (1474) (in the museum of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basilica_of_San_Domenico">Basilica of San Domenico</ref> in Bologna), a marble statue of St. John the Baptist (in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Escorial">Escorial</ref> in Madrid) and the terracotta figure of Saint Monica (c. 1478-1480) (Museum Palace in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Modena">Modena</ref>).</p>
<p>Also notable is the terracotta high relief of <hi rend="italic">Madonna di Piazza</hi> (1478) on the wall of the Palazzo Comunale in Bologna. In the marked drapery folds is seen the influence of Jacopo della Quercia and also traces of the dynamic naturalism of his contemporary <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrea_del_Verrocchio">Andrea del Verrocchio</ref>.</p>
<list type="unordered">
<item><hi rend="italic">Pietà</hi> (Arca di San Domenico)</item>
<item>Polychromed terracotta of Saint Dominic</item>
<item>Madonna di Piazza<hi rend="italic">, Bologna</hi></item>
</list>
</text>
