<text id="autogum_interview_doc563" title="Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Family Coalition Party candidate Blaise Thompson, St. Paul&amp;apos;s" shortTile="ontario-votes--interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-26" dateModified="2007-11-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Family_Coalition_Party_candidate_Blaise_Thompson%2C_St._Paul%27s" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Family Coalition Party candidate Blaise Thompson, St. Paul's</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 26, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blaise%20Thompson">Blaise Thompson</ref></hi> is running for the Family Coalition Party in the Ontario provincial election, in the St. Paul's riding. Wikinews' Nick Moreau interviewed him regarding his values, his experience, and his campaign.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>"We all want to vote for the best man, but he's never a candidate!"</p>
<p>I entered politics because you don't stand by when your mother is being attacked.</p>
<p>I chose to run in this constituency because I live here and generations of my family have lived here.</p>
<p>This is as good a place as any to make a stand. If not here, where? If not now, when?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>I have no prior political experience and I'm nobody's corporate whore.</p>
<p>I'm bringing the same skills to office that a passenger in a car brings to a driver who is heading for a wall.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why? What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?</hi></p>
<p>The big parties have money and money can buy votes.</p>
<p>As the Family Coalition Party candidate, I represent both past and future Ontarians, which is the best way to represent current Ontarians. Our population pyramid is no longer in the shape of a pyramid; it's in the shape of a hand-grenade. (<ref target="http://www12.statcan.ca/english/census06/analysis/agesex/charts/chart7.htm">Link</ref>)</p>
<p>If the anti-life, anti-family policies of the other parties continue to be applied, our infrastructure, way of life, and society itself will be crippled. The other parties have responded to the coming demographic tsunami by drawing the curtains. They have, in effect, disqualified themselves.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>Housing, health care, and school funding are the top issues to voters in my riding.</p>
<p>The greater includes the lesser. As I say, if we do not address the fact that we are killing our future then the other issues will not signify. The best way to ensure a healthy economy is to promote a healthy society that can sustain itself. If this is not done, we are just rearranging deck chairs on the <hi rend="italic">Titanic</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly?</hi></p>
<p>The first order of business is to end the assault on the unborn and on the family. We must promote a Culture of Life or head into a demographic winter.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are the property taxes in your riding at a fair level for the amount of services received in the municipality?</hi></p>
<p>The question betrays a certain confusion of mind. The game of hot potato between the Province and the Cities is a smokescreen for a much more serious issue.</p>
<p>Our province, and indeed our country, is heading for the retaining wall of reality. If present trends continue, our shrinking tax base will be unable to sustain even present levels of service, not to mention the greatly increased demands caused by the Boomer Generation retiring. No one's math is creative enough to disguise that fact, hence the slight air of unreality (and desperation) in all of these fiscal discussions.</p>
<p>Health care currently accounts for 46% of the Ontario budget. This percentage is bound to increase as more and more people retire, yet fewer and fewer people are taking their place in the work force. At this rate, the present system cannot be sustained. It is beyond the realm of sanity to suggest otherwise.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How can the province lead the way in stimulating job creation?</hi></p>
<p>The best way to ensure a healthy economy is to promote a healthy society that can sustain itself, so the province can lead the way in stimulating job creation by promoting Life and the Family. If this is not done, all measures will fail.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What are your views on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mixed%20member%20proportional%20representation">mixed member proportional representation</ref> (MMP) referendum?</hi></p>
<p>It's red herring time again.</p>
<p>Any system presupposes a moral people (just ask a bank manager). To MMP or not to MMP, that is not the question: Ontarians must choose between the present culture of death and a Culture of Life. A change of method without a change of heart will be an exercise in futility.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What role, if any, does “new media” play in your campaign, and the campaign of your party? (websites, blogs, Facebook, YouTube videos, etc) Do you view it as beneficial, or a challenge?</hi></p>
<p>Any system that favours the status quo by definition favours the incumbent. I have been shut out of every face-to-face debate (which the old-boy network still controls), whereas the Net tends to reroute around obstacles. It definitely has levelled the playing field for the little guy.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Of the decisions made by Ontario's 38th Legislative Assembly, which was the most beneficial to your this electoral district? To the province as a whole? Which was least beneficial, or even harmful, to your this riding? To the province as a whole?</hi></p>
<p>The least beneficial decision made by Ontario's 38th Legislative Assembly was to ignore the fact that they are literally bleeding us white.</p>
<p>The most beneficial decision was to call an election so they can be tossed out.</p>
</text>
