<text id="autogum_bio_doc248" title="Jafar Khan" shortTile="jafar-khan" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-01-21" dateModified="2019-03-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jafar_Khan" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Jafar Khan</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jafar Khan Zand</hi>, (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Persian_language">Persian</ref>: جعفر خان زند‎) was the seventh <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shah">shah</ref></hi> (king) of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zand_dynasty">Zand dynasty</ref> from 1785 to 1789. He was the son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sadiq_Khan_Zand">Sadiq Khan Zand</ref>, who was removed from the throne in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shiraz">Shiraz</ref> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ali_Murad_Khan">Ali Murad Khan</ref>, who had previously taken <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isfahan">Isfahan</ref> for himself.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>In February 1781, the Zand prince Ali Murad Khan put Jafar Khan's father Sadiq Khan Zand and all his brothers to death when he invaded <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shiraz">Shiraz</ref>. Jafar Khan was the only one who was spared, because he privately had reached an agreement with Ali Murad Khan. While Ali Murad Khan was in northern Iran in 1785, Jafar Khan took the opportunity to besiege <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isfahan">Isfahan</ref>. Ali Murad Khan then marched towards the city in order to defend it, but died on 11 February at Murchakhur, a town near Isfahan.</p>
<head>Reign</head>
<p>Jafar Khan then crowned himself as the new Zand king in Isfahan. At the same time, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qajar_dynasty">Qajar</ref> warlord <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agha_Mohammad_Khan">Agha Mohammad Khan</ref> marched towards Isfahan. Jafar Khan then sent his men to stop his advance towards the city, but they withdrew at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qom">Qum</ref> without even putting any resistance. Jafar Khan then sent an even larger Zand army towards Agha Mohammad Khan, who defeated the army near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kashan">Kashan</ref>. Jafar Khan then fled to Shiraz. Agha Mohammad afterwards arrived to Isfahan, where he discovered what was left of the Zand treasure and Jafar Khan's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harem">harem</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHambly1991118-1">[1]</ref> The Qajar troops then looted the city.</p>
<p>In 1786, while Agha Mohammad Khan was in northern Iran, Jafar Khan quickly marched towards Isfahan and re-captured it. He then sent troops towards Kashan and Qum, while he marched towards <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hamadan">Hamadan</ref>. He was, however, defeated by local tribal chieftains, such as a certain Khosrow Khan and Mohammad Hosayn Khan Qaragozlu.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHambly1991119-2">[2]</ref> Jafar Khan then withdrew to Isfahan. When Agha Mohammad Khan heard about the Zand invasion of Isfahan and its surroundings, he quickly marched towards the city, which made Jafar Khan retreat back to Shiraz once again. In 1788, Agha Mohammad advanced closely to Shiraz, where he hoped to bait Jafar Khan out of Shiraz, which was strongly fortified, making it very hard to besiege. Unfortunately for Agha Mohammad Khan, Jafar Khan stayed in the city, which made Agha Mohammad Khan return to Isfahan, where appointed his brother Ali Qoli as its new governor, thus succeeding Jafar Qoli Khan. He then left for Tehran.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHambly1991121-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>With Agha Mohammad once again in the north, Jafar Khan began raising an army to prepare another attack against Isfahan and its surroundings. When Ali Qoli found out about it, he sent a group of tribesmen to a city south to Isfahan, named Qumishah. However, Jafar Khan managed to easily defeat them. Ali Qoli thereafter retreated to Kashan.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHambly1991121-3">[3]</ref> Agha Mohammad Khan, learning of this, rapidly marched towards Isfahan, which made Jafar Khan withdraw to Shiraz once again. Agha Mohammad Khan, who was too unconfident to try and capture Shiraz, then went back to Tehran. Jafar Khan was murdered on 23 January 1789 by Ali Murad Khan's son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sayed_Murad_Khan">Sayed Murad Khan</ref>. After his death, a four-month civil war began between several Zand princes who fought for succession to the throne. Jafar Khan's son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lotf_Ali_Khan">Lotf Ali Khan</ref> emerged being the victor in this civil war in May.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHambly1991121-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Issue</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sons</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Prince <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lotf_Ali_Khan">Lotf Ali Khan Zand</ref></item>
<item>Prince Khosrow Khan Zand</item>
<item>Prince Abbas Qoli Khan Zand</item>
<item>Prince Najaf Ali Khan Zand</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">Daughter(s)</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Princess Maryam Begum Zand</item></list>
</text>
