<text id="autogum_interview_doc293" title="part4_Wikinews interviews Frank McEnulty, independent candidate for US President" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-15" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Frank_McEnulty%2C_independent_candidate_for_US_President" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">What are you/were you looking for in a running mate?</hi></p>
<p>I will be looking for someone who is smart, wants what is best for all Americans, is a moderate, a fiscal conservative and will put forth the time and effort to run in a real campaign.  I also believe that my running mate needs to be a business person because the government is a business and needs to run more like one.  I’m not worried about being outsiders in the Washington scene, because I believe that gridlock is good for the following reason.  If there is gridlock, then only legislation that makes sense for all Americans and benefits the vast majority of all Americans will get passed.  We’ve got hundreds of thousands of laws.  We don’t need new ones every day.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Can you win the 2008 Presidential election?</hi></p>
<p>I am willing to admit that my chances of winning the 2008 Presidential election are slight, but there is still a chance for the simple reason that I do not see a candidate on either the Republican or Democratic side who is looking to do what is best for all Americans and I strongly believe that most Americans are still looking for that person to lead them as their President.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Can any third party or independent candidate ever win?</hi></p>
<p>Yes, I believe the odds of a third party or independent candidate improve with every Presidential election.  People are becoming more and more frustrated with what they perceive as a complete lack of interest on the part of politicians, including their President, with what is best of the country.  The more noise the third party and independent candidates make, the more people will realize there is another choice and the better their chance becomes of winning the White House.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">If you can't make it into the Oval Office, who would you prefer seeing taking the presidency?</hi></p>
<p>None of the current candidates from the two major parties are suitable to be President at this time.  Right now, and I have heard this from a lot a people, it will be a choice of hold your nose and vote for who you think might do the least amount of damage.  None of the major candidates remaining (who have a chance per the newspapers) have any desire to do what is right for America in the long-term and do what is right for all Americans and not just what will get their party members elected and reelected.  Hard, unpopular decisions need to be made to get our country back on a decent track and no politician from a major party will take that track.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What should the American people keep in mind, when heading to the polls this November?</hi></p>
</text>
