<text id="autogum_fiction_doc453" title="Martin Hyde, the Duke's Messenger" shortTile="martinhydedukesmessenger" author="Masefield, John" type="fiction" dateCollected="2019-10-22" sourceURL="http://gutenberg.readingroo.ms/1/2/7/1274/1274-0.txt">
<head>CHAPTER VII. LAND RATS AND WATER RATS</head>

<p>I will say no more about our passage except that we were three days at sea. Then, when I woke one morning, I found that we were fast moored to a gay little wharf, paved with clean white cobbles, on the north side of the canal. Strange, outlandish figures, in immense blue baggy trousers, clattered past in wooden shoes. A few Dutch galliots lay moored ahead of us, with long scarlet pennons on their mastheads. On the other side of the canal was a huge East Indiaman, with her lower yards cockbilled, loading all three hatches at once. It was a beautiful morning. The sun was so bright that all the scene had thrice its natural beauty. The clean neat trimness of the town, the water slapping past in the canal, the ships with their flags, the Sunday trim of the schooner, all filled me with delight, lit up, as they were, by the April sun. I looked about me at my ease, for the deck was deserted. Even the never-sleeping mate was resting, now that we were in port. While I looked, a man sidled along the wharf from a warehouse towards me. He looked at the schooner in a way which convinced me that he was not a sailor. Then, sheltering behind a bollard, he lighted his pipe.</p>

<p>He was a short, active, wiry man, with a sharp, thin face, disfigured by a green patch over his right eye. He looked to me to have a horsey look, as though were a groom or coachman. After lighting his pipe, he advanced to a point abreast of the schooner's gang-way, from which he could look down upon her, as she lay with her deck a foot or two below the level of the wharf.</p>

<p>“Chips aboard?” he asked, meaning, “Is the carpenter on board?”</p>

<p>“Yes,” I said. “Will you come aboard?”</p>

<p>He did not answer, but looked about the ship, as though making notes of everything. Presently he turned to me.</p>

<p>“You're new,” he said. “Are you Mr. Jermyn's boy?” I told him that I was.</p>

<p>“How is Mr. Jermyn keeping?” he asked. “Is that cough of his better?” This made me feel that probably the man knew Mr. Jermyn. “Yes,” I said. “He's got no cough, now.” “He'd a bad one last time he was here,” the man answered. For a while he kept silent. He seemed to me to be puzzling out the relative heights of our masts. Suddenly he turned to me, with a very natural air. “How's Mr. Scott's business going?” he asked. “You know, eh? You know what I mean?” I was taken off my guard. I'm afraid I hesitated, though I knew that the man's sharp eyes noted every little change on my face. Then, in the most natural way, the man reassured me. “You know,” he said. “What demand for oranges in London?” I was thankful that he had not meant the other business. I said with a good deal too much of eagerness that there was, I believed, a big demand for oranges. “Yes,” he said, “I suppose so many young boys makes a brisk demand.” I was uneasy at the man's manner. He seemed to be pumping me, but he had such a natural easy way, under the pale mask of his face, that I could not be sure if he were in the secret or not. I was on my guard now, ready for any question, as I thought, but eager for an excuse to get away from this man before I betrayed any trust. “Nice ship,” he said easily. “Did you join her in Spain?” “No,” I answered. “In London.” “In London?” he said. “I thought you'd something of a Spanish look.” “No,” I said. “I'm English. Did you want the carpenter, sir?”</p>

<p>“Yes,” he answered. “I do. But no hurry. No hurry, lad.” Here he pulled out a watch, which he wound up, staring vacantly about the decks as he did so. “Tell me, boy,” he said gently. “Is Lane come over with you?” To tell the truth, it flashed across my mind, when he pulled out his watch, that he was making me unready for a difficult question. I was not a very bright boy; but I had this sudden prompting or instinct, which set me on my guard. No one is more difficult to pump than a boy who is ready for his questioner, so I stared at him. “Lane?” I said, “Lane? Do you mean the bo'sun?”</p>

<p>“No,” he said. “The Colonel. You know? Eh?”</p>

<p>“No.” I said. “I don't know.”</p>

<p>“Oh well,” he answered. “It's all one. I suppose he's not come over.” At this moment the mate came on deck with the carpenter, carrying a model ship which they had been making together in their spare time. They nodded to the stranger, who gave them a curt “How do?” as though they had parted from him only the night before. The mate growled at me for wasting time on deck when I should be at work. He sent me down to my usual job of getting the cabin ready for the breakfast of the gentlemen. As I passed down the hatchway, I heard the carpenter say to the stranger, “Well. So what's the news with Jack?” It flashed into my mind that this man might be his friend, the “Longshore Jack” who was to keep an eye upon me as well as upon Mr. Jermyn. It gave me a most horrid qualm to think this. The man was so sly, so calm, so guarded, that the thought of him being on the look-out for me, to sell me to the Dutch captains, almost scared me out of my wits. The mate brought him to the cabin as I was laying the table. “This is the cabin,” he was saying, “where the gentlemen messes. That's our stern-chaser, the gun there.”</p>
</text>
