<text id="autogum_interview_doc174" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Andy Martin, U.S. Republican Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-07-28" dateModified="2015-08-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Andy_Martin%2C_U.S._Republican_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">William S. Saturn</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : <hi rend="bold">You ran for president in 1988 as a member of the Democratic Party. Why did you choose to become a member of that party, and what caused you to switch to the Republican Party?</hi></item></list>
<p>Andy Martin: [The late] Congressman <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack%20Kemp">Jack Kemp</ref> and Rev. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Pat_Robertson">Pat Robertson</ref> invited me to join the Republican Party and I did.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : <hi rend="bold">Are you still in contact with Pat Robertson?</hi>
<p>Martin: No.</p></p></p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : <hi rend="bold">What is your response to the claims from Robert Gibbs and others that you are Anti-Semitic due to the alleged anti-Jewish language used in some of your previous lawsuits?</hi></item></list>
<p>Martin: Robert Gibbs engaged in a crude political smear based on lies, distortions and misrepresentations. For the past four or five years I have been the victim of a pro-Obama dirty tricks operation orchestrated out of Wikipedia.org and the Obama campaign apparatus. In one sense, Obama’s use of malicious smears against me shows how desperate he is to discredit my activity. In another sense, the fact that Obama goes to such lengths to attack me is a compliment to the seriousness with which he views both my research and my current presidential campaign. The national media may not yet take my presidential campaign seriously but Mr. Obama and his dirty tricksters very much do. What does Obama know that the media don’t?</p>
<head id="Presidential_campaign">Presidential campaign</head>
<p>Martin has centered his campaign in the state of New Hampshire and has discussed local issues. For environmental reasons, he opposes the Northern Pass transmission line, an energy project slated to connect New England to the hydroelectric resources of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hydro-Québec">Hydro-Québec</ref>. When asked if the project was under the purview of the office of the presidency, he replied that it requires a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/presidential%20finding">presidential finding</ref>. On July 28, Martin released a press release that described a planned march against the Northern Pass as "what could be the largest campaign event generated by any presidential candidate in New Hampshire during the 2012 election cycle." When asked to go into detail about the event, Martin responded that it was "too time consuming" to provide "personalized analysis" but remarked that "I'd say we are surprising a lot of people and we have many more rabbits to pull out of the hat as the campaign progresses."</p>
<p>Martin has not been invited to any <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republican%20Party%20(United%20States)%20presidential%20debates,%202012">Republican primary presidential debates</ref> and has not been included in any <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nationwide%20opinion%20polling%20for%20the%20United%20States%20presidential%20election,%202012">presidential preference polls</ref>.   </p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">William S. Saturn</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : <hi rend="bold">Why did you decide to run for president in 2012?</hi></item></list>
<p>Andy Martin: I did not think and still do not believe that any of the “leading” Republican candidates are capable of waging an effective campaign against Barack Obama. I believe I could do a better job because of my extensive understanding and study of Obama’s character and personality. I predicted his ineffectiveness as a president in my Psychological Study which was published as a chapter in my bestselling book <hi rend="italic">Obama: The Man Behind The Mask</hi> in 2008. I understood Obama before the American electorate did. They were not listening to me in 2008; maybe they will listen in 2012. To paraphrase former New York Mayor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ed%20Koch">Ed Koch</ref>, the American people did not listen to me in 2008 and they are suffering for it. Now I’m running formally as a candidate to take my case against Obama to the American people.</p>
</text>
