<text id="autogum_voyage_doc24" title="Gniezno" shortTile="gniezno" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=12875" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Gniezno</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.gniezno.home.pl/">Gniezno</ref></hi> is a city in <ref target="Greater%20Poland">Greater Poland</ref> in <ref target="Poland">Poland</ref>. It is traditionally regarded as having been the first capital of Poland, and has been witness to many important events in early Polish history. Gniezno has become the seat of the second Polish diocese (after <ref target="Pozna%C5%84">Poznań</ref>) and the first archbishopric. The coronations of several kings of Poland took place in the Gniezno cathedral.</p>

<p>Gniezno is situated in the northeastern part of the Greater Poland, between three lakes: Jelonek, Swietokrzyskie and Winiary, in what is called the Gniezno Lake District. It is only 50 kilometres away from <ref target="Pozna%C5%84">Poznań</ref> and relatively close to <ref target="Kujawsko-Pomorskie">Kujawsko-Pomorskie</ref>.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>The nearest airports with scheduled passenger service are in <ref target="Pozna%C5%84">Poznań</ref> (50 km) and <ref target="Bydgoszcz">Bydgoszcz</ref> (90 km).</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>Gniezno is an important railroad junction, so there are many options to travel to and from the city by rail. The main rail line through Gniezno is <ref target="Pozna%C5%84">Poznań</ref>-Gniezno-<ref target="Inowroc%C5%82aw">Inowrocław</ref>, where it is forks out to <ref target="Gda%C5%84sk">Gdańsk</ref> through <ref target="Bydgoszcz">Bydgoszcz</ref> and to <ref target="Olsztyn">Olsztyn</ref> through <ref target="Toru%C5%84">Toruń</ref>, with numerous connections:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> to Poznań up to 17 daily regional trains and 6-10 (depending on season) fast ones. The travel time to Poznań varies from 40-45 for fast trains to 55 for the local ones (stopping at every station).</item>
<item> to Bydgoszcz and Gdańsk : 4 regional trains and 4-7 fast ones</item>
<item> to Toruń and Olsztyn 2 local trains and 3 fast ones.</item>
</list>


<p>Another line runs from Gniezno to <ref target="Wrze%C5%9Bnia">Września</ref> and <ref target="Jarocin">Jarocin</ref>, with 4 local trains daily (including two coordinated in Jarocin with trains to <ref target="Wroc%C5%82aw">Wrocław</ref>).</p>

<p>An interesting alternative for those traveling to Gniezno from the South-East is a journey by a local narrow-gauge railway. It runs over a 38 km route during spring and summer weekends, and on other days by special request. Details (Polish only) - <ref target="http://www.gkw-gniezno.pl"></ref>.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>Gniezno is a big bus travel junction, as well. Most coaches go not - as you might think - to Poznań (trains are dominating on this route), but to other places in the region (only routes to tourist places are mentioned) :</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Bydgoszcz : 7 buses daily</item>
<item> Czerniejewo (a beautiful historic palace) : more than 30 daily</item>
<item> Imiolki (the Dominican Fish-Gate) : 11 daily</item>
<item> <ref target="Konin">Konin</ref> : 14 buses daily</item>
<item> <ref target="Kruszwica">Kruszwica</ref> through <ref target="Strzelno">Strzelno</ref> : 8 daily</item>
<item> Skorzecin (a lake resort) : 12 daily</item>
<item> <ref target="Wenecja">Wenecja</ref> through <ref target="Biskupin">Biskupin</ref> : 9 buses daily</item>
<item> <ref target="W%C4%85growiec">Wągrowiec</ref> : 9 daily</item>
<item> <ref target="Wrze%C5%9Bnia">Września</ref> : 18 daily</item>
<item> <ref target="%C5%BBnin">Żnin</ref> : 10 buses daily</item>
</list>


<head>By car</head>
<p>The main road passing through Gniezno is the country road nr 5, linking the town with <ref target="Pozna%C5%84">Poznań</ref> and <ref target="Wroc%C5%82aw">Wrocław</ref> in the south and with <ref target="Bydgoszcz">Bydgoszcz</ref> and <ref target="Gda%C5%84sk">Gdańsk</ref> in the north and passing through such attractions like <ref target="Biskupin">Biskupin</ref>, <ref target="Wenecja">Wenecja</ref> or Znin. The other roads passing through Gniezno are: country road nr 15 - enablling you to get to <ref target="Kruszwica">Kruszwica</ref>, <ref target="Strzelno">Strzelno</ref> or <ref target="Toru%C5%84">Toruń</ref>; local road nr 260 - for those travelling in the Lake District nearby Powidz, 190 - to <ref target="W%C4%85growiec">Wągrowiec</ref> and 197 to Slawa through the northern parts of Lednicki Landscape Park.</p>

<head>On foot</head>
<p>Most tourists will find it unnecessary to use public transport in Gniezno, as all main tourist attractions are situated in the very centre (6-8 minute walk from both rail and bus station).</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>The network consists of 16 city bus lines and 1 suburban line. Some lines run only few times a day (e.g. in peak hours).</p>

<p>The fee structure is simple - single ride will cost you 2 zloty (0.45€), the fee doubles at night (23-5). If you travel more, you can use 11-ride ticket for 21 zloty. Unfortunately, there're no multiple-day tickets, the only option for those staying in the city for longer are monthly tickets - for one line : 50 zlotys (12€), for two lines : 60, for the whole network : 100 zlotys.</p>

<p>More information : free phone number : 9285 or <ref target="http://www.mpk.gniezno.pl"></ref>.</p>

<head>Tourist information</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> The regional Tourist Information Centre, Rynek Sq., Phone / fax : +48 61 428 41 00, <ref target="http://www.szlakpiastowski.com.pl"></ref> mailto:turystyka@powiat-gniezno.pl</item>
<item> Polish Country-Lovers’ Society, the Gniezno department, 10, Łaskiego str. Phone : +48 61 425 37 37, fax +48 61 426 36 60</item>
</list>


<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> The <hi rend="bold">Assumption and St. Adalbert's Cathedral</hi>, with the reliquaries of St. Adalbert (Czech: <hi rend="italic">Wojtiech</hi>; Polish: <hi rend="italic">Wojciech</hi>), famous Romanesque bronze door from c. 1170, the most precious monument of romanesque art in Poland, the tombs of St. Adalbert and numerous Gothic, Renaissance and Baroque monuments and tombs of Gniezno bishops and archbishops and some Polish primates.</item>
<item> The <hi rend="bold">Archbishopric Archives</hi> contain numerous documents including papal bulls from the early Middle Ages, the most precious of which are the Golden Gniezno Codex, the bulla od pope Innocent II from 1136 and the pergamine Gospel book - a manuscript from France from c. 800.</item>
<item> The Gothic <hi rend="bold">Church of St. John the Baptist</hi> from the mid 19th century, with unique polichromy in the presbytery. More : <ref target="http://www.ambiento.net/bozogrobcy"></ref></item>
<item> The <hi rend="bold">Archbishopric Museum</hi> with precious liturgical vessels, including the chalice of St. Adalbert, chalice of Dobrava (the wife of first polish Dukre, buried in <ref target="Pozna%C5%84">Poznań</ref>) or the Royal Chalice.</item>
<item> The Gothic <hi rend="bold">Parish church of the Holy Trinity</hi> from the 15th century</item>
<item> The Gothic-Baroque <hi rend="bold">Franciscan Assumption and St. Anthony's Church</hi> with the miraculous icon of Our Lady, the Mistress of Gniezno; next door is the Baroque Franciscan Monastery from the 18th century</item>
<item> Gothic <hi rend="bold">Church of St. Michael Archangel</hi> from the 15th century, rebuilt in 1815 with a neo-Baroque rower from 1900.</item>
<item> The <hi rend="bold">Primates' Palace</hi></item>
</list>


<p>Visits to the Bronze Door and the cathedral's crypt are permitted only with a guide.</p>

<head>Museums</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> The Gniezno Archbishopric Museum, 2 Kolegiaty str., Phone : +48 61 426 37 78, open 9.00-17.30 (May-Sep, except Mondays) or 9.00-15.00 (Oct-Apr, except Sundays, Mondays and church holidays)</item>
<item> The Museum of Beginnings of The Polish State 1, Kostrzewskiego str. <ref target="http://www.mppp.pl"></ref>, mailto:info@mppp.pl, Phone : +48 61 426 46 41, open from Tuesday to Sunday 9:30 - 17:30 (May–Sep) or 10.00-17.00 (Oct-Apr). As the main part of the museum is an interactive show about the earliest polish history, one needs to make an obligatory advance booking!</item>
<item> The Municipal Museum - to be opened soon.</item>
</list>
</text>
