<text id="autogum_academic_doc211" title="On the Optimality of Interference Decoding Schemes for K-User Gaussian Interference Channels †" shortTile="optimality-interference" author="Ragini Chaluvadi, Madhuri Bolli, Srikrishna Bhashyam" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1099-4300/21/11/1053/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Wireless cellular networks have evolved significantly in terms of both channel-adaptive transmission and interference management. Early cellular systems were based on the <hi rend="italic">interference avoidance</hi> approach and relied on static resource allocation. However, current cellular systems allocate resources dynamically based on short-term channel state feedback. Interference decoding and cancellation are also implementable in today’s systems. The <hi rend="italic">K</hi>-user Gaussian Interference Channel (GIC) models a wireless network with <hi rend="italic">K</hi> transmit-receive pairs. The optimal transmission scheme for the <hi rend="italic">K</hi>-user GIC depends on the channel coefficients. Simultaneous channel-aware adaptation of multiple transmit-receive pairs requires a good understanding of the optimal scheme for each channel condition. </p>

<p>The capacity region and sum capacity of the general <hi rend="italic">K</hi>-user Gaussian Interference Channel (GIC) are not known. The 2-user GIC is the most well understood special case. The capacity region of the 2-user GIC under strong interference conditions was obtained in References. The sum capacity when the interference can be treated as noise was obtained in References. The sum capacity under mixed interference conditions was obtained in Reference. The capacity region of the 2-user GIC within one bit was derived in Reference using suitably chosen Han-Kobayashi (HK) schemes. </p>

<p>For the general <hi rend="italic">K</hi>-user GIC, the channel conditions under which Treating Interference as Noise (TIN) achieves sum capacity were obtained in References (Thm. 3) and (Thm. 9). The sum capacity of some <hi rend="italic">partially connectedK</hi> user GICs were derived in Reference under some channel conditions. <hi rend="italic">Z</hi>-like GICs, where the channel matrix is upper triangular with a specific structure, were studied in Reference, cascade GIC was studied in Reference and many-to-one and one-to-many GICs were studied in References. Some new outer bounds on the capacity of the <hi rend="italic">K</hi>-user GIC were recently derived in Reference. <hi rend="italic">Simple</hi> HK (S-HK) schemes with Gaussian signalling, no timesharing and no common-private power splitting, achieve sum capacity under the channel conditions obtained in References. S-HK schemes include the simple and practical TIN scheme and schemes that involve various levels of interference decoding and cancellation at each receiver as special cases. For the 2-user GIC, S-HK schemes are sufficient to achieve all known sum capacity results. For the <hi rend="italic">K</hi>-user GIC, we will generalize the sum capacity optimality results for the TIN scheme in References, to S-HK schemes. </p>

<p>There are some other related results for the <hi rend="italic">symmetric</hi> GIC or for GICs where the channel coefficients satisfy some equality conditions, respectively. For a <hi rend="italic">K</hi>-user interference channel, the sum capacity under a strong interference condition was obtained in Reference under conditions that include some equality conditions on the channel coefficients. Equality conditions cannot be satisfied if the channel coefficients come from continuous distributions. The symmetric <hi rend="italic">K</hi>-user GIC and many-to-one GIC have been considered in References, respectively. Unlike the other results discussed above based on S-HK schemes, in References, lattice coding and interference alignment are used to obtain the sum capacity when the interference is very strong. For the general asymmetric GIC, only approximate sum capacity and degrees of freedom results have been obtained using interference alignment. Other structured codes like coset codes have also been studied in Reference to show achievable sum rates better than those achieved by HK schemes for some 3-user interference channels. Interference alignment and structured codes are useful under channel conditions where HK schemes are not optimal. We identify channel conditions where S-HK schemes are sum capacity optimal for the <hi rend="italic">K</hi>-user GIC. </p>

<p>In this paper, we generalize the sum capacity optimality results for the TIN scheme in References to S-HK schemes. In particular, we derive two sets of channel conditions under which S-HK schemes are sum capacity optimal for general <hi rend="italic">K</hi>-user GICs. For the first set of channel conditions, we consider schemes where interference is decoded and cancelled before decoding the desired message. For the second set of channel conditions, we consider schemes where the one interference signal is jointly decoded with the message signal at one of the receivers. These two sets of channel conditions provide us new sum capacity results for several channel conditions under which sum capacity was not known earlier. Furthermore, existing results for the sum capacity of the 2-user GIC and some partially connected <hi rend="italic">K</hi> user GICs in References can be obtained as special cases of these results. To further understand the significance of the results, we evaluate, using Monte Carlo simulations, the probability that these channel conditions for sum capacity are satisfied for random wireless networks. Three different random network models are considered and we observe that this probability is significant under all three models. </p>
</text>
