<text id="autogum_reddit_doc116" title="The road to lvl100 in SSFHC: data and reflections" shortTile="road-lvl-ssfhc-data" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-04-30" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8g33k0" speakerList="#PPS2501" speakerCount="1">
<head>The road to lvl100 in SSFHC: data and reflections</head>
<sp who="#PPS2501">
<p>Hello fellow exiles! <ref target="https://www.pathofexile.com/account/view-profile/PPS2501/characters">I finished the grind to 100 in SSFHC on an ED Trickster</ref> the other day and recorded some data along the way. I thought I would throw it out on here to see how it compares to other people’s experience, and maybe start a discussion about a few topics too. (First, some background about me: I started playing in beta, farming docks and dying to multi-proj dogs. I came back at the start of Harbinger, and made it to 96 before dying. I died at 96 in Aybss as well, to a single rare Rhoa. I changed my playstyle a bit for this league and it paid off! In my personal life, I have a full time job and a family. I played about 3-4 hours a day on average. I usually don’t tell my wife much about the games I play, but I did this time. Despite her daily “didja die yet?” taunting, she helped me <ref target="https://imgur.com/a/bwjIx5Z">celebrate</ref>.) Here is the data I recorded. Note: this is not intended to be a scientific statistical analysis or anything. It’s just what I found, and what a typical player might encounter if they play to level 100 solo in hardcore.  <hi rend="bold">Currency:</hi>  I found 15 exalted orbs, 13 divine orbs, and 8 orbs of annulment on my trip to 100. I also picked up silver coins until the end (stopped running prophecies at around 95) and I have 710. Finally, I collected fusings until the end too. After converting jewelers, I found around 800 fusings going from level 97 to 98, 1400 going from 98 to 99, and about 1900 going from 99 to 100. Worth noting is that 5 of the exalts dropped going from 99 to 100. I also finished a set of Saint's Treasure for 2 more exalted.  <hi rend="bold">Gear:</hi>  I found every non-restricted unique in the game other than two: Koam’s Heart and Skyforth. Everything else dropped, including all flasks, build-enablers like Shavs, Tukohamas, Lycoside, etc etc, usually in multiple copies. I say this to embolden players who want to try SSF but are afraid they will be too limited on builds; you might not find the one item you want, but you’ll probably find something good! (And if you play long enough, you’ll find basically everything). On the other hand, I didn't see any un-corrupted 6-link drops.  <hi rend="bold">Breaches:</hi>  I collected 458 Tul, , 601 Xoph, 598 Esh, 214 Uul-Netol, and 89 Chayula splinters. I finished two sets of The Obscured, which gave a Tul and a Xoph breachstone.  <hi rend="bold">Abysses:</hi>  I found 47 Abyssal Depths, and 11 Liches (15 and 4, respectivley, going from 99 to 100). I never got the Shroud of the Lightless chest, but I did get a few pairs of 2s gloves.  <hi rend="bold">Bestiary:</hi>  I found 5 Tiger Bros and a jillion of the other spirit Pokémon.  <hi rend="bold">Maps and Zana:</hi>  I hit Zana8 at lvl98 and 20%. <ref target="https://imgur.com/a/qLlkKt7">Here is my map tab upon hitting 100.</ref> I recorded how many maps it took to go from 99 to 100(these numbers include wild Zanas): T10: 78, T11:196, T12:185, T13:234, T14:285, T15:13 (Total: 991) I elected to not run shaped T15s as almost all my previous characters have died in T15, hah! The few I did were wild Zanas. For 99->100, I would estimate less than a fourth of these maps had any elder/shaper influence on them, as I changed my atlas a bit to experiment with xp/hour and couldn’t be bothered to set up a new elder position. I found 3 Untained Paradises in the leveling process. That’s the majority of interesting data I collected - ask if you want to know anything else, or let me know if your experiences were different!  <hi rend="bold">Reflections/opinions</hi>  (*Warning: some of this might be controversial. Don’t get mad.*)  <hi rend="bold">The good:</hi>   <hi rend="bold"> PoE is an awesome game, and GGG is an awesome company. The grind from 97 to 100 was terrible and I really wanted to give up, because I had so much loot accumulated and I desperately wanted to reroll and try a new playstyle. </hi>  I improved a lot from Harbinger to now, and I have some ideas for how I want to improve next league too. I love that PoE has such a long learning curve.  <hi rend="bold"> Bestiary beasts - these guys were great. The yellows were better after the buff, but the reds really shined, because they didn’t just fall over, and they actually did damage to you when they were alive, making you move around the field. These and Abyss rares are great for the game I think, and I hope GGG adds even more high-health/damage resistant mobs in the next league. I had some epic fights where an abyss would path into a red beast, and I’d like to see more of that kind of stuff. </hi>  PoE is an awesome game (did I say that twice?)  <hi rend="bold">The bad:</hi>   <hi rend="bold"> Bestiary mechanics, from the nets to the crafting to the menagerie and everything in between. Enough has already been said about this, so I won’t beat a ~~stupid beast~~ dead horse. I hope GGG takes this as a learning experience. </hi>  Beasts when grinding to 100. I killed beasts all the way up to level 99 just because I liked fighting them, but skipping them (especially reds) netted better xp/hour so I skipped them thereafter. My dps is garbage, so maybe others had a different experience. On the other hand, I always got excited for abyss cracks and breaches, because while they did slow me down, it was to a much lesser extent, and added a lot of raw xp to the map. In a trading league I could catch the beasts and sell them for sextants or maps or something, but playing alone they gave no benefit. I hope future leagues find a way to award xp to players as well as (or instead of) items sometimes when we find a rare league mechanic. I just ran by the last 2 tigers I came across because they would have slowed me down - that’s a pretty poorly implemented mechanic in my opinion! (Or again, maybe my DPS just sucked too badly) * Challenge level in maps. Most of the danger in maps came from dead monsters -bearers, obelisks, nova boxes, DD, etc. Further, I would play 100 maps without taking much damage at all, and then <ref target="https://imgur.com/0NF6nK1">get hit like this</ref> and poop my pants... only to play 100 more maps before feeling real danger again. Players are incentivized to run easy maps, and currently, the challenge floor is too low and the ceiling too high. I feel that it’s weird I could get such good xp in a t10 map. I ate a few hits in t12 and t13 maps that would have killed me in a t15, but those hits come sooooo infrequently it puts me in a weird position where, because I know I can’t be “on my A game” for so many maps, I simply elected to run maps that I had a very low chance to die in. The game would be more fun if it was quite a bit harder more frequently, and less Gotcha!!Insta-gib!!! overall. * Abyss belts/jewels. I was pretty shocked when they announced they would keep these in the game, and lo and behold they have become ubiquitous. I dislike how these items are so strong that they render other items irrelevant. I wonder what the usage rates on Quartz and Silver flasks have fallen to, and a quick look through the SSFHC ladder leaderboards show basically everyone wearing a Stygian or a unique belt with few exceptions. Getting perma-onslaught and phasing is really easy on any character that kills monsters themself, which seems to go against the general design philosophy of making players choose which effects they get and needing to sacrifice something to gain them. Having them drop corrupted would have at least been a start.  <hi rend="bold">The ugly:</hi>  * Reddit whining did my head in. From "Nets are eating currency drops, I can't sustain alchs!!!" to "It's impossible to sustain red maps!!!" to "uber elder spawn position is too random and unfair!!!" people just seem so gosh-darn entitled. There are some really valid criticisms and concerns expressed on this board, but a lot of them are written in a way that read like children whining to their mommy. It's probably my fault for reading those threads though, I should just stick to the slipperyjim posts. So that's it! Come at me bros!</p>
</sp>
</text>
