<text id="autogum_news_doc779" title="Spanish King&apos;s &apos;shut up&apos; to Chávez becomes ringtone" shortTile="spanish-kings-shut" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-19" dateModified="2010-10-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Spanish_King%27s_%27shut_up%27_to_Ch%C3%A1vez_becomes_ringtone" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Spanish King's 'shut up' to Chávez becomes ringtone</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, November 19, 2007</hi></p>
<p>The angry "Why don't you shut up?" that King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juan%20Carlos%20I%20of%20Spain">Juan Carlos I of Spain</ref> uttered against <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Venezuela">Venezuelan</ref> President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hugo_Chávez">Hugo Chávez</ref> a week ago on Saturday has apparently reached a cult status in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Spain">Spain</ref> and Venezuela.</p>
<p>A mobile phone <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ringtone">ringtone</ref> remix of the quote text has been downloaded 500,000 times (generating some <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euro">€</ref>1.5 million revenues). The ringtone features a voice actor (avoiding legal issues) with beats and a loop effect emphasising the 'shut up'. A student group from the Venezuelan capital of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caracas">Caracas</ref> which opposes the President has downloaded the ringtone too. "It's a form of protest, it's something that a lot of people would like to tell the president. Now, whenever we call each other, that's what we hear," said Laura Solorzano, 21, in a telephone interview with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miami%20Herald">Miami Herald</ref>.</p>
<p>Today, the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Internet">internet</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/domain%20name">domain name</ref> of the quote was sold on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/eBay">eBay</ref> for €10,200 to a Spanish power seller called 'daikoku-design'. Juan Antonio Morales, 34, of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Almería">Almería</ref>, Spain, had reserved the domain shortly after news of the dispute broke. The video on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/YouTube">YouTube</ref> has been viewed over 1.3 million times, and there are numerous parodies using the quote. T-shirts and coffee mugs with the slogan are also selling well. The phrase has also become notable enough to merit <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/¿Por%20qué%20no%20te%20callas%3F">an article</ref> on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikipedia">Wikipedia</ref>.</p>
<p>At the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ibero-American%20Summit">Ibero-American summit</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santiago,%20Chile">Santiago</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Chile">Chile</ref> on November 10, Chávez called the Spain's former prime minister, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/José%20María%20Aznar">José María Aznar</ref>, a "fascist". Current Prime Minister of Spain <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/José%20Luis%20Rodríguez%20Zapatero">José Luis Rodríguez Zapatero</ref> tried to reply, but Chávez, although his microphone was switched off, kept interrupting him. The Spanish King first pointed a finger at Mr. Chávez, with the words "<hi rend="italic">Y tu</hi>" (and you). Then, while Zapatero still tried to reply, he said “<hi rend="italic">¿Por qué no te callas?</hi>” while making a gesture with his hand. Note that the King used the informal 'te callas' instead of the formal and polite third-person form. Zapatero finally  replied that "...in a forum where there are democratic governments ... one of the essential principles is respect. You can disagree radically, without being disrespectful." '</p>
<p>The rare outburst of the King has led to some disturbance in political relations between the countries; Chávez demanded an apology from the King but said he did not want a political conflict with Spain, while Spanish diplomats hope the situation will soon normalise. The Spanish PM stressed the incident was magnified by of the media attention it received. In statements to the press, the president of Brazil, Luiz Inácio Lula da Silva, minimized the incident between Hugo Chávez and the King of Spain: "There is little difference in opinion between King Juan Carlos and Chavez. There are many other differences between heads of State. Divergence is part of a democratic meeting."</p>
<p>The situation brings attention to changes Chávez has proposed to the Venezuelan constitution, which would lift the restriction on the number of terms for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/President%20of%20Venezuela">President of Venezuela</ref>.</p>
</text>
