<text id="autogum_whow_doc008" title="Handle the Empty Feeling After Finishing an Awesome Book" shortTile="handle-empty-feeling" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-04-12" dateModified="2018-01-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Handle-the-Empty-Feeling-After-Finishing-an-Awesome-Book" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Handle the Empty Feeling After Finishing an Awesome Book</head><p>You've just shut the back cover to a book that made you weep for the non-existence of fictional characters and their worlds. You've laughed, you've cried, you've become seriously emotionally involved, and now you're left with a void deep in your gut. Follow these steps to deal with finishing a great book.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Reread it! Flip back through the pages, settle in again with that wonderful book smell, and relive the experience. If you're not ready for that type of commitment, just rifle back through to your favorite passages, the best descriptions, or the most entertaining dialogues. <figure rend="Handle the Empty Feeling After Finishing an Awesome Book Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Highlight or sticky-note your favorites to make it easier the next time the mood strikes. Or better yet, copy down quotes or passages into a journal for future enjoyment. You'll thank yourself later.</item></list></item>
<item>Check out other books by the same author or of the same genre. If you love the book, chances are you're also in love with the author's writing style. Check the first few or last pages of your book for other works by that author, or do a quick Internet search. <figure rend="Handle the Empty Feeling After Finishing an Awesome Book Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>On the other hand, maybe it's the author's debut novel, or maybe you want something a little different. Try looking for books of the same or similar genre--you might just find your next favorite.</item></list></item>
<item>Participate in online forums! You're probably not the only person having a love affair with your book. Go online and search for forums centered around your title. People are passionate when they care about something; you might find that just reading or talking about it will bring the good feelings back! <figure rend="Handle the Empty Feeling After Finishing an Awesome Book Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Enjoy fan-made creations! There are some amazingly talented and undiscovered authors &amp; artists out there--go find them! <figure rend="Handle the Empty Feeling After Finishing an Awesome Book Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Visit one of the many fan-fiction sites and you're bound to find a few or a few hundred stories inspired by your favorite literature. This is a good way to get a taste for something that may have faded to black or was outside of a character's POV in the book itself.</item>
<item>Absorb the eye candy that is fan art. There's a lot of museum-worthy artwork floating around inspired by books. It's a breath of fresh air seeing other people's interpretations of something you both obviously enjoyed.</item>
<item>Head straight to YouTube. Fan-made videos inspired by novels are a must, and set to music, you may find some cool new songs along the way.</item>
<item>Make some of your own art or write stories! You don't have to be a master of your craft. After all, this is for you! Nobody else has to see your fan art or fan-fiction if you don't want anyone to.</item></list></item>
<item>Wait for the movie. In all honesty, what truly fantastic book is not made into a movie these days? Spend the time in between pondering what scenes might make it to the big screen, where it might be filmed, or who could be cast in your favorite roles. <figure rend="Handle the Empty Feeling After Finishing an Awesome Book Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do something else to fill the void! If all else fails, occupy yourself. The emptiness will fade with time. Season permitting, here are a few suggestions: <figure rend="Handle the Empty Feeling After Finishing an Awesome Book Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Go to the beach</item>
<item>Learn to skateboard</item>
<item>Bake a cake</item>
<item>Tour the Crayola factory</item>
<item>Build a snowman</item>
<item>Go to the gym</item>
<item>Play a sport</item></list></item></list>
</text>
