<text id="autogum_interview_doc460" title="part4_Former &amp;apos;Top Model&amp;apos; contestant Whitney Cunningham defends plus size models, celebrates the &amp;quot;regular woman&amp;quot;" shortTile="partformer-top-model" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-12-03" dateModified="2012-06-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Former_%27Top_Model%27_contestant_Whitney_Cunningham_defends_plus_size_models%2C_celebrates_the_%22regular_woman%22" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> How did they decide who was going to read the Tyra Mail for the episode? Was it random, planned, or was it really who 'discovered' the note each morning?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WC:</hi> It's definitely whoever discovered the note. Contrary to popular belief, the show isn't really scripted, planned, etc.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Were you forced to fake your excitement over Tyra Mail?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WC:</hi> We weren't forced to do anything, but I think that we all knew what our "expected" reactions were to the Tyra Mail readings. We had all seen the show, we all knew what the girls acted like when Tyra Mail was read, so we basically just kind of did the same thing. It's supposed to be an exciting moment, you know?</p>
<head id="Whitney_takes_more_fan_questions">Whitney takes more fan questions</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Do you still keep in touch with girls from your cycle? If so, who?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WC:</hi> Most definitely. I probably have hung out with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jaslene%20Gonzalez">Jaslene</ref> the most since we both live in New York together and that was my girl from the beginning. Diana and I still keep in touch. I still speak to Felicia every now and then, and Kathleen and I have been out on the town (she doesn't know it yet, but she's my new hairdresser too. That girl has got a fierce weave game.)</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> What were the pressures like in the house?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WC:</hi> I actually felt like the house was my refuge. It was home! It was where I could go and let my hair down, go to sleep, read a book, call my friends and family, etc. Some of the girls might say they hated it in the house, but I was really cool with mostly all of the girls so the house was somewhere I knew I could be and just be Whitney.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Is it common for agencies or clients to contact you after seeing the show? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WC:</hi> No way. Models come a dime a dozen. Established modeling agencies have no reason to go out and chase girls. I'd say it's more common for companies to contact girls about making special appearances, but not modeling agencies. It's up to you to go out and find a modeling agency.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> And do you get contacted from the guest designers that appeared on your cycle?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WC:</hi> I, personally, never have.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> A fan really wanted to know, "Was Dionne as funny as she was on the show?"</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WC:</hi> Dionne was really quiet and reserved. I was actually surprised to see how comedic she came off during her interviews.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> How did you feel when Dionne and Renee only got T-shirts as a prize for winning the acting challenge?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WC:</hi> Like I was the luckiest person in the world for winning the laser beam challenge. [laughs]</p>
</text>
