<text id="autogum_fiction_doc297" title="Hermione and Her Little Group of Serious Thinkers" shortTile="hermionelittlegroupserious" author="Marquis, Don" type="fiction" dateCollected="2019-10-22" sourceURL="http://gutenberg.readingroo.ms/7/7/776/776.txt">
<head>WAR AND ART</head>

<p>THIS war is going to have a tremendous in- fluence on Art -- vitalize it, you know, and make it REAL, and all that sort of thing. In fact, it's doing it already. We took up the war last night -- our Little Group of Serious Thinkers, you know -- in quite a serious way and considered it thoroughly in all its aspects and we decided that it would put more SOUL into Art.</p>

<p>And into life, too, you know.</p>

<p>Already you can see it on every hand how much serious purpose it is putting into lives that were merely trivial before. Even poor, dear Mamma -- and really, it would be hard to imagine a more trivial person than Mamma! -- is knitting socks.</p>

<p>She is going to send them to the Poles. She wanted to send them to the Belgians.</p>

<p>But I said to her, "Positively, Mamma, you are ALWAYS behind the times. Don't you know the Belgians are going out and the Poles are coming in?"</p>

<p>And, you know, it's been months since really Smart People have knit for the Belgians. The Poles are QUITE the thing now.</p>

<p>It's strange how great movements keep going on and on from mountain peak to mountain peak of usefulness like that, isn't it? -- changing their direction now and then as evolution itself does, but always progressing, progressing!</p>

<p>That is one wonderful thing about evolution -- it ALWAYS progresses.</p>

<p>When one thinks it over, one grows more and more conscious that the human race owes a great deal to Evolution, doesn't one?</p>

<p>WHAT could we have done without it?</p>

<p>It's as somebody said about something else one time -- if we hadn't had it, you know, it would have been necessary to invent it, though for the life of me, I can't remember who it was or what he said about it. Although likely it was Madame de Stael. We took her up once and it developed that she had said a most surprising number of things like that things, you know, that would be quite quotable if you could only remember them.</p>

<p>Isn't memory a wonderful facility, though?</p>

<p>I've always intended to go in for developing mine systematically and scientifically.</p>

<p>But I've never done it because I always forget whether I should order the book-shop people to send home a work on numismatics or a work on mnemonics. One of them is about money, you know, and the other is about memory. And once when I was shopping and thought I had it right it turned out -- the book did, when I got it home -- to be all about air and things. Pneumatics, you know! Wasn't it perfectly ridiculous?</p>

<p>But, of course, one learns by one's mistakes.</p>

<p>Have you seen dear Nijinsky?</p>

<p>We were discussing him last evening -- our little group, you know -- and decided that while he has more Personality than Mordkin he has less Temperament, if you get what I mean.</p>

<p>One of the girls said last evening, "Mordkin is more exotic, but Nijinsky is more esoteric."</p>

<p>And another said, "One of them shows intellect obviously mingled with spirit, but the other shows spirit occultly mingled with intellect."</p>

<p>Fothergil Finch said, "They are alike in their differences, but subtly differentiated in their likenesses, n'est-cd pas?"</p>

<p>Fothy has a simply delightful faculty of summing a thing up in a sentence like that, but it makes him very vain if you show you think so; so I put him in his place and closed the discussion with one remark:</p>

<p>"It is all," I said, "it is ALL a question of Interpretation."</p>

<p>And, quite seriously, when you come to think about it, it usually is, isn't it?</p>

<head>A SPIRITUAL DIALOGUE</head>

<p>Last night I met Hermione, And eagerly she said to me: "Thoughts from the ambient everywhere Electrify our worldly air."</p>

<p>"My soul," I said, "grabs off such hints As butter, whether pats or prints, Receives and holds all unaware Small strands of drifting, golden hair. But have YOU thought, O Maiden fair, O, have you thought profoundly of The psychic consciousness in crows? Or why the Malay when in love Wears rubber earrings on his toes?"</p>

<p>The lady shook her lovely head -- 'Twas coiffed divinely -- and she said: "Have you reflected on the part Primeval instinct plays in Art? It's simply wonderful the way Old things grow new from day to day!"</p>

<p>"That's true," I said, "I often ape The Ape to get my Art in shape -- And with the Simian going strong, Behold, another Rennysawng!"</p>

<p>"Perhaps," she said, "across the verge Of darkness, from the Cosmic Urge, The Light is speeding in bright waves, E'en now to show the way to slaves!"</p>

<p>"The thought," I said, "is cheerful -- but These Swamis WILL chew betel-nut!"</p>

<p>"Alas!" she said, "alas! too true! But oh! it's wonderful of you To sympathize and understand --" (She gestured with a jeweled hand) -- "The joy of being understood!"</p>

<p>"Our talk," I said, "has done me good."</p>

<p>WILL THE BEST PEOPLE RECEIVE THE SUPERMAN SOCIALLY?</p>

<p>WE'VE been taking up Metabolism lately -- our Little Group of Serious Thinkers, you know -- and it's wonderful; just simply WONDERFUL!</p>

<p>I really don't know how I got along for so many years without it -- it opens up such new vistas, doesn't it?</p>

<p>I can never think in the same way again about even the most trivial things since I have learned all about Protoplasm and -- and -- well, all these marvelous scientific things, you know.</p>
</text>
