<text id="autogum_interview_doc694" title="part2_RuPaul speaks about society and the state of drag as performance art" shortTile="partrupaul-speaks" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-06" dateModified="2019-02-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/RuPaul_speaks_about_society_and_the_state_of_drag_as_performance_art" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What keeps people from knowing the difference between what is real and important, and what is not?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RP:</hi>  Our belief systems.  If you are a Christian then your belief system doesn’t allow for transgender or any of those things, and you then are going to have a vested interest in not understanding that.  Why?  Because if one peg in your belief system doesn’t work or doesn’t fit, the whole thing will crumble.  So some people won’t understand the difference between a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/transvestite">transvestite</ref> and transsexual.  They will not understand that no matter how hard you force them to because it will mean <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/deconstruct">deconstructing</ref> their whole belief system.  If they understand Adam and Eve is a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/parable">parable</ref> or fairytale, they then have to rethink their entire belief system.</p>
<p>As to me being seen as whatever, I was more likely commenting on the phenomenon of our culture.  I am creative, and I am all of those things you mention, and doing one thing out there and people seeing it, it doesn’t matter if people know all that about me or not.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bat_for_Lashes_plays_the_Bowery_Ballroom:_an_Interview_with_Natasha_Khan">Recently I interviewed Natasha Khan</ref> of the band Bat for Lashes, and she is considered by many to be one of the real up-and-coming artists in music today.  Her band was up for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mercury%20Prize">Mercury Prize</ref> in England.  When I asked her where she drew inspiration from, she mentioned what really got her recently was the 1960’s and 70's psychedelic drag queen performance art, such as seen in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack%20Smith%20and%20the%20Destruction%20of%20Atlantis">Jack Smith and the Destruction of Atlantis</ref></hi>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Cockettes">The Cockettes</ref> and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paris%20Is%20Burning%20(film)">Paris Is Burning</ref></hi>.  What do you think when you hear an artist in her twenties looking to that era of drag performance art for inspiration?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RP:</hi>  The first thing I think of when I hear that is that young kids are always looking for the ‘rock and roll’ answer to give.  It’s very clever to give that answer.  She’s asked that a lot: "Where do you get your inspiration?"  And what she gave you is the best sound bite she could; it’s a really a good sound bite.  I don’t know about <hi rend="italic">Jack Smith and the Destruction of Atlantis</hi>, but I know about The Cockettes and <hi rend="italic">Paris Is Burning</hi>.  What I think about when I hear that is there are all these art school kids and when they get an understanding of how the press works, and how your sound bite will affect the interview, they go for the best.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You think her answer was contrived?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RP:</hi>  I think all answers are really contrived.  Everything is contrived; the whole world is an illusion.  Coming up and seeing kids dressed in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goth%20subculture">Goth</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hip%20hop%20subculture">hip hop</ref> clothes, when you go beneath all that, you have to ask: what is that really?  You understand they are affected, pretentious.  There’s nothing wrong with that, but it’s how we see things.  I love <hi rend="italic">Paris Is Burning</hi>.</p>
</text>
