<text id="autogum_academic_doc483" title="PD-L1/PD-1 Axis in Glioblastoma Multiforme" shortTile="pdlpd-axis-glioblastoma" author="Jakub Litak, Marek Mazurek, Cezary Grochowski, Piotr Kamieniak, Jacek Roliński" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1422-0067/20/21/5347/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 6. Angiogenesis in Glioblastomas</head>
<p>Features of glioblastomas are a high propensity to invade the surrounding tissues and extensive angiogenesis. They are characterized by a pathological vascular system with a dense network of winding vessels of different diameters, increased permeability, and with abnormally thickened basement membranes. These properties are often the cause of relapses and therapy failures because they hinder tumor access to cytotoxic chemotherapy. </p>

<p>Angiogenesis caused by the presence of a tumor is defined as the formation of new blood vessels based on existing ones, which can be visualized using ultra-high-field magnetic resonance angiography. The mechanism of this process is very complex. In GBM, the development of pathological vasculature is based on changes in adhesion molecules on the endothelial surface, the presence of an erratic basement membrane, a decrease in pericyte coverage, and a weaker binding of astrocytes to blood vessels. A common element for the large invasiveness and angiogenesis of glioblastomas is the loss of tumor cell boundaries with the surrounding microenvironment consisting of brain tissue, subarachnoid space, and blood vessels. </p>

<p>Angiogenesis occurs under the influence of various mechanisms, which we divide into hypoxia-dependent and hypoxia-independent. Hypoxia has been proven to inactivate prolyl hydroxylases. This increases the level of hypoxia-inducible factor-1α (HIF-1α), causing the release of vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) by glioma cells affected by hypoxia. The task of VEGF is to counteract oxygen deficiency by inducing vascular network growth. </p>

<p>In spite of this, hypoxia may not be the only trigger factor for angiogenesis. This applies particularly to the initial stages of carcinogenesis, when cell hypoxia is not yet severe. Regulation of VEGF secretion also takes place by a mechanism independent of hypoxia, involving dysregulated activation of mitogenic and survival pathways. This applies to phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase and Ras/mitogen-activated protein kinase. </p>

<p>The PD-L1/PD-1 axis may also have roles in regulating the level of VEGF mediating angiogenesis. In studies conducted by Shin et al., a positive correlation between PDL1 levels and VEGF expression was shown in 197 patients with renal cell carcinoma. Similar observations were noted by Song et al. The study was conducted in 64 patients with primary glioma. Also, they showed that PD-L1 expression levels correlated well with VEGF levels. However, not all studies agreed on this point. Research by Joseph et al. indicates the existence of a negative relationship between VEGF-related genes and the activity of the PD-L1/PD1 axis. A thorough understanding of the nature of this relationship requires further work. </p>

<p>EGF is another molecule with similar effects. It promotes tumor angiogenesis as well as an increase in cell motility and invasiveness. This is done by phosphorylating the EGFR receptor and activating further signaling pathways. It has been shown that both EGFR and its mutated form of EGFRvIII promote GBM angiogenesis. To allow vasculature growth and tumor invasion, it is necessary to reduce the integrity of the tumor microenvironment. The pathophysiology of this process is based on EGFR inducing an increase in the activity of some proteases, thereby causing the breakdown of collagen, fibronectin, and other basement membrane structures. The result is a loss of microenvironment integrity, an increase in tumor cell invasion into surrounding tissues and vessels, and an increase in angiogenesis. The proteases whose activity is influenced by EGFR include, among others:
<list>
<item>Serine Proteases</item>
<item>Matrix Metalloproteases (MMPs)</item>
<item>Cysteine Proteases.</item>
</list>
</p>

<p>Serine proteases are a large group of proteases which include tissue plasminogen activator (tPA) and urokinase plasminogen activator (uPA) with its receptor (uPAR). Their activation affects the degradation of the extracellular space by tumors, promoting their invasiveness. It has been shown that, the PAI-1 molecule mediates the regulation of the uPA/uPAR pathway in astrocytoma cells. Its expression is promoted by an increase in EGF and inflammatory cytokines. This results in greater uPA/uPAR activity, thus increasing tumor invasiveness. </p>

<p>Upregulation of uPA and uPAR is also achieved through the expression of the EGFR ligand transforming growth factor (TGFα). Studies confirmed that in malignant gliomas, both PAI-1 and EGFR activity correlate with higher tumor malignancy and worse prognosis for patients. </p>

<p>EGF also has a potential impact on another group of proteases, i.e., MMPs. They are a large group of enzymes whose effect is based on the regulation of metabolism and cell morphogenesis. Disruption of their function also affects the loss of cell integrity. It has been shown that the activity of certain matrix metalloproteases, such as MMP-2 (gelatinase A), MMP-9 (gelatinase B), MMP-14 (matrix metalloproteinase 14) is related to the pathophysiology of high-grade gliomas. It correlates with the severity of tumor invasion and its degree of malignancy. </p>

<p>Another group of proteases are cysteine proteases, examples of which are cathepsins. These include, among others, cathepsin B, involved in the degradation of the tumor microenvironment. Its expression (mRNA level) has been shown to correlate with EGFR expression level. It was also confirmed that its presence is increased in gliomas. The action of cathepsin B may be bidirectional. It promotes the degradation of the integrity of the environment of the tumor directly or through intermediate mediators such as uPA, MMPs, or plasmin. </p>
</text>
