<text id="autogum_reddit_doc002" title="I dont know what I am?" shortTile="dont-know-" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-03-22" dateModified="2018-05-31" sourceURL="http://redd.it/869wyd" speakerList="#Indoormam, #Orchipotamus" speakerCount="2">
<head>I dont know what I am?</head>
<sp who="#Indoormam">
<p>I am 15 years old. I dont believe I am a psychopath or a sociopath. I can feel a little guilt sometimes. The thing is that I feel pleasure or sexually aroused the way a psychopath would when I see physical suffering in an animal or another human being. However, when bullying or harassing someone mentally by making them feel bad, I do not feel the effect as much as from others' physical pain. A couple of years ago I had a buddy that moved to my area. I would physically and mentally abuse him. I would "play practice fighting" with him and would make him feel bad saying that he would be a loner if he pissed me off. I would tie knives to sticks and we would play games woth them where we dofge the knife. Once I threw it and it skimmed his right side, cutting him. It felt good to watch him on the ground. When i was in elementary school I remember stepping on a baby bird, watching it rip open and crunch under my foot, draining its blood. It also felt good. I am very careless. At school I get homework and 9 out of 10 times I will finish it late or last minute. I've noticed that this is because I dont have the motivation that other people do, or the focus. I rarely ever get stressed out. Whenever there is a big prohect due in a couple days I feel no stress whatsoever. Even when it comes to the last day. If I'm lucky I will start my work at 10 or 11pm on the last day and finish it at 4am on the day it is due. Other times I finish the work days or weeks after its due, or sometimes I never even do it at all. I want to get my act together so I dont fail my grade because I want to get a job and earn some money this year to save up for some things. I don't want to be homeless when I am older. I have held back my urge for seeking pleasure from others' pain in the recent years. I have shot a dog with bb guns. I have started to firmly elieve in karma, and that what goes, around comes around. This is why I no longer beat others up and steal their phones and money. I am considered "extreme" by others because I climb roofs of schools and jump off high places to feel something good like some adrenaline. I smoke weed sometimes. I can feel soft sometimes when someone snaps or gets angry at me. My temper is low and I dont get mad at others often like I see other people being angry. I used to be awkward in the crowd with others but I learned how to fit in and act casually like other people. I use breathing techniques to keep calm and my blood pressure down. I dont know what I am or if I have a disorder or disorders of some sorts. Please remember that I try to keep myself in line. I hope you guys dont "hate" on this much. Just drop the info if you know something about what is with me.</p>
</sp>
<sp who="#Orchipotamus">
<p>Disclaimer: I’m not a psychologist or a doctor. I am currently working on my Master’s in Forensic Psych and can only tell you what I think based on what I know of mental disorders and what I know based on what you have stated. </p>
<p>To me, it does seem as if you may have some psychopathic tendencies, namely lack of strong emotion, impulsive and thrill-seeking behavior, and a history of behavior that is harmful to others. However, the fact that you are addressing it now is a good thing. </p>
<p>The general consensus on the difference between psychopaths and sociopaths is that there psychopaths are born and sociopaths are made. There is strong evidence for genetic involvement in the development of psychopathy, and strong evidence for trauma and violence in the environment when it comes to sociopathic behavior. Sociopaths also are more likely to experience emotions such as remorse, although that is not true for everyone. Therefore, my first thought is how you have grown up and whether there are factors that may have contributed to a more sociopathic or antisocial disposition, such as growing up surrounded by crime or violence. You are still very young and are obviously aware of how you have developed thus far, which will be a great asset to you in the long run. Have you always felt this way, or is it something that has recently developed? Do you ever have explosive, violent, or destructive behaviors? Have you ever been diagnosed with conduct disorder or oppositional defiant disorder? (And btw you don’t have to answer any of these questions if you don’t want to—just throwing out things to think about) </p>
<p>There are also sexual preferences known as paraphilias, which are commonly known as fetishes or deviant sexual preferences. These include sexual sadism, pedophilia, necrophilia, cross-dressing, foot fetishes, and many more. It isn’t really known why some people develop paraphilias, but as long as no one is actively getting hurt, assaulted, or killed, or as long as no crime is being committed (like breaking into a morgue to have sex with a corpse or actually molesting a child downloading child porn), paraphilias are not necessarily harmful. Based on your description of arousal when others are in pain, it sounds like you may be a sexual sadist. In this case, there are safe and consensual ways to express this desire. BDSM (Bondage, Discipline, Sadism, and Masochism) is a fairly common practice for many people, and the BDSM community very much encourages safe and consensual practices. </p>
<p>I say, continue to examine yourself and why you feel the way you feel. If you feel therapy would be helpful, and if it’s an option for you, look into it, if only for the purpose of better self-understanding. Like I said, you’re young, and there is a lot of mental and biological development you have yet to go through. Good luck and I hope you are able to find peace with yourself.</p>
</sp>
</text>
