<text id="autogum_voyage_doc390" title="Fort Smith" shortTile="fort-smith" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=11893" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Fort Smith</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Fort Smith</hi> is in northwest <ref target="Arkansas">Arkansas</ref> and borders <ref target="Oklahoma">Oklahoma</ref>. It is the county seat of Sebastian County. The city has a population of 80,286 which makes it the second largest city in <ref target="Arkansas">Arkansas</ref> behind <ref target="Little%20Rock">Little Rock</ref>. It is located in the <ref target="River%20Valley">River Valley</ref> of Arkansas between the Ouachita mountains in the south and the Boston and Ozark mountains of the north and a gateway city to the <ref target="Ozarks">Ozarks</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>In 1817 Fort Smith was established as a military fort next to Indian territory in Oklahoma to keep the peace between the native Osage tribes and the recently relocated Cherokee groups. It is at the junction of the Arkansas river and the <ref target="Poteau">Poteau</ref> river at a place that early French explorers called Belle Point. The military fort was named after General Thomas A. Smith, the military's district commander. The military later relocated to nearby Fort Chaffee but the civilian settlers remained keeping the name of the fort and establishing a western frontier town that was often the last genteel layover for people from all walks of life before excursions into Indian Oklahoma including soldiers en route to the Mexican War in the Southwest.</p>

<p>Later Fort Smith became a popular stop for westward expansionists, gold rush diggers, and those seeking better opportunities due to the Great Depression and Dust Bowl of the 20th century.</p>

<p>Today as the second largest city in the state, the municipality and surrounding area is a major economic hub for the state of Arkansas with many major corporations with roots in the city still in operation and employing thousands. The downtown area and commercial zones are usually busy with voluminous traffic most days but beyond that you will find quiet residential zones and woods. Due to economic trends in the U.S. economy, some major factories and plants have closed and/or moved resulting in a swelling of the unemployed population and an uptick in local taxes.</p>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fort Smith Regional Airport</hi> (<ref target="Fort%20Smith%23By%20plane">FSM</ref> ). Service by American Eagle from Dallas/Fort Worth, and Delta Connection from Atlanta. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.nwara.com">Northwest Arkansas Regional Airport</ref></hi> ( XNA ) near <ref target="Bentonville">Bentonville</ref>, is about an hour and a half from Fort Smith.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.tulsaairports.com/">Tulsa International Airport</ref></hi> ( TUL ) (in Oklahoma) and <hi rend="bold">Little Rock International Airport</hi> ( LIT ) <ref target="http://www.lrn-airport.com/"></ref> are both about a two-hour drive away.</item>
</list>


<head>By train</head>

<p>Fort Smith does not have passenger rail service. The nearest cities with Amtrak stations are <ref target="Oklahoma%20City">Oklahoma City</ref>, which is the northern terminus of the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="http://www.amtrak.com/heartland-flyer-train">Heartland Flyer</ref></hi> to Fort Worth; and <ref target="Little%20Rock">Little Rock</ref>, which is served by the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="http://www.amtrak.com/texas-eagle-train">Texas Eagle</ref></hi> San Antonio - Chicago route.</p>
<head>By car</head>

<p>Fort Smith is at the intersection of Interstate 40, Interstate 540, and US Route 71. Approximate driving times are: 2 hours and 30 minutes west of Little Rock, 1 hour south of Fayetteville, and 3 hours east of Oklahoma City.</p>

<head>By bus</head>

<p>The <ref target="http://www.jeffersonlines.com">Jefferson Lines</ref> provides bus service to the east, west and north.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<p>The best way to get around and see Fort Smith is by car. Also, public transport is provided by <ref target="http://www.fortsmithar.gov/index.php/fixed-route-system-map">Fort Smith Transit</ref>. Although Fort Smith is Arkansas' second largest city, it is relatively compact and getting around shouldn't be much of a problem.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Miss Laura's Social Club and Visitor Center</hi>, 2 N "B" St., +1 479 783-8888, A house of ill-repute from Fort Smith's past, now a visitor center. It is listed on the National Register of Historic Places. This is a good starting point for any visit to Fort Smith.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fort Smith National Historic Site</hi>, South of Garrison Ave., near the Arkansas river. Parking and Park entrance near 3rd St. and Garland Ave. <ref target="http://www.nps.gov/fosm/index.htm"></ref> This site includes the original Fort sites and the reconstructed gallows of Hanging Judge Issac Parker.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Trolley Museum</hi>, 100 S. 4th, ☏ +1 479 783-0205 . Take a ride on the trolley past the Judge Parker court and the National Historic Site.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Belle Grove Historic District</hi>, 22 square block area north of downtown, On the National Register of Historic Places and has 25 restored historical homes.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fort Chaffee</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Chaffee Crossing</hi>, Hwy 22 <hi rend="italic">(east of Fort Smith)</hi> Former military fort with a rich history. Was built in 1941 and includes 22,000 acres. Elvis Presley was inducted into the military and started basic training there. The movies <hi rend="italic">Biloxi Blues,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">A Soldier's Story</hi> were filmed there.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Park at West End</hi>. - located in Fort Smith</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bowling World</hi>, 6100 South 36th Street, ☏ +1 479 646-5050 . Arkansas' largest bowling facility, with a whopping 72 lanes.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Jack's Skateland</hi>, 1413 Phoenix Avenue, ☏ +1 479 646-2538 . An ordinary roller skating rink, but with a unique distinction: it has the only artistic roller skating club in Arkansas.</item>
</list>


<head>Festivals</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fort Smith Air Show</hi>. The largest free air show in the United States held every October.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Riverfront Blues Festival</hi>. Annual in August each year. Free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Old Fort Days Rodeo</hi>. Annual event in late May/Early June.</item>
</list>


<head>Learn</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">University of Arkansas—Fort Smith</hi>, 5210 Grand Ave., +1 479 788-7000 <ref target="http://uafs.edu/"></ref> Fort Smith's local university branch.</item>
</list>


<head>Work</head>
<p>There are several major employers in Fort Smith, including Baldor Electric, Whirlpool Corporation, Rheem, Golden Ventures and Arkansas Best Corporation (ABF).</p>

<head>Buy</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Central Mall</hi>, 5111 Rogers Ave. <hi rend="italic">(Exit 8, I-540)</hi> This mall is the primary shopping mall in Fort Smith with shops, restaurants and movies.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Solemates On The Avenue</hi>, 505 Garrison Ave, ☏ +1 479 782-2313 , fax: +1 479 782-2313 . Women's clothing.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">T's Boutique</hi>, 507 N. Greenwood Ave, ☏ +1 479 484-5608 . Ladies' boutique.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Stringtown Yarn &amp; Fiber</hi>, 11 North 3rd Street, ☏ +1 479 434-2617 . Supplies for knitting, crochet, and handspinning.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>

<p>You will find the standard chain restaurants spread out for 2 miles on Rogers Ave. to the east of Interstate 540. They include Friday's, Applebees, Chili's, Outback Steak House, Red Lobster, Olive Garden, Arby's, Chick-fil-A, KFC, Wendy's, Schlotzsky's Deli, IHOP and Village Inn.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bella Italia Restaurant</hi>, 407. N. 8th St., +1 479 785-1550</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Calico Country</hi>, 2401 South 56th, ☏ +1 479 452-3299 . Family style restaurant with great cinnamon rolls.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Catfish Cove Restaurant</hi>, 1615 S. Phoenix Av, ☏ +1 479 646-8835 . Catfish, seafood and frog legs on a all you can buffet.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Doe's Steak House</hi>, 422 N. 3rd Street, ☏ +1 479 784-9111 . Great steaks and tamales.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Diamond Head Restaurant</hi>, 4600 Towson Ave., Suite 59, ☏ +1 479 646-2762 . A great Chinese dine-in restaurant.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hamburger Barn</hi>, 317 Garrison Av, ☏ +1 479 782-0233 . Design your own hamburger.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Jerry Neel's BBQ</hi>, 1823 S Phoenix Av, ☏ +1 479 646-8085 . Very good BBQ.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Art's BBQ</hi>, +1 479 452-2502, Even better BBQ.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Leoncia's</hi>, 1000 Garrison Ave (Downtown), ☏ +1 479 783-6500 . M-Sa 11AM-8PM. New Orleans sandwiches.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lin's Garden Chinese Restaurant</hi>, 7308 Rogers Ave, ☏ +1 479 484-5090 . Good Chinese buffet.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ole Feed House</hi>, 3801 Planters Rd, ☏ +1 479 649-9525 . Seafood and BBQ buffet, don't miss out on the homemade cinnamon rolls.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Rolando's Restaurante</hi>, 223 Garrison Avenue, ☏ +1 479 573-0404 . Nuevo Latino food in a Southern hospitality setting.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Taliano's</hi>, 201 North 14th Street, ☏ +1 479 785-2292 . Very good Italian food.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Varsity Sports Grill</hi>, 318 Garrison Ave, ☏ +1 479 494-7173 . TVs with all the games, pool and great homemade potato chips.</item>
</list>
</text>
