<text id="autogum_interview_doc055" title="part0_Wikinews interviews painter Pricasso on his art and freedom of expression" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-10-10" dateModified="2019-08-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_painter_Pricasso_on_his_art_and_freedom_of_expression" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews painter Pricasso on his art and freedom of expression</head>
 This article mentions the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Foundation">Wikimedia Foundation</ref>, one of its projects, or people related to it. <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> is a project of the Wikimedia Foundation.
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 12, 2015</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> interviewed <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia">Australian</ref> painter <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pricasso">Pricasso</ref> on his unique artwork created using his <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/penis">penis</ref>, and how his art relates to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Freedom_of_expression">freedom of expression</ref> and issues of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Censorship">censorship</ref>. He is to be featured at the upcoming adult entertainment event <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sexpo%20Australia">Sexpo Australia</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Melbourne">Melbourne</ref> this November 5 to November 8.</p>
<figure><caption>File photo of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pricasso">Pricasso</ref>, 2012. Image: Eva Rinaldi.</caption></figure>
<head id="Background">Background</head>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pricasso">Pricasso</ref> painting a portrait in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia">Australia</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sexpo">Sexpo</ref> (2012) Image: <ref target="http://www.flickr.com/photos/evarinaldiphotography/6846524602/">Eva Rinaldi</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>Pricasso is the stage name of Australian painter Tim Patch, in a nod to the artist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pablo%20Picasso">Picasso</ref> while using the word <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/prick#English">prick</ref>. Pricasso has been painting portraits using his penis for more than ten years.</p>
<p>Based in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia">Australia</ref>, Pricasso paints his artwork using his <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/buttocks">buttocks</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/scrotum">scrotum</ref> in addition to his penis. According to <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/640%20Toronto%20News">640 Toronto News</ref></hi>, Pricasso markets himself as "The World's Greatest Penile Artist".</p>
<hi rend="bold">I consider my work as satire just like late night TV, something that gives light relief to a serious subject.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pricasso">Pricasso</ref></p>
<p>He is able to create 20 paintings in one day. Pricasso also practices other styles besides portraits, including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/landscape%20painting">landscape painting</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nude%20(art)">nudes</ref>. Typically his portraits take him not more than 15 minutes to paint. He told Coconuts TV he chose to specialize in creating artwork in this manner because he felt it was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/niche%20market">niche market</ref>. </p>
<p>His fanbase is international; Pricasso has journeyed to locations including the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Holland">Holland</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">Germany</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brazil">Brazil</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mexico">Mexico</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China">China</ref> to paint portraits for people. Though he is willing to travel to display his talent, Pricasso told <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/In%20Touch%20Weekly">In Touch Weekly</ref></hi> most of his income is <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Internet">Internet</ref>-based.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> interviewed Pricasso about his artwork and asked for his thoughts on topics of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Censorship">censorship</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Freedom_of_expression">freedom of expression</ref>. We discussed what are considered appropriate forms of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/parody">parody</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/satire">satire</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/public%20figure">public figures</ref> — protected in the United States following the Supreme Court case <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hustler_Magazine_v._Falwell">Hustler Magazine v. Falwell</ref></hi>.</p>
<p>The interview touched upon a 2013 conflict which arose on our sister site for images and media, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikimedia%20Commons">Wikimedia Commons</ref>, when an image of a portrait of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikipedia">Wikipedia</ref> co-founder <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jimmy_Wales">Jimmy Wales</ref> painted by Pricasso was uploaded to the site. Wales called it "harassment" and a succession of deletion discussions ensued. We asked Pricasso about this as well as the different reaction from former-Mayor of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Cape_Town">Cape Town</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Helen_Zille">Helen Zille</ref>, who called his painting of her part of a "free society" where artists "exercise their freedom in unusual ways."</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Pricasso, thanks for agreeing to do this interview with Wikinews. </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Pricasso</hi>: Thanks for doing this, great questions.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> How long have you been painting in this particular fashion?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Pricasso</hi>: I first tried it over 10 years ago and realised it would be possible with practice to get as good with it but in a slightly more impressionistic style than I could with a brush, and I really liked the results, of course at first I had to work out the paint formula and what to paint on which was done by trial and error — and then finding somewhere to practice, which was a problem until I was invited to become a member of a Bondage club in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brisbane">Brisbane</ref>, my first patron. There I realised that there were so many people with totally different views on what is acceptable in society, and were always protesting over most <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Censorship">censorship</ref> issues.</p>
</text>
