<text id="autogum_whow_doc460" title="Perform Preventative Home Maintenance" shortTile="perform-preventative" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2017-09-12" dateModified="2018-02-24" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Perform-Preventative-Home-Maintenance" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Perform Preventative Home Maintenance</head><p>Maintaining that home is not something that most of us are prepared for and can sometimes be overwhelming. However, if planned correctly, home maintenance can be a rewarding experience. Home maintenance should be thought of like the maintenance of your car. To keep it performing at its best, it should be done on time, correctly and by someone who knows what they’re doing. The secret to lower out of pocket expenses and lowering the number of unplanned breakdowns is a good preventative regime. In the long run preventative home maintenance is much cheaper than reactive maintenance that you're unprepared for. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Doing Monthly Home Maintenance</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Check your water heater. Check pressure and temperature valves are working and pressure in line with owner’s manual guidance. A local plumber can do a more thorough inspection from time to time and fix more complex issues.</item>
<item>Check your water filters. Clean and wash these accordingly. These like air filters vary depending on device model. A qualified plumber can assist in inspecting or replacing filters as needed.</item>
<item>Unclog your drains. Inspect, unclog and clean as required. Checking for pests (animal or plant) to ensure no blockages. A pest control professional can be called to assist if you do spot an issue.</item>
<item>Clean your garbage disposal. Pass ice cubes through to clean blades. You can also mix in small amounts of vinegar to help with cleansing.</item>
<item>Check your air filters. Clean reusable filters as directed by supplier and replace non-usable filters. Life expectancy of these air filters varies, so be sure to check what the frequency ought to be for your filter/device. Clean filter means more efficient devices and a healthier home.</item>
<item>Keep your appliances in good shape. Inspect and clean as required home appliances. Replacing damaged parts as appropriate</item>
<item>Clean range top and burners</item>
<item>Deep clean laminate surfaces. Deep clean surfaces using appropriate tools and chemicals</item>
<item>Clean your tiles. Inspect and clean grouting.</item>
<item>Check your fire extinguisher. Inspect pressure gauge to ensure reading is in line with manufacturer requirements. Inspect nozzle is not blocked at tip.</item>
<item>Test your smoke detectors. Test using push button, and replace batteries if device is not operating. The entire device is usually changed out every 5 years.</item>
<item>Test your carbon monoxide detectors. Test using push button, and replace batteries if device is not operating. The entire device is usually changed out every 5 years.</item>
<item>Check your garage door. Test auto-reverse safety feature is working as intended.</item>
<item>Check your electrical wiring. It's always advised to get a licensed electrician to perform inspection on electrical wiring. For the obvious reason of safety, but also to ensure important issues are not missed and are caught by a trained person. Always hire a qualified electrician to perform electrical work.</item>
<item>Do an exterior and interior walk through. It's good practice to do a walk around of the exterior and interior of your home. Keeping an eye for anything that looks out of the ordinary. Such as, exposed wiring, cracked wall, water pooling where it shouldn’t be, etc. This will help you spot problem before they become major and costly.</item></list>
<head>Doing Annual Home Maintenance</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Go through this spring home maintenance checklist:
<list type="unordered"><item>Annual air conditioner (A/C) maintenance – a HVAC specialist should be called to perform the annual maintenance of you air conditioning system. Servicing means better performance and small problems can be captured before they become major.</item>
<item>Refrigerator maintenance – a HVAC specialist performing the above task can also take care of this. It includes cleaning of the condenser coils which collect dust and dirt. This task should be performed every season or quarterly if you have pets or allergies.</item>
<item>Attic inspection – you want to look out for pests, leaks, rot and fungus. The insulation should also be inspected for any abnormalities.</item>
<item>Landscaping – clear dead plants and trees and check trees and bushes have not grown to interfere with electrical wiring nor plumbing and pipes. You may also get a landscaper to work on areas where a professional is required.</item></list></item>
<item>Follow through with this summer home maintenance checklist:
<list type="unordered"><item>Heating system – during summer months its best to inspect and test your heating system. As winter approaches, you would have had time to fix any issues ahead of time and save money by planning in advance. Follow the owner’s manual as each system differs.</item>
<item>Plumbing systems – inspection plumbing systems including faucets, shower heads and toilet flush for leaks. Check water pressure in plumbing systems across the house. For any major plumbing problems hire a professional to avoid further damage. Fixing plumbing issues in the summer is better than frozen or burst piping in the winter.</item>
<item>Electrical systems – a simple check is turning off and on circuits. A qualified electricianshould be the only person to perform further intrusive testing.</item>
<item>Pest control – check interior and exterior of your home for pests (animal or plant). A pest control specialist can provide you with varying solutions should the need arise.</item></list></item>
<item>Complete the autumn/fall home maintenance checklist:
<list type="unordered"><item>Weather proofing – inspect the interior and exterior of your home to ensure weather proofing is intact. This includes the caulking, the finishes and seals around windows and doors. Most of these can be repaired with some DIY work, or you can hire a handyman to assist with the task.</item>
<item>Winter preparation – now is a good time to ensure you have sidewalk salt, snow snow shovels, etc. It’s also a good idea to flush out outdoor water faucets to avoid bust pipes.</item>
<item>Chimney – clean out chimneys.</item>
<item>Gutters and roofing – clean out gutters and check roof for cracks and get them sealed.</item></list></item>
<item>Finish up the year with the winter home maintenance checklist:
<list type="unordered"><item>Icicles – remove icicles from gutters and drainage systems to avoid breakages.</item>
<item>Snow – maintain good level of snow removal to avoid large build up. Always take precautions and follow best practices when shoveling snow.</item>
<item>Basement – during winter is the best time to inspect interior of your home and the much-needed attention can now be focused on the basement’s needs.</item>
<item>Plumbing – keep an eye out on your interior and exterior plumbing to avoid leaks and burst pipes.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
