<text id="autogum_interview_doc326" title="part13_John Reed on Orwell, God, self-destruction and the future of writing" shortTile="partjohn-reed-orwell" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-18" dateModified="2015-01-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Reed_on_Orwell%2C_God%2C_self-destruction_and_the_future_of_writing" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  I don't know if I have a most treasured, but I have a most precious possession.  Shall I go get it?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Yeah, definitely.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  This is a scraper.  A red chert scraper that I found walking along in the desert in New Mexico, about a year and a half ago.  Christmas, two years ago.  With two kids I work really hard--pretty much constantly.  But the thing about this is it has such an amazing energy, to hold it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Mmm.  I feel that, yeah.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  And the other--it may be prehistoric, it may be several thousand years old--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What makes it a scraper?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  This is what's interesting, to me--after you killed the meat, this is what you would use to scrape the inside of the flesh off the fur.  Scraping the fat or the gristle off the top of the meat.  And it's a reminder how much harder things were, you know?  Any time I'm feeling down on myself--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You could be scraping meat off bones.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  I could be scraping--and it was really like that, you know?  So--there's that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I have treasured possessions, but I also have treasured memories.  I found a suicide in the woods when I was thirteen: a kid my age, who was probably fourteen.  It's a treasured memory in some ways, one that’s lasted my whole life, and it's come back in a lot of ways.  On my MySpace profile, I make an allusion to that in my narrative.  I don't think people actually read that.  I think that people look at pictures, and then they move on.  But that's not really true.  I have been contacted by both that individual's younger sister, who was eight when he killed himself, and the girlfriend he killed himself over. Separately.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Yeah, people do read the stuff on there.  People do.</p>
<head id="On_raising_children">On raising children</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  The kids have made me a better writer.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Really?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Yeah, on the Shakespeare thing, I think part of what was holding me back from finishing it was--because I had written the first half in 2003--that I hadn't had kids.  I didn't understand the characters who had children.  I didn't really understand them.  And once I had had kids, I could approach them differently.  And it's great when kids appear in your work.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Gives it depth and also maybe opens you up to a new audience.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Yeah, I can't believe I didn't have any kids in my books.  I did have kids in my first novel, but not having kids or parents in your work is so weird.  It's just such a weird lack.  You often see literary books that don't have them.</p>
</text>
