<text id="autogum_news_doc356" title="AirAsia disaster: Bodies, wreckage found" shortTile="airasia-disaster" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-12-30" dateModified="2016-12-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/AirAsia_disaster%3A_Bodies%2C_wreckage_found" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>AirAsia disaster: Bodies, wreckage found</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 30, 2014</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Search%20and%20rescue">Search and rescue</ref> teams today began recovering bodies after debris from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Indonesia_AirAsia_Flight_8501">Indonesia AirAsia Flight 8501</ref> was spotted in the sea near <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Borneo">Borneo</ref>.</p>
<p>The flight from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Surabaya">Surabaya</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Singapore">Singapore</ref> vanished from radar screens early on Sunday morning over the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Java_Sea">Java Sea</ref>. 155 passengers and seven crew were on board. Most were <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Indonesia">Indonesians</ref>, with three <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/South_Korea">South Koreans</ref>, one <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Malaysia">Malaysian</ref>, one <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UK">Brit</ref> and one <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">French</ref> person on board.</p>
<p>An Indonesian naval ship today recovered at least three bodies. <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TvOne">TvOne</ref></hi> broadcast uncensored footage that was seen by distressed relatives at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Juanda_International_Airport">Juanda International Airport</ref>, where the plane departed. <hi rend="italic">TvOne</hi> has apologised and switched to blurred-out footage.</p>
<figure><caption>The crashed aircraft, photographed in April.Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Sabung.hamster">Oka Sudiatmika</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>Yesterday evening searchers stated they were using twelve helicopters, eleven planes, and 32 vessels. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia">Australia</ref>, Singapore, and Malaysia sent assistance with the search. Local fishing boats have also joined. The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US">US</ref>, UK, and France have been asked for help locating submerged remains. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/USS%20Sampson">USS <hi rend="italic">Sampson</hi></ref>, a US Navy destroyer, is due to join search efforts today.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/National_Search_and_Rescue_Agency">National Search and Rescue Agency</ref> head Bambang Soelistyo says a "shadow" on the seabed, spotted by the air force, is thought to be the wreck site. The nearest airstrip is in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pangkalan%20Bun">Pangkalan Bun</ref>, Borneo, about 160<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/kilometre">km</ref> away.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AirNav">AirNav</ref>, the Indonesian national <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/air%20traffic%20control">air traffic control</ref> (ATC) facility, yesterday said the aircraft was given permission to divert to avoid bad weather; the area was experiencing thunderstorms. That was at 6:12 local time. The flight crew next asked to climb from 32,000<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/foot%20(unit)">ft</ref> to 38,000ft. </p>
<p>Controllers conferred with Singapore and agreed the plane could climb as high as 34,000ft with another flight preventing a higher altitude. When they radioed permission at 6:14 they received no answer. The flight vanished from radar at 6:17. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/transponder">transponder</ref> ceased to be received a minute later.</p>
<p>A leaked screenshot from an ATC radar screen shows the flight ascending without permission through 36,000ft with a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ground%20speed">ground speed</ref> of 353<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/knot%20(unit)">knts</ref>. The aircraft would normally be travelling faster, with an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emirates%20(airline)">Emirates</ref> jet also on the screen showing a ground speed of 503knts at 36,000ft. An insufficient speed can cause an aircraft to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Aerodynamic_stall">stall</ref>.</p>
<p>Indonesian Pilot Iriyanto and French co-pilot Remi Emmanuel Plesel did not explain their request to climb. They have over 8,000 hours experience between them. They were flying <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Airbus%20A320-200">Airbus A320-200</ref> registration PK-AXC and serial number 3648, which was six years old. It last underwent maintenance in November. Management company <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doric">Doric</ref> own and lease the aircraft. The plane had accumulated 23,000 flying hours on 13,600 flights. It went missing around 40 minutes into a flight to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Changi_International_Airport">Changi International Airport</ref>.</p>
<p>Iriyanto's previous employers include the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indonesian%20Air%20Force">Indonesian Air Force</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merpati%20Airlines">Merpati Airlines</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Adam_Air">Adam Air</ref>. The 53-year-old also has ten years experience as a pilot trainer. He has flown for AirAsia for three years.</p>
<p>Investigations are to be led by the Indonesian <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/National_Transportation_Safety_Committee">National Transportation Safety Committee</ref>. France-based airframer <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Airbus">Airbus</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bureau_d'Enquêtes_et_d'Analyses">BEA</ref>, which investigates aviation mishaps in France, and the US <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/National_Transportation_Safety_Board">National Transportation Safety Board</ref> have all offered assistance.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Reuters">Reuters</ref></hi> spoke to an anonymous source within the investigation. "Why did [Iriyanto] request to climb at that stage?" said the source. "Should he have climbed earlier? Other aircraft were flying at a higher altitude in that area. How did the two pilots react to the weather? We are asking those questions." The source said radar, weather, and communications data was being analysed.</p>
<p>AirAsia owner Tony Fernandes said he has "full confidence in my[...] crew[...][Iriyanto] was extremely experienced". He added Iriyanto "came from the air force, one of their best graduates. He came from Surabaya, so he knows the area very well." Fernandes said it was "too early to speculate" about causes.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/AirAsia">AirAsia</ref> is based in Malaysia. 2014 has been a year of air disasters for the country; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malaysia%20Airlines%20flight%20370">Malaysia Airlines flight 370</ref> has been missing since March with 239 on board and in July <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malaysia%20Airlines%20Flight%2017">Malaysia Airlines Flight 17</ref> was shot down in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ukraine">Ukraine</ref> with 298 casualties. Both involved <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boeing%20777">Boeing 777</ref> aircraft.</p>
<p>AirAsia has a good record with no previous fatal accidents.</p>
AirAsia Emergency Contact Number: +622129850801Juanda Airport: [031] 8690945
</text>
