<text id="autogum_interview_doc553" title="part5_Ingrid Newkirk, co-founder of PETA, on animal rights and the film about her life" shortTile="partingrid-newkirk" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-20" dateModified="2018-02-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ingrid_Newkirk%2C_co-founder_of_PETA%2C_on_animal_rights_and_the_film_about_her_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  In your book <hi rend="italic">Making Kind Choices</hi> you have a chapter on bees.  Have you been following the recent development on the ‘<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colony%20Collapse%20Disorder">Rapture of the Bees</ref>?’  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  It’s fascinating.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do you think is happening with the bees?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  They think it’s a virus or a bacteria, don’t they?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That’s the thing: they can’t find any bee bodies.  Millions and millions have disappeared.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  It’s always fascinating how animals go off somewhere to die.  You don’t see a lot of dead birds anyway and there are birds in this city.  I don’t know.  Years and years ago I had not thought at all about bees and I went to a conference in upstate New York and there was a wonderful, gentle woman named Nermin Buyukmihci who talked about how violent bee keeping is.  I never thought about or known about this.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  In your book she calls them ‘honeystealers’</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  She talked about the wire brush tearing off the wings and the smoking out. I thought it was fascinating that she could even care about bees.  I thought to myself, “Well they make this <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Honey">honey</ref> and they make <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/propolis">propolis</ref> and everything else for their own nourishment and typical we come stomping along and take it all for ourselves, give them cheap sugar and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beesmoking">smoke</ref> them out and kill them.”  I thought that I don’t need honey.  It was just another thing where you think, “Why do I need this?”</p>
<head id="Religion_and_animals">Religion and animals</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Bible">The Bible</ref> talks about humans as custodians of the Earth, and the religious community is beginning to awaken to the notion that this means they need to be involved on environmental issues.  What is the religious community’s relationship to animal welfare?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  I think religion has departed so far from its origins that if you look at the root of all the large religions—<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christianity">Christianity</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Judaism">Judaism</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Islam">Islam</ref>—that you find there is always an admonishment to be kind to animals.  The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chief%20Rabbi%20of%20Israel">Chief Rabbi of Israel</ref> says no one should wear fur, for example.  There are other rabbis who say you can not keep <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kosher">kosher</ref> if you don’t keep away from eating meat.  In Christianity, being aware of the smallest sparrow who will fall—</p>
<figure><caption><hi rend="bold">"You look at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garden%20of%20Eden">Garden of Eden</ref> and that was a place where the lion lays down with the lamb and there is no slaughter."</hi></caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sam_Brownback_on_running_for_President,_gay_rights,_the_Middle_East_and_religion">Sam Brownback raised that exact same quote</ref> in my interview with him, that God cares even when the smallest sparrow falls—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  Yes!  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Compassion">Compassion</ref>!  I think people have departed.  Look at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ten%20Commandments">Ten Commandments</ref>.  How many people in organized religion abide by the commandments?  They lie, cheat and steal; covet their neighbors’ wives.  The fundamental root of religion is to be kind, compassionate, understanding; to reach out to others.  Religion is often a big business, but there are some people like the Reverend Andrew Lindsay in the U.K. who conducts animal rights lectures, and there are people in this country who are speaking out to say we need to consider the animals, but I think it is difficult.</p>
</text>
