<text id="autogum_interview_doc913" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Donald K. Allen, independent candidate for US presidency" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-10-02" dateModified="2009-03-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Donald_K._Allen%2C_independent_candidate_for_US_presidency" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="On_taxation">On taxation</head>
 HAVE YOUR SAY 
 Would Donald K. Allen be a good president? 
<ref target="//en.wikinews.org/w/index.php?title=Comments:Main_Page&amp;action=edit&amp;preload=Wikinews:Commentary_pages_on_news_events/body&amp;editintro=Template:Editintro_comments&amp;summary=create">Add or view comments</ref>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What will taxes be like if you become president?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Donald K. Allen</hi>: Both Senators Obama and McCain are talking about tax breaks.  The Tax Code is already 67,000 pages thick and nobody understands it.  Just dump it in favor of The Fair Tax Bill, which will repeal the 16th Amendment and do away with federal income tax.  In its place will be a National Sales Tax of roughly 18 to 23 percent on all new products, but I would not tax food or medicine and not give out a monthly "prebate," which is included in the current Fair Tax structure.  With wage earners keeping 25 to 35 percent of their income instead of the government taking it in income tax, the 18 to 23 percent will be more than affordable.</p>
<head id="On_immigration">On immigration</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What do you believe should happen to illegal immigrants in the United States?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Donald K. Allen</hi>:  Regardless of what country they come from, they should return to their home countries.  There are thousands of people around the world who are waiting for their legal immigration procedures to be finalized.  Why should they have to wait sometimes years before being allowed into the USA when others just walk in?  Return home and file for immigration the legal way.  No amnesty.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What do you believe should be done to secure the borders with Canada and Mexico?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Donald K. Allen</hi>:  We should complete a secure border fence on our southern border.  It will not be 100 percent effective, but people who live on our borders where there are fences will tell you that they do work.  Supplement the fence with unmanned aerial surveillance, infrared and motion detectors, and increased security personnel, and it will cut illegal immigration 95 plus percent.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What do you believe the guidelines on allowing immigrants into the US should be?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Donald K. Allen</hi>: Our immigration laws are sufficient.  They simply need to be enforced.  Follow the laws we have; they've worked for over 230 years.  They worked for my maternal grandparents, who immigrated from Lithuania around 1900.</p>
<head id="On_foreign_policy">On foreign policy</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What do you believe the government policy on war should be?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Donald K. Allen</hi>: Declaration of war should reside solely with Congress.  The President is allowed some leeway in small conflicts that require immediate action.  We should primarily be noninterventionist, but not isolationist.  In nearly every foreign conflict, it should be up to the United Nations to decide on military intervention, but we all know how ineffective the UN has been.  Why did the UN allow Idi Amin to slaughter his people, or the genocide in Darfur?  The whole world looks upon the UN as a paper tiger.</p>
</text>
