<text id="autogum_academic_doc567" title="A Graph Representation Learning Algorithm for Low-Order Proximity Feature Extraction to Enhance Unsupervised IDS Preprocessing" shortTile="graph-representation" author="Yiran Hao, Yiqiang Sheng, Jinlin Wang" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/9/20/4473/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Related Work</head><head> 2.1. Unsupervised Intrusion Detection Techniques</head>
<p>
Intrusion detection mainly includes signature-based intrusion detection and anomaly-based intrusion detection. In detail, signature-based intrusion detection is also known as rule-based intrusion detection. Signature-based intrusion detection has a high detection rate for known attacks, but has no ability to detect attack behaviors that are not in the rule base. Anomaly-based intrusion detection is also known as behavior-based intrusion detection. This algorithm has the ability to detect unknown attack behavior. Feature extraction based on accurately preprocessed network packets in anomaly-based intrusion detection is the basis for good performance. At present, it is easy to collect a large amount of unlabeled data in intrusion detection, and it is difficult to obtain a large amount of labeled data. Therefore, an unsupervised algorithm for intrusion detection has been introduced. </p>

<p>In recent years, there have been some studies based on unsupervised intrusion detection techniques. In 2007, Liu et al. used a hierarchical PCA model to detect intrusion behavior on the KDD99 dataset. In 2017, Gouveia et al. used RBM to detect intrusion behavior on the ISCX2012 dataset. In 2018, Farahnakian et al. used Deep Auto-encoder to detect intrusion behavior on the KDD99 dataset. The common point of the above studies is that the preprocessing ignores the similarity between network packets. Network packets with strong similarity relationship are closer in the similarity relation graph and have similar local proximity embedding. The preprocessing algorithm in the above studies ignores the similarity relationship between network packets, resulting in low accuracy of intrusion detection. Therefore, we introduce a graph representation leaning algorithm to solve the above problem. The network packet is preprocessed by using a graph representation leaning algorithm. In the proposed algorithm, the original features of the network packet are combined with the local proximity features describing the similarity relationship between the network packets as the input of the neural network. The proposed algorithm adds effective features by considering the similarities between network packets. </p>

<head> 2.2. Graph Representation Learning</head>
<p>
Graph representation leaning refers to the automatic extraction of proximity features of nodes in a graph.This algorithm has achieved effects in the application of approximate semantic classification of words, handwritten character classification and so on. The existing graph representation leaning algorithms are mainly the following, such as: Node2vec, Deepwalk, LINE. However, Deepwalk uses a simple unbiased random walk, which does not control the direction of random walks. Therefore, Deepwalk is easy to sample into the higher-order proximity range, which makes it impossible to accurately describe the local proximity features of the current node; LINE does not have the ability to simultaneously sample first-order proximity and second-order proximity, so the algorithm has limitations; Node2vec uses a random walk based on breadth first search (BFS) or depth first search (DFS) to explore the neighbor of the node. However, random walks based on BFS or DFS are blind searches. In other words, BFS lacks constraints on the range of random walks. Therefore, the random walk has the probability of sampling to the source node’s higher-order proximity, which makes it impossible to accurately extract the local proximity features of the source node that describe the similarity relationship between network packets. Therefore, we propose a node2vec with penalty for unsupervised automatic preprocessing. The proposed algorithm limits the range of random walks so that the sampling of random walks only occurs within the low-proximity of the source node. Therefore, the algorithm has the ability to obtain local proximity features that accurately characterize the similarity of network packets. </p>

<p>The literature that we surveyed has not used the unsupervised automatic preprocessing of graph representation learning algorithm with penalty in the field of intrusion detection. In the proposed algorithm, the original features of the network packet are combined with the local proximity features describing the similarity relationship between the network packets as the input of the neural network. The proposed algorithm adds effective features to get better intrusion detection performance. </p>
</text>
