<text id="autogum_interview_doc531" title="part4_Billy West, voice of Ren and Stimpy, Futurama, on the rough start that shaped his life" shortTile="partbilly-west-voice" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-13" dateModified="2013-06-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Billy_West%2C_voice_of_Ren_and_Stimpy%2C_Futurama%2C_on_the_rough_start_that_shaped_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  With computer animated voices?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  No, no, no. The stars will never go away. Let’s start there. If they have to become cartoons they will, because it’s a trend in the industry that these kinds of movies make more money than the regular ones do, for the most part. And they have no use for people that can create any kind of a character that’s shaped to whatever you want. That’s not useful in this case.</p>
<head id="Discovering_his_talent">Discovering his talent</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you remember a time in your life when you started recognizing your talent for being able to shape your voice into memorable characters?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  I never really noticed. It was just so natural to me. What I used to do was hide it because no one would say anything. When somebody’s mind got blown around you, they just resented you or would find a reason to not like you. What happened was, I grew up thinking that everybody could do it, but that they were just too cool to do it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You had a talent that seemed very trite to you, but very few other people could do it and you didn't recognize that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  Yeah. I didn’t even think that it was something that was gifted upon me. I mean I never thought of it like that. I thought everybody was exactly the same. And then I would hear that nobody was doing the kinds of thing that I did and I began to feel weird and I retreated for various reasons.  If I showed up at a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/softball">softball</ref> game I started calling the plays like an old-time sportscaster. You would think people would like that. But it would be met with, 'Who do you think you are?'</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You would feel a compulsion to do the plays in a voice?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  Yes. And I definitely wanted to get approval. Every kid wants that. But I would do those things because I heard the radio and I would listen to what people actually had to say. I just had my own approach to everything. Every little town weirdo like me grows up to come to the Mecca of weirdos, which is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hollywood">Hollywood</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I’m not a voice actor, but there’s times I’ll hear a person say a phrase. I covered the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Protests_mark_Ahmadinejad's_visit_to_Columbia_University">Iranian president speaking at Colombia</ref> for <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> and I watched these dueling ideologues who were normal citizens. One of them was this large black woman with a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bible">Bible</ref> yelling at this <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secular%20Jew">secular Jewish</ref> guy. I recorded these voices. She had one of those voices that I just couldn’t get out of my head. She just kept going, “You’re evil. You’re going to burn in Hell.” I found myself saying it aloud over and over and over again because her voice and what she said made such an impression on me that I wanted to imitate it. There was such a history behind that voice. She probably could have just said, “Buy <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tide%20detergent">Tide detergent</ref>,” and I would still be saying it over and over and over again.</hi></p>
</text>
