<text id="autogum_whow_doc421" title="Survive a Festival" shortTile="survive-festival" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2006-08-28" dateModified="2018-10-13" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Survive-a-Festival" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Survive a Festival</head><p>Glasto, Reading And Leeds or Download? Whatever festival you are going to, read this first!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Take wet wipes for your face. This is a good idea because the showers at such festivals are slightly unhygienic and probably cold. <figure rend="Survive a Festival Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't buy lunch, bring it packed in a cool pack. This will keep it well refrigerated and you don't have to sample any of the fast food stuff! But if greasy spoons (which are quite nice as an occasional treat) are your thing, then take plenty of money because food and drinks there tend to be twice as much as the average KFC where you live. <figure rend="Survive a Festival Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Stay Safe.</hi> If kids are coming with you, have them at your side at <hi rend="bold">all</hi> times. Children get lost very, very easily at these things and your child/children getting lost can be a very traumatic experience. But if you do get lost, make sure you report it to one of the festival tents; these should be located in several places around the grounds. Also, a good tip is to write your mobile/cell phone number on your child's arm so if someone can ring you if they find your child. <figure rend="Survive a Festival Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure all your money is in your wallet, not in your tent. It is a lot safer there than it is around the tent. <figure rend="Rebuild Credit After Bankruptcy Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you're crowdsurfing be very careful. 12% of A&amp;E emergencies are due to dangerous actions at gigs. <figure rend="Survive a Festival Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you are staying until Monday morning (this is possible at Roskilde), don't go too far away from your tent, or at least take all your belongings out of it. Sunday night is bonfire night, and they might trash or burn your tent! Alternatively, take it down (if it's worth taking down) and leave at a cloakroom or in a car. <figure rend="Survive a Festival Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Put a brightly coloured ribbon around your tent to know where yours is. Walking back from a gig in the middle of the night can be a real nightmare otherwise! <figure rend="Survive a Festival Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take plenty of dry clothes! Wet clothes can be horrific to wear the next day! <figure rend="Survive a Festival Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Most importantly <hi rend="italic">do not</hi> be tempted to try any drugs regardless of what other people say. They will completely wreck your festival experience and you could get very very much in trouble - by the police and getting hurt by using the drugs themselves. <figure rend="Survive a Festival Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't get too wasted, you will forget your experience and wake up with a banging hangover:(. <figure rend="Survive a Festival Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep a mobile (cellphone) with you at all times. <figure rend="Survive a Festival Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Never expect an on-site cashpoint. Either they're not there or the line is ten thousand miles long. <figure rend="Survive a Festival Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Last but not least, <hi rend="italic">have fun</hi>! <figure rend="Survive a Festival Step 13.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Keep kids safe</item>
<item>Keep a phone on you</item>
<item>Bring plenty of clothes</item>
<item>Take out cash before going on site..</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Wear a condom, and don't participate in oral sex. People don't wash, ok!</item>
<item>Don't try drugs</item></list>
</text>
