<text id="autogum_whow_doc200" title="Get Children to Eat a Healthy Breakfast" shortTile="children-eat-healthy" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-04-23" dateModified="2019-02-02" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get-Children-to-Eat-a-Healthy-Breakfast" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get Children to Eat a Healthy Breakfast</head><p>Having a healthy breakfast is a great idea and an excellent way to start anyone's day. Children have high nutritional needs. Giving your child a tasty, nutrious breakfast may help their memory during the day, provide them with energy and decrease their chances of developing conditions related to bad eating habits, such as type 2 diabetes. Get started at step number one below for how to get children of all ages to eat a healthy breakfast.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><figure rend="Sleep Naked Step 12 Version 2.jpg"></figure>Make time for breakfast. Eating a healthy breakfast should not be a special event, it should be a daily occurrence. This means your children have to get up out of bed and be at the breakfast table in time to have a morning meal and still have time to ready for school, nursery or college. As a parent, it is your job to have breakfast ready. Help your children get up in time to eat, or if they are old enough, make sure they have what they need to get up in time, e.g. alarm clocks, and enough sleep.</item>
<item><figure rend="Eat Healthy Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure> Provide a choice of breakfast foods. Children should be allowed to choose how much they eat, and what, as long as they choose from what is on offer and do eat something. If you have a fussy eater, serve a small amount of something you know they will enjoy to make sure they do eat something.</item>
<item><figure rend="Make Porridge Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure>Try offering wholemeal foods for breakfast. Whole grain oats made into porridge, whole grain cereals and whole grain breads are all good options. Eggs make a good nutritious breakfast if you have the time to prepare them. Fruit and yoghurt are good options too. Depending on the age of your child, offer whole milk. Think about what other cultures have at a morning meal to provide variety.</item>
<item><figure rend="Prepare Breakfast for a Toddler Step 1.jpg"></figure> Use breakfast to include some of the five plus portions of fruit and vegetables your child should eat everyday. It's easy to incorporate things like a small glass of freshly squeezed orange juice, a banana, some blueberries, a grilled tomato, some sauteed mushrooms, a half grapefruit, a tangerine, a portion of dried fruit, etc into a healthy breakfast based on something more substantial like cereal, toast or porridge.</item>
<item><figure rend="Prepare Breakfast for a Toddler Step 5.jpg"></figure> Avoid sugary cereals - even those aimed at children! Highly processed white bread, ready-made pancakes, pop-tarts, cereal bars and waffles are also unhealthy choices.</item>
<item><figure rend="Understand Positive Reinforcement Step 8.jpg"></figure>Be positive about breakfast instead of being negative. For example instead or saying "you need to eat your breakfast" say "it's important to eat your breakfast so you can be healthy and strong".</item>
<item><figure rend="Prepare Breakfast for a Toddler Step 16.jpg"></figure> Eat breakfast together as a family. Don't just make your kids eat a healthy breakfast - get yourself and your partner involved too. Maybe on weekends you and your family can all cook breakfast together - make breakfast fun.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Avoid getting into fights over breakfast, this turns breakfast into a bad time instead of a fun time.</item>
<item>It's OK to have an unhealthy breakfast once in a while as a treat.</item>
<item>Let your kids choose a healthy breakfast they like.</item>
<item>Try putting fruit on top of porridge or oatmeal.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Forcing your child to eat breakfast may lead to eating disorders later in life.</item></list>
</text>
