<text id="autogum_interview_doc346" title="part3_Wikinews interviews Jim Hedges, U.S. Prohibition Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-01-26" dateModified="2016-11-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Jim_Hedges%2C_U.S._Prohibition_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>For small parties, the states where they run has very little to do with where they have the most support and very much to do with which states have the easiest regulations.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What issues or policy stances form the basis of your campaign?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Inasmuch as beverage alcohol is our signature issue, I anticipate spending most of my time talking about the alcohol connection with various social problems:  public safety, public health, taxes, homelessness, spouse abuse,  child welfare, military preparedness, industrial efficiency, product quality, and so forth.</p>
<p>The platform most likely will address a lot of other things, but, let’s face it:  The Prohibition Party today is an exercise in living history.  We’re like the weekend warriors who put on costumes and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American%20Civil%20War%20reenactment">re-enact the Civil War</ref>.  The South is not going to rise again.  Neither is national prohibition going to come back (not, at least, in our lifetimes).  But in both cases, we think there are important historical lessons which ought not be forgotten.  And so, we soldier on against all odds.</p>
<p>Unless we stay on the message (of alcohol), our living history lesson will be lost.  </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Have you received any notable endorsements thus far?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> No.  Neither have I sought any.  </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">According to <ref target="http://weekendamerica.publicradio.org/display/web/2008/08/02/prohibition/"><hi rend="italic">Weekend America</hi></ref>, Vice-Presidential nominee Leroy Pletten was incapacitated following a stroke during the 2008 campaign. Have you chosen a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/running%20mate">running mate</ref>, and if not, will health be a factor in the decision?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> The Public Radio announcement appears to be a case of mistaken identity.  I have checked with Pletten, and no such thing happened.</p>
<p>I’ve been asking around.  I know who I’d like to have, but it’s still under discussion.</p>
<p>Health should enter into it.  We don’t need another <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ronald_Reagan">Reagan</ref>!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How often do you campaign, and how might that change should you win the nomination?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Very little campaigning, at this point.  I sent out a series of monthly postcards last year, presenting myself to the people on the Party mailing list.  There is also a (very rudimentary) campaign website – <ref target="http://www.hedges4-12.com">www.hedges4-12.com</ref>  I’m in touch with the people who will make the decision, at the Convention this coming June.</p>
<p>If I should receive the nomination, the website will have to be improved, and there will have to be press releases and some personal visits to states where we get on the ballot.  I’ll have to obtain advice on making more effective use of the internet. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Describe a typical day for Jim Hedges. How do you spend your time?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Before going to sleep each evening, I map out the following day in my mind.  Then, in the morning, I roll out (not too early), tend to personal care and a hearty breakfast, go to the other house (when my wife and I were married, 20 years ago, we each had a paid-for house, and it was convenient to keep both of them)  and tend to the pets.  The rest of the morning is spent dealing with paper mail and other clerical work.  In warm weather, afternoons are devoted to yard work and to gardening; in cold weather, I do household maintenance chores, work in the shop, work on the wood pile.  After supper, if there is not a rehearsal or a concert to go to, I practice half an hour on my tuba, then look at the internet or read.</p>
</text>
