<text id="autogum_interview_doc453" title="part7_US presidential candidate Duncan Hunter speaks to Wikinews" shortTile="partus-presidential" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-12-12" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_presidential_candidate_Duncan_Hunter_speaks_to_Wikinews" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> What about a pornographic website?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  Absolutely it would stop a pornographic website, if it is put out in a way that children should reasonably be expected to see it, it should be banned.  I think this: the trauma that is caused by young kids--and studies show now that a fairly substantial amount of young children are exposed to pornographic websites now--just sighing and saying that's life in modern America, well I think we should keep it from happening.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Are there any studies that show it actually harms children?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  Oh, absolutely!  That pornography harms children, there's lots of studies.  Don't you think pornography harms children?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> I've spent time in Europe, and I have spent time here.  It depends on what you are saying pornography is.  For instance, in Europe women are allowed to be bare-chested on the beach or in some places on television.  It doesn't seem to harm children there.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  If you've seen some stuff on the websites, it's much worse than that.  You're aware of that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Sure, but what is the bar for pornography, then?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  I think that is a matter of judgment and the court is going to have to make the judgment whether that is pornography or not.  That has always been a question of fact.  Once it is established and once a community--jurors--agree that it is pornography, that it has harmed children, then the people who spread it are going to be held accountable.  You have to be held accountable for what you throw out in front of children.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Would a website with a message at the front saying that a user confirms they are over 18 before they enter the site, would that be sufficient?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  I think that's a question of fact for the jury.  They are going to have to decide whether the key element in the Parents Empowerment Act, which is whether or not the purveyor of the pornography could reasonably expect children to see it.  It might be argued to the jury that there are movies which put restricted labels and don't go with the General Audience label because it actually intrigues young people and sometimes has proven to draw higher attendance if you have a label that implies there is something risque in the movie.  You've seen that.  Movie makers avoid the General Audience label.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> They also try to avoid the X label.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  It depends on what the case is and what the jury believes.  If the jury believes it was truly put in there in a way that the purveyor of the pornographic image set up his site to attract children, then he is going to be liable.  But it's a question of fact.</p>
</text>
