<text id="autogum_reddit_doc117" title="Insiders Tip #3: Prior address(es) of DeAngelo..." shortTile="insiders-tip--prior" author="Reddit community (see URL)" type="reddit" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2018-04-30" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="http://redd.it/8g39kt" speakerList="#saltwatertaff, #uncle_kevie" speakerCount="2">
<head>Insiders Tip #3: Prior address(es) of DeAngelo...</head>
<sp who="#uncle_kevie">
<p>First and foremost, I have read that the family of DeAngelo have been harrassed by members of the community of Reddit, Yelp, Facebook and the like. That's really not fair guys. While JJD is one of the worst people to ever set foot on the planet, his family (as well as former fiance, Bonnie) appear totally innocent, at least at this juncture. Therefore, I'm not going to post the full addresses, out of respect to those who currently reside at these properties. The second item to bear in mind is the fact DeAngelo and his wife Sharon appear to be separated for quite some time. Addresses below may only be attributable to Sharon, although, knowning they have three children (and grandchildren) together, could she ever have asked to him to keep an eye on her house while she was out of town...? Knowing him that would create the perfect moment to strike. What we should do is  <hi rend="bold">map out known addresses of rape incidents</hi>  to these streets. Can someone do that?  <hi rend="bold">Hackett Ave., Long Beach, CA 90808</hi> : as reported in the news, Joseph lived at this location for an undetermined period of time <ref target="http://losangeles.cbslocal.com/2018/04/25/golden-state-killings-families-sigh-of-relief/">CBS Los Angeles</ref>  <hi rend="bold">Teak Court - Roseville CA 95661:</hi>  this address is showing under searches for both Joseph and Sharon. Further details are being sought.  <hi rend="bold">Enright Drive, Citrus Heights, CA 95621:</hi>  (7/1/2008 - 10/16/2015) - information here shows Sharon lived at this location for roughly 7 years. Joseph deeded any interest he may have in the property to her, something commonly done in the lending industry to avoid one spouse claiming interest in the asset as community property.  <hi rend="bold">Sommerset Court, Roseville, CA 95661:</hi>  (10/29/1993 - 4/21/1998) - similar to Enright Drive (above) in that Sharon appears to have lived here while Joseph deeded any interest he may have in the property.  <hi rend="bold">N. Grove Drive, Monroe MI</hi> : a search ties this address to Sharon, which may mean Joseph lived here to. Details are fuzzy at the moment. I'm attempting to see if there are any similar unsolved crimes from the 70's - 80's that resemble DeAngelo. Could use some help if anyone has the time.  <hi rend="bold">Van Ness Drive, Roseville CA 95661</hi> : address is only tying to Sharon at this time; however, we haven't been able to rule out DeAngelo. </p>
</sp>
<sp who="#saltwatertaff">
<p>This is really bordering on posting too much details. What are we really gaining by getting this detailed? He lived in the current Citrus Heights for the better part of the last 30 years, as multiple neighbors have said. All you are doing is pulling up addresses associated with his family, which can only lead to trouble. Those websites are widely inaccurate, too (just search your own name and see for yourself). And try and search random people you know and tell me if you can find an address listed on there older than the late 70s. Whatever databases those sites are using to pull addresses seems to really only represent 1980s and more recent. Again, what are you really going to gain with those limitations? And more importantly, at what cost? </p>
<p>The Michigan address I can tell you for fact has nothing to do with him, but I won't share more than that. </p>
</sp>
</text>
