<text id="autogum_interview_doc500" title="part3_Eric Bogosian on writing and the creative urge" shortTile="parteric-bogosian" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-16" dateModified="2014-05-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eric_Bogosian_on_writing_and_the_creative_urge" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How do you break your novel out?  How do you get it to stand apart?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  I can't think about it that way.  It's very simple: All I do is write.  The way that I go about doing my work is very simple.  Imagine that somebody told you that some book was great, or a movie was great, or a play was great, but they didn't tell you anything about it.  You're on your way there to see it or hear it or read it, and in your mind, you're already imagining what it's going to be like.  That's what I write.  I write the stuff that I wish were up there because I'm so often disappointed.  I'm just trying to write the thing that would make me happy, you know, as if it was an audience of a hundred thousand of me out there, what they want to read.  That isn't necessarily what everybody does.  Although I think any successful writer has to be enthusiastic about their own writing.  But you might be writing in terms of, "Oh this is going to be my big blockbuster novel" or something.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Or if you have a particular point that you want to make.  Some sort of allegory or some sort of commentary on society.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  Well, my stuff reflects the way that I think and exist.  It's a little philosophical, but it's a little punk as well because I really believe in having a sense of humor about the world, even though it doesn't reflect in the way I talk.  I just think that humor in people and philosophy is what it's all about.  I push the envelope a little bit.  It just has to be entertaining, and entertaining can be whatever holds an audience.  And that might be ideas, or it might be sex or it might be terrific writing--obviously, I want my writing to be able to hold up when you read it.</p>
<head id="How_Bogosian_works_himself_into_his_writing">How Bogosian works himself into his writing</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Would you describe yourself as an experience junkie?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  An experience junkie?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Yeah.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>] Uh, well, I think I always did think of myself that way, but I know there's so many things that I actually don't know anything about.  I'm typical of the suburban know-it-alls that showed up in the cities twenty years ago and think of themselves as sort of on the edge, but really are so typical, it's embarrassing.  I went to college and I did <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drugs">drugs</ref> and I lived in the city, so big deal.  Me and ninety million other people did the same thing.  It isn't like I climbed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mount%20Everest">Mount Everest</ref> or I fought in a war or did anything genuinely interesting.  As fiction moves more and more toward this first-person type of fiction, then it becomes this competition of who's had the most exciting life or did the most exciting things.  And for me, that's not where literature comes from.</p>
</text>
