<text id="autogum_news_doc514" title="Explosions at Brussels airport and subway systems" shortTile="explosions-brussels" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-03-22" dateModified="2019-07-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Explosions_at_Brussels_airport_and_subway_systems" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Explosions at Brussels airport and subway systems</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 22, 2016</hi></p>
<p>At least 26 people, according to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Belgium">Belgian</ref> officials, have been killed and many more have been injured today following attacks on transport infrastructure in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brussels">Brussels</ref>, the capital of Belgium. Authorities have stated one of the explosions, at approximately 08:00 (Central European Time, UTC+1) in the check-in area at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brussels%20Airport">Brussels Airport</ref>, was likely conducted by a suicide bomber. There was a subsequent attack at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maelbeek/Maalbeek%20metro%20station">Maelbeek/Maalbeek metro station</ref>, very close to the offices of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/European_Commission">European Commission</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Council_of_the_European_Union">Council of the European Union</ref>.</p>
<figure><caption>Locations of the attacks in Brussels.  Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Rauletemunoz">Rauletemunoz</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>Passengers at the metro station were forced to walk along tracks to escape the blast. The Brussels metro system has been shut down.</p>
<p>Jef Versele, a business traveller intending to fly to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Rome">Rome</ref>, witnessed the events at the airport.  In remarks to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NBC_News">NBC News</ref>, he said, "There was dust everywhere, glass everywhere there was chaos. There were people on the floor everywhere. The roofing came down. It was quite a mess. [...] A lot of people were in panic. I saw a lot of blood, a lot of people were injured. People were crying, on the floor, covered by parts of the roofing. I saw a lot of leg injuries, a lot of people couldn't move anymore. There were quite a lot of people injured. In the departure hall — you saw people storming out, it was like run for your life."</p>
<figure><caption>File photograph of Maelbeek/Maalbeek metro station Image: bsubway.net.</caption></figure>
<p>All flights to Brussels Airport have been diverted and the airport has been shut down. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eurostar">Eurostar</ref> has stopped the international train service from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/London">London</ref> and the train company <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thalys">Thalys</ref> have shut down their entire network.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jan%20Jambon">Jan Jambon</ref>, the Belgian interior minister, said the country's alert level had been at maximum following the capture in Brussels of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salah%20Abdeslam">Salah Abdeslam</ref>, who is alleged to have been involved in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/November%202015%20Paris%20attacks">attacks in Paris on November 13, 2015</ref>.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles%20Michel">Charles Michel</ref>, Belgium's Prime Minister, described the attacks as "blind, violent and cowardly" and a "dark moment for our country".</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Donald_Tusk">Donald Tusk</ref>, the president of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/European%20Council">European Council</ref>, said: "These attacks mark another low by the terrorists in the service of hatred and violence"</p>
<p>The French President, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/François_Hollande">François Hollande</ref>, has held a cabinet meeting to discuss security. After the meeting, Hollande said "terrorists struck Brussels but it was Europe that was targeted". The French Prime Minister, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Manuel_Valls">Manuel Valls</ref>, said: "we are at war. We have been subjected for the last few months in Europe to acts of war."</p>
<p>British Prime Minister <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/David_Cameron">David Cameron</ref> has convened a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Cabinet_Office_Briefing_Room">COBRA</ref> meeting to discuss Britain's response. He said he was "shocked and concerned by the events in Brussels" and pledged Britain would do "everything we can to help". U.S. President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref> has been briefed on the attack during his trip in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Cuba">Cuba</ref>. The U.S. Embassy in Brussels has advised U.S. citizens in Belgium to not use public transport and to stay where they are.</p>
</text>
