<text id="autogum_interview_doc780" title="part0_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green Party candidate Brett McKenzie, London North Centre" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-06" dateModified="2008-10-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Green_Party_candidate_Brett_McKenzie%2C_London_North_Centre" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green Party candidate Brett McKenzie, London North Centre</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 6, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Brett McKenzie</hi> is running for the Green Party of Ontario in the Ontario provincial election, in the London North Centre riding. Wikinews' Nick Moreau interviewed him regarding his values, his experience, and his campaign.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>The first time I was able to vote, in the fall of the year I turned eighteen, I read the platforms and policies of the various parties and I voted Green.  After that, I started voting against people.  For ten years, I inflicted my vote on the politician I thought was the worst, rather than awarding it to the best.  I felt disenfranchised.  I really had no voice in this democracy, except to complain.  Finally, I had had enough, and voted the way I really wanted to.  After that, I was happy about democracy again.  I've been hooked ever since.  This is where the future is decided.  The exchange of ideas is vital to the process, and it's my favourite part.  Some of the highlights of this campaign have been conversations with competing parties.  I'm running in London North Centre because it's where I live, and I want to be able to shape the destiny of my neighbourhood, in my city, in my province.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>I've been a member of the Green Party since 2004, shortly after the last election.  I've been on the Constituency Association since shortly after I joined.  This is my first run for public office.  I have been involved politically with the Kinsmen and Kinettes of Canada: club executive, club president, district treasurer and secretary, and in a bid for national office, as well.  I understand democracy, the history of Ontario, the issues at hand, and the steps required to address those issues.  I understand other cultures and all faiths.  I understand people from all backgrounds.  I am intelligent.  I am a problem-solver.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why? What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?</hi></p>
<p>The incumbent is the biggest challenge, aside from the voters themselves.  The incumbent has the immediate benefit of name recognition and a pretty good track record in office.  She's done a pretty good job, just for the wrong party, in my opinion.  The voters are a challenge because some of the policies that the Green Party are suggesting seem strange and radical.  In some ways, they are: comprehensive, inclusive, and holistic.  We don't compartmentalize policy.  Transit=climate change=health=economy.  They're all connected.  And that's what makes any Green candidate the best option: we're thinking of the whole picture, now and tomorrow.  I understand this city.  I understand this province.  I understand the challenges we will face, and I'm prepared to take step NOW to address them.  I'm ready to educate the other politicians in Queen's Park, and tell them what I think needs to be done.  I also know that there's no such thing as a free lunch, and we're going to have to pay up, sooner or later.  i don't want my daughter to have to pick up the tab.</p>
</text>
