<text id="autogum_interview_doc704" title="part0_Canada&amp;apos;s Beaches—East York (Ward 32) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-beacheseast" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-21" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Beaches%E2%80%94East_York_%28Ward_32%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Canada's Beaches—East York (Ward 32) city council candidates speak</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday, November 3, 2006</hi></p>
<p>On November 13, Torontonians will be heading to the polls to vote for their ward's councillor and for mayor. Among Toronto's ridings is Beaches—East York (Ward 32). Four candidates responded to Wikinews' requests for an interview. This ward's candidates include Donna Braniff, Alan Burke, <hi rend="bold">Sandra Bussin</hi> (incumbent), <hi rend="bold">William Gallos</hi>, John Greer, John Lewis, <hi rend="bold">Erica Maier</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Luca Mele</hi>, and Matt Williams.</p>
<p>For more information on the election, read <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toronto%20municipal%20election,%202006">Toronto municipal election, 2006</ref>.</p>
<head id="Sandra_Bussin_(incumbent)"><ref target="http://www.sandrabussin.ca/">Sandra Bussin (incumbent)</ref></head>
<p>Sandra Bussin is the incumbent for Ward 32, Beaches—East York.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Describe the three most important issues in your campaign.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">1.  A Safe Environment and Our Community Health</hi>: Our community worked hard to shut down the incinerators at Ashbridges Bay Sewage Treatment Plant -the biggest producer of carbon-dioxide emissions and other significant airborne contaminants of all of the City's facilities. Today, our community's health and environment is greatly improved because of this shutdown.  However, the need to find a garbage solution for Toronto has placed a spotlight on this site as a potential location to build a garbage incinerator.  It is important that our community play an active role to ensure that thoughtful decisions are made.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">2. Planning Development Change</hi>: The popularity of the Beach has currently stimulated significant developer interest in land assembly.  The need to protect the unique character of our neighbourhoods is a critical and key concern. The new Official Plan will be put to the test in upcoming development applications verses the over-arching Provincial Planning Act and the Ontario Municipal Board.  I will push for "fine grain" tools that recognize the need to protect mature neighbourhoods, as well as to provide design guidelines to support the unique character of our neighbourhoods. Strongly enhancing community engagement in all aspects of the planning process is also needed.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">3. Clean Beach and Waterfront Renewal Strategy</hi>: The development of Toronto's waterfront is a key goal.  The success of the Beaches-East York community is attributed, in part, to its interface with Lake Ontario.  I am proud of the work underway to create significant landscape improvements at Ashbridges Bay which will be included in the expansive 750 acre Lake Ontario Park, stretching from the eastern border of Scarborough to the westerly edge of Etobicoke.  I will push the major clean-up of Coatsworth Cut/Ashbridges Bay.  The Balmy Beach area is also earmarked for the "Clean Beaches Strategy" which is a priority for me.</p>
<p>The major skateboard park I am building for the youth and young-at-heart is to be completed in 2007 -for all to enjoy.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What one election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> The looming garbage solution is a key issue.  The expansive lands at Ashbridges Bay and the Eastern Portlands are zoned to accommodate such heavy industrial uses.  Our community and I will be vigilant and active in the process underway by a citizen selected advisory team (CEAT) to recommend both the technology and the site for the method of disposing of the City's residual waste.</p>
</text>
