<text id="autogum_interview_doc319" title="part6_John Reed on Orwell, God, self-destruction and the future of writing" shortTile="partjohn-reed-orwell" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-18" dateModified="2015-01-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Reed_on_Orwell%2C_God%2C_self-destruction_and_the_future_of_writing" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1984%20(novel)">1984</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Yeah, there are people really pissed about 1984.   I've gotten a few emails from people saying that they want to go after 1984, suggesting that I should, but I don't know, I just didn't--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  All of a sudden you'll be in an Orwell genre:  Orwell criticism--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  For some reason, I don't mind that one as much.  There are also so many <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dystopia">dystopic</ref> . . .</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  1984 is used by both liberals and conservatives to attack each--each in different ways--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Yeah, 1984, as far as I know, doesn't have that history of being backed by the CIA.</p>
<head id="On_the_future_of_the_narrative">On the future of the narrative</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  As a writer there's always a desire to be innovative and original, but you can't be original anymore in writing.  It's very difficult.  Almost everything has been done.  I think that I read somewhere that the only genre of art that hasn't fully been mined is maybe poetry.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Yeah, could be.  Well--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How do you handle the challenge with wanting to be--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Well, there are new art forms that are forming.  The Internet is going to have much larger--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What are they?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Well, interestingly, the narrative forms.  Americans are extremely sophisticated in terms of narrative forms.  We see it in commercials, we see it on TV, we see it in movies.  But the narrative forms we're talking about are three acts, five acts, depending on how you want to look at it.  They're all based on a Christian model of sin, suffering, redemption; which is not a large model.  We've actually got a sophisticated view of a relatively narrow sort of idea of what narrative is.  But as the Internet enables larger shows--as TV, magazines and the Internet join--you're going to have much larger narrative structures.  Sort of like a soap opera, if you could imagine a soap opera that was on the Internet, where you would have a cross-section of narratives and could go in any direction at once.  The producers could get behind any narrative at once.  Essentially, then, what you've got is large epic structures, or Biblical structures, or mythological structures, where you have strains that interconnect--different storylines that interconnect and are often discrete--that make up a whole.  But the whole thing isn't three acts.  The whole thing isn't five acts.  It's an infinitude of three acts or five acts; it can be as big as you want.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Can you conceptualize that to an example?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Well, the best example I could give would be the Bible, or Greek mythology.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  On an Internet forum.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  I don't think that the technology is quite there yet.  It's close.</p>
</text>
