<text id="autogum_fiction_doc152" title="Bab: A Sub-Deb" shortTile="babsubdeb" author="Rinehart, Mary Roberts" type="fiction" dateCollected="2019-10-22" sourceURL="http://gutenberg.readingroo.ms/3/6/366/366.txt">
<head>``"Rags are royal raiment, when worn for virtue's sake."=</head>

<p>(I shall stop here and go down to the pantry. I could eat no dinner, being filled with emotion. But I must keep strong if I am to help Adrian in his trouble. The mince pie was excellent, but after all pastry does not take the place of solid food.)</p>

<p>LATER: I shall now go on with my recital. As the theater was almost empty, at the end of Act One I put on the pink hat and left it on as though absent-minded. There was no one behind me. And, although during act one I had thought that he perhaps felt my presence, he had not once looked directly at me.</p>

<p>But the hat captured his errant gaze, as one may say. And, after capture, it remained on my face, so much so that I flushed and a woman sitting near with a very plain girl in a skunk collar, observed:</p>

<p>"Really, it is outrageous."</p>

<p>Now came a moment which I thrill even to recollect. For Adrian plucked a pink rose from a vase--he was in the millionaire's house, and was starving in the midst of luxury--and held it to his lips.</p>

<p>The rose, not the house, of course. Looking over it, he smiled down at me.</p>

<p>LATER: It is midnight. I cannot sleep. Perchance he too, is lying awake. I am sitting at the window in my robe de nuit. Below, mother and Sis have just come in, and Smith has slammed the door of the car and gone back to the garage. How puny is the life my family leads! Nothing but eating and playing, with no higher thoughts.</p>

<p>A man has just gone by. For a moment I thought I recognized the footstep. But no, it was but the night watchman.</p>

<p>JANUARY 17TH. Father still away. No money, as mother absolutely refuses on account of Maddie Mackenzie's gown, which she had to send away to be repaired.</p>

<p>JANUARY 18TH. Father still away. The Hon. sent Sis a huge bunch of orchids today. She refused me even one. She is always tight with flowers and candy.</p>

<p>JANUARY 19TH. The paper says that Adrian's play is going to close the end of next week. No business. How can I endure to know that he is suffering, and that I cannot help, even to the extent of buying one ticket? Matinee today, and no money. Father still away.</p>

<p>I have tried to do a kind deed today, feeling that perhaps it would soften mother's heart and she would advance my allowance. I offered to manicure her nails for her, but she refused, saying that as Hannah had done it for many years, she guessed she could manage now.</p>

<p>JANUARY 20TH. Today I did a desperate thing, dear Diary.</p>

<p>"The desperate is the wisest course." Butler.</p>

<p>It is Sunday. I went to church, and thought things over. What a wonderful thing it would be if I could save the play! Why should I feel that my sex is a handicap?</p>

<p>The rector preached on "The Opportunities of Women." The Sermon gave me courage to go on. When he said, "Women today step in where men are afraid to tread, and bring success out of failure," I felt that it was meant for me.</p>

<p>Had no money for the plate, and mother attempted to smuggle a half dollar to me. I refused, however, as if I cannot give my own money to the heathen, I will give none. Mother turned pale, and the man with the plate gave me a black look. What can he know of my reasons?</p>

<p>Beresford lunched with us, and as I discouraged him entirely, he was very attentive to Sis. Mother is planing a big wedding, and I found Sis in the store room yesterday looking up mother's wedding veil.</p>

<p>No old stuff for me.</p>

<p>I guess Beresford is trying to forget that he kissed my hand the other night, for he called me "Little Miss Barbara" today, meaning little in the sense of young. I gave him a stern glance.</p>

<p>"I am not any littler than the other night," I observed.</p>

<p>"That was merely an affectionate diminutive," he said, looking uncomfortable.</p>

<p>"If you don't mind," I said coldly, "you might do as you have heretofore--reserve your affectionate advances until we are alone."</p>

<p>"Barbara!" mother said. And began quickly to talk about a Lady Something or other we'd met on a train in Switzerland. Because--they can talk until they are black in the face, dear Diary, but it is true we do not know any of the British Nobility, except the aforementioned and the man who comes once a year with flavoring extracts, who says he is the third son of a baronet.</p>

<p>Every one being out this afternoon, I suddenly had an inspiration, and sent for Carter Brooks. I then put my hair up and put on my blue silk, because while I do not believe in woman using her feminine charm when talking business, I do believe that she should look her best under any and all circumstances.</p>

<p>He was rather surprised not to find Sis in, as I had used her name in telephoning.</p>

<p>"I did it," I explained, "because I knew that you felt no interest in me, and I had to see you."</p>
</text>
