<text id="autogum_interview_doc046" title="part7_Wikinews interviews Rocky De La Fuente, U.S. Democratic Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-03-29" dateModified="2016-12-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Rocky_De_La_Fuente%2C_U.S._Democratic_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>We can also secure our borders without abandoning the values upon which our nation was built. We must first admit that our current system of immigration is broken and recognize that a wall is not the solution. Then, we must create a more intelligent, effective and efficient way of welcoming well-vetted immigrants to our borders and providing them with a clear pathway to citizenship.</p>
<p>With respect to national security: Again, Article I, Section 8 of the Constitution directs us to "provide for the common Defense . . . of the United States." However, it does not say that we must do it in a fiscally irresponsible way. It is not the government's responsibility to support a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/military–industrial%20complex">military–industrial complex</ref> simply because it has allowed that structure to become unduly important in the financing of our political parties.</p>
<p>Our focus should be to maintain a technological superiority over every other military on earth in as cost effective way as possible. Our ability to project force in a timely manner, when necessary, should be measured against current capabilities rather than historic principles. We do not need to maintain military bases abroad to the degree that we do. We can project force far more efficiently today than we could decades ago when many of those installations first were built.</p>
<p>We also have to recognize that the enemy has changed as has the weaponry. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cyber-attack">Cyber-attack</ref>s on infrastructure and financial services pose new threats as do terrorist attacks (as opposed to traditional invasion tactics). We need to build an intelligence capability that can identify and anticipate such threats and a counter-cyber capability that can defend against and respond to the delivery of any such attacks.</p>
<p>With respect to social equality: My number one priority as President would be to refocus our country on providing an equal opportunity to all with regard to jobs, education, healthcare, etc. We have established programs that make our leaders feel good but, from a practical perspective, fail to advance the cause of delivering an equal opportunity to all. As a result, we waste a great deal of time and taxpayer money on programs that have not improved our nation or the lives of its citizens. We need to return to the concept that "all men are created equal" and have the unalienable right to pursue happiness as they choose to define it. This does not mean that we all have to choose the same path or achieve parity in income, etc. It means that we should be given the tools and choices that are necessary to be able to pursue our individual definition of happiness.</p>
<p>"Equality" supports the right to be different; however, it demands the opportunity to choose which path to pursue. I would do everything in my power to provide every citizen with an equal opportunity to make that choice. This alone would stimulate our economy, resolve many of our social issues, and underscore the importance of the concept of individual Liberty that separates our country from any other nation on Earth.</p>
</text>
