<text id="autogum_bio_doc120" title="Claire Holley" shortTile="claire-holley" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-07-02" dateModified="2019-09-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Claire_Holley" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Claire Holley</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Claire Chamblin Holley</hi> is an American folk singer-songwriter from Mississippi. She has released eight albums and written for TV, Hollywood musicals and museums. She tours nationwide, is a wife and mom, and makes her home in Los Angeles, California.</p>
<head>Life and career</head>
<p>Holley grew up in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jackson,_Mississippi">Jackson, Mississippi</ref> where at an early age she learned to play the auto-harp, ukulele, piano, and guitar; though it was playing guitar that really piqued her interest. She has said, "I was never that good at playing piano, and maybe that's because I didn't practice enough, but I found the guitar fun to play. It wasn't a chore to practice."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Clairebio-1">[1]</ref> Her college days were spent in Chicago and, at the urging of a professor, she set to music a poem by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Blake">William Blake</ref>. Soon thereafter came Holley's first independent release, <hi rend="italic">Night Air</hi>. She moved to North Carolina where in 1999 she created a collection of traditional hymns and gospel songs which caught the attention of radio listeners and Yep Rock Records. She was signed and released her third album which was tilted simply, <hi rend="italic">Claire Holley</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Clairebio-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Holley has written songs for the cystic fibrosis foundation and the Metropolitan Museum of Art has used two of her arrangements of seasonal songs for one of their music releases. She was commissioned to write original music for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arlene_Hutton">Arlene Hutton</ref>’s play "See Rock City" which premiered at the Crossley Theatre in Hollywood September 2006 and LA Weekly magazine nominated her for "Best Original Music" for the LA Weekly theatre awards for the "See Rock City" songs.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Clairemusic-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Nienaber2008-3">[3]</ref> <hi rend="italic">Acoustic Guitar Magazine</hi> wrote, "Claire Holley is an observer, a romantic reporter from the backyards and front porches of the heartland."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Berkowitz2003-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Claire Holley has performed with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary_Chapin_Carpenter">Mary Chapin Carpenter</ref>, Kate Campbell, and Caroline Herring, and has composed music for <hi rend="italic">The Fence</hi>, an independent film which received the 2008 UCLA Directors Spotlight Award.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-imagejournal-5">[5]</ref> Mary Chapin Carpenter has said that Holley has an angelic style of writing.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> Two of her songs have appeared in the ABC TV show <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Men_In_Trees">Men In Trees</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> and she wrote the original music for the documentary <hi rend="italic">Looking For Lurch</hi> in 2008.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref>  Holley was also a member of Musette (formerly <hi rend="italic">Song Sirens</hi>), a group of female singer-songwriters that performed every so often in Sierra Madre, a little town in the mountains just north of Los Angeles.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-imagejournal-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>In 2013 she formed the group <hi rend="italic">Powdercoat</hi> and released a duet EP with fellow songwriter Kristin Mooney. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Huffington_Post">Huffington Post</ref> called it "one of the year's loveliest recordings."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> Holley announced that her eighth studio album, "Time in the Middle," will be released in June 2015. It was recorded at Sonic Temple studio in Ferndale, CA.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref></p>
<p>Ms. Holley now lives in the Los Angeles area with her husband, Chad.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Clairebio-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Discography</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Night Air (1997)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Clairemusic-2">[2]</ref></item>
<item>Sanctuary (1999)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Clairemusic-2">[2]</ref></item>
<item>Claire Holley (2001)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Clairemusic-2">[2]</ref></item>
<item>Dandelion (2003)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Clairemusic-2">[2]</ref></item>
<item>Live at St.Andrew's (2005) - w/Caroline Herring<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref></item>
<item>Hush (2008)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref></item>
<item>ABC's For Life (2012) - children's album<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref></item>
<item>Time in the Middle (2015)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref></item></list>
<p>Claire Holley has also scored the original music for Arlene Hutton's play <hi rend="italic">See Rock City</hi> which premiered at Hollywood's The Crossley Theatre.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>See Rock City, Original Music (2008)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[16]</ref></item></list>
<p>Partnered with Kristen Mooney in the band <hi rend="italic">Powdercoat</hi>.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Powdercoat (2013)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-17">[17]</ref></item></list>
</text>
