<text id="autogum_voyage_doc281" title="Incheon International Airport" shortTile="incheon-international" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=124021" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Incheon International Airport</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://www.airport.kr/ap/en/index.do">Incheon International Airport</ref></hi> (인천국제공항) ( ICN ) is South Korea's largest airport, its main international gateway, and the main airport of <ref target="Seoul">Seoul</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

 

<p>Incheon International Airport was built to the west of <ref target="Seoul">Seoul</ref> and opened in 2001, taking over from Seoul Gimpo airport as the nation's international hub. It has comprehensive connections to the South Korean capital, and is frequently rated in the top three airports in the world. The terminal buildings are architecturally very impressive, and are a pleasure to look at, even if you are not flying. The airport is beautiful, meticulously clean and well maintained. There's plenty to keep one occupied while waiting. The nearby city of <ref target="Incheon">Incheon</ref> is also a significant center of industry.</p>

<p>A second terminal was opened in time for the 2018 Winter Olympics.</p>

<head>Flights</head>

<p>Incheon is the main international hub for both Korean Air and Asiana, with many airlines flying from North America, Europe, Africa, Australasia and Asia.</p>

<p>The vast majority of domestic Korean flights, as well as some international flights to China, Japan and Taiwan, are still handled by <ref target="Seoul">Seoul</ref> Gimpo airport which is a short AREX train journey from Incheon airport.</p>

<p>There are a limited number of direct flights from Seoul Incheon to both <ref target="Busan">Busan</ref>'s <ref target="Gimhae%20International%20Airport">Gimhae International Airport</ref> and <ref target="Daegu">Daegu</ref> every day. These cost slightly more than the corresponding flights from Gimpo, but they are much more convenient if you arrive on an international flight. These are actually treated as international connections, and you will pass immigration later at your destination.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Terminal 1</hi>: All airlines not in Terminal 2</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Terminal 2</hi>: Air France, Delta, KLM, Korean Air (original members), Aeromexico, Alitalia, China Airlines, Garuda Indonesia, XiamenAir, Czech Airlines and Aeroflot (from October 28, 2018) - other Skyteam members will move after further expansion</item>
</list>


<head>A'REX (Airport train)</head>
<p>The <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.arex.or.kr/">A'REX</ref></hi> train link connects the airport to Seoul Station (for further connections to KTX high-speed services) and Gimpo Airport (most domestic flights), operating from 05:20 until 00:00. There are express services and all-stop services.</p>

<p>Express services to the city (every half hour) takes 43 minutes (Terminal 1 to Seoul Station) or 51 minutes (Terminal 2 to Seoul Station) and cost ₩8,500/₩7,000 (adult/child) (with WiFi available on board). There is a discounted fare of ₩7,500 for travelers taking a roundtrip within 15 days, groups of three and passengers of certain airlines (see <ref target="https://www.arex.or.kr/content.do%3Furl%3D%26amp%3BmenuNo%3DMN201503300000000003%26amp%3BcontentNo%3D%26amp%3BclientLocale%3Den_US%26amp%3BclientDevice%3DNormal">here</ref> for more details and discounts).</p>

<p>All-stop services (every 6 minutes as part of the Seoul Subway system) take an hour and cost ₩4,150 from T1/₩4,750 from T2. Many times it's faster to take the All-Stop than the Express train. </p>

<p>The All-Stop and the Express train leave from different platforms and have separate ticket booths. </p>

<p>Travelers coming from Seoul Station to Incheon need to enter the subway area with a T-money or single entry ticket to access the AREX platforms. The cost of the subway ticket is refunded when buying an AREX ticket. The All-Stop train requires a T-money card or single entry ticket, which require cash. The Express train can be paid with credit card as well. </p>

<p>If you are flying with Korean Air, Asiana Airlines, T'Way Air and Jeju Air you can check into your flight at Seoul Station before you get on the AREX Express train if you are there at least 3 hours before your departure time. Immigration officers are also on hand to stamp your passport, which means you are processed and can quickly go through the Diplomatic Departures entrance in Incheon Airport. Look for description of City Airport terminal below.</p>

<p>Travel time to Gimpo Airport is 28/35 minutes, with both services charging ₩3,100, making this the fastest and cheapest option for inter-airport transfer as well. </p>

<head>KTX</head>
<p>Korea's <ref target="high%20speed%20rail">high speed rail</ref> service (KTX) used to run to and from Incheon Airport, connecting directly to <ref target="Seoul">Seoul</ref> station, <ref target="Daejeon">Daejeon</ref>, <ref target="Daegu">Daegu</ref>, <ref target="Ulsan">Ulsan</ref> and <ref target="Busan">Busan</ref>. But this connection will no longer be operated from 2018. To use KTX to go to other cities, use AREX and go to Seoul Station or Bus No. 6770 (₩15000) to Gwangmyeong Station. Bus 6770 is operated by Korail, and there is a ₩3000 discount for the combined ticket for KTX and the bus. </p>
<p>City Airport Terminal at Gwangmyeong Station can be faster than going to Seoul station, so look for description below.</p>

<head>Maglev train</head>

<p>In February 2016, Incheon opened a new maglev line to the area around the airport and adjacent Yongyu Island. It begins at the airport A'REX station and ends at <ref target="Yongyu">Yongyu</ref> Station, stopping at the airport administration building, long-term parking lots, and a couple of other places along the way. With a maximum speed of , it is not exactly in the same class as the Shanghai Maglev, but may still be interesting to tourists wishing to ride a maglev for the first time or those in town for an event on Yongyu. The train runs every 15 minutes from 09:00 and 18:00, and fares are free for the first few years after opening.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>When traveling into Seoul with a lot of luggage or are heading to southern parts of Seoul (eg. Gangnam) then the airport buses are a very good option. <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.kallimousine.com/">Limousine buses</ref></hi> (₩15,000 to/from city for one way, ₩6,500 to/from Gimpo Airport (domestic flight)) travel directly to major areas and big hotels in Seoul, while public buses (₩8,000-9.000) will take you to major transit hubs. If you're visiting for the first time, it's worth paying a bit extra for the limousine bus. For either bus type, consult the big maps or staff to figure out which route best suits your needs; you can then find the shuttles outside 1st floor arrivals (if possible get this information from your hotel before arriving). Or simply, walk out and ask the many ticket sellers (they are wearing vests) which bus goes to your hotel because if it's a popular one or in a popular area, they'll surely know which you'll need. It's best to buy tickets at any of the ticket gates near the bus arrival area but you can also pay the fare using won or a T-Money card if you have one. The limousine bus drivers are extremely friendly but don't count on them knowing too much English. There are maps inside the buses letting passengers know which stops are upcoming and these are also announced in Korean and English. Pressing any of the red buttons inside signals to the driver you want off at the next stop.</p>

<p>You can purchase and recharge a T-Money card at the GS25 store which is located at the end of the arrivals area, next to "International Arrivals F" exit.</p>

<p>If you have a late flight and plan on getting into Seoul via bus, make sure you get out to the curb as soon as you can. The last buses run shortly after the last flights land. If you miss your bus, you'll be stuck paying for a taxi, as the trains will stop running too.</p>

<p>There are also inter-city and express bus to cities other than Seoul. </p>
</text>
