<text id="autogum_interview_doc639" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Flame about special effects at New Zealand&amp;apos;s Rock2Wgtn festival" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-22" dateModified="2014-04-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Flame_about_special_effects_at_New_Zealand%27s_Rock2Wgtn_festival" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Flame about special effects at New Zealand's Rock2Wgtn festival</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 7, 2008</hi></p>
<figure><caption>File photo of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kiss%20(band)">KISS</ref>, who headlined night one. Image: <ref target="http://www.flickr.com/photos/wok/">Wok</ref>.</caption></figure><p>Across <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Easter">Easter</ref> weekend <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wellington">Wellington</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_Zealand">New Zealand</ref> was host to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rock2Wgtn">Rock2Wgtn</ref>, an international two-day <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/hard%20rock">hard rock</ref> festival. Large crowds showed up at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Westpac%20Stadium">Westpac Stadium</ref> to see the various acts. The world has never seen an event of this kind before, and New Zealand has never had any kind of major rock festival or multi-day music festival.</p>
<p>Day one featured three theatrical acts. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Finland">Finnish</ref> band <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lordi">Lordi</ref>, known for their monster costumes, opened the night. They were followed by the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">US</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/shock%20rock">shock rocker</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alice%20Cooper">Alice Cooper</ref>, whose themed set included the horror theatrics regularly associated with him and a hanging stunt he recently restarted after a gallows collapse nearly killed him two decades ago. The night was headlined by the distinctively costumed band <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kiss%20(band)">KISS</ref>, complete with their famed black-and-white makeup.</p>
<p>The first major act on the stage on day two was the American hard rock/<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/glam%20metal">glam metal</ref> band <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poison%20(band)">Poison</ref>. After Poison, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Kingdom">British</ref> act <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Whitesnake">Whitesnake</ref> took to the stage and performed their set to the crowd. British-born American rocker <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ozzy%20Osbourne">Ozzy Osbourne</ref>, who, as well as a solo career, fronts the world-famous <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black%20Sabbath">Black Sabbath</ref>, was the second night's headline act.</p>
<p>The festival's entertainment did not stop at the six main acts. There was also support performances from three New Zealand bands - The Symphony of Screams, The Valves and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sonic%20Altar">Sonic Altar</ref>. Their sets were accompanied by a special effects package from award-winning studio <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Weta%20Workshops">Weta Workshops</ref>, who are known for their work on movies such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Lord%20of%20the%20Rings%20film%20trilogy">The Lord of the Rings film trilogy</ref>. This came in the form of 'Drusila the Dragon', which rose up to a height of six foot and wigspan and moved for the audience, shining lasers from its eyes and breathing red smoke. Flame Fire Productions were hired to put on a fire show featuring several dancers alongside the performers. Also performing were six local guitarists and a group of '<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/zombie">zombie</ref>' cheerleaders.</p>
<p>Wikinews was able to secure two exclusive interviews with those responsible behind the scenes for putting on such a show. Weta Workshop's Philip Sharpe, who supervised the project and Milly Bea, current manageress of Flame Fire Productions, discussed their roles. In the first installment, Milly Bea tells us about "a definite highlight" for Flame and lets us know everything from her thoughts on Gene Simmons's tongue to just how much kerosene it takes to put on a fire show at a rock fest.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews (Blood Red Sandman)</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How did you come to be involved with Rock2Wgtn?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Milly Bea:</hi> We came to be involved thru a recommendation from one of the stunt guys, unfortunately I am not sure who? Someone Holly Wademan had met in past years. Then Rok2Wtgn contacted us and we began liaising from about December.</p>
</text>
