<text id="autogum_interview_doc342" title="part2_Wikinews interviews former Congressman Virgil Goode, Constitution Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-02-27" dateModified="2017-02-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_former_Congressman_Virgil_Goode%2C_Constitution_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>I also would have supported <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Offshore%20drilling">drilling off the coast</ref>.  For example, I'm from Virginia. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virginia%20General%20Assembly">Virginia General Assembly</ref> has passed resolutions indicating its support of drilling off the coast of Virginia. I would have allowed that instead of blocking it like President Obama.  I will also support the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keystone%20Pipeline">Keystone Pipeline</ref>, which he is opposing. We need to have lower energy costs. Lower energy costs would do most to enhance jobs, and most little small initiatives done by the president in other areas.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Would you have ordered the killing of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Anwar_al-Awlaki">Anwar al-Awlaki</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Yemen">Yemen</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Goode</hi>: I don’t know if the president ordered that.   Our national defense forces found him and he was fought in parcel with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Osama_bin_Laden">Osama bin Laden</ref>, and I think they did the right thing in taking out Osama bin Laden.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">But was it right to take out Anwar al-Awlaki?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Goode</hi>: Let’s make sure we’re taking about the same one. Is that the guy in Yemen?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Yes, the internet <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Al-Qaeda">al-Qaeda</ref> leader.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Goode</hi>: I would want more intelligence than I have available to me right now.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Well he was an American citizen, so do you believe that we should treat American citizens overseas that are considered to be dangerous differently than others?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Goode</hi>: Well let me ask you this:  Did President Obama order his killing?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">I believe he did.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Goode</hi>: Well I want to know more facts before I say yes or no.  Did he do an act that effectively renounced his citizenship? He may have and may have committed treason. So to answer that precisely, I would have to have more. I would have to be privy to the intelligence briefings that president Obama had and that the members of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20House%20Permanent%20Select%20Committee%20on%20Intelligence">House</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Senate%20Select%20Committee%20on%20Intelligence">Senate intelligence committees</ref> had. And I would like to also get the opinions of the members of the intelligence committee of the House and the Senate. And I would want to ascertain whether he was truly a citizen of the United States. Was he a dual-citizen? You don’t know that do you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">I don’t know for sure.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Goode</hi>: Yeah, I don’t either so I want to know more facts before I could say flat out one way or another.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Okay, let’s talk more about foreign policy.  In 2002, you voted to authorize the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iraq_War">Iraq War</ref> and you supported the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraq%20War%20troop%20surge%20of%202007">troop surge in 2007</ref>.  However, the Constitution Party platform opposes undeclared wars, and supports a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20non-interventionism">non-interventionist</ref> foreign policy. Do you stand by your previous votes?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Goode</hi>: Now if I was voting on that situation in 2008, 2009, 2010, I would have said we shouldn’t go forward unless Congress debates the issue and declares war.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">As president, how would you address the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuclear%20program%20of%20Iran">nuclear situation</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iran">Iran</ref>?</hi></p>
</text>
