<text id="autogum_interview_doc779" title="part1_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Communist Party candidate Shona Bracken, Toronto Danforth" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-07" dateModified="2007-12-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Communist_Party_candidate_Shona_Bracken%2C_Toronto_Danforth" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly?</hi></p>
<p>To immediately raise the minimum wage, and immediately increase social assistance and OSDP rates above the poverty line.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are the property taxes in your riding at a fair level for the amount of services received in the municipality?</hi></p>
<p>We believe that residential property taxes should be restricted to cover only municipal services, police, fire, etc., and not include education, healthcare, housing, transit and so on. These costs should be uploaded to senior levels of government. This would allow for a 75% cut in property taxes to homeowners and tenants.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How can the province lead the way in stimulating job creation?</hi></p>
<p>There are many ways to create meaningful employment – expanding public healthcare, a universal system of affordable, publicly-run childcare, environmental services, reforestation, etc. But there must also be an emergency program to rescue manufacturing jobs in Ontario through public investment and by introducing plant closure legislation that has real teeth. Reducing the workweek to 32 hours with no loss in take-home pay would also generate hundreds of thousands of new jobs.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What are your views on the mixed member proportional representation (MMP) referendum?</hi></p>
<p>I will be voting “YES” to MMP. I am in favour of full proportional representation, one without minimum thresholds. However, this is an important first step towards a more comprehensive electoral reform – away from the undemocratic ‘first-past-the-post’ system.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Of the decisions made by Ontario's 38th Legislative Assembly, which was the most beneficial to your this electoral district? To the province as a whole? Which was least beneficial, or even harmful, to your this riding? To the province as a whole?</hi></p>
<p>This is a complicated question – I think that the increase in funding for both health and public education were probably the most important accomplishments of the McGuinty government in trying to reverse the extreme damage wrought by the previous Harris Conservative government to these vital services. On the other hand, McGuinty and the Liberals have continued to concede to the pressures to privatize healthcare through the expansion of P3 hospitals (under another name); they have also failed to introduce a comprehensive needs-based funding formula for our schools.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">You are running as a candidate for the Communist Party. A lot of people say that Communism is a dead idea or fear that a Communist government would implement some sort of repressive dictatorship. What do you say to this?</hi></p>
<p>Actually, the ideas of socialism are making a comeback in countries all around the world, as more and more working people feel the impact of spreading poverty and increasing social disparity as a result of neo-liberalism and so-called “globalization” policies. Look at what is happening in Venezuela, in Bolivia, Ecuador and other countries in Latin America. Even in European Communist Parties like the Greek and Portuguese CPs are growing again.</p>
</text>
