<text id="autogum_bio_doc105" title="Tranquility Bass" shortTile="tranquility-bass" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-07-09" dateModified="2019-03-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tranquility_Bass" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Tranquility Bass</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tranquility Bass</hi> was the stage name of <hi rend="bold">Michael Adam Kandel</hi>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> (1967/1968 – May 17, 2015) an American musician whose music has been variously categorized as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ambient_house">ambient house</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trip_hop">trip hop</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Funk_rock">funk rock</ref>. He released various singles during the 1990s, followed by his first full-length album, <hi rend="italic">Let The Freak Flag Fly</hi>, in 1997 on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Astralwerks">Astralwerks</ref>.</p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>Kandel was born and raised in Chicago. He learned to play guitar and keyboards at age 12. By the age of 15 he had begun to record experimental electronic music in his bedroom.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-reader-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Musical career</head>
<p>Kandel attended the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chicago_Academy_for_the_Arts">Chicago Academy for the Arts</ref>, after which he moved to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Los_Angeles">Los Angeles</ref> in the early 1990s to attend <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CalArts">CalArts</ref>. It was there that he met <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tom_Chasteen">Tom Chasteen</ref>, with whom he started the <hi rend="italic">Exist Dance</hi> label in 1991.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Bush-4">[4]</ref> The two released several singles, including some as Tranquility Bass, later that year.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-reader-3">[3]</ref> In 1993, Kandel released the single "They Came in Peace", which has been described as an ambient-house classic and appeared on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mo'_Wax">Mo' Wax</ref> compilation album <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Headz">Headz</ref> the following year.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Bush-4">[4]</ref> After the duo released this and a few other singles, including two songs that appeared on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FFRR">FFRR</ref> compilation album, <hi rend="italic">California Dreaming</hi> in 1994,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> Chasteen left Tranquility Bass and relocated to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tucson">Tucson</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-shapiro-6">[6]</ref> Tranquility Bass's touring bassist, Matt Lux, is also the bassist for Chicago-based band <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isotope_217">Isotope 217</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<head><hi rend="italic">Let the Freak Flag Fly</hi></head>
<p>In 1994, after Chasteen's departure, Kandel joined Tyler Vlaovich to record an album on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lopez_Island">Lopez Island</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Washington_(State)">Washington</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cmj-8">[8]</ref> More than two years later, the album was released as <hi rend="italic">Let the Freak Flag Fly</hi> on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Astralwerks">Astralwerks</ref> Records.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-shapiro-6">[6]</ref> Kandel sometimes ceased talking to people, or from using his voice, for two or three days on end during the recording process.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cmj-8">[8]</ref> According to <hi rend="italic">Billboard</hi>, the album led to Kandel developing "a cult following that spans several genres beyond the dance realm."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> The <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Los_Angeles_Times">Los Angeles Times</ref></hi> gave the album a rating of three stars (out of four) and described it as "the electronic progeny of acid rock."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> It was also reviewed favorably by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greg_Kot">Greg Kot</ref>, who described it as "a grand journey through nearly a century of recorded music, a densely layered montage of electronic manipulations and live instruments made under conditions that were certainly unusual."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref> The album contained the song "We All Want To Be Free", made more popular by its airplay on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MTV">MTV</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amp_(TV_series)">Amp</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref></p>
<head><hi rend="italic">Heartbreaks &amp; Hallelujahs</hi></head>
<p>After a long hiatus from studio recording and rumors of drug abuse, Kandel returned in 2012 with a sophomore effort entitled <hi rend="italic">Heartbreaks &amp; Hallelujahs</hi>. The album was completed on March 21, 2002. Kandel reportedly tried to have the album released on multiple labels, only to have each of them fold after he sent it to them.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref> The album ended up being released on <hi rend="italic">Exist Dance</hi>, although it is readily available in digital format on Amazon MP3 and iTunes. The album is mostly new material with the exception of yet another remix of an early days single, "Mike's House".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref> Kandel seemed to try to get away from the idea of being an electronic musician (although some of the album still has electronics), with a dose of various types of rock such as funk rock and surf rock.</p>
<head>Death</head>
<p>Tranquility Bass died on May 17, 2015, aged 47 in Chicago suburb Buffalo Grove, IL.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref> A cause of death was not released to the public.</p>
</text>
