<text id="autogum_whow_doc492" title="Look Cool in School Uniform (Muslim Girls)" shortTile="look-cool-school" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2016-10-10" dateModified="2016-10-10" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Look-Cool-in-School-Uniform-%28Muslim-Girls%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Look Cool in School Uniform (Muslim Girls)</head><p>Are you a Muslim who wants to look cool in their school uniform? This article may just help you. We will give you tips and loads on how to achieve this!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Choose the right clothing</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Your school may give you loads of different options in uniform like wearing trousers or skirts and clothe like that. Choosing true right one if very important.
<list type="unordered"><item>Wear trousers! Trousers are probably the best clothing to wear when you have a headscarf on your head as wearing a skirt may look a bit odd.</item>
<item>Make sure your clothes fit you nicely! You don't want to be wearing big clothing as it might look a bit odd as well!</item>
<item>Depends how it would look on you wear the right type of trousers. Maybe try on some skinny trousers or see if you can wear jeans (this is if your allowed to wear these type of clothes.)</item>
<item>Maybe roll up the sleeves of the shirt your wearing under your blazer (if your wearing a blazer.) It will make you look quite laid back about everything.</item></list></item>
<item>Another important thing about your clothing is your shoes. Shoes can make a very huge difference in your clothing!
<list type="unordered"><item>Wear trainers! If your school allows you to wear these type of stuff then do take advantage of it. Wearing trainers can really make you look so much cooler. But make sure you choose the right type of trainers because some trainers may just ruin your look. Maybe get a friend or someone to give their opinion about the trainers you choose and how they think it looks with your uniform.</item>
<item>If your school is very strict maybe wearing trainers won't be allowed. The best type of shoes for you would probably be shoes that aren't like those ones where it's got that one strap that you open and close. Also ballet type of shoes aren't that good as well. Get one where like you can't see the like top of the feet if that's how you say it.</item>
<item>Wear socks! But not any type of socks. Get socks that go up to your ankle. They do make you look cooler if they are seen.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Get a good bag</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Getting the right bag is very important! You must carefully choose one that will shout out your personality!
<list type="unordered"><item>Get a Nike, Adidas or like Ellesse bag. These companies bags can make you look much cooler because they are quite popular companies and will make you look good. These type of bags are good for people who are sporty.</item>
<item>Get a a quite basic bag. Maybe with pastel colours if you wanna maybe give that cute touch to your look. If your the kind of sweet/cute type of person.</item>
<item>Getting one of those hype bags that have lots of different things on it can make you look quite creative or arty.</item></list></item></list>
<head>The right headscarf</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Make sure you have a good headscarf and know how to put it on properly. Here are some tips
<list type="unordered"><item>If your school is strict about colours and only want you to wear certain colours then you will have to choose from these colours. Try these different colours and see how they look on you.</item>
<item>If you can choose your colours then you can try colours that go well with your uniform. Don't wear a bright pink headscarf when your uniform is green.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>When you choose a bag it will present your personality. If the bag isn't your type then don't buy it because honestly it's not you.</item>
<item>When choosing a headscarf it's not only about he colour. It's also about the type of the headscarf. If its thick it will look differently on you than it will if it's thin.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure that everything you wear is allowed in your school.</item></list>
</text>
