<text id="autogum_whow_doc416" title="Write Birthday Cards" shortTile="write-birthday-cards" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2010-06-26" dateModified="2019-06-16" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Write-Birthday-Cards" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Write Birthday Cards</head><p>Birthday cards are a wonderful way to let someone know that you are thinking of them on their birthday. Start with “Happy Birthday” and then add a few heartfelt and sincere sentences. Take the opportunity to share well wishes, kind words, funny memories, or maybe even a pun with the person. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Writing Kind Words</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Wish them well for the year to come. Birthday cards are a great chance to wish someone the best for the future. This is a great option for both close family and friends, and acquaintances. <figure rend="Write Birthday Cards Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, “All the best for the year to come” or “Wishing you a wonderful year full of great memories.”</item></list></item>
<item>Share what you love or appreciate about the recipient. This is a great way to make the card personal and sincere. Include traits that you love about the person and ways that they inspire you. Try to be as specific as you can, as this helps the card to feel more thoughtful. <figure rend="Write Birthday Cards Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, “You are such a kind, generous, inspiring, and fun Mum” or “You are a wonderful friend and partner to me. I am inspired by the way that you love so selflessly.”</item></list></item>
<item>Celebrate the year that they’ve had. Birthdays are a great chance to look back and reflect on the year that has passed. Celebrate any major achievements or milestones of the person, such as engagements, weddings, graduations, new jobs, or the birth of a child. <figure rend="Write Birthday Cards Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, “Congratulations on graduating from college this year. All the best for your new career.”</item>
<item>If the person has had a hard year, include something like “Congratulations on making it through a tough year.”</item></list></item>
<item>Tell them how they make your life better. This is a wonderful way to make the person feel celebrated. Write a sentence or two about the ways that the recipient of the card adds value to your life. This is particularly meaningful for a partner, close friends, or family member. <figure rend="Write Birthday Cards Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For your partner you could write, “Thanks for making my life more fun, exciting, and joyful. You make my life so rich.”</item></list></item>
<item>Share a happy memory that you shared together. Good memories are wonderful to reflect on. Think about some of your favourite moments that you have shared and then write a short note reminiscing that memory. For example, “I really treasure all the memories of our shared holidays at the beach.” <figure rend="Write Birthday Cards Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This is best for someone that you know well.</item></list></item>
<item>Express your love in the card if you are giving it to your significant other. Take the opportunity to write a meaningful message about how much you love them and how your love for them grows each year. Include specific things you love about them to make the note more personal. <figure rend="Write Birthday Cards Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, “I love you to the moon and back. My love for you increases every year. I’m so grateful to have such a kind, giving, and thoughtful partner.”</item></list></item>
<item>Write in a kind and formal tone if the card is for a co-worker. Let your relationship with the recipient dictate how you write the card. If you have a professional working relationship with the person, use traditional birthday wishes, such as “Wishing you a happy birthday and a wonderful year to come.” <figure rend="Write Birthday Cards Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>”Warm wishes” or “Best” are appropriate formal ways to sign off a card to a co-worker.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Including Humour</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Make a light-hearted joke about their age. The most common birthday jokes tend to be about getting old. For example, you could write “another year closer to receiving your seniors discount” or “Happy 20th! You’re halfway to 40!” <figure rend="Write Birthday Cards Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Avoid mentioning the person's age if you know they are sensitive about it. Also, try to stay away from jokes about death, as this will make some people uncomfortable.</item></list></item>
<item>Share a funny memory that you and the recipient have together. This is a great way to add a personal touch to the card. Mention any funny personal jokes that you share or any amusing memories. <figure rend="Write Birthday Cards Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, “Remember we dressed up as giraffes at Steve’s jungle party. I often look back and laugh at that memory!”</item></list></item>
<item>Write a funny pun. Think about the recipient's interests and write a relevant pun. For example, if the person likes golf, you could write, “I hope that your year to come is above par.” If the person likes to play rock music, you could say, “I hope your day rocks.” <figure rend="Write Birthday Cards Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you get stuck for puns, search online to get some inspiration.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Choosing a Card</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Look for a card with their age if they are celebrating a milestone birthday. Most gift stores stock cards with numbers on the front. These are especially popular for big birthdays, such as a 1st, 5th, 13th, 16th, 18th, 21st, 30th, 40th, 50th, 60th, 70th, 80th, and 90th. <figure rend="Write Birthday Cards Step 11.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you can’t find the right card in store, consider <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_a_Birthday_Card">making your own</ref>.</item></list></item>
<item>Pick a card that reminds you of the recipient. Think about the interests of the person that you are buying the card for. For example, if they love animals, consider purchasing an animal card. Popular card designs include flowers, cars, movie characters, and sports. <figure rend="Write Birthday Cards Step 12.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Purchase cards from a gift store, supermarket, or homeware store.</item></list></item>
<item>Send an eCard if the recipient lives overseas. An eCard is a great free way to let someone know that you are thinking about them. Search online for an eCard that has a design that you like. Type a message to the person and then send it to their email. <figure rend="Write Birthday Cards Step 13.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>SmileBox, Blue Mountain, and ThousandWordCards are popular eCard vendors.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don’t worry about trying to fill the card up with words. Simply write what feels meaningful and then sign off.</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
