<text id="autogum_whow_doc690" title="Use a Blackberry Overseas" shortTile="use-blackberry-overseas" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-09-23" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Use-a-Blackberry-Overseas" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Use a Blackberry Overseas</head><p>Using a Blackberry smart phone while traveling outside of the United States has become easier and even less expensive. Providers of the Blackberry device, including Verizon, Sprint and T-Mobile, have made international versions of the phone available, and their calling plans have become more compatible with the technology used overseas. Users can stick with their own calling plans and pay a roaming charge, or purchase a calling plan in the country they are visiting. Use a Blackberry overseas for making voice calls and for using data plans, just like you do at home.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Determine what network your Blackberry operates on. Smart phones and mobile phones operate on a GSM or CDMA system. Many Blackberry models can work on either network. Your wireless provider should be able to advise you of the network, and whether it is compatible with the country you plan to visit. <figure rend="Use a Blackberry Overseas Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Purchase an international roaming account through your wireless carrier. If you stick with your standard calling plan, you will be charged expensive roaming fees. <figure rend="Use a Blackberry Overseas Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Check calling rates for the country you plan to be in. Even with the international plan, you will still need to pay for each call you make.</item>
<item>Schedule your international calling plan to turn off after you return home. Most carriers will allow you to use the option for a limited time, and then return you to your regular calling plan.</item></list></item>
<item>Purchase an international data or email plan. For temporary travel, most carriers do not offer unlimited texting and email plans, like they do for domestic plans. You will need to choose a plan that provides a specific number of downloads, texts, emails and other data including videos and pictures. <figure rend="Use a Blackberry Overseas Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Find out if you can track your data usage online. This ability will keep you from going over the limit you set, and avoid costly charges.</item></list></item>
<item>Turn off the data roaming function if you decide to use your Blackberry only for calls. <figure rend="Use a Blackberry Overseas Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Go to the Manage Connections screen on your Blackberry and select Mobile Network Options.</item>
<item>Select "off" in the Data Services field.</item></list></item>
<item>Pack an adapter. You will need to charge your Blackberry while overseas, so remember to bring an adapter that will let you plug your device into electrical sockets in the country you are visiting.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Unlimited international emailing and data plans are available through certain carriers for a monthly fee. This might require a long-term plan commitment, however, and would not be suitable for occasional travelers.</item>
<item>Use BBM it's free chatting with any Blackberry. This is very fast Blackberry Messenger really helps!</item>
<item>If your Blackberry has UMA capabilities, it can make calls using a mobile network outside of cell towers. This will allow the phone to connect to the Internet, which will allow you to make calls through the Internet, using Wi-Fi. With the right data plan, this could be cheaper than an international calling plan.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be sure you understand all of the fees and charges associated with international calling, emailing, and texting on your Blackberry while you are overseas. Ask for them in writing. Otherwise, your bill may seem outrageous after you return, and you'll end up calling your carrier for an explanation.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Blackberry</item>
<item>Charger</item>
<item>Adapter</item></list>
</text>
