<text id="autogum_whow_doc698" title="Plan a Trip to the Rainforest" shortTile="plan-trip-rainforest" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2007-06-06" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Plan-a-Trip-to-the-Rainforest" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Plan a Trip to the Rainforest</head><p>Take a break from everyday life and take a vacation to the rainforest. Nothing can compare to the colorful scenery and the exotic atmosphere. It’s a welcome change of pace from everyday life, but a change that can’t be made last minute. Planning a trip to the rainforest may take thought and time but in the end it’s worth all of the work. Here’s how.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Pick a country. There are many countries with rainforests, and each has special features that make it unique. One of the most popular rainforest destinations is Costa Rica and Brazil because of its variety of tours and hotels, but there are numerous other countries with rainforest in Central America, South America, Africa, Oceania, and Southeast Asia. <figure rend="Celebrate-Your-Birthday-Abroad-Step-1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make reservations. Hotels, rental cars, and flights are all available at major ‘travel’ sites, like Expedia or Travelocity. If you search for hotels in your destination country you should be able to find some pretty exotic ones. <figure rend="Deal-With-a-Flight-Cancellation-Step-2-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make an itinerary for your visit. Think about the different types of tours, going to the beach, visiting museums, and sightseeing in towns. <figure rend="Pack-for-a-Trip-to-Montreal-Step-3-Version-5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure that your passport is up to date because without it you aren’t going anywhere. If it’s not up to date or you don’t have on the is key to do right away because they can take a long time to come in the mail. <figure rend="Choose-a-Travel-Destination-Step-2-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get up to date on your shots and vaccinations. Check for travel clinics in you area at and for look for tips about preparing to be in the rainforest and staying healthy while traveling visit. <figure rend="Find-Dialysis-Centers-While-Traveling-Step-6-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Go to your local library or to a bookstore to look for travel guidebooks and for a phrase book in the native language. Some big brand names for travel guidebooks are DK Eyewitness Travel and Fodor's. For phrase books check out Berlitz. Also, for overachievers try CDs to immerse yourself in the language. <figure rend="Pack-for-a-Trip-to-Montreal-Step-5-Version-5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Go to AAA (triple a) or your preferred currency exchange to exchange your money. Traveler’s checks are no longer widely accepted. Try to get cash but also get a debit card to use at ATMs to get cash there and to use in stores where they are accepted. Don’t wait until the airport to exchange currency because exchange rates tend to be higher. <figure rend="Pack-for-a-Year-Abroad-Step-19-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make a list of everything you need to pack. Plan for hot, humid weather, and of course, rain. Also, make sure to take into account bugs. Mosquito netting is definitely a must. Check off your list as you go, making sure you don’t miss anything. Make another copy of the list to check off when you come backs so you don’t leave anything. <figure rend="Celebrate-Your-Birthday-Abroad-Step-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Look at Consular Information Sheets and also understand the laws of the country that you’re traveling to. Better safe than sorry. <figure rend="Stay-Safe-During-International-Sports-Games-in-Unsafe-Cities-or-Countries-Step-3-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tell friends and family where you will be staying in case of emergency and also register at the relevant Embassy or consulate before leaving. This means that the embassy or consulate will know where you are and can assist you in the event of an emergency. Also think about travel registration, which will allow the State Department or other relevant agency to help you if an emergency arises. <figure rend="Find an Apartment Near Columbia University Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get to the airport early (and DON’T forget your passport). International airports are larger and harder to navigate then local ones. <figure rend="Enjoy-a-Holiday-Step-3-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be environmentally friendly. In the rainforest, do not dispose of your garbage in bushes, rivers or anywhere else in the forest. Carry a bag for garbage with you and dispose of it in the proper receptacles. <figure rend="Tidy-a-Room-Quickly-Step-6-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Pack a change of clothes and a toothbrush in a carry-on bag. Airlines like to loose baggage.</item>
<item>If you are renting a car at the airport pre-plan your route from the airport to your hotel. Foreign places can be hard to navigate, especially at night.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>What can go wrong will go wrong in an airport, so allow enough time for checking bags, security, finding the gate, and a little extra for cushion.</item>
<item>Wearing expensive jewelry or clothing may attract attention to you and make you a target for pickpockets.</item></list>
</text>
