<text id="autogum_whow_doc391" title="Create a Pour Painting" shortTile="create-pour-painting" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-10-06" dateModified="2019-10-21" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Create-a-Pour-Painting" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Create a Pour Painting</head>Pour paint could be the creative outlet you are looking for. Through this fun technique of pouring acrylic paint onto a canvas you will end up with a colorful piece to liven up any space. Mix colors and patterns to create your own pour painting.
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Preparing Your Workplace</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Prep your working area. Find a flat surface and lay some kind plastic or thick cloth to protect it from spills.Make sure that you have layers down seeing as the paint spills are an unavoidable part of this project. <figure rend="Prep your space yerp.png"></figure></item>
<item>Put on gloves and clothes you don't mind getting dirty. This project requires a lot of paint and it is bound to get messy. For a quicker more stress free clean up, make sure to be prepared. <figure rend="Old clothes yerp.png"></figure></item>
<item>Prepare your own pour medium. The pour medium is an important factor to the pour painting because it is what allows the paints to flow around the canvas without sticking and blending as much. It also allows for a vast amount of paint to dry without cracking and creasing.Mix a generous amount of white glue and water into a squeeze bottle or container. Make sure it is a 50/50 ratio. Mix about 3/4 of a cup for a 8x8 in canvas, adjust measurements to size of canvas. <figure rend="Glue medium.png"></figure></item>
<item>Prepare paint mix. There is going to be a vast amount of paint used in this project. To make this more economical, you could go to your local hardware store and ask for samples, or you could buy small amounts of different pigments in bulk at any art supply store. To prepare the mix, pour about three table spoons of acrylic paint into a container, then squeeze the pour paint medium from the previous step into the container. Mix with a plastic spoon, or some kind of stirrer until it is the consistency of buttermilk. Usually a 50/50 ratio does the trick. Repeat for all pigments. While mixing avoid air bubbles to the best of your abilities. Do so by mixing it slowly, do not whisk it or it will turn foamy. <figure rend="Paints prepared.png"></figure></item>
<item>Prop your canvas on a flat surface. Make sure that your work area is covered and materials are ready. <figure rend="Canvas in place.png"></figure></item></list>
<head>Creating</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Pour each pigment on canvas slowly. While pouring, focus on getting an even amount of pigments over the canvas, it should be in a random fashion. Add more of certain pigments to get desired look. <figure rend="Panit pour.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pick up canvas and tip it at an angle so that the paint moves around. You will not have complete control of where the paint moves but you will be able to steer it into the desired area. The excess paint will roll off of the canvas onto the plastic or cloth laid on surface.Be very careful while tipping, if the canvas is dropped or something touches the canvas, the paint will move and the image will be distorted. <figure rend="Add more.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Add more paint onto areas that you think need it. There is no correct way of making a great piece, just keep on adding until the canvas has no more uncovered spots and you are satisfied. <figure rend="Tip that boy.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Spread paint over any areas that are missing paint with a straight edge. An old card or a piece of cardboard will do. Lightly swipe paint over area until covered. If area can not be covered after two swipes add more paint to area. Be careful of not using excess force or swiping too many times. This will distort the paint and ruin the illusion of paint dripping down canvas.  <figure rend="Spred.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Spray rubbing alcohol over any air bubbles to get rid of them. When the canvas is fully covered and you are content with the way it turned out, spray for a more polished look. This will also give a bit of visual texture as the alcohol reacts with the paint. <figure rend="Alcohol yerp.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Let piece sit and dry for up to 36 hours. As the paint dries, more unique effects will begin surfacing. Make sure it is stored in a safe and dry environment. <figure rend="Let_sit.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Enjoy your very own pour paint piece! There is no other quite like yours, be proud of your creation! <figure rend="Perfecto.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>8x8 in Canvas</item>
<item>Plastic or Cloth</item>
<item>Multiple Acrylic Paints</item>
<item>Old Card or a Piece of Cardboard</item>
<item>Multiple Containers Such as Cups</item>
<item>White Glue</item>
<item>Stirrer</item>
<item>Water</item>
<item>A Flat Surface</item>
<item>Old Clothes</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>When picking colors be very conscious that some of the colors may mix, creating a new color. Choose colors that create flattering colors when mixed.</item>
<item>While picking out the paint you do not need to pick up anything very expensive. As a beginner it is recommended to get something more economical, perhaps paints in bulk. If you are looking to sell pour paints, acrylic paints of better quality would be recommended.</item>
<item>Tweak measurements depending on size of canvas.</item>
<item>Make sure everything is really well mixed.</item>
<item>Be sparing with the paint as you might need some more later.</item></list>
</text>
