<text id="autogum_whow_doc187" title="Think &apos;Inside of the Box&apos;" shortTile="think-inside-box" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2008-10-17" dateModified="2018-02-07" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Think-%27Inside-of-the-Box%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Think 'Inside of the Box'</head><p>In most real life situations, you are given specific hard parameters that cannot be changed. Creative thinking must involve inclusion of these boundaries. </p>
<p>Solutions that are created outside of the box cannot be implemented inside of the box. Thinking outside of the box is a powerful mental exercise, but it is not practical for solving actual problems.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Set_Goals">Define your goal</ref>. <figure rend="Think 'Inside of the Box' Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Define_a_Problem">Define the problem</ref> or obstacle that you will need to address to reach your goal. <figure rend="Think 'Inside of the Box' Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Divide a complex problem into basic components. <figure rend="Think 'Inside of the Box' Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Define parameters that frame your goal. This is the "box" in which you must work your solution.  If you are drawing these boundaries, be careful where you draw it, and be aware of what can and cannot be moved, if necessary, about them. <figure rend="Think 'Inside of the Box' Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Determine a timeline for solving the problem and reaching your goal. Can some components of your problem be postponed until later in the project? Must some of the components be solved before other components can be solved? <figure rend="Think 'Inside of the Box' Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make a list of solutions that have been tried unsuccessfully in the past. Ask yourself why each of these solutions failed. Many times a solution fails because of lack of <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Persistent">persistence</ref>. You need to hit a nail more than once before it is driven into place. <figure rend="Think 'Inside of the Box' Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Before discarding a possible solution that has failed, consider whether your situation is different somehow.  Have technologies, attitudes, or conditions changed?  Is yours a slightly different problem?</item></list></item>
<item>Start a list of solutions that have not been tried. Write down every idea regardless of merit and filter them later. Remember that it is easier to have too many ideas to choose from than not enough. <figure rend="Think 'Inside of the Box' Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Keep_a_Notebook">Keep a notebook</ref> and <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Choose_a_Pen">pen</ref> with you at all times. Jot down as many ideas as they come to you, whether or not they are "good".</item>
<item>Think about your goal and the components of the problem when you have idle time, such as during travel time, exercise, coffee breaks or even routine meetings.</item>
<item>Look to your supervisors, coworkers and companions for input. Accept every suggestion. You do not need to create your own solution, but can freely adopt and adapt a solution that has worked for someone else.</item>
<item>Work backwards.  Consider resources or solutions open to you and ask whether and how they could move you toward your goal.</item></list></item>
<item>Make a list of outside resources that would be needed for specific solutions. Include estimated budget requirements. <figure rend="Think 'Inside of the Box' Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Refine your lists. Re-write and re-phrase solutions. Organize the list, grouping the most viable solutions together. <figure rend="Think 'Inside of the Box' Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Choose a solution. Present it. Implement it. <figure rend="Think 'Inside of the Box' Step 10.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Just because you are working within a set of well-defined parameters, doesn't mean you can't exercise your creativity within those parameters or even on those parameters.</item>
<item>Be bold and take calculated risks.</item>
<item>Maintain a humble attitude, as this will facilitate your receptiveness to solution ideas from others.</item></list>
</text>
