<text id="autogum_whow_doc225" title="Avoid Stock Option Mistakes" shortTile="avoid-stock-option" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-06-17" dateModified="2018-09-10" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Avoid-Stock-Option-Mistakes" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Avoid Stock Option Mistakes</head><p>Options like Stocks take time to learn.  Here are the basic reasons why people lose money in options and how you can avoid them.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Avoid buying Calls or Puts with High Volatility because they are overpriced. If you plot a stock on BigCharts or StockCharts, you can select an upper indicator called "Bollinger Bands" on a "Weekly" chart.  If the Bands are wide, the volatility is high and the options are "Overpriced".  Avoid buying these options because stocks fluctuate between high volatility and low volatility, so when the volatility cools off, the options will fall in price and you will have lost money.  Consider "selling" options that have high volatility and are overpriced.</item>
<item>Avoid Options that are "out of the money" because they lose a lot of time value and have a higher risk of expiring worthless if the stock does not move in the direction you want.  You can just as easily buy options that are deep in the money because they will have less time value (less overpriced) and will follow the stock price more closely.</item>
<item>Buy Leaps instead of options that expire in a few months.  If you buy leaps, the time decay per month is low and the price you pay per week is far less. Options have the fastest time decay when they are close to expiration so don't buy options that expire in a few weeks or months.</item>
<item>Avoid buying calls after the stock has jumped in price.  If you buy a call after a rally, the chance of a pullback and the option losing price is the greatest.  Also the volatility is high so you "overpay" for the options. I try and buy the options after a fall and when the volatility is low so that the options will be cheap.</item>
<item>Only put 5% of your money in an option at a time.  This way if the option falls in half you will not be under any stress because you only lost 2.5%.  If you put a lot of money in an option and the market moves against you, you will get cold feet and sell at a loss.  Then if you sold and the stock rallies, you will wonder why you sold at a loss.  Work this in reverse and only put a lot of money in an option that is deep in the money on a dip.  It takes time to get your timing right and if you lose a lot of money, you will be tempted to take greater risks and have a greater chance of losing more money.  There is money to be made by taking "less" risk but you have to conserve cash to get to the point where you can get your timing right.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can plot option prices on bigcharts by going to "advanced chart", plot the stock, select "option chain" (2 inches above the chart), then selecting "quote". By charting the option you can get an idea of its pattern and avoid mistakes.</item>
<item>You can measure volatility to determine if an option is overpriced by selecting "bollinger bands" on stockcharts or bigcharts.  You must select "weekly" graphs because "daily" graphs fluctuate too wildly and are harder to see the patterns and harder to interpret.</item>
<item>On StockCharts you can change the chart "type" from "candlesticks" to "Elder Impulse System" (but you will have to scroll down to the bottom of the list to select it.) This is an advanced formula where the stock is green when you should be owning calls and red when you should be owning puts.  This keeps you going in the right direction and helps your timing.</item>
<item>If you make a lot of money on a trade, withdraw 30% of the money and pay bills.  This way if you give back a lot of money on some bad trades, you will at least have paid down bills and be in a better position to withstand a downturn.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Options are risky and you should not put more than 5% of your money in an option at a time.  This way you conserve cash for the really good trades.</item>
<item>If you make a lot of money on a trade in a non-ira account, be sure and withdraw the money to pay for taxes and save it for tax time. It is a lot of hassle to lose money in the beginning of the next year and not have the money to pay for taxes.</item></list>
</text>
