<text id="autogum_whow_doc529" title="Decide on a Pet" shortTile="decide-pet" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-09-07" dateModified="2019-09-20" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Decide-on-a-Pet" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Decide on a Pet</head><p>When deciding on a pet, you need to make the right choice, and several factors come into play when choosing. In this article, you'll learn how to make a good choice for a pet based on your lifestyle and personality. So what are you waiting for? Happy reading!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Evaluating Lifestlye</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Pick a pet that you have enough time to care for. For a busier lifestlye, you might want a neat pet that doesn't require that much care, which could range from anything from a gerbil to a cat (this range will be narrowed down later.) For a lifestyle where you aren't away from home often and have plenty of free time, you might want a dog that you can spend plenty of time with. When evaluating how much time you can dedicate to a pet, think of these factors:
<list type="unordered"><item>Do I travel often?</item>
<item>Do I want to spend the money it takes on vaccinations and checkups, is it worth it to me?</item>
<item>Will I be able to give my pet the time it needs?</item></list></item>
<item>Think about how much this pet will cost. A parakeet, for example, requires a cage, toys, treats, and plenty of food and clean water. You'll need to do some research and see how much it would cost you, based on the pet you were thinking of. You'll also need to think about whether or not your pet would need checkups or feather clippings. Think about your money and your needs, and from there see how much financial wiggle room you have.</item></list>
<head>Meeting Possible Pets</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find a pet you know you'll really care about. Go to a pet store and talk to one of the employees about which pets you're considering, and they can give you lots of helpful information. Mention some of the pets you were thinking of. If you were, for example, considering getting some koi, ask about the care they require. If you were considering getting a ferret, ask to hold one and ask about the care one would need. Find a pet that speaks to you.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you want to get a dog, you might want to try going to your local animal shelter. The dogs here all deserve good, loving homes, and shelter dogs I've had in the past have turned out to be the sweetest animals I've ever known. These dogs deserve kindness and love, and will be extremely loyal to you.</item></list></item>
<item>Buy the proper supplies. You may need to consult an employee about this to ensure you are being thorough. Then pick out which cat/bird/gerbil/rat/mouse/guinea pig/fish/whatever you want you liked the best.
<list type="unordered"><item>Look for pretty patterns on the fur or a cute personality before deciding which one you want.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>The more you spend time with your pet, the more comfortable it will be around you and the more trusting it will become.</item>
<item>It takes a lot more steps than this to decide on a bigger pet, such as a horse. If you are planning on getting a big pet, you should talk to local sellers about the care of such a creature and think deeply about your decision. It will cost a lot to effectively care for larger animals.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>It is crucial that you take good care of your pet. You need to note any unusual behavior or signs of pain or illness and talk to a vet right away.</item></list>
</text>
