<text id="autogum_whow_doc700" title="Choose a Travel Guide" shortTile="choose-travel-guide" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-06-10" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Choose-a-Travel-Guide" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Choose a Travel Guide</head><p>Going on a trip? Buying a travel guide may be on your list of things to do before you go. There are many travel guide books on the market, and choosing the right one is important. Some travel guides cater to the rugged adventurer, while others focus on five-star luxury, and many have a bit of both. Becoming familiar with the different types of travel books and focusing on your needs will help you choose a travel guide that's right for you.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Ask yourself, "What type of traveler am I?" Like any book, travel guides are made with a specific audience in mind. Are you backpacking through Asia or spa hopping in Europe?  Are you traveling with children? Look for a guidebook that targets your type and easily helps you find the information you need about your travel destination. <figure rend="Choose a Travel Guide Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Focus on your destination. Where exactly are you going?  This may sound like an odd question, but it's important to consider. If you are traveling all over North America, you may want to look for a guidebook that highlights the entire continent. Buying a book for each region of the U.S., Canada and Mexico may be too much. Likewise, if you are traveling to Nepal, you may want a guide that covers just that country rather than all of Asia. If you are spending the weekend in London, a city guide might be just what you need instead of something that covers England. <figure rend="Choose a Travel Guide Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Choose your medium. How do you like your information? Many smart phones have applications for travel, so if tiny and high-tech is what you like, this may be a good option. Handheld devices are easy to carry and easy to search, but the small print is sometimes difficult to read. If you want to go this route, check out a few apps for your destination and see if they will meet your needs. You may want to use your handheld device in addition to a guidebook. If you like quick bits of information, but less history or cultural commentaries, keep this in mind when shopping around. <figure rend="Choose a Travel Guide Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Visit your local book store or library to familiarize yourself with the major guidebook brands. Each guidebook takes a slightly different approach to organization, so find one that is right for you. Scan it for readability and ease of search. If you find the maps difficult to navigate or the information confusing, pick a different book. <figure rend="Choose a Travel Guide Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Narrow your search. Look at the books you are considering. Some books are very graphic with lots of pictures, others are detailed with history, while others offer step-by-step walking instructions around cities. Once you've looked through a few of the books, consider the one that kept your interest the longest and gave you the information you found most useful at first glance. <figure rend="Choose a Travel Guide Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Consider the size and weight of the travel guide. If you want to do research before traveling, a larger, more in-depth book might be just what you need. A smaller book is good to carry in your bag, and pull out as you go. Backpackers must consider the weight of each item they carry, so lightweight books are essential. If you are staying at a hotel and making day trips, it's easier to keep a larger book in your hotel room and peruse it nightly for the next day's information. <figure rend="Choose a Travel Guide Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Buy a book within your budget. You may save money by purchasing a used travel guide. The older guide books may have some out of date information when it comes to prices, opening times, and local events, so purchasing a book that is up-to-date but a bit more expensive may be worth it. <figure rend="Choose a Travel Guide Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can buy a travel guide online or in the book store, however, be attentive that this book is produced in the country you are going to, as it may be disappointing to buy a travel guide on China written by a Slavic man for example.</item>
<item>If you travel to a particular city or town, so it would be reasonable to buy a travel guide right there.</item>
<item>If you have a small-size travel guide, you should know that there may be tree times less information than in a big one.</item></list>
</text>
