<text id="autogum_whow_doc178" title="Think Coherently" shortTile="think-coherently" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-12-27" dateModified="2019-03-03" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Think-Coherently" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Think Coherently</head><p>Thinking affects every aspect of life; however, you usually want to think especially well when you are engaging in a few common activities: speaking, listening, writing, reading, deciding, or persuading. Thinking well helps you decide when others' opinions have merit, and you persuade others to see when your opinion has merit. For many people grappling with ideas in those situations, thoughts can become jumbled. If you are grappling with complexity, there is an easy place to start thinking well. The following suggestions can often help you identify and engage with coherent opinions. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Start with the basics. You would be surprised at how many think that the following suggestions are so basic that they do not engage with them systematically. As a consequence, people often do not know what to think, what their own opinions are.</item>
<item>List the ideas that you think are relevant to the situation, motivation, or topic. If you are reading an expert opinion, does she cover what you think is relevant? If you are writing your opinion, do you cover what others will find relevant? (2) Among the relevant ideas, which are the most important? The few important ideas will cause the merely relevant ideas to adapt their meanings to the situation in perhaps unique ways. Can you identify which ideas others find important when they are talking to you? Can you communicate which ideas you think are important when you are talking to them? (3) Once you have established a cognitive foundation of relevance and importance, you are in a position to tackle what most people think is the foundation of critical and coherent thinking: is the opinion you are listening to or enunciating true?</item>
<item>Sort them. Truth is easier to hear and say if you first know which ideas are relevant and which of those ideas are the most important. How will you know which ideas are relevant and important? Well, that is sort of a mystery, but your mind has been learning how to do that your whole life. You are so good at determining relevance and importance, that it has become subconscious. Trust those feelings. Allow them to the be foundation of what you think.</item>
<item>Work out what to say in advance. Thinking coherently is begun by forming what you need to say within your head, as a general rule of thumb. It is often said that thinking is like talking to yourself internally. The idea is to make this dialogue understandable to yourself so that you are very aware of what is going on internally.</item>
<item>Make sure that the words you use are adequate for the purpose they mean to serve. Use words that are accurate descriptors of the thing being thought, in order to gain greater accuracy in your depictions of that thing and in the sentences you formulate.</item>
<item>Make sure that what you are saying internally is clear. Be aware of any confusion.</item>
<item>Expand your vocabulary by reading and listening to people talk. This will help you to have the words you require to formulate streams of thought inside your head.</item>
<item>Look at where you are struggling to think. Consider what you are struggling to think about. Then, try to find ways to think about it using either more descriptors or better defining what you already know.</item></list>
</text>
