<text id="autogum_whow_doc194" title="Talk to Your Tween Daughter About Boys" shortTile="talk-tween-daughter" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-10-20" dateModified="2019-08-15" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Talk-to-Your-Tween-Daughter-About-Boys" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Talk to Your Tween Daughter About Boys</head><p>Nobody likes it when their child grows up too quickly. Sometimes, the only way to prevent this is to discuss things as a family to ensure your daughter knows the circumstances she is already or will face in the future. Here are some ways to connect and make this as easy as possible.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Finding the Right Time to Talk</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find a good place to talk. The setting should be private, quiet, and without distractions. Talking in the living room when both of you are home alone is a good idea. Try not to use her bedroom, as this is her place to gather her thoughts and emotions.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you can't find a place at home, try taking her somewhere like a coffee shop or a store she likes to shop at, so she feels more comfortable.</item></list></item>
<item>Make time to talk. Don't rush the conversation, or lose focus on the conversation with your daughter. Instead, make sure the time you have chosen is convenient for both you and your daughter, so that you can remove any distractions.
<list type="unordered"><item>Leave yourself enough time to allow the conversation to overrun. Your daughter might need more explanations or help with understanding certain parts during the conversation and she might have questions that she wants to know the answers to.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Being Open and Honest with Your Daughter</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Talk with your daughter’s interests at heart. Telling your daughter you want only the best life for her, she is more likely to pay attention and gain more from the conversation. This way, you’ll be sure that she understands where you are coming from, so that she takes the topic seriously.</item>
<item>Explain the importance behind the conversation. It’s important for your daughter to understand why the topic of boys needs to be addressed with your daughter. If she doesn’t know why you are having the conversation with your daughter, she may not spend the time listening to important information. </item>
<item>Be positive. Don't be angry when you talk; just know that she may not understand or believe everything you say. It’s important that you aren’t negative with your daughter as this could impact the outcome of the conversation and could change the way your daughter behaves.</item></list>
<head>Birds and the Bees</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Avoid going into too much detail. If you haven't talked about this particular subject before, it would be a good time to dig into it a little. Your daughter won't understand why you're talking to her about boys if you don't tell her the truth. Only explain what you believe to be most important at this stage otherwise your conversation may go off topic.</item>
<item>Explain the truth from the start. Don't scare her, but be open and honest from the start. If you start to change the truth, this could impact your daughters knowledge in the long run.</item></list>
<head>Discuss and Implement Boundaries</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Agree certain rules with your daughter. This is for her benefit and you should make sure that she understand this. Whether it means downgrading her phone, installing a parental app, or just simply being more involved in who she's speaking to, let her understand your motivation. Explain to her that you having knowledge of who your daughter is talking to will be important in the long run to keep her safe.</item>
<item>Ask her about how to be safe. This is not a one-man show. She needs to be involved for this to work. Find out what she thinks and let her give you her opinion on certain ideas. Ask her questions, and listen to her answers. Ensure you correct her on any incorrect information to make sure that she stays safe at all times.</item></list>
<head>Answer Her Questions</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Tell her what she wants to know. No matter how awkward or simple it is, answer her questions truthfully. You might even want to prompt her into asking questions if she doesn't have any.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make her favorite treats or snacks to lessen the "cringe" around you both.</item>
<item>Remove distractions so that you can focus on the conversation and have an open mind.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not be overbearing. The worst thing you can do is make her feel extremely vulnerable and like she has no privacy.</item></list>
</text>
