<text id="autogum_whow_doc344" title="Prepare for Knee Arthroscopy Surgery (Teens)" shortTile="prepare-knee-arthroscopy" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2016-10-04" dateModified="2018-03-19" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Prepare-for-Knee-Arthroscopy-Surgery-%28Teens%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Prepare for Knee Arthroscopy Surgery (Teens)</head><p>When teens have to have knee surgery, they often need to have an arthroscopy. An arthroscopy is a surgical procedure that uses a small camera and small instruments to see inside a joint (the knee in this case) and fix any problems. (It's Latin, <hi rend="italic">arthro</hi> meaning "joint", and <hi rend="italic">scopy</hi> meaning "see inside"). A knee arthroscopy is one of the most common surgical procedures, even for teens.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>As Soon as Possible</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find out what your pre-op instructions are. You might have to stop taking medications such as NSAIDs up to two weeks before your surgery. You will also want to know how long before your procedure you must fast. It is often from midnight the night before surgery on, but there are exceptions, so be sure to go over this with your surgeon. <figure rend="Prepare for Knee Arthroscopy Surgery (Teens) Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find out what you may need to get ready for post-op. This may include a brace/immobilizer, an ice machine/ice packs, pillows and blankets for comfort in the car on the way home from the hospital, or a prescription for pain meds (some surgeons will give you the prescription ahead of time, others will only give it on the day of surgery). <figure rend="Prepare for Knee Arthroscopy Surgery (Teens) Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Gather all the items that you find out you need from the previous step. <figure rend="Prepare for Knee Arthroscopy Surgery (Teens) Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take time off work/school if needed. If you are in school, try to get your homework ahead of time so you can do it before your surgery. If you can't do this for one reason or another (such as surgery being booked for the next day, it does happen), try to email your teachers at least, and this way they will hopefully give you an extension on the work being done on your surgery day, and potentially for a few days after your surgery (in case you need to stay out of town overnight, or are in too much pain to go back the day after). <figure rend="Prepare for Knee Arthroscopy Surgery (Teens) Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If needed, book a hotel. Especially in rural areas, there may not be an orthopaedic surgeon in your town/city, so you may have to stay in a hotel before and/or after your surgery, especially if you need to have a drain removed the morning after surgery. Make sure to ask for a medical rate, as many hotels offer discounts for medical appointment-related stays. <figure rend="Prepare for Knee Arthroscopy Surgery (Teens) Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>One Week Before Surgery</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Make sure you know all of your pre-op instructions. If you are to discontinue the use of some medications, this is especially important. You also need to know when to stop eating and drinking the night before surgery. <figure rend="Prepare for Knee Arthroscopy Surgery (Teens) Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Ensure you have all of the post op supplies discussed above. <figure rend="Prepare for Knee Arthroscopy Surgery (Teens) Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>The Night Before Surgery</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Eat a good dinner, and have a big snack, along with lots to drink. You won't be able to eat or drink after midnight (with exceptions) on this night, so make sure you are well-fed, and well-hydrated. <figure rend="Prepare for Knee Arthroscopy Surgery (Teens) Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure you follow your NPO, or Nil Per Oral instructions. This means no food or drink after a set time, usually midnight. Should you not follow your NPO directions, you may not be able to have your procedure done. <figure rend="Prepare for Knee Arthroscopy Surgery (Teens) Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have everything ready for the next morning, such as clothes, toiletries, entertainment etc. <figure rend="Prepare for Knee Arthroscopy Surgery (Teens) Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get a good night's sleep. Even though you will be "sleeping" with the anaesthesia the next day, you don't get rest with anaesthesia, so you still need to get a good sleep. <figure rend="Prepare for Knee Arthroscopy Surgery (Teens) Step 11.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>The Day of Surgery</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Stay NPO. This is for your safety, as you don't want to choke on your stomach contents while under general anaesthesia. <figure rend="Prepare for Knee Arthroscopy Surgery (Teens) Step 12.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Remember, if you eat or drink, your surgery may be cancelled.</item></list></item>
<item>Wear loose, comfy clothes. It helps to wear short, baggy shorts, or loose pyjama-type bottoms, as if you need a drain after surgery, this will make it easy to get your bottoms over the drain, and also the bulky dressing that will be on your knee after surgery. You may also have a knee immobilizer, which, again, is quite bulky. <figure rend="Prepare for Knee Arthroscopy Surgery (Teens) Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure you show up on time. If you don't, you will have to wait even longer to get your knee fixed. <figure rend="Prepare for Knee Arthroscopy Surgery (Teens) Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be ready to wait. Bring entertainment such as a phone or tablet, so you have something to do while you wait. <figure rend="Prepare for Knee Arthroscopy Surgery (Teens) Step 15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Prepare yourself for discomfort. After surgery, you will fell very tired, hungry and thirsty, and maybe a bit nauseous. You will also likely be in quite a bit of pain, and you may have a drain in your knee to drain excess blood and fluid from your knee. This will be removed about 18-36 hours after your surgery. <figure rend="Prepare for Knee Arthroscopy Surgery (Teens) Step 16.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure you follow any and all post-op instructions, such a as physiotherapy, weight-bearing restrictions and bracing/wrapping. Your surgeon should tell you or your parents all of this information. <figure rend="Prepare for Knee Arthroscopy Surgery (Teens) Step 17.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You may not sleep much the night after your surgery, as you may be in quite a bit of pain. This is a good night to stay up and watch TV!</item>
<item>If possible, ice your knee after surgery. Not only will the cold help with swelling, but also with pain. An automatic icing machine, or "cryocuff", while expensive, can be a worthwhile investment to simplify the post-op icing process.</item>
<item>If you're prescribed pain medication, take it on schedule, even if you are not in pain. It is better to be “ahead” of the pain than try to “catch up”. After a few days, you will want to start weaning off the prescription medication and onto an over the counter drug, such as Advil or Tylenol.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You may not be able to use all the timing suggestions in this article, sometimes you are only given a few days to prepare. You can still use all the information, just in a different time frame.</item></list>
</text>
