<text id="autogum_whow_doc202" title="Go on a Road Trip With Toddlers" shortTile="go-road-trip-toddlers" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-02-25" dateModified="2019-04-22" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Go-on-a-Road-Trip-With-Toddlers" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Go on a Road Trip With Toddlers</head><p>Not everyone has the same definition of a road trip. This article is aimed at those travelling by car for four hours plus. Whether you are sharing the driving or on your own, if you have to travel with an infant in a car, you should prepare before you head off. This article provides some general help and advice. Get started at step number one below.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><figure rend="Pack a Diaper Bag for a Newborn Step 20.jpg"></figure> Pack the essentials for the trip. If your child is still in diapers/nappies, make sure you will have enough for the whole journey, and some spares. Consider taking a change of clothes. If your toddler needs medicines, make sure you can give them their usual dose at the usual time during the road trip.</item>
<item><figure rend="Plan a Road Trip Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure> Plan your journey and make sure you know of any road closures, weather risks, local events etc that may cause you to be delayed or detoured. Make sure someone know what route you're plan to take and let them know when you arrive safely.</item>
<item><figure rend="Plan a Road Trip Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure> Be able to navigate the journey. You may know the way, you might use a SatNav device or a good old road atlas, just make sure you can find your way from A to B because being lost with a fractious toddler is not fun.
<list type="unordered"><item>Give your vehicle a maintenance check before you start. Don't risk your toddler's life because you have faulty brakes or bald tires. Check the levels of oil, windshield washer fluid etc, and of course fuel!</item>
<item>Use appropriate child restraints in your vehicle. Many vehicles with air bags are very specific about where in the vehicle car seats are placed. Look at your vehicle manual if you are unsure.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Pack a Diaper Bag for a Newborn Step 14.jpg"></figure> Provide entertainment suitable for the age of your toddler.
<list type="unordered"><item>Car trips can be boring for toddlers. Pack a box of toys and work out some games you can play in the car. Ensure you will not be distracted whilst driving.</item>
<item>You can play games like eye spy and who am I, a game where you choose an animal and tell your toddler three things about them then they have to guess what animal it is, if your child has the required vocabulary. Children of two have short attention spans so don't expect word games to entertain for very long.</item>
<item>You can also sing songs and nursery rhymes, if you know four hours worth!</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Help a Carsick Child Step 11Bullet2.jpg"></figure> Deal with your toddler getting car sick.
<list type="unordered"><item>Not every toddler gets car sick and there is no guaranteed way of preventing car sickness so make sure you always have a bag handy if your main concern is vomit. If you know your toddler suffers from stomach upsets and gets distressed on long car journeys, ask your doctor or paediatrician for advice. Whilst vomit on your car seats is very unpleasant, your child being distressed should be your main concern.</item>
<item>Keep a towel and wipes so you can clean things up if your toddler is sick  <figure rend="Help a Carsick Child Step 7Bullet1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you know how, teach your toddler to recognise the signs that they are going to throw up so they can warn you you so you can pull over in time. Remember, never pull over unless it is safe to do so, especially on motorways.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Discipline Toddlers Step 31.jpg"></figure> Deal with grumpy toddlers on a road trip.
<list type="unordered"><item>Your toddler may get grumpy if they are hungry or/and tired. Pack food so your toddler can eat. Make sure you keep your toddler hydrated and be very careful to avoid foods they make choke on if you let your child eat while you are driving and not supervising them.  <figure rend="Pack Healthier School Lunches Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Avoid giving toddlers sugary drinks. These are bad for their teeth and can cause peaks and troughs in their energy levels through out the journey. Pack fruit and a sandwich, perhaps.</item>
<item>If possible plan your road trip to let your toddler fall asleep in the car for as much of the journey as possible.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
