<text id="autogum_whow_doc168" title="Start a Spy School" shortTile="start-spy-school" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2012-11-29" dateModified="2017-11-23" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Start-a-Spy-School" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Start a Spy School</head><p>Do you have a spy club already, but need something else in the club? Or do you need to just DO something fun to pass the time? Either way, here's how you make a successful spy school... (just so you know, this article is meant to be for kids)</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>If you don't have one, start a spy club! They usually have 3-6 people in them. You can have a big army or a small group of spies. Here are the jobs you will need to assign: President: This is the main leader spy. You can have just one or, if your  group is big, you can even have a small staff of 3-5 people. Lone Spy: This is the spy who spies the most. This spy should be allowed around town already. Scout: This spy searches out the spying area for tiny cameras, hidden weapons, etc. This stuff you will probably only find if you have an enemy spy club. Computer Spy: <figure rend="Start a Spy School Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Gets info from web and keeps track of it in a notebook. Conclusion Spy: figures out things. Trainees: rookie spies who are being trained. <figure rend="Start a Spy School Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have everybody come up with a spy name (Agent ______). <figure rend="Start a Spy School Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Finally, let's get down to the school. If you have a staff, they will be teachers. If you do not have a staff then choose a few advanced spies. <figure rend="Start a Spy School Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make the arrangements. Who will teach defense/attack classes? Who will teach about disguising? <figure rend="Start a Spy School Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have at LEAST one person in your club take karate. They will be the defense/attack teacher. This is an optional step. If there is no karate person then just teach simple punching, kicking, and slapping routines. <figure rend="Start a Spy School Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>For more advice, add cathrinegrace101 on moshi monsters and send her a message on her pinboard. Cathrinegrace101 is me. <figure rend="Start a Spy School Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Optional: make a form of money, have a spy store with gadgets, and reward people with that form of money, and they get to shop in the store with it. For more info, contact cathrinegrace101 on moshi monsters. <figure rend="Start a Spy School Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have an official place for the school. <figure rend="Start a Spy School Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make a time every week for spy school- YOU get to choose how many times you have it per week. I would say only about 3 times, as spies need breaks, and they need time for homework/fun. <figure rend="Start a Spy School Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you want, you can occasionally assign homework. Only something that would take five or ten minutes though. Spies do not like wasting time. <figure rend="Start a Spy School Step 11.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Eventually, you WILL get caught on a mission. On missions, always have an excuse/Plan B. Your friends may get mad if you have the school too often, or if the homework is long/hard. They WILL quit if they get too mad! if they get mad at all, cut down on the spy school and spy homework!</item></list>
</text>
