<text id="autogum_whow_doc335" title="Resolve Your Delicate Mind" shortTile="resolve-delicate" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-02-23" dateModified="2018-09-23" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Resolve-Your-Delicate-Mind" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Resolve Your Delicate Mind</head>Your own mind is the only entity that you can depend on, trust and speak with freely and calmly because your mind is loyal only to you and does not lie to you. Your mind is your soul mate. Nothing can take that relationship away. Sometimes, a mind can become delicate when it experience a sudden shock or trauma.
<p>Often, those of us who appear to have tough skin on the outside are the most sensitive on the inside. This is especially true among men.</p>
<p>Women tend to be more expressive and open about their feelings, moods, and about themselves. Women usually are not ashamed of revealing their feelings or shedding their tears. </p>
<p>Children (in general) have trouble understanding their behavior and tenderness. This is seen in children from 12-16 years old. Most of them emotionally develop thick skin to protect themselves.</p>
<p>Some minds are naturally more delicate than others. These assertive steps will show you how to resolve and develop your delicate mind that troubles you. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Gathering the Scattered You</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Stay calm. Staying calm is the most important when your mind is scattered and your heart feels swollen and your head feels heavy. By staying calm you improve your reflection and your mind's reaction. Your nervous system becomes stable and you can help your brain and body to function properly. To stay calm, breath slowly and deeply. With each deep breath you take, your head stress and weight reduces to its initial level, your heart feels light weighted and your brain feels awake. The second verbalizing technique is chanting the echoic and metallic chant "Ohm" 108 times. It is a Sanskrit sound and mantra of Hindu origin. It is important and sacred in various religions such as Hinduism, Buddhism, Jainism and Santana Dharma. When the "Ohm" echoes in our ears, we are more stable throughout our entire body. <figure rend="Resolve Your Delicate Mind Step 1 Version 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Stop weeping. Crying about your condition and weeping is the most wrong thing you can ever do. One must exert control over their softness. By crying a person invites more depression. It damns your thinking stream. <figure rend="Resolve Your Delicate Mind Step 2 Version 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Think of next. Every story has a happy end, every life has also ended happily. So, it is obvious that every worst condition also has progressive results. By piling your hands on one another or staking your head with one is not the solution or even option ever. In such circumstances always think of your and everyone's betterment, by thinking and doing what should be done ahead. It has 2 advantages-one is that your thinking process stabilizes. Other, your decision making process progresses. <figure rend="Resolve Your Delicate Mind Step 3 Version 4.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Gathering the Scattered Everyone</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Make everyone calm. In adverse circumstances, you must calm the ones who are high BP patients and low BP patients. High BP boils the body and annoys the mind in a way that the thinking stream is resistant to any kind of happiness or other distraction because the person wants to focus at his/her condition and may suffer from any breathing problem and unconsciousness. Go to them, grip their shoulders tightly and warm up and rub their hands if they are low BP patients. Tell everyone about chanting the mantra OM and long breaths with some cold water. <figure rend="Resolve Your Delicate Mind Step 4 Version 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Stop weeps of everyone. As already told weeping is not the option, stop others from shedding tears. Supply them the warmth of your support and some hearty confidence. This is because, when you see your loved ones crying, your mind becomes careworn and troubled. <figure rend="Resolve Your Delicate Mind Step 5 Version 4.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
