<text id="autogum_whow_doc312" title="Hold a Fork" shortTile="hold-fork" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-02-15" dateModified="2019-09-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Hold-a-Fork" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Hold a Fork</head><p>Proper table etiquette may vary depending on where you are. There are two traditional Western schools of eating with a fork and knife: the European "continental" style, and the American "cut-and-switch" or "zig-zag" style. However, the American version may have actually begun several hundred years ago in France. In most modern settings, however, it doesn't much matter how you hold the fork as long as you're able to eat efficiently.
</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Eating "European Style"</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Hold your fork in your left hand. Most European eaters keep the knife in their right hand for cutting, and they keep the fork in their left hand for eating. In the American style, eaters switch the fork over to their right hand to eat the pieces that they have cut. Traditionally, this is the main difference between the European and American forking styles. The European style is often considered more efficient because you don't have to remove the fork from you hand until you are done eating. <figure rend="Hold a Fork Step 2.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you're setting the table for "European-style" eating: make sure to arrange the fork on the left-hand side of the plate, and the knife on the right-hand side.</item></list></item>
<item>Use the fork with the tines facing down. This is traditional European etiquette. Be aware, however, that many modern Europeans not longer pay much heed to which way their tines are facing. Hold the handle between your thumb and your middle, ring, and pinky fingers. Place your index finger at the end of the handle where it meets the base of the fork tines. Let the end of the handle rest in the crease of your palm. <figure rend="Hold a Fork Step 3.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The lower you place your index finger on the fork handle, the more leverage you'll have as you eat your food.</item></list></item>
<item>Pick up knife in your right hand. Hold it in your hand in the same closed-fist manner that you hold your fork. Use it to rake the food onto your fork. Fold or push the food onto the tines of your fork with your knife if it is a salad or soft food. Use a gentle sawing motion with the knife if you are cutting meat, pizza or a similar food. You can actually push more food securely onto your fork with the European method than with the scooping American method. <figure rend="Hold a Fork Step 5.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Eat your meal. Insert the fork into your mouth with the tines still scooping down. Don't turn the fork or put it into your right hand. When you are finished, rest your fork and knife parallel on the plate with the tines facing down. If you see the plate as a clock face: the tines and blade should be at 10 o'clock, and the handles at 4 o'clock. <figure rend="Hold a Fork Step 9.360p.mp4"></figure></item></list>
<head>Eating "American Style"</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Cut food with the knife in your right hand and the fork in your left. Hold the food in place with the tines of your fork. Then, saw with the knife to slice the food item into a bite-sized piece. This part is essentially the same as the European method. <figure rend="Hold a Fork Step 13.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Point the tines down. According to traditional "etiquette," your tines should face down, with your palm wrapped around the end of the handle. Extend your index finger to the base of the fork. <figure rend="Hold a Fork Step 11.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't worry about which way the tines are turned. It may be easier to pick up food if you turn your tines upward, like a shovel. Most modern Americans do not pay much heed to which way the tines are facing.</item></list></item>
<item>Switch your fork to your right hand to eat. After you've cut the piece of food, place your knife on the edge of the plate. Switch your fork to your right hand. The end of the fork will rest in the area between your thumb and index finger. Use your right hand to bring the food to your mouth, and then switch the fork back over to your left hand so that you can cut another piece with the knife in your right hand. Repeat, switching hands each time you take a bite. <figure rend="Hold a Fork Step 14.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered">
<item>The American method may be more efficient if you cut your entire meal into pieces before you switch the fork to your right hand. This way, you won't have to keep switching the utensils back and forth.</item></list></item>
<item>Decide which way is more efficient. Many modern eaters and etiquette critics claim that the European style is less formal and more efficient than the American method. It is less disruptive to the eating process. Know that archaic social rules notwithstanding, there is truly no "right" or "wrong" way to hold a fork as long as you can eat your meal.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Set your napkin in your lap before you pick up your utensil.</item>
<item>European-style eating may take some practice if you're used to the American method. However, it may be easier and more efficient to eat your meal in this fashion.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Table setting</item>
<item>Food</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
