<text id="autogum_whow_doc627" title="Apply the God Factor to Your Business" shortTile="apply-god-factor" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2016-07-14" dateModified="2019-02-05" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Apply-the-God-Factor-to-Your-Business" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Apply the God Factor to Your Business</head><p>Start Up and stay up</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>"&gt; First, you should off course come up with an ideal business idea and plan then, a business name. Just the fundamental stuffs mainly but, don’t forget to think big. How you do this is up to you really you can go from conducting a feasibility study or what not, to just spending more time at home with your neighbors figuring out what services are missing or lacking in your hood.</item>
<item>ne"&gt; Secondly, you start up by first getting capital. You should start small but, remember think big and grow fast (Fela Durotoye). If you are able to fund the business yourself well, good for you but, if you can’t; get investors check www.nairaland.com/investment, www.founded.com/ or just Google it (www.google.com/search ). You can also lend your capital from friends and family if you are trust worthy or get a bank loan. Next you set up your shop, store or whatever, and you can also set up online easy; Google it or better still hire experts if you don’t know any, trywww.SoutechVentures.com.</item>
<item>"&gt; Thirdly, you market your product or service the cheapest way to go is online marketing. Trust me no marketing no profits also, online is the freest way to go. If you have enough capital make handbills, banners, T-shirts, print nylons etc. but if you want free or cheap marketing go online you can just hire a specialist try www.SoutechVentures.com they’ve got all you will need. You can also learn for free by taking internet marketing fundamental courses on www.pushcv.com/course. Register your business on Google Place, yahoo local, Microsoft Bing etc. before all that register your business with the CAC not that anyone is searching for your business there.</item>
<item>ge-newline"&gt; Most importantly The God Factor. Everybody can figure out how to start and run a business online or anywhere else but, you need an extra/supernatural wisdom to keep it afloat. God created us to be able to know/see with our hearts; there is more to us than what we can see, hear, smell, and touch. The God Factor is the faith tool you need for your business and for your life {Hebrew 11:1 now faith is the assurance of things hoped for, the conviction/evidence of things not seen (in the physical)}. Faith is real; as real as you and me it is the ability to receive what you have asked and understand that you have received it now and not praying to receive it later. Faith is like when you ordered that car or whatever from a shop or a person abroad or anywhere. You have the receipt you know it’s yours. You’ve seen pictures all that is left, is for it to get to your physical location. Faith is the receipt, Faith are those pictures, and Faith is that tracking software that tracks its location; that tells you that it’s still on the way. At this point you rejoices, you tell people about that thing that’s on its way. You are excited everyone around you is excited you don’t get surprised when you see it you’ve already seen it. The God Factor is the most important tool grab onto the reality of your successful business and by the time it arrives at your door, you would have already ordered/seen the next level. {By faith we understand that the universe was created by the word of God, so that what is seen was not made out of things that are visible Verse 3}.</item></list>
</text>
