<text id="autogum_whow_doc030" title="Navigate Pixiv" shortTile="navigate-pixiv" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-07-16" dateModified="2018-10-11" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Navigate-Pixiv" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Navigate Pixiv</head><p>Pixiv is a popular Japanese website that serves as a place for artists to showcase their work. Top Japanese artists place their work on here for a variety of franchises, including some original works of their own. Be wary, however; mature artwork is allowed on this website, and sometimes may not be tagged as mature by accident. This article will show you how to browse the website with minimum fuss. No account is needed, but a translator is recommended.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Bring up the website. Bring up Pixiv by searching for it through a search engine. You can use Google, Bing, or anyone you like. You can also use the hyperlink <ref target="https://www.pixiv.net/">www.pixiv.net</ref> to jump directly to the website.</item>
<item>Begin searching. On the top, you will find the search bar. This bar is your gateway to the larger site. Start with an English-language tag, as this can will help you find the more populated tags. Alternatively, you can look for the Japanese terminology of whatever you’re searching for and put that into the search bar. Then, when you have your term, press  to search.</item>
<item>Examine the art. This is where you can find the artwork on Pixiv. Up top, you will notice some “tags.” These can link to other subjects which could be of interest to you. Click on a picture to view the image, and click on the bottom numbers to see more images.</item>
<item>View the artwork. When you click on a picture, you will be presented with the above screen. This displays a miniature preview of the artist’s work. The “Submitted Works” section includes other work by the artist, while the “Bookmarked Works” section includes work the artist likes and recommends to others.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>There are two kinds of tags on Pixiv: franchise tags, which represent the franchise the art belongs to (represented by figure 1 in the image); and image tags, which serve as definition of themes of the picture, of which up to 10 exist (represented by figure 2 in the image). This is where the internet translation program comes in. You can use this to find out what the tag means if you don’t know yourself. Click on a tag to begin browsing.</item>
<item>If you click on the name of the artist, you will see their page. This lists just about all the work the artist has submitted to the website. You can also find their bookmarks, works the artist has liked, and who they follow, as well as the artists they recommend.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Pixiv does not have any limits on what content can be submitted, and while most pornography is filtered, some of it is not. Be very careful when you are browsing, especially for popular topics.</item></list>
</text>
