<text id="autogum_whow_doc452" title="Unclog a Toilet with Dish Soap" shortTile="unclog-toilet-dish" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-10-11" dateModified="2019-05-13" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Unclog-a-Toilet-with-Dish-Soap" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Unclog a Toilet with Dish Soap</head><p>A clogged toilet is something we've all experienced: the rising of water to the brim, the sense of panic as it doesn't stop, the scurrying for the plunger. But dish soap is a simple solution that can bring you back from the fate of a flood of toilet water with nothing but your favorite product and some hot water! Whether you start by pouring the boiling water into the toilet or adding dish soap, if all goes well the end result is unclogged piping.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Soaking the Bowl in Boiling Water</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Locate the toilet flapper and stop water flow from the tank. Remove the lid from your toilet tank and locate the toilet flapper. The flappers are typically black, blue, or red and provide the seal for the flush valve. Either close it using the chain attached or with your hands. <figure rend="Unclog a Toilet with Dish Soap Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>To prevent water supply altogether, turn the handle behind the toilet near the floor in a clockwise direction. If you're having trouble turning the handle, apply an oil spray.</item>
<item>Don't worry about contaminated water in the toilet tank—germs do not enter this part of the fixture. If you're worried, wash your hands thoroughly afterward.</item></list></item>
<item>Boil a  pot of water. Turn your stove on high heat and place a water-filled pot onto the stove. Then, cover your pot with a lid and wait for the water to boil. You can also fill the pot or bucket with hot water from the tap, but make sure it's as hot as possible—the higher the temperature, the more effective it will be at fighting the clog. <figure rend="Unclog a Toilet with Dish Soap Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you only have a smaller pot or bucket, fill it up multiple times until you have about  of boiling, or very hot, water.</item></list></item>
<item>Pour  of hot water into the bowl. Pour gently and make sure the water doesn't pass the rim. Be careful not to spill any to avoid burning yourself. If your bucket has a metal handle, hold it up with one hand and tilt the bucket with your other hand by turning it from the bottom. <figure rend="Unclog a Toilet with Dish Soap Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Wait for the water to rise to the rim after pouring the water.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Adding Dish Soap</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Pour about  of dish soap into the water. The dish soap will float to the bottom of the bowl because it is heavier and denser than water. Let the soap sit for about 20 to 30 minutes. After this time, the water should lower. <figure rend="Unclog a Toilet with Dish Soap Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always pour the water slowly and be careful not to overflow the bowl.</item></list></item>
<item>Pour another  of boiling water into the toilet. Fill another  pot with hot water and place it onto the stove to boil. Again, hot water is also effective, but boiling water is always ideal. <figure rend="Unclog a Toilet with Dish Soap Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Turn the stove on high heat for the fastest results.</item></list></item>
<item>Continue pouring water into the toilet and let it sit. After about 2 to 3 rounds, flush the toilet to check if the clog is gone. Be sure to give each  of boiling water about 20 minutes to settle. <figure rend="Unclog a Toilet with Dish Soap Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Wait overnight if your toilet is still not flushing properly. If it's not unclogged in the morning, try using a plunger.</item></list></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Plunge_a_Toilet">Plunge your toilet</ref> if it's still clogged. Even if you've already tried to plunge the clog, dish soap can weaken it, so it's always worth a second shot! Place the plunger into the bowl and aim it at the hole. Press down sharply in short, fast strokes, and be sure to lift sharply to create suction. After 4 or 5 full strokes, lift the plunger on the last upward motion <figure rend="Unclog a Toilet with Dish Soap Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Run the plunger under hot water for 30 seconds prior to plunging to warm the rubber up.</item>
<item>If the clog still doesn't come loose, call a plumber.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item> bucket</item>
<item>Dish soap</item>
<item>Plunger</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always wash your hands clean with warm water and soap after working on your toilet.</item>
<item>Never plunge your toilet immediately after using drain cleaner.</item></list>
</text>
