<text id="autogum_whow_doc147" title="Facilitate a Group" shortTile="facilitate-group" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-04-05" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Facilitate-a-Group" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Facilitate a Group</head><p>A group facilitator’s job is important, because they encourage communication without strongly influencing the discussion. Successful group leaders can control and enhance a group with good planning, open-ended questions and positive reinforcement.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Organizing a Group</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Announce your group. Choose the best possible mode of communication to reach anyone who might be interested. Try multiple channels if possible.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are organizing a work group, use company email. <figure rend="Facilitate a Group Step 1Bullet1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you are organizing a school group, ask for telephone numbers or emails. Also, research a school LISTSERV to encourage new membership. <figure rend="Facilitate a Group Step 1Bullet2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you are hosting a church group, make sure the meeting time is in the church bulletin. <figure rend="Facilitate a Group Step 1Bullet3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you are starting a support group, post the information at hospitals, online and in counselor/doctor offices. <figure rend="Facilitate a Group Step 1Bullet4.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Research possible topics ahead of time. Look online and in books for ideas on what topics to choose. If you are leading a work group, get all the research and reports sent out a few days ahead of time so that everyone can be on the same page for the meeting. <figure rend="Facilitate a Group Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Learn time management skills before you facilitate a group. Starting and ending meetings require an outspoken person who will keep track of time and any remaining agenda items. Wear a watch and refer back to it occasionally to make sure you are on track.
<list type="unordered"><item>Announce the start and end time in your communication with group members. Also, consider announcing topics and the time structure so that members can adequately prepare. <figure rend="Facilitate a Group Step 3Bullet1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>One important structure to announce is whether it is an open group and whether the group has “cross-talk.” This means that the group can discuss, rather than just sharing an opinion when it is their turn. <figure rend="Facilitate a Group Step 3Bullet2.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Mentally prepare yourself for facilitation. It can be exhausting to lead a group, especially for professional and emotional topics. Get a good night sleep and do some deep breathing techniques before you start the group meeting. <figure rend="Facilitate a Group Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Set up an environment that facilitates discussion. Sitting in a circle is a classic approach, because no one is left out. Move chairs into a circle before anyone else arrives. <figure rend="Facilitate a Group Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Avoid a “classroom” approach. If everyone must see you, but can’t see each other, you will be more of an authority figure and have a harder time encouraging discussion between group members.</item></list></item>
<item>Practice neutrality. It is your job to encourage participation without affecting the outcome. If you are an opinionated person, practice holding your tongue in political or opinionated discussions. <figure rend="Facilitate a Group Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Starting Discussions</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Introduce yourself. Keep it brief, but announce your qualifications or interest in the success of the group. Aim to keep the introduction between one and two minutes long. <figure rend="Facilitate a Group Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>State the group rules if they are necessary for the function of the group. Groups like Alcoholics Anonymous have steps and traditions that are to be read at the beginning of each meeting. Don’t go overboard with rules, as they might restrict expression in the group. <figure rend="Facilitate a Group Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Announce the purpose of the meeting. If there are desired outcomes or agenda points, review them now. Set times if necessary. <figure rend="Facilitate a Group Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Adjust the structure of group discussion based on how many members you have. If you are leading a small group, you may be able to go around in a circle (Round Robin) so that everyone has a chance to speak. If you are leading a large group, you may need to encourage the raising of hands or free speaking. <figure rend="Facilitate a Group Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Announce the structure of the group before you start, so that everyone has the same expectations.</item></list></item>
<item>Don’t fall into “teaching behaviors.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> This is when you begin to answer questions, state facts or speak frequently. You are serving as a neutral party, not a teacher. <figure rend="Facilitate a Group Step 11.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Facilitating Discussion</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Ask open-ended questions. Avoid asking questions to the group with yes or no answers. If they must be yes/no answers, ask group members to elaborate on why that is the answer. <figure rend="Facilitate a Group Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Continue with follow-up questions if discussion doesn’t start immediately. Good follow-up questions include “How does that change the way you feel about X,Y,Z?” and “How do you think that applies to other issues that we are discussing?” <figure rend="Facilitate a Group Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Break the group into smaller groups for projects or intimate discussion. If you are afraid that the group is too large to encourage adequate participation, small group work is a good way to encourage everyone in a group to interact. <figure rend="Facilitate a Group Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Give positive reinforcement. Encourage positive interactions. Thank people for their contributions. <figure rend="Facilitate a Group Step 15.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don’t be critical. Even if your group is created for critiques, criticism should be only give in small doses. Start each comment with positive reinforcement.</item></list></item>
<item>Suggest an energizer activity if you have a long meeting. Between subjects, encourage people to play a game, watch a related YouTube clip or get up and move around. <figure rend="Facilitate a Group Step 16.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Deal with disagreements by finding common ground. It is your job as the group leader to recognize potential arguments and try to move on in a productive way. <figure rend="Facilitate a Group Step 17.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Say, “It sounds like we have a difference of opinion.”</item>
<item>“Different points of view are encouraged in our group.”</item>
<item>“It sounds like you both feel passionate about this.”</item>
<item>“It seems that we can agree on X,Y,Z.”</item></list></item>
<item>Encourage other people to lead future discussions. This is a good way for people to feel joint ownership of a group and its goals. <figure rend="Facilitate a Group Step 18.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Create an evaluation process. Ask people to take a questionnaire or discuss changes or issues wit you. <figure rend="Facilitate a Group Step 19.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Watch</item>
<item>Research/reports</item>
<item>Email addresses/flyers</item>
<item>Chairs in a circle</item>
<item>Evaluation form</item></list>
</text>
