<text id="autogum_whow_doc548" title="Research Salary Ranges and Benefits for a Veterinarian" shortTile="research-salary-ranges" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-04-17" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Research-Salary-Ranges-and-Benefits-for-a-Veterinarian" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Research Salary Ranges and Benefits for a Veterinarian</head><p>One way to begin preparing for a career is to learn about the salary and benefits typically offered to members of the considered profession. When researching veterinarian salary ranges and benefits, there are a number of resources available to you over the Internet. Using multiple sources will allow you to develop a realistic understanding of the earnings you might expect. Salary research can give you an advantage when considering whether to pursue a career and when negotiating a salary with an employer, either at the time of hire or during review.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Determine the type of veterinary work you want to research. There are a number of different jobs within the veterinary field, including veterinary technicians, nurses and veterinarians. Each position may require different education and training. Before you begin to research veterinarian salary ranges, make note of those jobs within the field that most interest you. <figure rend="Research Salary Ranges and Benefits for a Veterinarian Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Write down your work and educational history for reference. Be sure to include details about your highest educational level and the number of years you have worked within the veterinarian field. When you begin research with some sources, you will need to refer to this data in order to retrieve the most accurate results. <figure rend="Research Salary Ranges and Benefits for a Veterinarian Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Collect salary information for the type of position and level you are researching. The United States Department of Labor and veterinary associations are reliable resources from which to gather salary information. You can also research veterinarian salary ranges at the state level by contacting your state's department of labor. Some job boards, such as Monster, also provide salary information through third-party resources. <figure rend="Research Salary Ranges and Benefits for a Veterinarian Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Note what reported salaries include, beyond hourly or annual pay. Sometimes, when salary information is reported, it includes benefits, bonuses, vacation and sick time, company-sponsored insurance plans and company contributions to retirement plans and stock options. By reading carefully, you will be able to understand exactly what comprises each reported salary for a given job title within the veterinary field. Sites that report salaries in this way enable you to research veterinary benefits while investigating salary information as well. <figure rend="Research Salary Ranges and Benefits for a Veterinarian Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Analyze the results. It's possible, and likely, that results will vary somewhat depending on the source. Some sources, such as salary calculators found on many job boards, gather their data by asking visitors to input information related to their job and career. Other sources report directly from employers. Sources such as industry associations might poll association members (this is important to note if the association is affiliated with a particular university or state). When analyzing your research, remember to consider such elements as repayment of student loans (if applicable) and the cost of living in your current or intended area. <figure rend="Research Salary Ranges and Benefits for a Veterinarian Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Gather information from as many reliable sources as possible. This will enable you to develop a more accurate understanding of your research.</item>
<item>Keep your expectations realistic. Before beginning your research, avoid making presumptions about how much you will earn as a veterinarian or what benefits you will receive.</item></list>
</text>
