<text id="autogum_whow_doc115" title="Build a Better Reputation Online" shortTile="build-better-reputation" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2016-05-12" dateModified="2018-09-12" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Build-a-Better-Reputation-Online" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Build a Better Reputation Online</head><p>When we want to learn more about another person, the first place we turn is to Google. Every day, over 100 million names are searched on Google. Did you know most HR professionals and recruiters are required to Google potential employees during the hiring decision process? If you want to improve your reputation online in order to build a personal "brand", start with step one, below.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Secure a website with yourname.com. Your domain name is critical for your personal brand and to make it easier to establish your website. The domain name can be purchased from your preferred registrar, but, to be effective, it should be made up of your full name and have the “.com” extension if available. If the .com version is not available, there are other extensions available that will work. Regardless of the extension you choose, the important takeaway is to include your full name. Your website should include some important information that will help the search engines and your visitors learn more about you. At the very least, you should provide:
<list type="unordered"><item>A detailed biography of yourself</item>
<item>An explanation of what people can expect from working with you</item>
<item>Links to your social media profiles</item>
<item>Blog that's updated regularly</item></list></item>
<item>Create and optimize personal profiles on all the major social platforms. It often seems like there’s a new social media platform that “all the cool kids are using” every other day. Before you start jumping into the latest thing, though, make sure that you are fully established on the major platforms. This means you should create and optimize a profile on Facebook, Pinterest, Twitter, Tumblr, Instagram, and Google+.
<list type="unordered"><item>Optimize your profile by always using your full name on each profile, and take the time to fill out the profile on each of these platforms in entirety. Always add a link back to your website within the profile section of the social profile. Links on social media are often considered higher-quality links because social sites have a high web authority from the get-go. Even if your Facebook page is new, it’s likely to rank high in the search results.  It may sound obvious, but make sure that you include a working link to your website in your content as well as every social profile you have. In addition to increasing traffic to your site, it’s also highly valuable for link building.</item></list></item>
<item>Blog with fresh content. Google loves fresh, relevant content, and a simple blog that you update regularly constantly freshens up your site and gives your visitors a reason to keep coming back.  A blog is a great place to share your personal experiences in leadership, mentoring, entrepreneurial success, or challenges you have overcome. Each individual blog post doesn’t have to be long, but it should be relevant and provide some engaging information.
<list type="unordered"><item>The most important part of blogging, though, is consistency. If you keep to a regular blogging schedule, both the search engines and your visitors will know when to expect something new – and they’ll show up to check it out. Once you create this content, you can then inform all your followers about it by sharing it on your social media networks. This helps promote your blog while simultaneously increasing your social presence.</item></list></item>
<item>Stay active on social media. You’ve signed up for the major social media networks, now it’s time to use them. Staying active on social media helps people learn a little more about you and start building a personal connection. It lends a personable touch to your business efforts and creates opportunities to promote your personal brand.
<list type="unordered"><item>As you build a strong following, you can create and curate some great, relevant content. Have you created a great new blog? Share that with your followers. Have you discovered some other great content on the internet? Share that with your followers.   You can use social content to link to your website, but do it carefully. While these links are a great way to build website traffic and search engine rankings, too much will feel like you’re trying to bury them in advertisements.</item></list></item>
<item>Do guest blogging if you can. A guest blog is a chance to share your expertise with others in the industry. Many websites are always looking for new content, new angles, and new writers. You can reach out to these sites and find opportunities to write a blog that answers important questions or shares some of your unique experiences. This is a great way to build your reputation around the internet. You may find opportunities with beauty blogs, leadership blogs, and other relevant categories where you can develop a strong presence and new relationships with industry insiders. When it’s appropriate, you can start to link back to relevant pages on your own website, which will help with your Google rankings and increase traffic.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>These six steps are not meant to live in isolation. They are tied very closely together and rely on each other to produce the best results. A holistic approach that combines quality websites, active social presence, and a flow of new, relevant content will build a much stronger foundation that will secure more spaces on the front page of the search results. Your social media will send visitors to your website. Your website will host important content and engaging blogs. Your blogs and social media presence can build your reputation so other websites will want to have you write for them. All of these efforts can produce links that tie back to your website and other positive properties. Each of these steps plays an important role in establishing an online reputation. As you take a more comprehensive approach, it will be much easier to maintain your search engine standings.</item></list>
</text>
