<text id="autogum_whow_doc211" title="Create a Long Term Care Plan" shortTile="create-long-term" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2016-05-13" dateModified="2019-09-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Create-a-Long-Term-Care-Plan" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Create a Long Term Care Plan</head><p>Financial security today and in the future is what most of us aim for. However, no matter how carefully you plan, your finances and quality of life can still crumble if you are unprepared for long-term care.  Long-term care planning involves going through a myriad of concerns, but the process becomes more bearable if you know what steps you need to take. With this guide, start planning for long-term care today and involve your family in doing so.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Know your needs. Nobody can say for sure what your long-term care needs will be, but there are several ways to help you have a forecast.
<list type="unordered"><item>Look at your present health situation. Do you have a current condition? Are you in any risk of incurring illness or injury because of your lifestyle or job? At the same time, look into your family's health background? Are you susceptible to certain health conditions that run in your bloodline? As you think about these factors, you can consult your doctor so that you'll have a better assessment of your possible long-term care needs in the future.</item></list></item>
<item>Explore different care options. Long-term care can come from different sources and can be administered in different settings. Learn what these are, determine what's available to you, and decide which among the options you prefer most.
<list type="unordered"><item>In most cases, loved ones and family members become the main providers of care when a long-term care event takes place. Though they usually assume the role of caregivers out of love and concern, you also need to consider how this situation can affect their job, income, relationships and overall quality of life.</item>
<item>Meanwhile, long-term care can also be provided by professionals. Depending on the level of care needed, care services can be administered in the home, assisted living facilities, adult day care centers, or nursing homes.</item></list></item>
<item>Learn about the cost of care in your area. As you create a plan, make sure that you're familiar with how much long-term care costs in the area where you intend to receive care. This will help you gauge how much you need for care-related expenses.The cost of different care services and settings vary from state to state. For instance, the median annual cost of a private room in a nursing home in Florida is $96,725, whereas in South Carolina, the annual average is only at $75,008.</item>
<item>Determine how you're going to cover care expenses. Care-related expenses can be covered in different ways. You can opt for self-insurance and pay from your own pocket, purchase long-term care insurance or hybrid products like life insurance or annuities with long-term care coverage, or seek assistance from Medicaid. Each payment option has its own sets of pros and cons. You need to carefully examine these alongside your financial situation to know which is most suitable for you. Asking the help of a professional can help you in doing so.</item>
<item>Create the necessary documents. Advance directives such as a health care power of attorney and living will should also be part of your long-term care plan. These documents are essential because they will serve as your mouthpiece should you become unable to decide and speak for yourself.
<list type="unordered"><item>A health care power of attorney states the name of the person who will be responsible for making health care related decisions for you when you can no longer do so.</item>
<item>Meanwhile, living will is a document that contains your wishes, preferences, and requests when it comes to medical treatment and health care.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
