<text id="autogum_whow_doc601" title="Find Your Inner Strength" shortTile="find-inner-strength" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-11-07" dateModified="2018-10-05" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Find-Your-Inner-Strength" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Find Your Inner Strength</head><p>This article isn't about being strong and defending yourself. It's about showing your INNER strength which means emotion and power. NOT FINISHED YET!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Overcoming Self-Destructive Behaviour</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Learn to love how you are. If someone doesn't like you, then who cares? You are YOU and you should love yourself more and more each day. You don't have to be similar to everyone. Being different is the most important thing of all.</item>
<item>To be very healthy, DO NOT smoke. Smoking is so bad for your health, and can lead to lung cancer and loss/shortage of life. It's very hard to stop when you've already started.</item>
<item>When you eat too much junk food, your body may not like it. Soon you may become fatter and no one likes that! To be slim eat fruit, vegetables, and meat. Anything like chocolate, cake, and chips are bad for your health, and can damage your body. Refined sugars and saturated fats are health disasters waiting to happen!</item>
<item>Try to avoid getting sick. If you see someone who has caught a cold, don't get too close to them. Try to avoid getting cancer or breaking a leg, and be careful where you head! Falling down the stairs, on the road, dropping from a building. Be SO careful!</item>
<item>Lastly, if someone you hate or a bully tries to hurt you in some way, STAY AWAY. If you are so close to them, then act nice to them. Bullies hate when you do that. If nothing works, try a compliment. If it still won't work, then you must defend yourself with your INNER strength and FAITH.</item></list>
<head>Fighting Health Challenges</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Take very good care of your health. There are many kind of causes out there causing injury, so look out for them!</item>
<item>If you SO BADLY want to lose wait, and feel stronger, go on health shows and challenges. Usually people drop half their weight or more.</item>
<item>Some medicine can help your muscles. Also, milk can help your muscles grow. But, inner strength is when your emotions help you become strong. It happens!</item>
<item>Everyone knows drugs are bad for you, but medical drugs are ok. They help your body and can clear yourself from cancer.</item>
<item>Maybe you could stop the health challenges and diets and stuff. Instead, be yourself. Strength isn't everything, and soon one day you may not be strong, but you won't turn into a bully. Sometimes things like this happen, so watch out!</item></list>
<head>Powering Through Loss</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>When a very well loved person dies, it is hard not to cry. But, to help you power on and stop worrying, you could maybe talk to a friend or family member.</item>
<item>Another thing to do is to write about it and express your feelings in journals and diaries. Soon, it won't sound so bad, and you won't be teared up in agony anymore.</item>
<item>If you are still crying and don't know what to do, try remembering all your cherished moments with that particular person in your life. You will always remember the person who helped you get through life, be happy after tears, and make you feel good about yourself.</item>
<item>Sharing your story with others can help you feel better. Talking about it to a teacher, friends, and your parents can help you soften those tears.</item>
<item>If all else fails, and you are still teared up in sadness, pretend that he/she is still living. Daydream/dream/act out plays and stories of how he/she is still living and as good as ever. Then, he/she wouldn't be in his/her grave, after all! He/she will be with you only.</item></list>
<head>Moving Past Disabilities</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>There are many ways to show people that you are in pain. I will tell you how to feel better about the way that you are in pain and misfortune. Some painful stuff include:
<list type="unordered"><item>Wheelchair</item>
<item>Crutches</item>
<item>Blood</item>
<item>Crying</item></list></item>
<item>Wheelchairs are used for people who can't walk anymore. If you can't walk and you are in a wheelchair, people may stare at you. If you can't ride a wheelchair well, get a best friend or family member to help you wheel along.</item>
<item>People use crutches when they can walk, but it hurts. If crutches is the way to go, don't feel too bad. If you find it hard to hop for so long, get someone to help you while you are hopping. Maybe, they can help you hop on your foot. Hold you while you hop, so you don't fall over.</item>
<item>Blood is painful, and can be red, but also maroon. To fix blood pouring down your legs or arms or stuff, get a bandage or a band-aid (bandage would be better) and wrap it around where your blood is. Remember to change your bandage once a day or it may stick there forever! Soon, when it doesn't hurt anymore, get rid of the bandages, and you're fine!</item>
<item>Crying can tell that something is wrong. Everyone cries sometime, and crying can bring lots of attention. Feeling lost? Broke your leg? Your life is horrible? Many people will usually come to your rescue. And when you tell them about your pain, they will almost always help. Crying is nothing to be ashamed of, and can save your life sometimes!</item></list>
<head>Accepting the New Normal</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Being different is important, and no one is the same. Blonde, brunette, red, black, green, purple, grey, white hair. Blue, green, yellow, grey, orange, hazel eyes. You could have green hair, white eyes, and wear crazy clothes, and you could be known as beautiful. It doesn't matter what you where, as long as it's something!</item></list>
</text>
