<text id="autogum_whow_doc014" title="Crowdfund a Concert" shortTile="crowdfund-concert" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-09-27" dateModified="2019-10-11" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Crowdfund-a-Concert" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Crowdfund a Concert</head><p>This article explains how a musician, a band or their teams can launch and run a crowdfunding campaign for a concert, show or a gig.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Plan your program. Decide on your tracklist, host, supporting acts, any additional entertainment, like quests or contests.</item>
<item>Calculate your budget. Consider what costs an event you are planning is going to include:
<list type="unordered"><item>venue</item>
<item>artist and host fees</item>
<item>equipment rentals</item>
<item>staffing the event</item>
<item>transportation and accommodation costs</item>
<item>stage decor</item></list></item>
<item>Select the crowdfunding platform. You can go with a general-purpose crowdfunding platform (Kickstarter, Indiegogo) or a concert-specific platform (Show4me).</item>
<item>Produce promotional materials. Prepare an exciting, engaging description of your event, promotional images, posters, flyers, images for social media. A promo video can be a great way to make your campaign much more enticing for potential concertgoers, as well as existing fans.</item>
<item>Fill out the campaign page and launch. Enter all the information about your campaign: the title of your show, prospective date and venue (subject to change), description, upload video and photos. On concert-specific platforms for crowdfunding you can list event sponsors or any age restrictions. Set ticket types and prices and launch your campaign.</item>
<item>Promote your campaign. Announce your launch on all your best social media, let your fans and friends know, put up posters close to your prospective location and/or handout flyers, run ads if you have the budget to.</item>
<item>Set your date and distribute tickets. Once your minimum funding budget is met, you can contact and book the venue and set your performance date. If you are using a general-purpose crowdfunding platform, you'll have to take care of ticket design, production and distribution. If you are using a concert-specific crowdfunding platform, the tickets will be generated and delivered to attendees' inboxes automatically. Withdraw funds to finance your production.</item>
<item>Hold your event. Complete the preparations for your show and host the event!</item>
<item>Thank contributors. With all the effort you've put into promoting your show and getting all the contributions, you wouldn't want that to go to waste. Keep your supporters engaged with your music, art and career by running a fan hub on a social media platform or continue interacting with your backers on the crowdfunding platform, as some offer the social network-like features, making it easier to crowdfund your next event.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure your campaign description is exciting and you know exactly the audience you want to attend your event. The more your description appeals to your target audience, the better are your chances of getting the campaign fully funded.</item>
<item>If you want your tickets to be sent out to your backers automatically, go with a concert-specific crowdfunding platform.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>The success of your campaign is contingent on your promotional efforts. The bigger the budget, the more promotional effort your campaign will require.</item></list>
</text>
