<text id="autogum_whow_doc020" title="Burn MP3 to CD" shortTile="burn-mp-cd" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-11-07" dateModified="2019-03-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Burn-MP3-to-CD" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Burn MP3 to CD</head><p>Burning MP3 files to CD allows you to listen to your favorite tunes in CD players, which is convenient for those who lack digital media players and MP3 players. MP3 files can be burned to CD in most popular music player applications, including iTunes, Windows Media Player, RealPlayer, and Winamp.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>iTunes</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Launch iTunes and click on “File.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> <figure rend="Burn MP3 to CD Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on “New” and select “Playlist.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> <figure rend="Burn MP3 to CD Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Type a name for the playlist, then drag and drop songs from your iTunes library into the playlist window on the right. You must have a playlist created before you can burn songs to CD. <figure rend="Burn MP3 to CD Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Insert a blank CD-R disc into the optical disc drive in your computer. <figure rend="Burn MP3 to CD Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select your playlist and click on “File.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> <figure rend="Burn MP3 to CD Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select “Burn Playlist to Disc,” then select either “Audio CD” or “MP3 CD” as the disc format, based on your preference. <figure rend="Burn MP3 to CD Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on “Burn.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> The process will take up to several minutes to complete, and iTunes will notify you when burning is complete. If your playlist is too large to fit on disc, iTunes will prompt you to insert another disc to finish the burning process. <figure rend="Burn MP3 to CD Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Windows Media Player</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Launch Windows Media Player and click on the “Burn” tab. <figure rend="Burn MP3 to CD Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Drag and drop songs and playlists into the burn list on the right. The songs must be added to the burn list in the order in which you want them listed on the CD. <figure rend="Burn MP3 to CD Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Insert a blank CD-R disc into the optical disc drive in your computer. <figure rend="Burn MP3 to CD Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on the burn tab at the top right corner. The icon resembles a piece of paper with a green checkmark. <figure rend="Burn MP3 to CD Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select “Audio CD,” then click on “Start Burn.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> The process will take up to several minutes, and Windows Media Player will eject the CD when burning is complete. <figure rend="Burn MP3 to CD Step 12.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>RealPlayer</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Launch RealPlayer and click on the “Burn” tab. <figure rend="Burn MP3 to CD Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select “Audio CD Burner,” then insert a blank CD-R into the disc drive in your computer. <figure rend="Burn MP3 to CD Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on “Burn” at the top of RealPlayer. <figure rend="Burn MP3 to CD Step 15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on “Select CD Type” under Tasks in the right sidebar. <figure rend="Burn MP3 to CD Step 16.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select “Audio CD” or “MP3 CD,” then click on “OK.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> <figure rend="Burn MP3 to CD Step 17.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on “Add Tracks from my Library,” then select “All Music.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> <figure rend="Burn MP3 to CD Step 18.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Drag and drop tracks from the left into the burn list on the right. RealPlayer will keep you updated as to how much space is remaining on the disc as you move tracks to the burn list. <figure rend="Burn MP3 to CD Step 19.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on “Burn Your CD.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> The process will take up to several minutes to complete, and notify you when the CD has been burned successfully. <figure rend="Burn MP3 to CD Step 20.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Winamp</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Launch Winamp and insert a blank CD-R into the disc drive in your computer. <figure rend="Burn MP3 to CD Step 21.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on “View” and select “Media Library.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> <figure rend="Burn MP3 to CD Step 22.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select “Blank Disk” from the list under Media Library, then click on “Add” at the bottom of the Winamp window. <figure rend="Burn MP3 to CD Step 23.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select the playlist you want burned, or click on “Files” or “Folders” to search for music. <figure rend="Burn MP3 to CD Step 24.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select the tracks you want burned to CD, then click on “OK.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> <figure rend="Burn MP3 to CD Step 25.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on “Burn” at the bottom of Winamp, then select “Enable Burn-proof mode.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> <figure rend="Burn MP3 to CD Step 26.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on “Burn” in the Burn dialog box. The process will take up to several minutes to complete, and Winamp will notify you when the CD has been burned successfully. <figure rend="Burn MP3 to CD Step 27.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>When selecting a disc format, opt for “MP3 CD” if you want hundreds of songs burned to CD versus an average of 20 songs to CD. MP3 files can be compressed more efficiently than other file types, which allows for hundreds of audio tracks to be burned to a single disc.</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
