<text id="autogum_whow_doc198" title="Recognize a Good School for Your Ward&apos;s Admission" shortTile="recognize-good-school" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-07-23" dateModified="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Recognize-a-Good-School-for-Your-Ward%27s-Admission" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Recognize a Good School for Your Ward's Admission</head><p>Many parents rushed and admitted their ward(s) in most schools because of their packages presented during sensitisation. Mostly, the name of the school can be influential in the selection of the best Nursery School. When once the name of the school is an English type ending with either school or international; then may influenced the choice of any parent coming around the school for inquiry. Outside this, some schools may be attracted to rich parents when the tuition fee is of the high tone. If your school is low fee, you will attract low estate parents (average parents).The following are the steps to make proper decision when admitting your ward(s):</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>When you receive any information from a particular school through printing flyer, flex banner, radio jingle, television announcement, newspaper advert, website announcement, social media, verbal communication, sms, or phone call, First, read or listen carefully to get more details about the school. Note their phone number, email address, website address, school contact address, administrator or contact person and put it down on a piece of paper for your verification.</item>
<item>Pray for the true vision, prepare and visit the school on your own spare time. Do not inform them that you are coming. Surprise them with a visit. Do not drive down there if you have a car, but take a commercial vehicle and walk down to the school. You did this so as to know how they receive a rich and an average man.</item>
<item>Tell who ever is in charge to walk you around to see the facilities they have in place. Ask of restroom, canteen, playground, safety gargets, entrance and exist doors, Monster point, Library, etc. This is to enable you know how they have prepared to handle your kid(s) for you. Knowing that, school is a home away home.</item>
<item>Ask the school administrator if there is any insurance scheme governing the children in case of any incident in the school or at home. The typical example for school that has arranged for the insurance scheme for pupils can be seen on their flyers.</item>
<item>Ask the head of teachers the qualification of the employed teachers and custodians. The learning process of your child matters a lot, therefore, qualification and experience are required in this part. If possible, demand to see the CV (Curriculum Vitae) of the teacher who may happen to handle your kid in learning. Reason is that, most schools framed around telling people that they have qualified and experienced teachers just to get you admit your child, meanwhile they have none. Most schools employed SSCE (school leavers) to teach, which is not good for educational sector.</item>
<item>Ask them the admission process. If their admission into the school is just to obtain a form and pay fee, don't enroll your ward. A standard school will first receive you, give you a refreshing juice and before issuing admission form. The form is not a gateway to your admission, rather a step for entrance examination. After submission of the form, entrance exams shall be conducted upon the scheduled date. This exam is to access the child capability in the intended class and help for recommendation</item>
<item>Require to know the tuition fee. Don't be discouraged if the tuition is lower than your expectation. Most school can be high fee but no standard of teaching. Most school with low tuition fee employed qualified and experienced and updated teacher.</item>
<item>If your ward pass exams, rush and make payment. But before that, make sure you are briefed on the payment method. If the school has a corporate account, demand to know account name and number.</item>
<item>Special subjects are necessary to make enquiry if the school offers: Computer French</item></list>
<p>Creative arts Music Mathematics English Igbo etc</p>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>This steps is free in wikiHow</item></list>
</text>
