<text id="autogum_whow_doc467" title="Plant an Avocado Pit" shortTile="plant-avocado-pit" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-07-24" dateModified="2019-07-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Plant-an-Avocado-Pit" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Plant an Avocado Pit</head><p>Avocado is one of the beautiful fruits typically grown in summer. High in both flavor and vitamins, this fruit is also surprisingly easy to grow and nurture. It makes a simple, satisfying project for people of all ages. Though avocados may take a long time to bear fruit, something about homegrown avocados make it worth the wait! Read this article to learn how to grow an avocado; from pit to fruit. This fruit is delicious but also healthy with lots of vitamins.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Take an avocado and cut it in half. Be careful not to damage the pit (also known as an avocado seed). Use a knife and make a small cut in the avocado skin.  <figure rend="Cut an Avocado Without Touching the Flesh Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Twist both sides of the fruit to release the seed. Use a knife as needed to take out the pit.  <figure rend="Grow an Avocado As a Houseplant Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Rinse the avocado pit; make sure you don't damage it. The seed is the most crucial part of the process!   <figure rend="Grow an Avocado As a Houseplant Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Stick the 3 toothpicks in the avocado: careful not to poke it in the line in the center of the pit. Stick it in at approximately a 45-degree angle.  <figure rend="Grow an Avocado As a Houseplant Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take a plastic cup and fill it up with water. Place the avocado pit in the water. Soak at least half of the avocado pit. Next just put it in a warm, sunny spot (out of direct sunlight) on a windowsill, and let it sit there. Be patient; avocados take a long time to grow.  <figure rend="Grow an Avocado As a Houseplant Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Change the water on a daily basis. Remove it out of the old water and switch it out with new water. Make sure to wipe the avocado pit down; as the old water can cause the seed to rot over time.  <figure rend="Grow an Avocado As a Houseplant Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Allow the seed to sit in the cup when your seed starts sprouting and growing roots. Once the leaves start yellowing and curling up, it is a sign that it needs to be put in the soil.  <figure rend="Grow an Avocado As a Houseplant Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>When you plant the avocado pit in soil, don't put in the whole seed. The avocado will not grow completely if done so. Put half of the seed under soil and half of the seed above the dirt. Make sure to water the avocado regularly; avocados require a lot of water to bear fruit.  <figure rend="Grow an Avocado As a Houseplant Step 17.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If possible, plant the avocado near fully grown trees; this will aid with pollination.</item>
<item>You can also leave the seed outside for a week before you soak it in water. That makes it easier to peel the skin off.</item>
<item>Plant the seed outside in an undisturbed spot. Make sure it has lots of sunlight.</item>
<item>When your avocado tree gets larger, you may consider trimming it.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>The avocado needs time to grow. It will not sprout as fast as you think it will.</item></list>
</text>
