<text id="autogum_whow_doc595" title="Investigate the Perception Aggregate" shortTile="investigate-perception" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2010-06-03" dateModified="2019-01-27" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Investigate-the-Perception-Aggregate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Investigate the Perception Aggregate</head><p>Perception is actually a very subtle one to watch, because you can get an idea of it intellectually, but only until you see it will you see what's going on. While this does require a strong background in mindfulness or awareness of the sequence of rapid mental events, complete beginners can do this with the focus just on perception.
Here's what to look for.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Read <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Investigate_the_Feeling_Aggregate">Investigate the Feeling Aggregate</ref> or other similar works on the subject. Feeling and perceptions are very closely linked. <figure rend="Investigate the Perception Aggregate Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select a comfortable meditation posture. You can do this in day to day circumstances, but this one is harder to see as its usually buried under all the other feelings and senses. <figure rend="Investigate the Perception Aggregate Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Examine whatever feelings arise. Try to see the process of "recognition" or "awareness" or any words that mean knowing that a feeling has happened. <figure rend="Investigate the Perception Aggregate Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Study the recognition of those feelings - how, where, when and why. The aim of the game is to see the micro-processes in action. <figure rend="Investigate the Perception Aggregate Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Think about this. Feeling requires contact of the body (nerve endings etc) and the sense object (such as tension, body chemicals, sound, sight, taste etc), if there is no perception of the contact or feeling, the mind doesn't recognize either and feeling just doesn't register.</item></list></item>
<item>Look for the distinction or separation as well as the link connection between feelings and what happens afterwards in the mind. That distinction &amp; link is perception. <figure rend="Investigate the Perception Aggregate Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Consider the accuracy of it, is it 100% accurate and perceives everything? <figure rend="Investigate the Perception Aggregate Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Understand the order that it arises: <figure rend="Investigate the Perception Aggregate Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>first materiality - the body, physical objects and their characteristics,</item>
<item>then feeling,</item>
<item>then perception,</item>
<item>then mental fabrications, activities, constructions, formations, responses or any word that works for you.</item>
<item>After that comes the conscious states or any words that describes the mental states that support and dominate the others.</item></list></item>
<item>Try to see it happen in action. Trying to understand does not make understanding happen, although exploring the ideas can start the process. <figure rend="Investigate the Perception Aggregate Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try to consider why there is only 5 of these aggregates and explore things that happen. You might find everything slots into these 5. <figure rend="Investigate the Perception Aggregate Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Consider these 3 similes. They are more for the serious investigator of this subject, but make sense when you test them. <figure rend="Investigate the Perception Aggregate Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Materiality is like the sick room and the patient, feeling is the affliction of the sickness, perception is the provoking of the illness (because it makes you want it to go away), formations is the wanting of it to go away and the consciousness is like an incurable illness because it isn't ever free of feeling.</item>
<item>Materiality is the prison, feeling is the punishment, perception is the crime, mental formations are the punisher and the consciousness the punished.</item>
<item>Materiality is like a lump of atomic foam, feeling like a bubble on the water (because it doesn't last), perception is a mirage because it makes illusions (perception of the "me, mine" etc), mental formations like a banana or plantain trunk, because while it grows it doesn't have a core of solid heartwood. Consciousness is like a stage illusion. It isn't ever how it seems.</item></list></item>
<item>Finally consider the "un-manageability" or the "auto-pilot" nature of perception. Its not something we can turn on or off. When someone who studies perceptions with the angle of testing ownership, self or entity, they can make a breakthrough this way as they'll see the starting blocks of new thoughts, feelings and mental processes and that they are empty of any entity. Then illusions are broken and there are no mysteries left. <figure rend="Investigate the Perception Aggregate Step 11 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Take it a step at a time. It gets easier when you know what you are looking for as well as what you are seeing.</item>
<item>This really does take time. Perception isn't easy to see because its in between contact, feeling and the response to feeling. You have to break things down first to see it.</item>
<item>Perception is 9/10th's of the law. That is, "The Law" within each of us which is the basis of our understanding of all things external to ourselves. We form ad follow this individually based on our perception of the world, the people in it and factions involved from early childhood. What most fail to do to this day, is to 'Walk a mile in someone else's moccasins', which is to see from someone else's perspective. This lends insight, compassion, understanding, and discernment in place of judgementalism, prejudice and intolerance of our fellow man. Furthermore, egotism and self-centeredness, which are foundational to mental instability and civil unrest, are too easily fostered when we to limit our perception and fail to take others' into consideration.</item></list>
</text>
