<text id="autogum_whow_doc363" title="Make a Simple Solar Viewer" shortTile="make-simple-solar" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2009-03-10" dateModified="2019-09-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-a-Simple-Solar-Viewer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make a Simple Solar Viewer</head><p>You have probably been told never to look directly at the sun, but that begs the question “How do you study it?” The sun is very intense and can do serious damage to your eyes if you gaze at it for even a moment. Luckily, astronomers have a few tricks for getting around this. The most common way is to use a solar viewer, which allows you to see the sun's image on a piece of paper or cardboard. They are easy and inexpensive to make and use, and they give you the ability to safely study the sun.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Building a Pinhole Camera</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Cut a  square in a cardboard box. Cut into the short side of a cardboard box. This way, the light shining through the hole can travel the length of the box to the other side. Letting the light travel the length of the box will enlarge the image. You should use a box that is no less than  long to produce a clear, viewable image. <figure rend="Make a Simple Solar Viewer Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you do not have a cardboard box that is  long, you can cut smaller pieces of cardboard and tape or glue them together to make a box that is the appropriate length. Make sure the pieces are joined completely and that no light shines through the places where they are connected.</item></list></item>
<item>Cover the square with aluminum foil. Tape a piece of aluminum foil over the hole in the box. Aluminum foil will block excess light from shining through the hole you created. Be sure that the foil is pulled tight so that it is smooth. <figure rend="Make a Simple Solar Viewer Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make a small hole in the foil. Use a toothpick or a needle to prick a hole in the center of the aluminum foil. This will allow just a small amount of light to be focused through the hole and projected at the other end of the box. This will provide an image of the sun that is safe to look at. <figure rend="Make a Simple Solar Viewer Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Projecting the Image</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Tape up your screen. To improve the quality of your image, you can project it on a white screen. The easiest way to do this is to take blank white paper and tape it at the end of the viewer (furthest from the hole). One sheet of paper is sufficient. <figure rend="Make a Simple Solar Viewer Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Aim the pinhole at the sun. In order for your viewer to capture the an image of the sun, you have to aim it. Avoid looking at the sun to aim the viewer. Instead, point the viewer in the general direction of the sun and then move it around slowly until you see the sun on your screen. <figure rend="Make a Simple Solar Viewer Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>View the image of the sun. Once you have the sun on your screen, it is safe to look at. You do not need any safety glasses or other special equipment. The image is much less intense than actually looking at the sun. <figure rend="Make a Simple Solar Viewer Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Studying the Sun</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be safe. You should never look directly at the sun. Even doing so briefly can damage your eyes. You have to use a solar viewer to project the image or buy special glasses and/or telescopes that filter out enough light to be safe. <figure rend="Make a Simple Solar Viewer Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Sunglasses will NOT protect your eyes from the sun. Only special filtered lenses will be safe.</item></list></item>
<item>Watch for patterns. If you are serious about studying the sun, you can watch for patterns. Look for sunspots in your image (they will show up as dimmer spots on the image). Observe the sunspots over time and see how they move. <figure rend="Make a Simple Solar Viewer Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>To make accurate comparisons, you should observe the sun from the same place every time.</item></list></item>
<item>Brush up on your math skills. You can use some basic measurements of your image and viewer to find interesting facts about the sun. This is because the image you are viewing is a scaled down image of the sun. Even though it's smaller, it is proportional to the actual sun. For example, you can find the diameter of the sun by following these steps: <figure rend="Make a Simple Solar Viewer Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Divide the diameter of the image by the distance from the pinhole (the length of the box).</item>
<item>Multiply that answer by the distance between the earth and sun (approximately 150,000,000 kilometers or 93,000,000 miles)</item></list></item>
<item>Find other ways to watch the sun. You can watch the sun without a specially made solar viewer. Find a tree or other object that provides shade. If there are any holes or spaces in the object, you can study the spots of sun that shine through. You can also hold your hands up and study the sunlight that shines through the spaces between your fingers. <figure rend="Make a Simple Solar Viewer Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Put white paper or cardboard under whatever you are using to view the sunlight and look at the image of the sun on the paper or cardboard.</item>
<item>Keep in mind that you should never look directly at the sun.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>The image of the sun will be small, but you can adjust the size of this image by moving the screen back and forth. Moving the viewer away from the screen will make the image larger, but blurrier.</item>
<item>You can study other celestial bodies using a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Buy_a_Good_Telescope">telescope</ref>.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Never look directly at the sun.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Cardboard box</item>
<item>Aluminum foil</item>
<item>Tape</item>
<item>Toothpick</item>
<item>Scissors</item>
<item>Ruler (for measuring)</item>
<item>Pen or marker</item>
<item>Paper (white)</item></list>
</text>
