<text id="autogum_whow_doc653" title="Rally a Team" shortTile="rally-team" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2017-07-27" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Rally-a-Team" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Rally a Team</head><p>Rallying your team means getting everyone ready for a big event. Help your team be enthusiastic by playing music and building excitement.  Encourage unity by using team spirit and recognizing individual and group efforts. Do some team building exercises to help your teammates feel cohesive and ready to work together. Rally your team and you’ll be ready to succeed!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Preparing Your Team for an Event</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be enthusiastic. Part of getting a team rallied is building the excitement. If you’re excited about being a team and succeeding, then your teammates will build on that excitement. Being enthusiastic helps you communicate more effectively and makes things more fun. <figure rend="Rally a Team Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Keep your energy up and speak louder than you would normally speak.</item>
<item>Remind your team what hurdles they’ve already pushed through and that they can fight through the current ones, too.</item></list></item>
<item>Set a clear goal. It’s not enough just to say, “Let’s get out there and have a good game.” Have something for your team to focus on specifically.  Create a goal for your team each game or event. This will keep them focused and ready to win. <figure rend="Rally a Team Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, have them work on a specific skill or encourage better team unity while playing.</item></list></item>
<item>Motivate the team after failures. Maybe your sports team is coming off of a few losses. Previous losses can dampen team morale, especially before going into another event. Frame the  obstacles to encourage your team to work harder and keep their eye on the prize. Overcoming hurdles can be rewarding and help the team to keep pushing forward. The strive to experience success instead of failure the next time around can motivate your team. <figure rend="Rally a Team Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Motivate your team to succeed by saying, “We’ve had a slump, so it’s that much more important to work hard today and start a winning streak.”</item></list></item></list>
<head>Creating a Positive Atmosphere Around Games and Events</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Listen to high-energy music. Music can help your team get into a positive mindset and mood. Choose a song to get your team pumped and play it before the game. This can help the team feel connected and increase team unity. <figure rend="Rally a Team Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Choose a song that’s upbeat and gets your team fired up. Some potential songs include, “Eye of the Tiger” or, “The Final Countdown.”</item></list></item>
<item>Practice team rituals before and during games. Have a cheer or clap to encourage your team. Before games or events, say a chant or have a phrase that everyone says together. Having these rituals can help teammates feel united as a team and supportive of each other. <figure rend="Rally a Team Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, have everyone put their hands in and say “Go team!” or “Go! Fight! Win!”</item></list></item>
<item>Encourage team spirit outside of the team. Encourage spectators to come and watch the game and support your team. Get fans excited for games by wearing team colors and cheering loudly. Building team spirit can help the teammates to feel united and excited about what they do. <figure rend="Rally a Team Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Having fans and supporters can help teammates feel proud and excited to be a part of the team.</item></list></item>
<item>Wear themed clothing. Get your team pumped up by having them wear themed clothing. Choose a theme for each day leading up to a major event. For example, one theme might be sports attire from the 80’s, pajamas, or their favorite athlete. This can be a fun way to rally your team and bring out a silly side. <figure rend="Rally a Team Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Building Cohesion on the Team</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Recognize individual efforts. Every member of the team should feel like they contribute and have a role in making the team what it is. Notice how your teammates work and play, both as a team and individually. When one teammate does a great job, recognize them. If possible, recognize their efforts and good work in front of the team. This can help other teammates also recognize them and feel good about their teammates. <figure rend="Rally a Team Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, say, “Annie, you did an exceptional job today. You put in your all and it showed. Thanks for leading the team.”</item></list></item>
<item>Encourage creativity. Let your teammates think for themselves and creatively problem-solve. If something doesn’t go as planned, applaud your team’s quick thinking and ability to solve a problem quickly. If you’re making a play or brainstorming ways to succeed, allow your team to give input and come up with a game plan. <figure rend="Rally a Team Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>When a teammate has a good idea, acknowledge it and thank them for their input.</item></list></item>
<item>Create some competition. Encourage teammates to engage in some friendly competition. For example, if teammates are engaged in training, see who can perform the most training exercises. Give your team opportunities to go head-to-head and beat other players as well as their own personal bests. <figure rend="Rally a Team Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, one person might be named the MVP of each game or event. Each player may want that honor, so they will work hard to get it.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
