<text id="autogum_whow_doc180" title="Identify the Difference Between Synchronous and Asynchronous Activities" shortTile="identify-difference" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-02-03" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Identify-the-Difference-Between-Synchronous-and-Asynchronous-Activities" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Identify the Difference Between Synchronous and Asynchronous Activities</head><p>Learning environments can be categorized in two ways, synchronistic and asynchronistic. With this article, you will learn the differences between then two. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Asynchronous</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Defining asynchronous. Asynchronous learning describes a learning environment where students can learn the same material at different times and in different places. This is most commonly used in online schools or distance learning.
<list type="unordered"><item>In the traditional classrooms asynchronous activities include projects, reports, and daily homework.</item></list></item>
<item>Asynchronous learning is very flexible. This method offers additional time to complete work as the class is available around the clock.
<list type="unordered"><item>Many mature students such as parents and working professionals prefer this method of learning as they are free to complete courses around their daily schedules.</item></list></item>
<item>There are numerous advantages of asynchronous learning. This type of learning environment has proven to be quite successful when used by students with higher the average, disabled students, and international students. The benefits include;
<list type="unordered"><item>Learning environment is available anytime and anyplace.</item>
<item>Allows student the opportunity for country wide or worldwide collaboration.</item>
<item>With less interruption from classmates, students have more time to reflect on the material.</item></list></item>
<item>Asynchronous online training requires a higher level of  discipline and self-direction. Each student is responsible for their individual learning.
<list type="unordered"><item>Effective time management skills are an asset when determining time windows for assignments and postings.</item>
<item>Students may become easily distracted.</item></list></item>
<item>Asynchronous learning can pose some challenges to student, teachers and schools. All parties involved with Asynchronous learning must be tech savvy and able to access the internet. Successful learning in this environment hinges on how comfortable all parties are with the technology being used. Other disadvantages include;
<list type="unordered"><item>Email or social media overload.</item>
<item>Written ideas may be misinterpreted.</item>
<item>Hardware and software can be costly.</item>
<item>Potential lack of input from students.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Synchronous</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Defining synchronous learning. This is where students learn together at the same time, in the same place.
<list type="unordered"><item>Traditionally, schools have used synchronous learning in classroom environments and lecture based teachings.</item>
<item>Increasingly, synchronous learning has been adapted for online classrooms as well. These programs use tools such as web and video conferencing programs that accessed by students during set class times.</item>
<item>These classes usually have shorter deadlines for homework and readings assignments.</item></list></item>
<item>This type of learning is less flexible than asynchronous. This may lead to missed deadlines or imbalance between school and home life.
<list type="unordered"><item>With shorter deadlines and higher class sizes there is a potential for ineffective or lacking communications between students or collaborators.</item></list></item>
<item>Some students may benefit from the social aspect or synchronous learning. Students studying in this style of learning environment may benefit from the communication that comes with a group setting, this is beneficial for reducing feelings of isolation while learning.
<list type="unordered"><item>Students may also feel more engaged in this setting.</item>
<item>Immediate responses and feedback is available with synchronous learning.</item>
<item>Appropriate academic pacing is also present during this type of learning.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Ensure you are fully aware of the differences between traditional and Online training before engaging in future studies.</item>
<item>Ensure you are prepared for effective time management between work, home, studying, and  reading.</item>
<item>Carefully chose which method is best for you by;
<list type="unordered"><item>Looking at previously established commitments to family and work.</item>
<item>Understanding how you learn best.</item>
<item>Subject matter you will be learning.</item>
<item>Your comfort level with the technology and programs being used.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
