<text id="autogum_whow_doc228" title="Contact Coinbase" shortTile="contact-coinbase" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-06-20" dateModified="2019-10-09" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Contact-Coinbase" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Contact Coinbase</head><p>Coinbase is a company which specializes in online and digital currency exchange. You can exchange currencies like Bitcoin, Ethereum, and Litecoin on the site. The company was set up in 2012 and is now one of the most popular currency exchange websites online. If you have a problem or need any help, Coinbase has extensive customer support facilities to help you fix your problem as quickly as possible.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Reaching out to Customer Support</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Call +1 (888) 908-7930 for help over the phone. Unfortunately, the Coinbase phone support team cannot help you with account specific queries over the phone. They are, however, available 24 hours a day, 7 days a week to help you with any other query you may have. <figure rend="Contact Coinbase Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tweet at Coinbase support on Twitter. Click the “tweet” button in the top right corner of the page. In order to contact Coinbase support, enter @CoinbaseSupport in the text box. Coinbase won’t be able to reply to account-specific queries on Twitter. <figure rend="Contact Coinbase Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Write out your query as best as you can. While you only have 280 characters, try and provide the Coinbase Support team as much information as you can about your problem.</item>
<item>If you don’t have enough room in 1 tweet, enter “1/2” to let the Coinbase staff member know that that tweet is only 1 of 2 tweets.</item>
<item>Click the “tweet” button after you’ve finished your tweet. This will publish the tweet and send it to the Coinbase Support account.</item></list></item>
<item>Use the Coinbase Support Center to email Coinbase. Emailing Coinbase allows you to get account-specific information. At the following web page <ref target="https://support.coinbase.com/customer/portal/emails/new">https://support.coinbase.com/customer/portal/emails/new</ref>, scroll to the bottom and click "Contact Our Team" next to the number 2. Fill out the form that loads and select the relevant information in the drop-down menus. <figure rend="Contact Coinbase Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Enter the email address linked to your Coinbase account. This is necessary as Coinbase will need to be able to find your account to resolve any issues you have and they will also need to contact you with an answer to your query.</item>
<item>Click “submit” and check the box next to “I am not a robot.” Double-check the form first to make sure you filled in all the information correctly. Then click “submit” to send the form to the relevant Coinbase support member.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Using Coinbase Online Support</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Go to the online support hub. Click the following link to access the support hub <ref target="https://support.coinbase.com/customer/portal/emails/new">https://support.coinbase.com/customer/portal/emails/new</ref>. Clicking on this link will bring you to Coinbase's specialized page for dealing with customer queries and problems. <figure rend="Contact Coinbase Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Chat with the Coinbase support bot. On that page, you will see a large text box with a message above it saying "Chat with us. Thousands of customer issues are resolved within minutes every day." In actual fact, you will be chatting with Ada, the Coinbase support bot. <figure rend="Contact Coinbase Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Ask Ada how to solve your query in the format of a question. For example, "What is the Bitcoin exchange rate?" will lead to a response of "You can view the current and past Coinbase prices and volumes using this link."</item>
<item>If you don't ask Ada how to solve your query in the format of a question, you will get a response like "I'm not sure I know the answer to that yet. Please try one of the suggested buttons, re-phrasing your question, or searching our support center."</item></list></item>
<item>Search the support center if the bot couldn't solve your problem. Go to the top of the page and you'll see a search bar. You can enter your query here and it'll bring you to a page of results that match your question. <figure rend="Contact Coinbase Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, typing in "What is the currency exchange rate?" in the search bar will load a page of similar questions on the site.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
