<text id="autogum_whow_doc183" title="Think Independently" shortTile="think-independently" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-11-10" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Think-Independently" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Think Independently</head><p>The burden of history, society, family, friends etc. keep many people captives. In fact, unbelievable as it may sound, no human being can claim to be totally Independent nor act and speak independently. We are always in one way or the other influenced by others -people, facts, events, dogmas, religion...- However, in order to be the master of his own, ones need to Think Independently. How?</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be confident and trust yourself. If you want to choose things for yourself, decide on your own, try to be confident and trust yourself. Ex: you should learn to like your choices, accept that you are a human being like the President, the Queen, the top 500... <figure rend="Think Independently Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>You must learn to say "no" and "yes", even if the whole world in unison says the contrary. But be sure that what you think is what you feel and is the Right thing! <figure rend="Think Independently Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Claim independence from people, beliefs, dogmas, prejudices that keep you captive. Don't let yourself be influenced negatively. Take a stand even if it is against the will and the point of view of your most loved or trusted ones. <figure rend="Think Independently Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't let anybody decide for you unless you think it Right. <figure rend="Think Independently Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do things that make you feel confident and happy. But if you do any harm to anybody, refrain... <figure rend="Think Independently Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try to be responsible and don't fear to tell the truth. Ex: Inadvertently you broke the glass of your neighbor or you throw a stone on the roof of somebody. Be courageous enough to say I did it. I do apologize...</item>
<item>Read books, magazines, articles that build on your self-confidence.</item>
<item>During debates, at school or even in daily conversation, don't be afraid to give your point of view and say what you think or feel even if it seems silly. If you don't feel like your opinion is well formed, or maybe you're not as well educated in a subject as you'd like to be, it never hurts to take a step back from the debate and admit that you need time to think.</item>
<item>Talk to people who take you as their equal as individual but not those who see you as immature, castaway or else. Once you've learnt to be confident about yourself, you'll be able to accept what you think.</item>
<item>Are you a believer? Ex: if you are a christian, you may have a leader -priest, pastor, prophet...- If you do not agree or you do not trust what he says, don't just say yes because he is the servant of God. Go and read the bible yourself and ask God to help you understand. But you can rebel to the teachings of your community, church, group if you feel that it is contrary to the divine prescriptions.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Thinking independently is good. But accept the point of view of other people about your decisions and your stands. What you think could have negative impact on others -in your neighborhood, community, city country or on the whole world- So be moderate and accept sometimes the point of view of others if your decision is Hazardous</item></list>
</text>
