<text id="autogum_whow_doc096" title="Bring Your Desktop Computer to a Foreign Country" shortTile="bring-desktop-computer" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2007-12-04" dateModified="2018-10-08" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Bring-Your-Desktop-Computer-to-a-Foreign-Country" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Bring Your Desktop Computer to a Foreign Country</head><p>If you want to take your desktop computer with you to a foreign country, you may need to buy a current converter to make it work in some countries, including most of Portugal.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<p>According to <ref target="http://www.hoteltravel.com">http://www.hoteltravel.com</ref>, the current in Portugal is "220 volts AC, 50 Hz. Some areas provide 110 volts and in certain southern regions 230 DC is used. Continental two-pin plugs are in use." In Canada and the USA, the standard current is 110 volts and 60 Hz.  Many computer manufacturers build a dual transformer into their desktop systems that would allow you to use them on either voltage and cycle of current. Therefore, you may not even need to buy anything to make your computer work in Portugal. To find out if yours has this capability;</p>
<list type="ordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Check</hi> the installation guide that came with your computer.  It will tell you if it is configured to run on both 110 (or 115) volt and 220 (or 230) volt systems. <figure rend="Bring Your Desktop Computer to a Foreign Country Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If your manual says it does run on both, or if you cannot find your manual, <hi rend="bold">look</hi> on the back of your computer.  There should be a small window near the power switch with a red or orange tab showing that reads "115".  Attached to this tab is a small orange switch that can be moved with a pen or small screwdriver.  This switch may be covered with a small label, to prevent accidental movement.  If you have this on the back of your CPU, it is made to handle dual currents. <figure rend="Bring Your Desktop Computer to a Foreign Country Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>You can <hi rend="bold">confirm</hi> this by completely disconnecting the power supply, and then sliding the switch to one side (toward the "115").  This should reveal a similar small orange tab that says "230".  You will still need a plug adapter to convert it to a type C or E plug. <figure rend="Bring Your Desktop Computer to a Foreign Country Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If your computer does not have this capability built in, you will need to <hi rend="bold">purchase</hi> a 230&lt;-&gt;115 step down transformer to power your computer.  This, however, will not change the frequency of the current (from 50Hz to 60 Hz), so you may experience a reduced life expectancy on your computer due to heat build up.  You will need the step down transformer to power most other peripherals, such as your monitor or printer, unless your CPU has outlets on the back that these connect to.  I suggest the somewhat higher priced ones with a built in power converter. <figure rend="Bring Your Desktop Computer to a Foreign Country Step 4.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Check with your computer manufacturer via phone or online to find out more about your CPU's capability of handling dual currents, and if using it with 50Hz current will reduce its life expectancy.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>DO NOT buy a cheap plug adapter to adapt the CPU's plug to the European style unless it can handle dual current and unless you moved the switch on the back to the correct position!</item></list>
</text>
