<text id="autogum_whow_doc568" title="Handle a New Dog" shortTile="handle-new-dog" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2017-10-25" dateModified="2017-10-25" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Handle-a-New-Dog" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Handle a New Dog</head><p>Getting a new dog can be exciting and a life changing experience. In fact, you may grow to become best friends with your dog! Although, getting a new dog can be frustrating and stressful. Here's how to handle it.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Feeding your dog can be extrememly difficult! When you have a dog, food matters a lot. A dog with food is a happy dog!
<list type="unordered"><item>Add different meat to the food if your dog is picky. (Make sure the added food is healthy.) You can get canned dog food at stores that is high in protein and nutrition.</item>
<item>Get the right type of kibble for your dog. Kibble depends on breed, age, and size.</item></list></item>
<item>Lots of people think that dogs don't to bath that much because they'll just get dirty again, but bathing your dog is highly important.
<list type="unordered"><item>Get flea bath shampoo that rids your dog's fur of ticks and fleas.</item>
<item>Check the ingredients and the prices.</item>
<item>Be gentle when bathing your dog.</item>
<item>If you notice that your dog's skin is flaking or dry, go to a vet near you. Your pet's doctor should give you some advice or special shampoo that will help your dog's skin.</item></list></item>
<item>Let your dog out as often as possible! Exercise and pottying is important for you dog at all times.
<list type="unordered"><item>Tell your dog a certain word everytime they use the bathroom. For instance: "Go potty" or "Drop a duse". They will get used to the certain word and potty on command.</item>
<item>Don't let your dog in until they poop/pee.</item>
<item>Use training pads if peeing/pooping in house continues. Keep moving it closer to your door and finally outside. Your dog will start to get use to pottying outside.</item>
<item>If you have to work away from home, always let your dog out as soon as you get home.</item>
<item>Let your dog get 1-4 hours of running outside per day.</item></list></item>
<item>We all know that we need our naps. If we don't get them, there will be issues! It's the same thing for dogs!
<list type="unordered"><item>Have a certain bed time. (This may sound weird, but it helps your dog get lots of sleep.)</item>
<item>Use a certain word everytime you go to bed. For instance: "Time for bed" or "TO BED NOW, YOU HEATHEN!". (Just jokin'!) Your dog will begin to go to his/her bed on command.</item>
<item>Allow them to get used to sleeping on your bed or theirs.</item></list></item>
<item>Try not to get to irritated. The more you yell at your dog, the more your relationship will drift apart.
<list type="unordered"><item>If your dog gets out of control (Jumping, clawing, biting, etc.), simply tell them to stop. If nothing happens, ignore them and they will realise they aren't getting your attention. Finally, walk away or keep your dog on a leash until they learn to stop.</item>
<item>When your dog poops or ruins your brand new purse (Or anything else), keep calm. Simply show them it and say "No" or "Bad". This will take some time, but will be worth it in the end.</item>
<item>If your dog escapes from your yard, remain calm. Call their name a few times. Don't run after them. This is a threat towards them. Get a bit low to show that they have dominance (But they don't, you're just tricking them!) and slowly approach them. Say stuff like "Come here, buddy/girl. Want some treats?". Say it in a soothing voice. DO NOT yell.</item></list></item>
<item>Make sure you get plenty of quality time with them. Instead of family bonding, your just bonding with you dog!
<list type="unordered"><item>Get out as much as possible with your dog.</item>
<item>Lay with them on the couch.</item>
<item>Pet them often.</item>
<item>If you can't spend quality time with your dog, don't even own a dog.</item></list></item>
<item>Finally, if you just can't handle a dog, get rid of it. If it's an attacking dog, put him/her down.
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure they are going to a loving home.</item>
<item>Get the new owners at least some starting supplies (Your dog's favorite toy, his/her dish, kibble, etc.).</item>
<item>Make sure they (your dog) understand.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
