<text id="autogum_whow_doc066" title="Sell a Used Boat" shortTile="sell-used-boat" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-05-23" dateModified="2019-06-23" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Sell-a-Used-Boat" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Sell a Used Boat</head><p>There are many facets to consider and tips to follow in order for you to sell your boat for the right price. A crucial aspect of used boat selling is exposure. If no one is aware your boat is for sale, you will most likely not sell it. The market for used boats is vast because boating is a huge enterprise in the United States. Use these used boat selling tips to help guide you through the process.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Assess the boat's condition. <figure rend="Sell a Used Boat Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Determine if the boat operates. Start up the motor (if it's a motorized boat) and make sure it floats. The standard of used boats range dramatically. Some used boats are sold in perfect condition; others hardly run at all. Selling a used boat that is in working condition is much easier than selling a poor-quality boat.</item>
<item>Check for surface damage. A boat can run just fine but be plagued with dents and scratches from use. Some of the superficial issues can be fixed prior to sale, but it's important to get a full account of the boat's problems. <figure rend="Sell a Used Boat Step 1Bullet2.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Decide whether to repair the boat or sell it as is. <figure rend="Sell a Used Boat Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Hire a professional to perform boat repairs or fix minor damage yourself. If the damage is extensive, you might not want to put too much money into repairs before you have found a buyer. Otherwise, you might end up paying more money to repair the boat then you will make off its sale.</item></list></item>
<item>Clean the boat thoroughly. <figure rend="Sell a Used Boat Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Scrub the boat from bow to stern. If there is considerable grime, you might consider renting a power washer. A brand new boat would be hard to sell if it were dirty, so cleaning your used boat until it shines is key to selling it.</item></list></item>
<item>Take flattering photographs of your boat. <figure rend="Sell a Used Boat Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Snap photos from all angles for buyers who aren't located near you. The more photos and the higher quality of photos you have of your boat, the more likely you are to attract a buyer.</item></list></item>
<item>Determine a price. <figure rend="Sell a Used Boat Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Browse the Internet for similar used boats being sold. <figure rend="Sell a Used Boat Step 5Bullet1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use the official NADA guide (<ref target="http://www.nadaguides.com/Boats?nozip=1&amp;nopop=1)">http://www.nadaguides.com/Boats?nozip=1&amp;nopop=1)</ref> for another price quote.</item>
<item>Have your boat appraised by a professional to discover its worth.</item></list></item>
<item>List your boat on online sites. <figure rend="Sell a Used Boat Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Write a detailed description of the boat that contains the following information: when the boat was purchased, special features on the boat, when extra features were installed, price paid for the boat new and price for the special features, any and all maintenance records.</item>
<item>Use proper spelling and grammar when writing your description.</item>
<item>List the boat on multiple sites, including sites specifically for used boats and sites for the selling of all items (eBay, Craigslist).</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Let potential buyers examine and test-drive your used boat.</item>
<item>Include your contact information when listing your boat. If a buyer cannot get a hold of you, he or she will not buy your used boat.</item>
<item>If your boat is worth more than $50,000, consider hiring a professional broker to sell your boat. He or she will take a 10 to 15 percent commission, but you are more likely to receive a good price for the boat.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always practice honesty when selling a used boat. Do not attempt to mislead potential buyers.</item>
<item>A used boat that has been in salt water will sell for less than freshwater boats.</item></list>
</text>
