<text id="autogum_whow_doc420" title="Go to Burning Man" shortTile="go-burning-man" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-06-21" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Go-to-Burning-Man" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Go to Burning Man</head><p>Burning Man has become one of the largest (and most popular) festivals in the world, despite the fact that many don't consider it a festival. Top hippy scientists have been trying to define what this event is for years, but haven't been able to come up with something concise. The truth it seems is that Burning Man is something different for every different attendee. Care to try your hand at figuring out what it is for yourself? Simply read on.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Get committed. The present demand for this event far outstrips the available supply by more than double, according to some unattributed accounts, resulting in this prediction for the future: Burning Man tickets are going to get more expensive and harder to come by. As a result, you must be ready to fight tooth and nail in order to attend. You're going to also want to get to know the Burning Man culture. Learn the ten principles before you commit. <figure rend="Act-and-Look-Smart-Step-4-Version-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find out how to buy a ticket (or two). Tickets tend to go on sale in February every year, and usually require advanced registration to be able to purchase them. As an added fun-bonus, the actual details of the ticketing process changes from year to year. Learning as much as you can about this year's process will be an investment of time well spent. <figure rend="Buy-Sundance-Film-Festival-Tickets-Step-15.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Save up! Now that you know how to buy tickets, and how much of what currency you'll need, it's time to start stock-piling that currency so that you can actually afford to buy a ticket. So do whatever it is you do for money and stick as much of it as possible into a giant sack with a dollar sign on it that you will keep under your bed for the next four months.</item></list></item>
<item>Buy your tickets. This may be much easier said than done. Okay, here's how to do it. Prior to sale day make sure you have the following: A burners.me profile, an account on the ticketing website being used that year (not absolutely mandatory.... but why risk it?), a confirmation of registration for the sale you're planning on taking part in, an extremely reliable internet connection, and some kind of plastic that will magically transfer money to Burning Man LLC.  <figure rend="Buy Sundance Film Festival Tickets Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Log onto the ticketing system as soon as possible the day of the sale, which usually starts at high noon. So at 11:50, you should be sitting cozy, already logged in and waiting in the digital line. Unless you didn't really want a ticket, then feel free to log in whenever. Note to the wise, general tickets have been selling out in about an hour recently. That's 20,000 tickets in an hour. Impressive, eh?</item></list></item>
<item>Plan how to get there. Okay, you did the hard part. Your path to Black Rock City will, quite obviously, depend on where you live. You may need to take a plane or something. Recently, BM has implemented a policy of vehicle passes in order to mitigate vehicles on the playa. If you're planning on driving in, or bringing an RV (lame), make sure you get your grubby little hands on a vehicle pass prior to the event. If you are not planning on driving, investigate flights and such. There are a few bus services that provide transportation to and from the playa during the course of the event, so it might be prudent to check those out. <figure rend="Not Get Bored on a Long Car Ride Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pack! Burning Man is a high adventure camping experience in a delightful place that really wants to kill you, so pack wisely! This is not meant to be an all inclusive list, but generally it's a good idea to bring camping gear, provisions, wacky costumes, and of course an open mind. For a full list check out the millions of blogs about the topic.  <figure rend="Prepare for a Camping Trip Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Here's a tip: bring lights. A LOT OF LIGHTS. The playa is very dark at night, and if you're out running around like an idiot with no lights on you're going to get pancaked in a hilarious fashion by any number of pieces of moving art that roam the desert at night. When lighting yourself up, try to think, christmas tree, Vegas strip, the sun.</item></list></item>
<item>Find a camp to travel with. This can be a bunch of friends, or one of the dreaded turnkey camps. Going with friends will make your journey easier and more fun. It might also be helpful and fun to attend a regional event closer to your locale before the big one. These are held all over the world now, and can even be a good substitute for the real thing. Midburn, the middle-eastern burn, just made big headlines too, so you know regionals are growing in popularity! <figure rend="Help Stop Pollution Step 4 Version 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get out there! Okay, the day is here, it's time to go. Well go already! Just remember to obey all local laws and ordinances, The BLM, Sheriff's office, etc. loves burning man, because it is a huge source of income every year. Feel free to contribute to the local law enforcement offices by doing something stupid either on the way out there, at the event, or on the way back. Don't you worry! There's plenty of cops out there, so if you're doing something wrong they'll find you! <figure rend="Make-a-Fire-to-Survive-Step-1.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Burners are really mean. Burning Man places a paramount value on free expression. Sometimes this expression comes out as insults. So if you can't take being called names, you may want to stay home.</item>
<item>Many things at Burning Man will try to kill you, so have fun with that. Safety not guaranteed!</item>
<item>Black Rock City has one of the nation's best law enforcement to civilian ratios.</item></list>
</text>
