<text id="autogum_whow_doc249" title="Execute a Successful and Ethical Marketing Campaign" shortTile="execute-successful" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-05-07" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Execute-a-Successful-and-Ethical-Marketing-Campaign" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Execute a Successful and Ethical Marketing Campaign</head><p>Executing a successful marketing campaign will help you generate a substantial amount of exposure for your products and also portray your business in a positive light. A successful marketing campaign will also translate into stronger sales. As with any area of life, ethics is one of the things that you have to take seriously when creating an advertising campaign. While taking shortcuts may be advantageous in speeding up the process, sometimes they may work against you. The following five tips will help you run a successful and entirely ethical marketing campaign.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Strive for high-quality content. Your advertising should clearly state how your product or service are different from others. This is true whether you employ videos, images or text. <figure rend="Execute a Successful Marketing Campaign Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not present a simplistic explanation of the products you are offering.</item>
<item>Use a descriptive approach, and provide a link to where customers can make purchases. The content should catch the attention of the audience and motivate them to take action.</item></list></item>
<item>Insist on honesty. When sharing your story with the public, make sure your ads tell the truth. While being less than truthful about your products or services may possibly help you get ahead in the short-term, there is always a chance that it will come back to bite you in the future. If something like that happens, it will ruin your credibility and make it hard for people to believe you ever again. <figure rend="Execute a Successful Marketing Campaign Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do <hi rend="bold">not</hi>  misrepresent facts. As with outright lying, you may feel like distorting facts to improve your image, but that may work against you in the long run. When you twist facts to suit your needs, you risk destroying not only your credibility but also the credibility of the media outlet carrying your campaign. You will also be deceiving the public by providing them with incorrect information. <figure rend="Execute a Successful Marketing Campaign Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do <hi rend="bold">not</hi> slander your competitors. It's natural to want to represent your products as being better than theirs, but you should do it the right way by actually providing a superior product or service. If your product/service is not superior in any way, you should strive to <hi rend="italic">make</hi> it so. <figure rend="Execute a Successful Marketing Campaign Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>It is valid to present a distinction for the sake of comparing your products with someone else's, but don't sound "whiny" or defensive about it. If you criticize a competitor, it never looks good. It just reflects poorly on your own character.</item></list></item>
<item>Avoid offering bribes for press coverage. Even though you may really want a reporter or producer to cover a launch event for the products and services that you are offering, it is a bad idea to bribe them in order to make that happen. <figure rend="Execute a Successful Marketing Campaign Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Doing that makes you look desperate, and it also makes your story less worthy of  exposure.</item>
<item>If the reporter even considers taking a bribe, he/she risks getting fired.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
