<text id="autogum_whow_doc388" title="Build A Magnetic Catch Bottle Opener" shortTile="build-magnetic-catch" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2016-10-20" dateModified="2018-03-05" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Build-A-Magnetic-Catch-Bottle-Opener" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Build A Magnetic Catch Bottle Opener</head>
<p>Not much is more satisfying that making something with your own hands. A magnetic catch bottle opener makes a great gift for friends, for family, groomsmen, house-warming or just about anyone who has ever needed to use a bottle opener. Whether you're a first time builder, hobbyist or woodworker, this will walk you through the steps on how to make your very own!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Gather your supplies and clean your work area.</item>
<item>Charge batteries on any cordless tools.</item>
<item>Consider how you want to lay out a design. This project will be using a simpler method and you can keep this as easy or as complex as you want.</item>
<item>Determine the length and the width that you would like your finished project to be. At the very simplest (using only one piece of wood) those will be your final dimensions. In this guide, you’ll be using two different species of wood. Using a main piece, made of red oak, and a secondary piece made of walnut. This finished project will be 4 inches wide and 9.5 inches tall.</item>
<item>Cut the wood to the appropriate length and width using a miter saw, and a table saw or circular saw (for all cuts). Cut the wood to 10 inches in length. You will trim down excess later. For the width cut, you can go as narrow or as wide as you would like depending on how you want your finished product to look. In this project, we will cut two pieces of the red oak to 1 inch in width, one piece of the red oak to 1.5 inches in width, and the walnut we will cut two pieces to 0.25 inches in width.You should now have: (x2) Walnut – 10” x 0.25” (x2) Red Oak  - 10” x 1” (x1) Red Oak – 10" x 1.5”</item>
<item>Arrange vertically in whatever pattern you like. Glue the wood together lengthwise. For this project, starting from left to right, take one of your red oak pieces cut to 1” wide, then a piece of the walnut. Next is the larger, 1.5” wide red oak, then the walnut again, then the final piece of oak. This is the main design of the bottle opener. Once you’re happy with your design, apply glue to the sides of each piece and begin to glue them together.</item>
<item>Clamp the wood together to really get that glue in there. Clamp tightly and with even pressure. Remove any excess glue while it’s still wet with a rag, or an old t-shirt.</item>
<item>Let dry for the glue manufacturer’s recommended time (most will be dry after 1-4 hours).</item>
<item>Sand the face of the board down to make sure everything is flat. Start with a heavy grit paper and work your way to a fine grit. Start with 80 grit to remove the glue and sand flat some raised spots, then move on to 120, then finish with 220 grit.The plan here is to make sure that both sides are nice and flat and that there are no raised pieces along the face of the newly formed board.</item>
<item>Trim each end of the board using a miter saw or circular saw. Pick one of the ends and cut off a very small amount, only enough to make sure it’s nice and square. After the cut, measure  down the length, mark your line, and cut to square off the end.</item>
<item>Plan out where you want the bottle opener on the face of the board. Try it by hand first and see where you like it most. This is completely up to you, just make sure to leave some room underneath for the magnet later on, and a little room above for a mounting screw to attach to the wall (optional).</item>
<item>Measure the width of your board and divide by two. Make a very light line on the half-way mark to line up with the screw holes on the bottle opener.</item>
<item>Place opener where you chose, and pre-drill holes along the mid-point line. Pre drilling helps drive a screw and also helps prevent the wood from splitting (especially as you get near the end of a board).</item>
<item>Determine position of magnet. You’ll want a few inches of space to let the cap fall naturally for a brief brief moment before being attached to the magnet. You'll want to use a forstner drill bit that is slightly larger than the diameter of your magnet. The main idea here is drill as far as you can <hi rend="bold">without</hi> drilling through. One trick: measure the thickness of your board, then transfer that thickness to your drill bit. Mark it with a piece of tape (leaving a small amount of room for error).</item>
<item>Glue the magnet into place using the epoxy and let dry. This brand recommends one full day for a complete set time.</item>
<item>Use a stain or paint of your choice. You can also use a polyurethane finish to help protect the wood. Pictured is a spar urethane which will leave a natural finish, but protect the wood. You can really do anything you want here, the choice is yours!</item>
<item>Drill your mounting holes above the bottle opener and well below the magnet.</item>
<item>Attach the bottle opener to your previously drilled pilot holes (from step 10) using the screws that come with the bottle opener.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Drill</item>
<item>Saw (specifically a miter saw and table saw, however all cuts can be made using a circular saw as well)</item>
<item>Clamps</item>
<item>Sandpaper (80, 120, 220 grit) and a random orbital sander (optional)</item>
<item>Wood glue</item>
<item>1 Forstner bit (slightly larger than the diameter of your magnet). This project used a 1 5/8"</item>
<item>1 Mounted-style bottle opener</item>
<item>1 Rare earth magnet, round</item>
<item>Epoxy or any industrial strength adhesive for metal and wood</item>
<item>Wood of course! This project used Red Oak and Walnut hobby wood, 1" thick.</item></list>
</text>
