<text id="autogum_whow_doc589" title="Stop Feeling Like a Self" shortTile="stop-feeling-self" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2017-06-05" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Stop-Feeling-Like-a-Self" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Stop Feeling Like a Self</head><p>In many Eastern philosophies, it has been said that the cause of suffering in human beings is the Ego, also known as Ahamkara, Identity, character, etc. Desire and resistance are opposite forms of attachment, and the misperception of our true nature is connected to "feeling like a self." "Feeling like a self" translates to a term known as Asmita. In order to access true, genuine happiness, it is suggested amongst many wise scholars that human beings end their idea of selfhood.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Acknowledge that you are a Self. There is no way that we can solve our problems until we recognize that we have a problem. So, it is best to first admit to your Self that sometimes you are feeling like a self.</item>
<item>Identify the characteristics of your Self. What makes you feel like a Self? What are the qualities? Do you have interests? Things you don't like? Do you experience sensations? Do you care about the past or future? Do you have positive or negative opinions about things? Do you have sight, hearing, taste, smell, feeling? All of these sensations are qualities of Feeling Like a Self.Do you have labels that you attach to things? When you label something, you make it different from your Self with your mind. So, it is like the backwards tricky way of feeling like a self. It's like being able to tell how you Don't feel like a self. If you make something Not you, then that means there is a You! And identifying as You is the cause of suffering.</item>
<item>Renounce feeling like a Self. Through breath control, aware movement, and decades upon decades of deep meditation, begin to end caring about your Self. Think often upon the inner true nature of all things, and recognize that the qualities of all things are inherently the same, and there is no difference between you, me, or anybody else. Slowly notice your desire and aversion to things, and over time, by noticing the many sensations you experience daily, begin to renounce your reactions to stimulus. By actively engaging in this practice you will end "feeling like a self" and asmita will leave your experience. This is known as "coalescence," or a glittery shimmering purification of your consciousness that develops in pervading throughout all things, dissolving differentiation.</item>
<item>Practice. Practice makes practice! And the harder you try, the harder you will get better at it. This is cited in many research articles and scholarly texts! Never give up!</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You are more likely to stop feeling like a self if you surround yourself with a community of people who are also actively working towards not feeling like a self! You are also more likely to enjoy your experience on Earth, as feeling like a Self is said to be the root of all suffering.</item></list>
</text>
