<text id="autogum_whow_doc177" title="Use Your Thinking" shortTile="use-thinking" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2016-01-06" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Use-Your-Thinking" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Use Your Thinking</head><p>This Article will show you how to use your brain and think positively, be successful, and exploit others' failures.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>First Thing</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>All of the humanity knows how to think, but have you ever tried to think in a way that you know your thinking is right? Have you pushed your thinking to the limits? Ordinary people like us have made inventions for many years. For instance, Thomas Edison had invented electricity, Albert Einstein had created the theory of the speed of light, and Isaac Newton exposed the law of gravity. These individuals neither were not super heroes nor were they extra-ordinary people. What they all did were using their brains and knew how to think in an unadulterated way. The apple that fell on Newton’s head made him think. If he hadn’t sit under the apple tree, maybe he wouldn’t have established the laws of gravity. Also, if there were not Edison, we wouldn’t get electricity ever. Nowadays, scientists still using the laws of these old-school scientists to discover new theories and develop new advances to help the humanity live a modern life style. In the same way, Apple Company wouldn’t be that popular if it didn’t have the creator of iPhones (Steve Jobs). There are many successful people who have altered the whole humanity by bringing new ideas to human’s life-style. This article is a simple guide that could give you a unique description to let a person exploit his/her time to benefit the human beings, raise his/her name, and get good profit. There are a lot of people who have skills that they are not going to find in others. At the same time, they do not exploit their talents and show the world how much they are skillful.
<list type="unordered"><item>You can acknowledge that thinking rationally is inherited from 1.     Our genetic endowment. 2.     Our geological system. 3.     Our cognitive system (perceptions, thoughts, and memories) 4.     The social environment. 5.     The cultural environment. 6.     Our previous life experiences (including your childhood.)  7.     Our personal characteristics (including personal intelligence, mental health, and personality). Book by: Michael W. Eyenck  Page numb: 4 Book title: Psychology Student Handbook.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Use Your Surroundings</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Every moment you fall down, try to talk with someone that is really close to you. That one might know you more than yourself, and he/she could give you enough motivation to make you stand up again and keep moving forward. The reason is sometimes motivational advises would push a person to the limits and inspire him/her achieve his/her goals. And, by saying surroundings I don’t mean that you should just talk with people. You might get motivated by watching a movie, a picture of something that could touch you hard, or a circumstance that might change the whole of your personality in a small period of time. “Motivation is the art of getting people to do what you want them to do because they want to do it.” Dwight D. Eisenhower. On the other hand, train yourself to motivate yourself is a conjecture that lead a person to inspire himself by visualizing positive thinking in his/her brain. This state could vary many dis-courage people.</item></list>
<head>Read Books</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Most of you might think and say that this section is totally weird. But, after all, most of the time, reading books would change a person’s life in many aspects. First, he/she will get new information as well as being more educated, and the feeling of being educated is really an astonishing reaction. Intellectuality will increase a person’s confidence. Try not to read a book, don’t even watch T.V, and don’t read any newspaper or magazine for a year. Just hang out with your friends and don’t talk about any new ideas or any new things. Try to talk about a specific thing that you want to talk about every time.  You will realize that you are in an “everyday routine cycle” and this will lead you to get psychological issues. A person might be frustrated and feel that he/she has not achieved any single ambitions while they might be really smart and ambitious. This life is full of spots of success, but we should have enough to know how to fill these spots. “Whenever you read a good book, somewhere in the world a door opens to allow in more light.” Vera Nazarian.</item></list>
<head>Exploit Others’ Failure</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>It is has been said many times that people have to learn from their mistakes. But, have you ever thought to learn from others’ failures? Probably not. According to Bill Gates, “It is fine to celebrate success but it is more important to heed the lessons of failure.”</item></list>
</text>
