<text id="autogum_whow_doc071" title="Donate a Boat to Charity" shortTile="donate-boat-charity" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2012-12-22" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Donate-a-Boat-to-Charity" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Donate a Boat to Charity</head><p>Do you have a boat you no longer want, or no longer want to maintain? It’s not easy to sell a luxury item like a boat in today’s economy, but you can still alleviate your burden as a boat owner and enjoy some financial gain, if only in terms of a tax deduction, and help a charitable organization at the same time. The steps outlined here apply to the United States.
</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Choose a Reputable Charity</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Research before you donate. There are a number of sites that offer charitable deductions for your boat, but check to see if they are legitimate before you give away your boat: <figure rend="Donate a Boat to Charity Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>See if the organization has 501(c) status with the IRS.</item>
<item>Look up the status of the organization on the nonprofit list of the Better Business Bureau.</item>
<item>Consult Charity Navigator.</item>
<item>Remember, due to the Separation of Church and State, churches and religious organizations are exempt from applying for nonprofit status. Donations made to these organizations are still considered tax deductible, and as an added benefit, they are 50% organizations which means that you will be allowed to deduct up to 50% of your AGI. If you cannot find a specific charity in the IRS database, consult the charity to determine whether they fall into this category.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Donate Your Boat</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Go to the website of the charity you have selected.  <figure rend="Donate a Boat to Charity Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Follow the website’s instructions. These websites generally have FAQ pages to explain how to donate your boat. Most websites will provide answers to all your questions; if not, contact the relevant person or webmaster to ask for more information. Typical questions that are usually answered in the FAQs include: <figure rend="Donate a Boat to Charity Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>How to determine if your boat donation is tax deductible</item>
<item>How to determine the value of your donated boat</item>
<item>How to arrange for your boat to be picked up (or where you can drop it off if preferred)</item>
<item>The paperwork you will be required to provide</item>
<item>The timetable for picking up your boat.</item></list></item>
<item>Be sure to let the charity know whether related items are included. For example, you may wish to include boating gear, life jackets, fishing paraphernalia, electronic equipment, etc. <figure rend="Donate a Boat to Charity Step 4.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Most charities accept all types of watercraft, from small motor boats to yachts.</item>
<item>Deducting the actual price the charity receives from the sale of your boat is a sure way to prevent overstating the value of your boat deduction on your tax return.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Most organizations must have the title to your boat. However, if you don’t have the title, you can usually make some alternative arrangements with the charity.</item>
<item>If your boat is worth more than $5,000, then you will need an appraisal and a signed 8283 IRS tax form. Most charities provide these services to you at no cost.</item></list>
</text>
