<text id="autogum_whow_doc687" title="Exercise for the First Time" shortTile="exercise-first-time" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2017-10-01" dateModified="2019-09-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Exercise-for-the-First-Time" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Exercise for the First Time</head><p>Starting to exercise for the first time may seem difficult. However, this process can be very simple. If you follow these steps, you will be on your life-changing path to a healthier lifestyle. The fact that you are looking at this page indicates you're ready to start exercising, so let's get started!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Seek a Medical Professional.    Your doctor will outline what you may or may not be able to do without affecting your health in a negative way.  <figure rend="790241 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Write down exercise goals.  Sit down and decide what exactly you want to accomplish with your new exercise program.
<list type="unordered"><item>Do you want to begin lifting weights, cardio, or both?</item>
<item>Do you want to put muscle on or maintain your body type?  <figure rend="Write a Goal Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Create an exercising schedule.       Pick a time in the day when you will be able to exercise on a regular basis. Decide where you will  exercise. Your schedule will be based on your goals you made for yourself.  <figure rend="Make a Schedule Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Research proper stretching techniques.   Stretching is different depending on what type of exercise. Stretch until you feel a little tension in your muscles and hold that position for 15-20 seconds.  <figure rend="Stretch Your Legs Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Investigate correct form of motion.  It is important to know how to perform the specific task. Range of motion is the most important while you are exercising. Correct form of motion will depend on your goals.  <figure rend="Use Abdominal Exercise Equipment Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Obtain appropriate workout attire.    Workout clothes should include:
<list type="unordered"><item>Loose fitting shirts, shorts, pants, and tennis shoes.</item>
<item>Do not worry about looking your best.</item>
<item>Jeans, sandals, heals, and dresses should not be in your workout attire.  <figure rend="Pick Right Workout Clothing Step 3.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Find an exercise partner.    Find someone who would be willing to exercise with you. Coordinate a schedule that fits both of your schedules.  <figure rend="Exercise with Friends Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Eat nutritious pre-workout meal.  Fuel yourself for your exercise. Include carbohydrates or protein. Do not eat too much before you begin your exercise. Eat 45 minutes before you begin your exercise. Examples could be the following:
<list type="unordered"><item>A sliced apple</item>
<item>Healthy choice yogurt</item>
<item>Granola bar  <figure rend="Choose a Pre Workout Meal Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Do appropriate stretching for you muscles.    Whether you are exercising your legs, arms, or another part of your body, it is important to stretch those muscles prior to your exercise. Stretching should be 10-15 minutes, and it should occur before you begin. Do not take stretching lightly; make sure you take this step seriously! Stretch after you are done.  <figure rend="Stretch Your Biceps Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Start slow.     It is important to start slow and build up.
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, if you are starting a running schedule, you do not want to go run  the first day.
<list type="unordered"><item>Your first few weeks do not need to be intense, rather get your body in the habit of exercising and sticking to your schedule.   <figure rend="790241 5.jpg"></figure></item></list></item></list></item>
<item>Hydrate throughout.     Hydrate your body throughout your workout.
<list type="unordered"><item>Muscles need water. Give your muscles water.</item>
<item>Invest in a water bottle you can keep on you.  <figure rend="Get Hydrated Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Know your limits, but challenge yourself.    Exercising is intended to push your body. You should feel some discomfort while your exercising.
<list type="unordered"><item>Stop if you feel pain.</item>
<item>Talk to your doctor if you continuously feel pain.</item>
<item>Do not be afraid to push your body, but know your limits.
<list type="unordered"><item>A good exercise will end with a little discomfort in your muscles, but this should not be painful  <figure rend="Motivate Yourself to Work Out Step 5 Version 4.jpg"></figure></item></list></item></list></item>
<item>Replenish electrolytes and eat a proper post exercise meal.    A post workout meal should consist of protein. Protein will help to rebuild the muscles you just worked out. You should eat protein as soon as you can after you finish. You should also fill up on some electrolytes after a good day's exercise.
<list type="unordered"><item>Protein shakes with whey protein</item>
<item>Gatorade is a good way to refill electrolytes.</item>
<item>Mix 8 ounces of your Gatorade choice with water.  <figure rend="Eat After a Workout Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Never give up.   Never, never give up.
<list type="unordered"><item>Put in some off days to give your body some rest.</item>
<item>Push through the early days.</item>
<item>You will be happy you never gave up!  <figure rend="Never Give Up Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Consult your doctor for personal recommendations on your health.</item>
<item>Overworking your muscles may cause injury. Do not push yourself too much; if you feel pain, stop!</item></list>
</text>
