<text id="autogum_whow_doc336" title="Deal With a Breakdown" shortTile="deal-breakdown" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2012-05-04" dateModified="2018-09-23" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Deal-With-a-Breakdown" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Deal With a Breakdown</head><p>Do you ever feel like the ground below you is quaking in its tyranny, that the sky is weighing down upon your shoulders and you can barely hold up a pencil with your trembling hands? Ever get sick of the constant sobbing and the way your soul may feel like a tiny wisp of paper inhabiting an empty shell? Constant stress and/or grief can cause this feeling, a feeling of sheer hopelessness and anxiety. It is in this state that many make the rash decision to end their lives, since so many are reaching out for a release. Read along and you may find a coping skill that may stick, that may free you so you can finally... breathe.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Get this bottled up energy out. Rip up paper, scream into a pillow, yank grass out of its roots, throw around a stuffed animal, etc. Do it all in order if you have too, it gets that itch from crawling under your skin like an insipid snake. <figure rend="Avoid Talking in Class Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Distract your body. Get a cup and fill it up with ice cubes, then, one by one, grip each cube in your hands until you feel you`ve had enough. While doing this, think of the longest words in your head and add up their syllables. After about five minutes, you should feel slightly better. <figure rend="Treat a Fat Lip Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Lay Down. It is better if you do this on the floor. Put on some music, and place your hands on your stomach. Let your stomach rise and fall gently along with your breathing. Sing if you feel the urge. Wiggle your toes and fingers, and be aware of them moving to your every command, remind yourself that you're in control. <figure rend="Do a Side Crunch Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you can, jot down what you feel, even if it is just a few words. <figure rend="Convince Your Parents to Let You Be in a Beauty Pageant Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Refresh yourself. Take a shower, scrub off all of the pain and stress, or drink a large glass of cold water. Water has healing powers, use it to your best advantage. Feel muggy and ill? Mix salt and water together and wait 30 seconds. Get a rag and soak it in for a minute, then rub the rag on your skin and the walls of your house. Within seconds you should feel the difference. <figure rend="Be Motivated in the Morning Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Indulge in what you enjoy doing. Play the piano, sketch a bit, write a poem, whatever you like. Watch a cartoon and smile at the innocence of it. Call a friend or look up some jokes on the Internet. Distract yourself. <figure rend="Convince Your Parents to Buy You a Piano Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Talk about it. Grab your Teddy Bear and pour out your emotions. Cry to your goldfish. Try speaking with a friend or a member of your family. Communicating is key. Even though at first it may not sound right to say it out loud, it helps. Don't ask for advice, just say everything that is troubling you. No need to be ashamed even if it might sound ridiculous. If you can't find someone to say all of this to, write it down.  <figure rend="Deal With a Younger Sister's Attack Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>When you hold the ice cubes, don`t hold them for TOO long.</item></list>
</text>
