<text id="autogum_whow_doc161" title="Start a Primary School Media and School Newspaper Publishing Company" shortTile="start-primary-school" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2007-10-01" dateModified="2018-08-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Start-a-Primary-School-Media-and-School-Newspaper-Publishing-Company" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Start a Primary School Media and School Newspaper Publishing Company</head><p>Are you keen on running your own mini-media empire at an early age in school? This can be a fantastic grounding for a future career and gives you a very early opportunity to learn about managing people, deadlines, and expectations. This article provides a brief overview of the things to consider when developing your publishing company.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Build your team of at least 4 "staff". You will likely have to double up on a number of the tasks and have each person responsible for several jobs. Jobs could be: <figure rend="Start a Primary School Media and School Newspaper Publishing Company Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>reporter</item>
<item>photographer</item>
<item>editor</item>
<item>sub-editor</item>
<item>picture-editor</item>
<item>columnists</item>
<item>researchers</item></list></item>
<item>You will also need to consider the need for a: <figure rend="Start a Primary School Media and School Newspaper Publishing Company Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>complaints officer; and/or a PR Manager</item></list></item>
<item>In addition to your staff you may need a board of directors, consisting of: <figure rend="Start a Primary School Media and School Newspaper Publishing Company Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>A President, Vice President, Treasurer, Secretary, and representatives from all 4 classes, the board of directors President, VP, Treasurer and Secretary should be appointed by the representatives, and the representatives should be appointed be the class officers.</item></list></item>
<item>Give your newspapers(s) a cutting edge name. Brainstorm with your team for a suitable name. <figure rend="Start a Primary School Media and School Newspaper Publishing Company Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Decide how many pages you will have and what will be the contents. <figure rend="Start a Primary School Media and School Newspaper Publishing Company Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use a page layout and word processing program to build your paper. Suggestions are in tips. <figure rend="Start a Primary School Media and School Newspaper Publishing Company Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Cut down on ink and paper; try to get your school to print it. <figure rend="Start a Primary School Media and School Newspaper Publishing Company Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Decide a price, it can be free if you have ads in it or sponsors. Your team will need to go around and rally sponsors and funds for it if you do not sell it. Even if you have sponsorship, you might need to sell it to cover overheads and to give the paper value in people's minds. People often dismiss that which is freely given. <figure rend="Start a Primary School Media and School Newspaper Publishing Company Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try to get people into it. Be a motivator and sell the virtues of being a part of the newspaper team for their future careers, their sense of community involvement and their love of helping others and writing. Be careful not to overdo it though and use people up. Everyone deserves a fair go and nobody should be left feeling that they have been used up when they are volunteering their time, efforts, and ideas. Recognize their efforts and reward them in appropriate ways as possible. <figure rend="Start a Primary School Media and School Newspaper Publishing Company Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Write your articles in a word-processor first. Suggestions include <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Use_OpenOffice.org_Writer">OpenOffice.org Writer</ref>, Corel WordPerfect, AbiWord, Apple Pages and Microsoft Word.</item>
<item>Use desktop publishing (DTP) software. The industry standard is QuarkXPress and Adobe InDesign, but for a free alternative, try <ref target="http://www.scribus.net">Scribus</ref>. A cheap alternative is Serif PagePlus. If you already paid for Microsoft Office, there is Publisher in some (but not all) editions.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>A PC</item>
<item>Staff</item>
<item>A Board Of Directors</item>
<item>Desktop publishing (DTP) and word-processing software</item>
<item>A School</item>
<item>Paper</item>
<item>Ink</item></list>
</text>
