<text id="autogum_whow_doc220" title="Have a Family Meeting" shortTile="family-meeting" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2010-05-28" dateModified="2018-10-08" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Have-a-Family-Meeting" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Have a Family Meeting</head><p>Every family has its time when they have to talk about things and get everyone to agree on something. Whether it's something about when to watch TV, or discussions about a new house, we all have a good reason. But how do you put it together? Follow these steps to make the family meetings a little easier for every person in your household. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Decide on what you want to discuss. It is important to go into a family meeting with something important to discuss, or it will be pointless to even have it. Do you need to talk about who owns the remote? Or what about the many concerts coming up? Or maybe it is a topic that is a little bit harder to discuss. Make sure you know what to talk about and some replacement topics just in case things get a little too rough. <figure rend="Be-Calm-Step-21.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Set up the meeting. When do want to have the meeting? Talk it over with your significant other and decide if your time is reasonable. Then, talk it over with each of your kids individuality. Tell them the time and, if appropriate, the subject. Make sure that they are available. If they say they don't want to come, which will most likely occur with teenagers or tweens, tell them that they have to come because the meeting is very important. <figure rend="Be-Mature-Step-10-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure that everyone didn't forget about the meeting the day before it is due to happen. Especially if you planned it out well in advance, there is a chance that they might have. Remind everyone if possible. If they aren't available at the moment leave them a reminder on their desk or something. Leave a note on the refrigerator. <figure rend="Choose-the-Right-Divorce-Lawyer-Step-7-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Go to the meeting. Make sure everyone's there. If they are not, go get them. If they still can't make it, cancel the meeting and reschedule. If they make it, discuss the topics and make sure everyone gets a chance to say something. If there are a ton of bad responses from everyone in your household, then attempt to change the subject. If things go smoothly, then you'll know that you did a great job. <figure rend="Become-a-Stronger-Person-Through-Caregiving-Step-18.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Apply the discussion in real life. For example, if you discussed a TV schedule, abide by that schedule. If your whole household has to do something and you don't, they will most likely think that it is unfair, and they will become very upset with you. <figure rend="Become-a-Stronger-Person-Through-Caregiving-Step-14.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Sometimes some meetings may have information that some kids are not ready to hear. If they seemed confused during then meeting, then sit down with them after the meeting is over and explain what you talked about in terms that they can understand better.</item>
<item>If any of your younger kids throw a fit about any topic because they don't like it, then excuse them and yourself, and go to talk to them for a minute so that they can work to accept the change.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure not to yell at anyone if they are upset or confused. It will only make things worse for everyone in the household, because yelling may start an argument.</item></list>
</text>
