<text id="autogum_whow_doc274" title="Make Kefta and Batata (Meat and Potatoes Lebanese Style)" shortTile="make-kefta-batata" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-10-09" dateModified="2019-09-16" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-Kefta-and-Batata-%28Meat-and-Potatoes-Lebanese-Style%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make Kefta and Batata (Meat and Potatoes Lebanese Style)</head> Kefta and batata, also known as “kefta bi seniyah,” which means in English kefta in a pan. Kefta is a traditional Lebanese casserole that many grandmothers have been making for centuries. Kefta is ground meat mixed in with chopped onions and parsley. It's super fast and easy to make, kefta is shaped into patties topped with potatoes and onions simmered with seasoned tomato paste. This traditional Lebanese casserole is served with white vermicelli rice, and/or baked Lebanese bread. This wikiHow will teach you how to make kefta and batata.
<head>Ingredients</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>¾ lb. Kefta</item>
<item>3 Potatoes</item>
<item>2 Onions(optional)</item>
<item>2 Tomatoes(optional)</item>
<item>4 tsp. Tomato Paste</item>
<item>2 ½ cups water</item>
<item>1 cube chicken bouillon/ or chicken broth</item>
<item>2 tsp. Salt</item>
<item>1 tsp. Black Pepper</item>
<item>1 T. Vegetable oils or coconut oil</item>
<item>Onion powder(optional)</item>
<item>Dill(optional)</item>
<item>.5 tsp. Thyme(optional)</item>
<item>.5 tsp. Basil(optional)</item>
<item>2 cups medium grain rice</item>
<item>1 cup broken vermicelli pasta</item>
<item>2 ½ T. olive oil</item>
<item>1 tsp. salt</item></list>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Wash your hands before touching the kefta. You do not want to touch kefta and then touch the rest of the ingredients. This will avoid any food-borne illness.</item>
<item>Form the kefta into circular patties with your hands. You can make them as small or large as you want just depending on how large your casserole dish is. Then place your kefta on the side on a separate plate. Preheat your oven to 375F.  <figure rend="5753C8F7 F5DC 43FB 89D3 A9B2334CCD2A.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Spray your casserole dish with PAM or use coconut/vegetable oil.</item>
<item>Grab a separate casserole dish. Then wash your potatoes and either peel or leave the skin depending on your preference. Some people like to soak the potatoes for at least 15 mins before laying them on top of the kefta.</item>
<item>Let the potatoes soak for 15 minutes. Then peel and slice them into ¼ inch thickness. You want them to look like flying saucers.  <figure rend="KQRZb8GRQaWUX2Bv0b2y w.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Sprinkle the potatoes with salt and drizzle vegetable oil. Lay on a baking sheet lined with parchment paper or even just aluminium foil. You can also add onion powder and dill for extra flavor (optional).</item>
<item>Start baking the potatoes before the kefta. It does take the potatoes a little longer to cook than the meat, you want everything to be cooked evenly. Bake the potatoes in the oven for 25/30 minutes on 375F.</item>
<item>Flip the potatoes over halfway through baking. If you soaked your potatoes before it might take less then 30 mins for them to turn a little brown.</item>
<item>Place the potatoes in too of the kefta patties. You can do this once the potatoes have been in the oven for about 25/30 mins and are brown. Add sliced ¼ thick onions and tomatoes on top if you desire.  <figure rend="272F07A3 8512 4892 9E71 7B3C60528545.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Grab a separate bowl. Add the tomato paste and dissolve it with water. Stir the two ingredients for about 3 minutes then add in the chicken bouillon and stir for another 3 minutes. You might want to add some extra seasoning.</item>
<item>Pour the mixture on top of the casserole. Do not get worried that there is a lot of liquid it will dissolve. Season with salt and pepper and then cover with aluminium foil and bake for 45 minutes on 375F. Continue to check on the casserole halfway.  <figure rend="XF9 TdGfSb rHLDzd8Bs1g.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make the rice and baked bread. Rinse the rice, and let it soak in water for about 15-20 minutes. Then grab a medium non-stick cooking pot, heat the olive oil and low/medium and add the vermicelli and stir continuously.  <figure rend="Fullsizeoutput_1abb.jpeg"></figure></item>
<item>Add in the rice and continue to stir. Add in 3 ½ cups of water and bring to a boil until the water is reduced, then turn heat to low.  Cook for 15-20 minutes while the kefta is still in the oven.  <figure rend="OViWC69ISPWO xryAme8KA.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remove the kefta from the oven after 45-50 minutes. You may then add a piece of Lebanese bread on the plate along with the rice and top the kefta for a fine garnish.  <figure rend="IMG_4659.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you do not have chicken bouillon you can use chicken broth. Again, that is totally optional for you.</item>
<item>You can also add extra vegetables on top for extra flavor. If you would like to add a different vegetable depending on the preference you may (ex. zucchini, eggplant).</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>When adding the vermicelli, you have to make sure you keep an eye on it and stir continuously or it will burn and you will have to throw away and start all over.</item>
<item>Let the Kefta sit for about 10 minutes before eating because it will be extremely hot.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Casserole Dish</item>
<item>Cooking Pot</item>
<item>Measuring Cups (½ and 1 cup)</item>
<item>Aluminum Foil</item></list>
</text>
