<text id="autogum_whow_doc028" title="Find an Illustrator" shortTile="find-illustrator" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2007-12-30" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Find-an-Illustrator" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Find an Illustrator</head><p>Buying custom made artwork requires some degree of understanding of what the artist needs to know in order to fulfill your vision.  This is a guide to help you sound like a professional custom art buyer with ease.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>A list of your requirements describing the art you envision.  For instance: a color drawing of a dog running up a hill, past a tall tree.</item></list>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Know what you're asking for. Once your quest for the right illustrator has ended the next step is knowing how to instruct the artist to draw what you have in mind.  The best way to be satisfied with the art you order is to be extremely clear in your instructions.  The artist will appreciate a concise, to the point order.   Below is a list of questions designed to help organize your requests. <figure rend="Find an Illustrator Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Know how many illustrations you want. <figure rend="Find an Illustrator Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be prepared for providing needed info. <figure rend="Find an Illustrator Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>For each illustration provide the following list of the elements to be included in the composition. For example:  A drawing of a collie dog, walking down a lane, in profile, past a line of trees with a clear, blue, cloudless sky in background.  The dog should be wearing a collar and have a pleasant expression. <figure rend="Find an Illustrator Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Decide if the art will the art be in color or black and white. <figure rend="Find an Illustrator Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Decide whether you want one or more prints, a digital image, or both. <figure rend="Find an Illustrator Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you are ordering prints, decide how many and what size you want. <figure rend="Find an Illustrator Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Decide what purpose you'll use the art for. <figure rend="Find an Illustrator Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Know ahead of time, what the eye, hair and skin color of the subjects are.  <figure rend="Find an Illustrator Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Decide if you will be providing reference material or if you expect the artist to procure it. Some artists will charge for finding reference material as it can be very time consuming. You might consider finding the reference to save fees. <figure rend="Find an Illustrator Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Decide if there will be any text on the page.  Do you want the artist to provide the text or leave room for your printer to place the text on the finished art.  If you want the artist to do it what font should be used.  If you are having your printing company place the text they can superimpose it on the digital art. <figure rend="Find an Illustrator Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do you need the artist to design a logo and if so what are your ideas for it?  What is the message you want to convey? <figure rend="Find an Illustrator Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do you want a logo you already have placed on the art?  Can you supply a digital image of the logo. <figure rend="Find an Illustrator Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>You can ask the illustrator to show you samples of art they have which conveys the type and quality of the illustrations they create, however, do not expect them to have the exact thing you have in mind.  For instance if you want a picture of a bride on a skateboard and they have drawn skateboards and brides separately you can be confident they draw them together.   If the artist can draw an airplane but has not drawn a skateboard be confident they can draw the skateboard. <figure rend="Find an Illustrator Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Ask the artist if you will be supplied with a sketch before they go to the final finish. Do not expect the artist to redraw the picture if you change your mind for the original layout without incurring more fees. <figure rend="Find an Illustrator Step 15.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be as specific in your instructions as possible to avoid disappointment and frustration.  The artist cannot read your mind so it is vital to provide good, solid instructions.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Expect to pay for time consuming changes.</item></list>
</text>
