<text id="autogum_whow_doc136" title="Buy a Robot Online" shortTile="buy-robot-online" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-05-14" dateModified="2015-05-26" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Buy-a-Robot-Online" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Buy a Robot Online</head><p>Robots are a great pass-time. Most people don't play with robots, so you will need to buy one. There are many sites that offer robots, and you will need to know how to buy one.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Shop By Store</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Log on. Log on to your computer. Open a new browser tab and take care of anything that needs to be taken care of. Finally, get to a clean search engine page.</item>
<item>Deciding where you will buy the robot. Many places offer robots for sale. You will have to decide where you want to buy your robot. Do you want to buy it by auction (eBay) or standard money (Amazon)? Do you want it new or used? There are many steps to make the final decision.</item>
<item>Searching for your robot. Once you have made up basic preferences, search them. Be sure to be as specific as possible. If no results show up, check your spelling, then reword your search. Click on results to read basic details. Find a robot that is in your price range and works for you.</item>
<item>Purchase your robot. Most sites require you to make an account then add money and your information to the account. Most sites also require that you are 18+ years old. Once you have made an account and verified you are eligible to purchase the robot, buy it. Eventually, your robot will arrive in the mail.</item></list>
<head>Shop By Robot</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Log on. Log on to your computer. Open a new browser tab and take care of anything that needs to be taken care of. Finally, get to a clean search engine page.</item>
<item>Deciding on the robot. There are many different types of robots. Each has their own special qualities, so see which best match you. Read robot catalogs of many sites to make your final decision. Be sure to read reviews on the robot.</item>
<item>After researching, find the model you want. Many stores will probably sell the same model. Chose the store you want and purchase....</item>
<item>Purchase your robot. Most sites require you to make an account then add money and your information to the account. Most sites also require that you are 18+ years old. Once you have made an account and verified you are eligible to purchase the robot, buy it. Eventually, your robot will arrive in the mail.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Check different sites to see which have the cheapest price. Also, make sure the sites you use to purchase the robots are reliable. Unreliable shops can steal your information.</item>
<item>Read reviews to see how well the robot performs and where and how it can best run. Reviews often have useful tips in them. Don't solely base your purchase on reviews though.</item>
<item>Try to find sites that have a guarantee or warranty under their products. If the robot malfunctions, you can always return the robot for a refund or a functional robot.</item>
<item>If a site seems to ask for too much information(social security numbers, etc.) that won't be needed to make the purchase, don't enter it. The site might steal this information.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Unreliable sites may steal the information you enter onto their site. Check their site credits and/or computer safety software before you begin entering key information.</item></list>
</text>
