<text id="autogum_whow_doc599" title="Make a Top 10 List" shortTile="make-top--list" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2012-01-23" dateModified="2018-10-11" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-a-Top-10-List" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make a Top 10 List</head><p>Top 10 list are a fun and interesting way to show your opinions on how strongly you feel about a subject. From music, actors, sightseeing and more, there are many things you can make a top 10 list about.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Pick a topic or genre that you like and that an audience can relate to for a top 10 list. If you were to pick a topic you like then a top 10 list will be a lot easier and more enjoyable to make in the long run. Also when it’s a topic that a large audience can relate to more people will want to read it.</item>
<item>Give the list a title that relates to the list so people know what they are clicking on. If there isn’t an accurate title or no title at all people might look at it with expectations of something else or no even look at it. An accurate title is necessary so that you can gather the audience that you intended the list for.</item>
<item>Think of 10 things, places, people, or whatever your list is about where you personally think one is better than the other. If you picked a topic that you really like but you can’t even think of 10 things for it, then you might want to pick a different topic. You will also want to make sure that you can actually order these thing from least to greatest otherwise there is no point to the list.</item>
<item>Pick a format to put this top 10 list on whether it’s Youtube, a slideshow, a poster, etc. Once you have picked a platform to put it on you can find out where to put the list. If it’s on Youtube then you can post it on social media or if it’s a poster then you can hand it on a wall in a classroom or public area.</item>
<item>Number the page or slides 1-10 starting with the number 10 and going down by one. Numbering from 10 then going down to one will show the audience that you think 10 is the worst of the best and one is the best of the best.</item>
<item>Put the items, places, or people that you chose on the list from least to greatest. Greatest being the number one slot and worst would be number 10. This is just the most common way to order a top 10 list.</item>
<item>Give a short description under every number to describe why you put that item,person, or place in the spot you did. The description will help justify your reasoning on why someone is in that spot. This will show the readers that agree or disagree with your opinion on why you chose it and it might even change their mind on the placement of the list.</item>
<item>Add some cool pictures that relate to every number as you go down the list. These pictures can give your list a lot more flare and encourage people to read it. If your list is just a bunch of black text on a white piece of paper might not be the most enticing to someone. With pictures they could catch a person's eye and draw them in.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can make list of any thing you want.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be careful not to make mistakes in your final copy. If so, you have to start completely over again!</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Two pieces of paper</item>
<item>Pencil</item></list>
</text>
