<text id="autogum_whow_doc468" title="Pick Runner Beans" shortTile="pick-runner-beans" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-07-19" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Pick-Runner-Beans" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Pick Runner Beans</head><p>Runner beans, also known as string beans, are long, slender bean pods that are popular in many vegetable gardens. Throughout the growing season, runner beans will ripen and be ready for you to eat. With simple harvesting techniques and kitchen prep, you can enjoy fresh vegetables at any time!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Harvesting Your Beans</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Start picking your beans in the middle of summer. Beans planted in the spring can be harvested in the later summer months, typically August and September in the Northern hemisphere. Keep track of when you planted your beans to determine the best time to start your harvest. <figure rend="Pick Runner Beans Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Runner beans take about 3 months to fully develop from seeds.</item></list></item>
<item>Harvest the pods when they are  long. Look for bean pods that still have a smooth texture. If you can see the beans through the outer pod, the beans are past their prime and may have a tough, stringy texture when you eat them. <figure rend="Pick Runner Beans Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Larger bean pods may look impressive, but they’ll have a rougher and less desirable texture.</item></list></item>
<item>Pull the bean pod off the stems by hand. Grab the bean where it connects to the stem with your thumb and index finger. Hold the stem with your other hand and gently pull the bean off. <figure rend="Pick Runner Beans Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Keep the beans you pick in a bag or bucket so you don’t have to carry them.</item></list></item>
<item>Check your plant every 2 days for ripe beans. Runner beans can grow quickly and they will grow multiple times throughout the growing season. Keep checking your plant until the first frost. <figure rend="Pick Runner Beans Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you have too many beans, ask your neighbors to see if they want to pick any for themselves.</item></list></item>
<item>Leave some of the pods on your plant to dry. Let the seed pods turn a pale straw-color until early autumn. Once the seeds rattle inside the pods, remove them from the plants and bring them inside. Remove the beans from the pods and let them dry on a tray until they feel light and hollow. Store the beans in mason jars in a cool, dark place. <figure rend="Pick Runner Beans Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>When you want to eat the beans, soak them in cool water for 8 hours before you cook them.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Storing Runner Beans</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Separate the good beans from bad beans. Get rid of any beans that are soft to the touch or yellowing. Also dispose of any pods where you can see the beans through the skin. Only keep beans that are smooth, firm, and a solid green color. <figure rend="Pick Runner Beans Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep fresh beans in the fridge for 1 week. Put your beans in an airtight container in the vegetable drawer of your refrigerator. Make sure they are dry before you store them or else they could develop mold. <figure rend="Pick Runner Beans Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Freeze the beans for up to 1 year. Put your beans in a freezer-safe bag and squeeze all the air out from it. Seal the bag and use a marker to label them with the date so you know how long you’ve had them. <figure rend="Pick Runner Beans Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Trimming and Cooking Runner Beans</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Cut the ends off the beans. Rinse your beans thoroughly with water and pat them dry. Use a chef’s knife to remove the tips from each side of the bean. Cut off  and throw away the pieces when you’re finished. <figure rend="Pick Runner Beans Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remove the strings from the sides of the beans with a vegetable peeler. Hold the bean so the inside edge faces up. Start your vegetable peeler on one end of the bean, and pull it down the length of the bean where it looks like there’s a seam. Flip the bean over and remove the string from the other side. <figure rend="Pick Runner Beans Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you leave the string on, it will be tough to chew when you eat them.</item>
<item>Fresh runner beans can be stored in the freezer for up to 8 months.</item></list></item>
<item>Cook the beans in boiling water for 3-4 minutes. Drop the beans into water over medium heat. After 3-4 minutes, the beans should be bright green and tender. Use your knife to see if the beans cut apart easily. <figure rend="Pick Runner Beans Step 11.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Salt your water before you add the beans so they can absorb the flavor.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Runner beans can be eaten fresh or cooked.</item>
<item>Check your beanstalks multiple times during the season to get the most out of your harvest.</item></list>
<head>Things You’ll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Bucket or bag</item>
<item>Chef’s knife</item>
<item>Cutting board</item>
<item>Vegetable peeler</item>
<item>Stove</item>
<item>Pot</item>
<item>Freezer-safe bag</item></list>
</text>
