<text id="autogum_whow_doc255" title="Bring In and Keep Customers" shortTile="bring-keep-customers" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-01-30" dateModified="2019-03-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Bring-In-and-Keep-Customers" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Bring In and Keep Customers</head><p>The first step to any successful business is promotion and marketing, and the second follow-up step is retention. To learn how to bring in and keep customers can be challenging if you have never been exposed to marketing or public relations. By following a few easy steps, however, you should be able to not only boost business but keep it steady and/or growing as well.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Start with noticeable and recognizable signage. You want your drive-by traffic to know who you are and what your business does. <figure rend="Bring In and Keep Customers Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make any day an excuse for an event. Be it a sale, an anniversary, or an open house, celebrate by promoting an event and opening your doors to the general public. <figure rend="Bring In and Keep Customers Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Offer an incentive to visit or refer your business. <figure rend="Bring In and Keep Customers Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Run a time-sensitive sale or special to drive in traffic.</item>
<item>Offer a referral incentive for those who refer new customers your way.</item></list></item>
<item>Consider print advertising such as the newspaper, magazine, or ads or listings in the phone book. <figure rend="Bring In and Keep Customers Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Devote time and energy in a website and in maintaining a social networking page for your business. Both of these tools can be low cost and offer you means to keep your name in front of the crowd electronically. <figure rend="Bring In and Keep Customers Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Think about radio or television ads. Radio works wonderfully for event-driven exposure, and television can help you build brand recognition. <figure rend="Bring In and Keep Customers Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Network with local professional organizations to build a referral system for year-round leads. <figure rend="Bring In and Keep Customers Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Work to keep the customer base that you have built. <figure rend="Bring In and Keep Customers Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Start with quality customer service. Be polite and respectful to everyone who comes in your door, and treat that person as you would want to be treated.</item>
<item>Train your staff not only how to be polite but how to successfully do their jobs as well. Being nice doesn't sell your product, nor does it help your staff avoid mistakes. Instead, that comes with good training and practice.</item></list></item>
<item>With their permission, sign your customers up for your mailing or email list. You can do this in the store or on your website. <figure rend="Bring In and Keep Customers Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Institute a best practices methodology that includes not selling or sharing the customers' information with anyone outside of your business. Make sure that this policy is shared on your website for full transparency.</item>
<item>Follow up with emails to join your Facebook page, send a copy of an online newsletter or send emails about upcoming sales or special events. You want to keep your clients engaged in what is going on at your business, but on the other side be sure not to inundate them.</item>
<item>Mail out fliers, hard copy coupons or newsletters if the printing and mailing costs are affordable for you.</item>
<item>Always include an opt-out option so that customers don't feel like they are stuck getting your correspondence if they don't really want to.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try to boost your search engine status by embedding pertinent tags into your web pages. You should also link your home page to the majority of the pages on your site.</item></list>
</text>
