<text id="autogum_whow_doc438" title="Make Your Apartment Bathroom Look and Feel Larger" shortTile="make-apartment-bathroom" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2007-11-29" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-Your-Apartment-Bathroom-Look-and-Feel-Larger" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make Your Apartment Bathroom Look and Feel Larger</head><p>Unless you're living in your own home, you may find yourself wishing for a larger bathroom. While it’s not a problem for homeowners to completely remodel and redecorate, apartment renters are rather limited. It can be a challenge, because you have to work with what is provided.  There’s still a lot you can do without replacing tiles or knocking down walls. With a little bit of planning, some creative organizational skills and clever use of color, you can easily make your apartment bathroom seem more spacious than it really is.  These simple decorating tips are quick, easy, and best of all, cheap. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Color</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>If your landlord approves, you may be able to paint. <figure rend="Make Your Apartment Bathroom Look and Feel Larger Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Colors of the same tone create an illusion of greater space. <figure rend="Make Your Apartment Bathroom Look and Feel Larger Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Choose soft, pale, neutral pastels for both the walls and the flooring. <figure rend="Make Your Apartment Bathroom Look and Feel Larger Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use a large rug to cover dark or unflattering floor tiles. <figure rend="Make Your Apartment Bathroom Look and Feel Larger Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Bright, strong and exciting colors (such as red) should be saved for accessories and towels. <figure rend="Make Your Apartment Bathroom Look and Feel Larger Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Mirrors</head>
<p>Mirrors provide an illusion of expansion without adding a single square foot.</p>
<list type="ordered"><item>Consider a few small mirrors arranged artistically throughout the room. <figure rend="Make Your Apartment Bathroom Look and Feel Larger Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Replace a bulky medicine chest with a wall mirror.  Store a first-aid kit in a kitchen cupboard. <figure rend="Make Your Apartment Bathroom Look and Feel Larger Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try one full-length mirror on the back of the bathroom door. <figure rend="Make Your Apartment Bathroom Look and Feel Larger Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Declutter</head>
<p>A clean, neat bathroom will always look bigger. Yes, this means you’ll have to spend some serious time organizing your stuff.</p>
<list type="ordered"><item>Cut down on the number of towels, rugs, pieces of art and decorative accessories. <figure rend="Make Your Apartment Bathroom Look and Feel Larger Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use one large rug or runner instead of several small rugs. <figure rend="Make Your Apartment Bathroom Look and Feel Larger Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Items that are infrequently used should be stored out of sight.  This doesn’t mean you have to hide everything out of sight, though. There are plenty of attractive smaller storage options that allow you to put your items in place and on display at the same time. <figure rend="Make Your Apartment Bathroom Look and Feel Larger Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tall and thin cabinets always come in handy when space is at a premium. <figure rend="Make Your Apartment Bathroom Look and Feel Larger Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Vertical displays also create an illusion of greater space in height.  Narrow shelving over the toilet will not impinge upon floor space.  Fold towels in thirds to stack neatly on the shelves.  Store cosmetics in a basket on the shelf.  Include a toothbrush case, toothpaste and a small glass in a separate basket. Place the more cluttered basket on a higher shelf so that the contents will not be within view.  Provide space for a tissue box.  Keep these shelves limited to a few items that require quick access on a daily basis. <figure rend="Make Your Apartment Bathroom Look and Feel Larger Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Avoid multiple dispensers and holders around the sink.  #Replace a wide soap dish with a thin liquid soap dispenser. <figure rend="Make Your Apartment Bathroom Look and Feel Larger Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Place a towel hook near shower and sink. <figure rend="Make Your Apartment Bathroom Look and Feel Larger Step 15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Place a garment hook on the back of the bathroom door. <figure rend="Make Your Apartment Bathroom Look and Feel Larger Step 16.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try to avoid using a rack with multiple hooks in an already crowded space.  One hook and one item on the hook provides for a neat appearance. <figure rend="Make Your Apartment Bathroom Look and Feel Larger Step 17.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Once dressed, remove all garments from the bathroom. <figure rend="Make Your Apartment Bathroom Look and Feel Larger Step 18.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Decide what items can be kept elsewhere - other than in the bathroom. <figure rend="Make Your Apartment Bathroom Look and Feel Larger Step 19.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Store your bathrobe on a hook in your bedroom closet instead of on the back of the bathroom door. <figure rend="Make Your Apartment Bathroom Look and Feel Larger Step 20.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Store your laundry in a pillowcase hung on a hook in your  bedroom closet. <figure rend="Make Your Apartment Bathroom Look and Feel Larger Step 21.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Store your scale beneath your bed or a bedroom chair. <figure rend="Make Your Apartment Bathroom Look and Feel Larger Step 22.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Visual Pathway</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>With a single swoop of the arm – push back the shower curtain to one side when it’s not in use. If you can see all the way to the back wall (instead of just to the curtain), your eye will think the room is larger. <figure rend="Make Your Apartment Bathroom Look and Feel Larger Step 23.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>One sheer curtain covering the entire window will provide privacy and abundant light during the day.  A shade behind the curtain can be pulled down at night. <figure rend="Make Your Apartment Bathroom Look and Feel Larger Step 24.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If fixtures are being replaced, consider a small corner sink. <figure rend="Make Your Apartment Bathroom Look and Feel Larger Step 25.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
</text>
