<text id="autogum_whow_doc208" title="Not Mess Up Your Kids Life" shortTile="mess-up-kids-life" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-04-09" dateModified="2017-06-15" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Not-Mess-Up-Your-Kids-Life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Not Mess Up Your Kids Life</head><head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Don't punish them for being happy and thinking their own thoughts. Don't punish them for thinking their own thoughts. Don't isolate them with nothing to do. Don't keep them in a dark place. Don't get one parent to give one set of orders and the other parent giving another set of orders (which are somewhat insane) (as in double bind where your given contradictory orders damned if you do and damned if you don't) but coercing the child to obey and if they don't they will be punished and never allowed to see anybody until they comply and agree and only think and say the things as the parents. The parents will be very upset if the child disagrees. Don't make the child do all the work and never praise them and hold them accountable for everything. Don't tell them they can't do something in a coercive way then punish them or treat them like shit for not doing it.. Don't leave them hanging wondering what you were about to say or meant then start yelling at the when they can't open their mouth for words and promise you'll get back them after assuring them you will then don't make it seem like you wont.Don't isolate them enough to drive them crazy. Don't make everyone turn against your child and have no one to turn to when he wants to tell what your doing to him by isolating him and making these crazy ideas. Don't tell your child to sympathize with the world and not be a victim and then call him a victim whenever he is upset and when he refuses to have sympathy or whatever don't punish him.Don't punish your child for being himself.Don't tell your child he has to do everything and then convince him he can't do anything. Don't punish your child for asking to do stuff and make him afraid to have his own hobbies. When your child makes something don't sell it disregard it and call it as your own.Don't take your childs stuff away from him Don't just ignore your child. Don't tell your child he is never allowed to leave the house alone and then drive him crazy staying in the house. Don't tell him he must never behave in a certain way and then drive him crazy for obeying you.Don't punish your child for obeying you. Don't tell your child you want him around and then tell him hes not allowed to be around.Don't leave him alone all day.Don't tell him he has to learn maths and then be mean about it when he asks you to teach him.Don't teach him stuff hes already going to learn at school and then wonder why he doesnt pay attention to class.If he has trouble in school make sure he gets help if he doesnt understand don't blame him for failing.If your child treats you as you want to be treated cause you taught don't punish him for treating you as you want to be treated.If your child does something for you cause he wants to be happy don't punish the child for not doing enough for you.If the child wants to get a job don't tell him he can't get a job after telling he must get a job and don't tell people you don't want him to get a job and he can't get a job and repeatedly tell him to get a job and go out.If your child helps you with cleaning don't punish him for it.If your child doesnt do the right cleaning you want tell them what to do then don't punish them for doing it wrongly cause you didn't tell them what to do.Don't ignore your child long enough that they get mad and start being mischievous.Don't say your child can't have any friends unless he thinks and acts like you and keep him away from anyone. Don't threaten the child with stupid things like your going to mess up his brain if he doesnt obey you.</item>
<item>Don't make a child do something for so long and without praise that they don't want to do it and give up on everything in life.</item>
<item>This is not saying you should not help your parents.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>There are situations when It is necessary to say no when a child does help you and you don't want him to.This is not saying that children should be arrogant but shouldn't punish child from being themselves you must find another way!</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>I am not to responsible for any consequences to following this. If you want to sell something of your childs you should get permission.</item></list>
</text>
