<text id="autogum_whow_doc191" title="Describe the Process of Bone Healing to Kids" shortTile="describe-process" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-01-31" dateModified="2019-06-12" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Describe-the-Process-of-Bone-Healing-to-Kids" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Describe the Process of Bone Healing to Kids</head><p>When a child breaks a bone, they are often scared and have many questions about how it is going to fix itself. Explaining what is going on to the child can be quite difficult as the answers are often way beyond their comprehension.  It is important to use diagrams and terminology they can understand.  This article will provide strategies for explaining complex processes to children, along with a format to explain the bone healing process in a way a child can understand.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Meeting Them at Their Level</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Ensure they know what a bone is. Although the child may have heard the term bone several times they may not be entirely sure what it is.  Show the child pictures of a bone and explain where they can be found in the body and the role they play. <figure rend="Identify Human Bones Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use visuals. It is important to show the child pictures and labelled diagrams of each step in the bone healing processes.  Providing visual aids will help to captivate the child's interest by increasing their focus.  Having visuals will also aid in the child's comprehension. <figure rend="Teach-a-Child-to-Read-Step-6-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep it simple. Try to use vocabulary they already know.  Avoid using scientific terms but rather describe it using physical attributes or the function.</item>
<item>Use similes. There will be some new terms you cannot avoid using.  When this happens use smilies to help the child understand.  A smilie is the comparison of two different things in order to create a new meaning.  The comparison is usually made using the words "like" or "as." <figure rend="Bone_Simile.png"></figure></item>
<item>Eliminate the details.  Providing the child with every little detail about the bone healing process will only confuse them.  Try to focus on the major components of the process and eliminate any that seem insignificant.</item></list>
<head>Explaining the Bone Healing Process</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Explain the hematoma formation as a pool of blood. Explain to the child that when the bone breaks it tears the blood vessels surrounding it. The blood coming from the blood vessels then pools around where the break happened.  The torn blood vessels slowly stop releasing blood because they are clogged with cells.  By saying the blood vessels are clogged you can avoid using the term clotting process. <figure rend="Hematoma_pool.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If the child does not know what a blood vessel is explain it as a tube which blood flows through much like a garden hose with water flowing through it.</item></list></item>
<item>Explain what happens to the surrounding cells by comparing what happens to people when they don’t eat. Explain to the child that blood carries nutrients to cells.  Tell the child nutrients are like food for our cells.  When blood vessels tear during a break blood can no longer flow through them properly so nutrients cannot get to the bone cells around the break and they die. Just like how people can't live without food, the bone cells can't live without nutrients so they begin to die. <figure rend="Blood_Vessels.png"></figure></item>
<item>Compare the blood vessels growing into the hematoma as roots growing into the soil. A few days after the break, tiny blood vessels start to grow into the pool of blood. These small blood vessels grow off of the broken blood vessels much like how roots branch off a trunk into the soil.  Inform the child that these small blood vessels connect the ends of the broken blood vessels back together. Make sure the child understands that this allows blood to flow normally again. <figure rend="Regenerating_bv.png"></figure></item>
<item>Explain phagocytic cells as special cells that eat dead cells. Do not use the proper name, phagocytic cells, as this could be confusing for the child. Refer to phagocytic cells as "special cells" that come and eat the dead cells to get rid of them.  By calling them special cells the child will get the idea that they are different from other cells. <figure rend="PhagocyticCells.png"></figure></item>
<item>Express the bone formation process by the physical features or the function of the biological term. <figure rend="Collagen_Fibers.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Instead of using the proper terminology, fibroblasts and osteoblasts, refer to them as bone forming cells.  Bone forming cells enter the area where the blood pool occurred and begin to remake the bone.</item>
<item>You can avoid using the term collagen fibers by explaining their physical properties. The broken bone ends are connected with bundles of long thread like structures made out of protein.</item>
<item>You can refer to fibrocartilaginous callus as a repair tissue.  A temporary repair tissue is built between the broken bones.</item></list></item>
<item>Explain about spongy bone by focusing on its physical attributes. The repair tissue is turned into spongy bone.  This spongy bone forms the inner layer of all bones and it looks a lot like a sponge.  It takes about 2 months for the broken bone ends to be joined together.  Show a picture of spongy bone to help the child understand. <figure rend="Spongy_bone.png"></figure></item>
<item>Define remodeling to explain bone remodeling.  The spongy bone is then remodeled meaning the old bone is replaced by new bone.</item>
<item>Compare compact bone to a shell.  Lastly, a hard outer layer forms over the bone to provide protection and strength much like a shell. <figure rend="Compact_bone.png"></figure></item></list>
</text>
