<text id="autogum_whow_doc056" title="Improve Your Gas Mileage for Free" shortTile="improve-gas-mileage" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-08-26" dateModified="2016-01-08" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Improve-Your-Gas-Mileage-for-Free" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Improve Your Gas Mileage for Free</head><p>When gas prices go up most people think more about getting better gas mileage. Many people think that it is hard and/or expensive to improve their gas mileage. This is simply not true. The truth is that is it easy to improve gas mileage. Keep reading to find out how to boost fuel mileage for free!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Keep track of your fuel mileage. When you are at the gas station keep the receipt. After you fill up with gas make sure to reset your trip meter to 0. You can calculate your fuel mileage by dividing the driven distance by the amount of fuel used. Keep a record. There is no way to tell how much your mileage has improved unless you keep a record. <figure rend="Improve Your Gas Mileage for Free Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get in the right mindset when you drive. Think about how much fuel you are using when you are driving. Always keep it in your mind until you get in the habit of driving for fuel economy and not for speed. <figure rend="Improve Your Gas Mileage for Free Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Avoid idling. Sometimes it is necessary but keep it to a minimum. When you start your car in the morning don't let it sit and idle for 10 minutes, you are using gas and getting 0 miles/kilometers per gallon! <figure rend="Improve Your Gas Mileage for Free Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't be the first one off of the line at a stop light. Most of the time the people who are off of the line first are also the first ones to slam on their brakes at the next stop light. This is a huge waste of fuel. <figure rend="Improve Your Gas Mileage for Free Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Watch the road way ahead. If you see the traffic light turn red or cars brake lights coming on then take your foot off the accelerator and let your car coast. By doing this you are using the momentum that you already have (from using gas to get your car up to speed) to get to the next stopping place. <figure rend="Improve Your Gas Mileage for Free Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Drive slower. Your car is most efficient around . After that you are wasting fuel. Drive as close to  as possible when it is appropriate. <figure rend="Improve Your Gas Mileage for Free Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take the route that is the shortest and has fewer stop lights. The longer you are driving and the more you are sitting at stop lights the more fuel you are using. <figure rend="Improve Your Gas Mileage for Free Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Have a goal. If your goal is to get 15% better gas mileage then you will be more likely to get there.</item>
<item>Think about how much money you are saving by driving differently. This will help you justify it.</item>
<item>Try not to be in a big hurry when you drive. If you can drive slower and think about how much fuel you are using you will be able to save more.</item>
<item>Drive a car that gets good mileage. Some people have multiple cars and like driving one over the other for various reasons, but it might be worth it to use the one that gets better mileage.</item></list>
</text>
