<text id="autogum_whow_doc688" title="Live in a Different Country for a Short Time" shortTile="live-different-country" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2007-09-10" dateModified="2019-03-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Live-in-a-Different-Country-for-a-Short-Time" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Live in a Different Country for a Short Time</head><p>Let's say your parents have decided to take you abroad for a year, maybe because they have a sabbatical, or maybe just for "fun". To an adult, it may seem like the perfect opportunity for you to learn a new language and make new friends, but you it's a whole different story! What about the friends you're leaving behind? What about the whole part where you have to LEARN A NEW LANGUAGE?</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Stay calm or freak out ahead of time. But when that fateful day arrives, the first day in a foreign school, act as if this is what you do everyday. Scream and pound your fists in your head and curse the heck out of everyone, in your head, but play it cool. Remember, everyone around you is wondering how they would react to this situation, and it impresses them to see you so collected. <figure rend="Live in a Different Country for a Short Time Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Evaluate other people. There are always some kids who want to be the first to know the new kid, to veto them or accept them. It's usually the popular ones. The great thing about a new school is that they don't know the first thing about you! So, watch them, and either laugh at them (this always helps in a pinch) or mold to them. They are actually usually nicer to you than the other kids. <figure rend="Live in a Different Country for a Short Time Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Beware of the opposite sex, especially if you're a girl and especially in France. They can get pretty crude, and don't take no for an answer. Just brush them off if you need to. Getting flustered does NOT help. <figure rend="Live in a Different Country for a Short Time Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use lots of sign language. Point at things and make funny faces. If you can make people laugh while making them understand, you get even more points! <figure rend="Live in a Different Country for a Short Time Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Talk. Talk. Talk. Talk. Not just with teachers when they ask you a question, but with all the kids, whether you like them or not. They will be so busy trying to understand you that they won't notice how weird you speak. And if anyone makes fun of how you talk, other people will get mad at them, seeing how much you try. <figure rend="Live in a Different Country for a Short Time Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Enjoy yourself. Reminisce about your old home, but don't dis the new one. It's got its quirks, sure, but mostly its an okay place. As long as you work with everyone around you, you'll catch on faster than you had EVER imagined. <figure rend="Live in a Different Country for a Short Time Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Ask for help. If there is a word you forget or don't understand, ask a friend to help you understand. Mime it out if you have to. And don't worry, you will make friends very quickly.</item>
<item>Speak as often as you can, but what's even more important is reading. If you have a study period, and you can go to the library, go. Read a comic book. Read a fairy tale. It doesn't matter, just read. When you read, your mind doesn't stumble over the words, it just goes a little slower, unlike your mouth. Its the best practice you could possibly hope for.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Never cry in school, except maybe on the last day when you have to say goodbye and its incredibly hard. All your friends will cry too.</item>
<item>Don't complain. People will immediately look over all your good qualities and see just the complaining, which is not attractive, especially in someone who has so many reasons to complain.</item></list>
</text>
