<text id="autogum_whow_doc644" title="Play the Shuriken Game" shortTile="play-shuriken-game" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2009-04-04" dateModified="2016-01-09" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Play-the-Shuriken-Game" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Play the Shuriken Game</head><p>The "Shuriken Game" is a game which involves the use of paper throwing stars (shuriken), generally played 1 on 1, in an effort to hit the opposing player.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Gather the materials in "Things You'll Need" found below. <figure rend="Play the Shuriken Game Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Before the game starts, give each player x number of shuriken they can hold. When the game starts, each player can throw shuriken at their opponent in order to "hit them out"(similar to dodge ball), in an open area. Players must stay in the boundaries of established "open area" for the duration of the game, as they are free to move in it. <figure rend="Play the Shuriken Game Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>First player to get hit by a moving(thrown) shuriken loses. By throwing your shuriken, if a launched shuriken connects with your opponent's body then lands elsewhere, you win. <figure rend="Play the Shuriken Game Step 2Bullet1.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Use the Element of Substitution. This is a special move which allows a player to trump a hit. However it requires the player to see ahead and "costs" 2 shuriken. To do this move, you must have at least 2 shuriken in your hand, both ready to drop on the ground. For instance, a player sees they are about to get hit by a shuriken. Taking one shuriken, they drop it on the ground, BEFORE getting hit. Then, the player is hit by the shuriken. Finally, the player drops another shuriken on ground, thereby successfully accomplishing a "substitution". <figure rend="Play the Shuriken Game Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Note: the pattern must follow "drop-hit(s)-drop" and flow consecutively, otherwise, it is considered a fail substitution(and that player loses). For a legal substitution, the first shuriken can only be dropped immediately after the shuriken you believe, will hit you, was launched. A player finishing a substitution must drop the last shuriken within a second after getting hit, otherwise it's also a fail substitution. <figure rend="Play the Shuriken Game Step 3Bullet1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>The element of substitution voids shuriken hits in-between the first dropped shuriken and the second dropped shuriken. So, it is possible to get hit by more than 1 shuriken during a substitution and still be in the game.(For example, you drop a shuriken, then you are hit by one. Not even a second later, you are hit by another. You see that this would be the last in the "chain" of shuriken in the current situation, so you drop a shuriken within a second after the 2nd shuriken that hit you.) In addition, it is perfectly legal to be moving during a substitution, as long as the dropping portion is not interfered. <figure rend="Play the Shuriken Game Step 3Bullet2.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>If you are able to catch a launched shuriken, you are not out and can use the shuriken. The definition of "catching" means any 2 body parts of a player quickly come together so that the shuriken is lodged in between and stopped from its path of motion. Catching shuriken with your hands is just as legal as catching one between your knees or just as a shuriken touches your body, you slap the shuriken against your body so that it stops. All this is considered catching and you are not out. However, the shuriken cannot fall out of its lodged position for at least a second, thereby proving you have "caught" it. There are not "hot potato" catches allowed nor second catches(meaning you catch it, it falls, then catch it again). The shuriken must come at you, then stop when it connects to your body. <figure rend="Play the Shuriken Game Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Know that a shuriken on the floor may or may not be picked up off the floor, based on the game style: SHURIKEN RETRIEVAL or NO SHURIKEN RETRIEVAL. If not permitted, shuriken from the hand is exhausted via throwing and stays on the ground for the duration of the game. Note the number of shuriken in the "starting hand" should be more. If permitted, players may pick up shuriken off the ground and into their hands. Once a shuriken leaves contact with the ground, it is considered "in the hand", thereby legal for substitution, for instance. <figure rend="Play the Shuriken Game Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>No human contact is permitted. <figure rend="Play the Shuriken Game Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Adapt a comfortable throwing style that's right for you. This mostly involves which fingers to hold it between, and how your fingers curve around the center.</item>
<item>Practice concepts that are implemented in the Shuriken Game. For instance, practice throwing shuriken at targets, stationary and moving. Try to master "substitution"; it's all about timing. Also, practice basic dodging and catching shuriken.</item>
<item>Remember to always use "holed" shuriken, they will generally fly better and farther.</item>
<item>If you know any acrobatic type move which will aid in dodging, use it. It's perfectly legal.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure the shuriken you are using are not of substantially hard material that could hurt. Always try to use soft yet sturdy material when making shuriken to avoid any damage.</item>
<item>If necessary, wear protective gear. Shuriken thrown may hit face or eyes.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Paper Shuriken. These are no more than throwing stars made from origami. To start, assemble paper shuriken with the help of online guides. Paper Shuriken need to be "holed" in order to fly; this can be done by tracing a coin (preferably nickel size) in its center, and slowly cutting the image of the circle with a box cutter. When hollowed through, use the knife and smooth out the insides of the shuriken. Also, try to find sturdy paper, as sometimes cheap printer paper make flimsy shuriken. You need lots of paper shuriken, preferably 20 minimum to get started. Other holed-shuriken made from harder material may be used, provided you don't mind getting hit by them.</item>
<item>Open Area. This is where the game takes place. The arena should be relatively fair for 2 people, ideally wrestling ring size. Shuriken will be launched in every direction, so make sure they don't go off somewhere. Obstacles can be used.</item>
<item>Referee. This is optional. Hits may be viewed differently by players, so its always good to have a final judge.</item></list>
</text>
