<text id="autogum_whow_doc048" title="Fit Wind Deflectors" shortTile="fit-wind-deflectors" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-02-07" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Fit-Wind-Deflectors" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Fit Wind Deflectors</head><p>Wind deflectors allow you to open your car window during a stormy day without getting rain on your upholstery. They can also reduce the noise made when you roll your window down by deflecting the wind away from your window. Because wind deflectors are easy to install, fitting them to your car does not require a trip to the mechanic or any special tools. As long as you clean the channels beforehand and insert the deflectors carefully, they should fit comfortably in your window frame.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Preparing the Window Frame and Deflectors</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Buy wind deflectors made for your car model. Wind deflectors are specially designed for different car models. Make sure that the wind deflectors you buy are suitable for your car. If you purchase the wrong kind, you will not be able to achieve a perfect fit. <figure rend="Fit Wind Deflectors Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can find the car model information on the wind deflector's packaging. If you're not sure what kind to buy, ask a salesperson for advice.</item></list></item>
<item>Roll your window down. To fit the wind deflector in, you will need to roll your window at least halfway down. If your window does not roll down to the bottom, you can still fit your deflector in but may not be able to clean your window as thoroughly. <figure rend="Fit Wind Deflectors Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Clean the window frame and channel.  Spray a window cleaner or mild solvent over the tops and sides of the window and wipe it off with a paper towel or dry cloth. Rub off any dirt, dust, or debris in the window frame so your wind deflector will fit in securely. <figure rend="Fit Wind Deflectors Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are installing an adhesive wind deflector, clean off the window's trim (the painted door frame to the top and sides of the window) as well with the cleaner and dry cloth.</item></list></item>
<item>Use a damp cloth or screwdriver to scrape dirt away from the bottom of the frame. Pull your cloth through the slot and pick out any large pieces of debris that might be stuck in the slot. If you cannot pull out the debris using the cloth, pick it out with a screwdriver instead. <figure rend="Fit Wind Deflectors Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Let the window frame dry before fitting in the deflector. If you install the deflector while the window frame is still wet, your deflector may not attach as tightly. Give the windows time to air dry or wipe the frame and slot down with a dry towel before you prepare your wind deflector. <figure rend="Fit Wind Deflectors Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Inserting In-Channel Deflectors</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Place the wind deflector into the top window channel. Lift the deflector into the top corners of the channel first and push it into place. Press up on the middle and sides of the wind deflector to keep it securely fitted into the frame. <figure rend="Fit Wind Deflectors Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Attach any window clips, if applicable. Some wind deflectors come with clips to adhere the wind deflector's edges in place. If your wind deflector comes with any clips, push them up between the deflector and the window to fasten it in place. <figure rend="Fit Wind Deflectors Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Your wind deflector's instructions should indicate where, specifically, to put the clips in.</item></list></item>
<item>Check the window for obstructions. After you have put the deflector in place, roll the window up to check that it still works properly. If your window cannot roll up, try adjusting the wind deflector to shift it out of the way. <figure rend="Fit Wind Deflectors Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This is especially important for electric windows, which may refuse to roll up if they sense an obstruction in the way.</item>
<item>If you adjust the wind deflector, be careful not to force it in any position, as you may accidentally damage it.</item></list></item>
<item>Keep your window rolled up for 24 hours. Roll the window back up after you've finished adjusting its alignment and let it sit for at least 24 hours. This will give the wind deflector enough time to mold into the window so it will stay in place. <figure rend="Fit Wind Deflectors Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use a maintenance spray on the window if it works slowly. If your wind deflector seems to slow your windows down, use maintenance spray around the window channels and slot to keep it from catching on the frame while rolling up or down. <figure rend="Fit Wind Deflectors Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can purchase maintenance spray online or at most auto shops.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Applying Adhesive Deflectors Instead</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Peel off a small section of the double-sided tape liner from both sides. Several inches or centimeters is enough to test the deflector's fit. Place the wind deflector along the top of the window trim to test its approximate fit. <figure rend="Fit Wind Deflectors Step 11.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not remove all of the double-sided tape until you've aligned the wind deflector.</item></list></item>
<item>Adjust the wind deflector's alignment. Line the wind deflector up with the top of the window trim as closely as possible. When you've achieved an even fit, apply pressure to the peeled ends of the adhesive to secure the wind deflector in place. <figure rend="Fit Wind Deflectors Step 12.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If the wind deflector does not align with the top of the window, it may be the wrong size.</item></list></item>
<item>Remove the remainder of the adhesive tape. Pull on the adhesive tape's end strips until you have entirely removed them from the wind deflector. Apply pressure to the wind deflector as you peel off the tape to stick it firmly on your car. <figure rend="Fit Wind Deflectors Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Test the wind deflector for adherence. After you've bonded the wind deflector to your car, try to wiggle the deflector up and down. If the deflector has adhered properly, it shouldn't move. Apply more pressure to loose areas or adjust the wind deflector's positioning if it does move. <figure rend="Fit Wind Deflectors Step 14.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Wear gloves while cleaning your car and handling the wind deflectors to avoid smudging either as you work.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Paper towel</item>
<item>Microfiber cloth</item>
<item>Maintenance spray</item>
<item>Window clips (optional)</item></list>
</text>
