<text id="autogum_whow_doc029" title="Make Artwork More Realistic" shortTile="make-artwork-more" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-08-03" dateModified="2018-10-17" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-Artwork-More-Realistic" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make Artwork More Realistic</head><p>Realistic artworks are works of art that looks cool. This article provides guidance on how to make any artwork more realistic.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Pick the artwork you want to make more realistic. For example, an image of a snake. This will be your "base" artwork. It could take some time to get it perfect if you're drawing it from scratch.
<list type="unordered"><item>Try using shapes to get the base perfect. Use a circle for the head and eyes (Half circle for Evil eyes, oval for the body, etc.)</item>
<item>Make sure to add two lines to get the face right.</item></list></item>
<item>Create some texture in your art. For a lion, make it look furry, A snake or fish will be scaly, a bird will be feathery. Some animals or things can have more than one texture. Try many different kinds of textures.</item>
<item>Add some shading. Think of where the light would be. If it's coming from behind, the front would be darker then behind. If it's in front, the back would be a bit darker then the front.
<list type="unordered"><item>Try to think of it as a shadow.</item></list></item>
<item>Include some interesting effects to the art. Like glowing eyes, a slight glow, magic or flames, for example. This will add in some details to the drawing. Plus, it would look cool and neat.
<list type="unordered"><item>For most effects, you can use an oil brush, a big paintbrush or a water brush. This will add some realistic effects to the artwork. If you are creating an artwork using a computer programme, these brushes may be tools or options in the programme.</item>
<item>This can also apply to water to make it look real. Like a reflection.</item></list></item>
<item>Take a look at the art work. If it looks real, It's done. (Unless you want to add backgrounds)</item>
<item>Add in a background (optional). This will make the artwork more enjoyable and add a bit of scenery.
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure to add some depth to the artwork (Optional). This can be things like small object in the back, big objects in front, this kind of idea.</item></list></item>
<item>Submit the artwork online. You can use Devintart or any online art sites for it. Others can see it if you decide to do so. Just make sure to add your signature onto it to prevent art theft.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Take some time. Huge artworks aren't usually finished within a day. It can take weeks or even months to get it done.</item>
<item>Always save your work. You don't want to start all over again from scratch, do you?</item>
<item>You can always watch other artists draw artwork. This can help you make a good art work later on.</item>
<item>If doing it in real life, make sure to let the painting dry before sending it.</item>
<item>Make sure to get the shapes right or it'll look weird and cartoony.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't steal other peoples work. Nobody likes art theft.</item>
<item>Always remember to save or you could lose all the hard work on your art.</item>
<item>If you found out someone stole your work, report it.</item>
<item>Don't add in too many elements. Put in a little bit of elements to make it real.</item>
<item>Take time. Don't rush. It can take weeks or months to finish.</item>
<item>Always remember the Rules of thirds. This will help with making any artworks real or not.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Laptop (If your doing a digital artwork)</item>
<item>Paper (If your doing a drawing or painting)</item>
<item>Pencil</item>
<item>Colored pencils</item>
<item>Eraser</item></list>
</text>
