<text id="autogum_whow_doc323" title="Act at a Formal Dinner or Fancy Restaurant" shortTile="act-formal-dinner" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2008-06-02" dateModified="2019-08-08" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Act-at-a-Formal-Dinner-or-Fancy-Restaurant" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Act at a Formal Dinner or Fancy Restaurant</head><p>Are you trying to keep from reliving another embarrassing moment in a social setting or simply trying to prevent one from ever happening?  Regardless, you're in the right place.  This simple guide covers everything from simple ways to look elegant and formal to how to act from your steps to the way you sit and eat at the table.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Look the part. If you have long hair consider having your hair up, a less popular, but practical and sleeker option. Although down-dos are more common, up-dos are simple, neat, and stylish. Up-dos will not only make your hair stand out amid combed out hairdos, but keep it clear of your face as you eat. Your nails should be manicured: clean, cut and if painted, coloured to match your outfit. If you put makeup on, highlight either your eyes or your lips, or go for a more natural look. Less is more. <figure rend="Act at a Formal Dinner or Fancy Restaurant Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Choose a suitable outfit. Dress codes can be difficult to navigate, so be sure you know what it is. For a restaurant, check their website. For a dinner party, look at the invitation. If you are still in the dark, ask your host or a friend who you know is going. The best bet if you are unsure is a jacket and tie or a chiffon dress to the knee. If you are carrying a handbag match your bag with your shoes. <figure rend="Act at a Formal Dinner or Fancy Restaurant Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Sit properly.  Cross your legs at the heels with your knees together and ankles tucked back, this is especially important when wearing skirts and dresses. <figure rend="Act at a Formal Dinner or Fancy Restaurant Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you have been invited to a restaurant by someone else, do not complain about the food or the service.</item>
<item>Anything that is in your hands when you sit at the table, such as your gloves or little bag, should be put in your lap. To avoid the things in your lap from slipping off, put the napkin across your knees, folded diagonally from corner to corner, and tuck the two side corners under, pinning your things into place.</item>
<item>When a dinner has been prepared by a chef who prides himself on being a decorative artist, you may have quite a problem to know which part of an intricate structure is to be eaten and which part is scenic effect. The main portion is generally clear enough. If there are six or more, the chances are that they are edible and that one or two of a kind are embellishments only. Rings around food are nearly always to be eaten, whereas platforms under food seldom are. Anything that looks like pastry is meant to be eaten. Again, take direction from the host.</item>
<item>Manners are key! Keep the conversation flowing, but never interrupt anyone.</item>
<item>It is impolite for more than one person to leave the table at a time, regardless of the number of people at the table.</item>
<item>If at a fancy or formal restaurant, some will expect the inviter to pay the bill, not the invitee. However, in this day and age, it's not uncommon to split a bill.</item>
<item>Always keep the napkin or cloth on your lap when eating. When leaving, kindly excuse yourself from the table and place your napkin on the table.</item>
<item>Do not use your cell phone at the table while you're eating. Turn your cell phone onto silent mode during the meal. If you must leave it on, excuse yourself if it rings to go outside or to a private area.</item>
<item>Follow the direction of the host/hostess.</item>
<item>Be courteous. Say "please" and "thank you". You may call elders or people with whom you are unfamiliar "sir" or "ma'am", although it is an uncommon courtesy that is definitely unnecessary when speaking to friends or peers.</item>
<item>It is better to keep your legs closed rather than crossing them in public, especially when sitting at the table.  This can cause discomfort especially if the table is not high enough.</item>
<item>Never <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Apply_Makeup">apply makeup</ref> at the table.  Once again, excuse yourself to the powder room.</item>
<item>When walking in high heels the heel should hit the ground first, then the toe.  It has been proven not to be necessary to pace yourself in formal footwear, but walking turtle slow will make you appear as if you're trying too hard to be impressive.</item>
<item>Always show up on time. For meals, there is no such thing as fashionably late. If you aren't there by five minutes past the time on the invitation, the food will begin to get cold and fellow guests hungry. In Europe you are given exactly 15 minutes leeway, known as the 'academic quarter'.</item>
<item>Remember your table manners, don't talk when you still have food in your mouth.</item>
<item>Never start eating until the hosts are seated and they begin to eat.</item>
<item>Don't talk over somebody else; it is rude. If you must, push your chair back slightly and speak behind them.</item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Gracious">Be gracious</ref> and congenial - after all, your hosts have gone to great lengths for you.</item>
<item>Don't sit silently at the table, try participate in conversation even if you are nervous, some remembered lines can be helpful, for example 'have you come far?' might get a conversation going, without being as prying as the question  'where do you live'.</item>
<item>When getting out of a vehicle try your best to exit without showing your undergarments.  If there is a someone opening the door for you, remember to thank them.</item>
<item>It is impolite to refuse dishes. Take at least a little on your plate and make a pretense of eating some of it, unless you are allergic to it or reasonably <hi rend="italic">cannot</hi>.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Though your friends are your friends and you should always <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Yourself">be yourself</ref>, treat everyone with the same respect and get out of those slang using habits.  People will also lose respect for you if you use gross humor in any setting.</item></list>
</text>
