<text id="autogum_whow_doc023" title="Make Marble Art" shortTile="make-marble-art" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-09-06" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-Marble-Art" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make Marble Art</head><p>Marble Art is fun and easy to make with colorful swirling and stripy patterns.After you have finished,you can use it to make cards or use it to decorate your room!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Gather your ingredients. Make sure that you have all of them before you start making Marble Art.</item>
<item>Cut the piece of poster paper. According to the size you want it to be.You'll need the piece of paper for the art part later so make sure it is the size you want it to be (not bigger than the dish though).</item>
<item>Fill the dish/bowl with a thin layer of shaving foam. About a centimeter will do.This step is important so make sure the shaving foam covers the bottom of the dish and you can't see the bottom any more or it might not show the pattern after you have finished.(But again not too much).</item>
<item>Add the food coloring to the shaving foam. One drop at a time,make sure that you have a nice mixture of colors.Red,yellow and blue works best as they will mix together to form orange,purple and green.The colors need to be equal or the pattern might come out slightly uneven (but if you want,you can also make it more reddish,blueish or yellowish).</item>
<item>Use a tooth pick (or a chopstick) to draw some patterns. For example: swirls,loops,stripes and lots more! You can even mix the patterns that you like together to make your own funny unique patterns!</item>
<item>Put the paper flat onto the dish and press it lightly. About half a centimeter into the shaving foam.This will make the pattern stick to the paper so make sure you like your pattern before doing this step! (Be careful not to press too hard here).</item>
<item>Lift the paper up from the dish. You should see that a layer of shaving foam has stuck to the paper.Use the plastic lid to scrape the foam off,if the pattern comes out smudgy,scrape it once more until you see the pattern.(You should still scrape it off once more even though you see the pattern just to make sure).</item>
<item>Repeat the process until you have used up all your paper. If your shaving foam gets a bit mixed up,dirty or grayish,you can make a new layer of shaving foam but this time,you can make it a little bit thinner.</item>
<item>You should see that Marble Art comes out really nice and also easy to make. The patterns that you make can vary from curls to zigzags so if you want a different pattern,just draw your patterns differently or even mix up your patterns!After you've finished,go ahead and make it into a card or use it to decorate your room!!!</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>It might be useful if you wear an old shirt or an apron as it might get a little bit messy!</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Shaving Foam</item>
<item>Food Coloring</item>
<item>A Wide Dish/Bowl</item>
<item>Poster Paper</item>
<item>A Tooth Pick Or A Chop Stick</item>
<item>A Plastic Lid</item></list>
</text>
