<text id="autogum_whow_doc686" title="Choose a Fitness Tracker" shortTile="choose-fitness-tracker" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-05-30" dateModified="2018-06-19" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Choose-a-Fitness-Tracker" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Choose a Fitness Tracker</head><p>As more and more people are working towards leading healthier lives, the role of fitness trackers is increasing. For a beginner, maybe you don’t really know why you need a fitness tracker, or have no idea how to choose one that suits you. So, here are some things you should know before you order one.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Understanding the Benefits</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Know that a fitness tracker is more of a fitness friend and a strict coach than just a gadget. Its major functions are the standard of measurement and motivation. It lets you view all your activities in the form of information, so you can see how and where you spread your efforts during the workout routine. This information will later help you set smarter goals.</item>
<item>Understand your fitness goals. Since detailed orientation and clarity are high in priority when setting your fitness goals, a visual impression of your improvements will give you a great sense of accomplishment. Knowing what you have accomplished and what is yet to be accomplished is the main ingredient for setting better fitness goals. First, you need to write down the purpose of your tracker; whether it is losing weight, building your body, tracking your sleep or any other purpose you have.</item>
<item>Know that a fitness tracker will make it easier to monitor your heart rate. It is important to monitor your heart rate especially but not exclusively during your workout sessions. A fitness tracker will continue collecting data during your workout and even as you rest. This makes it convenient for you to single out the activities that overload you during exercises.</item>
<item>Know that a fitness tracker will help track your sleep. A fitness tracker has a role in every activity within the course of your lifestyle. This includes when you are resting or sleeping. Getting good quality sleep optimizes your rate of success in your fitness program. The whole of your body should be relaxed for you to make up for exhaustion and proper tissue building and repair.</item></list>
<head>Choosing the Right Fitness Tracker</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Choose the design you like and and the one that will be easy for you to use.</item>
<item>Make sure the tracker you choose is comfortable to wear. You are going to be wearing it for most of the time.</item>
<item>Choose the tracker according to your specific needs. Fitness trackers come with different tracking features. Though all activity trackers come with tracking features, some offer you more specific ones, such as GPS tracking, blood pressure monitor, etc. Some examples are:
<list type="unordered"><item>Heart rate monitoring feature - this feature can provide a big boost in accuracy of calorie burns.</item>
<item>Calorie tracker - this gives you the precise outcomes of your activities.</item></list></item>
<item>Choose a tracker with a good battery life. The battery life can range from one day to several months. The battery life of the fitness tracker for 5-7 days would be fine, but if you get a longer battery life, that would be even better.</item>
<item>Make sure your fitness tracker has water and sweat resistance. This allows you to easily wear them during exercise and swimming sessions.</item>
<item>Have a budget to buy a fitness tracker, depending on what company is selling it. Apple fitness trackers can be $400, while some Amazon fitness trackers are $15 or less. However, MoreFit fitness trackers are usually $20-$40.</item>
<item>Buy a fitness tracker with good compatibility. You should look for fitness bands that can seamlessly connect with your device. This is important and necessary. Consider buying a tracker that offers smartphone integration. </item>
<item>Consider buying a wireless fitness tracker. This lets you easily connect your fitness band to other wireless devices. Most of the fitness trackers come with a screen for displaying vital information.</item></list>
</text>
