<text id="autogum_whow_doc219" title="Host a Family Gathering" shortTile="host-family-gathering" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2010-07-05" dateModified="2019-09-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Host-a-Family-Gathering" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Host a Family Gathering</head><p>Family gatherings can be a chance for family members to reconnect and bond with each other.  If you happen to be hosting one, here are some tips to help you plan and host a fun reunion of your immediate family.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be precise but flexible when inviting family members.  In too many situations, hosts can be overly unclear on arriving times, or they can be too strict.  The best thing to do is create a window of time that is appropriate for a guest to arrive at your house. <figure rend="Host a Family Gathering Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't make all the food yourself.  Ask a person in each family unit to prepare a dish.  If they are famous for a certain dish in your family, ask them to make that.  Keep an even balance between appetizers, entrees, and desserts. <figure rend="Host a Family Gathering Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Decide what parts of your house are off-limits.  Inform each person as they walk in your door, and if you feel the need, make signs and tape them to doors of off-limits areas. <figure rend="Host a Family Gathering Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep children in mind.  Chances are that small children may be running around your house, and since the adults will most likely going to be occupied, leave out some child-friendly toys and activities in a common space, like a living room.  These items could be: <figure rend="Host a Family Gathering Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Board games</item>
<item>Toy cars or blocks</item>
<item>Video games</item>
<item>Television (block all inappropriate channels)</item></list></item>
<item>Privately tell an older child, minimum age 12, that they need to keep an eye on younger kids.  This will retain order in rooms where there is not constant adult supervision.  You can include a small monetary incentive, like $2 per hour.  Remind them not to be too “bossy” and to simply resolve small quarrels and retrieve adult help in case of problems on a bigger scale, like physical fighting or injuries.  This also gives a preteen a sense of importance, which is always good. <figure rend="Host a Family Gathering Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Purchase assorted crackers, chips, cheeses and dips.  Display them nicely on a coffee table or in a dining room.  This can be a common space where all guests are allowed, which gives them an opportunity to converse and bond, which is the goal of your party. <figure rend="Host a Family Gathering Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Create an adult dinner table and a kid's dinner table.  Chances are that you will not have room for all family members to dine together in the same room, so the practical thing to do is seat the children in the kitchen and the adults in the formal dining room.  Remember to check in on the kids occasionally. <figure rend="Host a Family Gathering Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Finally, say goodbye to all your guests as they leave your house.  This may be the last impression they have of you for a while, and you never know when you will see them again. <figure rend="Host a Family Gathering Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>A clean, childproof house</item>
<item>Appetizers, entrees, and desserts</item>
<item>Patience</item></list>
</text>
