<text id="autogum_whow_doc284" title="Cook Einkorn" shortTile="cook-einkorn" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-05-02" dateModified="2019-08-04" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Cook-Einkorn" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Cook Einkorn</head><p>Einkorn is one of the ancient grains that you've probably seen on grocery shelves. These berries are similar to farro or brown rice when cooked and they make a nutritious side. For basic boiled einkorn, simmer 1 part of einkorn in 2 parts of water until the berries are tender. Try a sweet breakfast porridge that's topped with fruit, nuts, and cream. You can also make a savory risotto that uses einkorn instead of traditional rice. </p>
<head>Ingredients</head>
<head>Basic Boiled Einkorn</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>1 cup (200 g) einkorn berries</item>
<item> water</item></list>
<p><hi rend="italic">Makes 4 servings</hi></p>
<head>Einkorn Breakfast Porridge</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>1/2 cup (100 g) einkorn berries</item>
<item>2 teaspoons (9 g) butter</item>
<item> whole milk</item>
<item> water, divided</item>
<item>Sliced fruit to serve</item>
<item>Sliced or chopped nuts to serve</item>
<item> heavy cream to serve</item></list>
<p><hi rend="italic">Makes 2 servings</hi></p>
<head>Savory Einkorn Risotto</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>1/2 (100 g) cup einkorn berries</item>
<item>1 garlic clove, minced</item>
<item> vegetable broth</item>
<item> water</item>
<item>1/2 cup (50 g) grated parmesan</item></list>
<p><hi rend="italic">Makes 2 servings</hi></p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Boiling Einkorn</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Put the einkorn and water into a pot. Measure 1 cup (200 g) of einkorn berries and  of water into a pot on the stove. <figure rend="Cook Einkorn Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Bring the einkorn and water to a boil. Turn the burner to high and leave the lid off of the pot so the water comes to a boil. <figure rend="Cook Einkorn Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Cover and simmer the einkorn for 30 to 35 minutes. Turn the burner down to medium or medium-low so the water bubbles gently. Put a lid on the pot and simmer the einkorn until most of the water is absorbed. <figure rend="Cook Einkorn Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The einkorn will swell as it cooks. Taste the einkorn to ensure it's soft to your liking.</item></list></item>
<item>Serve the basic cooked einkorn. Turn off the burner and serve the einkorn while it's hot or let it cool and serve the einkorn once it's warm. You can season it simply with butter, herbs, or spices. <figure rend="Cook Einkorn Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try using einkorn in place of rice in your favorite recipes.</item>
<item>Refrigerate leftover einkorn in an airtight container for up to 3 to 5 days.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Making Breakfast Einkorn Porridge</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Pulse the einkorn until it's coarsely cracked. Put 1/2 cup (100 g) of einkorn berries into a food processor. Put the lid on and pulse the berries 3 to 4 times until they're cracked. <figure rend="Cook Einkorn Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you don't have a food processor, you can crack the berries in a high-speed blender.</item></list></item>
<item>Melt the butter in a pot and stir in the einkorn. Place 2 teaspoons (9 g) of butter into a pot on the stove. Turn the burner to medium and melt the butter. Stir in the cracked einkorn and stir until it's coated in the butter. <figure rend="Cook Einkorn Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Let the einkorn cook for about 1 minute so it toasts a little and smells nutty.</item></list></item>
<item>Add the milk and water and bring it to a boil. Pour  of whole milk and  of the water into the pot with the einkorn. Turn the heat to medium-high so the liquid comes to a boil. <figure rend="Cook Einkorn Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you prefer, use low-fat, soy, nut, or hemp milk.</item></list></item>
<item>Cover and simmer the einkorn for 30 to 35 minutes. Turn the burner down to medium-low and put the lid on the pot. Let the einkorn bubble gently until it absorbs the liquid and becomes soft. <figure rend="Cook Einkorn Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If the einkorn has absorbed the liquid but isn't soft enough, pour in the reserved  of water and cook it for another 5 to 10 minutes.</item></list></item>
<item>Serve the breakfast porridge with fruit, nuts, and cream if desired. Turn off the burner and transfer the cooked einkorn to serving bowls. Sprinkle sliced or chopped nuts over the einkorn and serve it along with your favorite fruit. You can also drizzle a few spoonfuls of heavy cream over the porridge. <figure rend="Cook Einkorn Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>To add a little protein and crunch, top the einkorn with almonds, pecans, walnuts, or hazelnuts.</item>
<item>For a little sweetness, add sliced raisins, pears, peaches, or diced apples to the einkorn.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Cooking Savory Einkorn Risotto</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Pulse the einkorn until it's cracked and dusty. Put 1/2 (100 g) of cup einkorn berries into a food processor and put the lid on. Pulse the einkorn 4 to 5 times so the berries crack and make a little flour. <figure rend="Cook Einkorn Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Mince the garlic and put it in a pot with water and broth. <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Mince_Garlic">Mince 1 clove of garlic</ref> and scoop it into a large pot on the stove. Pour  of vegetable broth and  of water into the pot. <figure rend="Cook Einkorn Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Simmer the liquid. Turn the burner to high so the liquid comes to a boil. Then turn the burner down to medium so the liquid bubbles gently. Keep simmering the liquid the entire time you're cooking the einkorn. <figure rend="Cook Einkorn Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Put the cracked einkorn in a skillet. Put the skillet on the burner and turn it to medium-low. Once it's warm, stir in the cracked einkorn and let it toast for 1 to 2 minutes. <figure rend="Cook Einkorn Step 13.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The berries should smell a little nutty once they've toasted long enough.</item></list></item>
<item>Stir  of the liquid into the einkorn. Use a ladle to scoop about  of the liquid out of the pot and slowly pour it into the skillet with the einkorn. <figure rend="Cook Einkorn Step 14.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Stir well while you add the liquid so the einkorn absorbs it.</item></list></item>
<item>Keep stirring  of liquid into the einkorn until it's tender. Once the einkorn has absorbed the cupful of liquid, slowly stir in  at a time. The einkorn should be cooked and soft by the time you've finished adding the liquid. <figure rend="Cook Einkorn Step 15.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>It should take you 40 to 45 minutes to stir in all of the liquid. Avoid rushing this or the risotto won't cook properly.</item></list></item>
<item>Stir in the parmesan and serve the einkorn risotto. Turn off the burner and stir in ½ cup (50 g) of grated parmesan. Spoon the risotto onto serving plates or bowls and serve it along with your meal. <figure rend="Cook Einkorn Step 16.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If the risotto is too thick for your liking, you can add another splash of water or vegetable broth.</item>
<item>Store the leftover risotto in an airtight container in the refrigerator for up to 2 to 3 days.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<head>Basic Boiled Einkorn</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Measuring cups</item>
<item>Large pot with lid</item>
<item>Spoon</item></list>
<head>Einkorn Breakfast Porridge</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Food processor or high-speed blender</item>
<item>Measuring cups and spoons</item>
<item>Pot with lid</item>
<item>Spoon</item>
<item>Serving bowls</item></list>
<head>Savory Einkorn Risotto</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Measuring cups and spoons</item>
<item>Pot</item>
<item>Skillet</item>
<item>Ladle</item>
<item>Spoon</item>
<item>Food processor</item>
<item>Serving plates or bowls</item></list>
</text>
