<text id="autogum_whow_doc189" title="Entertain a Child on a Rainy Day" shortTile="entertain-child-rainy" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-10-21" dateModified="2019-10-21" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Entertain-a-Child-on-a-Rainy-Day" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Entertain a Child on a Rainy Day</head><p>A rainy day can make it difficult to keep a child entertained all day inside but it gives for the perfect opportunity to try new activities together. This article will provide you with a whole day of activities to keep your child engaged in fun. We’ll cover how to build a pillow fort, make blueberry muffins, and activities to do with friends.</p>
<head>Ingredients</head>
<head>Making Blueberry Muffins</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>1 cup flour</item>
<item>1 cup oatmeal</item>
<item>3 tablespoons sugar</item>
<item>1 teaspoon salt</item>
<item>4 teaspoons baking powder</item>
<item>1 cup blueberries, washed</item>
<item>1 egg</item>
<item>1 cup milk</item>
<item>¼ cup vegetable oil</item></list>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Building a Pillow Fort</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Ask the child you are watching to help build a pillow fort with you. Go into a room with a couch. This will be the room your pillow fort will be built in. Measure the area and rearrange furniture to accommodate the potential size of your fort. Avoid building your fort near windows, doors, and exterior walls.</item>
<item>Arrange two chairs about 3 feet from the couch, facing each other to make the other two corners of your fort. These chairs will also serve as shelves in your fort.</item>
<item>Drape a bedsheet over the top of the chairs and the couch to provide a roof. Make sure the long edge is covering the top of the couch backrest for a maximized space. Lightly tug on the ends of the bed sheet to ensure it is covering all sides.</item>
<item>Secure the roof by holding down the ends of your blanket with clean, heavy items (books, large toys, canned goods, etc.) or string to stabilize your fort. Make sure you leave space for an entrance/exit and gaps between blankets for ventilation.  <figure rend="4603035328_f4935c8383_o.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Adjust the distance between your chairs and the couch to be closer together to prevent the bed sheet from slipping.</item></list></item>
<item>Cover the floor of your fort with comfortable items to sit on. Don’t use the comforter from your bed, instead try layering the floor with sleeping bags, thick blankets, and pillows you don’t mind getting dirty.</item>
<item>Divide areas in your fort with couch cushions to section off smaller rooms within your fort and add glow sticks or a flashlight for lighting. Ask your child if they would like to bring their favorite toy or stuffed animal into the pillow fort as well.</item></list>
<list type="unordered"><item>Bean bags and air mattresses make for enjoyable seating. Make sure your roof is high enough before attempting to include them to your fort.</item></list>
<head>Making Blueberry Muffins</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Wash your hands with soap and water. Be sure your child does too, then ask them to help prep the work space. Clean off all surfaces with a sponge and hot, soapy water. Preheat oven to 400° F. Get out all ingredients and measure them.  <figure rend="3283330787_3813a61404.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Mix together flour, oatmeal, sugar, salt, and baking powder in a large bowl, then mix in blueberries.
<list type="unordered"><item>Don’t add more than the instructed amount of blueberries. They might look sparse in the batter, but there will be plenty of blueberry in the muffins because blueberries bleed while baking.</item></list></item>
<item>Break the egg into another bowl and use a fork to beat it. In the new bowl, add the milk and vegetable oil, then mix together. Add this mixture to the mixture from step 2 in the large bowl. Using a mixing spoon, gently stir all the ingredients together to avoid squishing the blueberries. Your mixture should have lumps so don't mix more than 25 to 30 stirs.</item>
<item>Spray a muffin tray with nonstick spray and spoon in the muffin mix. Fill 12 muffin cups about two-thirds of the way up. Clean excess muffin mix from spills on the tray.</item>
<item>Put the tray in the oven after it’s finished preheating and bake for about 20 minutes. When muffins are finished baking, remove from oven. Allow muffins to cool about 5 minutes before transferring to a wire rack to cool completely.</item>
<item>Clean up after you’re done. After your snack is ready to go, put away all the unused ingredients in the fridge or cupboard. Wash the muffin tray, mixing bowls, and mixing utensils. Use a sponge with soap and hot water to wipe up crumbs and sticky spills on the counters.  <figure rend="217409802_1f39065618_k.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Eat your blueberry muffins. All your hard work will taste delicious! Leftovers should be stored inside a container and kept in a pantry.</item></list>
<head>Doing Activities with Friends</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Invite a friend of the child you are entertaining to come over. Ask the child which of their friends they would like to have over, then call the chosen friend on the phone to invite them over. Confirm the play date details with the friend’s parent before having them over.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you don't have the friend’s phone number beforehand, obtain it from the child’s parent or a phonebook.</item></list></item>
<item>Play a game of Go Fish.
<list type="unordered"><item>Sit together in a circle and shuffle a deck of cards. Deal 7 cards to each player, then set the remainder of the deck face down in the center of the circle. Each player should look at their cards, careful not to show any other players. Then it is the player to the left of the dealer’s turn to ask any player for a card with a value (numbers, jack, queen, king or ace), which they must have in their hand while asking.</item>
<item>If the person asked has the card, they must hand it over to askee. This makes a match and the askee can set down their two matching cards for points. The askee receives another turn until asking a player for a card they do not have.</item>
<item>When the person asked does not have the card, they say “Go Fish”. The askee’s turn is over and they must pick a card from the center. The player to the left of them now has a turn.</item>
<item>Continue taking turns until all cards run out. The winner is the player with the most matches.</item>
<item>Example: “Adam, do you have any sevens?” “Go Fish”</item></list></item>
<item>Watch a movie. Bring a laptop inside the fort you made in part 1 and let the children choose a DVD or a movie from a streaming site rated PG or lower. Make sure the children are comfortable and have enough blankets before playing the movie. Provide them with water and leftover snacks from part 2. You can now relax, you have provided entertainment to last a child all day inside.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>blankets</item>
<item>bedsheet, size queen or larger</item>
<item>two chairs</item>
<item>couch</item>
<item>cushions and/or pillows</item>
<item>nonstick spray</item>
<item>oven</item>
<item>mixing bowls</item>
<item>muffin tray</item>
<item>wire rack</item>
<item>mixing utensils</item>
<item>cleaning supplies</item>
<item>phone</item>
<item>card deck</item>
<item>laptop</item>
<item>movies</item>
<item>a friend</item></list>
</text>
