<text id="autogum_whow_doc482" title="Garden in the Tropics" shortTile="garden-tropics" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-04-05" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Garden-in-the-Tropics" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Garden in the Tropics</head><p>Gardening is a fun and rewarding hobby that will also offer self-satisfaction. There’s nothing like planting a seed and watching it grow into a full plant. Tropical gardening is not much different than any other types of gardening. Plants still share the same basic needs: healthy soil, water, and proper fertilization.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Preparing for Gardening</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Research your area's climates and plants that grow well there. Find out what plants do well in the tropics and make sure they can withstand any difficulties they could face.
<list type="unordered"><item>Research the native plants in your area. Native plants tend to grow more successfully in your area as they can grow in every condition that your area gives. They also can adapt to changes more easily than other plants.</item>
<item>Research your area's weather conditions. This way, you'll be able to better assess your plants' needs</item></list></item>
<item>Pick a location that provides for the necessities of your plants. This one matters the most when the preparation is brought to mind. You should assess the following:
<list type="unordered"><item>The amount of sunlight exposure during the day. The location must receive the right amount of sunlight exposure, depending on what kind of plants you want to grow. Some plants need less sunlight while others require more.</item>
<item>The texture of the soil. For the most part, plants do well in loamy, well-draining soil. The fertility content of the soil, however, does depend on your plants.</item></list></item>
<item>Prepare the necessary materials. You should have the following at hand:
<list type="unordered"><item>Rake</item>
<item>Spade or shovel</item>
<item>Fertilizer</item>
<item>Water</item>
<item>Seeds (purchase them from gardening stores or get seeds from fruits/existing plants)</item></list></item>
<item>Prepare the area.
<list type="unordered"><item>Remove any weeds and debris of any kind.</item>
<item>Till the soil for at least  deep.</item>
<item>Work the fertilizer (or the kitchen waste if you can't find fertilizer) into the soil.</item>
<item>Rake the fertilizer all over the area.</item>
<item>Poke holes, about  apart from each other.</item></list></item>
<item>Start planting. Insert seeds into the holes. Remember, the planting depth and space requirements may differ from one plant to another, so take them into consideration when doing this.
<list type="unordered"><item>Among the major field crops, oats, wheat, and rye are sown, grasses and legumes are seeded, and maize and soybeans are planted.</item>
<item>Cover the seeds lightly with soil.</item>
<item>Water generously until germination.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Caring for the Plants</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Apply <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/Apply-Weed-and-Feed">weed and feed</ref> regularly. This will keep weeds from germinating in your yard.
<list type="unordered"><item>People and pets should stay away from the treatment areas during weed and feed application, and until the product's dust settles. Wear protective clothing including gloves, long sleeves, and long pants when you use weed and feed products.</item></list></item>
<item>Mulch the plants. This will retain moisture and hinder the growth. You can lay down dead leaves from trees nearby.
<list type="unordered"><item>Soil amendment can also be used as mulch.</item></list></item>
<item>You should always be prepared for problems that may occur in the garden, such as:
<list type="unordered"><item>Pests. You can eliminate them by planting attractants for predacious creatures or by using organic pesticides.</item>
<item>Diseases. You can eliminate them by having a schedule and keeping it consistent (ex. a watering schedule). Some diseases could infect and kill plants easily, so getting rid of the problem at an earlier stage will ensure your peace of mind.</item>
<item>Excessive heat. Although plants generally like the sun, they can get overwhelmed if they're being exposed to it for too long. Covering them or determining the perfect location can defeat the excessive heat of the sun.</item>
<item>Stress. Plants can get stressed when crowded, provided the least amount of their needs or the wrong requirements for them to survive. This can be solved by <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/Organize-Your-Ideas-With-a-Planting-Plan">planning</ref> carefully before beginning the plantation.</item></list></item>
<item>Enjoy your wonderful garden! Following these steps will ensure you a happier experience and a bountiful garden.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't use any chemicals on your plants. This will harm and kill plants and other insects that are helping your garden flourish.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Rake</item>
<item>Spade or shovel</item>
<item>Fertilizer</item>
<item>Water</item>
<item>Seeds (purchase them from gardening stores or get seeds from fruits/existing plants)</item></list>
</text>
