<text id="autogum_whow_doc667" title="Start a Relay for Life Team" shortTile="start-relay-life" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2010-06-08" dateModified="2016-01-08" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Start-a-Relay-for-Life-Team" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Start a Relay for Life Team</head><p>Relay for Life is a 24-hour event on your community's local track and football field, dedicated to people cancer has affected in any way. This event was created by the ACS, or American Cancer Society. If there is a Relay for Life scheduled for your community, make a team and join in! Read this article to find out how.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Ask about 15 close friends or family members if they are interested. If they are, write down their names, and ask for team name ideas and possible fundraising methods. <figure rend="Start a Relay for Life Team Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Hold a team meeting. It doesn't have to be formal; meet at your house or at a local coffee shop or somewhere similar. If you can, bring a laptop so your future team can be there when you sign them up. Decide on a team name, and brainstorm more fundraising ideas. At the relay you are expected to set up a booth selling a service or product to other relay participants to raise more money for cancer. Good ideas are baked goods, used books, or t-shirts. <figure rend="Start a Relay for Life Team Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Vote on team captains and chaperones. You will most likely be the captain since you organized the team. <figure rend="Start a Relay for Life Team Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>At the meeting, register your team and all the members on <ref target="http://www.relayforlife.org">http://www.relayforlife.org</ref>. It is convenient to do this in one sitting so you don't have to constantly remind your team members to sign up. <figure rend="Start a Relay for Life Team Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you have team members under the age of 18, there are more forms for them and their guardians to sign. Print these out, and distribute them to their respective recipients. <figure rend="Start a Relay for Life Team Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Create a small folder and a workspace for you to keep papers and money. It is imperative that you keep organized to assure that you don't lose any important documents. <figure rend="Start a Relay for Life Team Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have another team meeting. Set a donation goal for your team. Ask team members to collect money from people to reach your goal. Participants who raise at least $100 get a Relay for Life t-shirt. Also, decide who will bring a large camping tent for your team to sleep in. You will additionally need another tent or shelter for your booth at the relay, along with tables, markers, signs, and other things. Distribute the flyer that describes what each individual team member should bring. <figure rend="Start a Relay for Life Team Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Check the weather the day before the relay. Protocol states that in the event that there is torrential rain, thunder, and/or lightning, all people must go to their cars or some other indoor area, like locker rooms or bathrooms. Make a plan with your team in the event that there is bad weather. <figure rend="Start a Relay for Life Team Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't use solely this article for guidance; consult the Relay for Life website and your team.</item>
<item>Above all, keep you and your team safe during the relay.</item>
<item>Always meet with your team when making decisions.</item></list>
</text>
