<text id="autogum_whow_doc153" title="Communicate Effectively With a Teenage Daughter" shortTile="communicate-effectively" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2012-08-23" dateModified="2019-01-15" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Communicate-Effectively-With-a-Teenage-Daughter" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Communicate Effectively With a Teenage Daughter</head><p>Teenage girls have a lot on their minds, and because they're young, sometimes don't know how to cope with it all. This unfortunate fact can sometimes create tension between them and you. But what they may not know is that you are their biggest fan, and this article will tell you how to show them that, and how to develop a comfortable, expressive, loving relationship with her.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Figure out what makes her tick. If you know what she likes and dislikes, this will give you common ground. <figure rend="Communicate Effectively With a Teenage Daughter Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Let her know that you love her. Don't be overbearing with this one. Maybe you could start small.Write a little note and stick it on her mirror. Make her cookies. Give her a ride somewhere. Come to her games or plays. <figure rend="Communicate Effectively With a Teenage Daughter Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Forgive her. She is young and is still figuring things out. Teach her what she did wrong if she's made a mistake, but make sure she knows you still love her. Let her know that you forgive her and understand that everybody makes mistakes. <figure rend="Communicate Effectively With a Teenage Daughter Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Realize that teenage girls are EXTREMELY emotional. This is true for every single teenage girl, whether they show it on the outside or not. Just because she yells at you doesn't mean she hates you. If she does, it's probably because she has reached the end of her rope and doesn't know how to react to her situation. Let her cry if she needs to. Cry with her, but not too much. Rejoice with her. Be a strong anchor for her while her emotions are unsettled from hormones, lack of sleep, and too much going on. <figure rend="Communicate Effectively With a Teenage Daughter Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do things with her. Find activities you both enjoy and spend time together. <figure rend="Communicate Effectively With a Teenage Daughter Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try to see things from her perspective. This is a big one. Try to see what circumstances and emotions are making her think the ways she does. <figure rend="Communicate Effectively With a Teenage Daughter Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure she knows she can come to you with concerns. This is huge. When a teenage daughter knows that they can go to their parent(s) with concerns, problems, and joys, it makes communication meaningful and easy. <figure rend="Communicate Effectively With a Teenage Daughter Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure she knows that you are interested in her life and concerns. <figure rend="Communicate Effectively With a Teenage Daughter Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Give her hugs, if she likes it. But even if she doesn't hug her once in a while.</item>
<item>Make sure you have a general idea of where she is and what she's doing.</item>
<item>Make sure she knows that you are there for more than just telling her what to do.</item>
<item>Even if it seems like you're not getting through to her, you really are. She is probably too proud or emotional to show it.</item>
<item>Every once in a while, give her a break with chores and such if she needs it. This will help her know that you realize she needs breaks sometimes and that you love her.</item>
<item>Sometimes, but not always, you need to initiate the conversations. There's a delicate balance of initiating and not initiating conversation which depends on each girl.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't scold her in front of her friends or other people she cares about.</item>
<item>Don't let her control you. That is, make sure that you are still the boss. Parents need to teach their children, but do it gently.</item>
<item>Don't let her have too much or too little freedom. Both of these can have very bad outcomes.</item>
<item>Don't tease about boys too much. This will push away open conversation about boys and dating.</item></list>
</text>
