<text id="autogum_whow_doc017" title="Be a Beatles Fan" shortTile="beatles-fan" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2010-09-10" dateModified="2019-06-05" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be-a-Beatles-Fan" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be a Beatles Fan</head><p>Do you like The Beatles, but you're not really a true fan? The Beatles are still popular today, and have been for years! Be a fan with article, and you'll be a fan in no time!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Buy all the music you can find on online stores and at Target. You are bound to find their music under "Classic Rock." "Sgt. Pepper's Lonely Hearts Club Band" is really popular, as is "Strawberry Fields Forever" and "Rubber Soul", but almost all their music is a must have if you want to be a true fan. <figure rend="Be a Beatles Fan Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Buy various T-shirts. T-shirts are essential when you're a Beatles fan. You can find all sorts of T-shirts of The Beatles on Amazon or eBay. Try to buy brand new ones. <figure rend="Be a Beatles Fan Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Buy some memorabilia. You can find all your Beatles stuff on eBay and Amazon. Memorabilia is also a good thing to have when you're a true fan of something. <figure rend="Be a Beatles Fan Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have/make some posters. Posters of The Beatles can be found in a lot places. Try to get one with all four of them in the picture. <figure rend="Be a Beatles Fan Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Listen to their music all the time. Don't play it aloud late at night when people are sleeping, though. Then you'll just be a nuisance. <figure rend="Be a Beatles Fan Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wear your T-shirts all the time and let people see your memorabilia! <figure rend="Be a Beatles Fan Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Study up on the history of the Fab Four. Read biographies and autobiographies, watch documentaries (the Beatles anthology videos are very good), films the four starred in like, "A Hard Day's Night" and "Help!" Study Lennon's artwork. Anything that will help you connect and feel closer to the Four Lads from Liverpool! <figure rend="Be a Beatles Fan Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Listen to the solo work. If you learn a bit about John and his Plastic Ono Band, Paul McCartney and Wings, George Harrison and his Traveling Wilburys, and Ringo and his All Starr Band, you'll begin to recognize each member as an individual person, and not just as one whole group known as The Beatles. You'll grow familiar with their music styles, the things they sing about, and the way each man was. <figure rend="Be a Beatles Fan Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Learn the meaning behind each song. It helps you learn about their lives, families, and interests. You'll begin to feel close and you may even be able to relate to each member! It adds a bit of a story and even more meaning to the songs they had written. <figure rend="Be a Beatles Fan Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Wearing your T-shirts will help people to realize you love The Beatles.</item>
<item>Knowing about The Beatles' backstory is all about being a fan of them.</item>
<item>If you want to listen to the Beatles in a really nostalgic and traditional way, listen to them on vinyl. However, this may be difficult as many original copies of Beatles' albums are worth a fortune nowadays.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Memorabilia</item>
<item>Posters</item>
<item>T-Shirts</item>
<item>Beatles music</item>
<item>Biographies</item>
<item>Documentaries</item></list>
</text>
