<text id="autogum_whow_doc632" title="Find the True Religion" shortTile="find-true-religion" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-07-18" dateModified="2018-01-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Find-the-True-Religion" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Find the True Religion</head><p>This is NOT an article about which religion is the right one for you. This is more like which religion is right and who will go to hell.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Read the Holy Books!                                                                                                                                       Reading the source should give you all the information needed about that religion. Now, about religions that have no books... İ can't guarantee that the information that you will get will be %100 procent correct. İt will however be more peaceful then old books which are ofthen a lot more hatefull than adapting, bookless religions! Read the most common choice of your country first! İt could hurt to try other books but who could stop you! Who knows, maybe you have been born in the wrong country!:)</item>
<item>Use your sense of Logic! Now, this is important because you have to use your own sense not common sense, ok? Do you think what you read is the right answer? İf not then try reading another one! Continue until you either totally loose direction or find peace! İt is important that you DO NOT read another book if you think you found the right one.</item>
<item>İf you found it by now, congrats! Please immediately stop reading. As for you, lost reader... you know why you are lost? Because all those stories... all those books... are all the same. There is no difference but a symbol and a few characters. İ don't even want to mention that there are SO MANY religions! Who is right?! Now you have to understand that people kill each other because of these symbols... Wars were started because of these symbols...  But only written religions, right? Well, yes actually! See if you can find a religion that is totally based on development and culture!</item>
<item>Happy? Or did İ awake something in you by mentioning all those disturbing things... All, İ wanted to say was that you should use your own sense of logic before believing! İf you happen to realize something off with all of the things you have heard up to now İ would highly suggest Agnostizm or Deizm. İ really do! Try it!</item>
<item>İf you happen to still be reading then you might be a 'realistic' person? You shouldn't consider trying to find the true religion if you lack on fate about the pure existence of God. İf you do though then welcome to club. you can feel at home between peaceful Atheists or rebel against religiouse people on YouTube! İ can't say that you should do that though... People have feelings. And some really believe, unlike you maybe? İf you happen to stumble into non-believing just remember, you are not alone. Google all those celebrities that are like you! Even if we are going to hell, no matter who we are or what we really believe in, we will be in good company.:)</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>These might be of your interest: Hinduism, Buddhism would be common and peaceful choices! There are also less known ones like:Pastafarianism. They believe that their deeds on Earth can affect the afterlife. They use the Pastafarian core values to guide them.A bit non believing but there is Jainism which is pretty much Atheism with Rules!The first vow in Jainism is to minimize intentional and unintentional harm to living things.</item></list>
</text>
