<text id="autogum_whow_doc338" title="Use Modern Psychology to Live a Happy Life" shortTile="use-modern-psychology" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-04-05" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Use-Modern-Psychology-to-Live-a-Happy-Life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Use Modern Psychology to Live a Happy Life</head><p>The field of Psychology had long been dominated by disorders. Since the 1990s, however, a new breed of psychologists, led by Martin Seligman, Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi, and Jonathan Haidt, among others, launched the "positive psychology" movement, focusing their research and projects on human flourishing - how to develop our values, strengths, virtues, and talents, and find meaning, purpose, and fulfillment in our lives.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Know yourself. <figure rend="Use Modern Psychology to Live a Happy Life Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Quiz thyself at the University of Pennsylvania's free Questionnaires Center. Try the General Happiness Scale, Satisfaction with Life Scale, Optimism Test, and Character Strengths (long form);</item>
<item>Listen to your critics - a good place to look for wisdom is where you least expect it: in the minds of your opponents;</item>
<item>If you've been feeling down for weeks, take the CES-D (depression) Questionnaire. If you score below 16, seek help from a mental health professional, and let your doctor know.</item></list></item>
<item>Strengthen your body and your mind. <figure rend="Use Modern Psychology to Live a Happy Life Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Body - walking even just 15 mins/day, 5 days a week, makes a big difference (bonus points if you walk with a friend); take 2 fish-oil pills a day to help your mood, brain, and heart;</item>
<item>Mind - meditate even just 15 mins/day - there are tons of free resources for an easy, guided, start; try Cognitive Behavior Therapy; hypnosis (no, really); happy pills - selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRI) - ask your doctor.</item></list></item>
<item>Work on your relationships harder than you do your work. On your deathbed, will you wish you had spent more time at the office, or with your friends and family? <figure rend="Use Modern Psychology to Live a Happy Life Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Work on your most valued relationships. Do something thoughtful and out of the ordinary. Write gratitude letters. Learn the science of love &amp; attachment, together;</item>
<item>Join a gang, or start one. Get together weekly or monthly to share an activity;</item>
<item>Perform random acts of kindness;</item>
<item>Get a dog - they co-evolved with us, and their ability to bond and to love meshes well with our own</item></list></item>
<item>Like what you do. <figure rend="Use Modern Psychology to Live a Happy Life Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Focus on how you help people and contribute to the common good;</item>
<item>Focus on your strengths (see Step 1) and use at least one of them every day, in a new way;</item>
<item>Master your work;</item>
<item>Find Flow - do challenging tasks that use your strengths; concentrate; get immediate feedback as you progress;</item>
<item>Take control, even a little control, over how your work is done;</item>
<item>Build alliances - connect and engage with people who can make your work better</item></list></item>
<item>Reach outside of yourself. <figure rend="Use Modern Psychology to Live a Happy Life Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be a bee - our lives only make full sense as members of a larger hive, or as cells in a larger body. Try religion, teaching, science, political campaigns;</item>
<item>Join an organization that has a noble purpose and a noble past. Any volunteer work can take you beyond yourself, but one that has history, traditions, and rituals makes it easier;</item>
<item>Try to live a virtuous life - enhance peace, harmony &amp; cooperation; exercise your best virtues (see Step 1);</item>
<item>Be One with The Multiverse - in a unified whole, where everything is accepted, nothing is judged; lose your self in an infinity of wonder, awe, joy, love, and gratitude (f.e via an ecstatic religious experience, or psilocybin mushrooms - ask your shaman).</item></list></item></list>
</text>
