<text id="autogum_whow_doc499" title="Get on Track" shortTile="get-on-track" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2007-02-18" dateModified="2019-08-09" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get-on-Track" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get on Track</head><p>We all need help getting organized and to stop splitting ourselves in two, trying to accomplish too much. Whether it's for work, school, or just daily activities, we need to approach personal organization methodically and with a sense of routine, in order to catch up with everything we need to do in our busy lives.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Utilize your time efficiently.  Perhaps you are the person who likes to have "Star Trek" playing in the background, but make sure that you do not spend too much time watching the television or just staring at the ceiling.  It may be uncomfortable to sit in your chair the entire time; you can occasionally walk around for a few minutes.  If you about an hour for one task, make sure that you are working most of the time. <figure rend="Get on Track Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Just get started, even if you are not exactly sure what to do.  Getting started is the most difficult step, and once you get started, you are much more likely to finish. <figure rend="Get on Track Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Prioritize.  Do the most important things first to ensure that they will get done, even if you know that you will not have time to do everything. <figure rend="Get on Track Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make time to do the things you need to do first thing in the morning. Start out by giving yourself plenty of time in the morning to get ready. If this means getting up half an hour earlier than normal, accommodate this - simply go to bed half an hour earlier to make up for it. You may want to read the paper, exercise or just <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Listen">listen</ref> to music. Whatever it is, make this time special and uninterrupted. <figure rend="Get on Track Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Eat a good breakfast. Do not skip this important meal that provides your with morning energy. <figure rend="Get on Track Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make a checklist that will help you to remember what to take from the house and what to bring back home each day. It can be a written list to begin with, and as you familiarize yourself with it, you will form a mental checklist. Before heading to or from work, school, activities, etc., use this checklist to make sure you have everything, such as your briefcase, backpack, purse, wallet, swimming gear, sports equipment, and notes. <figure rend="Get on Track Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Discover how you can be most productive.  Some people like to work on a project until they finish; others need many breaks.  Some prefer long sessions; others prefer short, concentrated sessions. <figure rend="Get on Track Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Change your perception of time by balancing things. If you concentrate too much on one thing, one project, or one person, time may start to disappear on you. You may have more fun if you have several projects that you are working on at once.  You probably have several tasks to tackle each day, so spend some time on one and then spend some time another.  This is especially important if you become stuck and do not know what to do next for that task.  If you take a break and come back later, you may be able to see something that you missed before.  Spread your talents, your time and your interests more widely and it will also seem as if time stretches a little to accommodate these things.  Remember not to overdo commitments, however. This is just about making your focus wider. <figure rend="Get on Track Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Relax">Relax</ref> and unwind when you go home. Do not rush into household chores, but relax for about an hour. Sit down over a cup of coffee or a snack and then start to attend to other things once your relaxation time has settled you back in comfortably. Work, chores, laundry, dinner, homework, etc. will all benefit from a rest and your rejuvenation. <figure rend="Get on Track Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Prepare for bed. When you have finally finished your chores and activities for the day, start to get ready for bed.  If you have children, put them to bed and make a little "me" time at night.  You will want to be well rested for the next day. <figure rend="Get on Track Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Reward yourself when you finish a task or achieve one of your goals.  A reward can be something as simple as a small snack or a walk around the neighborhood. <figure rend="Get on Track Step 11.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure you have enough time for all of your activities.</item>
<item>Avoid distractions that could wreak havoc with your entire schedule.  Are you distracted by the television or the conversations of family members?  Find a quiet room in the house in which you can concentrate.</item>
<item>Stay on a schedule. Wake up and go to sleep at about the same time each day.  That way, you can spend less time in bed trying to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Fall_Asleep">fall asleep</ref> or trying to get up when you are tired.  Consider eating dinner at a set time each day.  Buy a nice calendar to help you finish projects on time.</item>
<item>When you feel overwhelmed, do the easy tasks first.  You will be making progress (instead of just staring and wishing that you were doing something else), and it will help restore your confidence.</item>
<item>Stay organized!  You can waste a great deal of time looking for things that are always being misplaced.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Never overwork yourself.</item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Forgive">Forgive</ref> yourself if you occasionally get off track.  You have failed only if you do not get back on track and give up.  A day of rest may even make you more productive.</item>
<item>Remember that you will be very busy for some periods of time.  When you have several other important events happening in your life, you may not be able to get as much done for a while.</item></list>
</text>
