<text id="autogum_whow_doc636" title="Learn About Voodoo" shortTile="learn-voodoo" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-03-30" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Learn-About-Voodoo" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Learn About Voodoo</head><p>Have you ever been interested in the religion based in the rich African/Catholic culture of New Orleans? If so, this article is for you!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Identify What You Want &amp; Learn About Voodoo.</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Understand the difference between Voodoo and Hoodoo. Voodoo is a religion that originated in Africa (and is practiced in Haiti), and was brought to the Americas and the Caribbean by slaves, while Hoodoo is the witchcraft most usually associated with Voodoo.
<list type="unordered"><item>Voodoo and Hoodoo often can go together though! So if you're interested in both, they go together very well. You don't have to want to learn Hoodoo if you're interested in Voodoo, and vice versa. Many Hoodoo practitioners were/are Roman Catholic.</item></list></item>
<item>Make sure Voodoo is for you. Don't try to force yourself to believe in something for the social factor of it. Religious beliefs can be incredibly important, and you shouldn't do it to seem "cool" or "different".</item></list>
<list type="ordered"><item>Once you're certain you know what you want, go to a popular chain bookstore. Often, in the "New Age + Spirituality" section, they will have books detailing Voodoo and Hoodoo. If they don't, don't worry! There are plenty of online resources.</item>
<item>Go online. Starting in places like Wikipedia is smart, to find out if the religion suits you. After that, you can look at their sources at the bottom of the page and be re-directed to sites that can be extremely helpful.</item>
<item>Look for practitioners blogs, and see if they have details on their religion. Usually, these are the best people to go to in order to understand how it is applied in the modern day and age.</item>
<item>See if you can meet people in real life that practice Voodoo and get them to detail some things for you. Of course, don't annoy them profusely or try to get them to teach you full-time, just ask them how it works for them, how it affects their daily life, etc.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be careful what you believe. Not everyone understands every aspect, and since it is such a personal religion, it can be fraught with opinions of others. Identify how each aspect makes you feel, and decide how you apply it to your faith.</item>
<item>Research on each author you find. Many in the community may not agree with the person, and it can lead you to many misunderstandings.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not force others to believe in the things you do.</item>
<item>Try not to freak others out, as it can harm personal relationships. Present Voodoo as a regular religion, and try to explain the finer details.</item>
<item>Reading resources that refer to Voodoo itself as Hoodoo- the witchcraft associated with Voodoo- are most likely not veritable.</item></list>
</text>
