<text id="autogum_whow_doc387" title="Make a Smoker Out of Aluminum" shortTile="make-smoker-out-aluminum" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2017-10-03" dateModified="2017-10-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-a-Smoker-Out-of-Aluminum" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make a Smoker Out of Aluminum</head>Once summer comes around you want to sit outside with friends and do something fun, like have a barbecue! Unfortunately, buying a barbecue smoker could be pretty expensive, so why not make one at home? In this wikiHow, you'll learn just how to do that!
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Get all the materials. There's a list at the bottom of the article under the Things You'll Need section. Luckily, most of these things can be found at your local home improvement retailer! If something can't be found, then you can probably ask a friend or order it online. <figure rend="Wikihow tools.png"></figure></item>
<item>Prepare the oil drum. Make sure that your drum doesn't contain anything that could cause a problem, like flammable liquids, for example. After you have made sure that your oil drum is safe, you will want to strip the paint off with the angle grinder. Make sure you are wearing your eye and face protection at this point! <figure rend="Oil Drum.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you don't know how to check for flammable liquids, it is best to speak to a professional and have them make sure your oil drum is safe to work with!</item></list></item>
<item>Create the Chimney for the Smoker <figure rend="Cut pipe.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Cut your steel tubing at a 45-degree angle, and then twist the portion 180 degrees to weld it back on. Make sure the weld is all the way around the tubing, so you have a good seal.</item></list></item>
<item>Make a lid. <figure rend="Lid cut.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Create some dimensions with your measuring tools for the lid now, and mark them with the permanent marker. Make sure the oil drum is stable and then use your angle grinder with a cutting disk here to cut along the lines.</item></list></item>
<item>Weld the lid onto the drum <figure rend="English23.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Weld your strips of steel sheeting onto the oil drum. This will add stability and let the lid rest in place when closed.</item></list></item>
<item>Clean the inside of the BBQ <figure rend="Clean Drum.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The main goal for cleaning the inside is not so it can be spotless, but for two reasons: 1) If it is not clean of oil the paint will not stick. 2) If the oil is there once you start it it will emit thick black smoke.</item>
<item>Remove the grease by using a de-greaser. You can use the same one you use for your oven or you can buy one at any supermarket.</item></list></item>
<item>Fabricate the collapsible frame <figure rend="Brackets.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>A collapsible frame consists of two rectangles that will fold inside of each other. Using a hacksaw, cut a length, you decide the size, and then you will weld the two triangles and make sure they are right angles.</item>
<item>The second step is to know where the center of each is located and you can drill in holes, size does not matter, and this is where the frames will hinge. After you have put the two parts together you will now need to position the frame correctly so the oil drum can be on top of it.</item>
<item>An obstacle you might run into is preventing the frame from falling, so you may have to use a string to keep the pieces together. Then when you are done the frame will close.</item></list></item>
<item>Attach hinges to the lid <figure rend="Attach.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You will need nuts and bolts for this step. For this step, you will need to place your hinges correctly and to do that you should use a permanent pen to mark the spots of the hinges.</item></list></item>
<item>Add the safety edging <figure rend="Safety edges.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You will need to add the safety edging in sharp areas of the lid and oil drum. A tip is to do it on the inside so it can also hide the welds.</item></list></item>
<item>Attach the handle  <figure rend="Handles.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You will need a handle fabricated from steel. Weld the handle in the middle of the lid. Make sure to remove all the little pieces of metal created from cutting the steel.</item></list></item>
<item>Add the grill supports and hooks  <figure rend="Holes.png"></figure> <figure rend="Bars.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Weld two bars of steel for the main grill and other two for the smoker grill, with all of them going through the extension of the oil drum. At the bars' tips of the main grill, weld another piece of steel to form a hook on both sides. When placing the bar, be certain that the holes from left side to right side are aligned.</item>
<item>Weld 3 small hooks on one side of the drum to form holders for BBQ`s tools.</item>
<item>Drill a hole in the lid for temperature dial, drill two large holes on each side of the oil drum for ventilation, and several small ones in the middle of the drum (on the bottom) for drainage.</item></list></item>
<item>Create the grill. Weld the steel mesh with the safety edgings. Make sure the material of your mesh is stainless steel in order to avoid bits of rust in your food. <figure rend="Mesh.png"></figure></item>
<item>Finish the smoker. Now you have successfully made the grill! <figure rend="Smoker 003426.png"></figure> <figure rend="Aluminum.png"></figure></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Some quick safety tips when welding are:
<list type="unordered"><item>Always wear proper face sheilds.</item>
<item>Always close-toed shoes.</item>
<item>Always wear a long-sleeved, non-flammable shirt.</item>
<item>Always wear proper welding gloves.</item>
<item>Always wear proper ear protection (to prevent  sparks from entering your ear canal).</item>
<item>NEVER weld near an area that was cleaned with chlorinated hydrocarbon like brake-cleaner. When combined with UV light and chlorinated hydrocarbon it creates a toxic gas that can cause sever injuries or death.</item></list></item>
<item>When buying your oil drum you must decontaminate the drum. You can sanitize your oil drum by following these simple steps:
<list type="unordered"><item>Empty as much material out of the drum as possible.</item>
<item>Add absorbents or adsorbents bentonite, kitty litter to take up any free oil left in the drum.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>An MIG Welder and some wire</item>
<item>An angle grinder, along with some cutting disks, sanding disks, and grinding disks</item>
<item>Hammer</item>
<item>Hacksaw</item>
<item>Engineer's square</item>
<item>Ruler</item>
<item>Tape measure</item>
<item>Permanent pen</item>
<item>Drill</item>
<item>Some drill bits</item>
<item>Center punch tool</item>
<item>Oil drum</item>
<item>High-temperature barbecue paint</item>
<item>Steel hinges</item>
<item>Chrome coach hook</item>
<item>Barbecue temperature dial</item>
<item>Mild Steel box section</item>
<item>6 millimeter Mild Steel round bar</item>
<item>U section safety edging</item>
<item>Strips of steel sheet</item>
<item>Stainless steel grill or stainless steel mesh</item>
<item>Nuts and bolts for the hinges and frame</item>
<item>Large Steel tubing for the chimney</item>
<item>Safety protection (optional, examples are gloves, a face mask, and goggles)</item></list>
</text>
