<text id="autogum_whow_doc137" title="Control a Robot’s Motion using Linear Actuators" shortTile="control-robots-motion" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-05-14" dateModified="2017-05-05" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Control-a-Robot%E2%80%99s-Motion-using-Linear-Actuators" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Control a Robot’s Motion using Linear Actuators</head><p>Linear actuators are popularly used in robotic applications. They are designed to help the robot to perform complex motions. While there are advanced methods of using the linear actuator for robotic movements, this is a simple method that one can try. </p>
<p>As linear actuators require an external power source, you will require a DC motor with an attached gearbox. You will also need a servo motor controller and a micro controller. Other general tools include a drill, an aluminum sheet, fasteners, and four small wheels.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Decide on the Primary Attributes. The first thing you need to do is decide on the actuator’s primary characteristics of movement, length, and speed. Depending on the size of the robot and its accessories, determine the maximum distance of the length and movement of the linear actuator. Decide on the speed of the actuator and the amount of force it should place on the robotic components. <figure rend="Control a Robot’s Motion using Linear Actuators Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Install the Motor. Choose a DC motor that can run on low torque and perform quick rotations at the same time. You need to use the aluminum sheet to install the motor to the robot’s body. Drill two holes into the top left and bottom right hand corners of the sheet. Drill two similar holes into the installation panel of the motor. Then install the motor onto the robot with the fasteners. <figure rend="Control a Robot’s Motion using Linear Actuators Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Connect the Controllers. First, connect the servo motor controller to the DC motor. Then connect the servo controller to the micro controller. This will provide the power supply to the robot and the actuator. The micro controller will also help you to decide on the amount of power needed to run the robot and the actuator. The servo motor controller is also used to ensure the correct amount of voltage for the linear actuator. <figure rend="Control a Robot’s Motion using Linear Actuators Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Install the Wheels. The wheels are installed to the robot to simply provide fluid movement to the robot during the application. Drill holes into the wheels and attach them to the robot and the motor. Use the fasteners to install the wheels properly onto the devices. <figure rend="Control a Robot’s Motion using Linear Actuators Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Turn on the Motor. Once the motor is turned on, you adjust the amount of power that you need for the application. Generally, linear actuator comes with control boxes and remote controls that allow you to control the movement of the actuator. <figure rend="Control a Robot’s Motion using Linear Actuators Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>For small robotic applications, you should use DC linear actuators. They consist of a screw, which turns with the rotations of the motor, thus creating the necessary actuator movement.</item>
<item>If your application requires the robot to lift a heavy object, then pneumatic or hydraulic linear actuators would be the best choices. These actuators are designed to provide long strokes and move at high speeds.</item></list>
</text>
