<text id="autogum_whow_doc212" title="Use Video Communication in Homecare" shortTile="use-video-communication" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-12-10" dateModified="2018-07-14" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Use-Video-Communication-in-Homecare" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Use Video Communication in Homecare</head><p>Video communication services are the most trending features over the Internet where with a web-cam, microphone and  Internet access, Video calls to  family and friends around the world are just one click away. As with any type of communication over the network, we are going to share a lot of  private and Personal Information, and here, the most important point,"Privacy". In this article we are going to list some of the steps and tasks we can do with our computers in the home-care to set a safer environment for our video calls.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Ensure computer safety. Firewall, to protect your computer from different types of Intrusion attacks (computer hackers), system security preferences need to be established. One of them is the Firewall. In order to get all the benefits, the firewall needs to be activated and check the list of programs which are allowed to connect to the internet. The rest of the programs won't be able to use the network.
<list type="unordered"><item>Sometimes, there are requests from running programs to allow them to use the network, Be careful and allow only programs you know.</item></list></item>
<item>Install anti-spyware software before  installing the video call software or even before  continuing on to using the Internet, make sure that your system is protected by an anti-virus which can stop the malware, spywares and viruses , and gives some Internet protection to keep your computer safe.
<list type="unordered"><item>Note that so called "good antiviruses" usually need a paid subscription,However, there are several  free anti virus programs which are as good if not better than some paid versions. A search for Free Antivirus Programs will help you immensely. Start with free anti-virus, If the system is not protected yet,</item>
<item>Activate the system default program (Windows Defender on Microsoft systems and Mac Defender on Apple systems) until downloading and installing a better anti-virus.</item></list></item>
<item>Use video calling software. Choose the software you are comfortable with, and don't forget that privacy is the most important thing in all these steps.The Software developer's reputation is important to determine if your call data is well protected or not, where these developers  provide more security to their servers, the more potentially secure they are,  these servers are used to save data about their clients' accounts and their software users,usually, the video streaming will go through their server also.</item>
<item>Download the software. After choosing the software, search its main website for the download link. Use the  software company's product website to get the latest versions, Most applications will update themselves once installed.</item>
<item>Click on "Install Manually" if the option is available, here you will see if any "Bundled Software" is included, be sure to uncheck ALL, these are usually not required for the application to perform normally and you don't get anything you didn't ask for!, Create an account. search for contacts you want to add to your contact list and wait for their response.BEWARE! if you do not personally know the person you are adding to your contact list, he/she could be dangerous.
<list type="unordered"><item>Never ever trust an unknown, they are only words on a screen and you have  <hi rend="bold">no idea</hi> who or what is behind there!! NEVER initiate a video call with an unknown person,no matter what they say or how persuasive they are! So much information is seen in the background of the video by stalkers and generally bad people.</item></list></item>
<item>Develop communication environment. Before your friend  can see you, position the camera to hide or show what you want in the house if you care about background details,Keep the room nicely lit so that the camera image is clear, after setting the video call environment, you will be able to enjoy your video calls, whether Family or Professional.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Avoid Unknown Contacts. For your own security, don't talk to strangers about your personal life nor enter into a video call, always to talk to those who you know are that person, class mates, real life friends,The Internet is NOT safe in any respect, a Firewall and all the antivirus in the world will only slow but not stop some-one who is determined, so don't give them any reason to try to "Hack" you.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Social App Allow Access. We are surrounded by an infinite number of social apps, we need to be very careful dealing with them, where each time for some and mostly not important reasons, you get a request from a social app that wants  access to your profile and friends Info, and here you need to be AWAKE.</item>
<item>Every click on the Allow button means you are sharing your private Info to some-one you don't know nor what they do with your Info. We need to use only necessary applications and only from reputable Software Companies. , this will keep you safer and help keep your privacy where it belongs, PRIVATE!.</item></list>
</text>
