<text id="autogum_whow_doc401" title="Paint a Landscape with Acrylic Paint" shortTile="paint-landscape-acrylic" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-02-13" dateModified="2018-04-14" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Paint-a-Landscape-with-Acrylic-Paint" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Paint a Landscape with Acrylic Paint</head><p>Landscape painting with acrylic paint is easy. There are 4 basic steps to any landscape Painting: Set up, Background, Detailing and Finish. This guide is meant for beginner painters and provides only the fundamental steps in Acrylic Landscape paintings. To help understand the steps and to have an example to follow, this guide will present and walkthrough an example landscape painting.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Setting Up &amp; Materials</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Gather &amp; Organize Materials. Before painting it is necessary to gather materials and prepare them before painting. Here are the materials used in the example painting and suggested for any landscape painting. <figure rend="IMG_1555555522.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Canvas (11in x 14in)</item>
<item>Paint brushes ( 4in Square Painters brush, thin detailing brush, small fan brush, Medium Flat)</item>
<item>Water</item>
<item>Cups</item>
<item>Paper plates</item>
<item>Acrylic Paint (White, Black, Red, Blue, Yellow)</item>
<item>Newspaper</item>
<item>Paper towel</item>
<item>Easel</item></list></item>
<item>Create a painting space. First find a quiet private space with minimal distractions so it is easier to paint, make sure the space has access to clean water and sufficient air flow. Lay down newspaper over the workspace to prevent unwanted paint stains. <figure rend="IMG_15222222223.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get  ready to paint. Fill a medium cup with warm soapy water for cleaning paint brushes. Put the paints on the paper plate to mix and use. Secure canvas on the easel. Organize all the materials close for easy access while painting. Finally, decide what landscape to paint. Either find an image on the internet or in a book or have a landscape already drawn. Pick a simple landscape with more background than detail so it is easier to paint.</item></list>
<head>Starting with the Background &amp; Blending</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Prepare the canvas. First “activate” the canvas by brushing a small amount of regular water throughout the whole canvas preferably using the 4in painter’s brush, this allows the paint to blend better. <figure rend="IMG_1522222224.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Prepare the colors. Identify the main background colors of each section, for example, on the example painting:
<list type="unordered"><item>Top- Red and Redish-Orange</item>
<item>Middle- Orange and Yellowish-Orange</item>
<item>Bottom- Black</item></list></item>
<item>Mix paint for background color. Mix and experiment with paint on the paper plate to create the desired color for a section of the background, use the flat medium brush to stir. It is better to have more than enough of a created color rather than have to attempt to recreate the color afterwards. Do each color one at a time for simplicity. Tips; <figure rend="IMG_152222227.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Red+Yellow=Orange</item>
<item>Red+Blue=Purple</item>
<item>Yellow+Blue=Green</item></list></item>
<item>Paint the background. Using the medium flat brush take a “brush full” of the desired color and paint it onto the canvas with easy back and forth strokes. Do not paint the details or the foreground until after all the background is completed. After completing a color section, wash your brush and move onto the next section, if the next section is adjacent to another section, and you do not wish to blend the colors let the previous section dry before painting the adjacent section.
<list type="unordered"><item>On the example painting, the top and middle sections are blended together to create a sunset but the bottom and middle section are not blended to create a horizon.</item></list></item>
<item>Blend colors. After painting two colors on the canvas next to each other, mix a color a shade in between the two colors on a paper plate and paint it in the area between the two colors and take the two wet color on the canvas slightly blend them together on the canvas. <figure rend="IMG_15222228.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Finish  the background. Once the background is completely painted and there are no more “white spaces” on the canvas, let the canvas dry before continuing onto the detailing and foreground. <figure rend="IMG_15333332.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Detailing</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Work basic detailing.
<list type="unordered"><item>Identify the depth of the painting and what aspects need to be painted first, for example in the example painting the sun must be done before the blades of grass and the horizon.</item>
<item>Using the small detailing brush, paint the smaller and more precise details of the foreground, Such as the rocks on the ground and the tree silhouettes and using the fan brush with a light amount of paint horizontally, softly dabbing the canvas to create leaves</item>
<item>Paint  slowly and carefully with the thin detailing brush to create smooth lines and borders</item></list></item></list>
<head>Finishing</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Complete the painting
<list type="unordered"><item>After all the detailing has dried, look over the painting and observe areas where the paint may need another coat because it is streaky or thin.</item>
<item>It may be necessary to go over small details again to fix mistakes or make the detailing cleaner.  <figure rend="IMG_15333333336.jpg"></figure> <figure rend="IMG_154444440.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Add your signature. After all the paint has dried and the painting looks satisfactory, autograph the canvas in the bottom right corner, using a sharpie in the negative color of the paint in the area.
<list type="unordered"><item>Put away the materials and clean the workspace</item>
<item>Sell the superior painting at an auction for $1.37 million</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>The more paint, the less streaky the paint is on the canvas</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Acrylic Paint stains permanently! Be careful wear painting appropriate clothing and use newspaper to cover the workspace</item>
<item>Do not leave Paint Brushes in water! It will ruin the brushes</item>
<item>Make sure to put the cap on when done.</item>
<item>Wipe off any extra paint with a towel or tissue to avoid getting the cap stuck on the paint.</item></list>
</text>
