<text id="autogum_whow_doc649" title="Play Full Contact Spoons" shortTile="play-full-contact" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2006-09-04" dateModified="2019-01-16" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Play-Full-Contact-Spoons" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Play Full Contact Spoons</head><p>Full Contact Spoons, or FC Spoons for short, is sort of like rugby, but with no teams, only one goal, and almost no rules.
(This game has some similar elements as &amp; is often mistaken for the game popular in some elementary schools "Smear the Queer", however, that game does not have any goal.)
<hi rend="bold">History:</hi>
It originally evolved from the card game called 'spoons'; in the current version there are no cards, a goal has been added, and there is only one object instead of one less than the number of people.  There are also no actual spoons.
This game was first played in San Pablo, CA between 1995 and 1996.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Set Up</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find 3 to 14 people who are willing to play. <figure rend="Play Full Contact Spoons Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find a big grass field. <figure rend="Play Full Contact Spoons Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Set up a goal on one end, about  wide. <figure rend="Play Full Contact Spoons Step 3.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Game Overview</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Everyone lines up near the goal. <figure rend="Play Full Contact Spoons Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Someone throws the ball out into the field somewhere. <figure rend="Play Full Contact Spoons Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Everyone runs to get the ball. <figure rend="Play Full Contact Spoons Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Whoever gets it, everyone else tries to get the ball from them. <figure rend="Play Full Contact Spoons Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If anyone gets it away from the first person, then everyone tries to get it from them. Repeat. <figure rend="Play Full Contact Spoons Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Eventually, someone gets the ball through the goal. They win! <figure rend="Play Full Contact Spoons Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Start over. <figure rend="Play Full Contact Spoons Step 10.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Rules</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Score is not kept.  When a goal is made, that game has been won.  The next round is a new game, independent of the last.  You can not lose at spoons, you either win, or you don't win.</item>
<item>You cannot throw the ball into the goal. You must be actually holding the ball to win. <figure rend="Play Full Contact Spoons Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>The ball must go through the goal. If you are holding the ball on the ground, and you manage to edge one foot over the goal line, you have not won yet. <figure rend="Play Full Contact Spoons Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>On the other hand, if you are tackled right near the goal line and you reach the hand with the ball just barely past, even though your body is not past the goal line, you win. <figure rend="Play Full Contact Spoons Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If one person is holding the ball in their hand and someone else is touching it, the person holding it gets the point. <figure rend="Play Full Contact Spoons Step 15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>However, if two people are both holding the ball about equally, it gets thrown back down-field. <figure rend="Play Full Contact Spoons Step 16.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>You have to go through the goal in the correct direction (as in, if you run around behind the goal, and then try to come through, no goal). <figure rend="Play Full Contact Spoons Step 17.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If one person has the ball, and someone else carries them through, the person doing the carrying gets the point. If you get picked up near the goal, the best thing to do is to throw it down field. <figure rend="Play Full Contact Spoons Step 18.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You just play until someone wins, then after everyone rests, you play again.</item>
<item>You can tackle, you can trip, you can grab, you can push.</item>
<item>Spins and jukes can be very useful in this game as you can evade players very easily.</item>
<item>We don't punch or kick or bite or anything like that, but there are no fouls, no time outs, no penalties, none of the silly time wasting rules that most sports have.</item>
<item>It's probably obvious, but if you play, wear something which you won't be too upset when it gets grass stains and rips in it.</item>
<item>We also don't bother with pads and all that crap. There have never been any major injuries in spoons.</item>
<item>It's really really simple. It's great exercise.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Please don't wear cleats or heavy boots because, while you try not to accidentally step on anyone, you might.</item>
<item>You may get sprains or strains, or any of the other things you might suffer in any full-contact sport. If this is a problem for you, do not play this game.</item>
<item>No jewelry, watches, glasses or hard objects in pockets. If you bring 'em, you have to set them aside when you play, and then you have to worry about theft, so it's better not to bring anything valuable.</item>
<item>You will get bumps, bruises, and minor cuts, and you will be sore the next day.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>A ball.  Football or Rugby ball works well.  You want something you can grab onto, but not too well.  A basketball will make for a game where the ball changes hands quickly and often.  A baseball is very hard to grab out of the pile.  In a pinch, an empty re-sealed plastic soda bottle works well.  In the beginning, we used 20oz Sprite bottles exclusively.</item>
<item>A goal.  Crushable safety cones work very well, but two jackets or backpacks or anything soft works just as well.</item>
<item>A big grass field (alternatively, Astroturf, or a large padded cell would probably work just as well)</item>
<item>3-14 other people - the more the better</item></list>
</text>
