<text id="autogum_whow_doc676" title="Use a Protein Shaker" shortTile="use-protein-shaker" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-01-16" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Use-a-Protein-Shaker" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Use a Protein Shaker</head><p>Whether you're hitting the gym or just trying to stay healthy, a protein shaker is a great way to get all of the protein and nutrients you need into one quick meal. But not so fast! Between mixing your shake and cleaning your shaker, there are a few things you should know before you start making your favorite healthy concoctions.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Mixing Your Shake</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Add liquid ingredients to your protein shaker. Take a look at some <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_a_Protein_Shake">protein shake recipes</ref> and select your favorite. Now, pinpoint all the liquids (juices, milk, water, coffee) in the recipe and pour them all in one by one. <figure rend="Use a Protein Shaker Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try using regular milk, almond milk, soy milk, water, or orange juice.</item>
<item>Use the measurements printed on the outside of your shaker (if it has any) as a guide.</item></list></item>
<item>Scoop protein powder into your protein shaker. After the liquids are in, start adding in your desired amount of protein powder. Be sure to follow the directions in your recipe to ensure that you have a good ratio of powder to liquids. Afterward, stir it in gently with a spoon to make the shaking process easier. <figure rend="Use a Protein Shaker Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you're not sure how much protein powder to use, add  of protein per  of lean body weight.</item>
<item>For the liquid: protein powder ratio, try using about 10 ounces (29.57 milliliters) per 1 scoop of protein or enough to dissolve all of the powder.</item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Calculate_Body_Fat_Percentage_Accurately">Calculate your body fat percentage</ref> using a measuring tape, calipers, or your body mass index (BMI). Now, determine your lean body weight by subtracting your body fat percentage from your total body weight—this is a good guideline for the amount of protein you should use in your shakes.</item></list></item>
<item>Mix in your solid and thick ingredients. Find all the solid ingredients like nuts, dry fruits, and vegetables and add them in. Afterward, add thicker ingredients like maple syrup and yogurt. <figure rend="Use a Protein Shaker Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try not to use more than 1/2 cup (64 grams) of solid ingredients and 1/2 cup (64 grams) of thicker ingredients. For example, use 1/4 cup (32 grams) of dried oats and 1/4 cup (32 grams) of ice cubes for solid ingredients and 1/2 cup (64 grams) of Greek yogurt. You can also just use 1/2 cup (64 grams) of either solid or thick ingredients—experiment and see what you prefer!</item>
<item>Try out different nuts, fruits, and vegetables. Don't be afraid to stray from the recipe!</item></list></item>
<item>Screw the shaker lid firmly shut and close the cap. Start screwing on the lid by turning it clockwise. Continue this until it is firmly in place. Afterward, press the flip cap down onto the lid until it snaps shut. <figure rend="Use a Protein Shaker Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you don't hear the flip cap snap, it hasn't been securely closed—try again.</item>
<item>If your protein shaker has a ball whisk, drop it into the bottom of the bottle before screwing on the lid. If it has a mesh screen, be sure to attach it first.</item></list></item>
<item>Shake your protein shaker up and down for 20 seconds. After putting the lid on your shaker and flipping the cap down, shake it vigorously in up and down motions. As you shake it, count slowly to 20. Once you reach 20, stop counting. Afterward, remove the lid and make sure it's a smooth consistency. <figure rend="Use a Protein Shaker Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Continue shaking for another 10 seconds if your shake isn't mixed.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Cleaning Your Protein Shaker</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Hand-wash your protein shaker after each use. Wash it by hand with warm, soapy water or a wet wipe for the simplest and fastest option. Use microfiber cloths for the best results. <figure rend="Use a Protein Shaker Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be sure to clean your protein shaker before you use it for the first time.</item></list></item>
<item>Clean your protein shaker in a dishwasher once a week. Although hand-washing is effective, regular dishwashing is a great and thorough option. Always place your shaker parts on the top rack of the dishwasher if it's listed as safe for this use. <figure rend="Use a Protein Shaker Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Check which parts of your shaker are dishwasher safe before putting them in.</item></list></item>
<item>Soak your shaker with baking soda and vinegar to remove odors. If your protein shaker is made from BPA-plastics, it's prone to retaining odors. Start by filling your bottle with a 1:1 mixture of vinegar and baking soda. Now, let it sit overnight with the flip cap open. Afterward, dump the mixture out of the shaker. <figure rend="Use a Protein Shaker Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Use this cleaning method only on days when you use the protein shaker.</item></list></item>
<item>Add water and vanilla extract for an alternative odor removal method. Sprinkle some water on a piece of newspaper or paper towel. Just make sure the pieces are small enough to be crumpled and fit into your shaker. Now, get some new pieces of newspaper or paper towel and add 3 to 4 drops of vanilla extract to each. Crumple your papers and paper towels, stuff them in the bottle, and let it sit for 24 hours with the flip cap open. The moist paper will absorb odors and the vanilla will create a pleasant odor. <figure rend="Use a Protein Shaker Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Mix paper towel and newspaper if you'd like or just use one or the other.</item></list></item>
<item>Scoop damp coffee grounds into the bottle to add a nice smell. Touch your coffee grounds—if they feel dry, add  of water to dampen them. Now, scoop 1 tbsp (14.15 g) into your shaker and let it sit overnight. Make sure the flip cap is closed for the best results. <figure rend="Use a Protein Shaker Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Rinse out your bottle after letting your coffee grounds sit overnight.</item></list></item>
<item>Air-dry your shaker bottle after cleaning it. No matter what cleaning method you choose, always let it air-dry afterward. This will minimize the chances of bacteria, mildew, and mold growth. <figure rend="Use a Protein Shaker Step 11.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always make sure your bottle is dry before using it.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
