<text id="autogum_whow_doc360" title="Learn More About Hubble" shortTile="learn-more-hubble" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-08-15" dateModified="2015-11-15" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Learn-More-About-Hubble" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Learn More About Hubble</head><p>This article talks about how the magnificent Hubble space technology has changed astronomers' views upon our world and worlds beyond it, forever.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Hubble was 'born' in 1990- as a joint project of NASA and the European Space Agency. The telescope orbits Earth 353 miles above the planet's surface. No telescope before Hubble had the high quality resolution to see distant galaxies, home to various different planets and stars. There are three stages of Hubble's sight- the Hubble Deep Field, which was discovered in 1995, contains 3,000 galaxies in it. The second is Hubble Ultra Deep Field, discovered in 2004, with about 10,000 galaxies and the last one, which contained 30,000 of these wondrous galaxies. <figure rend="Hubble 3D pic.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>The deeper Hubble telescope looks into space, the further it gazes back in time. Over a period of time, Hubble teamed up with other observatories to examine patches of the sky in high resolution. Surveys like like the Hubble Ultra Deep Field have provided pictures of vast, deep collections of galaxies- including some that existed when our universe was less than a billion years old.</item>
<item>Zooming in, you can see small stars and large planets, moons orbiting planets and stars, and countless galaxies. These galaxies merge together to form a single, larger galaxy, and this will be explained later on. Scientists have known for a long time that the universe has been expanding, ever since the Big Bang, which was when our galaxy was born. Some astronomers believe that if they measure the universes's size, they can calculate the approximate age of the universe.</item>
<item>You might be thinking... how can they measure the distance of the universe? Since you cannot extend a ruler into the stars, they estimate by studying objects' brightness- for example nearby or distant stars. So if the scientists can measure the length of a star, which is part of a galaxy, they can also measure the distance from the Milky Way to that galaxy, too.</item>
<item>The NGC 4603 galaxy is the most distant galaxy- 108 million light years away. It has been found by the same method that scientists use to measure distances between stars- Cepheid variables. From Earth, this galaxy's stars appear very faint.</item>
<item>Among these magical and intriguing discoveries in outer space, there are also some deathly dangers...Black Holes were originally named 'quasars' by the first astronomers, and they were thought to be the incredibly bright centers of those faraway galaxies. An approximate size of a quasar is the size of our very own solar system- not very big at all in comparison to the universe. Luckily, Hubble observations saved the day again, determining that those bright galactic centers are powered by giant black holes. They come in various different sizes, but some range form giant black holes in the center of galaxies to small black holes a few times larger than our sun.</item>
<item>And so we come to the part where we refer back to part 3 where galaxies are said to merge together to form new galaxies. Well, Hubble has observed the collision between two galaxies and determined with a lot of evidence, that in the future, our galaxy, the Milky Way, and another close galaxy named Andromeda galaxy will collide in around 4 billion years, when we might not be alive. Did you know that Andromeda is the closest galaxy to us? Well, Hubble's resolution is powerful enough to see its individual stars! The stars in the Andromeda have different ages- ranging from six billion years up. Scientists believe that this happened because another galaxy has already collided with the Andromeda, making it larger and bigger than before. And when the two monster galaxies in the universe collide, there will be an almighty effect. But however, some predict that this mighty sight will not cause an effect on Earth and its fellow planets- only the Sun will change its orbit direction and we will become a much larger, wider galaxy. <figure rend="Hubble Snaps Heavyweight of the Leo Triplet.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Eventually, Hubble telescope's time will come. It will have to 'die' or 'end its life' as the telescope we look up to as our eye to the universe. But that won't be the end- a new telescope, named the James Webb Space Telescope, is Hubble telescope's successor and will use Infrared vision, instead of Hubble's usual visible vision to convey the secrets of the universe to us. They say infrared is much better than visible light; you can see fainter objects and the new telescope will be useful for that. Webb is made to stand up to -233.3 Celsius- extreme cold weather. The James Webb will be the largest telescope ever to orbit our planet. The launch for James Webb telescope is scheduled for 2018, where some lucky people will witness the launch of the James Webb Space telescope, the new eye for our universe.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Get books about the Hubble Space Telescope and read them.</item>
<item>Also, watch one of the many documentaries about the Hubble.</item>
<item>Look on NASA's website for information about Hubble too.</item></list>
</text>
