<text id="autogum_whow_doc611" title="Be the Person You Were Meant to Be" shortTile="person-meant" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2012-08-11" dateModified="2018-09-27" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be-the-Person-You-Were-Meant-to-Be" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be the Person You Were Meant to Be</head><p>If you are reading this, you have found yourself not content with the way your life is headed. Maybe you're just wanting a little self-help. Possibly none of these apply to you and you're just reading this because you feel like it. Whatever it may be, you're reading it, and if you finish this article I can guarantee that you will learn something about yourself, something that you may desperately be seeking or needing at this point in your life.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Move forward. Have you made mistakes? Of course you have. Take a second to close your eyes and tell yourself that you're normal, it's normal to make mistakes. Have you ever done something that you wish you could take back? Something that you wouldn't tell anyone? That's normal too. Today is the day that you become the person that you were always meant to be. That can't happen if you have baggage. Leave the past in the past. You my friend, have a chance to restart, and all you have to do is forget all the bad things that you did, all the things that has happened to you, and just move forward. <figure rend="Be the Person You Were Meant to Be Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Accept yourself. We all wish we could be someone else, wish that maybe for just one day we wouldn't be so insecure, have the need to buy material things, as if that would make us more perfect, or more like that one person you wish you could be. But let me tell you something; someone looks at you every day and thinks "Man, I wish I was like them." You may be saying to yourself "yeah, right." But it's so true. When we can accept ourselves the way we are, and not always try to be better than someone, we could finally see that no one can be compared to us, no one can make you look bad, because your were made the way you are for a reason, and no one can take that away from you. When you find self-acceptance you will be that much closer to living a full and happy life you deserve. <figure rend="Be the Person You Were Meant to Be Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Love yourself. You can't change what you did or who you were, but absolutely nothing can prevent you from being the person you want to be, from shaping yourself into the human that you want everyone to see when they look at you. You're so lovable with all your flaws, and you don't even need someone to tell you that. If you can't love yourself, than why should others love you? <figure rend="Be the Person You Were Meant to Be Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Grow. You're constantly growing. Physically, that is. Today, grow spiritually. Accept yourself, try new things, grow in knowledge of yourself. Inside all of us, there is a light. A light that burns brighter than any flame. This light cannot and will not be extinguished, only hidden. Why, oh why, would you hide such a mesmerizing light? Could it be that some one else may overpower yours? Perhaps another person told you that yours is not beautiful? Friend, yours is the most beautiful of anyone, none can overpower yours, for yours is unique. The hard part is not keeping this light on, but finding it, yours has been hidden for so long that you may not find it. Show the world your light, and let them see that your a person of such greatness that all will love you and respect you. <figure rend="Be the Person You Were Meant to Be Step 4.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Love is an action, not a feeling. Love is the most natural thing in the world. Love everyone, and your true self will shine through.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't forget how loved you are.</item></list>
</text>
