<text id="autogum_whow_doc166" title="Start an Alternative School" shortTile="start-alternative" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2009-09-14" dateModified="2017-06-05" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Start-an-Alternative-School" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Start an Alternative School</head><p>Maybe you don't like the education your children are getting. Maybe other parents in the area feel the same. Sometimes this involves little geniuses that don't adapt to the lower level kinds of education. Or, one may use alternative kinds of education to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Graduate_Early_from_High_School">graduate early</ref> from high school using homeschooling, and/or take classes at a junior college while finishing high school -- as ways to advance. This may be about children working at or above grade level who are bored -- or, conversely, those below grade level who may be repeating a grade, for one reason or another, without learning anything new. Another possibility is that the public school lessons do not go well with your religious or political beliefs.  If your school doesn't offer a special gifted/talented class (or when you think that's not good enough) you can <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Homeschool_Your_Children">homeschool</ref> your child and others' children, by setting up an private alternative kind of school.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Decide on a location</hi> for your new school. For small starters, your living room should do it, but depending on the number of children it may not be practical for you or for them. Maybe someone's garage could be a good option if they don't own a car or maybe a rented space (depending on how many children you intend to enroll in the school one room may be enough). <figure rend="Start an Alternative School Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get the basic supplies. These would be for the average classroom a table for each student with a chair (or maybe a big table with chairs all around) and a separate desk with chair for the teacher(s). You may want also a bookcase to keep the students' text books, tests and record their progress and keep their files and worksheets. A cork bulletin board for notes (such as announcements, for field trips and lunch menu, etc.) and a white/chalk board will also come in handy. <figure rend="Start an Alternative School Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Write your <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Homeschool_Your_Children">school plan</ref> as you want it to be: consider the schedules for you and the children. Think about what subjects you want to teach and who will teach the children if not yourself. This won't be too hard as it will be most likely the main reason why you are doing this anyway. ~ Add subjects that your children may need and don't have at regular schools - anything goes, including both religious and secular subjects. ~ Abolish any subjects you don't find appropriate: Many parents don't want the children to have sex education while they're quite young. ~ <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Choose_a_Homeschool_Curriculum">Write the curriculum</ref> of studies: consider schedules, and how to make the classes -- or hire someone to do that for you. <figure rend="Start an Alternative School Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Work_at_Home_While_Homeschooling">Prepare to start homeschooling</ref>: make sure everything is in place and ready to work. Open for sign ups and sign up your children. <figure rend="Start an Alternative School Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Check online to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Buy_Used_Homeschool_Textbooks">Buy Used Homeschool Textbooks</ref>. Each parent should be aware of how homeschool may be<ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Homeschool_Your_Teenager"> for teenagers</ref> or is so beneficial to the young children of parents who share the same religious/political views as you. <figure rend="Start an Alternative School Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Consider mixed schooling. Children may attend public school and attend your school on an extra-curricular basis. <figure rend="Start an Alternative School Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If this is the most of your students, arrange the schedule of subjects that aren't covered by <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Change_Schools_in_the_Middle_of_the_School_Year">regular schools</ref> so you need to know the time when these children can be there.</item></list></item>
<item>Explain how it differs from the regular schools, and why that is so much better. One may want to get out of and beyond the "special accommodations" in public school class. That school must teach so that programs for the gifted and talented or exceptional (called GATE, G/T, or TAG) "accommodate" the below grade-level, physically or scholastically disabled students (hearing, visually or learning handicapped) to include Special Education students. <figure rend="Start an Alternative School Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Interview the parents to find volunteers: coach, science or mathematics specialist who may help with those assignments doing some or all of the teaching in certain topics. <figure rend="Start an Alternative School Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Find out when and how often (one day a week, or 2 or 3 evenings) they would be able to assist, and what expenses may warrant charging a fee for such classes.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Special education students - those having special individual programs legally may <hi rend="bold">not</hi> be "excluded" from attempting G/T classes, if parents insist on putting them in such education with individual ARD - Admission, Review, and Dismissal process and Individualized Education Program (IEP) processes which implement the (IEP) developed for that student in special education which provides rights and responsibilities in the process for children perhaps working below grade level, (but they may earn an "A" while working at grade levels well below the regular education goal) and actually not receiving much in the way of learning accommodations which are stated on paper, that the regular teacher tries implement.</item>
<item>Check the legal standing and obligations and to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_a_Good_Impression_when_You're_Homeschooled">Make a Good Impression when You're Homeschooled</ref> in your state or nation.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Your may want or need to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Hide_the_Fact_That_You_Were_Homeschooled">Hide the Fact That You Were Homeschooled</ref> for reasons of privacy -- or to avoid discrimination.</item></list>
</text>
