<text id="autogum_whow_doc439" title="Create an Apartment Fit for a Professional" shortTile="create-apartment" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2007-01-23" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Create-an-Apartment-Fit-for-a-Professional" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Create an Apartment Fit for a Professional</head><p>Many professionals choose apartment living over home ownership. The flexibility that renting provides is a perfect solution for professionals in dynamic careers. Access to transit services is close by or you can find properties right downtown! And who needs the added stress of property taxes, building maintenance and bill after bill after bill when renting is so simple? Apartment living is clearly a great choice, but how do you turn those eggshell-white walls into a comfortable home to match your professional lifestyle? It's not as hard as you might think!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Read the lease or rental agreement. What can and can't you do? Can you drill into the walls? Can you paint? Knowing your restrictions will help you determine what you can do. If in doubt, speak with your building landlord before beginning any questionable projects–this could save you headaches down the road. <figure rend="Create an Apartment Fit for a Professional Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Add colour!  The walls are the background of your home and set the tone for each room. White walls in apartments can make an apartment seem cold and institutional. Make yourself feel truly at home by dressing up the walls. If you paint, select a light or neutral colour. Many lease or rental agreements require that you return the walls to their original colour when you move out. Lighter colours are much easier to paint over than dark, bold colours and they can make small rooms look larger. If you don't want to paint, you can still dress up your walls with wall hangings, fabric, removable wallpaper boarders and stickers, stencils or artwork. <figure rend="Create an Apartment Fit for a Professional Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Create a theme. A staple of a student apartment is mix-and-match furniture. Professionals often hang onto these not-so-treasured heirlooms far longer than necessary. Pull the room together by getting rid of those worn-out hand-me-downs and invest in furniture that compliments your style and taste. Accent your room with decorations and colours that create unity. <figure rend="Create an Apartment Fit for a Professional Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Focus on functionality.  Apartment living is all about functionality. Create a useful space that is also stylish by dressing up your storage space. Unique wall-shelves make a statement and make use of vertical space. Doors on cabinets and shelves create a clean and organized look by keeping otherwise cluttered looking items out of sight. <figure rend="Create an Apartment Fit for a Professional Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Know that less is more. Clutter shrinks rooms. When decorating a small space, chose a few key pieces and keep the knickknacks to a minimum. Create the illusion of more space by choosing furniture and accessories that have clean light lines and let light pass through the room. Use doors and dividers that are made from glass or mirrors. Find furniture that has exposed legs and light materials. Hanging lights, shelves and plants can increase vertical space and keep the floor from feeling heavy. <figure rend="Create an Apartment Fit for a Professional Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
