<text id="autogum_whow_doc210" title="Evaluate the Needs of a Senior" shortTile="evaluate-needs-senior" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-04-04" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Evaluate-the-Needs-of-a-Senior" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Evaluate the Needs of a Senior</head><p>Age progression generally brings forth various issues regarding physical health, mental health, mobility and daily living. Seniors typically value their independence and believe they would become a burden to family and friends if they were no longer self-reliant. Learning to evaluate the needs of a senior citizen can help ease transitions from living healthy and self-sufficient to assisted living or home care if help is needed.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Observe daily living and note any significant changes that may need to be addressed with your senior loved one. Respect their independence by offering assistance with daily living objectives. <figure rend="Evaluate the Needs of a Senior Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Physical restrictions preparing meals or completing household tasks such as laundry.</item>
<item>Signs of neglect or elder abuse.</item>
<item>Maintaining schedule of medications.</item>
<item>Timeliness paying bills.</item>
<item>Keeping up with general appointments.</item></list></item>
<item>List possible needs for assistive technology that offers improved mobility, in addition to hearing and vision assistance. <figure rend="Evaluate the Needs of a Senior Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Wheelchair access will require home remodeling that may include installing a wheelchair access ramp or modifying a bathroom.</item>
<item>Upgrade land-line and cell phones with hearing enhancements or larger buttons.</item>
<item>Provide walking and seating aids when mobility becomes difficult due to arthritis, after an injury, surgical procedure or other condition.</item>
<item>Consider assistive technology options for reading such as an electronic reader, audio and Braille.</item></list></item>
<item>Evaluate health for physical and mental changes. Becoming involved in your elder loved one's health care can help them feel secure about challenges ahead. Health and wellness is a critical area that may need the guidance of a medical professional. <figure rend="Evaluate the Needs of a Senior Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Assist in maintaining schedule of medications.</item>
<item>Supervise changes in medication or therapy.</item>
<item>Monitor significant shifts in mood such as extreme sadness, anger or irritability.</item>
<item>Notate changes or difficulty of mobility not observed previously.</item></list></item>
<item>Suggest group activities or therapy after the loss of a spouse. Grief can go through stages that may include depression, withdrawal, guilt, blame and loss of appetite. <figure rend="Evaluate the Needs of a Senior Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Include your senior loved one in family activities and celebrations.</item>
<item>Encourage participation in senior citizen programs.</item>
<item>Recommend individual or group grief counseling.</item>
<item>Offer to listen whenever he or she would like to talk.</item></list></item>
<item>Note changes in the way business is handled. Paying bills and completing tax returns may become difficult or forgotten. Patterned behavior may be a sign that assistance is needed. <figure rend="Evaluate the Needs of a Senior Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Plan time to help with paying bills, grocery shopping or going to the bank.</item>
<item>Explain the risk of scams and how they can affect life.</item>
<item>Offer assistance with legal issues.</item></list></item>
<item>Record specific information when visiting your elder family member in a nursing facility. Maintaining documentation of the living conditions, physical differences and personality changes may indicate signs of declining care or elder abuse. <figure rend="Evaluate the Needs of a Senior Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Is he happy to see you with open arms or a handshake?</item>
<item>Is the living environment clean?</item>
<item>Is your loved one clean and properly dressed?</item>
<item>Are there any bruises, scratches or pressures sores on their body?</item>
<item>Is communication with staff pleasant or hesitant?</item></list></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Contact your local Adult Protective Services (APS) if you believe you senior loved one is experiencing physical, emotional, sexual or financial abuse.</item></list>
</text>
