<text id="autogum_whow_doc258" title="Communicate in a Business Crisis" shortTile="communicate-business" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-09-16" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Communicate-in-a-Business-Crisis" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Communicate in a Business Crisis</head><p>Communication is an important part of any business's crisis management plan. A crisis in business is any occurrence that interferes with business operations and that draws public scrutiny and media attention, and may be anything from serving a customer tainted food to finding a major error in accounting. In business, news of crisis spreads fast and a business that is not prepared to handle crisis could be in danger of tarnishing its reputation. Therefore, knowing how to handle a crisis when it arises could be necessary to a business's survival. Follow these guidelines for how to communicate in a business crisis.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Prepare for a crisis ahead of time. It is important to establish a method for handling a crisis before a crisis happens. The following steps will lead to an effective crisis management plan. <figure rend="Communicate in a Business Crisis Step 01.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Identify what could go wrong. This list will be different for each company, and should be as thorough as possible. For example, a cake delivery business may experience a crisis caused by food allergens, an accident during transportation and/or a fire in the kitchen. Maintain a fact sheet outlining each and every crisis possibility, as well as the people who must be involved, the methods that must be used to divert the crisis and the audience you must deliver crisis information to.</item>
<item>Familiarize yourself with your audience. Depending on how large your company is, your audience may be composed of 1 or a combination of the following: employees, customers, board members, politicians, the press and/or the media.</item>
<item>Create a crisis communication plan. This plan should direct the flow of information in the event of a crisis. Taking into account each of the segments of your audience, decide on the outlets you will use to communicate with your audience when a crisis does happen. For example, if your audience is composed of your employees, customers and the press, then your crisis communication plan should incorporate methods for communicating with all 3 of them; this could mean holding telephone conferences for employees, sending mass emails to customers and writing a press release for newspapers.</item>
<item>Assign responsibilities to members of a crisis communication team. For each item on your communication plan, you will need to assign a task to a communication team member. For example, you may delegate the task of drafting the crisis message to the marketing director, the task of conducting telephone conferences to the human resources manager, the task of sending mass emails to your Internet sales division manager and the task of working with newspaper editors to the vice president. Additionally, you may want to choose a company spokesperson for high-profile crisis situations.</item></list></item>
<item>Draft your messages. When a crisis occurs, it is time to enact your crisis communication plan. Gather all of the information you can about the crisis in order to prepare your crisis messages - 1 tailored to each segment of your audience. A crisis message should include the following elements: <figure rend="Communicate in a Business Crisis Step 02.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>An explanation of the crisis. Be as succinct as possible. Try to give the audience enough information to satisfy their inquiries but not so much information to seem as though you are trying to explain your way out of something.</item>
<item>A revelation of your concern. Let your audience know that you are genuinely affected by the impact the crisis may have on everyone involved.</item>
<item>A claim to responsibility, as applicable. Own up to your part in the crisis, and offer a sincere apology, if it is warranted.</item>
<item>A pledge to address the cause of the business crisis, and to work to find a solution. Offer a firm commitment to preventing a future repeat of the crisis.</item>
<item>An assurance that the crisis is an isolated event - not to be confused with the company's overall efficiency - and that you are still confident in your company. However, you should only provide this assurance if you can stand behind it without reservation. Do not lie, exaggerate or twist the facts in a way that only provides false hope to your audience.</item></list></item>
<item>Deliver your messages as soon as you possibly can. Your goal is to get information to your audience members before they get it from less reliable or damaging sources. Use the avenues outlined in your crisis management plan to communicate your messages to each segment of your audience. <figure rend="Communicate in a Business Crisis Step 03.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always handle your business affairs in a forthcoming manner, and with honesty and transparency. That way, when a crisis does present itself, you have the advantage of a good reputation to aid the effectiveness of your crisis management plan.</item>
<item>Public relations firms specialize in communicating with the public through media outlets on behalf of businesses. You can hire such a firm to help you develop a crisis management plan suited to your business needs and/or to handle communication for your business when a crisis presents itself.</item>
<item>Your website is a great communication avenue for delivering crisis messages to every segment of your audience. Make sure you have an information technology specialist on your crisis communication team so that you can provide real-time updates to your audience when a crisis happens.</item>
<item>After you deliver your messages, monitor the reaction of the public in the media and on the Internet so that you can respond as needed to counter negative backlash and correct misinformation.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Avoid withholding a crisis message, as the act of stonewalling will only make you appear uncooperative and unapologetic, which will work against your company's reputation and make it even harder for you to recover from a crisis.</item></list>
</text>
