<text id="autogum_whow_doc122" title="Make Your Polyvore Set Popular" shortTile="make-polyvore-set" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2008-12-03" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-Your-Polyvore-Set-Popular" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make Your Polyvore Set Popular</head><p>Polyvore is a popular website that allows you to create collages (or sets) that fall into one of four categories: fashion, beauty, home, or art &amp; expression. This guide tells you how to promote your set once it has been published, so that you can get lots of views, comments and favorites.
</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Put lots of effort into creating your set. The better it is, the easier it will be to promote. <figure rend="Make Your Polyvore Set Popular Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Submit your set to the max of five groups. In choosing the groups: <figure rend="Make Your Polyvore Set Popular Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure they are relevant.</item>
<item>Try to choose a mixture of specialised groups, for example, punk, and general groups, everyone on Polyvore.</item>
<item>Choose semi-popular groups with a few hundred members; it they're too unpopular, no one will ever check the page. Equally though, if they're too popular, your set will be knocked off the 'recent sets' section too quickly.</item></list></item>
<item>Change the groups that your set is submitted to regularly. Change it perhaps every two-four weeks. <figure rend="Make Your Polyvore Set Popular Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Optionally, you can create your own group and invite lots of people to join it. <figure rend="Make Your Polyvore Set Popular Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Submit your set to as many different contests as possible. <figure rend="Make Your Polyvore Set Popular Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure you have a lot of contacts. <figure rend="Make Your Polyvore Set Popular Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Comment regularly on other peoples sets (contacts or not), this makes it is very likely they will comment back on yours and is the best way of attracting interest. <figure rend="Make Your Polyvore Set Popular Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Add hash tags. When you make your set, put # (hash tags) on them so when people search for the relevant word, your set/collection/group will come up. <figure rend="Make Your Polyvore Set Popular Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, if your set has a day dress in it put #daydress. Make such it relates to your set.</item></list></item>
<item>Add tag lists of people. Add someone like @shans10, for example. Then that person will see your set, thank you for the tag and look on your wall. People may then tag you back! <figure rend="Make Your Polyvore Set Popular Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make your sets visually appealing and unique. <figure rend="Make Your Polyvore Set Popular Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, don't make an outfit with a bland t-shirt and skinny jeans. Polyvore is used to be creative, not show what you wear every day.</item>
<item>Let's be honest, those sets with items far apart, photographs that aren't incorporated well, and overused (and ugly) fonts and background colors are eyesores. Use only photographs with muted colors in the background to make it visually appealing but not distracting, and try using newspaper articles and quotes to make it look cool. When you aren't putting anything in the background, try to organize your items so that they fit well together, like pieces of a puzzle.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Success on Polyvore isn't everything. Having fun is a better goal.</item>
<item>Give your best, Polyvore fans would love to see you try your all, have fun during the process!</item>
<item>Basically just add a lot of hashtags and you will get likes in just a couple of minutes or hours depending on how good and how much effort you have put to your items/outfits.</item>
<item>Follow other people and like their sets. In return, they'll follow you and like your sets back!</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't comment only on very popular sets. If they're getting dozens every day, they probably won't bother looking at every one.</item></list>
</text>
