<text id="autogum_whow_doc458" title="Check a Licensed Contractor in New York" shortTile="check-licensed-contractor" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-12-08" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Check-a-Licensed-Contractor-in-New-York" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Check a Licensed Contractor in New York</head><p>In the state of New York, all contractors in the home improvement field must have a license as issued by the New York Department of State's (DOS) Division of Consumer Protection. Licensed contractors are required to have workers' compensation insurance and have passed written examinations on contracting laws in addition to a criminal background check. The benefit to checking a contractor's license is that it protects you as a consumer in the event a contractor damages your home or refuses to finish the project you hired them for. To check the status of a licensed contractor in New York City, you must consult with the New York Department of Consumer Affairs (DCA); however, if you are located anywhere else within the state of New York, you may consult directly with the New York DOS. Continue reading this guide to learn about the methods you can use in New York State to check the validity of contractor's licenses.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Checking a Contractor in New York City</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Access the DCA "Instant License Check" tool. The New York DCA website allows you to search for contractors online and verify whether they have a license. <figure rend="Check a Licensed Contractor in New York Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Go to the New York City government website provided to you in the Sources section of this article.</item>
<item>Scroll down on the website until you reach the "Quick Tips" section, then click on the link for "Instant License Check." You will then be taken to the Instant License Check tool.</item></list></item>
<item>Search for the contractor in the New York DCA database. <figure rend="Check a Licensed Contractor in New York Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Enter criteria for the contractor into the fields specified; such as the name of the contractor's business or legal name, the 7-digit license number of the contractor, or the zip code in which the contractor works.</item>
<item>Click on the "Search" button to display your search results.</item></list></item>
<item>Examine search results to locate the contractor. If your contractor is licensed, their name or business will appear in the search results along with their address, contact information, and license number. <figure rend="Check a Licensed Contractor in New York Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Verify the status of the contractor's license. Although a contractor is listed in the DCA database, you may want to consult the DCA to verify that the contractor's license is active and has not been suspended or revoked due to unethical business practices. <figure rend="Check a Licensed Contractor in New York Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Call the DCA by dialing 311 from anywhere within New York City and provide the DCA representative with the contractor's name or license number. You will then be given the complaint history and license status of a particular contractor's license.</item>
<item>If you do not have Internet access, call the New York DCA at 311 from anywhere in New York City to obtain license details for a specific contractor.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Checking a Contractor in New York State</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Consult with the New York DOS to check a contractor's license. The Division of Consumer Protection within the New York DOS can provide you with the status of a contractor's license and their complaint history. <figure rend="Check a Licensed Contractor in New York Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Call the Division of Consumer Protection at 1-518-474-8583 or 1-800-697-1220 between Monday and Friday to speak with a representative.</item>
<item>You may also fax your inquiry to 1-518-486-3936 or send a letter to: New York Department of State (line 1), Division of Consumer Protection (line 2), Consumer Assistance Unit (line 3), Alfred E. Smith Office Building (line 4), 80 South Swan Street (line 5), P.O. Box 22001 (line 6),  Albany, New York 12201-2001 (line 7).</item>
<item>Provide information regarding your inquiry about the contractor to the DOS; such as the contractor's name, business name, address, or license number. The DOS will then correspond with you regarding complaints and the status of the contractor's license.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are located in New York City, and the licensed contractor you hired either refuses to finish working on your home, cannot be located, went out of business, or damaged your home, you can consult with the New York DCA, who may reimburse you a maximum of 15,000 dollars (11,249.44 euros) for your loss.</item></list>
</text>
