<text id="autogum_whow_doc409" title="Celebrate Your Birthday Abroad" shortTile="celebrate-birthday" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-08-12" dateModified="2018-07-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Celebrate-Your-Birthday-Abroad" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Celebrate Your Birthday Abroad</head><p>Birthdays are days to definitely be remembered. Some can remember all the way back to one of their first birthdays because it was made memorable. Would you like a memorable birthday? Then go abroad! There are plenty of selections and landmarks that can make your birthday definitely one to be remembered. Here is a how-to on the best way to do this! Enjoy!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Decide where you want to go. Do you fancy a trip in Europe? How about an American adventure? Maybe an Asian week of fun is more your style? Wherever you want to go, make sure you have planned out how many days you are going for, who you are going with, and what you are going to do and see. A spot of cuisine-tasting is a must! <figure rend="Celebrate Your Birthday Abroad Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Book accommodations. Know what hotel you are staying in and what the prices are. Make sure you don't go somewhere too pricey because you will be too worked up worrying about how you can pay it and won't take as much from the vacation as you would. Be sensible. <figure rend="Celebrate Your Birthday Abroad Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make a list of what you will pack but keep it down to the bare minimum. You don't want to be carting lots of bags everywhere. Take the essentials and a couple of other things and you should be fine. When you do come to packing, choose a wheely-case so it's easier to carry. <figure rend="Celebrate Your Birthday Abroad Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Research restaurants near the place you are staying. You don't want to arrive at a place where there is no food you like for your birthday meal. Once you dine at the restaurant, make sure to leave room for cake! <figure rend="Celebrate Your Birthday Abroad Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't worry about the plane journey. Make sure you have all the required things for the plane such as times and your passport. Check your passport is up-to-date and ready for the trip. <figure rend="Celebrate Your Birthday Abroad Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Once you have everything packed and organized, enjoy your birthday! This is the most important step you cannot do without. You shouldn't be stressing about the organization of your birthday but instead be having as much fun as you can. Don't just limit the vacation to your birthday, make a week or weekend out of it. This has got to be the most important step! Enjoy! <figure rend="Celebrate Your Birthday Abroad Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Treat yourself! Make sure you buy yourself a nice meal on your birthday or something along that lines.</item>
<item>Enjoy the national cuisine!</item>
<item>Make sure you don't forget to miss out on the opportunity to check out the country's best landmarks. Don't visit London without seeing Westminster Abbey! Don't check out France without seeing the Eiffel Tower!</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't forget to update your passport. The oldest trick (a very mean trick!) in the book.</item>
<item>Don't forget any essentials! Some prices abroad for basics are expensive so watch out!</item>
<item>Don't worry! Relax and enjoy your day!</item></list>
</text>
