<text id="autogum_whow_doc279" title="Cook Piyazi" shortTile="cook-piyazi" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-09-27" dateModified="2018-12-08" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Cook-Piyazi" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Cook Piyazi</head><p>Piyaz refers to onion in Bengali and indicates that this appetizer’s main ingredient is onions. This recipe originated in South Asia and is made in many South Asian households. </p>
<head>Ingredients</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>1 cup of red lentils (or other types)</item>
<item>Onion</item>
<item>1 teaspoon salt</item>
<item>1 teaspoon red chili powder</item>
<item>½ teaspoon turmeric powder</item>
<item>½ teaspoon cumin powder</item>
<item>1 teaspoon curry powder</item>
<item>1 teaspoon coriander powder</item>
<item>2 cups of vegetable oil (or another oil)</item>
<item>Chili peppers</item></list>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Gather the necessary ingredients. <figure rend="80CA1D08 2C25 4BFA 8571 402FC7C4291E.jpeg"></figure></item>
<item>Wash one cup of lentils and let it soak in a bowl of water for an hour. This will make them soft. <figure rend="121E0EF3 8E47 46A4 B2FA DEE456DADCEE (1).jpeg"></figure></item>
<item>Rinse the lentils thoroughly with water.</item>
<item> Prepare a bowl to add the next ingredients in. Wash it and rinse it clean.</item>
<item>Blend the lentils until it becomes a thick paste. Use a blender or immersion blender on low.  Scoop out the lentil puree into the bowl with a spoon. <figure rend="737E9B25 5183 420F A3C8 48B6ADF76568.jpeg"></figure></item>
<item>Peel and dice an onion. Remove the tip and the root of the onion. Cut the onion in half and start dicing. Put it into the bowl.</item>
<item>Put a teaspoon of salt into the bowl. Add more if you would like.</item>
<item>Put a teaspoon of red chili powder. Red chili powder is to give the lentil puree spice. Adjust the amount of spice to your liking.</item>
<item>Put in one teaspoon of curry powder. This adds a bit of seasoning and just enough spice.</item>
<item>Put one teaspoon of coriander powder. Coriander powder is used to give the Piyazi aroma and a savory taste.</item>
<item>Put in half a teaspoon of cumin powder. Cumin powder is used to give the Piyazi fragrance.</item>
<item>Put in half a teaspoon of turmeric powder. This gives the Piyazi some color. <figure rend="9082551D 8D20 4E54 904B 1C47C019B5CE.jpeg"></figure></item>
<item>Mix all the ingredients together using your hands. Wash your hands before so that they're clean.</item>
<item>Put two cups of oil in frying pan and let the oil heat up on medium heat for two to three minutes. Use any cooking oil of your choice, preferably vegetable oil. <figure rend="A79CEED5 06A2 488F B5AD 363A0DA18ACD.jpeg"></figure></item>
<item>Put the lentil paste into the frying pan in a circular shape. Roll the lentil paste into a bite-sized ball with both hands. Use both hands and flatten the ball into a small patty, no bigger than the palm of your hand. <figure rend="82158572 67DF 4BE4 BC9C 2003F7602655.jpeg"></figure></item>
<item>Fry each side of the lentil paste for 15 minutes or until it becomes golden brown and hardened on each side. Be sure the Piyazi is cooked thoroughly, or else it will be raw and too watery inside. It should be crisp on the outside and chewy on the inside. <figure rend="7114CCB0 31F7 45D1 A9E3 4EC5B7D3A190.jpeg"></figure></item>
<item>Wait 30 more minutes. Take the Piyazi out of the frying pan. Pat the Piyazi with paper towels to rid it of excess oil. Let the Piyazi cool for a few minutes before enjoying a delicious snack. Garnish the dish with chili peppers. <figure rend="DB25ECF2 5532 41AE BD4F 85B5813FB52A.jpeg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Bowls</item>
<item>Spoon</item>
<item>Blender</item>
<item>Frying Pan</item></list>
</text>
