<text id="autogum_whow_doc562" title="Make Dogs Adapt to the New Environment Quickly" shortTile="make-dogs-adapt-new" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-07-31" dateModified="2019-08-03" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-Dogs-Adapt-to-the-New-Environment-Quickly" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make Dogs Adapt to the New Environment Quickly</head><p>When you bring your dog home, don't rush to train it. Give it a few days to understand its current situation and know who you are. You can also use this time to understand its natural nature and personality, and once it has adapted to your environment and its surroundings, you can start teaching them. The one exception is to get the dog to get used to the new home it lives in as soon as possible.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Create a good living space for your dog. Because the environment has changed, it has brought a lot of pressure on the dog. Therefore, after bringing the dog home, the dog should be placed in the proper position at home as soon as possible. If the place is not big, arrange a dog in a corner of the living room, and prepare food and water, as well as toys to stabilize the dog. If necessary, you can install a fence in a certain range to make the dog more secure, and also adapt to the new environment.</item>
<item>Introduce family members carefully. Not every dog is approachable; it doesn't mean it's not good, but it may take time to get used to it. Introducing dogs and family members one by one, allowing dogs to adapt to this strange environment more quickly. Pay attention to the reaction of the dog when it comes into contact with other people. If the dog suddenly growls or wants to rush to the family, it should be stopped in time. After all, not every member of the family can accept such a warm hug. If the family is gone at night and the dog is already asleep, it should not be forced to wake the dog. This will only be counterproductive.</item>
<item>Use appropriate reward training. Training dogs should start small, which will make the dog listen to you more. Of course, when the dog has just arrived at your home, it will not be forced to learn on the first day. To get your dog accustomed to your instructions, keep in mind that instructions should not be complicated, and it is best to do it in single words. When the dog follows the instructions, it can be rewarded, such as snacks or praise. The dog will soon remember that obeying the instructions is good for it and expects to continue to receive the approval of the owner.</item>
<item>Arrange the toilet area. It is also a big problem for dogs to go to the toilet. After all, the owner has to work for a long time, and may not have time to take the dog out for a walk. If you can't take your dog out to the toilet every day, you should prepare a special dog toilet for the dog and train the dog to use it. Once you have decided on the location of the dog's toilet, do not make changes as much as possible to avoid confusion.</item>
<item>Observe the dog carefully.. When a dog comes to your home, you may be very excited. At this time, as a master, you should try to keep the dog calm. Don't let too many strangers visit the first week of taking the dog home, so as not to affect the dog's mood. Let the dog have enough time to adjust the mood, and let you observe the behavior of the dog, there is no need for improvement.</item>
<item>Don't be impatient. Dogs, like humans, must have a break-in period to adapt to the new environment.  What you can do is to treat with patience, let love tolerate dogs, and make appropriate guidance to let the dog adapt to your home as soon as possible.
<list type="unordered"><item>Try to spend time with the dog. Then the dog will soon be able to integrate into the new environment and live happily.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
