<text id="autogum_whow_doc515" title="Start an Accessory Business" shortTile="start-accessory-business" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2012-04-02" dateModified="2018-07-04" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Start-an-Accessory-Business" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Start an Accessory Business</head><p>If you are interested in selling accessories (jewellery, bags, hats etc.) then follow these few steps that should get you up and running.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Think of a name. <figure rend="Start an Accessory Business Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>When thinking of a brand name, it's usually best to get a notepad ready for a list that will help you remember all the name and make the process of elimination easier. Try to think of something that emphasises your persona or brand message.</item></list></item>
<item>Practice makes perfect <figure rend="Start an Accessory Business Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Go on the Internet to try to find some accessory-making courses/classes. This will help make your brand more original, creative and will also make your days a bit easier.</item></list></item>
<item>Choose your brand's theme. <figure rend="Start an Accessory Business Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Consider how you want to represent yourself and your brand. If you're a happy person, opt for light colours and fun designs. If you're a serious, practical person, design the whole brand to how it suits you! This is one of the most important parts.</item></list></item>
<item>Get inspired. <figure rend="Start an Accessory Business Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Before you actually start making anything or finalising your brand, go to craft fairs and look at some of the homemade jewelry they have created. Take a note down of the properties and design features of the ones that you like so you can mix them up and add to yours when you do start making!</item></list></item>
<item>Have patience. <figure rend="Start an Accessory Business Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make the jewelry! If you couldn't find much inspiration, go on YouTube and see how they make the jewelry in different ways to give effect.</item>
<item>Tell and show people. <figure rend="Start an Accessory Business Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>After making all your fabulous pieces, it's time to spread the word and put on a jewelry party! Get a few friends to come round, have a few drinks, mingle but most importantly, ask for feedback and try to sell the bracelets! Obviously, you shouldn't have high prices as they are not part of a big brand yet, but hopefully soon will be!</item></list></item>
<item>Advertise your products. <figure rend="Start an Accessory Business Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Put flyers up around town and posting business cards on bulletin boards really help improve business. Also, setting up your own website is another really helpful way to get people to buy your jewelry and try to get 'founded' by shops and big accessory brands.</item></list></item>
<item>Meet the managers. <figure rend="Start an Accessory Business Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>iI the jewelry is selling, it's time to talk to some high street store managers that could maybe give you a brand funded by that shop. Making an appointment with a lower end fashion store is a good way to start. Keep on trying until you finally get accepted.</item></list></item>
<item>Help out. <figure rend="Start an Accessory Business Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>As you went to craft fairs earlier on, do the same and sell some of your accessories there, maybe to help someone in the same position as you were! Make multiple of the same design just in case some are more popular than others.</item></list></item>
<item>Have a grand opening. <figure rend="Start an Accessory Business Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>if you think you have enough money, and the accessories will do well enough, maybe it's time to open up your own shop! Look around town and the high street to see if there are any places to let, or set up your own stall in the middle of a shopping centre. You could maybe think about getting a ground floor apartment close to where you live and use that as the shop, with the landlord's permission.</item></list></item>
<item>Get some staff and your own shop! As the job market is rapidly getting lower, you could help a non-working friend out by giving them a job. Even though you have your own business, it never hurts to carry the store on and try to set up a brand in another shop.
<list type="unordered"><item>Choose an employee of the month. <figure rend="Start an Accessory Business Step 11.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Never give up. <figure rend="Start an Accessory Business Step 12 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If the business isn't going so well, ask your friends to recommend you and advertise more on the radio or tv.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Ask a lot of stores if they wouldn't mind using your designs for their store. Don't just use only one and keep persisting.</item>
<item>Only open a store if your positive the accessories are doing well. Otherwise stick to the Internet or open a stall.</item>
<item>If you have a 3+ story house, why not consider using the ground floor as your store? It's cheaper and it won't be that far to travel to.</item>
<item>At the jewelry parties, ask your friends to bring a few of their friends for more recommendations.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You may experience debt if you are not sure about the business levels and profits.</item></list>
</text>
