<text id="autogum_whow_doc675" title="Do a Chest Dip" shortTile="chest-dip" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-01-30" dateModified="2019-07-31" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Do-a-Chest-Dip" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Do a Chest Dip</head><p>Chest dips are similar to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Do_Dips">tricep dips</ref> but—as you can probably guess—they work the chest muscles instead. Whether you have your own parallel bars, a gym membership, or some furniture that you can do the motion from, chest dips are simple exercises that can create great results. With a bit of effort and perseverance, you can start adding weight as you do your dips and pack on the chest muscle!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Performing a Basic Chest Dip</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Use parallel bars or similar equipment. Either purchase parallel bars from an online supplier, head to a local gym and use the parallel bars there, or use something such as monkey bars, a pair of sturdy chairs or bar stools, or even a pair of sawhorses. Regardless of what you use, make sure they are about the height of your hands and shoulder-width apart for the best results. <figure rend="Do a Chest Dip Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you purchase parallel bars, be sure that they are listed for a weight capacity that is more than your bodyweight.</item></list></item>
<item>Hold your body above the parallel bars at arm's length.  Grip each bar with one hand and raise yourself above them with your arms locked. Keep your arms parallel with your torso, your head in a neutral position (not looking up or down), and your knees bent so your thighs are perpendicular to your torso. <figure rend="Do a Chest Dip Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Point your heels behind you so that your body makes an "L" shape.</item>
<item>Keep your torso angled slightly forward—about 20 to 30 degrees—as opposed to upright to work your chest muscles instead of your triceps.</item></list></item>
<item>Lower yourself down slowly while breathing in. Continue until your shoulders are just below your elbows, but be careful not to go too far! If you do, you may injure your shoulder. Keep your torso leaning forward at an angle of about 30 degrees and flare your elbows outward from your body until you can feel your chest muscles stretch slightly. <figure rend="Do a Chest Dip Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you're having trouble flaring your elbows, imagine you have a gun holstered on each hip and you're ready to reach for both at the same time. This is also known as the "gunslinger" position.</item>
<item>Make sure to keep your head in alignment with your spine. Do not drop your head or jut out your chin. Look at a position on the floor slightly in front of you as you do this exercise.</item></list></item>
<item>Lift yourself back into the starting position while breathing out. Once you feel a slight stretch in your chest muscles, push yourself back up and make an effort to use these chest muscles as much as possible to take the pressure off your arm muscles. Be sure to breathe out slowly and steadily throughout this entire motion. <figure rend="Do a Chest Dip Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't lock your elbows once you reach the top—this is only necessary when getting into position, not during the midst of the exercise.</item>
<item>Squeeze your chest for 1 second while at the top of this motion.</item>
<item>Repeat the chest dip motion as many times as you need to. Start by doing 3 sets of 6 to 8 and work your way up to 3 sets of 10 to 12 repetitions.</item></list></item>
<item>Add extra weight once you can do 10 to 12 repetitions with just your bodyweight. Once you can do 10 to 12 chest dips in a row, add some resistance with a weight vest or weight belt. Start by adding  and do 3 sets of 6 to 8 repetitions. <figure rend="Do a Chest Dip Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Keep adding  of weight at a time after you're comfortable doing 3 sets of 6 to 8 repetitions.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Using a Dip Assist Machine</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Use a dip assist machine at a gym or purchase your own. Sign up to a local gym to use their equipment. The dip assist machine makes it much easier to start doing your chest dips slowly and gradually build your strength. <figure rend="Do a Chest Dip Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Check the membership prices for the closest gyms and compare them to help you make the most affordable decision.</item>
<item>Use a dip assist machine if this is your first time doing chest dips or you don't have the necessary strength to perform them yet.</item>
<item>Purchase a dip assist machine from an online supplier if you'd rather invest in one yourself.</item></list></item>
<item>Conduct 1 chest dip to gauge how much help you need. Start by ensuring that the dip assist machine's weight is set to "0." Now, kneel on the levered platform, grip each bar tightly, and lift yourself into the air. With your arms parallel and locked and your head in a neutral position, lower yourself down. Once you feel your chest muscles start to stretch, push yourself back up. If you're having trouble, you need to add weight to the machine. <figure rend="Do a Chest Dip Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always keep your torso angled forward at 20 to 30 degrees.</item>
<item>Point your heels behind you and keep your knees bent so your thighs are perpendicular to your calves.</item>
<item>Focus on using your chest muscles more than your arms when you lift yourself back up.</item>
<item>Breath in as you lower yourself and out as you raise yourself.</item>
<item>Don't lock your elbows at the top of the position during your repetitions—only at the beginning of the set.</item></list></item>
<item>Adjust the weight until you have the assistance you need. Adding weight will actually make the exercise easier. For example, a  plate will lighten your load by . Locate the metal bar that inserts through the appropriate weight slot and put it through. <figure rend="Do a Chest Dip Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try a few different weights and use the one that gives you enough of a challenge without pushing yourself too much.</item>
<item>Ask a staff member if you're having trouble using the machine.</item>
<item>Continue adjusting the weight until you can dip smoothly but start to struggle as you reach your final rep.</item></list></item>
<item>Continue your sets and decrease the dip machine weight as needed. Give yourself a 60-second break between each set. As you progress and become more comfortable, decrease the weight. You don't have to do this all in one session, but remember the weight you use during each gym session so you can decrease it next time if necessary. <figure rend="Do a Chest Dip Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, if you do 3 sets of 8 reps with  of help from the dip assist, decrease the assistance to  for the next gym session, and then remove assistance completely from the following one.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always keep your parallel bars or makeshift bars shoulder-width apart.</item>
<item>Start on your knees if any pair of furniture pieces is too close to the ground. Afterward, push your body up while keeping your knees bent and your heels pointing behind you.</item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Perform-Chest-Stretches">Stretch your chest</ref> to help relax the pectoral muscles after doing this exercise. For an easy way to do this, lie on your back and reach your arms out to your sides.</item></list>
</text>
