<text id="autogum_whow_doc525" title="Start a Bangle Selling Business" shortTile="start-bangle-selling" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-03-13" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Start-a-Bangle-Selling-Business" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Start a Bangle Selling Business</head><p>Bangles are bracelets that have been a fashion staple for decades. If you have design talent and are interested in selling handmade jewelry, making and selling bangles could be a great work from home business niche. Specialize in fun decorated plastic bangles or make more intricate cuff bangles from wire. To get started, learn how to start a bangle selling business, market your products and grow your business.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Decide what kinds of bangles to sell and who to sell to. Start by defining your target customer, and then figure out what kind of products the customer will buy. For example, plastic bangles can be marketed to children or young women, while wire or metal cuff bangles are a good choice for adults. Any type of bangle can be promoted as a gift item or customized for special occasions like holidays, weddings and parties. <figure rend="Start a Bangle Selling Business Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find and order supplies. Build a relationship with suppliers who are reliable and sell quality products. Keep track of where you order supplies from and the item numbers for quick ordering. Some supplies you may need include plastic bangles, wire, beads, pliers and glue, depending on what type of bangles you decide to make. <figure rend="Start a Bangle Selling Business Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Organize and create your work area. You'll need spaces for making and decorating bangles, shipping orders and handling correspondence, marketing and orders.</item>
<item>Get advice from an attorney, small business advisor or accountant about how to start a bangle selling business, including handling taxes, insurance and licensing. Find out whether to set up your company as a corporation or sole proprietorship.</item>
<item>Register your business with the IRS. You can either register in your name, or come up with a name for your business and then register the name. Get necessary local and state licenses. Call your local zoning office or business association to find out what licenses you need. <figure rend="Start a Bangle Selling Business Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Team up with other craftspeople. Look for people who make jewelry or accessories that are complimentary to your bangles. Join together to sell your products wholesale or retail. <figure rend="Start a Bangle Selling Business Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Come up with a marketing plan of how to sell and advertise your handmade jewelry. Places to sell include local boutiques, craft shops, party and holiday related stores and jewelry stores. Set up shops on Etsy, eBay or other online storefronts and boutiques. Consider adding other handmade jewelry items to increase sales. <figure rend="Start a Bangle Selling Business Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Read books, get information online, and take local or online classes to learn the practical aspects of running a home business. Learn how to keep records, do basic accounting and market your products. <figure rend="Start a Bangle Selling Business Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Create a website and other online profiles. A blog can help personalize your bangles, show how they can be used and make it easier to find your bangles. Create profiles on social networking sites, especially Facebook, Myspace and Flickr. Promote your handmade jewelry on forums and sites that your customers visit, like mom forums to promote childrens' bangles for children or fashion related sites to market products for adults. <figure rend="Start a Bangle Selling Business Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
