<text id="autogum_whow_doc175" title="Straighten Out Your Thoughts" shortTile="straighten-out-thoughts" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2016-02-19" dateModified="2017-01-13" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Straighten-Out-Your-Thoughts" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Straighten Out Your Thoughts</head><p>Do you ever find yourself tripping over all of the thoughts in your head? Do you ever just want to straighten them out so you can focus on more important things in life like work, school and relationships? Well here you will find step-by-step ways on how to let your thoughts untangle so you can focus on more important things.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>The first thing to do is to tidy your room or house, while doing this your mind will focus on other things, it will give you more room to think. While going through your stuff you might be able to unravel some of your thoughts, and also tidy up a bit!
<list type="unordered"><item>Look through old photos and relive old times.</item>
<item>Think about the time you bought or recieved the things you have in your hands.</item>
<item>Listen to your favourite music.</item>
<item>Light some nice smelling candles.</item></list></item>
<item>Once you've had a relaxing cleanse of the area around you its time to clean up your mind, sit down and write down what you felt like when you were going through your stuff.
<list type="unordered"><item>Once you've wrote that down write about what you've done today and who you've talked to and how that made you feel, what were you thinking while you were talking to them? What do you like about them? What do you dislike?</item>
<item>Think about other days that have made you feel happy or sad. What happened in these days that were different from others, how can you prevent the sad days and increase the happy days?</item>
<item>Write down everything you think about when you think of certain people or objects or subjects.</item>
<item>Write down why you have a this certain feeling for one thing but not for another. What's the difference?</item>
<item>How are you going to make your happy days increase? Now you know and understand what things happen on a happy day you can try do them more often. It can be anything big or small like talking to a old friend again or trying out a new sport.</item>
<item>To finish it of on a positive note write down what your goals for the future are, write what you want to do and achieve, write about how your going to achieve this, what are you going to do and change to fufill your goals?</item></list></item>
<item>After all that thinking you should relax and think about your goals or anything that makes you happy, here are some ideas:
<list type="unordered"><item>Take a long relaxing bath.</item>
<item>Go out for a run and/or exersize.</item>
<item>Read a book.</item>
<item>Go out for coffee with a friend.</item>
<item>Lie down and listen to music.</item>
<item>Go for a walk out in the park.</item>
<item>Cuddle up with a loved one.</item>
<item>Go for a drive somewhere peaceful.</item>
<item>Stay home make yourself some tea and watch your favourite TV shows or movie.</item></list></item>
<item>Everynight while your lying in bed think about:
<list type="unordered"><item>How well your doing with your goals</item>
<item>Think about what you done that day and how that made you feel</item>
<item>Think about happy days</item>
<item>Sort though your thoughts by just reliving certain days, pick out everything you felt, ask yourself, Why did I feel this way? Is this a good or bad thing? If bad how can I prevent it? If good how can I continue feeling this way?</item></list></item>
<item>Everytime your feeling muddled just repeat these steps over and over again. You will see improvements because over time you might of have achieved these goals and that is a very good feeling, or you might have new things you want to achieve.Never give up on your goals keep trying and trying again.I believe you can do it.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Remember that its best to write your thoughts down rather than bottle them up.</item>
<item>Remember what makes a good day and a bad day, how can you decrease the bad days and increase the good?</item>
<item>Remember you can achieve your goals if you try hard and work hard. Remember; you have no boundaries.</item></list>
</text>
