<text id="autogum_whow_doc641" title="Play Volleyballoon" shortTile="play-volleyballoon" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2013-10-21" dateModified="2019-07-11" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Play-Volleyballoon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Play Volleyballoon</head><p>Volleyballoon is a fun variation on volleyball, where you use a balloon instead of a ball. It works great at birthday parties and slumber parties, where you probably already have some balloons lying around. It's also fun and easy to play in the classroom or living room on a rainy day. Blow up a few balloons, grab some friends, and you're ready to play! </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Preparing the Game</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find a large space indoors. Make sure there isn’t anything fragile around that players could accidentally knock over and break. If you’re playing in the living room and have a coffee table, you should move it out of the way so nobody trips. If you’re playing in a classroom, move the desks to two sides of the room, with a space in the middle.</item>
<item>Divide the space in half with a string. Take a long piece of string and tape it to each wall so that it is about the height of a volleyball net. For an easier variation, for younger children, just put the string on the floor. A rope or a long length of yarn can work too.
<list type="unordered"><item>Also make sure you decide on what will be out of bounds. You can mark out of bounds with string or masking tape, or just decide on it as a group.</item></list></item>
<item>Blow up a few balloons. If you need help <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Blow_Up_a_Balloon">blowing up the balloons</ref>, ask an adult. You’ll only use one balloon at a time to play, but it’s important to have spares in case one of them pops!
<list type="unordered"><item>Don’t use a helium balloon, because that would just float to the ceiling and get stuck up there.</item></list></item>
<item>Divide the people playing into even teams. If you have twelve people, get six on each team. That’s how many you use to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Play_Volleyball">play volleyball</ref>. But don’t worry if you have fewer or more people! Volleyballoon is a very casual game and can be played with any number of people. Decide which team is going to serve first.
<list type="unordered"><item>If some of the team members are much taller than others, like if you’re playing with a mixture of adults and kids, you might want to have the taller players play on their knees.</item>
<item>If you’re playing in a classroom, have everyone sit on top of their desks to play. Nobody can leave their desk during a play, but you can rotate desks after each play.</item></list></item>
<item>Decide how long you will play the game. This is important to decide before you start, so that you know who will win. You can choose to play until one side reaches 25 points, in which case they will be the winner. That’s how many points it takes to win one set of a real volleyball game. Or you can choose to play for 10 minutes, and see which team has more points at the end. Talk with your friends to come to a decision. Now you’re ready to play!</item></list>
<head>Playing Volleyballoon</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Have one person serve the balloon over the dividing line. Serve the balloon by throwing it in the air and whacking it with the heel of your hand across the line. After the balloon is served, the game has begun. The balloon will be in the other team’s possession. They will pass it back and forth between each other and try to hit it back over the line.</item>
<item>Pass the balloon at least two times before you hit it over the line. This means that at least three separate teammates will touch the balloon before it goes over the line. This rule only applies if you have more than three people playing on each team. It's to make sure more people get a chance to hit the balloon.
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not catch the balloon and throw it to your teammate. Instead, hit it. If you accidentally catch the balloon, the other team gets a point.</item></list></item>
<item>Stay on your side of the dividing line when you play. Don’t run into the other side of the room or even reach over the net! That’s the other team’s territory. You have to stay on your side of the line. If you accidentally reach over the net, the other team gets a point.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you want, you can have positions and rotate each play. This is helpful if you’re playing in a classroom and all sitting on desks. Or, all the teammates can just run around on your side of the net.</item></list></item>
<item>Try using volleyball moves to hit the balloon. You can <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Bump_a_Volleyball">bump</ref> the balloon by clasping your hands and hitting the balloon with both arms between your wrists and elbows. If the balloon is coming from above, you can <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Set_a_Volleyball">set</ref> the balloon by extending your hands over your head, and positioning them so that there is a triangular window between your two hands. Then lightly hit the balloon with your fingers.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you don’t want to do these fancy volleyball hits, just hit the balloon with your arm, elbow, head, shoulder, or knee. Anywhere works, because the balloon is soft enough that it won’t hurt you.</item></list></item>
<item>Keep track of the points each team has won. If the balloon touches the ground on your side, the other team gets a point. If you hit the balloon out of bounds, the other team gets a point.[
<list type="unordered"><item>If the balloon goes under the dividing line, instead of over, the other team gets a point.</item></list></item>
<item>Play until one side reaches a set number of points or until you reach your time limit. In real volleyball, each set goes until 25 points, and the best of three sets wins. Volleyballoon is more casual, though, so go until the time or number of points you and your group decided. In real volleyball, you have to win by 2 points, but just 1 point is fine for volleyballoon.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make the game extra challenging by playing with multiple balloons at once.</item>
<item>Another good challenge is to have everyone play on their knees.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>A few balloons</item>
<item>String or rope to divide the room</item>
<item>Friends to play with!</item></list>
</text>
