<text id="autogum_whow_doc276" title="Roast Mushrooms" shortTile="roast-mushrooms" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-02-22" dateModified="2019-04-17" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Roast-Mushrooms" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Roast Mushrooms</head><p>To add a meaty depth of flavor to your food, include roasted mushrooms. It's easy to season a sheet of your favorite mushrooms and throw them in the oven while you prepare the rest of your meal. Consider using fresh herbs, garlic, balsamic vinegar, oil, or butter. Once the roasted mushrooms are tender and fragrant, serve them with a hearty steak or make them the main course of a vegetarian meal.</p>
<head>Ingredients</head>
<head>Roasted Mushrooms with Herbs</head>
<list type="unordered"><item> of button or cremini mushrooms</item>
<item> of extra-virgin olive oil</item>
<item>Kosher salt and freshly ground black pepper</item>
<item>8 to 12 sprigs of fresh thyme or rosemary</item>
<item>2 tablespoons (5 g) of chopped parsley, chives, tarragon, or other fresh herbs</item></list>
<p><hi rend="italic">Makes  of mushrooms</hi></p>
<head>Garlic and Balsamic Roasted Mushrooms</head>
<list type="unordered"><item> of mushrooms, wiped clean</item>
<item>4 cloves of garlic, minced</item>
<item> of olive oil</item>
<item> of balsamic vinegar</item>
<item>1 teaspoon (1 g) of fresh thyme, minced</item>
<item>Salt and pepper to taste</item>
<item>4 tablespoons (56 g) of butter, diced</item></list>
<p><hi rend="italic">Makes  of mushrooms</hi></p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Roasted Mushrooms with Herbs</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Preheat the oven to  and line a sheet with foil. Use a rimmed baking sheet so the mushrooms don't slide off as you're transferring them to the oven. Tear a sheet of aluminum foil and lay it on the bottom of the rimmed baking sheet. <figure rend="Roast Mushrooms Step 1 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you don't have aluminum foil, use parchment paper.</item></list></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Clean_Mushrooms">Rinse</ref> the mushrooms and cut them into quarters. Get out  of button or cremini mushrooms and pull off the stems. Rinse the mushroom caps under cold water to remove any dirt or debris. Then cut each cap into quarters. <figure rend="Roast Mushrooms Step 2 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Discard the stems or add them to the pot when you make <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_Vegetable_Stock">vegetable stock</ref>.</item></list></item>
<item>Mix the mushrooms with olive oil, salt, and pepper. Put the mushroom quarters into a bowl and pour  of extra-virgin olive oil over them. Sprinkle kosher salt and freshly ground black pepper to taste. Then use a large spoon to toss the mushrooms until they're coated with the oil.{{greenbox:<hi rend="bold">Moroccan Spice Variation:</hi>1/2 teaspoon (1 g) of ground cumin1/4 teaspoon (0.5 g) of ground coriander1/8 teaspoon (0.3 g) of chili powder1/4 teaspoon (0.5 g) of paprika1/4 teaspoon (0.5 g) of ground cinnamon1/2 teaspoon (1 g) of ground ginger}} <figure rend="Roast Mushrooms Step 3 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Spread the mushrooms on the sheet and scatter herb sprigs on top. Spoon the seasoned mushroom quarters onto the foil-lined sheet. Arrange them so they're in an even layer. Then place 8 to 12 sprigs of fresh thyme or rosemary over the mushrooms. <figure rend="Roast Mushrooms Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The herbs will flavor the mushrooms as they cook.</item></list></item>
<item>Roast the mushrooms for 15 minutes and drain the liquid from the pan. Put the baking sheet in the preheated oven and cook the mushrooms until they soften a little. Then remove the sheet and set a bowl on the counter. Carefully tilt the sheet so the liquid from the mushrooms drains into the bowl. <figure rend="Roast Mushrooms Step 5 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Save this liquid to use in a different recipe. For example, use the liquid as a marinade or seasoning sauce for a stir fry.</item></list></item>
<item>Roast the mushrooms for 30 more minutes. Return the baking sheet to the oven and let the mushrooms finish cooking. They should become tender and they'll shrink a little. <figure rend="Roast Mushrooms Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Since you removed the liquid that the mushrooms gave off, they'll become browned and slightly caramelized instead of mushy.</item></list></item>
<item>Toss the mushrooms with chopped herbs and serve them. Turn off the oven and remove the baking sheet. Discard the sprigs of thyme or rosemary and spoon the mushrooms into a serving dish. Stir in 2 tablespoons (5 g) of chopped parsley, chives, tarragon, or other fresh herbs and then serve the mushrooms while they're still hot. <figure rend="Roast Mushrooms Step 7 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Store the leftover mushrooms in an airtight container for up to 3 to 5 days.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Garlic and Balsamic Roasted Mushrooms</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Preheat the oven to  and grease or line a baking sheet. Get out a rimmed baking sheet and lay a sheet of aluminum foil on it. If you prefer, spray the sheet with nonstick cooking spray instead. <figure rend="Roast Mushrooms Step 8 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you don't have a rimmed baking sheet, use a  baking dish.</item></list></item>
<item>Wipe the mushrooms with a damp cloth and remove the stems. Get out  of mushrooms and dip a paper towel in water. Wring out the water and wipe the mushrooms with the damp cloth to remove dirt and grit. Then pop off the stems from each mushroom and discard them. <figure rend="Roast Mushrooms Step 9 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Use your favorite type of mushroom for this recipe. For example, try button, cremini, or shiitake.</item></list></item>
<item>Mix the whole mushrooms with garlic, oil, vinegar, and seasonings. Put the whole mushrooms into a large bowl and pour  of olive oil along with  of balsamic vinegar over them. Add 4 cloves of minced garlic and 1 teaspoon (1 g) of minced fresh thyme. Then use a large spoon to toss the mixture. <figure rend="Roast Mushrooms Step 10 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can also add salt and pepper according to your taste.</item></list></item>
<item>Put the mushrooms on the sheet and scatter butter over them. Arrange the mushrooms so they're in a single layer. This will help them roast evenly. Then take 4 tablespoons (56 g) of diced butter and sprinkle the small cubes across the mushrooms. <figure rend="Roast Mushrooms Step 11 Version 2.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The butter will melt to create a flavorful sauce as the mushrooms roast.</item></list></item>
<item>Roast the garlic and balsamic mushrooms for 20 to 25 minutes. Put the baking sheet into the preheated oven and cook the mushrooms until they're soft. Then remove the baking sheet and serve the mushrooms while they're still hot. <figure rend="Roast Mushrooms Step 12 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The mushrooms and garlic should smell fragrant once the mixture has finished cooking.</item>
<item>Store the leftover mushrooms in an airtight container for up to 3 to 5 days.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>For a simple way to round out a meal, serve roasted mushrooms with crusty bread and a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_a_Garden_Salad">garden salad</ref>.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<head>Roasted Mushrooms with Herbs</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Measuring cups and spoons</item>
<item>Knife and cutting board</item>
<item>Rimmed baking sheet</item>
<item>Bowl</item>
<item>Aluminum foil</item>
<item>Serving bowl</item></list>
<head>Garlic and Balsamic Roasted Mushrooms</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Measuring cups and spoons</item>
<item>Knife and cutting board</item>
<item>Baking sheet</item>
<item>Aluminum foil</item></list>
</text>
