<text id="autogum_whow_doc373" title="Make a Bracelet on a Cardboard Loom" shortTile="make-bracelet-cardboard" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-07-02" dateModified="2019-10-21" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-a-Bracelet-on-a-Cardboard-Loom" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make a Bracelet on a Cardboard Loom</head><p>You want to make a bracelet, but you don’t know how. You don’t have a loom and you don’t have the money to buy one. That's okay, you can just make a loom out of cardboard. This is a fun activity that is easy to learn. You can turn the bracelets you make into friendship bracelets, regular bracelets, or any other type of bracelet. Here are some simple steps to help you out. Happy bracelet making!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Organizing The Thread</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Pick out your colors. You can have as many as 7 and as little as 1 color. The more colors you have, the more exciting your bracelet will be!</item>
<item>Measure your threads so you can tie them. Take one thread color and wrap it around your wrist or ankle about 7-8 times. Your bracelet won't need to be this long, but it is better to have it longer than not have enough to finish! After you cut this thread, use it as a template for all your other colors and cut them the same length, too. You will need 7 total threads so you can have three, fold in half, then add one and tie, or have four ties and then cut one out. Combine all your threads and fold them all in half. (This helps tie it off later) On the end with a loop, tie a knot about half an inch 1/4 to 1/2 an inch. Now you are ready to make the loom.</item></list>
<head>Making The Cardboard Loom</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find a piece of cardboard. You can use anything from a cereal box to a packing box, but you need some sort of cardboard that will be stable enough for you to pull things through it.</item>
<item>Cut the cardboard into the right shape. Take a cup or bowl and trace it on your cardboard and cut it out. To make it your loom, you will need to measure 8 cuts all around the circle all about 1/2 inch deep. They should be about 1 inch apart from each other but that will depend on how big your circle is. To finish it off, poke a small hole in the center and you are done with your loom.</item></list>
<head>Making the Bracelet</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>To set it up, you will need to put the knotted end in the center hole. If it is too small, you can make it bigger but be careful because the knot might slip out of the hole if it is too big. Then flip the loom around and organize your threads, one into each slot. You can organize them into a certain pattern or just place them around, it doesn't matter. You may notice you have an empty slot. Don't worry because you will be using this later.</item>
<item>Point the empty slot toward you and begin moving the threads. To move the threads around, count three away from the empty slot going clockwise. Move that third thread to the current empty slot and repeat. Turn to the new empty slot, count three, move the thread to the slot.</item></list>
<head>Tie The End</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Once the bracelet is long enough or it has almost run out of thread, you need to tie it. To secure the bracelet, you can either tie one big knot or tie two threads together at a time.</item>
<item>Split the end into two parts. You can braid them to make it cleaner or leave them as they are. The best way is to put both ends in the loop on the other side and pull them opposite ways. Then thread one side over the top of the loop in the middle. Do that with both sides so there is a pretzle looking knot in the middle. Bring the two sides up and tie them in a single knot. This part is best done with help. You are now finished!</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>The cardboard loom is easiest circular so that the strings are all evenly spread out.</item>
<item>Using 3 or 4 colors are easiest and isn't too crazy to look at.</item>
<item>If you braid your bracelet to the very end and tie it off of your wrist, then you can fold it over twice and have a chain looking bracelet.</item></list>
</text>
