<text id="autogum_whow_doc613" title="Discover More About Who You Are and Be Confident" shortTile="discover-more-confident" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2012-01-18" dateModified="2019-03-26" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Discover-More-About-Who-You-Are-and-Be-Confident" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Discover More About Who You Are and Be Confident</head><p>In the World that we live in today, it is hard for people to find and be okay with themselves. This can be especially hard if you are a teenager or if you are more sensitive than most people. The things that you were told as a child and the beliefs that you have placed upon yourself because of this might have a dramatic effect on the reason why finding yourself seems so difficult.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Recognize the negative messages you've been told. Or the beliefs you have about yourself and when you tell yourself these messages the most. Is it around others? When you're alone? Going out? Speaking in front of people? When you feel insecure about the way you look? Etc. This is important to know because once you know where your irrational beliefs are coming from it will be easier for you to tackle them and get on track to finding yourself and build confidence. <figure rend="Discover More About Who You Are and Be Confident Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Build Up Your Confidence. Once you have recognized the messages you've been believing or telling yourself, its then that you can change them. You can start by analyzing them.It's okay if you can't get to the root of it right away. It takes time. Don't give up! Spend some time, read stories of others with the same struggles as you,listen to songs a lot of times songs will analyze struggles and might even offer advice,Try to get a therapist/counselor but pay attention to whether they understand you or not. <figure rend="Discover More About Who You Are and Be Confident Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be Kind To Yourself. If you catch yourself saying "I'm so stupid" or "I'm a failure" all the time. Recognize it and start changing it. You don't have to go from saying I'm so stupid to I'm so smart. Stay neutral at first then when you're ready,go for the positive. Try saying positive statements to  yourself, like, "I am a positive force in the world!" <figure rend="Discover More About Who You Are and Be Confident Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try Not To Spend a lot of Time Alone or Silent. For some people their negative thoughts come out mostly when they're alone. So try to talk to people, like your mom, friends, brother, sister, cousins, grandma, grandpa. Just to get your mind not thinking of negative things. Try doing hobbies, taking your dog for a walk, joining a club , do sports. <figure rend="Discover More About Who You Are and Be Confident Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get The Thoughts That Everyone is Judging You Out of Your Mind. This sometimes affects a persons confidence and drags them away from themselves. Know that judgments are quick predictions and are usually wrong. <figure rend="Discover More About Who You Are and Be Confident Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Create a List of Who You Are. This might take you a while and that's perfectly fine. Include what you like,the hobbies you like,music,your personality traits,what you're proud of, anything related to you. Maybe creating a collage would be more fun than a list! <figure rend="Discover More About Who You Are and Be Confident Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Know That People Like to See a Unique Positive Person. If you're a little meaner than some people, they might find that funny. If you think you're nicer, people will definitely notice this. You might even inspire others to be nice! <figure rend="Discover More About Who You Are and Be Confident Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Start Saying Positive Affirmations To Yourself. Tell yourself how great you are. Examples: When I believe in myself, so do others, I am my own unique self - special, creative and wonderful. <figure rend="Discover More About Who You Are and Be Confident Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Stay Away From Triggering People or Objects. It important to see and stay away from triggering things. Or talk to a person that might be a hazard to you. <figure rend="Discover More About Who You Are and Be Confident Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Stand Up For Yourself. To stand up for yourself, you don't have to be mean,yell or fight with others. You can be nice but still not let people walk all over you. If you don't stand up for yourself or don't do it in the right way this can affect your confidence. <figure rend="Discover More About Who You Are and Be Confident Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find Inspirational People. This is effective if you want to find who you are. Go searching on YouTube for interviews of famous people whom you like. They might share interesting stories. Taylor Swift is a great one! Also find people that are comfortable in their own skin. Young Leonardo DiCaprio is someone who is comfortable in his own skin. <figure rend="Discover More About Who You Are and Be Confident Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Lastly, Know That You Are NOT Alone. A lot of people put themselves down and into a dark place by thinking they're all alone and no one is experiencing the same thing they are. The truth is, There's billions of people on this Earth! You are not alone. It will help you to know that whatever you do or however you feel you are not alone. <figure rend="Discover More About Who You Are and Be Confident Step 12.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You might not believe yourself when you say positive things about you. This is okay. Say to yourself that you want to and choose to feel happy today.</item>
<item>Speak in a group. After a few times it gets easier.</item>
<item>Acknowledge yourself for even the smallest improvements. Recognize them and know that YOU improved. By doing this you will encourage yourself to keep going.</item>
<item>Search articles or videos on the Internet about confidence or finding oneself.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Feeling anxious most of the time</item>
<item>If you find yourself depressed.</item>
<item>Out of control emotions</item>
<item>Self harm</item>
<item>Eating Disorders or substance abuse occurs</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
