<text id="autogum_whow_doc236" title="Work Out the Payback Period" shortTile="work-out-payback" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-08-04" dateModified="2019-04-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Work-Out-the-Payback-Period" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Work Out the Payback Period</head><p>The "payback period" is an accounting metric used for investment decision making. The metric is very simple, and is designed to estimate how quickly a company will recover a cash investment. When used alone, the payback period can be misleading and oversimplified. However, when analyzed alongside other decision-making metrics, the payback period can be clarifying and helpful. Learning how to work out the payback period for a particular investment or project is a matter of estimating a few cash flows and performing a simple calculation.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Familiarize yourself with the basic computation of the payback period. The payback period specifies how quickly (in years) the cash invested in a particular project will be recovered. For example, consider a project that requires a $100,000 cash outflow immediately, but is expected to bring in an additional $10,000 in cash each year for 20 years. The payback period is 10 years, because after 10 years the original cash outflow has been recovered ($10,000 * 10 = $100,000). <figure rend="Work out the Payback Period Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Note that the payback period calculation does not take the time value of money into account. Future cash flows are not discounted to their present values, but are instead used at face value.</item>
<item>Note also that the payback period only considers cash flows, and does not take into account the effect of depreciation or other non-cash expenses. This, along with the time value exclusion, is a shortcoming of the payback calculation.</item></list></item>
<item>Assess the immediate cash outflow associated with the project in question. This is the amount that must be paid out in cash at the start of a project. <figure rend="Work out the Payback Period Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, consider a company's decision to buy a new copy machine to replace an old one. The machine costs $10,000, and is expected to save $1000 in toner and electricity each year for 8 years, and then save $800 each year for the next 10 years. The immediate cash outflow associated with this project is $10,000.</item></list></item>
<item>Assess the future cash flows expected from a project. These cash flows should be estimated before undertaking any project. Before calculating the payback period, it helps to write these cash flows down on paper in timeline form. In the example above, there are 8 cash flows of $1000, followed by 10 cash flows of $800. <figure rend="Work out the Payback Period Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Sum together the future cash flows until you recover the initial cash investment. Begin adding the cash flows together in chronological order. When the sum is equal to the initial outflow, you have found the payback period. <figure rend="Work out the Payback Period Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>In the example above, after 1 year the company has recovered $1000. After 5 years, the company has recovered $5000. After 8 years, $8000 has been recovered. After 10 years, $9600 has been recovered. After 11 years, $10,400 has been recovered; this amount exceeds the initial investment, so the payback period must be between 10 and 11 years.</item>
<item>The cash flow in year 11 was $800. After $400 of this cash was received, the initial investment of $10,000 had been recovered. This is exactly half of that year's cash flow, so the payback period for this investment is 10.5 years.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>The sample calculations above will also work when expressed in other currencies.</item>
<item>The payback period should always be used in conjunction with other decision-making metrics, such as return on investment (ROI) and internal rate of return (IRR).</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Pencil</item>
<item>Paper</item></list>
</text>
