<text id="autogum_whow_doc172" title="Get Along With Conceptual Thinkers" shortTile="along-conceptual" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2012-02-23" dateModified="2018-09-11" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get-Along-With-Conceptual-Thinkers" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get Along With Conceptual Thinkers</head><p>Ever dealt with someone who cannot put anything in concrete terms? Someone who speaks big words and has a broad image of how the world works, but whenever you try to get specifics out of them, it's like herding cats?</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Take stock of the individual's relevance / importance for your everyday life. The more important the person is the more you should make an effort to relate to them (and them to you). <figure rend="Get Along With Conceptual Thinkers Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Explain things on their terms. For example, is it important to convey to your dad what your college major classes are about? If this matters to you think about "transferable skills" and important lessons you learn - your dad may not care to know about the second derivative problem you failed on the exam if he's a conceptual thinker and not a math-whiz. Do you need to explain to your roommate why you need to be alone on Friday night in the apartment? If he or she is a conceptual thinker they will be confused by all your literal (and detailed) Friday evening plans. Hearing concepts such as "privacy" , "personal space" , "date" , "movie night" may be more important to them than the details of who your date is or what movie you are planning to see. <figure rend="Get Along With Conceptual Thinkers Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you are planning to do something with them, patiently and respectfully of your thinking styles try to get them to commit to concrete steps or specifics about what will you do. For example, if your friend talks about "big life change" plans, get her or him to commit to running once a week with you, start an online dating profile, or pick up the call and inquire about open position about her or his dream job. Conceptual thinkers sometimes have a hard time making their plans concrete because they need to think about details. Help them (and they can help you think in conceptual terms about your business idea, or your career/ life plans). <figure rend="Get Along With Conceptual Thinkers Step 3.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Conceptual and literal thinkers may have a hard time getting along but, with the right communication skills and patience, they can be wonderful life or work partners. Think for example of CEO-COO teams: the CEO is in change of vision, mission, inspiring people; the COO spends time on the nitty-gritty of everyday life. Both are important, and the two have to work together as a team: mission without good execution is bad, and so is execution without good, clear mission.</item>
<item>Check out <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Get_Along_With_Literal_Thinkers">How to Get Along With Literal Thinkers</ref>. You may be one of them in which case conceptual thinkers will make you very uncomfortable with their high-level ideas.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Working with someone of an opposite thinking type can be both a blessing and a curse (and sometimes both at the same time). Learn to recognize and use each other's strengths.</item></list>
</text>
