<text id="autogum_whow_doc095" title="Prepare Your Computer for Gaming Use" shortTile="prepare-computer" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-08-19" dateModified="2018-10-08" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Prepare-Your-Computer-for-Gaming-Use" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Prepare Your Computer for Gaming Use</head><p>Welcome to a brief tutorial on how to squeeze every last bit of performance out of your computer, for gaming. This is going to be strictly software based and will show you ways to fine tune your system to get slight performance increases without having to buy new hardware.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Now the first thing I always like to do when I get my hands on a new system, is to do a clean install of whichever Windows system is newest. So in this case I would make a bootable flash drive using the official Windows 10 ISO, and placing it onto a flash drive using the Rufus application.</item>
<item>Now after the system has had a clean install, with no bloatware or other pre-loaded junk that hardware manufactuers love to load onto our systems. It's always a good idea to run the disk cleanup, as well as defrag and optimize the disk. These programs can be found and launched in the "Windows administrative tools" folder.</item>
<item>Now you can access what we need in this next step by clicking on the little batter icon on the far right side of the Windows taskbar, and select "more power options". This should take you to a control panel window with options for "powersaver mode" and "balanced mode", as well as a hidden third option. To get to this hidden option you will need to click the little dropdown icon on the far right of the window. You'll see an option come down called "High performance mode". Which will typically keep restrictions on your processor state off regardless of the battery life (assuming you have a laptop).</item>
<item>Next up you want to access your control panel and go to System and Security &gt; System &gt; Advanced System Settings in the far left toolbar. This will open up a new, smaller window for system properties. Click the settings button under performance and click the circle choice for "Adjust for best performance", apply and click "OK" to exit the window.</item>
<item>Next thing is the most important. Find out what graphics card you have. It'll let you know where to go in order to get updates for the graphics card driver, which will help your system better take advantage of your video card's resources.</item>
<item>If you're really scrimping for system memory then I would suggest downloading Razer Cortex (formally known as game booster). It not only can dynamically shut down processes when a game launches, but it also has some great tweak tools to adjust system settings that are generally harder to find, which can lead to some more performance increases.</item>
<item>Now, some more steps to take are to clean up your system and just generally do some housekeeping work on it from time to time. Keep as few items on the desktop as possible (I typically only keep the recycle bin icon on my desktop), clean out your downloads folder whenever you can, and organize any files you use constantly. Running the defrag tools periodically won't hurt either.</item>
<item>Make sure ALL of your drivers are up to date. You never understand how important an updated  Wifi driver is until you experience lag spikes and performance issues with any kind of online game.</item>
<item>Make sure you know what is running in the background at all times. Not only is it a good rule of thumb, but also, I can't tell you how many times I've had to quit or alt+tab out of a game to turn off Google Chrome when it was running in the background.</item>
<item>Finally, restart your computer every now and then. Don't just leave the thing going on for days, even weeks on end. I'd say at least once a day just run a restart, it'll let the system dump some loose data and get a fresh start.</item></list>
</text>
