<text id="autogum_whow_doc322" title="Be a Polite Vegan/Vegetarian in Social Situations" shortTile="polite-veganvegetarian" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2006-11-20" dateModified="2017-05-05" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be-a-Polite-Vegan%2FVegetarian-in-Social-Situations" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be a Polite Vegan/Vegetarian in Social Situations</head><p>If you are a  long-time vegetarian or newly-turned vegan, you might find that some social situations can be awkward. However, this little list can help fellow veggies get through such situations.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>As a Guest</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Remember that when the host or hostess of a party does make a special vegetarian dish for you, be sure to thank them at the party, and also send them a note following the party. <figure rend="Be a Polite Vegan_Vegetarian in Social Situations Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Know that when someone offers you a non-vegetarian/non-vegan dish to try, you can simply say, "No Thanks".  Make a point to mention how much you liked a vegetarian dish. <figure rend="Be a Polite Vegan_Vegetarian in Social Situations Step 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Hosting Your Own Event</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Try to make foods which are familiar to most people, such as falafels, hummus, vegetable soups, bean chili, salad, salsa, pasta salad, and vegan versions of common sweet-foods such as cookies and cakes. <figure rend="Be a Polite Vegan_Vegetarian in Social Situations Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Let people bring their own dishes as well. While vegan and vegetarian meals are no different than regular meals (except for the fact that they don't have animal products) and are just as tasty, some people may not care for them or be open to trying them. <figure rend="Be a Polite Vegan_Vegetarian in Social Situations Step 4.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>At a Restaurant</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be polite and patient when asking the waiter about which dishes could be made without animal products. If you do ask a lot of the servers, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Tip_Your_Server_at_a_Restaurant">tip them appropriately.</ref> <figure rend="Be a Polite Vegan_Vegetarian in Social Situations Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Realize that you may have to skimp a bit or make do. If all of their entrees use meat or animal products, it might be easier to just order a sandwich and a few "safe" side dishes instead of insisting they make special accommodations. This is especially wise in busy restaurants. <figure rend="Be a Polite Vegan_Vegetarian in Social Situations Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If at all possible, contact the restaurant <hi rend="italic">before</hi> you arrive and inform them of your special requirements. Most chefs are happy to accommodate any diet, some even see it as a welcome change of pace. However, a little time for planning can mean the difference between passable food and stunning food. <figure rend="Be a Polite Vegan_Vegetarian in Social Situations Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If little is available, be gracious and simply order a drink and some side dishes. Remember that dining out should also be about the company, and raising a fuss can make for an uncomfortable if not ruined dining experience.  <figure rend="Be a Polite Vegan_Vegetarian in Social Situations Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you know you are stuck going to a restaurant that has little to offer, be proactive--eat before you go, and order coffee and dessert, or a soda and salad at the destination.</item>
<item>If you are with a group of co-workers, there often is one "motherly" person in the group who encourages you to order some meat because he or she noticed you didn't. Just <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Smile">smile</ref> and say you are happy with what you ordered.</item>
<item>Most of the time, two or three side dishes will be a satisfying meal</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't feel embarrassed that you're a vegetarian or vegan.</item>
<item>When going out for the day, it's always good to carry a protein bar with you, so if you can't find someplace to have lunch or dinner, you'll at least have some food.</item></list>
</text>
