<text id="autogum_whow_doc485" title="Wear Duck Boots with Jeans" shortTile="wear-duck-boots-jeans" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-09-20" dateModified="2019-10-07" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Wear-Duck-Boots-with-Jeans" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wear Duck Boots with Jeans</head><p><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Wear_Duck_Boots">Duck boots</ref> are a hardy, waterproof style of boot that go great with a variety of outfits. These boots often fit the bill regardless of your daily routine, whether you’re hiking, going to work, or opting for a casual looks. If you’re getting dressed for work, or a job that requires a lot of manual labor, consider rolling up the cuffs of your jeans or tucking them into your boots. For those looking for more casual styles, try slipping on some fun socks, or wearing some ripped jeans for a more rugged look. As you experiment, you’ll find that there’s countless possibilities of how you can wear your duck boots with a pair of jeans!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Dressing for Work</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Try on <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Find_the_Perfect_Jeans_for_You">jeans that fit</ref> without being too baggy. Stay comfortable at work by choosing a pair of jeans that fit you well. Choose a pair of straight jeans that don’t feel too tight on your waist and that give your legs enough breathing room. If your line of work involves a lot of dirt and dust, opt for jeans in a darker color. <figure rend="Wear Duck Boots with Jeans Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Ideally, you shouldn’t need a belt to hold up your jeans.</item></list></item>
<item>Roll up the cuffs of your jeans to tuck inside your boots. Take the bottom edges of your pant legs and roll them up about . Feel free to roll them up more or less as needed—ideally, you want them to be snug against the top edge of your duck boots. Whenever you go to work, make sure that you’re wearing socks that cover your ankles so all your skin is protected. <figure rend="Wear Duck Boots with Jeans Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This is a great fix if your jeans are a bit too long around the ankle.</item></list></item>
<item>Tuck your jeans around your duck boots as an alternative. If your jeans are a perfect fit for your height, you might not want to roll up the cuffs that much. In this case, take the edges of your jeans and tuck them into your duck boots. Pinch and push in the denim around your ankle so that it fits snugly in the boot and looks even on both sides. <figure rend="Wear Duck Boots with Jeans Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This might be easier to accomplish with thinner socks.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Creating a Casual Outfit</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Pair your boots with a nice blazer to give off an equestrian vibe. Wear your jeans with a nice top and blazer so you look like you’re about to go for a ride. Even if your duck boots aren’t as tall as traditional riding boots, feel free to tuck the edges of your jeans into the boots to give off a polished look. If you don’t want to worry about tucking in any material, opt for skinny jeans instead. <figure rend="Wear Duck Boots with Jeans Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you actually are going for a ride, make sure you choose jeans that fit your body comfortably and aren’t too tight.</item></list></item>
<item>Pair your jeans and boots with a neutral top. Go for a casual vibe by including more neutral tones in your outfit. Keep in mind that many duck boots consist of dark, earthy tones like tan and dark brown. With this in mind, set other elements of your outfit to match the tones in your boots. You can really tie your ensemble together with a tan or dark brown top. <figure rend="Wear Duck Boots with Jeans Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try wearing a neutral-toned jacket or coat with your outfit as well!</item></list></item>
<item>Roll up your jeans to make your socks visible. Take the bottom edges of your jeans and roll them up to form about a  cuff. Beneath your jeans, wear some long, fuzzy socks that you want to show off. If you’re feeling more traditional, opt for socks with solid tones and traditional patterns, like stripes and argyle. <figure rend="Wear Duck Boots with Jeans Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you want to make your look funkier, try wearing fuzzy socks, or socks with cute and fun patterns!</item></list></item>
<item>Opt for <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Rip_Your_Own_Jeans">ripped jeans</ref> to give off a rugged vibe. Add a pair of jeans to your outfit that has some rips and tears around different spots, like the knees and thighs. If your jeans aren’t already ripped, try fraying some areas of your jeans with any grit of sandpaper. For less obvious distress marks, try going over certain spots on your jeans with the edge of a bobby pin. <figure rend="Wear Duck Boots with Jeans Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you want a more dramatic look, feel free to cut into your jeans with a pair of scissors.</item></list></item>
<item>Pull your jeans over the edge of your boots for a classy look. Go for a no-nonsense style by tucking the edges of your boots into your jeans. If you don’t want your duck boots to be the focal point of your outfit, this is a great option to try. Try pairing this look with a polo or dress shirt to finish off the outfit. <figure rend="Wear Duck Boots with Jeans Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can dress this style up or down. If you’d prefer to look more casual, vie for a flannel or plaid shirt instead.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
