<text id="autogum_whow_doc125" title="Change Your Apple ID" shortTile="change-apple-id" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2013-02-05" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Change-Your-Apple-ID" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Change Your Apple ID</head><p>This wikiHow teaches you how to change the email address that you use to sign in to iCloud, the iTunes Store, and across Apple devices and services. If your Apple ID ends in @mac.com, @me.com, or @iCloud.com, it cannot be changed.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Using a Web Browser</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Sign out of Apple ID. Do so on all devices and services, such as iCloud and iTunes, that you're signed into with your current Apple ID. <figure rend="Change Your Apple ID Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Go to <ref target="https://appleid.apple.com">the Apple ID website</ref>. Do so by clicking the link to the left or by typing appleid.apple.com in the search field of any Internet-connected Web browser. <figure rend="Change Your Apple ID Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Enter your current Apple ID and password in the labeled fields. <figure rend="Change Your Apple ID Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on or tap ➲. It's on the right side of the "Password" field. <figure rend="Change Your Apple ID Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you have two-step verification enabled, tap or click on "Allow" on another device, then enter the six-digit code in the spaces on the screen.</item></list></item>
<item>Click on or tap . It's a blue link on the right side of the screen under the "Account" section. <figure rend="Change Your Apple ID Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on or tap . It's next to the email address under the "APPLE ID" section at the top of the window. <figure rend="Change Your Apple ID Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If your Apple ID ends in @mac.com, @me.com, or @iCloud.com, you will not see this option.</item></list></item>
<item>Enter a new email address. Use an address that's neither already associated with an Apple ID nor likely to change soon. <figure rend="Change Your Apple ID Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If prompted, answer the security questions you set up with your Apple ID.</item></list></item>
<item>Click on or tap . Apple will send an email with a verification code to your new email address. <figure rend="Change Your Apple ID Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The button may read <hi rend="bold">Continue</hi>, depending on the browser you're using.</item></list></item>
<item>Check your email. Look for the message sent by Apple. <figure rend="Change Your Apple ID Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Enter the verification code. Type the code from the email message in the spaces that appear in the browser window. <figure rend="Change Your Apple ID Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Sign in with your new Apple ID. You can now sign back in to your devices and Apple services with your new Apple ID. <figure rend="Change Your Apple ID Step 11 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you have two-step verification enabled, tap or click on "Allow" on another device, then enter the six-digit code in the spaces on the screen.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Using iPhone or iPad Running iOS 10.3</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Sign out of Apple ID. Do so on all devices and services, such as iCloud and iTunes, that you're signed into with your current Apple ID, EXCEPT the device you're using to change your Apple ID. <figure rend="Change Your Apple ID Step 12 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Open Settings. It's a gray app with gears (⚙️) that's typically located on your home screen. <figure rend="Change Your Apple ID Step 13 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tap your Apple ID. It's the section at the top of the screen that contains your name and image, if you've added one. <figure rend="Change Your Apple ID Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tap . It's at the top of the first section. <figure rend="Change Your Apple ID Step 15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tap . It's a blue link on the right side of the screen next to "REACHABLE AT." <figure rend="Change Your Apple ID Step 16.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Swipe left on your current Apple ID. It's the first email address in the list, with the words "Apple ID" in small text just below it. <figure rend="Change Your Apple ID Step 17.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>On some devices, you may need to tap a "<hi rend="bold">-</hi>" next to the email address rather than swiping left.</item>
<item>If your Apple ID ends in @mac.com, @me.com, or @iCloud.com, you will not be able to swipe left.</item></list></item>
<item>Tap . It's a red button to the right of your Apple ID. <figure rend="Change Your Apple ID Step 18.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tap . You'll be prompted to choose another email address already associated with your Apple ID, if there is one, or to enter a new email address. <figure rend="Change Your Apple ID Step 19.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Enter a new email address. Use an address that's neither already associated with an Apple ID nor likely to change soon. <figure rend="Change Your Apple ID Step 20.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If prompted, answer the security questions you set up with your Apple ID or your Apple ID password.</item></list></item>
<item>Click on . Apple will send an email with a verification code to your new email address. <figure rend="Change Your Apple ID Step 21.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Check your email. Look for the message sent by Apple. <figure rend="Change Your Apple ID Step 22.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Enter the verification code. Type the code from the email message in the spaces that appear on your device's screen. <figure rend="Change Your Apple ID Step 23.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Sign in with your new Apple ID. You can now sign back in to your devices and Apple services with your new Apple ID. <figure rend="Change Your Apple ID Step 24.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you have two-step verification enabled, tap or click on "Allow" on another device, then enter the six-digit code in the spaces on the screen.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Apple recommends you use your primary email address for your Apple ID.</item></list>
</text>
