<text id="autogum_whow_doc497" title="Dress Appropriately" shortTile="dress-appropriately" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2007-07-31" dateModified="2018-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Dress-Appropriately" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Dress Appropriately</head><p>Sometimes you need to dress nicely. Sometimes you don't. But all the time, you need to dress in a way that compliments you and others.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Organize your closet. Fold your clothes neatly, hang up your dresses and jeans, and sort shirts and shorts into drawers or baskets. <figure rend="Dress Appropriately Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find out where you are going. You don't want to go to the grocery store in your favorite Sunday clothes, and you probably wouldn't like to go to a fancy restaurant in your PJ's. <figure rend="Dress Appropriately Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pick out an outfit. First, choose a shirt or blouse. Then find a skirt or pants to go with it. Picking the top first helps you picture the entire outfit better. <figure rend="Dress Appropriately Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Accessorize! Jewelry is very important to the entire appearance, since it ties the whole outfit together and adds a focal point. Also, you should make sure that if you are going to carry a handbag or purse, be sure that it does not contrast too much. With shoes, be sure that they are comfortable and will not attract too much attention. <figure rend="Dress Appropriately Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Apply makeup right before leaving. Don't put on too much- you shouldn't want to appear fake. You don't want it to look like you have makeup on.Less is best sometimes especially when you are older and start to have some wrinkles. <figure rend="Dress Appropriately Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Smile and be kind. A person is only as good as her personality, and you don't want people to think that you are sour or unkind. <figure rend="Dress Appropriately Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Check some style websites and see what the different age groups are wearing.  Copy it or as close as you can.  Like what you wear and be comfortable in your cloths. <figure rend="Dress Appropriately Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Dress yourself nicely wherever you go. People notice if you don't take care of yourself, and when you do, chances are that others will be more open to meeting and talking to you.</item>
<item>Be confident! A sparkling smile is an important part of any outfit.</item>
<item>Look people in the eye when meeting them or speaking to them, and always offer your hand to shake before and after introducing yourself.</item>
<item>Always be friendly to people. Don't insult them when talking to them. Also, keep eye contact when they are speaking to you. It shows that you are paying attention and it says, "I respect your values and opinions."</item>
<item>Always dress as if you were going to meet the love of your life!</item>
<item>Never go out in sweat pants (unless to the gym) or pj's.</item>
<item>Always wear clean and pressed clothing. (dirty and wrinkled says something about you):{</item>
<item>Wear good shoes, clean and in good repair - good heels.</item>
<item>Walk talk and confidently.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Keep yourself clean and well groomed. Also, <hi rend="bold">brush your teeth.</hi> Bad breath is not a good way to have people think of you.</item>
<item>If someone insults you, don't insult them back. Laugh it off.</item>
<item>Don't wear clothes that show too much cleavage. People will consider you to have low values and will think you are a slut.</item></list>
</text>
