<text id="autogum_whow_doc306" title="Store Cooked Food" shortTile="store-cooked-food" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2017-07-12" dateModified="2017-07-27" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Store-Cooked-Food" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Store Cooked Food</head><p>Food preparation is somewhat a tough task. There is always an element of challenge available the time of food preparation considering how advanced kitchen appliance you may have how proficient the cooking techniques may be, or how easy the recipe might be. Moreover, the task is not after preparing the food because you have to store the food for the further meal. There are many innovations available to store the foods, as an example Refrigerator.   Food storage processes have also gone through an evolution over the century. With the invention of refrigerators, people can breathe a sigh of relief as they made it too easy to store any food easily inside them. Moreover, deep freezers were also introduced primarily for bulk storage of food. Ever thought about storing the food without a refrigerator? Do you now how to store cooked food properly. Here you will come to know about storing the foods in many ways.Well, every innovation that arrives on the market brings some new set of problems which are hard to deal. Refrigeration and food storage also have some common issues where food turns deteriorate, or it no longer remains the same as new. In the article, we are going to address you to some of the most common food storage problems. We will also advise some tips and tricks focusing on frozen storage which will help you store the food for a longer period without losing the flavor of the food or rotting it.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">== Wrap your Food</hi>
<hi rend="bold"> ==</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Wrapping/Covering is one of the most proficient food storage techniques most widely used around the globe. This method is suitable for travelers who cannot carry any other food storage with them. The main thing while storing food is to preserve the moisture in the food without letting the air get to it. By wrapping the food, you can hold the moisture in it and also the food will remain fresh for an extended period.So, what material should you use wrap food? Well, there are many food wrappers available these days. Aluminum foil is the best material to wrap and store food while traveling. If you wish to store your food in freezers, the best options are freezer storage bags, plastic wraps and plastic coated freezer paper.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">== Store Foods in Plastic Materials</hi>
<hi rend="bold"> ==</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you want to store foods for eating it later you have to use plastic box or bags. When you are intending to store cooked foods like meat fish or desserts you should use plastic boxes and bags to wrap it over.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Freezing Cooked Poultry and Meat</hi>
</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Poultry and meat are the most troublesome ingredients to store. Cooked meat contains more content of moisture than the raw meat, so it is important to preserve the moisture. For storing cooked meat and poultry in a freezer, the best technique is to wrap the meat tightly in a plastic wrapper/aluminum foil or keep it in a plastic box. Make sure to debone the meat and keep it in larger pieces before wrapping. Also, you should ensure that the air cannot get into the food.  After wrapping, immediately store the food in zero degrees Fahrenheit.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">Type of meat you should freeze:</hi>
</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can freeze almost all kinds of meat. People sometimes ask whether they can freeze tenderized meat or not. As tenderizing comes into effect while cooking meat, it can be frozen. However, you cannot store or freeze canned meat because</item></list>
<p>•	Most canned foods have liquids inside them, and seals of the can prone to breakage while you freeze it.
•	Canned items are covered with moisture.Hence, the food inside a can is already stored, so there is no need to store a can full of foods. You can keep it in a cool place, on your shelf or in the refrigerator in a normal cooling mode.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold"> Freezing Time:</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>One common issue about storing the food is freezing time. Well, there is no such limit regarding how long you should store/ freeze the foods in a refrigerator. But due to dehydration, the food may lose somewhat its flavor. Wrapping your foods well can keep the flavor of the foods for a long time.  If you wrap the food well it may remain fresh for years or two.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">Nutrients Preservation:</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>There is another primary objective of food storage and it is to preserve the nutrients of food. Hence, food storage addresses to the requirement very well. While you freeze the food, it does not lose the nutrients. Sometimes, the food only loses the flavor. However, the protein content of meat or poultry slightly reduces while freezing. But it only occurs if you store it crossing the limited time of 9 months.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">Storing Food In a pressure cooker:</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Modern day pressure cookers are like hotpot. After cooking your dish, you can also store it in a pressure cooker. If you cook large dishes like a roast with vegetables, fish, meat dishes, and chicken, then you may want to store it overnight and have the leftovers the next day. As the <ref target="http://www.bestelectricpressurecooker.net/">Best Electric Pressure Cooker</ref> can keep the food warm even after 5 hours of cooking you can easily store the food in it.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Freezer Burns is the process where the surface of the food dries off in a while freezing. In case you forget to cover your food before storing it in the freezer, there can be high chances of freezer burns to your food. It makes food dehydrated, and the dehydrated spot is left dry, tasteless and affects the quality of food.   Freezer burns happen because insufficient covering allows the air to get to the food. Leaked plastic bags are also responsible for freezer burn. Freezer burns leave brownish gray spots on foods, and the food becomes dry. However, it damages the food to an extent where the food no longer remains eatable.</item></list>
</text>
