<text id="autogum_whow_doc603" title="Find Your Calling in Life" shortTile="find-calling-life" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2016-02-22" dateModified="2018-10-04" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Find-Your-Calling-in-Life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Find Your Calling in Life</head><p>We all search for our calling, even though we speak it in It our heads we are still looking for it. It may be different for us all. It could be loosing weight for one and maybe gaining it after some terrible disease for another. I may be being a motivational speaker for one and practising meditation in an alone place for another. Here you will get a little direction to what your must do, to find yours.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Look into the mirror.</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><list type="unordered"><item>Look into the mirror and you will see someone who has come here for a purpose.</item>
<item>You are witnessing the one who has the potential to change the world, to make a difference here and you could be starting from this very moment.</item>
<item>You can make this day count, you can make your life count and it begins today.</item>
<item>Smile... something great is upcoming</item></list></item></list>
<head>Pick up a diary.</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><list type="unordered"><item>Leave the initial few pages blank and write down point by point, all you want to "BE".</item>
<item>All you want to have may have a very long list but all you want to be would sum up in around 2 pages.</item>
<item>You might want to be funny, charming, loved, confidant, intelligent, puntual, preety, stylish, polite, fit, brave.</item>
<item>Not everybody wants the same things.</item>
<item>Keep this list safe, because now you have met yourself and expressed what you want to be.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Start planning out.</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><list type="unordered"><item>These diaries are going to be your friend for life if you let them be.</item>
<item>You now have an idea of what you want to become, so start looking up in books, internet, right people from whom you will get ideas so that you can map out your day in such a manner that you start to approach your targets in small but meaningful steps each day.</item>
<item>Once you are done with the plan execute it for a week.</item>
<item>See how it goes, then make the necessary changes.</item>
<item>Your week could have stuff planned like 30 min of cardio+ 1 hr reading a motivational book+ 15 min of gratitude(V.V.Important)+8hours of work+1 hour of playing the piano/cooking/vocabulary/Enhancing your body language skills/Lerning about dresses and the list goes on.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Calling involves being of value.</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><list type="unordered"><item>What you possibly might have skipped out of your list would be making your life more meaningful. In order to get, give..</item>
<item>The people who found their purpose had two things in common, one they were grateful and values their lives and second they gave something back to the world.</item>
<item>Mother teresa, Oprah Winfrey, Anjelina Jolie, Nelson Mandela, Abraham Lincon, they all has this in common and so can you.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Discipline is the key to achieve it.</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><list type="unordered"><item>It may look hard initially when you begin the journey.</item>
<item>you might wanna just stop and take the long rest, but be disciplined with your efforts and flexible with your methods.</item>
<item>You have to know, that with the effort that you are looking for your calling in life, it i looking for you too.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Try this for a month</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><list type="unordered"><item>Plan your days, set up weekly tasks and try this for a month.</item>
<item>You will get to know yourself better, you will become better and stronger with each step you take.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
