<text id="autogum_whow_doc303" title="Protect Food While Camping" shortTile="protect-food-camping" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-09-05" dateModified="2019-06-10" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Protect-Food-While-Camping" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Protect Food While Camping</head><p>Camping can be a fun and rewarding experience, as long as forest creatures don't ruin the trip by getting into your supplies. Learning how to protect food while camping, keeping it safe from predators big and small, can keep your trip from taking a turn for the worse.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Arrange your campsite properly. <figure rend="Protect Food While Camping Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Store food away from any tents in your campsite. Storing food in your tent will attract animals to your sleeping area, and some may go in to predatory mode in trying to access the food you have. This is especially critical in camping areas where bears may be present.</item>
<item>Cook and store food at least  away from your camping area. Again, food should be prepared and stored in an area that won't attract animals to the place you are sleeping.</item></list></item>
<item>Store your food and garbage in your car trunk. Only if you have easy access to your car. Store food away whenever you are not actively preparing or consuming it. This will help keep animals from following the scent of food to your campsite, and provides a barrier they are unable to get through. Even coolers should go in the trunk, as animals like raccoons can generally figure out how to break in. <figure rend="Protect Food While Camping Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep food in animal-proof containers and positions when a car is not available. <figure rend="Protect Food While Camping Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Some hike-in campsites have food storage boxes available. This is generally a small wooden box with a latching or locking lid that is built to keep animals away from your food. Make sure the lid is completely secured at all times, and that there are no cracks between the lid and the box. Small animals, such as mice and bugs can squeeze through very small openings and ruin your food. Also, properly locking the box is important, as animals that live near campgrounds are often very adept at breaking into human contraptions.</item>
<item>If no food box is available, you'll need to store your food another way to keep it safe. One method is to put it in a canvas or nylon bag and hoist it up onto a tree branch where it can hang in a place that animals can't reach it. Your food should be hung at least  off the ground,  out on the branch, and a few feet below the branch. You can do this by attaching the rope to a sock filled with rocks, or another heavy object that you can throw, then toss it over a high, sturdy branch. Tie the other end to your food bag and hoist it up. Your food should be hung at least  off the ground,  out on the branch, and a few feet below the branch. Once the food is hanging at an appropriate height, tie the end in your hands securely to the tree trunk.</item></list></item>
<item>Pack out what you packed in. Remember to keep garbage safe the same way you keep food safe. Animals will be attracted to your garbage as well as your food, so minimize temptation in order to keep your food safe. When you are draining your dishwater, strain it first and toss food particles in with your trash. Make sure to dump dishwater at least  from your sleeping area and the area where you are keeping your food, because the smell might also attract animals. <figure rend="Protect Food While Camping Step 4.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If a racoon does come to your campsite such as when you are around a campfire, don't scare the racoon off right away (if you don't have food out). Let them explore and see that you don't have any food. The racoon will then realize that you don't have anything and will stay away.</item></list>
</text>
