<text id="autogum_whow_doc507" title="Get Organized over the Summer" shortTile="organized-over-summer" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2008-06-14" dateModified="2018-12-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get-Organized-over-the-Summer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get Organized over the Summer</head><p>The summer is a great time of the year to become organized. Becoming organized may be easier said than done, but this article  should help you to organize your lifestyle in an easy way.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Decide what needs to be organized. Take a couple of days to create a big list of things you need to become more organized at.  <figure rend="Get Organized over the Summer Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Ask your family members and friends for some tips on what to put on this list so you can have absolutely everything written down.</item>
<item>If you can't think of everything right away, go ahead and take a couple of hours for a break. When you come back to the list after having a break, you will probably find yourself capable of listing new ways of organizing.</item>
<item>Keep in mind that if your handwriting is very sloppy or hard to read, you may go ahead and type the list on a computer if you have the access to one.</item></list></item>
<item>Organize the small things first. Do you need to help your children organize their toys? Try to do things similar to that concept first. These should be the easy things on your list that only take a small amount of time to accomplish.  <figure rend="Get Organized over the Summer Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If the task will take over five hours to do, try to do that task later on in the summer.</item></list></item>
<item>Move on to the big tasks. After all of the small tasks have been completed, it is time to move on to bigger tasks. These tasks will definitely take up more time, and if you can only accomplish one task a day, that is fine. Your goal should be to try to accomplish at least five big tasks a week until you are finished. <figure rend="Get Organized over the Summer Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do a major cleaning of your house. Go through all of your drawers, closets, etc. to make sure you are positive of where everything is. Donate the things you don't need or use anymore.  <figure rend="Get Organized over the Summer Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try to avoid putting random objects that don't belong together in one area, as this will be confusing when you are looking for something. Instead, try categorizing all of the items into separate containers based on what they do. For example, keep all of your cleaning supplies (broom, dust pans, etc.) in one closet of your house.</item></list></item>
<item>Have your schedule figured out. Besides doing the organizing of your home, you will also need to organize your life on a daily basis. Try not to plan too far ahead when doing this, though, for you probably do not know what events will be occurring in the winter. Instead, plan your schedule week by week in a planner or on a calendar.  <figure rend="Get Organized over the Summer Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure to write down where the event will be taking place, the time of the event, what days the events are on, and other important information.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't worry about rushing this process. If you decide to hurry through everything, you will regret it when things are still a mess later on.</item></list>
</text>
