<text id="autogum_whow_doc522" title="Become an Avon Sales Consultant" shortTile="become-avon-sales" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2012-04-25" dateModified="2019-06-19" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Become-an-Avon-Sales-Consultant" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Become an Avon Sales Consultant</head><p>If you have a passion for cosmetics and sales, then becoming an Avon representative might be for you. To become a representative or obtain more information about becoming one, first complete an application online. Through this application, a rep in your area will get in touch with you to set up a meeting. Use this meeting to ask your rep questions that you have about setting up a business with Avon. Once you have been appointed, you will have access to brochures, samples, and sales and training tools. Then, begin selling Avon products by setting up your online store, handing out brochures, and by hosting an Avon “get together.” </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Signing Up</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Complete the application. In order to find out more information about becoming a representative for Avon you will need to fill out the application. Fill out the application on Avon's website. Avon has branches in different countries, so make sure you are on the website for your specific country when filling out the application. You will not be charged an application fee until you place your first order. In other words, it is free to sign-up. <figure rend="Become an Avon Sales Consultant Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The application fee is $15 in the U.S. and 16 Euros in the U.K.</item>
<item>You will need to fill out your name, address, contact information, and your preferred type of communication.</item>
<item>If you do not have Internet access, contact Avon’s customer service at 1-800-367-2866.</item></list></item>
<item>Meet with an area manager. Once you have filled out the application, a local area manager will contact you. Arrange a meeting with your area manager. Your manager will explain how Avon works, as well as the materials you will receive and need to purchase to get started. <figure rend="Become an Avon Sales Consultant Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Your manager will explain that you can receive up to 50 percent on the products you sell.</item></list></item>
<item>Ask questions. Ask about earning potential, work hours, and the most effective methods and tools for selling products, i.e., the online website, apps, "get togethers," and brochures. You may also want to ask about turnover rates, and how to cancel your application if you decide Avon isn’t for you. <figure rend="Become an Avon Sales Consultant Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are interested in becoming a sales leader, use this time to express your interest. As a sales leader you will have a team of members that you appoint and mentor.</item></list></item>
<item>Register online. After you are appointed to be a representative, you will need to register on the Representative website online. This is where you will be able to place your fist order. Once you are registered you will also receive brochures for your first two campaigns (20), samples, and sales tools. The sales tools include an appointment pack, a calling book, customer order slips, and your own online store. <figure rend="Become an Avon Sales Consultant Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You will have access to training tools such as guides and tutorials, as well.</item>
<item>You will not be charged the application fee until you complete your first order.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Finding Support</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Go to a local meeting. For every campaign, meetings are held locally. At these meetings you will be able to meet novice and experienced representatives. Top sellers and sales leaders also speak at these meetings. These meetings are a great way to find local support. <figure rend="Become an Avon Sales Consultant Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Ask experienced representatives about the methods and tools that produce the most sales, as well as other tactics they use to promote and find more business.</item>
<item>For example, "How has the website and the mobile app affected your sales? Have they increased or have they remained the same?"</item></list></item>
<item>Find support online. Through “Avon Beauty Connects”, you can find support online. Through this forum, experienced representatives share tips on how to build an Avon business. The forum also allows new representatives to ask specific questions and to ask for advice. <figure rend="Become an Avon Sales Consultant Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, ask experienced representatives, "How have you managed to keep your customers?" or "What tactics do you use to keep customers interested, as well as find new customers?"</item>
<item>You can also find online training in the “My Learning Zone” in your portal. It is filled with personalized training modules that will help you develop your skills at every phase in the process of becoming a representative.</item></list></item>
<item>Download the guide. Avon has developed a free guide for representatives, as well as for those who are still considering becoming a representative. Top experts in the industry made the guide. The guide discusses self awareness, self confidence, and self management; tools that are crucial to becoming a successful sales representative. <figure rend="Become an Avon Sales Consultant Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Find a copy of the guide here: <ref target="https://www.avon.uk.com/help-support">https://www.avon.uk.com/help-support</ref>.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Selling Avon Products</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Set-up your online store. Representatives are given their own online store called “My Avon Store.” You can set up your online store in a few easy steps by following the instructions online. Online stores are great because they allow your customers to shop from you online. <figure rend="Become an Avon Sales Consultant Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Create business cards that contain your information, including your website, when you are marketing your business.</item>
<item>You can also choose to opt in to Avon's mobile phone app, Avon Brochure. This app connects you to new customers who are looking for a representative in your area.</item></list></item>
<item>Hand out brochures. Every three weeks Avon produces a new brochure. The brochures are filled with deals, promotions, and new products. Therefore, they are a great way to market your business. <figure rend="Become an Avon Sales Consultant Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Carry brochures with you at all times so you can hand them out to your friends, family members, and customers (old and new).</item></list></item>
<item>Host an Avon get together Another great way to market your business is to host an Avon "get together" at your house. You will be given brochures, samples, and information on new products to pass out to your guests. Invite friends, family members, and existing customers. <figure rend="Become an Avon Sales Consultant Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>To create new customers and contacts, ask your guests to bring along one new person to the event.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
