<text id="autogum_whow_doc556" title="Become a Veterinary Anatomist" shortTile="become-veterinary" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-04-16" dateModified="2019-03-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Become-a-Veterinary-Anatomist" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Become a Veterinary Anatomist</head><p>Veterinary anatomy is a specialized field of veterinary science that studies the biological structure and the different systems that make up an animal's body.  Veterinary anatomists can apply their skills by helping animals at a veterinary clinic, or by advancing the field of veterinary medicine in a laboratory.  Preparing for a career in veterinary anatomy can be a long process; study science and veterinary medicine, work with animals, meet other veterinary anatomists, and you'll be able to start your career in the field of veterinary anatomy.  </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Studying to be a Veterinary Anatomist</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Study science and math in high school.  You can start preparing for a career as a veterinary anatomist in high school.  Taking classes in biology, anatomy, and chemistry is a great way to prepare for a career in the veterinary field.  Math and statistics classes will also be very helpful if you want to do veterinary research. <figure rend="Become a Veterinary Anatomist Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take pre-requisite classes as an undergraduate student. Veterinary anatomists, like all veterinarians, must go through many years of education before they can be licensed to practice medicine or perform research in a lab.  Take math, biology, chemistry, and anatomy classes while completing a bachelor's degree to fulfill the prerequisite requirements for enrolling in veterinary medical schools. <figure rend="Become a Veterinary Anatomist Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Some colleges offer pre-veterinary tracks for undergraduate students. Enrolling in a school with a pre-veterinary track will help you make sure that you take all of the pre-requisite classes.</item>
<item>Majoring in biology, chemistry, or anatomy can be helpful, but it is not required for attending veterinary school.</item></list></item>
<item>Specialize in veterinary science for your master's degree.  Some veterinary schools require students to have a master's degree before enrolling to get their doctoral degree.  A master's degree might not be necessary for the school you want to attend, but earning a Master's in Veterinary Science will give you plenty of helpful knowledge and experience for your future as a veterinary anatomist. <figure rend="Become a Veterinary Anatomist Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Enroll in an accredited school of veterinary medicine.  Earning a Doctorate of Veterinary Medicine is the last step in a veterinarian's education.  Research accredited universities, learn about the funding and financial aid those schools provide, understand their academic requirements, and learn about the faculty members who teach at that school. <figure rend="Become a Veterinary Anatomist Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Apply to schools that employ well-known veterinary anatomists to have the opportunity to learn from them.</item>
<item>Unlike medical schools, it is unusual for schools of veterinary medicine to offer formal tracks or specialties to students.</item>
<item>Some schools offer dual Ph.D./DVM programs where students graduate with a DVM and Ph.D. in a related veterinary science.  Having a Ph.D. in addition to your DVM will provide you with a great background for a career in veterinary research.</item></list></item>
<item>Earn your license to practice as a veterinarian. After you graduate, you must meet licensing and certification requirements in order to practice as a veterinarian. Each state has its own rules and regulations. File the appropriate paperwork and take any required exams, and soon you can enter the veterinary workforce. <figure rend="Become a Veterinary Anatomist Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Developing the Skills to Be a Veterinary Anatomist</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find opportunities to work with animals. Volunteer with local animal shelters, zoos, and veterinary clinics, or find a job at a local pet store.  Earning experience with animals of all shapes and sizes will help you decide if you would like to work with animals in a clinical setting, or if you would prefer to do research. <figure rend="Become a Veterinary Anatomist Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Colleges and veterinary schools both appreciate candidates who have volunteering experience. Start volunteering as soon as possible, and continue volunteering through college and veterinary school if you find the time.</item></list></item>
<item>Complete an internship or externship with a veterinarian or with a laboratory.  Applying to do an internship or an externship is a great way to earn first-hand experience in a veterinarian's office or a laboratory. Many students get their first opportunity to work in a professional setting through an internship or externship, and they are a great way to get to know people who work in your chosen field. <figure rend="Become a Veterinary Anatomist Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Continue your education in veterinary anatomy. Veterinary anatomy is an emergent field. To succeed in it, you will need to know the latest developments in veterinary science. Attend conferences, read research journals, and talk with other veterinary anatomists to learn more about your field. <figure rend="Become a Veterinary Anatomist Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The American Veterinary Medical Associations requires all members to participate in a continuing education program.Take advantage of continuing education classes that can teach you more about veterinary anatomy.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Finding a Job as a Veterinary Anatomist</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Create a professional and distinctive resume.  While you search for a job as a veterinary anatomist, make yourself stand out from your peers.  Create a strong, professional resume that clearly displays your education and describes your previous work experience.  Include your experience working with other scientists and veterinarians as well as your experience working with animals. <figure rend="Become a Veterinary Anatomist Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Network with other veterinary anatomists. Meeting other veterinary anatomists is a great way to learn more about your field, share information, and make professional contacts. <figure rend="Become a Veterinary Anatomist Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Join the American or the World Association of Veterinary Anatomists.  These groups host conferences, share exciting scientific developments in veterinary anatomy and provide information about job openings to their members. </item>
<item>Join online discussion groups and veterinary forums to meet and communicate with other veterinary anatomists.</item></list></item>
<item>Search for open positions at laboratories, universities, and with private companies.  Veterinary anatomy is a specialized field, and you may struggle to find open positions through a general job-searching website.  Be specific in your job search by look for open positions at veterinarian's offices and at places that perform research that benefits animals. <figure rend="Become a Veterinary Anatomist Step 11.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can find jobs openings through the American Medical Veterinary Association.</item>
<item>If you have specialized in veterinary anatomy research, look for openings with research universities, or with private companies that specialize in creating products like medicine, food, or toys for animals.</item>
<item>If you would like to teach veterinary anatomy to others, search for open positions at schools of veterinary medicine.</item></list></item>
<item>Prepare to talk about your experience with veterinary anatomy during job interviews. Be prepared to talk about your previous experience and education with the people who are conducting your interview.  Expect to explain why you decided to study veterinary anatomy, the subjects you researched while in school, and your previous experience working with animals. <figure rend="Become a Veterinary Anatomist Step 12.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be prepared to explain the work experience and educational opportunities that you included on your resume.</item>
<item>Practice answering these questions before your interview to develop well-rounded, honest answers and to calm your pre-interview jitters.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
