<text id="autogum_whow_doc361" title="Stargaze Without a Telescope" shortTile="stargaze-without" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-03-26" dateModified="2018-05-15" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Stargaze-Without-a-Telescope" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Stargaze Without a Telescope</head><p>Not everyone has, or wants to use, a telescope for stargazing. It's still fine to watch the stars as the ancients did it, by simply looking up and recognizing familiar constellations.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Decide what you want to look at. You may have heard about it from a friend, or read about it, or found it on the internet. <figure rend="Stargaze Without a Telescope Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Check if the constellation or star is bright enough. For this, you need to know your target's magnitude. Bigger magnitude = dimmer object. To see if it's bright enough, identify the five dimmest stars in the sky that you can see without straining your eyes. Take an average of their magnitudes. If the magnitude of your target is less than this average value, then you will be able to see it. Anything with a magnitude of less than 1.5, you will definitely be able to see, unless you have extreme light pollution. Anything more than about 6 cannot be seen from anywhere except under exceptional circumstances. <figure rend="Stargaze Without a Telescope Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find the star or constellation on a star map. You need to know where it is to be able to see it. Also find a few signposts - bright objects that you can use to locate your target. <figure rend="Stargaze Without a Telescope Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, Orion's belt is a signpost to a star called Procyon. Star maps can be accessed online, or can be bought from decent bookstores.</item></list></item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Use stargazing app on mobile phones</hi>. Apps are very helpful to search for what is in the night sky with the timing . Most of the app provided are Paid .One of the best app is Stellarium[ <ref target="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.noctuasoftware.stellarium&amp;hl=en">https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.noctuasoftware.stellarium&amp;hl=en</ref>]</item>
<item>Wrap up and keep warm. It can get very cold outside at night, even in summer. Take a deckchair or recliner with you. You're going to be looking up at the sky, so if you can orient yourself so that you are facing the sky without bending your neck, it can help avoid a stiff neck. Alternatively, you can get a stiff neck and take two aspirin when you get back inside. <figure rend="Stargaze Without a Telescope Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get to a place where you can see your target. This may be your back garden, your roof, or a dark site way out in the countryside. You can get the best views from dark sites, but they can be a bit tricky to get to. <figure rend="Stargaze Without a Telescope Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wait for ten minutes so that you can see better. Don't look at any light sources or it will ruin your night vision. Use your signposts to locate your target. Enjoy! <figure rend="Stargaze Without a Telescope Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>It is recommended that you choose four or five targets for one night, so you can move on to another after you get bored.</item>
<item>Stargazing with naked eyes need lot of patience so give yourself time before fed up.</item>
<item>Search the internet to know in which class your city falls in context of light pollution this will help you know which celestial bodies will be easily seen with naked eyes.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Astronomical observations always look better in photos than in reality. Ever seen that cool photo of the Andromeda galaxy? Know what it looks like without a telescope? A little grey fuzzy patch, that's what.</item>
<item>Never look at the Sun. It will burn your eyes out.</item></list>
</text>
