<text id="autogum_whow_doc381" title="Melt Glue Sticks" shortTile="melt-glue-sticks" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-07-09" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Melt-Glue-Sticks" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Melt Glue Sticks</head><p>Glue sticks can be melted down for a number of applications. Whether used in crafts, manufacturing, packaging, fashion, or in any other creative function, glue sticks are a cheap and easy to come by product. All-purpose or school glue sticks and hot glue gun sticks can both be melted in the microwave, and hot glue gun sticks can, of course, be melted in a glue gun. If handled carefully and done properly, the processes are extremely quick and can help you adhere all kinds of surfaces to one another.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Microwaving Glue Sticks</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Remove the glue sticks from their original packaging. All-purpose or school glue sticks can be unscrewed and pulled or broken off from their plastic casings. Hot glue gun sticks simply need to be removed from any packaging or wrappers. <figure rend="Melt Glue Sticks Step 1 Version 3.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure there are no plastics or other wrappings in or on the glue you want to melt. Most wrappings and plastics are not intended to be melted and can be unsafe to do so.</item>
<item>If your glue stick has a plastic piece through the center, carefully cut the glue away from the plastic using a knife.</item></list></item>
<item>Put the stick(s) into a microwave-safe dish. Since the glue will be very messy and hard to clean, use a single-use paper bowl. If you are dedicating the dish to the craft of melting glue sticks, a ceramic or glass mug or bowl will also work. <figure rend="Melt Glue Sticks Step 2 Version 3.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be sure the glue sticks are fully inside of the dish. If they overhang the mug or bowl, they will melt outside of the dish.</item>
<item>Start with smaller quantities to test how long your particular glue takes to melt.</item></list></item>
<item>Microwave the glue on full power in 20-second intervals. Depending on your microwave and amount of glue, you should at least be able to partially melt the sticks. If there are still solids, microwave the glue for an additional 20 seconds after stirring it with a craft stick or plastic spoon. <figure rend="Melt Glue Sticks Step 3 Version 3.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not leave the microwave unattended. If something goes wrong, you should be there to stop the microwave.</item>
<item>Do not heat the sticks for extended periods of time. It may look like nothing is wrong while it heats, but overheating the glue can create fumes that are unsafe.</item></list></item>
<item>Remove the glue from the microwave carefully. You should use it immediately, but be careful as the glue will be quite hot. Depending on how long it was heated, the dish can be hot as well. <figure rend="Melt Glue Sticks Step 4 Version 3.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Use the glue fresh out of the microwave so it will be easy to apply.</item>
<item>If the glue re-hardens, simply microwave it for another 20 seconds.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Melting Glue Sticks with a Glue Gun</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Obtain a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Use_a_Glue_Gun">glue gun</ref> at least as big as the glue sticks. Only use hot glue sticks intended for glue guns—not all-purpose or school glue sticks. If the sticks won’t fit into the glue gun, you cannot melt them. If the sticks are too small, you will just have to use your hand to feed them through. <figure rend="Melt Glue Sticks Step 5 Version 3.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure your glue sticks are meant for a glue gun. You should not use other types of glue sticks because they can damage your glue gun.</item></list></item>
<item>Plug in the glue gun over cardboard or newspaper. As the tip of the gun heats, the gun may start to drip as it melts. By putting a piece of cardboard or newspaper underneath, you can protect your working surface. <figure rend="Melt Glue Sticks Step 6 Version 3.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always follow the instructions specific to your glue gun regarding electricity and timing.</item>
<item>Do not leave a glue gun unattended. They can tip over or otherwise cause severe burns if you are not careful.</item></list></item>
<item>Squeeze the trigger of the glue gun to feed the sticks. If the sticks match the size of the glue gun, the trigger will allow the stick to press and feed through the heated tip. The glue will then melt and drip out wherever you point the gun. <figure rend="Melt Glue Sticks Step 7 Version 3.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not touch the metal tip of the gun or the melting glue. They will both be extremely hot.</item>
<item>If the glue is not feeding through, it may either be too large of a stick or may still be heating up.</item>
<item>If your glue stick is smaller than the glue gun, you will have to push from the back end of the stick to feed it through.</item>
<item>Use gloves to protect your hands from the heated materials.</item></list></item>
<item>Insert another stick once the first no longer feeds through. If the gun or your fingers can no longer safely feed the first stick through the rear of the glue gun, use another glue stick to press it through. It will then be caught by the plastic feeding mechanism and continue melting. <figure rend="Melt Glue Sticks Step 8 Version 3.360p.mp4"></figure></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not touch melted glue. It will be extremely hot and adhere to your skin, making the burn worse.</item>
<item>Do not inhale melted glue fumes. Some glues are non-toxic, but not all of them are. Regardless, the fumes can be dangerous, and you may need to wear a respirator while working.</item></list>
</text>
