<text id="autogum_whow_doc684" title="Get Rid of Hip Dips" shortTile="rid-hip-dips" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-06-07" dateModified="2019-04-18" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get-Rid-of-Hip-Dips" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get Rid of Hip Dips</head><p>Hip dips refer to a harmless, cosmetic gap between the upper and lower hip. If you want to minimize them, do exercises that will tone your core and fill out your hips. Aim to target this body area 4-6 times a week to attain the best results possible. Beyond exercise, you can camouflage hip dips by dressing in clothing that fits well and improves your silhouette. Remember that hip dips are not a bad feature and you should feel proud of your body whether you have them or not!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Toning Your Core</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Do glute bridges to tone your hips. Lie on your back with your knees bent and feet shoulder-width apart. Lift your hips off the floor while keeping your back straight. Hold your position for 2 counts, then lower your hips back down slowly. <figure rend="Get Rid of Hip Dips Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do 2 to 3 sets of 10-15 reps, 2-3 times a week for the best results.</item>
<item>Start by doing this exercise with your body weight and work up to holding dumbbells at the front of your hips.</item></list></item>
<item>Try <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Do_Lunges">lunges</ref> to shape your hips, stomach, and behind. Stand with your feet a bit more than hip-distance apart and place your left leg forward. Drop your right knee towards the floor while bending your front knee. Continue until your front knee is directly over your ankle, then return to the starting position. <figure rend="Get Rid of Hip Dips Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do 20 reps, then switch sides and repeat the exercise with your right foot forward.</item>
<item>Aim to do lunges 2-3 days per week.</item>
<item>Stay straight by focusing on dropping your hips towards the floor.</item></list></item>
<item>Practice bench step-ups to target your hips and glutes. Stand next to a fitness bench, length-wise. Step up with your right foot and lift your left leg to the side. Hold this position for 3 counts, then step down with the left foot followed by the right foot. <figure rend="Get Rid of Hip Dips Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do 15 reps, then repeat with the other leg. Do 2 sets on each side.</item></list></item>
<item>Get into the <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Perform_the_Plank_Exercise">plank position</ref> for 30-60 seconds to work your core muscles. Lie face down with your hands under your shoulders and your toes curled to grip the ground. Straighten your arms and lift yourself off of the floor. Hold this position with your abs and buns tightened, then lower yourself back down. <figure rend="Get Rid of Hip Dips Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Start by holding yourself up for 30 seconds at a time, then work up to a full 60 seconds per plank.</item>
<item>Your body should be positioned in a diagonal line while you hold this position.</item>
<item>For the best results, do this exercise every 1-2 days.</item></list></item>
<item>Do advanced crunches to tone your abs and upper hips. Lie flat on your back with your legs straight up in the air, perpendicular to your torso. Cross your hands over your chest. Flex your stomach to bring your elbows to your knees, then lower yourself back down. <figure rend="Get Rid of Hip Dips Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do 2 sets of 25 reps, 3-4 times per week.</item></list></item>
<item>Do squats to strengthen your core. Stand with your feet slightly wider than hip-width and your arms extended in front of you, palms down. Bend your knees slowly while sending your hips backward, keeping your back straight. Squat as low as you can while maintaining your balance, then push up on your heels to get back into a standing position. <figure rend="Get Rid of Hip Dips Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For a full workout, do 2-3 sets of 15-20 squats.</item>
<item>Try to do squats at least twice a week to see improvement.</item></list></item>
<item>Work on doing donkey kicks. Get on your hands and knees, making sure your arms are fully extended and perpendicular to the ground. Keep your knees at a 90-degree angle and lift one of your legs until your thigh is in line with your torso and parallel to the ground. <figure rend="Get Rid of Hip Dips Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do 10 to 15 reps with each leg for 2 to 3 sets.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Camouflaging Them With Clothing</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Go for clothing that looks tailored, not tight. Tight-fitting clothing will highlight your hip dips by clinging to your body. Opt instead for looser clothing, or clothes that are tailored to fit well without hugging your body. Pair long, loose tops with slim-fitting bottoms to balance out your look. <figure rend="Get Rid of Hip Dips Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Fit and flare dresses can give you an hourglass shape while covering your hip dips.</item>
<item>Tailored blazers and blouses can camouflage your hip dips without looking baggy.</item></list></item>
<item>Choose fabrics that won't cling to your body. Loose, flowing fabrics like cotton are the best choice for disguising your hip dips as they fall around your body without clinging to it. Thick, structured materials like denim may also offer good camouflage by holding their own shape outside of your silhouette. Avoid clingy fabrics like spandex and lycra, which will accentuate your hips dips. <figure rend="Get Rid of Hip Dips Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wear long sweaters and tops that fall below your hips. To cover your hips completely, opt for long cardigans, blazers, shirts, or blouses. Shop for tops that skim past your hips for the best coverage. Choose the right size by making sure that the shoulders are not baggy and that the top does not cling to your body anywhere. <figure rend="Get Rid of Hip Dips Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>A waterfall cardigan, which cascades down in front and has no buttons to close it, can make a good addition to your wardrobe.</item></list></item>
<item>Wear peplum style garments to cover the gap between your high and lower hips. Peplum is a style of dress, top, and jacket that flares out in a bell shape just above your hips, creating an hourglass shape. This design also covers hips dips completely, making them unnoticeable. Shop for chic peplum dresses or peplum shirts, blouses, and blazers to pair with slim-fitting pants or skirts. <figure rend="Get Rid of Hip Dips Step 11.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Peplum style clothing also camouflages a thicker waist by creating a curvy shape.</item>
<item>Make sure the flared part of the clothing is beyond the widest part and drop below the hip dip.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Exercises and Routine to Get Rid of Hip Dips</head>
<p><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Doc:Exercises_to_Get_Rid_of_Hip_Dips,Beginner_Routine_to_Get_Rid_of_Hip_Dips">Doc:Exercises to Get Rid of Hip Dips,Beginner Routine to Get Rid of Hip Dips</ref></p>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Changing your diet will not really affect you hips dips as they tend to occur based on the structure of your body than your overall weight.</item>
<item>Note that you will likely never get rid of hip dips completely, though you can make them less noticeable.</item>
<item>Hip dips are not uncommon and they are not a sign that you are out of shape. Feel free to embrace them and show them off proudly!</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
