<text id="autogum_whow_doc163" title="Arrange a Classroom for Tuition Kids in Your Home" shortTile="arrange-classroom" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2016-03-04" dateModified="2018-09-14" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Arrange-a-Classroom-for-Tuition-Kids-in-Your-Home" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Arrange a Classroom for Tuition Kids in Your Home</head><p>Some of us here have a lot of problem while we're taking children for learning, through tuition, and more trouble if it's in the home. Let's do it! Let's find out how to maintain a perfect classroom for them, right under your roof!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Your room has to be pretty spaciously built. If it is a smaller room, call different children at different times. This will also help you build your stamina, and stop confusion in the kids. The size of the room will now fit the children. The lowest you can get for a small room is to take four kids at a time.</item>
<item>Gather all the waste. To maintain the classroom, you'll need plenty of things you decided to trash in the barn or give to the garbage-picker. Take out that chair! Get those tables! Where is that drawer you saved a few years ago, and forgot all about it?</item>
<item>Get the room to be painted brightly. With the exception of red, any color will be suitable. The colors should be bright, but not hyper. If it's pale pink, add a combination of purple and yellow! If it's red, give it a tinge of orange or green! Give it a slightly entertaining twitch. Design a peaceful-looking garden with birds flying. Paint a serene landscape. If you want to spend a lot for those little children, get a wallpaper. Do NOT choose a wallpaper which has congested designs, as this will psychologically effect the child's attentiveness.</item>
<item>Organize everything. Organizing will help you not to get flustered and effect the way children look at you. Make a resource-pocket right beside a white-board, or a blackboard you will use. In it keep all the stationery. Keep a cupboard neatly designed and in it, put your necessary belongings there. Keep entertaining items to get your children more interested. This not only effects their keenness, but also their thinking skills and sharpness of mind.</item>
<item>Arrange two tables in a row with four chairs, or as many as the kids you're taking in. At the front wall where their vision will mostly be, hang a blackboard or whiteboard. Do NOT put your duster on a spare stool or chair, as the stains of chalk and dried ink from the marker will be hard to remove. Keep a piece of cardboard over the stool, and let your duster rest there.</item>
<item>Hang a little basket at the other side of your board. This will contain flashcards and all the other various entertainment item you're going to use that day. After you're done with using those pieces, take out different ones from the cupboard, and put them in for the next day.</item>
<item>In the resource pocket, always have stationery. This includes:These are if the children, supposedly, lose their item or haven't brought any. You can lend it to the for the time being until the time is over.
<list type="unordered"><item>Color pencils</item>
<item>Pens</item>
<item>Pencils</item>
<item>Erasers</item>
<item>Sharpeners</item>
<item>Scales/rulers</item>
<item>Markers</item>
<item>Paint brushes</item>
<item>Crayons</item>
<item>Scissors</item></list></item>
<item>Keep a small dustbin at the far end of the room. Instruct the children that all garbage should go there. Ensure that there are no pencil-sharps on the ground.</item>
<item>At the other corner, keep a small decorated box with gift-wrapper or some bright-looking covering. Put a label on it saying, "LOST ITEMS' BOX". Make a small opening in this box. Shove in anything that you find after your class.</item>
<item>Nail, stick or paste anything the children have created. Example:- They've given a test and the results will come tomorrow. Check all papers and put them on the wall. This will be called the Children's Corner.</item>
<item>Keep a noticeboard. On this noticeboard, you'll stick everything which you're currently teaching OR what the children have learnt. Cut out stories from newspapers that might interest your kids. Put a moral or some quote there as well. This noticeboard has to be bright and attractive, so that your kids may read it.</item>
<item>In one corner, put a two-board table. It will have one board on the top and one board at the bottom. In the bottom keep papers, canvases and paints. On the top, keep books tidily arranged. This is for the children's free-time. After they have done everything and still time is remaining, with them idle, pass around the papers, canvases, books, paints, scissors, crayons, color pencils, pencils, pens and everything singly in your resource pocket. It will relax their mind and make them happy, which urges them to come tomorrow. Psychologically, they become at peace, and their mind is fresher and more eager and cheerful. Memory also increases with this method.</item></list>
</text>
