<text id="autogum_whow_doc230" title="Measure Market Volatility" shortTile="measure-market-volatility" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-07-13" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Measure-Market-Volatility" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Measure Market Volatility</head><p>Volatility in financial markets is a concern among finance professionals, traders and investors, and anybody else looking at the ongoing market situation for a particular region or exchange. But volatility is a word that many individuals use in many different contexts. If you need to measure market volatility as an investor or anyone up with a stake in changes to a financial market, here are some of the best ways to examine volatility, or changes in market price, according to some experienced professionals and others.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Choose a time frame in which to examine market volatility. Volatility is a variable that is only accurate within a certain time frame. That's why most brokerage accounts and other services provide time adjustable charts that show how an asset, a market or a collection of financial products has changed over a specific amount of time. <figure rend="Measure Market Volatility Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use formulas to further define volatility. Within your given time frame, you can make use of simple or more complex formulas to calculate volatility technically. <figure rend="Measure Market Volatility Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use an index to look at how volatility has affected multiple assets. Single stocks or financial products have their own specific volatility within a market, but traders often use an index to define volatility for multiple stocks or products. An index is simply a collection of values for stocks, funds and other products that provides a total change in price. <figure rend="Measure Market Volatility Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>One of the most basic formulas for calculating volatility is the following: range multiplied by (maximum price minus minimum price) for your time period.</item>
<item>Other more complex formulas like VIX or Beta help finance professionals and others understand more about how prices are changing within a given market.</item></list></item>
<item>Calculate percentage changes. Using individual assets or the index tools mentioned above, take a look at how much a price has changed over time and calculate that as a percentage of the total value to find a "total volatility" that you can use to predict future markets. <figure rend="Measure Market Volatility Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Assess various stock index tools to see how they can help you measure volatility. For example, in the American market, the Dow Jones industrial average, a collection of blue-chip stocks, has its own volatility calculations that can help you better understand where a market has been and where it is going.</item></list></item>
<item>Evaluate moving averages. For many traders, it's not enough just to see how much a price has changed. It's also important to see which direction that change has gone within a greater context. Even if you have identified your specific time frame for volatility, you may want to go back further and look at how the stock or other asset has changed over a greater time frame. A moving average helps financial professionals to do this by providing an average price for the asset over a longer period of time such as 1 year. <figure rend="Measure Market Volatility Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Account for market sentiments. Use random number method like Random Number tables or concept of 'Brownian Motion for financial analysis' especially in case of Stock market volatility. <figure rend="Measure Market Volatility Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
