<text id="autogum_whow_doc070" title="Find a Private Boating Class" shortTile="find-private-boating" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-05-01" dateModified="2019-08-27" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Find-a-Private-Boating-Class" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Find a Private Boating Class</head><p>Private boating classes offer instruction that provides guidance and tips on a variety of boating topics including personal safety and boat handling, navigation systems and rules as well as boating laws and registration requirements. Individuals can take classes for different types of private boating that may include sailing, powerboats, yacht training, and personal watercraft jet boats as well as kayaking. Private boating classes are available globally so regardless of where you live opportunities abound to learn how to successfully navigate and cruise the open waters within the boat of your choice.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Determine what type of boat that you want to learn more about in a private boating class. What are your interests and what type of access do you have to local lakes, rivers and the ocean that may border the area where you reside? <figure rend="Find a Private Boating Class Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Assess your location in relation to where the private boating classes are offered. Some long distance travel may be necessary to get to your private boating class. Think of it as a short vacation to learn more about boat safety and navigation so that you can better enjoy the activity. <figure rend="Find a Private Boating Class Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Consider the costs for the training offered in a private boating class. Do some initial research to explore the various options that may be available in your area to get comprehensive instruction for a reasonable fee. <figure rend="Find a Private Boating Class Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure that the private boating class instructors themselves have proper training, education and experience in boating instruction. If they are licensed and certified, that is an added plus. Look for professional level instructors having extensive expertise and knowledge. <figure rend="Find a Private Boating Class Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Conduct some research on the Internet to explore available opportunities for private boating classes in your region. Many private boat instructors have websites providing extensive information on the types of private boat classes available. Also check out the yellow pages both online and in your local phone book for those private boat instructors that may not have a website. <figure rend="Find a Private Boating Class Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Consider taking some online courses that focus on boat safety and navigation as well as boat laws and regulations before you actually venture out onto the water and take your private boating class. Preparation and prior knowledge will better equip you toward becoming a better boater. <figure rend="Find a Private Boating Class Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Realize that some private boat instructors may offer the option of coming to you to provide you with private boating classes. Such instruction would likely encompass a more expensive rate and additional fees. <figure rend="Find a Private Boating Class Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Choose private boating classes that will meet the needs for the particular type of boat that you will be learning to navigate. There are private boating classes that cover just the basics but do not expand on topics geared to specific types of boats. If you are new to sailing, for example, your private boating class should include instruction to prepare you navigate and handle one successfully. <figure rend="Find a Private Boating Class Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Contact and obtain more information about those private boating classes that you are most interested in. Have the instructors provide you with additional detailed information to help you decide if their course is the right one for you. <figure rend="Find a Private Boating Class Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Complete any necessary registration forms required for admission to your private boating class. Chart out your goals, attend your private boating classes and learn how to successfully and safely navigate the open waters. <figure rend="Find a Private Boating Class Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
