<text id="autogum_whow_doc655" title="Prepare in High School for College Soccer" shortTile="prepare-high-school" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-09-19" dateModified="2019-09-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Prepare-in-High-School-for-College-Soccer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Prepare in High School for College Soccer</head><p>College soccer (football to most of the world) puts extreme physical demands on its players. High school students must prepare for a faster and more stamina-taxing game than they may be used to. They should also understand that they're entering a world comparable to professional sports, in the sense that they are competing for scholarships and recruitment.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Training Physically</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Train for a rigorous practice schedule. A typical college varsity soccer team trains five or six days a week, and competes in one or two games. As a student athlete, you must develop excellent physical fitness, endurance, and recovery habits. <figure rend="Prepare in High School for College Soccer Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you aren't getting enough training with your current school team, look for leagues in your area.</item></list></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Improve-Your-Running-Speed-and-Endurance">Improve your speed and endurance</ref>. These traits are incredibly important to your success. Try to achieve excellent speed and above average stamina in high school. If you're still falling short on your goals in college, you'll be under a lot more pressure to catch up. <figure rend="Prepare in High School for College Soccer Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Gain-More-Muscle-Mass-and-Strength">Strength train (recommended)</ref>. Schedule dedicated muscle-building workouts if you don't already. North American recruiters tend to favor bigger, stronger players, although this depends on the coach's mindset. Other regions may have different philosophies, but being stronger certainly won't hurt you. <figure rend="Prepare in High School for College Soccer Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Prevent-Injuries-While-Participating-in-Sports">Avoid injury</ref>. Follow good warm up practices and safety precautions. If you do get injured, even in a minor way, get it checked up and follow your doctor's advice. Besides avoiding the disaster of injuring yourself out of recruitment, you'll learn habits to protect yourself in more demanding situations. <figure rend="Prepare in High School for College Soccer Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remember to rest. Your life should not be all about playing soccer. Even professional athletes take rest days to renew their body and mind. Get enough sleep every night, and make some time for friends, fun, and family. <figure rend="Prepare in High School for College Soccer Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Improving Your Recruitment Chances</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Understand the position you're aiming for. College coaches often recruit based on position, since they know how returning players will fill out the roster. Focus on the position you're best at, and understand its role in the team. <figure rend="Prepare in High School for College Soccer Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If your current coach can't help you with this, look up training videos online. Learn the most important skills for each position, and find drills to improve your weak areas.</item>
<item>In countries with highly competitive college soccer, you may need to demonstrate versatility. Learn to play comfortably in every position, including goalkeeper.</item></list></item>
<item>Play at the highest level you can. College coaches place a high value on players who have proven their talent in playoff games and regional or national competitions. The more experience of this kind on your resume, the better. <figure rend="Prepare in High School for College Soccer Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Contact the college coach. Don't be afraid to call the coach yourself to ask questions, even early in the season. <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be-Confident">Project confidence</ref>, mention your soccer achievements, and keep a positive attitude. Besides piquing the coach's interest, you'll learn valuable information to guide your training and decision-making. Ask him to tell you about the team, and which positions he's recruiting for. <figure rend="Prepare in High School for College Soccer Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Watch as much soccer as you can. Many high school students underestimate how important this is. Watching local and televised games will vastly improve your understanding of the game. Analyze individual and team decisions, and apply the lessons you learn to your own play. <figure rend="Prepare in High School for College Soccer Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep your grades up. Many schools do not allow students to play sports if they have poor academic grades. It is important to balance athletics and academics, as this will only get harder in college. <figure rend="Prepare in High School for College Soccer Step 10.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Begin training on your own before the season starts, to get a head start.</item>
<item>Make sure to eat a healthy diet suitable for your level of exercise.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Avoid overworking yourself. It will only hurt or damage your muscles.</item></list>
</text>
