<text id="autogum_whow_doc089" title="Check Your Computer&apos;s System Information" shortTile="check-computers-system" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2012-07-19" dateModified="2019-10-19" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Check-Your-Computer%27s-System-Information" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Check Your Computer's System Information</head><p>This wikiHow teaches you how to view your computer's hardware and software specifications.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Mac</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Click the Apple menu. It's the apple-shaped icon in the top-left corner of your Mac's screen. <figure rend="Check Your Computer's System Information Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . This option is near the top of the drop-down menu. <figure rend="Check Your Computer's System Information Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Review your Mac's system information. There are several tabs at the top of the "About This Mac" window that you can use to view different type of information: <figure rend="Check Your Computer's System Information Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Overview</hi> - View your Mac's operating system, processor, and memory information here.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Displays</hi> - View information about your Mac's screen and any attached displays.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Storage</hi> - View your Mac's storage allocation, including how much space files are taking up and how much space remains.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Support</hi> - View a list of resources to help solve any potential problems.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Service</hi> - View your Mac's service history (e.g., warranty information).</item></list></item></list>
<head>Windows 10 and 8</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Click the Start  button. It's in the bottom-left corner of the screen; doing so will open the Start menu, which has a built-in search feature. <figure rend="Check Your Computer's System Information Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Type  into the search bar. It's in the bottom-left corner of the screen. <figure rend="Check Your Computer's System Information Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Press . Doing so will open the System Information window. There are four tabs listed in the top-left corner of the window: <figure rend="Check Your Computer's System Information Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">System Summary</hi> - This is the default tab to which System Information opens; it contains details about your computer's operating system, installed memory, and processor type.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Hardware Resources</hi> - View a list of all hardware drivers and information associated with devices (e.g., webcams or controllers) associated with your computer.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Components</hi> - View a list of technical components on your computer such as USB ports, the CD drive, and speakers.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Software Environment</hi> - View drivers and running processes on your computer.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Windows 7, Vista, and XP</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Hold down  and press . Doing so will open Run, which is a program that allows you to run system commands. <figure rend="Check Your Computer's System Information Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Type  into the Run window. This command opens your Windows computer's system information program. <figure rend="Check Your Computer's System Information Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . It's at the bottom of the Run window. Doing so will open the System Information window. <figure rend="Check Your Computer's System Information Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Review your PC's system information. There are several tabs in the top-left corner of the window that you can use to view different aspects of your system: <figure rend="Check Your Computer's System Information Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">System Summary</hi> - This is the default tab to which System Information opens; it contains details about your computer's operating system, installed memory, and processor type.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Hardware Resources</hi> - View a list of all hardware drivers and information associated with devices (e.g., webcams or controllers) associated with your computer.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Components</hi> - View a list of technical components on your computer such as USB ports, the CD drive, and speakers.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Software Environment</hi> - View drivers and running processes on your computer.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Internet Settings</hi> - Your computer may not have this option; if it does, you can use this tab to view various pieces of information about your computer's internet connection.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
