<text id="autogum_whow_doc379" title="Make Cyber Falls" shortTile="make-cyber-falls" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2009-11-02" dateModified="2019-01-16" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-Cyber-Falls" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make Cyber Falls</head><p>The cyber look is becoming increasingly popular in today's teenagers and young adults. This article is for those people who wish to learn how to make their own Cyber Falls hairstyle.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Gather your materials. Cyber falls can be made of many different materials, such as foam, cyberlox (crin), plastic tubing or synthetic hair (dreaded or undreaded). decide which material is the best for the look you want to achieve. <figure rend="Make Cyber Falls Step 1.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Dreadfalls</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Get synthetic hair. Purchase your synthetic hair from a well-respected seller such as Cyberlox or I Kick Shins. Once you have the hair, decide what length you would like your dreads to be. For beginners, it is easiest to start out with the hair folded in half, as once you backcomb you already have a loop at the top, and it will be much more secure to work with. <figure rend="Make Cyber Falls Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Backcomb the hair. Secure the hair to a piece of material that is pulled tight, as you will have to pull on it later. Backcomb the hair several times, separating as you go, until it is knotted thoroughly. <figure rend="Make Cyber Falls Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Seal the dread. Sealing is done by applying heat to your twisted dread to melt the hair into the final dread shape. This can be done with a steamer, a boiling kettle, a saucepan of water, or a standard hair straightener with a damp cloth draped over the dread, which is the preferred method. Using the straightener, start by twisting the fur-ball as tight as you possibly can, starting from the top and working your way to the end. Wet the cloth, and squeeze most of the water out. Place your preheated hair straightener over the dread and hold for 5 seconds. Continue all the way to the end of the dread. Remove the cloth and voila - your first Synthetic dread. <figure rend="Make Cyber Falls Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Thread the dreads. Once you have completed your recommended amount of dreads, thread the dreads onto elastic so you can tie it around your ponytails. Usually dread falls come with two sides to be worn over two ponytails. A standard set of dreadfalls is 30 dreads per side for thin hair or those people with an undercut, or 45 dreads per side for those with thicker hair. <figure rend="Make Cyber Falls Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Cyberlox</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Buy your materials. Cyberlox are quite simple, yet the material can be quite expensive. Buy your materials from a respected seller, such as the ones mentioned above. <figure rend="Make Cyber Falls Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Fold and sew the crin. Using a hair tie or piece of elastic, carefully fold your crin over the hair tie/elastic and secure by sewing with a standard needle and thread. Continue this until you have your desired thickness. <figure rend="Make Cyber Falls Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Add some Rexlace. Cyberlox look best when teamed up with Rexlace, which is attached simply by tying it onto the hairtie/elastic. <figure rend="Make Cyber Falls Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Dreads that start one color (Ex. match your roots) then change into a different color (Ex. Neon Green) look best.</item>
<item>When making/purchasing dread falls, make the base color (or overall color) match your hair color.</item>
<item>Dread falls can get extremely heavy. it is recommended that you wear a headband in the front of your hair to prevent pulling.</item>
<item>To save money, if you're looking for a basic color for dread falls (synthetic hair) go to your near by salon store such as Sally's and purchase your hair there.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>People will gawk at you like you're a rainbow-colored unicorn, so beware.</item>
<item>Many people will ask if they can touch your hair, however, it's up to you if you want to let them.</item>
<item>Keep in mind it <hi rend="bold">will</hi> be expensive if you order anything online due to paying for shipping and handling.</item></list>
</text>
