<text id="autogum_whow_doc591" title="Live with Meaning in a World Without Purpose" shortTile="live-meaning-world" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-01-24" dateModified="2018-03-20" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Live-with-Meaning-in-a-World-Without-Purpose" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Live with Meaning in a World Without Purpose</head><p>First introduced by philosopher Soren Kierkegaard, and later discussed by philosophers such as Friedrich Neitzche and Jean-Paul Sartre the idea of existentialism is a simple one: Human existence is not, does not have an objective purpose. Instead, meaning for life must be made by the individual and is entirely subjective. In order to accomplish this goal of creating meaning in a purposeless world, there are a few important steps, which will be described in this wikiHow.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Understand that life has no objective purpose. Philosopher Jean-Paul Sartre established the idea that existence precedes essence, which means essentially that humans existed before any meaning to life was thought to have existed, therefore he claims meaning is not given objectively. Philosopher Viktor Frankl created a theory in philosophy of Logotherapy which states that one must understand first, that our main motivation in life is to find meaning, because life is inherently meaningless and that we have inalienable freedom to find meaning. Both theories are grounded in the notion that in order for something to have an objective purpose it must have been created with that purpose in mind. For example, a hammer is created with the purpose of hammering nails and therefore its essence precedes its existence. Existentialists believe this is not the case with humans and therefore, there is no objective purpose to life. It is still possible to live a fulfilling life according to philosophers, and the first step to achieving this is to come to terms with the reality that life has no objective purpose.</item>
<item>Accept your freedom and personal responsibility. According to Jean-Paul Sartre, existentialism requires one to take personal responsibility for their purpose and to actively use their freedom to make their purpose. This presupposes that you possess free will, an idea accepted by most notable existentialists. Another important component of choosing purpose freely is the existentialist notion of authenticity introduced by Soren Kierkegaard, which states that one must remain authentic by choosing a purpose which is true to themselves and their own desires and passions. Therefore one must embrace their own personal responsibility and choose their purpose freely and authentically.</item>
<item>Understand that death is unavoidable. If you can recognize deaths inevitability it will help you appreciate your life, and add extra importance and meaning to your actions. According to existentialist philosopher, Martin Heidegger an awareness of death and mortal fragility gives allows authentic existence, a crucial component of existentialism, to be possible. Furthermore, philosopher Karl Jaspers argues that if one is unable to face the inevitable reality of death he will either resort to mythical beliefs to avoid death, or immerse himself in worldly things neglecting his need to form his own meaning.</item>
<item>Find your own purpose in your life. Because there is no objective meaning or purpose to your life, according to existentialists, you must find your own. Whether it is in helping other people, becoming the best in your career you can possibly be, all that matters is that you find a purpose which gives meaning to your life. In the words of Jean-Paul Sartre: “Life has no meaning a priori… It is up to you to give it a meaning, and value is nothing but the meaning that you choose.”</item></list>
</text>
