<text id="autogum_whow_doc005" title="Become a Book Lover" shortTile="become-book-lover" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2017-08-07" dateModified="2019-11-02" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Become-a-Book-Lover" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Become a Book Lover</head><p>People often say they don't like to read books, and only do so because of work or school. But reading provides opportunities to grow, expand your horizons, and even improve your health. If you would like to reap the benefits of reading but don't know where to start, here are a few ideas.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Overcoming Obstacles to Reading</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Address reading difficulties. Whether you have a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Know-if-You-Have-a-Learning-Disability">learning disability</ref> such as dyslexia, never learned to read, or view reading as something to be endured rather than enjoyed, there are steps you can take to make reading an enjoyable experience. <figure rend="Read a Book If You Don't Enjoy Reading Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Find an adult literacy program. Contact your local school district or public library to see if they offer literacy programs. If they don't, ProLiteracy.org, a worldwide adult literacy organization has a directory of literacy programs throughout the United States.</item>
<item>Find a literary style you enjoy reading. You don't need to read long novels or thick textbooks. You can read poetry, short stories, graphic novels, or any written format.</item>
<item>Listen to audio books. Want to enjoy a book but don't have the time? Listen to it on audio! Studies show listening to audio books has benefits that reading does not provide, like the ability to multitask while listening to a book.</item></list></item>
<item>Read with an open mind. Books are entertaining, thought provoking, and educational. You may have to challenge yourself to read more, thinking that reading is a waste of time. But if you are willing to put in some extra effort, you will find reading provides many benefits, including <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Have-Fun-Reading-Books">fun</ref>.
<list type="unordered"><item>Set aside time for reading. Pick a book that interests you and read for a set amount of time. It can be as short or as long a time as you want.</item></list></item>
<item>Get through a book you don't <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Read-a-Book-You-Don't-Like">enjoy</ref>. Sometimes you have required reading you can't avoid. Here are some tips to read material that doesn't pique your interest: <figure rend="Read a Book Faster Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Divide your reading into manageable sections. When reading a textbook in particular, there are some steps that can help:
<list type="unordered"><item>Read from the end to the beginning. If have to read a textbook, skip to the questions at the end of the chapter. Then go back to the beginning and find the answers to the questions.</item>
<item>Find the main ideas. Look at the headings and subsections to get an overview of the chapter. This will make it easier to get through the mountain of information.</item>
<item>Take notes. Not only will this help you remember what you are reading, it will give you something to refer to after you have finished the assignment.</item></list></item></list></item>
<item>Put the book down. If you're reading a book you don't enjoy, go ahead and put it down if it's not required reading. You can always come back to it later.</item></list>
<head>Selecting Reading Material</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Choose a literary style that interests you. There are any number of genres available. Whether you prefer mysteries, non-fiction, or any other type of literature, you can find a book to suit your taste. The challenge may be to narrow down your choices. You may want to: <figure rend="Get Into Reading a Book Step 16.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Check out the cover. If the title or artwork looks interesting, check the inside for information such as a content summary, review excerpts, and information about the author.</item>
<item>Find book summaries online. There are many websites providing summaries of books you may be interested in reading. The Power Moves and Softonics.com are two sites reviewing the best summary websites.</item></list></item>
<item>Read with friends. Joining a discussion club can introduce you to books you wouldn't otherwise know about, and provide insights on what you have read. There are a number of benefits to being in a reading club: <figure rend="Make a Habit of Reading Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>It gives you an incentive to finish. Having a deadline may give you the push you need to finish the book.</item>
<item>It can decrease stress. You can express your opinions freely to a group with common interests.</item>
<item>It can improve your writing skills. Reading and discussing the writing styles of different authors can provide ideas you may want to incorporate in your own writing.</item></list></item>
<item>Select your preferred format. Whether you prefer print or digital, there is a format to suit every reader.
<list type="unordered"><item>Read with an e-reader. When you have time to read but don't want to carry a book around, e-readers like Kindle or Nook can be a virtual library of reading material.
<list type="unordered"><item>Depending on the available features, e-readers cost between $75 and $250.</item>
<item>Online review sites like PCMag.com and Cnet.com can help you find the best e-reader for your use.</item></list></item>
<item>Read a traditional print book. Despite the conveniences of an e-book, print books do have some advantages.
<list type="unordered"><item>Books provide a multi-sensory experience that e-readers don't. Studies have shown that people retain more when reading in print due to having more than one sense involved.</item>
<item>It is easier to keep your place in a print book. Many e-books do not have a way to get back to a previously viewed page.</item></list></item></list></item>
<item>Go to the <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Use-a-Public-Library">library</ref>. You'll find a wealth of information on a variety of topics in a number of formats.  And much of it's for free!</item></list>
<head>Reaping the Benefits of Reading</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Read to improve wellbeing. It has been scientifically proven that people who cultivate a reading habit become happier and healthier than non-readers. The benefits of reading include: <figure rend="Get Into Reading a Book Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Increased longevity. According to a 2016 study, reading 3.5 hours or more resulted in a 20% increase in life expectancy as compared to non-readers.</item>
<item>Reduced stress. Reading has been shown to be effective at reducing stress levels along with such healthful activities as listening to music, drinking tea or coffee, or walking.</item>
<item>Improved relaxation and sleep. The relaxation that comes with reading makes it a perfect way to get ready for sleep. Experts recommend reading a print book rather than an e-book, and the subject matter should be conducive to relaxation.</item>
<item>Improved memory. Studies have shown that people who read experience a slower decline in memory later in life than non-readers.</item>
<item>Reading is a mental work-out. Reading a book encourages "deep thinking," or thinking critically and making connections to each page as well as the outside word. This results in the brain creating neural networks that can promote quicker thinking and improved cognitive skills.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you like to watch movies, there are any number of books that also have a movie tie-in. Diary of a Wimpy Kid is one example of a young adult book that was adapted into a movie.</item>
<item>While reading, try to visualize what is going on.</item></list>
</text>
