<text id="autogum_whow_doc334" title="Identify Emotional Disabilities" shortTile="identify-emotional" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-05-19" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Identify-Emotional-Disabilities" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Identify Emotional Disabilities</head><p>Parents and teachers alike often find themselves trying to identify emotional disabilities in children. Early identification of any disorder helps a child to receive the help he or she needs. Children display some actions that are very similar to others within a specific age range. While comparison of children on a one-to-one basis is discouraged, a comparison within age groups presents a point of reference from which to work.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Track the emotional issues the child exhibits that concern you. Think clearly about your concerns in contrast to any social problems the child has shown. <figure rend="Make a Behavior Intervention Plan for an Autistic Child Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Ask yourself if the issues are recurrent enough to warrant this alarm.</item>
<item>Judge these issues against other developmental or behavioral disabilities that exist with the child.</item></list></item>
<item>Acknowledge any other challenges that are going on. Many emotional issues are actually developmental or behavioral disabilities. <figure rend="Make a Behavior Intervention Plan for an Autistic Child Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>A child with one disability will frequently have more.</item>
<item>It is important to note the differences in issues. The treatment differs in some instances.</item></list></item>
<item>Compare your concerns relating to one child (quietly to yourself) with those of others you know within the same age group. You will then determine whether there is anything out of the norm. <figure rend="Calm Hyperactive Children Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Know the available health screenings that identify emotional disabilities. <figure rend="Make a Behavior Intervention Plan for an Autistic Child Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>These will include vision and hearing assessments as well as psychological testing to determine intellectual development.</item>
<item>Deficiencies and ratings of emotional skills are noted in testing. Combine this with historical information of abilities, education and behavior evaluations.</item></list></item>
<item>Investigate these screenings and determine the issues they will prove and/or rule out. <figure rend="Identify Emotional Disabilities Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Teachers who suspect a child has emotional disabilities must investigate possibilities thoroughly. They will discuss their suspicions with the school counselor before approaching parents.</item>
<item>All those involved with the child must discuss the issues together if the child is within school age.</item></list></item>
<item>Schedule medical or psychological assessments necessary to help the child. Parents should make the appropriate appointments and attend them with the child. <figure rend="Identify Emotional Disabilities Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Medical evaluations will identify or rule out many health problems that are known to cause emotional problems.</item>
<item>Age appropriate psychological testing requires a long block of time. Make certain the child understands this if you go this route.</item>
<item>Make it clear in your mind that the medical or psychological professional you visit has all of the information on which you have based your concerns.</item></list></item>
<item>Follow up with the professionals recommendations as appropriate. Discuss educational needs the physician suggests. <figure rend="Be _=_quot_=_Merry_=_quot_=_ Every Day Until Christmas Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>There are intellectual disorders that involve some very serious emotional disabilities. Stay alert for this possibility.</item>
<item>Applied Behavior Analysis therapy is a controversial autism therapy that has led to tremendous success stories and stories of terror and trauma. Be cautious, and <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Tell_if_an_Autism_ABA_Therapy_Is_Harmful">recognize the difference</ref> between teaching skills and forcing compliance.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>A child who is marked by peers as emotionally disabled will have difficulties in school and experience serious life problems.</item></list>
</text>
