<text id="autogum_whow_doc346" title="React when a Doctor Says Nothing More Can Be Done (Surgery)" shortTile="react-doctor-nothing" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-03-10" dateModified="2017-08-30" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/React-when-a-Doctor-Says-Nothing-More-Can-Be-Done-%28Surgery%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>React when a Doctor Says Nothing More Can Be Done (Surgery)</head><p>If a doctor tells you nothing more can be done with respect to a surgery, just thank him or her and go home and relax a minute. Then, proceed to locate the nearest teaching hospital in your state with specialty department that meets your needs. Remember that even "C" grade students become doctors. Try to find the geniuses who are available at teaching hospitals with technology and staff not available in your hometown.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Note: This article applies to the USA.</hi></p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be aware that a doctor who says that nothing more can be done just doesn't have the knowledge or experience to know what else can be done. However, there is always something else that can be done if you ask a surgeon at a teaching hospital, even if they don't know yet what it is. The doctors in these hospitals are the best of the best. They will research and consult and research some more until they come up with the plan for care. They will be confident in their skills and your outcome from surgery and they may have better technology and staff available than a hometown hospital. <figure rend="React when a Doctor Says Nothing More Can Be Done (Surgery) Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>These hospitals take Medicare and Medicaid happily so that's not an issue either.</item>
<item>You may be able to have bad outcomes from previous surgeries fixed.</item></list></item>
<item>Expect to have a nurse assigned to you who will handle all the details of beforehand testing and preparing you for your surgery and recovery, so don't worry about the details. Just keep notes and follow directions.  <figure rend="React when a Doctor Says Nothing More Can Be Done (Surgery) Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Ask as many questions as you have until you feel comfortable. That's what makes for better outcomes too, when you know what to expect. <figure rend="React when a Doctor Says Nothing More Can Be Done (Surgery) Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be sure you have completed all pre-surgery testing necessary at least ten days ahead of out-of-town surgery to eliminate any need to postpone a surgery. And only have complex and invasive tests done at the recommended facility because some tests aren't familiar to your local providers and they may not even know what you are talking about in some instances. It may be inconvenient but just do it for the best results.  <figure rend="React when a Doctor Says Nothing More Can Be Done (Surgery) Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't cut corners when it comes to your recovery. If the doctors suggest an acute rehab hospital after you leave their hospital, go there. An acute rehab hospital will teach you how to move without injuring yourself and improve your recovery too. Prepare yourself mentally for surgery, surrounding yourself with good energy and positive thoughts. <figure rend="React when a Doctor Says Nothing More Can Be Done (Surgery) Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't leave any issues up in the air before surgery. Nail down who will care for your pets and have a back up just in case.  Once all of the details are confirmed, you'll be able to relax during your hospital stay. Keep lists to help keep track of the details and don't stress yourself out.  Once an issue is resolved, don't worry about it anymore. Move on to the next thing. And be happy––tell your loved ones what they mean to you because they could be gone tomorrow and no one wants a regret either. <figure rend="React when a Doctor Says Nothing More Can Be Done (Surgery) Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If travel is an issue, organizations like Angel Flights will fly you to and from appointments and surgery at no cost to you. Get in touch with them to work out details. It's very easy.</item>
<item>Prepare your home beforehand, for your recovery. Have supplies on hand so you don't have to worry about shopping when you come home.</item>
<item>If you'll need assistance, have it agreed upon before surgery who caretaker/s will be. Don't leave that to chance. Nail it down beforehand.</item>
<item>Purchase a cheap cell phone to call home long distance if you don't already have one.</item>
<item>If clean hair will be an issue, take some waterless shampoo.</item>
<item>A blanket from home helps with long hospital stays too.</item></list>
</text>
