<text id="autogum_whow_doc359" title="Find Other Galaxies" shortTile="find-galaxies" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-08-24" dateModified="2015-11-05" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Find-Other-Galaxies" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Find Other Galaxies</head><p>Galaxies are vast collections of stars in space. They can be pretty awesome to look at, especially if you can see the structure of the galaxy. Here's five ways that you can find a galaxy in outer space. The first three only work in the northern hemisphere, while the fourth only works in the southern hemisphere.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>The Andromeda galaxy</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find the constellation of Andromeda. You should see three bright stars in a line, plus a bunch of dim stars.</item>
<item>Find the star Mirach. It's the middle star in the line of three bright stars.</item>
<item>Look slightly north and to the right of Mirach. A star map will help you pin down the location. The galaxy should appear as a fuzzy patch.</item></list>
<head>The Triangulum galaxy</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find the Andromeda galaxy using the method above.</item>
<item>Go from the Andromeda galaxy to Mirach, then go the same distance again. the galaxy should look like a dimmer version of the Andromeda galaxy.</item></list>
<head>Bode's galaxy (M81)</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Go to a dark site. M81 is very faint - it's the dimmest galaxy that can be seen with the naked eye.</item>
<item>Find the Big Dipper. This will point the way to the galaxy.</item>
<item>Go from Phecda (bottom left of the trapezoid), through Dubhe (top right of the trapezoid, used to find the pole star), then go the same distance again. The galaxy should appear as a very faint fuzzy patch - if it's dark enough, and if you have good eyesight. A star map is very helpful.</item></list>
<head>Magellanic clouds</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Look south. These galaxies are very bright - brighter than most stars. You should see two large fuzzy sparkly patches. these are the Large Magellanic cloud (LMC) and the Small Magellanic cloud (SMC). If you want to be more precise, the SMC is in the constellations of Tucana and Hydrus, and the LMC is in Dorado and Mensa.</item></list>
<head>Telescope method</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Get a telescope and a star map. Other galaxies are only visible through a telescope, you can't see them with the naked eye.</item>
<item>Decide on a galaxy to look at. For starters, you can try finding the galaxies already mentioned. You'll be able to make out details that you can't see with the naked eye. I'd also recommend M51, the Whirlpool galaxy - a favourite among photographers.</item>
<item>Use the star map to find the co-ordinates of the galaxy. You can also find them on the internet.</item>
<item>Point your telescope at the galaxy and take a look. If you have a computerised mount, just enter the co-ordinates of the galaxy and it will find it by itself.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Keep trying. Galaxies are very far away, and this makes them very dim and hard to find. If you can't find it one night, try again tomorrow.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Never look at the sun.</item>
<item>If you're hoping to see images like the amazing photos that you can find on the internet, you're in for a shock. Unless you buy a really powerful and expensive telescope, you won't see very much in the galaxies that you look at.</item></list>
</text>
