<text id="autogum_whow_doc173" title="Learn to Think by Learning to Write" shortTile="learn-think-learning" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-09-04" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Learn-to-Think-by-Learning-to-Write" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Learn to Think by Learning to Write</head><p>Within modern academia, the process of thinking has become somewhat jumbled and one-dimensional. Critical thinking tends to win out over a more relaxed and creative approach, pushing the population toward a strict system of thinking. By taking a look at the process of writing, this article aims to help with separating and individually appreciating these two branches of thought.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Identifying the Types of Thinking</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Identify "first order" thinking.
<list type="unordered"><item>First order thinking is creativity- that frame of thought when you're not worrying about grammar or logic. It's a productive period of brainstorming and simply allowing thoughts to pour out and follow their own sequence of events. You disregard any form of organization or control, and the ideas flow.</item></list></item>
<item>Identify "second order" thinking.
<list type="unordered"><item>You might have heard of second order thinking as revision. It's the type of thinking that you resort to when you're proof-reading an essay or writing an outline. Second order thinking is logical, concise, and meticulous.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Separating "First Order" Thinking from "Second Order" Thinking</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Take a step back.
<list type="unordered"><item>It's easy to let the two types of thinking run together and become a mess of premature revision and lack of content. Loosen your grasp on efficiency and simply allow ideas to flow before you start chopping them up.</item></list></item>
<item>Find a rhythm.
<list type="unordered"><item>Try to consciously break first and second order thinking into separate processes. Write in a stream of conscious style for as long as you can before you start to revise anything, even if you're not making any sense at all. Cycle back and forth between the types of thinking, producing blocks of information and revising them in chunks.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Applying the Process</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be creative.
<list type="unordered"><item>First and second order thinking don't just apply to writing essays. Meaningful thought and writing go hand-in-hand, and the process of writing ideas down before scrutinizing and refining them can be applied almost endlessly, whether you're making a WikiHow article or just trying to figure out where you stand on a political problem. Be creative in your application of first and second order thinking and notice a new depth in your insight!</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't be frightened by a lack of organization and clear direction when brainstorming! Just allow yourself to think freely, without censorship!</item>
<item>Thinking critically and logically are important tools, but so is a more relaxed, and creative thought process. Take time to learn when each mindset works best!</item>
<item>Don't be afraid to write, even when you're confused about an issue that has nothing to do with academics! Writing allows you to examine your thoughts from an outside perspective and really refine your thinking.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't fall into the trap of overactive revision! It's easy to constantly proof-read as you go, but your ideas may never reach their full potential if you're constantly censoring yourself.</item>
<item>Don't completely disregard proof-reading. Even though revision is commonly overused, it is an incredibly important step toward a refined thought.</item></list>
</text>
