<text id="autogum_whow_doc695" title="Know Where North Is" shortTile="know-north" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-12-13" dateModified="2018-08-03" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Know-Where-North-Is" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Know Where North Is</head><p>Regardless of if your compass is broken, you don't have a compass, you lost it, or where you are, if you are lost it is important to know where north is. If you don't you could end up in the desert when you want to be closer to the arctic or vice versa.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Sunrise and Sunset</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Watch the sun
<list type="unordered"><item>The sun always rises and sets from east to west. If you watch the sun and have west to your left and east to your right you are facing north.</item>
<item>Note: This only works if it isn't summer or winter if you are at the arctic or antarctic circle and if you aren't at the equator.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Moonrise and Moonset</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Watch the moon
<list type="unordered"><item>On some clear nights you can't see the stars but you can see the moon. It rises and sets in the same direction as the sun.</item>
<item>Note: This only works if it isn't summer or winter if you are at the arctic or antarctic circle and if you aren't at the equator.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Find the north star</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Watch the stars
<list type="unordered"><item>On a starry night you might be able to see the north star. Contrary to popular belief it isn't the brightest star(Alpha centauri is the brightest). It is the only star that doesn't appear to move in the night sky.</item>
<item>Note: This only works if you are in the northern hemisphere and not at the true north pole. At the true north pole, every direction is south.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Find the southern cross</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Watch the stars
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are in the southern hemisphere you can't see the north star. You can however see the southern cross. The stars at the edges of the cross are like a compass.</item>
<item>Note: This only works if you are not at the true south pole. There, every direction is north.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Arctic and Antarctic summer</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Watch the sun
<list type="unordered"><item>The sun will be at the horizon, still moving east to west. However during the arctic and antarctic summers there is no night.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Arctic and Antarctic winter</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Watch the stars
<list type="unordered"><item>The moon won't be as accurate of a guide during the polar night. The polar night is when it is completely dark for 24 hours in the arctic or antarctic. The stars can still help you at this time.</item></list></item></list>
<head>WCS: Completely Cloudy Polar Night</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Survive in the arctic or antarctic
<list type="unordered"><item>If it is completely cloudy and it is the polar night, the only thing you can do is survive in the arctic or antarctic until you can see the stars again.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Find Orion</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>If you are at the equator Orion will help you find north
<list type="unordered"><item>Note: This works for the northern and southern hemispheres also but only during certain times of the year.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always wear 4 layers in the arctic and more in the antarctic.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Antarctic winds can be as strong as 200 mph(That is about as strong as a category 5 hurricane or an F3 tornado). That is strong enough to blow you across Antarctica into the cold ocean. Water is the worst thing to be in when it is very cold.</item></list>
</text>
