<text id="autogum_whow_doc575" title="Make Owning a Dog Easier" shortTile="make-owning-dog-easier" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2016-02-08" dateModified="2019-08-04" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-Owning-a-Dog-Easier" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make Owning a Dog Easier</head><head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be sure you have time to take care of the dog. You have to be home at all times or most of the times, but being home all day might give you more time to take care of the dog. Your dog may be uncomfortable around you if you don’t have the time.</item>
<item>You need to have a dog that is less playful while indoors. Aim for a breed that is smart. That will help to take care of the dog.</item>
<item>Buy weeks worth of dog food, so you don't have to go and get food everyday. But you need to read the lables to make sure the food doesnt get old, or you can give your dog the amount of food that will be enough and will not be wasted.</item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Potty_Train_Small_Dogs">Potty train your dog</ref>. You will need a leash and a pad. When your dog will need to go to the bathroom, which you can tell if your dog is whining or having an excretion, you take your dog to the pad. Repeat the same thing for a week. If your dog still doesn’t get it, then continue doing the same thing.</item>
<item>For potty training outdoors, you need to see which area outside is avalible for your dog to potty. You need to pick it up with a plastic bag. Turn the bag around and throw it out. You need to do this everyday until your dog knows which area to potty in.</item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Walk_Your_Dog">Walk your dog</ref> in the morning. Wake up the dog before getting your dog because you need to wake up early to walk your dog. If your dog isn’t awake yet, you still need to get up and wait for your dog to get up. It’s ok if your dog doesn’t wake up, because then you know when to wake up.</item>
<item>Giving your dog a bath might be easier by taking your dog to the groomers. You can also do it at home, but in a tub with dog shampoo.</item>
<item>You may need a dogsitter to take care of your dog while you’re not home.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>it makes it easier to own a dog if you get a calm dog like the old english bulldog</item>
<item>it is a good idea to get your friends or a family member to take care of your dog while you are not hom because your dog will get to know the people in your life.it is easier if you com home soon to take care of your dog</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>make sure to bring your dog to the vet and the vet will tell you when to feed your dog what to feed your dog and all the other information.make sure that the dog is safe and doesnt bite</item>
<item>warn the person about the dog what it need and the information</item></list>
</text>
