<text id="autogum_whow_doc633" title="Create a Religious Home Environment" shortTile="create-religious" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-05-06" dateModified="2017-02-09" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Create-a-Religious-Home-Environment" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Create a Religious Home Environment</head><p>For those who are religious, whichever faith you may be, home environments are often a very important thing. You want to instill the right beliefs and morals into your family without pushing them into anything. For some easy steps on how to create a religious home environment, read on! </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Set a good example. As parents we want to give our children the freedom to choose for themselves while still maintaining the kind of discipline that will give them the kinds of rewards and opportunities' that we know they deserve in life. This can be a hard balance to maintain and no parent ever does a perfect job at this. It is far easier to lecture than it is to live up to what we believe in, and this will always be a constant struggle for any parent. Just remember that all of the ascended masters in most of the world's major religions have all taught by example. When it does come time to talk to your children about issues that need to be dealt with you will be more able to do it with conviction and honesty, because you will have learned from experience what really works and doesn't work. When our children see how much happiness that can come into our lives through living up to our religious principles they will be more likely to want to copy us.</item>
<item>Be honest with yourself and others. This always takes a lot of courage.  C.S. Lewis considered courage to to be one of the most important virtue's of mankind.</item>
<item>Forgive yourself for making mistakes. Part of being brutally honest with yourself is admitting to yourself at the end of the day, that as humans beings, you all make mistake's, and you will continue to make mistakes. Some of the best fathers and mothers aren't always the best of best. They just did one thing that even a lot of really wonderful people didn't always do, and that was show up for the job, as much as they could. (let's face it you all have to work and spend time away from home in order to take care of the ones you love) You all will make mistakes, feeling guilty won't change things, taking action will.</item>
<item>Practice, Practice, Practice. Try to have daily scripture reading and family prayer, even if it's only for 10-15 minutes. Once a week  try to have family  Developing healthy daily and weekly habits in both yourselves and in your children, in any aspect of life, just takes good old fashion practice. Any body who's ever achieved any thing great in life will tell you that it took a lot of practice and persistence in order to get good at what they were doing. A peaceful and god fearing home is no exception to that rule!</item>
<item>And of course, last but not least, find joy in both your religion and/or your spiritual beliefs. If your belief system is not uplifting or motivating to you, then it's time to either rethink your interpretation of it, or find one that works best for you. Life is too short to be spent in  belief systems that drag us down, Both religious or otherwise. Ask yourself "what kind of results am I achieving by living this one principle and do I like it"? Children often have a "B.S. detector" that's sharper than yours. They may not logically be able to put facts together in their heads like you can but they will often follow their feelings and gut instincts more than you will. If you are always doing things because you "should" then they will often see right through that even when you can not. This is probably the number one reason why children rebel against their parents. Granted, there will always be moments of struggle, doubt, sacrifice and even hardship, but if your hearts are not in it, then you have to seriously ask yourself if, deep, deep down, you really believe in what you are doing with all of your heart. This is called having a spiritual crises, and believe if or not you all have them from time to time. It is not a sign of moral weakness, but a sign of simply being human. The greatest spiritual teachers throughout history who accomplished the greatest amount of good, did not do it out of a sense of guilt or obligation. They did so out of a sense of great love and conviction for the the moral beliefs that helped them to change and grow and to become the people that they were.</item></list>
</text>
