<text id="autogum_whow_doc528" title="Recover a Clothing Store" shortTile="recover-clothing" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-02-02" dateModified="2018-10-12" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Recover-a-Clothing-Store" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Recover a Clothing Store</head><p>After a busy day in a clothing store or department, don't just walk out, recover the store! When doing this, think of how you would like your store to look  if you were the customer and you'll have plenty of motivation. Get started at step one below.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Start with the fitting rooms. To ensure that the fitting rooms are in a good state, you'll need to deal with the following: <figure rend="Recover a Store Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Take out all of the go backs.</item>
<item>Throw away all the trash left behind by customers.</item>
<item>Spray and wipe down the mirrors.</item>
<item>Take any lost property to the lost and found area. If there is identifying information, make that clear.</item></list></item>
<item>Deal with the go backs. The items that customers tried on and changed their minds about, the items they carried around the store but then dumped in the wrong section, the non-purchased goods left at the cash register and any other items that customers have removed from their original spot will all need to go back to where they belong. To do this: <figure rend="Recover a Store Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Keep all go backs at the cash wrap or assign a special shelf or rack to place them on.</item>
<item>Do a sweep of the store or your section of the store to find misplaced stock.</item>
<item>Put clothing go backs on appropriate hanger or fold them them place them where they belong.</item>
<item>Bring all damaged clothing and items to the break/stockroom.</item>
<item>Look for anything else out of place and put them in the correct location.</item></list></item>
<item>Tidy up the sales floor. To make it easier for the cleaners and to ensure that the next day starts neatly, you'll need to do the following: <figure rend="Recover a Store Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Walk the floor.</item>
<item>Clean up all racks and re-hang, size and color code the clothes. Make sure everything is properly hung and facing the right way.</item>
<item>If there are tables for clothing, fold the clothes neatly and stack them biggest to smallest size. Make sure that the tables look nice and neat,</item>
<item>Keep accessories in the appropriate location (for example, keep the matching purses and wallets next to each other).</item>
<item>Tidy up display areas and any boxes and other items that are stacked anywhere.</item>
<item>Pick up things that have fallen off or have been dropped off shelves.</item></list></item>
<item>Do your daily housekeeping. This will depend on whether you have cleaners coming in or you are responsible, so pick and choose from this list: <figure rend="Recover a Store Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Sweep all around the floors, fitting rooms, behind the cash registers and bathrooms.</item>
<item>Wet mop the floors. Then dry mop.</item>
<item>Spray down counters and wipe them clean.</item>
<item>Wipe down mirrors and windows.</item>
<item>Dust all fixtures.</item>
<item>Gather trash and replace trash bags.</item>
<item>Clean cash register counters. Make sure that the registers are already counted and locked to prevent anything getting lost).</item>
<item>Clean the toilets and bathrooms, if relevant.</item>
<item>Spray room freshener through the store.</item></list></item>
<item>Deal with the cash counter. Lock drawers and put away the money according to your store's policy. <figure rend="Recover a Store Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Wipe down computer screens.</item>
<item>Throw away paper or notes that are unwanted.</item>
<item>Arrange pens, pencils, stapler etc., neatly.</item>
<item>Organize receipts in a box.</item>
<item>Stack all necessary papers.</item>
<item>Mop the floor behind the cash counter.</item>
<item>Wipe down the counters.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If possible, assign one to two associates to each "zone" or section of store, depending on how large your store is.</item>
<item>Fully walk to the floor two to three times, in order to make sure that everything looks beyond great.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Before cleaning at or near the cash wrap, make sure that the registers are locked, off and that the money has already been put away to prevent loss or damages!</item></list>
</text>
