<text id="autogum_whow_doc040" title="Incorporate Art Into Your Life and Into Your Child&apos;s Life" shortTile="incorporate-art-life" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2010-10-15" dateModified="2017-12-05" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Incorporate-Art-Into-Your-Life-and-Into-Your-Child%27s-Life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Incorporate Art Into Your Life and Into Your Child's Life</head><p>Creative?  Yes, You!  If you don’t think so, think back to your childhood days when you made meals out of dirt and water: Yummy MUD PIES… Think back to times when your family was hungry and you hadn’t gone shopping yet and you made real meals out of whatever was in your refrigerator.  That’s simple creativity and some of the best recipes come from days like that!   You don’t have to be born with paint running through your veins to be an artist.   </p>
<p>When we open our hearts and lives to creativity, we also invite other feelings in like:   </p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Stress reduction</item>
<item>Self expression</item>
<item>Inner peace</item>
<item>Increased confidence</item></list>
<p>As a parent, it is not only important for you to live a creative lifestyle, it is equally important for you to teach it to your children.  Your child’s love for the arts will depend a lot upon how you feel about it.  Through the process of creating art, children can:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Increase their awareness of themselves and others</item>
<item>Learn how to control themselves</item>
<item>Cope with stress and negative experiences</item>
<item>Enjoy the pleasures of making art.</item></list>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Always have on hand a variety of creative, artistic materials.  These materials can include, but are certainly not limited to, crayons, markers, paint, clay, various paper styles, glues, and scissors. <figure rend="Incorporate Art Into Your Life and Into Your Child's Life Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Let them experiment. <figure rend="Incorporate Art Into Your Life and Into Your Child's Life Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be specific with your encouragement.  Instead of simply saying “I like your painting”, say, “I like how you used blue for the color of your sun, and the stripes on your frog are amazing!” <figure rend="Incorporate Art Into Your Life and Into Your Child's Life Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don’t guess what their art is; ask them to tell you about it. <figure rend="Incorporate Art Into Your Life and Into Your Child's Life Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Choose a time and place without any interruptions. <figure rend="Incorporate Art Into Your Life and Into Your Child's Life Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don’t rush their creativity.  If they aren’t finished in the time allotted, let them finish it later.  Be sure to follow through with the finish day and time you both decide on. <figure rend="Incorporate Art Into Your Life and Into Your Child's Life Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try not to introduce too much.  If the activity becomes too overwhelming, stop.  Remember it is supposed to be fun, so be patient with their learning abilities. <figure rend="Incorporate Art Into Your Life and Into Your Child's Life Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Now, you are ready to make a self portrait of your creative self.  Here’s how:
<list type="unordered"><item>You will need a piece of paper for each person, and a pencil, scissors, glue, and magazines to share.  Have each person sketch themselves on their piece of paper (simple head, with eyes, nose, mouth, etc. will do).  Cut magazine pages in various colors and small sizes.  This can be done ahead of time.  Form a background behind the sketch with magazine pieces glued down.  Next, have them glue pieces onto their self-portrait sketch.  Place the pieces so that they form the eyes, nose, mouth and hair. Hello, creative you!</item></list></item></list>
</text>
