<text id="autogum_whow_doc440" title="Reduce Noise Levels in Your Apartment" shortTile="reduce-noise-levels" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2007-09-06" dateModified="2018-03-02" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Reduce-Noise-Levels-in-Your-Apartment" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Reduce Noise Levels in Your Apartment</head><p>We’ve all heard the horror stories of noisy neighbours living in the apartment next door. You know, the ones with the barking dogs, screaming babies, super-loud movies and blaring stereos? If this describes your neighbour, don’t let the noise stress you out any longer. Believe it or not, there are several ways you can easily dampen the noise entering your apartment, without getting apartment management or the police involved in the situation. You’ll actually be surprised by how effective these simple techniques can be in reducing the noise levels inside your rental apartment.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Carpeting and Rugs</hi> The more items you have in your apartment that can absorb and soak up sound, the better. Carpets do a surprisingly good job of absorbing sound in the home (instead of reflecting sound, like hardwood floors). But what if your apartment isn’t carpeted? Simple – use rugs. The more throw rugs and area rugs you have around your apartment, and the larger and heavier they are, the more noise they will absorb. <figure rend="Reduce Noise Levels in Your Apartment Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Wall-Hangings and Curtains</hi> Sure, carpets work if it’s the tenants below your apartment that are making all the noise. If it’s the people beside you that you have to worry about, try putting up a few wall-hangings, curtains or tapestries on the side of the apartment that the noise is coming from. These can make a big impact on reducing the amount of noise in your apartment, while also adding a little bit of style to your home at the same time. Curtains or drapes are useful in reducing noise wherever they are located, whether it’s on a wall, over a window (to block out exterior noises) or simply placed across an open space in the apartment. Special soundproof wall-hangings, ceiling panels and room dividers, all of which are made of materials that are specifically designed to block out sound, can also be purchased at specialty shops. <figure rend="Reduce Noise Levels in Your Apartment Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Appropriate Noise Levels – It’s a Two-Way Street</hi> The techniques listed above are excellent suggestions – but they wouldn’t even be necessary if you, your neighbours and everybody else in your apartment building were slightly more aware of the apartment you’re living in and the effect noise has on all of the tenants living there. You can be a more considerate neighbour by following by these common-sense <figure rend="Reduce Noise Levels in Your Apartment Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>·	Place felt cushions under chair and table legs to prevent them from noisily scraping across the floor;</item>
<item>·	Place your stereos and audio equipment away from the walls that are shared with other apartment units;</item>
<item>·	Keep the volume of your computer and TV at reasonable levels, especially late at night. As well, don’t wait until late at night to get started on your other noisy activities such as vacuuming, repairs and moving heavy furniture.</item>
<item>·	Use carpets or mats in areas where objects such as shoes and kitchen utensils are more likely to fall or be dropped;</item>
<item>·	Avoid walking in high heel and hard-soled shoes, especially in apartments for rent with tiled or hardwood floors, as the sound will reverberate throughout your unit and the ones beside you;</item>
<item>.      Try switching the polarity of the cables to your speakers. If one is black into black snaps, trade the other side for red in the black snaps. This will cause destructive interference, canceling the sound at distance.</item></list>
</text>
