<text id="autogum_whow_doc651" title="Run an Effective T‐Ball Practice" shortTile="run-effective-tball" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-05-21" dateModified="2018-06-01" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Run-an-Effective-T%E2%80%90Ball-Practice" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Run an Effective T‐Ball Practice</head><p>Volunteering to coach a T-Ball team for the first time can be a daunting experience. It can be difficult to keep one 4-5-year-old entertained, so the prospect of keeping the attention of an entire team of them could be intimidating. This wikiHow will help you learn how to make the season a fun – and successful – experience for the kids’ development, as well as your sanity.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Expect a wide range of ability on your T-Ball team. Realistically, there will be at least a few kids on your team that haven’t yet been in preschool and are not accustomed to taking directions from adults that aren’t their parents. Some kids will be shy, and others will follow you around the field telling you about their favorite stuffed animal. Some will hit line drives off your every pitch, others won’t be able to hold a bat off their shoulders. Some parents will expect a retired pro player or a 3x World Series champion to be coaching their children. The important thing is to make it fun for the kids, teach the basics of baseball, and to enjoy it along the way.</item>
<item>Begin with stretching exercises and warm-ups. For many children, this may be their first exposure to an organized sport. Learning to stretch out their muscles prior to running and exercising could save them from avoidable injuries in the future. Jumping jacks, “reaching to the sky”, and toe touches are a few good examples of fun stretches at this age. Throwing in a quick verse of the ‘Hokey Pokey’ is sure to get some giggles and laughs from your little ones.  <figure rend="T ball_coach says small.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>“Coach Simon Says” is another fun exercise to stretch their legs while familiarizing them with the field positions. Shout out a position for the kids to flock to, and throw in the traditional “Simon Says” rules.</item></list></item>
<item>Encourage the children to participate in throwing practice drills. It is important to keep the drills simple. Throwing in too many steps may quickly cause children to lose interest or the coach to become impatient. When setting up a target for the children to aim for, you should ensure that it's big enough for a high chance of success. Several ways to make throwing practice drills fun is to use a hoola-hoop or large net as the target for kids to aim at. In addition, it can allow them to build confidence while moving forward. <figure rend="T ball_target small.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>When starting out, using whiffle balls can avoid some serious tears and/or injuries. Advance to standard t-ball level baseballs when ready.</item></list></item>
<item>Start catching practice drills. Catching is the most difficult ability for a preschool or kindergarten age child to perform, and it is one of the last skills children master at the lower levels of Little League. The fine motor skills required to catch the ball will demand precision which isn’t realistic for the majority of children at this age. Therefore, it may be best to stick with grounders and “alligator arms” for now. “Alligator Arms” involves using the un-gloved hand to help secure the ball in the glove as they catch it, similar to an alligator’s mouth chomping down. As with throwing drills, the simpler the drill, the better at this point. <figure rend="Grounder drills small.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Engage in batting drills. Teaching bat safety is of utmost importance at this level. Make sure the children use helmets whenever they hold a bat or are in an area where they may wander into a hitting zone. At this point, there is real value in breaking into smaller groups, which would require having an assistant coach or some helpful parents. One-on-one time is extremely valuable here and will pay dividends throughout the season.  <figure rend="Hitting stations small.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>End with closing out practice. For a 4 or 5-year-old child, paying attention for over an hour can be hard work. To keep it interesting, hard work should be followed up with a fun activity. After throwing aside gloves, a game of freeze tag or a relay race should invoke giggles and cheers. Ending practice on a high note can not only keep it exciting out on the field but also reward kids for all their hard work learning these new skills. <figure rend="Freeze tag small.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep the kids engaged throughout the season. To maintain their attention and connection to baseball, it’s important to build comradery and a love for the game throughout the season. For instance, treating children to a local frozen yogurt shop could be a fun field trip. If there are professional teams near you, you could consider organizing a group trip. In addition, handing out baseball cards after practice is a great way to keep your team excited in the professional game. As a coach, it’s important to remember that you’re an ambassador of the game of baseball for these kids, and above all else, it’s important to make this fun.</item></list>
</text>
