<text id="autogum_whow_doc604" title="Cope in the World of Ego" shortTile="cope-world-ego" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-05-27" dateModified="2019-01-19" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Cope-in-the-World-of-Ego" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Cope in the World of Ego</head><p>Ego is Latin for 'Self'. Everyone has an ego, it is how they want to project themselves to others, how people expect others to treat them, ego is our expectation of our own self. It isn't even a bit simple as it sounds and it tends to get extremely annoying when people impose their ego on us. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be humble. Thy should be humble first in order to cope up with the ego of others. You should be aware of your ego and should restrict its imposition on others - unnecessarily. <figure rend="Cope in the World of Ego Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Acknowledge. People impose their ego or are "egoistic" due to want of acknowledgement and/or acceptance from others. They may not seem like your average attention seekers but they do crave for it - unconsciously. <figure rend="Cope in the World of Ego Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remember. Remember the points of imposition of ego and try not to impose yours in those 'dangerous' waters. <figure rend="Cope in the World of Ego Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Understand. Understand that ego is the image that a person associates with himself and it is natural to be present. It by understanding that everyone is different and unique in their own way that we can cope in the world of ego. <figure rend="Cope in the World of Ego Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Lose to win. When its the war of egos, the first one to lose is actually the winner. If a heated argument is one, lose it. As the argument ends - you win. Though know when you can afford to lose and when it is required to win. <figure rend="Cope in the World of Ego Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be ahead of the curve. Always be ahead of the matters in order to escape the trap of ego conflict. Once the opposition knows you are no longer in their league, you will never be bothered. <figure rend="Cope in the World of Ego Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Learn. Learning how others exert their ego on us, how we exert/impose our ego on others, what is the cause for it, why we do it are some questions worth contemplating over. When we tend to find answers to these questions, coping with ego will seem a lot more easier. <figure rend="Cope in the World of Ego Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Trade fairly. All egoistic people tend to expect something in return from us, either in form of appreciation or favour or applause or flatter or respect or acknowledgement. Knowing this demand and catering to it in our bounds &amp; comfort zone is the right way to tackle and cope with the world of ego. <figure rend="Cope in the World of Ego Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Become a pacifist. Being a pacifist, not being too aggressive or offensive in your opinions or views or speech can be quite helpful in coping with ego. People tend to use their ego as a defense mechanism to protect themselves or their beliefs from what they find to be threatening or offensive. <figure rend="Cope in the World of Ego Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Smile gently and behave in a friendly way.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Being humble never akin to low self image or morale or allowing others to exploit oneself. It just means not to assert thy ego on others - unnecessarily.</item>
<item>Always look out for your imposition of the ego on others.</item></list>
</text>
