<text id="autogum_whow_doc494" title="Fit in the Crowd With Being Who You Are" shortTile="fit-crowd-being" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-01-17" dateModified="2019-08-08" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Fit-in-the-Crowd-With-Being-Who-You-Are" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Fit in the Crowd With Being Who You Are</head><p>You know..
Sometimes we're wondering of what we're going to do in the future.
We keep on wondering, until there's a time where you feel lonely and your life isn't that fun.
Well, get up! Keep on reading this to fit in the crowd without having to change your style or personality. Only changing the way you treat people would make it.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Don't be stubborn when people are telling good compliments about you. This makes people think you're overreacting. Especially for girls. What's the hard thing of saying "Thank You" on every compliment that people are giving? <figure rend="Fit in the Crowd With Being Who You Are Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>"If there's just one kind of folks, why can't they get along with each other? If they're all alike, why do they go out of their way to despise each other?" .. Just look at that quote for a minute. What comes to your mind is about your worst enemy or your hypocrite friend or whatever kind of person that is treating you really bad if I am not wrong. The thing here is, don't start a fight with anyone if you don't know how to end it. Don't say sorry if you don't mean it. It's just going to make people think you're a person, who treats people as you want to. <figure rend="Fit in the Crowd With Being Who You Are Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you have any hidden talents, try to find it out whether it matches to you or whether it's not. If you have found out, show the world your talent(s) and let it be a personal achievement for you if you did something with it. With letting people know your talent(s), you'll get a chance to be called "a unique person" by the crowd. <figure rend="Fit in the Crowd With Being Who You Are Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be honest at every situation. It's the important thing to be honest to everyone you know. Especially when an honesty action is needed, don't hesitate to be honest. <figure rend="Fit in the Crowd With Being Who You Are Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be fun! Don't be mad at every little jokes your friend made on you. It's just a joke and nothing is more. If you're being mad, than.. it means the joke is a fact of which involves you. Unless if someone did a really annoying thing and really mean thing, you can do something. Or, if you found those kinds of people, leave them alone and they're gonna be shy themselves because of their joke aren't accepted by any deal. <figure rend="Fit in the Crowd With Being Who You Are Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be nice to everyone! People won't accept you if you're perfect but mean! when someone needs a help, give them one and don't hesitate of giving your energy. <figure rend="Fit in the Crowd With Being Who You Are Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be who you are. You will fit in the crowd if you're following the tips above. But it doesn't mean you're gonna fit in the crowd happily. The only thing to be happy is being who you are. <figure rend="Fit in the Crowd With Being Who You Are Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>don't change the way you walk, eat, talk or anything. Just be who you are and everything will be just perfect.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>NEVER overreact!</item>
<item>Because that will only make people get annoyed.</item></list>
</text>
