<text id="autogum_whow_doc051" title="Change the Engine Air Filter on a WK2 Jeep Grand Cherokee" shortTile="change-engine-air" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2017-09-29" dateModified="2019-06-24" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Change-the-Engine-Air-Filter-on-a-WK2-Jeep-Grand-Cherokee" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Change the Engine Air Filter on a WK2 Jeep Grand Cherokee</head><p>Maintenance is arguably the most important path to ensuring vehicle longevity. Following the owner's manual maintenance schedule is critical to keeping your vehicle in good condition. Changing the engine air filter on your own can help ensure that the job is done correctly, and will allow you to avoid being overcharged by crooked maintenance shops. The following steps will show you how to change the engine air filter on a WK2 Jeep Grand Cherokee.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><figure rend="0thPic.png"></figure> Get an air filter. Although there is always a lot of controversy on what brand should be purchased, getting an OEM (original equipment manufacturer) will always be your best bet. It is what was tested in your vehicle for optimal efficiency and longevity, and it will not void your warranty if something goes wrong with your air flow system.</item>
<item><figure rend="Broooooooooo.png"></figure> Locate the hood release switch. This switch is located below the "gas cap" release button and has a picture of a car with the hood open. Once found, pull on the switch to release the "safety" latch.</item>
<item><figure rend="2NDPic.png"></figure> Unlatch the hood. Go directly in front, and to the middle of the vehicle. Place hand underneath the hood and locate the latch. Once located, unlatch it and the hood should open up by itself.</item>
<item><figure rend="3rdPic.png"></figure> Locate the air box. The air box is the first stage in which air goes through to get to the engine. It is usually connected to a longer, cylindrical tube. In this Jeep's case, it is behind the drivers side headlight.</item>
<item><figure rend="4thPic.png"></figure> Locate the fasteners. There are 2 fasteners holding the air box in place. Both are located on the same side. One is under the power steering reservoir.</item>
<item><figure rend="5thPic.png"></figure> Release the clip fasteners from place. This is done by simply pushing the fasteners away from the air box. Once off the air box, The clips will stand in place, so there is no worry about losing them.</item>
<item><figure rend="6thPic.png"></figure> Open up the air box. Grab the edge opposite of the black tube, and lift.</item>
<item><figure rend="7thPic.png"></figure> Remove the air filter. Grab on to any side of the filter and take it out. These filters are quite flexible, so don't worry about how you handle them.</item>
<item><figure rend="8thPic.png"></figure> Inspect your filter. According to the owners manual in all WK2 Jeep Grand Cherokee's, these filters should be replaced every . But If the engine is under constant heavy loads, like when towing, or driving in dusty areas, these filters might need replacing more often. Take a look and see how the condition of your filter is, and replace it accordingly.</item>
<item><figure rend="9thPic.png"></figure> Place new filter in. It is very important that you pay attention to the "air flow" directional arrow. This will let you know how to place in the filter. Luckily, these filters are only designed to fit in one way, with the fenced off metal portion facing the hood. So there is no way of messing up this step!</item>
<item><figure rend="10thPic.png"></figure> Secure air box back into place. Place the air box back into the original position. Once back into the original position, secure the clips back on to the air box.</item>
<item><figure rend="Sure.png"></figure> Close the hood. After disposing of the old air filter and closing the hood, you're good to go back on the road!</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Wear gloves to help keep dirt from underneath your nails and to help protect your hands from minor cuts or scratches.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do NOT change your air filter while the car is on. Opening up the air box while the car is on will not allow air flow to travel to the engine. This will cause your engine to run rich (to much fuel to air mixture), and leave unburned fuel in the exhaust system, which could cause carbon build up.</item></list>
</text>
