<text id="autogum_whow_doc433" title="Ride a Destination Dispatch Elevator" shortTile="ride-destination" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-01-08" dateModified="2019-06-24" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Ride-a-Destination-Dispatch-Elevator" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ride a Destination Dispatch Elevator</head><p>A destination dispatch elevator is an elevator that uses a different algorithm than most elevators.  Unlike most elevators, there are no floor buttons inside the lift, or, if there are floor buttons, they are usually disabled.  Knowing how to use a destination dispatch elevator is important if you encounter one.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Before You Enter the Car</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Approach the keypad or touchscreen knowing your destination floor.</item>
<item>Enter your destination floor on the keypad or touchscreen.
<list type="unordered"><item>To return to the ground floor, press the  key, and to go to any basement floors, press the  or  key followed by the basement number.</item>
<item>If you have a disability, press the handicap  button and follow the prompts read aloud to you.  This will also hold the elevator doors open for longer when the elevator arrives.</item></list></item>
<item>Proceed to the car listed on the display.  Follow the arrow.  The elevator will group you to a car going to the specified destination floor.
<list type="unordered"><item>The appropriate elevator hall lantern will also light up and will blink upon arrival.</item></list></item>
<item>Wait for the doors to open. Then confirm the lift is going to your destination floor by checking the floor numbers on the inside or outside of the car match the number of your destination floor.  Once you have confirmed that, step onto the elevator, be mindful of the gap, and hold the doors for all the other passengers.</item></list>
<head>Inside the Elevator</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Allow all passengers going to your floor to board the car.  Destination dispatch elevators group passengers by putting passengers going to similar floors in the same car, reducing the number of stops.</item>
<item>Press the "Door close" button like normal once everyone entered the car.  This may not work if you pressed the handicapped "♿" button.</item>
<item>Watch the floor indicator and/or the numbers on the door jamb.  Your number will blink when you are about to arrive at your floor.</item>
<item>Be courteous of other passengers.  Practice normal elevator etiquette under <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Ride_an_Elevator">Ride an Elevator</ref>.  Destination dispatch elevators are still elevators, they just use a different algorithm that you need to be aware of.</item>
<item>Exit promptly when your floor comes.  You do not want to be carried past your floor, as it wastes more time on a floor you do not want to go to.  Plus, there are no floor buttons, so you cannot just select your floor.  Should you miss your floor, exit at the next floor, enter your destination floor, and repeat the process again.</item></list>
<head>Responding if the Elevator Stops</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Locate the floor panel.  The floor buttons on the panel are disabled, except in emergencies.</item>
<item>Press the floor buttons like on normal lifts.  Sometimes, the destination dispatch system fails, forcing passengers to push floor buttons like they had to before destination dispatch.</item>
<item>Press the  and  button.  Sometimes, the door jerks open while the elevator is in motion.  This breaks the safety and applies the emergency brake.</item>
<item>Press the  button.  Newer elevators will call for help should the alarm button be held for extended periods of time.</item>
<item>Press the  button.  Give the operator the elevator number, which floor you are at, and any other useful information.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Travelling in a group?  Press the group button or enter your floor as many times as there are passengers.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not ride elevators in the case of a fire, a building evacuation, or any other emergency.</item>
<item>Do not overload an elevator.  An elevator that is overloaded will announce it is overloaded and refuse to move.  You can also break the elevator or its cables, causing serious injuries.</item>
<item>Do not attempt to obstruct the doors with limbs to hold it open.  Once the elevator alarm sounds, the doors will continue to close and ignore any sensor input that holds the door open.</item>
<item>Do not ride an elevator that was taken out of service.  The elevator could malfunction, causing serious injury or death.</item></list>
</text>
