<text id="autogum_whow_doc206" title="Handle an Aggressive Child" shortTile="handle-aggressive" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2017-12-04" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Handle-an-Aggressive-Child" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Handle an Aggressive Child</head><p>If a child repeatedly acts aggressively, you might wonder “What am I doing wrong?” Instead of getting down on yourself about a child's tendency to shout, hit, or push, use the problem as a benchmark for teaching the child more appropriate ways to behave. Be sure not to respond to their aggression with your own. Keep your cool and show the child how to problem-solve common situations and express themselves using assertiveness.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Reacting to Aggression</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Stay calm. Resist the urge to behave aggressively yourself. Take a few deep breaths or silently count to 10 to maintain your composure. <figure rend="Handle an Aggressive Child Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>When you are in control of your own emotional reaction, the child can look to your example for managing tough situations.</item></list></item>
<item>Remove the child from the environment. Break aggressive behaviors by making the child leave the situation. For example, if they are playing rough with siblings, make them take a timeout. <figure rend="Handle an Aggressive Child Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If they act up in the grocery store, leave. If you're shopping with a companion, have that person escort them outside.</item>
<item>If the child purposefully uses aggression to get out of undesirable activities or situations, use another approach. Don't allow them to leave.</item></list></item>
<item>Don’t spank the child. Because you're trying to instill the idea that aggression isn't the solution, avoid spanking an aggressive child. Instead, use consequences that help them actually learn from their mistakes and inspire better behavior in the future. <figure rend="Handle an Aggressive Child Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For instance, you might have the aggressive child repeat writing a sentence, like “I will not push in line. I will keep my hands to myself and wait until my turn.”</item></list></item>
<item>Set clear limits and adhere to clear consequences. Be sure the child knows what's expected of them by explaining the rules. Post them in a common area, such as on the refrigerator or in the common room. When the child breaks a rule, calmly state what they did wrong and the consequence for their acting out. <figure rend="Handle an Aggressive Child Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Say something like, “We don't kick one another, Bryan. Because you kicked your brother, you won't be allowed to finish watching the show. Go to your room and read a book.”</item></list></item>
<item>Be consistent with discipline. Across situations and caregivers, it's important to maintain consistency. Don't overlook aggressive behaviors at home, but discipline the child when they occur in public. Similarly, if one parent sets a rule or consequences for aggression, the other parent needs to get on board also. <figure rend="Handle an Aggressive Child Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you don't consistently stop and address aggressive behavior, the child won't be motivated (or reminded) to change it.</item></list></item>
<item>Take a timeout to regulate your own emotions if the child hurts you. If you get caught in the middle of the child's aggression, take a moment to take care of yourself. Tell the child "Ow, you hurt me! I will talk to you once I've calmed down." Then, go into another room, nurse your wounds, and calm down before enforcing any consequences. <figure rend="Handle an Aggressive Child Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>It's easy to respond unfavorably if the aggressive child has caused you physical pain. To prevent a reaction that starts a cycle of violence, pause and take care of yourself first.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Building New Habits</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Brainstorm replacement behaviors. Once you tell the child that their behavior is unacceptable, encourage them to use their words to think of solutions. You might say, “Can you think of a better way to ask for the toy?” <figure rend="Handle an Aggressive Child Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Role-play how the child should react. Go over effective ways of reacting to common situations together. Act as the other person and let the child practice using their words to express themselves or ask for something. <figure rend="Handle an Aggressive Child Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, you might practice letting the child ask nicely to use something rather than pushing another child or snatching away a toy.</item></list></item>
<item>Reward appropriate behaviors. Increase the child's likelihood of behaving appropriately by praising or rewarding those behaviors when you see them. Say, “I like how you used your words!” or give them a treat for practicing self-control. <figure rend="Handle an Aggressive Child Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Rewarding positive behavior is a much more effective method than punishing the child for negative behavior.</item></list></item>
<item>Channel aggressive energy in positive ways. Help the child release energy in adaptive ways like exercising or playing. Let the child run in the park, do jumping jacks, or play Frisbee with the dog to release aggressive energy. Some children need more frequent and consistent outdoor time than others, and this could be the case for this child.\ <figure rend="Handle an Aggressive Child Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Having these outlets might reduce their aggressive, acting-out behaviors.</item></list></item>
<item>Appeal to the child's self-interest. Help them see that acting out gets them into trouble and doing replacement behaviors helps them avoid consequences. Show them what's in it for them when they behave appropriately. <figure rend="Handle an Aggressive Child Step 11.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You might say, “You get into trouble when you push or hit. When you use your words, you are more likely to get what you want.”</item>
<item>Whether you're dealing with a teen or a younger child, you won't necessarily curb aggressive behaviors by trying to make the child empathetic to the victim.</item>
<item>Continue to make it very clear that aggressive behaviors won't be tolerated.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Seeking Help for Aggression</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Look for patterns in their aggression. Most kids act out in the same ways over and over again. Spotting these recurring patterns can help you get to the core problem. <figure rend="Handle an Aggressive Child Step 12.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For instance, maybe the adolescent is more likely to push and hit when they are feeling scared. Perhaps the toddler kicks when they are tired.</item>
<item>Noticing the context of aggressive behavior can help you come up with practical solutions, such as addressing the child's fear or ensuring they are well-rested.</item></list></item>
<item>Get feedback from others. Coordinate with other caregivers and teachers to determine if they witness aggressive behavior. Talking to others can also clue you in on the cause of the behaviors. <figure rend="Handle an Aggressive Child Step 13.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For instance, maybe the child has been acting out at school. If the behaviors aren't happening at home or in other environments, you may need to work with the school to address the root cause, which could be bullying or even a learning delay.</item></list></item>
<item>See a therapist. If you feel stumped about handling the aggressive child, consider seeing a professional. They can work with the child to figure out the unmet underlying need that leads to aggression. They can also teach you more positive parenting practices to curb aggressive behavior in the child. <figure rend="Handle an Aggressive Child Step 14.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
