<text id="autogum_whow_doc542" title="Adopt a Pet if You&apos;re a Senior" shortTile="adopt-pet-re-senior" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2010-05-26" dateModified="2019-07-16" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Adopt-a-Pet-if-You%27re-a-Senior" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Adopt a Pet if You're a Senior</head><p>As a senior it can be hard to get out and about, so a nice companion in the home is a good opportunity for company and a source of happiness.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Decide which pet is best for you. If you have limited mobility it is probably best to go for a low maintenance pet that won't require regular physical exercise and constant clean up. A cat, a hamster, or a bird may be a good choice if you want a pet you can physically interact with. However, aquarium pets can bring much joy and are very easy to maintain. If you aren't a fish person, many aquarium hobbyists are fascinated with colorful species of dwarf shrimp, dwarf frogs, and if your budget isn't tight, jellyfish are currently being domesticated. <figure rend="Adopt a Pet if You're a Senior Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Research your decided pet. Obviously you will have already done some of this to make the decision, but in-depth knowledge on the specifics will be needed in order to have a successful relationship between you and your pets. Knowing things such as diseases the species and/or breed is prone to, the amount of space needed, and special care or treatment commonly needed in old age. Other details such as portion amounts, what might annoy your pet, and what pleases them will also be useful in growing the bond between you and your new friend. <figure rend="Adopt a Pet if You're a Senior Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure the requirements of the pet fit your lifestyle. Never cut corners with an animal. Check that if you live in an apartment complex that the needs of your pet comply with the standards set by the landlord. Also, make sure the services and care you can provide meet (better yet, exceed) the requirements of your pet. <figure rend="Adopt a Pet if You're a Senior Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Prepare for the arrival of your new friend. Purchase all needed materials and assemble them before you purchase your new pet. This will make the transition from the pet store to their forever home much less stressful, for both the pet and yourself. <figure rend="Adopt a Pet if You're a Senior Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>For cats and dogs, make sure that you are purchasing from a healthy pet from a reputable breeder. An independent breeder is your best bet since you can in most cases see the parents and the conditions they have been living in. If you do go to a pet store to purchase the animal, ask lots of questions and talk to someone informed. Pick the best available animal: one that looks healthy with a friendly demeanor. <figure rend="Adopt a Pet if You're a Senior Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure if they are contained, their container will not fall over on the way home. If they are to be let roam around (which is not advised) make sure they are in an area where they will not disrupt your driving. <figure rend="Adopt a Pet if You're a Senior Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take caution around them for the first couple weeks. Make sure they are comfortable and don't show signs of stress or disease. If they do, be sure to call the solicitor and let them know. <figure rend="Adopt a Pet if You're a Senior Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you find yourself incapable of physically going out to purchase the supplies and pet, most pet stores will happily ship the supplies to your step. In the matter of purchasing the actual pet, shipping would not be in the pets best interest. However, employing a neighbor or youth would be perfectly fine. The Internet these days lets you preview the stock of mammals in most pet stores.If you are going for reptilian or aquatic, just inform the person picking them up of what to look for and if you have specific color preferences.</item></list>
</text>
