<text id="autogum_whow_doc665" title="Do Team Building Exercises" shortTile="team-building-exercises" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2012-03-04" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Do-Team-Building-Exercises" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Do Team Building Exercises</head><p>Team building exercises can be an excellent way to boost morale, encourage productivity, and build trust among your staff. It can also help you identify assets and areas in need of improvement. Start with simple activities that let you break the ice and focus on communication, collaboration, and trust. That way, you can lead group exercises that will help your team work more effectively--and have fun at the same time.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Doing Communication Exercises</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Play Question Ball. Have team members write simple questions (such as “what is your favorite food? or “what’s the last movie you watched?”) on a beach ball. Everyone stands in a circle and tosses the beach ball around, and each team member that catches it has to answer the question that is closest to their pinkie finger. <figure rend="Do Team Building Exercises Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This will help break the ice if your team is fairly new or doesn’t often interact in person.</item></list></item>
<item>Do a Story Puzzle. Print out the pages of a children’s picture book and cut the text off of each page. Hand pages out to team members in random order. Team members must describe the picture on their page (without showing it) and figure out together what order the pages should go in. The whole team will have to participate and communicate effectively to achieve success. <figure rend="Do Team Building Exercises Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Play Sneak Peek. Build a small structure out of children’s blocks and hide it out of view. Divide your team into groups. Each group can have one member come look at the block structure for 10 seconds, then return to the group to describe it as well as possible. Each group must try to draw the structure from their member’s descriptions. <figure rend="Do Team Building Exercises Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This exercise can be particularly helpful if you feel that some of your team members are not prioritizing thorough communication in their work.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Trying Cooperation Exercises</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Do a Barter Puzzle. Divide your team into groups and give each one a simple jigsaw puzzle. The twist is that each puzzle is mixed up with the others, which means each group has to get their missing pieces from the other groups. They can do this through bartering pieces or even trading members, but each strategy has to be decided on by the group as a whole. <figure rend="Do Team Building Exercises Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you don’t get much face time with your team or if you manage them remotely, this can be a good way to observe group dynamics.</item></list></item>
<item>Build an Egg Drop. Teams must work together with limited supplies (for instance, paper, rubber bands, pencils, straws, tape) to construct a package that can keep an egg safe during an 8-foot drop. This is a great way to encourage cooperation and see how each group works together. <figure rend="Do Team Building Exercises Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do a Human Knot. Have everyone stand in a circle. Each member reaches out their right hand and grabs someone else’s hand at random. Do the same thing with left hands. The goal is for the group to untangle themselves until they can form a circle again, without letting go of the hands they’re holding. <figure rend="Do Team Building Exercises Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Teams will learn to cooperate by working together to determine who should move where, and coming to a consensus on the most effective strategy.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Using Trust Exercises</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Play Blindfold Minefield: Team members divide into pairs, with one wearing a blindfold. Pairs have to navigate a parking lot or other open space full of obstacles (such as chairs, boxes, etc.). The team member who can see must clearly communicate to the blind-folded one where to walk. <figure rend="Do Team Building Exercises Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This can be a good method for strengthening relationships between team members who have had previous conflicts.</item></list></item>
<item>Write Shout-outs. Write each team member’s name on a piece of paper. Have everyone choose one name from a hat and write a “shout-out” to that person, thanking them for something they did well recently. This will encourage team members to recognize and appreciate people they may otherwise rarely interact with, and form positive connections in the group. <figure rend="Do Team Building Exercises Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This exercise is particularly helpful if office drama has had your team on edge lately.</item></list></item>
<item>Do trust falls. Have team members gather in a circle and trade off standing in the center. The person standing in the center will close their eyes, fold their arms and fall backwards, allowing the people in the circle to catch them. <figure rend="Do Team Building Exercises Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Although this is a classic team building exercise, it may not be an ideal activity for every group. Consider whether every member of the team would be physically and emotionally comfortable taking part.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Encouraging Participation and Enhancing Impact</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Choose a time and place that’s convenient for everyone. Make sure you know everyone’s schedule. Avoid choosing a time when team members will be overwhelmed with work, or unable to attend for any other reason. <figure rend="Do Team Building Exercises Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>In order to prepare your team for an especially demanding time, you may want to plan your exercise(s) before a big meeting or project. (Do this only if you are not under a tight deadline.)</item></list></item>
<item>Explain your goals for team building. Communicating what you hope the exercises will accomplish will help your team understand the purpose behind what they’re doing, and encourage them to focus on positive outcomes. Businesses that clearly communicate and track their goals are more likely to meet them. Some common goals for team building are: <figure rend="Do Team Building Exercises Step 11.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Boosting morale</item>
<item>Improving communication</item>
<item>Identifying strengths and weaknesses</item>
<item>Increasing productivity</item>
<item>Establishing trust</item></list></item>
<item>Provide an incentive for team members to participate. Team building exercises are often assumed to be awkward or unnecessary, so team members may be unmotivated at first. Sweeten the deal by buying a pizza for everyone to share, or having the exercises take place at a fun location like the beach. <figure rend="Do Team Building Exercises Step 12.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you plan on doing the exercises outside of normal working hours, you should offer to pay your employees for their time or offer significant compensation in some other way.</item></list></item>
<item>End by acknowledging the work your team has done. Mention specific successes and achievements, emphasizing how the group(s) worked together during the exercises. This is also a good time to recognize the team’s achievements in general and thank them for the work they do, which is important in maintaining positive working relationships. <figure rend="Do Team Building Exercises Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get feedback from your employees after the exercises. Whether you lead an informal de-briefing afterwards or invite team members to write anonymous comments, their feedback will be valuable in determining how effective the exercises were and how they can be improved. <figure rend="Do Team Building Exercises Step 14.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Invite team members to make their own suggestions for future activities. Improving engagement means continuing to find new and interesting ways to encourage teamwork.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
