<text id="autogum_whow_doc697" title="See the World&apos;s Most Beautiful Mountains" shortTile="see-worlds-beautiful" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-07-03" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/See-the-World%27s-Most-Beautiful-Mountains" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>See the World's Most Beautiful Mountains</head><p>The world is filled with beautiful mountains, from majestic ranges like the Ozark and the Himalayas to single breathtaking peaks like Mt. Everest. Depending on where you live, seeing such wonders may be as simple as a Sunday afternoon drive or as complex as a trip around the world. Here are a few suggestions that will show you how to see the world's most beautiful mountains.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Decide where you want to go. This first step may be the most difficult, as there are many factors to consider before narrowing your choice down to a final destination. <figure rend="See the World's Most Beautiful Mountains Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Set a time to go. Do you want to explore the mountains in the mild and beautiful weather of springtime, or are you more interested in seeing snow-capped peaks?</item>
<item>Set a budget. Will you be going to see the mountains that are close to home, or do you prefer to travel around the world to see more exotic locations?</item>
<item>Determine your activities. What do you want to do when you get to the mountains? Is hiking and sightseeing on the agenda? Will you be discovering your inner primal man (or woman) with some serious camping, hunting and fishing? Or is sipping hot chocolate in front of a roaring fire after a long day on the slopes more your idea of the ideal mountain trip?</item></list></item>
<item>Decide how to get there. <figure rend="See the World's Most Beautiful Mountains Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Enlist the help of a reputable travel agency to put together an affordable itinerary for a longer trip to explore the mountains.</item>
<item>Choose an experienced adventure travel company that provides guides and activities for the more extreme vacationer.</item></list></item>
<item>Pack for the trip. <figure rend="See the World's Most Beautiful Mountains Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Pack according to the length of your stay and the activities you plan on enjoying once you're there. Packing for a camping trip to the mountains will be quite different than packing for a ski trip or an afternoon picnic, so make your list and plan accordingly.</item></list></item>
<item>Hit on the road! Stay safe, enjoy the trip, and when you get home you'll have a ton of memories to share and look back on as you plan your next trip to the mountains. <figure rend="See the World's Most Beautiful Mountains Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't be too ambitious. For example, if you're not an experienced hiker,you may not want to take on the Appalachian Trail your first time out. Go see a mountain that offers activities you and your trip mates will enjoy, and that are equal to your level of experience.</item>
<item>Build time into your schedule to relax. Enjoying a beautiful mountain is tough to do if you've planned too many activities. Leave space for some quiet time to sit back and drink it all in.</item>
<item>Research the area. There are plenty of travel books and websites devoted to the world's mountains that can give you the perspective of travelers who have already been there and know what the place has to offer.</item>
<item>Seek out some local flavor. Look for the little out-of-the way places when it comes to shopping and dining. Why eat in a chain restaurant you can eat in at home when there are plenty of locally-owned places that will give you a real feel for the mountain area you've come to see.</item></list>
</text>
