<text id="autogum_whow_doc204" title="Help a Suicidal Child" shortTile="help-suicidal-child" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-01-29" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Help-a-Suicidal-Child" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Help a Suicidal Child</head><p>Children and adolescents may not always know how to articulate what they're feeling inside, which means they may have trouble asking for help when they need it. If you think a child is suicidal, the most important thing you can do is to take it seriously. Take precautions to keep them safe and get them professional help. After setting them up with a professional, be supportive and suggest constructive activities that help them feel better.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Reacting to Suicidal Behavior</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Know the warning signs of suicidal behavior. Most youth demonstrate some red flags in their behavior that indicate they are considering suicide. A sense of hopelessness about the future and comments or plans pertaining to suicide are often clear indicators. However, other warning signs may include: <figure rend="Help a Suicidal Child Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Experiencing changes in sleep or eating habits</item>
<item>Withdrawing from friends and family, spending more time alone</item>
<item>Displaying acting out or angry behaviors</item></list></item>
<item>Take threats seriously. If you spot any of these warning signs in a child, take action immediately. Come straight out and ask them if they are feeling suicidal or thinking of hurting themself. <figure rend="Help a Suicidal Child Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Some people think a child may say things like, "I don't want to live anymore" or "Everyone would be better off if I were dead" to get attention. Such threats are often cries for help from adolescents who don't know how to cope with what they are feeling, and these types of statements should be taken seriously.</item>
<item>Never ignore threats or warning signs that a child is feeling suicidal.</item></list></item>
<item>Don't leave a suicidal child alone. If you suspect a child is suicidal, stay with them. Make sure that they are with someone around the clock until the threat passes, or until they are able to seek professional help. <figure rend="Help a Suicidal Child Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remove any weapons or drugs. Check the environment for any knives, guns, narcotic medications, or anything else that can be used as a weapon. Lock these items away so the child cannot use them to hurt themself. <figure rend="Help a Suicidal Child Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get them to a professional as soon as possible. Most suicidal youth have an untreated psychiatric disorder such as <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Help_a_Depressed_Child">depression</ref>. Have the child seen by a professional <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Choose_a_Mental_Health_Counselor_or_Psychotherapist">therapist</ref> who can help alleviate symptoms of depression and get to the root of the issue. <figure rend="Help a Suicidal Child Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The child may require therapy and/or medications, depending on the underlying cause.</item>
<item>In the meantime, the therapist will likely create a safety plan for the child, which includes contact numbers and resources they can access if they feel suicidal.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Offering Support</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Encourage them to talk. The child may feel better if they talk about the thoughts and feelings they are having. Ask, “Do you want to talk about it?" to encourage them to open up. <figure rend="Help a Suicidal Child Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The child may resist your efforts to get them talking. If this happens, make sure they know that you are open to talk whenever they feel ready.</item></list></item>
<item>Be an <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Actively_Listen">active listener</ref>. If the child or adolescent wants to talk to you, practice active, non-judgemental listening. Turn to face them, make eye contact, and hear what they're saying without interrupting. <figure rend="Help a Suicidal Child Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Avoid saying things like "You should have..." or "I can't believe you would think that way." These comments can come off as judgmental and critical. Simply be there and allow them to share their feelings.</item></list></item>
<item>Show empathy for what they're feeling. Rather than criticizing them, be empathetic and compassionate. Let the child know that you understand where they are coming from. <figure rend="Help a Suicidal Child Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This might sound like, "I can see that you have been dealing with this for a while" or "It seems like you've been very overwhelmed."</item></list></item>
<item>Attend a support group together. Help the child overcome suicidal thoughts and feel less alone in what they're going through. You can do this by accompanying them to a suicide support group for youth. <figure rend="Help a Suicidal Child Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>These groups offer practical strategies for dealing with upsetting thoughts and feelings as well as support and encouragement.</item>
<item>Ask the child's therapist to recommend support groups in your area.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Improving Their Outlook</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Exercise">Exercise</ref> with them to brighten their mood. Physical activity releases feel-good chemicals called endorphins. Endorphins can help the child feel more energetic and have a more positive outlook. Try exercising for at least 30 minutes each day. <figure rend="Help a Suicidal Child Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>By exercising with them, you'll help them engage socially and make sure they are doing something good for their bodies.</item>
<item>Consider going for a walk around the neighborhood, shooting hoops, or going for a swim.</item></list></item>
<item>Encourage them to spend time doing things they enjoy. Drive a budding photographer to a beautiful landscape for pictures. Purchase lessons for a child who is interested in guitar or piano. <figure rend="Help a Suicidal Child Step 11.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Hobbies and passions can help the child feel better about life and remember things they are good at.</item></list></item>
<item>Work with them to pare down their responsibilities. The child may be stressed out due to demanding school work and extracurricular activities. Sit down with them and look at their schedule. Are they over-committing? <figure rend="Help a Suicidal Child Step 12.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If so, help them trim down their weekly routine so that they have a more balanced, realistic schedule.</item></list></item>
<item>Encourage social activities over solo ones. Suicidal children may be more likely to pull away from others and spend time alone. Stress the importance of social engagement and provide opportunities for them to spend time with friends and family. <figure rend="Help a Suicidal Child Step 13.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Host a BBQ and invite kids from school or the neighborhood, or plan a family movie or game night.</item>
<item>You might also encourage the child to join new clubs or organizations at school so they can make new friends.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>While there are things you can do to help and support your child, remember that nobody can entirely prevent suicide. You cannot control your child’s thoughts or actions. What you can do is be supportive and encouraging, give them the help and resources they need to get better, and let them know that you are there for them.</item></list>
</text>
