<text id="autogum_whow_doc631" title="Make a case for Pandeism" shortTile="make-case-pandeism" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2016-05-27" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-a-case-for-Pandeism" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make a case for Pandeism</head><p>Pandeism is a theological theory originating in Germany in the 18th Century, which proposes that our Universe has a Creator which set forth our Universe by becoming our Universe.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Evaluate the rationality of your conversant. Pandeism is a theological theory born from reason and derived from logical thought; and so a person who is irrational, unreasonable, incapable of logical thought, will simply not have the mental tools necessary to comprehend Pandeism. And likewise, a person who has such tools but will not exercise them out of fear, psychological conditioning, or outright ego-driven arrogance, will not be able to grasp what Pandeism proposes. Now, mind you, this is not a claim that any rational or reasonable person will necessarily find Pandeism compelling to believe, but it takes such a mindset to understand the theory well enough to fairly consider it.</item>
<item>Establish that both participants in the conversation recognize their own nonomniscience. The only way that anybody could know anything absolutely is if that person was omniscient; but as that state of being applies to no human, it is a lie to claim to know anything absolutely, and doubly so to make such claims as to any spiritual reality, of which it is well recorded that men very convincingly have contradictory experiences. And so, no person can honestly claim to know the truth; everything we believe may be mistaken.</item>
<item>Establish the known parameters of our Universe. Since we know we are nonomniscient, we can not know if our Universe is infinite or eternal, but it appears to be expanding from a point from which it originated approximately 13.72 billion years ago. If it began from a point and continues expanding, it can not be infinite. Even for those unable to understand the science supporting this determination of the age of our Universe, it must be conceded that as we are nonomniscient, so are we incapable of grasping an universal infinitude.</item>
<item>Establish that there are a great many religions in the world, and that as a matter of empirical fact, every one of which has failed in its efforts to be adopted by a majority of the world's people. Indeed, each religion is rejected by billions of people, and the number of unbelievers as to each is billions more than the number of believers as to each. And further establish that most every religion has texts or claims passed down from the founders believed by followers to be holy and truthful, and that most every religion reports miracles of healing and enlightenment and so on by followers of that religion appealing solely to the deity as outlined in their own religious texts. Your conversant may claim that believers in faiths other than his own have been deceived, but such a claim simply establishes that it is possible for anybody to fervently belief in the rightness of their faith and their religious texts and their deity, and yet to have been deceived into so believing. Through this understanding it is established that what each person has in their religion -- or even in their irreligion -- is a guess, a matter of faith, an unassured possibility.</item>
<item>Establish that if we presume ours to be a created Universe, then the possibility exists that an entity able to create such a Universe would have been equally able to create it ex materia (out of its own substance) as ex nihilo (out of nothing). And if it does have the power to have created our Universe ex materia, there is then no reason to presume that it either possessed or exercised a power to create ex nihilo.</item>
<item>Establish that any sufficiently intelligent being able to have created our Universe ex materia would have, as well, the ability to create it evolutionarily. Such a Creator could create by setting forth energy and initial conditions of physics designed to unfold through a series of processes until such time as planets form, life arises, intelligence evolves, and the intelligent beings so evolving invent languages and writing, and put into writing all manner of stories reflecting some glimmer of a universal memory of a Creator having become our Universe in order to experience existence through it. And this is Pandeism.</item></list>
</text>
