<text id="autogum_whow_doc118" title="Become an Internet Master" shortTile="become-internet-master" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2017-01-24" dateModified="2018-08-08" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Become-an-Internet-Master" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Become an Internet Master</head><p>A new common culture is arising from the increasingly ubiquitousness of technology in our everyday lives. It became really relevant part of communication and spreading of trend. If you are new to this it can be really difficult to understand because often a stratification of layer of meaning or has to be seen as very ironic/ post-ironic critic.Here's a little step by step guide into the Internet Culture.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Browse 4chan.4chan is an image board where you can post anonymously. Since it is a community you have to learn and respect the rules, if you don’t like them you can go to a similar website like 8 chan or other image board like reddit, imgur or 9gag. The member of the community usually refers to each other using the term /b/ros. There’s a specific language that you should learn in order to get along with the other users. The website is divided into different categories depending on the topic, learning the difference between each boards can be very useful. Users can open a thread about a certain issue, each thread is identified by an automatically random generated number. There are some moderators that can ban you if your comments or threads are inappropriate, but basically it doesn’t have really strict censorship rules like Facebook or Instagram.</item>
<item>Get into a weird Facebook group. Weird Facebook, or Post-Ironic Facebook is a loose agglomeration of Facebook pages, also known as “Meme Pages,” that create and distribute dank memes, often along a certain theme or topic. Many of these pages have become popular both because of their absurd humor, but also because of possible advantages given to the “Page” format in the Facebook algorithm. If you get into the group you can follow the spreading process of viral content and you can be aware of the meaning of what you see on your Facebook home.</item>
<item>Drown in Deep Web. The deep web, invisible web, or hidden web are parts of the World Wide Web whose contents are not indexed by standard search engines for any reason. To surf the deep web you’ll need a specific browser called Tor.  The deep web includes many very common uses such as web mail, online banking but also paid for services with a paywall such as video on demand, and many more. But of course is also the place where a lot of illegal activities take place. You can buy drugs (on Silkroad that was a kind of ebay for illegal substances), weapons, fake documents, hacking services and datas, but it was also used by terrorists to keep in touch. To buy on the deep web you’ll need Bitcoin, a cryptocurrency and a payment system invented by an unidentified programmer, or group of programmers, under the name of Satoshi Nakamoto.  For its elitarian nature deep web was chosen to reach an alternative public rather than the surface web. A lot of indie-alternative games are only available there (Sad Satan is the most famous) and also a popular experimental music group, called Death Grips choose the deep web for the release of one of their album “No Love Deep Web”.</item>
<item>Scroll Tumblr. Tumblr is a blogging social network. When you register you automatically create your own blog. There you can post your own contents or reblog other people. You can have many blogs from one profile and dedicate each blog to a specific topic. Tumblr is mostly used by teenager this explains the large amount of porn and self harm/suicidal content. It’s a kind of journal but mostly composed from images, through which you share your own aesthetic. The more you get followers, likes and got reblogged the more you become popular on tumblr. The most popular tumblr has actually reached 100 000 followers and is kept from a 16 year old girl. Tumblr has a really precise aesthetic and was for a long time the cradle of a lot of artistic currents on the internet like tumblr-core, sea punk, vaporwave, health goth, sad boys etc...</item>
<item>Sleep deprivation is good. To proficiency into becoming a master of the internet the best thing is to sleep not more than 4 hours a night. If you think going out can distract you form the real joy of becoming an Internet master avoid any social contact outside, except convention where the main topic is Internet or any subculture related. Buy sugary soft drink or energy drink and junk food so you won’t need to waste time in cooking. Get into online gaming, became a moderator of a forum and find your own community on the internet.</item>
<item>Praise Kek. The Cult of Kek, also known as the Church of Kek, is a satirical religion based around the worship of the ancient Egyptian deity Kek (also spelled Kuk or Keku), an androgynous God of darkness and chaos who is often depicted as a frog or frog-headed man in male form or a snake-headed woman in female form. On 4chan, the character Pepe the Frog is often considered a modern avatar of the diety, who uses ancient Egyptian meme magic to influence the world, often by fulfilling the wishes of posts that end in repeating numbers. Additionally, the deity is often associated with the popular 4chan slang term “Kek”, and is often embraced by supporters of 2016 Republican presidential candidate Donald Trump. Practitioners are known to frequently write “praise Kek,” and jokingly refer to the church as a “religion of peace.”</item></list>
</text>
