<text id="autogum_whow_doc553" title="Become a Veterinary Specialist in Sonora, Arizona" shortTile="become-veterinary" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-05-30" dateModified="2019-03-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Become-a-Veterinary-Specialist-in-Sonora%2C-Arizona" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Become a Veterinary Specialist in Sonora, Arizona</head><p>Veterinarians are the doctors responsible for the diagnosis, treatment, and care of all types of animals. After receiving their undergraduate degree, veterinarians then complete 4 years of veterinary school. Veterinary specialists are those who specialize in a certain type of animal care such as surgery, emergency medicine, or oncology. Although you can find work in numerous locations all over the world, read on to learn how to become a veterinary specialist in Sonora, Arizona.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Begin preparing early if you wish to become a veterinarian in Sonora, Arizona. High school students should achieve high grades, high test scores, and try to work or volunteer in some capacity with animals. Working at an animal clinic is an ideal way to gain experience with animal care, watch medical treatment, and to determine if the job is really what you want to do. <figure rend="Become a Veterinary Specialist in Sonora, Arizona Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Graduate from a university with a bachelor's degree, preferably with high grades and top honors. Although technically you may graduate in any discipline, those who have degrees in any of the following may have a competitive edge when applying to veterinary school: biology, chemistry, zoology, biochemistry, animal biology, and other similar hard sciences. <figure rend="Become a Veterinary Specialist in Sonora, Arizona Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Apply to veterinary school either after graduation or while in your final year of undergraduate school. There are 28 veterinary colleges in the United States that meet the standards set forth by the American Veterinary Medical Association (AVMA). There are no veterinary schools in Arizona, so you must be prepared to attend a school in another state. <figure rend="Become a Veterinary Specialist in Sonora, Arizona Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>When applying to veterinary schools, you must have taken all prerequisite classes, which are usually completed while earning your undergraduate degree, and submit test scores, which include the GRE, VCAT, or MCAT. Every school has different requirements, so you must make sure you fulfill the requirements before you apply.</item></list></item>
<item>Apply for an internship upon receiving your Doctor of Veterinary Medicine (DVM). Interns are typically paid very little but you gain valuable knowledge and experience that can help you secure employment in the future. Many schools begin preparing their students for internships before they graduate. <figure rend="Become a Veterinary Specialist in Sonora, Arizona Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Contact the Sonora Veterinary Specialists group, which may help you become a veterinary specialist in Sonora, Arizona. Inquire about its internship program. Interns will spend 12 months working the various veterinary specialties, such as surgery, neurology, dermatology, oncology, and medicine. There are also opportunities to work with exotic animals at the Southwest Wildlife Rehabilitation Center. <figure rend="Become a Veterinary Specialist in Sonora, Arizona Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Enter a residency program. This is one of the first training periods for veterinarians after an internship. To become board-certified in a specialty, you must complete 3 to 4 years of training in your specialty and then pass the board exams. The AVMA currently has 39 recognized specialties. <figure rend="Become a Veterinary Specialist in Sonora, Arizona Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get your license by the Arizona State Veterinary Medicine Examination Board. To become a veterinarian in Arizona, you must be licensed to practice in the state. You must also pass the national North American Veterinary Licensing Exam, which is a multiple-choice test with 360 questions that cover all aspects of veterinary medicine. <figure rend="Become a Veterinary Specialist in Sonora, Arizona Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>As a student, you should gain as much experience as possible before and during veterinary school to have a competitive edge over your competition.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You must make sure you have all of the requirements before becoming a vet in Arizona. Check with the AVMA and the Arizona State Veterinary Board frequently to make sure that the specifics have not changed.</item></list>
</text>
