<text id="autogum_whow_doc217" title="Celebrate Dad with a Rental Projector" shortTile="celebrate-dad-rental" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-05-31" dateModified="2016-08-18" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Celebrate-Dad-with-a-Rental-Projector" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Celebrate Dad with a Rental Projector</head><p>Does your dad really need another tie? Whether you're celebrating dad for Father's Day, his birthday, or "just because," look at all the great reasons to gift him a weekend rental projector.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Rent a projector. Most rentals are fairly affordable ($130-160 for a full weekend), but if that's outside your price range, consider asking your siblings to chip in. You can rent online and have it delivered most anywhere, or rent from a local rental shop (available if you live in a fairly large city). <figure rend="Celebrate Dad with a Rental Projector Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Buy your dad an excellent greeting card, or make a "certificate" on your computer. This is a fun and unique way to gift an intangible present, like a weekend projector rental. <figure rend="Celebrate Dad with a Rental Projector Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Talk to the rest of the family to decide on a weekend that works best for the rental. When is everyone available for at least one afternoon or evening? <figure rend="Celebrate Dad with a Rental Projector Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Choose a theme (or let Dad decide). Check out the Tips section for ideas. <figure rend="Celebrate Dad with a Rental Projector Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Rent movies or arrange for pay-per-view if dad wants to watch the big game, or a heavyweight fight. It's easy to connect a rental projector to your television, DVD player, or laptop computer. <figure rend="Celebrate Dad with a Rental Projector Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Provide the snacks. Remember to choose the snacks dad likes to munch on -- whether that includes fried chicken and chili, or salted nuts, sweets and popcorn. <figure rend="Celebrate Dad with a Rental Projector Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Part of the fun of this gift involves family participation, so be sure to rent the projector on a weekend when everyone can attend. If you can't arrange this ahead of time, give Dad a gift certificate for a date "TBA" and work with the family to get it scheduled.</item>
<item>You might let Dad decide what he wants to watch during his weekend rental, but here are some suggestions.</item>
<item>Sports weekend. This might involve renting a projector during Super Bowl weekend, the Indy 500, a boxing match, or the Final Four (depending on what's upcoming, and what dad loves best).</item>
<item>Film Fest. Choose dad's favorite films and gather the family to watch these classics together.</item>
<item>Family Movies. Have old home movies transferred to DVD and showcase them in larger-than-life format with a rental projector for dad and the family to enjoy together.</item>
<item>Surprise Night at the Movies. Let each person choose a film dad hasn't seen, but that he's sure to love.</item>
<item>Combo Ticket. Choose from one or more of the above options, or create your own. For example, perhaps your dad loves video games -- in which case you can hook up a rental projector to your favorite gaming system.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Remember to keep the focus more on dad, as opposed to the wants or desires of you and your siblings.</item>
<item>Don't book the projector rental until you've talked with dad to ensure he's game, and available.</item></list>
</text>
