<text id="autogum_whow_doc400" title="Make Pattachitra" shortTile="make-pattachitra" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-06-01" dateModified="2018-06-04" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-Pattachitra" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make Pattachitra</head><p>Considering the medium, the paintings of Odisha can be divided into three categories: painting on cloth or canvas is known as 'Patta Chitra'; paintings on walls is called 'Bhitti Chitra'; and painting on palm leaf, where art is engraved with a sharply pointed slender piece of metal, namely 'Lekhani', is called 'TalaPatra Chitra' or 'Pothi Chitra'. Pattachitra represents a vigorous style of dexterous play of bold lines and bright hues which is quite captivating to the eye.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Prepare the canvas. The process of painting Pattachitra begins with the preparation of the canvas. Traditionally, cotton canvas was used, but now most of the Chitrakaras (artists of Odisha) use silk cloths since they are much softer than the cotton.
<list type="unordered"><item>Dip the cloth in a solution of crushed imli seeds and water for 4-5 days.</item>
<item>Dry the cloth in the sunlight.</item>
<item>Layer both sides of the cloth with a paste of chalk powder, imli, and gum.</item>
<item>Let it dry in the sun again.</item>
<item>Rub khaddar stone on it to make the canvas smooth.</item>
<item>Thereafter a specific kind of smooth stone is rubbed on it to make the canvas shine. <figure rend="Pattachitra 01.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Prepare the colours. The artists create a variety of colors from natural elements, though nowadays, synthetic primary colors are used to produce a set of secondary and tertiary colors.
<list type="unordered"><item>A white colour is prepared by grinding mollusk and conch shells.</item>
<item>A stone called Haritala is used for yellow.</item>
<item>Blue is prepared from indigo.</item>
<item>Black is obtained by burning the coconut shells or from the lamp black.</item>
<item>Red oxide stone is used for a red color. <figure rend="Pattachitra 02.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Draw borders along the four sides of the canvas. Bordering a canvas gives a perfect look to the entire art. Border may contain two or three lines according to their size. Later, the border can obtain a colorful appearance through the detailed work of the artist. <figure rend="Pattachitra 05.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Draw outlines of the figures with pencil. The typical name of this procedure is called 'Tipanā' (ଟିପଣା), which implies the process of making a well-defined skeletal sketch on the canvas. <figure rend="Pattachitra 06.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Start filling in the hues. Coloring the Pattachitra accommodates various steps.
<list type="unordered"><item>The first step is 'Hingula Banaka'(ହିଙ୍ଗୁଳା ବନକ), which means filling in red since traditionally red is used for the background of Pattachitra. This step alludes the filling colours to the background, anyway.</item>
<item>Secondly, 'Luga Pindha' (ଲୁଗା ପିନ୍ଧା), or coloring the attire, is done.</item>
<item>The body colors are then added followed by coloring of attires.</item>
<item>Then comes 'Gahana Lagi' (ଗହଣା ଲାଗି). It involves the coloring of ornaments in a chrome yellow shade. Artists paint some of the ornaments with whitish yellow to render them pearl-studded look and the other with yellow for gold. <figure rend="Pattachitra 09.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Add detail. During the detailing process, first, thick outlines are drawn, namely 'Mota Kala' (ମୋଟା କଳା) and then finer detailing is done, called 'Saru Kala'(ସରୁ କଳା). <figure rend="Pattachitra 08.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Add fine detail to the ornaments. The final step is 'Gahana Kuta' (ଗହଣା କୁଟା), or adding finer details to the ornaments. Artists of earlier times used gold foil during the procedure. One can use fluorescent color to add the fine decorative features to the Pattachitra. <figure rend="Pattachitra 10.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are a beginner you don't need to be worried about the above method of preparation of colors. You can simply buy synthetic colors available at a market and you can get different shades of colors by mixing those primary colors with each other. For example, a combination of red and white gives pink.</item></list>
</text>
