<text id="autogum_whow_doc549" title="Become an RSPCA Inspector" shortTile="become-rspca-inspector" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-05-10" dateModified="2019-03-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Become-an-RSPCA-Inspector" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Become an RSPCA Inspector</head><p>The Royal Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals (or RSPCA) is an organization based in the United Kingdom that investigates and take steps to prevent and/or intervene upon poor treatment of animals. An RSPCA inspector is a highly trained employee who does the actual work of investigating and intervening, often encountering conflict. In order to enter this rewarding career path, you must meet several basic qualifications and undergo a multi-step application process. Before doing so, you must also consider the social, physical, and psychological strains of this demanding career. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Meeting Basic Qualifications</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Pass five GCSEs. The first qualification necessary to become an RSPCA inspector involves passing at least five GCSE (General Certificate of Secondary Education) exams with a grade of C or better. Of these exams, one must be Maths, and one English. <figure rend="Become an RSPCA Inspector Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Obtain a UK driver’s license. In order to qualify for work as an RSPCA inspector you must have a valid UK driver’s license. You must also be able to operate a vehicle with a fully manual transmission. <figure rend="Become an RSPCA Inspector Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Practice swimming. Some of your work as an RSPCA inspector can involve water. As such, strong swimming ability is important. In order to qualify for the role of RSPCA inspector, you must be able to swim  fully clothed within 2.5 minutes. <figure rend="Become an RSPCA Inspector Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Gain experience working with animals. In order to work with the RSPCA, it is required for you to have experience working with animals. You can gain experience by volunteering with an animal welfare charity, animal refuge, or ideally for an RSPCA animal care center. <figure rend="Become an RSPCA Inspector Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Ensure that you are in good physical shape. This job can be physically demanding, requiring you to lift heavy objects or animals, run, and/or swim. As such, your physical health and ability will be taken into consideration. Be sure that you are in very strong physical health, and perhaps even begin training, before you apply. <figure rend="Become an RSPCA Inspector Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Begin swimming daily.</item>
<item>You may want to run and/or lift weights.</item>
<item>Consider your diet. Focus on consuming veggies, fruit, lean meats, and whole grains.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Gaining a Position with the RSPCA</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Apply to be a trainee. If you find yourself suitably qualified, the next step is to locate a trainee opening with a local RSPCA chapter. You can visit the RSPCA website to search job openings. When you find an opening near you, submit your application online. <figure rend="Become an RSPCA Inspector Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>To apply you will send a curriculum vitae (or resume) and cover letter, along with a brief application.</item>
<item>In these materials, you will outline the ways in which you meet various minimum qualifications, as well why you are a good fit for the position.</item></list></item>
<item>Complete an interview and assessment. If you are chosen to move on to the next level, you will be invited to a Selection Board Interview, where you will be asked about your background and criminal history. If you pass this phase (called Preliminary Declaration), you will then be asked to participate in a series of psychometric assessments, as well as a physical examination and fitness assessment. Based on the results of these tests, the selection board will determine whether or not you are suitable for this role. <figure rend="Become an RSPCA Inspector Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Undergo 7-12 months of training. If you are selected to move on as an RSPCA trainee, you will head into your first of 26 training modules. (You must pass all 26 to qualify). Each module will take between one and eight weeks, and you must pass all 26 within one year of registering for your first. Lodging and board is provided during training modules. <figure rend="Become an RSPCA Inspector Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Training modules will cover subject areas including: investigation skills and interview techniques, court work, media and public speaking, boat rescue techniques, and basic veterinary and animal-handling skills.</item>
<item>Typically, training modules must be completed in a consecutive order.</item></list></item>
<item>Pass a swimming assessment. Near the beginning of your training, you will be asked to undergo a swimming assessment. Some of your time working the RSPCA may be on, in, or around water, so being able to swim well is a crucial component of the job. For this assessment, you will be expected to swim  fully clothed in 2.5 minutes or less. <figure rend="Become an RSPCA Inspector Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Receive a job offer with the RSPCA. After you have completed your training, you will be given an official job offer by the RSPCA. Be aware that this job may require you to relocate to a new area. Congratulations! You have succeeded in becoming an RSPCA inspector. <figure rend="Become an RSPCA Inspector Step 10.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Considering the Demands</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Understand that the hours are “unsociable.” As an RSPCA inspector, you will regularly be asked to work evenings, weekends, and holidays. These hours and dates will not be negotiable, so it is important to consider if you will be happy with the schedule before pursuing this career. <figure rend="Become an RSPCA Inspector Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Recognize that there will be lots of driving. A major component of this career is time spent on the road. If you become an RSPCA inspector, understand that you may travel over 25,000 miles (40,234 kilometers) each year. You must operate a manual transmission vehicle, traveling across both urban and rural landscapes. <figure rend="Become an RSPCA Inspector Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be aware of the physical demands. Working as an RSPCA inspector involves periods of very high physical activity. You may need to run and swim. You may need to work at heights, or in confined spaces. You will also be required to lift heavy cages, and carry, haul, and otherwise handle animals. <figure rend="Become an RSPCA Inspector Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Consider the psychological demands. Perhaps even more taxing than the physical demands of working for the RSPCA are the psychological demands. You will experience a great deal of confrontation with other humans, and you must be able to stand your ground. You will encounter animals in poor situations. You may need to restrain or even euthanize an animal. All of this can be hard on the average person. <figure rend="Become an RSPCA Inspector Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Asses your communicative abilities. In order to succeed as an RSPCA inspector, you must have exemplary communication skills. You must be able to defuse situations and confrontations. You must be able to talk yourself out of difficult situations. Most of all, you must be able to communicate clearly, concisely and assertively. <figure rend="Become an RSPCA Inspector Step 15.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You have to be able to withstand working by yourself for long periods of time.</item>
<item>A friendly, confident person stands more chance of becoming an RSPCA Inspector than a shy, quiet person.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>This career is not recommended if you are allergic to some animals.</item>
<item>You must not be afraid of certain animals, for example: spiders or snakes. (If you are then you must learn to overcome your fear).</item>
<item>A conviction within the past 10 years for a number of criminal offenses may result in your application being rejected.</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
