<text id="autogum_whow_doc668" title="Establish a Workout Routine" shortTile="establish-workout" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-10-28" dateModified="2019-10-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Establish-a-Workout-Routine" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Establish a Workout Routine</head><p>This article is intended to help people who are struggling or do not know how to put
together a solid routine for working out along with bulking while doing it. It does not just include what you while in the gym. You must care for your body all day long seven days a week. Sleep and eating right are also adequate parts of the equation when it comes to building muscle and having smooth workout routines. Routines are where it all starts, and creating one can seem overwhelming at first, but this article will able to lead anyone who has questions about this topic in the right direction. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Part 1.) Setting a Time and Place</hi>
1.)	Mark a calendar each month with obligations and/or required things you must do on specific days. Attempt to mark down each thing in detail that goes on in your day-to-day life. Depending on your work/school schedule (whichever applies), set yourself a routine. Try to work out around the same time each day.</p>
<p>2.)	Set an adequate sleep schedule. 7-9 hours a night of sleep is normally plenty of sleep in order to go about your day and provide enough energy to do everything you must do, including working out. Without sleep, you may get through your day, and by 4-5 pm you will not feel like going to the gym. Sleep takes care of this common problem. </p>
<p>3.)	No excuses. Once you set your sleep schedule along with your day-to-day calendar, you must make it consistent. Depending on your shifts or classes if you are a student, plan your workouts accordingly. If you know at the end of your day you will be tired, workout before your shift or class starts instead of waiting until after and not being willing to go. </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Part 2.) Working Out and Choosing Your Workout</hi>
1.)	Get to the gym. Getting to the gym is half the battle when it comes to working out. Many people preach how much they would like to work out, but never even end up going. It is much easier mentally and physically once you are in the environment. Working out is a culture, and once you are around people who are just as motivated as you are, it makes it extremely enjoyable. </p>
<p>2.)	Once at the gym, determine which muscle groups you will hit on certain days of the week. Try to get a routine, so you’re working the same muscles the same days of the week and keep your days off consistent as well. This will ensure muscle growth, and your body will eventually become acclimated to it. (I mean same muscle groups, not necessarily same lifts every day). </p>
<p>3.)	There are many exercises you can do. Legs, back, shoulders, chest, arms, and core all have multiple lifts to work the muscles.
Legs: Squats, deadlifts, calf-raises, RDL’s, leg-press
Back: Lat-pulldown, rows (barbell and dumbbell), cable pulls, pull-ups
Shoulders: Military press, seated press, barbell over-head raise, lateral raises w/ dumbbells, upright-rows
Chest: Bench press, dumbbell bench press, pectoral flies, pec-deck
Arms: Bicep curls (dumbbell/barbell), tricep skull crushers, over head tricep extension (cables or dumbbell), bicep curling machine
Core: Tybo twisties (medicine ball), sit-ups, crunches (can use weight), bicycles, leg raise s, planks (sideways and forwards)</p>
<p>4.)	Mix the lifts up as you progess through your routine day-to-day and month-to-month.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Part 3.) Stretching Before and After Working Out</hi>
1.)	Dynamic stretching before you lift/run. Lots of high knees, Russian march, jumping jacks, and burpees. </p>
<p>2.)	Static stretching after you work out. Flamingo, butterfly, hip flexor, calves, and over the head and across the body arm stretches. </p>
<p>3.)	Understanding why. You work out your muscles in order to warm them up and allow them to be able to be stretched. Without stretching, you will be more sore than not (days after lifting), and you will not see as much progress as you’d like to as opposed to if you were stretching consistently and adequately. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Part 4.) Eating Right Post Work Out</hi>
1.)	Before you work out, carbs and proteins are great in moderation. You can take a pre-workout of your choice. You also need something to give you energy/boost throughout your work out. In other words, food gives you something to burn off while exercising. Peanut butter toast, bananas, apples, chicken pot pies, etc are great food choices pre working out.</p>
<p>2.)	After working out depending on your lift that day, try to eat lots of protein and lots of carbs. Tons of chicken, rice, green beans or broccoli (vegetable groups). The amount of protein that you should consume in order to gain muscle weight, is 0.8 grams/kg of body weight. Average man consumes 56 grams of protein a day, and woman consumes about 46 grams a day (in order to bulk/build muscle). </p>
<p>3.)	Drinking water before, throughout, and after your workout will help hydrate you and replenish you as you will sweat fair amounts during exercise. (I drink 3 gallons a day at 215 lbs). </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Part 5.) Post Workout Supplements</hi>
1.)	Creatine is an essential thing to take after you work out. The body naturally produces it, but not enough if you are attempting to build muscle. It speeds up muscle growth, while retaining water in your muscles.</p>
<p>2.)	Protein supplements are also essential for muscle growth. You can get protein in food, but it is necessary to get it from another source in order to see muscle growth.</p>
</text>
