<text id="autogum_whow_doc024" title="Write a Baby Card" shortTile="write-baby-card" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-12-10" dateModified="2018-12-11" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Write-a-Baby-Card" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Write a Baby Card</head><p>Imagine that you have been invited to a friend or coworker's baby shower. Along with a nice toy you purchased as a gift, you'll need a card. Now, what to write in it?</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Finding a Card
<list type="unordered"><item>Pay attention to the baby shower invitation; Does it say if the child is a boy or a girl? If so, it is sort of 'traditional' to get a gender themed card, such as a blue one with pictures of toy trucks for a boy or a pink one with glittery decals for a girl. However, it is up to you how genderfluid you would like to be. Browse the card aisle of the Dollar Store and find something you like!</item></list></item>
<item>Beginning to Write the Message Inside the Card
<list type="unordered"><item>Begin with a pen or sharp pencil. Adress the parents/mother (there are multiple ways of doing this, such as 'Dear Mr. and Mrs. Last Name,' 'Dear Soon to Be Parents,' 'Dear Mother on the Way,' 'Dear Excited Almost-Father').</item></list></item>
<item>First Paragraph
<list type="unordered"><item>After adressing the recipient(s), skip down a line and indent. Begin the paragraph by writing something along the lines of 'I can't believe you're going to be a parent!' (such as 'Aaaah! I'm so excited for you to have your child!' or 'It's so hard to believe you're pregnant!').</item>
<item>Staying in the first paragraph, back up this excited first sentence with a memory that you share with this person/these people. It can be as simple as the time the wife complimented your shirt or as deep as the first time you sat next to the dad on the bus in second grade.</item>
<item>After that, jot down something along the lines of 'You/The two of you are such amazing people. You will be awesome parents.'</item>
<item>Customize this last sentence a bit.</item></list></item>
<item>Second Paragraph
<list type="unordered"><item>Once again, skip down the paper a little and indent.</item>
<item>Begin with a quote or Bible verse about parenting/birth. For example, the first sentence of this paragraph could be '"Fathers, do not embitter your children, or they will become discouraged." Colossians 3:21.'</item>
<item>Go on to explain this quote/verse.</item>
<item>Reflect on how this quote will be true to their parenting.</item></list></item>
<item>Concluding
<list type="unordered"><item>Skip down the page a bit and indent.</item>
<item>Keep it short and sweet: 'I hope you and Jr. enjoy the gift.'</item>
<item>Remind them that you are always availible to help them out with babysitting or encouragement. 'I hope you are aware that it would be my pleasure to watch the baby any time you need.'</item></list></item>
<item>Signing Off
<list type="unordered"><item>Skip down to the very bottom of the paper.</item>
<item>Think about your connection to the parent(s) and decide if you should use 'Love,' 'Sincerely,' etc.</item>
<item>Use a legible handwriting, and write your (first and last) name, not your initials. I, for example, would write Erika Alabaster, not EA or Erika.</item>
<item>Add the date.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>EXAMPLE USING GIVEN STEPS AND FORMAT: (Let's imagine the parents are named Chad and Denise)Dear Soon to be Parents,     I can't believe you're having a baby! I remember the first time I ever talked to Denise. It was in third grade, on a red play ground slide. I also remember when she first told me about Chad, and when the two of you started dating. You seemed so young then; we all did. You two are so amazing, it will be impossible for you not to raise an awesome child. I'm excited to meet them!     A quote I once heard about parenting is "my kids are the reason I laugh, smile, and get up in the morning". It's true. My children Reena and Jaelyn are the reason I do everything from smiling to breathing. They are the lights of my life, just as your child will be for you!     I do hope you enjoy the gift. It's so exciting to shop for this new arrival! I'm always willing to babysit or watch the baby whenever you need me to.Love,         Erika Alabaster</item></list>
</text>
