<text id="autogum_whow_doc502" title="Use a Document Organiser" shortTile="use-document-organiser" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2008-02-13" dateModified="2019-09-10" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Use-a-Document-Organiser" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Use a Document Organiser</head><figure rend="Citizen Agency gets Incorporated 9955.jpg"></figure>Document organisers are an excellent way of keeping your documents organised.  They can help you keep all your important documents organised, but only if you use the organisers effectively.  So here are some simple steps for using yours well.
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Purchase a document organiser. The size will be determined by the documentation that you intend to keep.  If you only wish to store receipts, you may choose a smaller document organizer rather than if you are going to store larger pieces of paper and documents then you should probably choose a large document organiser. <figure rend="Use a Document Organiser Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Decide what categories you want to include.  Once you have decided on your categories, then you will need to label the tabs on the separate compartments.  It is usually best to alphabetize the separate compartments because later on when you are looking for a particular document, you will know what category it is under due to the nature of the document and will be able to either retrieve the document or file a new document because your separate compartments are already alphabetized, thus making it easier to locate. <figure rend="Use a Document Organiser Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Choose categories for your document organiser. Some examples could include: <figure rend="Use a Document Organiser Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Agreements</item>
<item>Bank account(s), Loan record(s) and Safe Deposit Instructions</item>
<item>Birth, baptismal and death records</item>
<item>Credit card company documents</item>
<item>Divorce, marriage, and separation documents</item>
<item>Financial: Bonds, home ownership paperwork, investments, tax documentation, land Deeds, mortgage paperwork, out of State home ownership paperwork, stocks, treasury bills, etc.</item>
<item>Important correspondences and documents</item>
<item>Insurance Records:  Life, disability, medical, property and vehicle</item>
<item>Legal:  Cemetery and funeral arrangements, health care proxy documents, last will and testament (include attorney name with will instructions), and living wills</item>
<item>Miscellaneous</item>
<item>Retirement and superannuation documents</item>
<item>Tax records (7 years in many jurisdictions)</item>
<item>Travel:  Passport and Visa documents</item>
<item>Vehicle ownership:  Auto insurance documents, DMV documents (title, and/or transfer paperwork), and gasoline (petrol)/mileage (kilometerage) documents.</item></list></item>
<item>Keep your organisers up-to-date and in order. Once you receive a new document, try to file as soon as possible.  Also if a document is needed that is currently in the document organiser, retrieve document, take necessary steps of why document was retrieved and after steps are completed, put retrieved document back in  the document organizer under correct category originally retrieved from. This takes only minutes and your organiser stays organised. <figure rend="Use a Document Organiser Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Consider a separate organizer for receipts. If you need to keep receipts it may be a good idea to have a separate "Receipts Organiser".  The Receipts Organiser can be a cross-reference to your document organiser whereas you can insert in the relevant category a photocopy sheet which could include a brief description written on it.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you find that a document organiser just is not big enough for all your documents, then you can still use the breakdown above for a filing cabinet system.</item>
<item>Another option is to have a range of document organisers - one for each category that is needed. These separate organizers could then be individually inserted into a filing cabinet in either alphabetical or most-used order.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Document organiser(s) of size(s) required.</item></list>
</text>
