<text id="autogum_whow_doc283" title="Make Pan De Yuca" shortTile="make-pan-de-yuca" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-06-03" dateModified="2019-09-13" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-Pan-De-Yuca" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make Pan De Yuca</head><p>Pan de Yuca is a traditional South American cheese bread that is made commonly in Ecuador and Colombia. This bread is made with yuca flour (also known as cassava or tapioca flour), which is a gluten-free starch extracted from the cassava root. Pan de Yuca is also often paired with a traditional fruit and yogurt smoothie. There is even an entire restaurant chain in Ecuador called Naturissimo, which is dedicated to the "pan de yuca con yogurt" combination. However, you can easily make this to enjoy at home.</p>
<head>Ingredients</head>
<head>Pan de Yuca</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>1 cup yuca flour</item>
<item>1 teaspoon baking powder</item>
<item>2 cups shredded queso blanco (or any other white cheese, such as mozzarella or Oaxaca cheese)</item>
<item>2 egg yolks</item>
<item>2 tablespoons melted butter</item>
<item>2-3 tablespoons heavy cream (or milk)</item></list>
<head>Yogurt Smoothie</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>2 cups ice</item>
<item>1/2 cup plain yogurt</item>
<item>1 cup chopped fruit of choice</item>
<item>2 tablespoons sugar (optional)</item></list>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Making Pan de Yuca</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Preheat oven to . Line a baking sheet with aluminum foil and lightly grease with cooking spray. Set aside for now.</item>
<item>Combine yuca flour and baking powder in a large bowl. Mix the ingredients together using a fork until they are evenly mixed. <figure rend="How to make pan de yuca.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Add cheese to the bowl. Using the same fork, mix the cheese in with the flour mixture until everything in the bowl is mixed evenly together. <figure rend="How to make pan de yuca 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Beat egg yolks. In a separate bowl, lightly beat the egg yolks, and then add them to the mixture in the large bowl. Stir the ingredients together until mixture is even. The mixture should now appear light yellow and chunky. <figure rend="How to make pan de yuca 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Add melted butter. Mix well. This should make the mixture slightly more clumpy, but it will likely still be too dry to form a ball of dough. <figure rend="How to make pan de yuca 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Add heavy cream. Do this by mixing in one tablespoon at a time, until mixture is dense enough to roll into a ball. This may also be substituted for milk, following the same instructions as for the cream, but will result in a slightly less dense bread.</item>
<item>Remove mixture from the bowl and knead on a floured surface until completely smooth. Note that it will still appear chunky even when the dough is smooth because the cheese will give it a bumpier texture. <figure rend="How to make pan de yuca 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Divide dough into ten even parts and roll them into balls. Place these on the baking sheet at least one inch apart from each other so that they have room to expand as they bake. <figure rend="How to make pan de yuca 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Place the baking sheet in the oven. Bake for 10-15 minutes, or until the bottoms appear golden brown. Note that pan de yuca is a very pale bread, so it will not appear as golden-brown as many other baked goods do when they are finished. <figure rend="How to make pan de yuca 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Poke a toothpick into the bread to check for doneness if needed.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Yogurt Smoothie</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Add chopped fruit and yogurt to blender. Blend the fruit and yogurt together until the mixture is smooth and consistent. <figure rend="How to make pan de yuca yogurt 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Add ice and blend. Blend the ice into the fruit and yogurt mixture to thicken the texture and chill the drink. It may help to crush the ice into smaller pieces before blending, depending on the strength of your blender, to prevent it from getting jammed.</item>
<item>Add sugar (optional). If you wish to sweeten the flavor of the fruit, add sugar and blend well.</item>
<item>Serve in a glass and enjoy with warm Pan de Yuca. You may want to try dipping the bread into the yogurt smoothie and taking a bite, as is traditionally done. <figure rend="How to make pan de yuca with yogurt.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Yuca flour can be found at a local Hispanic grocery store, and sometimes at other stores with international grocery sections.</item>
<item>Queso blanco is a typical Caribbean white cheese which can be found at Costco, Walmart, and Hispanic grocery stores.</item>
<item>Do not hesitate to use combinations of two or more cheeses in your bread. Just make sure to use the same total amount of cheese in the bread for similar results.</item></list>
</text>
