<text id="autogum_whow_doc431" title="Be Lucky on Friday the 13th" shortTile="lucky-friday-th" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2009-12-28" dateModified="2019-03-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be-Lucky-on-Friday-the-13th" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be Lucky on Friday the 13th</head><p>Friday the 13th is supposedly an ominous date, steeped in superstition and assumed by some to bring bad luck. But if you're more inclined to turn the tables and make Friday the 13th your super lucky day, while there's no forcing luck, a good attitude and a relaxed approach to daily life on Friday the 13th might just bring you some much needed fun and excitement.
</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be good luck-oriented. There are a few <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Stop_Being_Superstitious">superstitions</ref> aimed at bringing you luck that you might like to try: <figure rend="Be Lucky on Friday the 13th Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Get out of the bed on the right side (that is, <hi rend="italic">not</hi> the left side). This side is guaranteed to make your day luckier according to some superstitions. If you can't get out on that side because it is next to the wall or for another reason, just skip this step.</item>
<item>Wear red <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_a_Bra_Out_of_Underpants">underpants</ref>. Apparently this color will bring you more luck than other colors. Whatever you do, don't choose green underpants or luck might abandon you.</item>
<item>Get your most trusted <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_Charms">lucky charm</ref> out. Place it in your pocket and wear it all day.</item>
<item>Forget the cleaning. Few need to be told this most days but Friday the 13th is a great excuse because apparently handling a broom is unlucky on this day, as is changing the sheets, flipping the mattress, or doing the laundry. So forget the cleaning and just enjoy your day.</item></list></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Think_Positively">Think positively</ref> all day. Make this the day to put aside bad moods, irritability, and your ongoing petty argument with a co-worker or family member. This is the day for choosing good things, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_a_Comedian">good thoughts</ref>, and good outcomes. Indeed, not believing in bad luck is a good approach because research has shown that people who believe in bad luck tend to bring it on! <figure rend="Be Lucky on Friday the 13th Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Tell everyone that 13 <hi rend="italic">is</hi> your <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Find_Your_Lucky_Numbers_in_Numerology">lucky number</ref>. Let them know how excited you are that the date has fallen on the 13th again, and that you expect this to be a <hi rend="italic">great</hi> day.</item></list></item>
<item>Test your luck. Go out and deliberately do a few things that involve chance and where your luck takes you. Buy a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Choose_Lottery_Numbers">lottery ticket</ref> for the next big draw, buy some scratch tickets, play a game at the casino, or place some sports bets. If you're too young to gamble, or dislike it, play some games of chance at home with friends and guess who is going to win, or watch a game on TV and guess who will win. <figure rend="Be Lucky on Friday the 13th Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Apply for a new job you've really been wanting. Realize that the very superstitious don't all think that Friday 13th is a good day to start anything new, not even opening a new packet of cereal. But why not turn that superstition on its head and do something to force Lady Luck's hand? Today could be the day luck sways your way!</item></list></item>
<item>Organize something fun to do after work, studies, or other duties. Mark the day by celebrating and having fun with your friends. Go to a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Attend_a_Concert">concert</ref>, eat out, visit a bar, watch a show in the park, etc. Just use the day as an excuse to party! <figure rend="Be Lucky on Friday the 13th Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Think about how <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Realise_You_Are_Lucky">lucky</ref> you are. Spend a little part of your day <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Thankful">counting your blessings</ref>. What are all the things you're grateful for in your life? Who are the people in your life that matter most to you? What wouldn't you change about your life for all the world? Remind yourself of all the people, opportunities, and things that make you feel lucky in your life whenever you feel a sense of impending doom about anything! <figure rend="Be Lucky on Friday the 13th Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Dispense with the superstitious nonsense and take responsibility for the things that happen to you. If you carry on thinking about luck all day, you're likely to be distracted and possibly something less-than-lucky might happen. Eyes open, head up, and brain in charge! Moreover, psychologist Richard Wiseman who carried out the study on believing in bad luck mentioned earlier, suggested that believing in superstitions can actually be a way of avoiding taking responsibility for your own failings. So perhaps this is as good a day as any to re-examine any loopy superstitions you might have inherited through the grapevine of folk <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Gossip">gossip</ref> and finally take a stand to let logic rule your concerns rather than fears and half truths. <figure rend="Be Lucky on Friday the 13th Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Luck is usually the result of effort and common sense combined. Sometimes people choose to see things as lucky because they were unexpected; if your entire life is full of the unexpected though, it's probably time to reassess your gullibility.</item>
<item>To make 13 be your lucky number, you need to see that number a lot. If you play a sport, have 13 be your jersey number. If you think of other ways, go ahead and use it.</item>
<item>Pet a black cat. The luck has to go somewhere, right? Better still, give it some cat treats or catnip. Any other color of cat helps too, just close your eyes and scratch, listen for the purr. Don't do this if the cat hisses or walks away, let the cat decide how much affection it wants. Consider adopting a black cat or kitten from a shelter - they face terrible discrimination from the superstitious. It still counts if it's got white mittens or tuxedo markings.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>The marking out of Friday the 13th as a day of concern is superstition. Feeling lucky or unlucky on this date is a superstitious action. Nothing is guaranteed either way but you are the master or mistress of your own destiny, so use your common sense and rein in your illusions.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Party plans</item>
<item>Red underwear</item></list>
</text>
