<text id="autogum_whow_doc003" title="Buy the Copyright for an Old Book" shortTile="buy-copyright-old" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-04-01" dateModified="2018-08-16" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Buy-the-Copyright-for-an-Old-Book" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Buy the Copyright for an Old Book</head><p>If an old book still has a following but is no longer in print, buying the copyright is a good way for writers or publishers to meet the demand and earn extra money. Obtaining the copyright to old books is also a good way to start an online collection of books to share or sell. However, it is essential to understand copyright law and to follow the proper procedure in order to avoid possible legal objections from the original copyright holder or his or her heirs. The process to transfer copyright is straightforward, but it can be time consuming.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Locate the original copyright holder of the old book. This will be the person or company you will work with to transfer copyright from the original owner to you. <figure rend="Buy the Copyright for an Old Book Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Look at the copyright page of the book to find the original author's name and the original publisher's name and location. This should tell you whether the author or publisher holds the copyright.</item>
<item>Contact the government department that handles intellectual property rights if the information is missing or illegible. You can request a search of copyright records to locate the copyright holder.</item>
<item>The department may use a name like the copyright office. You can try the United States Copyright Office, the Canadian Intellectual Property Office or the German Copyright and Publishing Law Directorate.</item></list></item>
<item>Determine whether the copyright is still in effect. Time limits on copyright vary by country. <figure rend="Buy the Copyright for an Old Book Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If the copyright has expired, the book is in the public domain, and you will not need to do further research. If the book is in the public domain, you won't need to buy the copyright. Public domain books are the property of the public at large, and you may use, modify or republish the work.</item></list></item>
<item>Track down the copyright holder or his or her heirs. Copyright extends beyond the death of the author, so you need to find the person who has the authority to transfer copyright to you. <figure rend="Buy the Copyright for an Old Book Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Contact the copyright owner and explain why you want to buy the copyright of the old book. <figure rend="Buy the Copyright for an Old Book Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Negotiate the terms to purchase the copyright. You and the copyright holder can decide on terms that are beneficial to both parties. You don't necessarily need to hire a copyright attorney. However, if the copyright transfer involves a large amount of money or the copyright owner has specific demands, it may be best to have an attorney draft a contract for the purchase. <figure rend="Buy the Copyright for an Old Book Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Complete the purchase and record the transfer of copyright with the copyright office or other appropriate government agency. The copyright office can provide the forms necessary to transfer the copyright legally. <figure rend="Buy the Copyright for an Old Book Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can often find publisher contact information in Bowker's Books in Print database and author information in the Authors Registry or the Writers, Artists, and Their Copyright Holders (WATCH) database.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Not all countries require authors to file copyright notices with the government. For example, Australia does not have a system for copyright registration; all works have a copyright upon creation. If you cannot locate the copyright holder and the copyright office cannot provide the copyright information, you will need to do more research to try to find the original author or his or her heirs.</item>
<item>Orphan works are copyrighted pieces of work whose copyright owner cannot be found. It may be risky to re-publish orphan works since the original copyright holder may come forward later and assert a claim.</item></list>
</text>
