<text id="autogum_whow_doc658" title="Play Wall Bat" shortTile="play-wall-bat" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-12-04" dateModified="2019-05-08" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Play-Wall-Bat" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Play Wall Bat</head><p>Wall bat is a fun new game which involves the use of action, strategy, teamwork.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Preparations before playing</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find a good place to play wall bat, such as a gym or a tall school. You would need a big open area and a very big wall and make sure that there are no windows in your playing field. <figure rend="Hitane_Elementary_School_gym_front.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pick your captains by the oldest, second oldest, and youngest. Pick two people, then pick one person until all the players are on an even and fair team. Determine who will pitch and who will catch for defense.
<list type="unordered"><item>The batter should be 20 yards away from the wall and the catchers of the other team 10 yards away from the wall and the pitcher should be  away from the wall.</item></list></item>
<item>Organize a batting order that will bring your team the maximum amount of points.</item></list>
<head>Playing wall bat</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>If you are the batter.
<list type="unordered"><item>Throw the tennis ball very hard at the bottom of the wall sending the ball back in the way of the batter if you are the pitcher.Calculate where the ball will end up then go there if you are the batter.</item>
<item>Try to smack the ball with the bat so that the ball reaches high up on the wall. The ball will bounce off the wall and it will be the catcher's turn to make a play.</item></list></item>
<item>If you are the catcher.
<list type="unordered"><item>You have two options if you are catcher.Catch the ball and get 1 out or drop it and let the player start running.When the player runs, he must be tagged with direct contact from the tennis ball. Remember you cannot throw the ball at the runner unless you are playing with a softball or you are using street rules. Street rules involve horrible pitches and throwing the ball at the runner.</item>
<item>Get 3 outs in order to switch the defense and the offense meaning the offense becomes defense and vice versa.The game ends when there are 6 switches or one team scores 20 points,whichever is earlier.</item>
<item>Get to the starting base, but to do so, he must run all the way around to 1st base, 2nd, 3rd, 4th, and back to home to score points. This puts 2 points on the board. Stop at the 3rd base to get 1 point. This makes the point process slower, but it is very effective and puts points on the board at least.</item>
<item>Jail an opponent to score on defense. Tag him on the run before he gets to base 2 to jail an opponent. He is a prisoner on your team for the rest of the switch unless he drops a catch. He will go back to the opposing team and the defense scores 2 points and the offense loses 1 point.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure you wear good shoes and don't tackle each other, or someone may get hurt.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Plastic bat</item>
<item>A 30 ft tall wall</item>
<item>Tennis ball</item>
<item>30 yard playing area</item></list>
</text>
