<text id="autogum_whow_doc232" title="Find Information on Money Market Accounts" shortTile="find-information" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-11-11" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Find-Information-on-Money-Market-Accounts" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Find Information on Money Market Accounts</head><p>Money market accounts are insured by the government, which makes them safe places where risk-averse individuals can keep extra cash that won't lose value when the stock market declines. This type of savings vehicle is similar to a savings account, only it usually has a better interest rate for investors. In return for a higher interest rate, the account holder must keep a higher average balance and agree to somewhat restricted access to the money. To find information on money market accounts, ask representatives at your regular banking institution and compare interest rates online at investment education and banking comparison websites.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Read about money market accounts. Look for unbiased financial education at credible websites such as MoneyRates.com's "Money Market Primer." <figure rend="Find Information on Money Market Accounts Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Evaluate your savings needs and short-term financial goals. Know how much money you have in the bank, then consider how much of that money you need to access within the next year. <figure rend="Find Information on Money Market Accounts Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are considering making a major purchase and paying with cash sometime during the next year, keep your money "liquid," which means easily accessible, in a money market account.</item></list></item>
<item>Approach a banking representative at your financial institution. <figure rend="Find Information on Money Market Accounts Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Ask to speak to a branch manger, who will usually know more about money market interest rates and investment requirements than a bank teller.</item></list></item>
<item>Describe your savings goals to the bank manager. Ask to learn about the money market account with the best interest rates at your bank. <figure rend="Find Information on Money Market Accounts Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Ask your banker about account restrictions. For example, some money market funds only allow a few transactions a month. Some have check-writing privileges, but some do not. The more restrictions, the less access you will have to your money when you need it. <figure rend="Find Information on Money Market Accounts Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Compare your bank's interest rates with other financial institutions'. <figure rend="Find Information on Money Market Accounts Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Go online to interest rate comparison websites such as Bankrate.com.</item>
<item>Click on "Compare Rates."</item>
<item>Select "Find the best CD &amp; investment rates."</item>
<item>Choose whether you want an account at a local institution ("Locally available") or a national one ("Highest nationally available"). The difference between local and national is minimal if online banking is available. However local institutions are useful if you want a personal relationship with your account manager.</item>
<item>Select "MMA" (Money Market Account) for a product.</item>
<item>Sort the selected list of banking institutions according to product (choose "MMA"), annual percentage yield (how much interest you can earn annually) and the minimum deposit you will make into the account.</item></list></item>
<item>Review the annual percentage yield (APY) interest rates. Annual percentage yield (APY) is the amount of interest a financial institution pays depositors. <figure rend="Find Information on Money Market Accounts Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Calculating APY is done through an algebraic formula with parameters that vary by country. Most financial institutions include an online calculator on their websites to help visitors determine APY. Compare these APY results against your regular bank's money market savings account yields, fees and restrictions to find the best interest rate.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Remember that money market accounts are best used as short-term investment vehicles of 1 year or less. Although these accounts pay interest, you'll find higher earnings by placing your money in a Certificate of Deposit (CD) account, if you agree to forgo access to your money during a specific time frame.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>When researching money market accounts, utilize financial education websites. Avoid conducting research found at investment websites for private companies, since their main goal is to attract customers.</item></list>
</text>
