<text id="autogum_whow_doc519" title="Price Tattoos" shortTile="price-tattoos" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2010-05-23" dateModified="2019-09-05" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Price-Tattoos" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Price Tattoos</head><p>The only way to get a reliable quote for a tattoo is to set up a consultation with your tattoo artist. This is because prices can vary by hundreds of dollars depending on your shop and specific tattoo. If you can't wait until your consultation, though, there are a few ways you can get a rough estimate for your tattoo. You can try emailing your artist or estimating based on their hourly rate. You can also check reviews for your shop to see how much others have paid for tattoos there. Just remember that the cost of your tattoo will depend on a number of factors including size, color, and level of detail.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Talking to Your Artist</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Schedule a consultation with your intended artist. To get an accurate estimate for your tattoo, the best thing you can do is schedule a consultation to talk specifically about what you want. Generally, artists will require you to make an appointment in advance for a consultation, so call your intended shop or artist so that you can talk about the tattoo you plan to get. <figure rend="Price Tattoos Step 1 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have an idea for both your tattoo design and placement. When you go to your consultation, you should have a rough idea of not only the design but also about how big you want your tattoo to be and where you want it placed on your body. Be prepared to talk about things like color palette and shading, too. <figure rend="Price Tattoos Step 2 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>It can help to bring along pictures or drawings that you are using for inspiration so that your artist can get a better idea of exactly what you want.</item></list></item>
<item>Send an email inquiry. Many shops' websites have forms you can use to make initial inquiries. Include as complete a description of your tattoo as you can when you fill out the form. If they allow image uploads, include any drawings or photos that you have been using for inspiration. <figure rend="Price Tattoos Step 3 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Email estimates will typically not be as accurate as those from consultations, but they can give you a general range of potential prices.</item></list></item>
<item>Ask your artist about their hourly rate if you are planning on a big piece. Larger pieces are often priced by the hour instead of by the piece. If you plan on getting a larger tattoo, such as a sleeve or full back piece, ask your artist about their hourly rate. Give them an idea of the piece you want so they can give you an estimate of how long it will take. <figure rend="Price Tattoos Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Evaluating Price by Shop</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Inquire about the shop minimum if you are getting a small piece. If you are getting a small tattoo such as a single word in a basic font or a small symbol with no shading, you may be subject to a shop minimum. Your artist or the shop manager should be able to tell you the minimum. <figure rend="Price Tattoos Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Consider the popularity of the shop. Getting your tattoo done at a popular shop could increase the price you pay for your piece. If your shop has a world-famous artist working at it, expect to pay more. Likewise, if your shop is locally popular and consistently booked due to its reputation for high-quality tattoos, you can expect your tattoo to be more expensive. <figure rend="Price Tattoos Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Check online reviews for the shop. Sites like Yelp are great places to check to get an idea of how much a tattoo could cost. Check online reviews for your shop to see how much people have paid in the past for pieces of similar size and with similar styles and levels of detail. <figure rend="Price Tattoos Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Estimating Cost</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Look at your artist's past works to get an idea of their skill. More talented and experienced artists will generally have higher prices. Take a look at your artist's portfolio and work history to get an idea of their skill level. If they are known for their elaborate or detailed tattoos, don't be surprised if they have an hourly rate of over $120-150 USD. <figure rend="Price Tattoos Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Consider the size of your tattoo. The larger your tattoo will be, the more you will pay for it. A small tattoo without much detail will often cost no more than the shop minimum, while larger tattoos about the size of a deck of playing cards could easily run anywhere between $100 and $200 USD. <figure rend="Price Tattoos Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Placement will also impact the cost of your tattoo. The more sensitive the area or the more difficult it is to tattoo, the more the piece will cost. An inner lip, tattoo, for example, may cost more than other small tattoos.</item></list></item>
<item>Factor in the amount of detail you want in your tattoo. Size, alone, is not going to determine the cost of your work. The amount of detail in your tattoo will also factor into the cost. The more fine details, vivid colors, and shading you have, the more expensive your tattoo will be. <figure rend="Price Tattoos Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If, for example, you choose to get a tribal turtle tattoo, you may pay around $100 USD for the piece. If you get the same size turtle tattoo with photorealistic detail, your piece might be closer to $250 - $300 USD.</item></list></item>
<item>Decide whether you want a custom or a flash piece. A flash tattoo, such as one that you would pick from the wall or a binder in your shop, will typically cost less than a custom design. This is because your artist won't have to spend any time drawing out an original piece. Be prepared to pay more if you are getting a custom piece. <figure rend="Price Tattoos Step 11 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Add in the cost of the tip. It is customary to tip your tattoo artists after they complete a session. The customary tip for a successful tattoo is 20% to 25%. At an absolute minimum, you should plan for a 10% o 15% tip. <figure rend="Price Tattoos Step 12 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Remember that the cheapest tattoo is not always the best tattoo. You are paying for quality and experience. Shop around to get a competitive price, but be prepared to pay for a higher-end piece.</item></list>
</text>
