<text id="autogum_whow_doc091" title="Post Private Videos on YouTube on PC or Mac" shortTile="post-private-videos" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-01-31" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Post-Private-Videos-on-YouTube-on-PC-or-Mac" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Post Private Videos on YouTube on PC or Mac</head><p>This wikiHow teaches you how to post private videos to YouTube on PC or Mac.  When you post a private video on YouTube, it does not appear in any search results, or on your channel.  Comments are not allowed, and only those you share the video with can view the video.  You can select to upload the video as private on the same web page you upload videos from.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Uploading a Private Video</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Go to <ref target="https://www.youtube.com">https://www.youtube.com</ref> in a web browser.  You can use any web browser or your choice on PC or Mac. <figure rend="Post Private Videos on YouTube on PC or Mac Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are not already signed into YouTube, click <hi rend="bold">Sign In</hi> in the upper-right corner and sign in with the email address and password associated with your YouTube/Google account.</item></list></item>
<item>Click on your profile picture in the upper right corner of the screen. <figure rend="Post Private Videos on YouTube on PC or Mac Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select YouTube Studio (beta) from the drop down menu. <figure rend="Post Private Videos on YouTube on PC or Mac Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . You should see this button in the middle of the screen. <figure rend="Post Private Videos on YouTube on PC or Mac Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the drop-down menu that says .  It's below the upload icon in the center of the screen.  This drop-down menu allows you to select different privacy options for the video you are about to upload.  By default, videos you upload are set to Public. <figure rend="Post Private Videos on YouTube on PC or Mac Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select .  It's the third option in the drop-down menu.  This sets the uploaded video to Private.  This means that only people you invite to view the video can view it. <figure rend="Post Private Videos on YouTube on PC or Mac Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click .  It's the icon with an arrow pointing up.  It's above the drop-down menu.  This opens a file browser you can use to browse for video files on your computer. <figure rend="Post Private Videos on YouTube on PC or Mac Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can also drag and drop video files to the upload icon.</item></list></item>
<item>Select a video and click .  Use the file browser to navigate to the video you want to upload.  When you find it, click on it and then click <hi rend="bold">Open</hi> in the lower-right corner to begin uploading it to YouTube.  This takes you to another screen that informs you of the processing progress.  You can also edit the details of the video while it is processing. <figure rend="Post Private Videos on YouTube on PC or Mac Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Type a name for the video (optional).  YouTube automatically names new videos after the file name.  If you want to change the video title, delete the file name in the first box and type your own name for the video. <figure rend="Post Private Videos on YouTube on PC or Mac Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Type a description for the video (optional).  If you wish to add a description of the video, type it in the large box labeled description. <figure rend="Post Private Videos on YouTube on PC or Mac Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click  (Optional).  If you want to share the video with specific users, click <hi rend="bold">Share</hi> below the drop-down menu that says "Private" on the right.  This displays a pop-up allows you to share the video with users. <figure rend="Post Private Videos on YouTube on PC or Mac Step 11 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Type the email addresses of users and click .  If you are sharing the video with specific users, type the email address associated with their YouTube account.  Then click the blue button that says <hi rend="bold">Ok</hi>. <figure rend="Post Private Videos on YouTube on PC or Mac Step 12 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can only share a private video with users that have a YouTube account.</item></list></item>
<item>Click .  This option is available once the video is finished processing.  It's the blue button in the upper-right corner.  This uploads the video as private.  Only you and other people you share the video with can view the video.   <figure rend="Post Private Videos on YouTube on PC or Mac Step 13 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Sharing a Private Video</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Go to <ref target="https://www.youtube.com">https://www.youtube.com</ref> in a web browser.  You can use any web browser or your choice on PC or Mac. <figure rend="Post Private Videos on YouTube on PC or Mac Step 14 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are not already signed into YouTube, click <hi rend="bold">Sign In</hi> in the upper-right corner and sign in with the email address and password associated with your YouTube/Google account.</item></list></item>
<item>Click your profile icon.  Your profile icon is the image you selected for your Google account.  It's in the upper-right corner of the screen.  This displays your profile menu. <figure rend="Post Private Videos on YouTube on PC or Mac Step 15 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you have not selected a profile picture for your Google account, your profile displays a colored circle with your initial.</item></list></item>
<item>Click .  It's near the top of the profile menu.  It's next to an icon that resembles a gear.  This opens the Creator Studio, which allows you to edit video. <figure rend="Post Private Videos on YouTube on PC or Mac Step 16 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If "YouTube Studio (Beta)" appears in your profile menu, instead of Creator Studio, click <hi rend="bold">YouTube Studio (Beta)</hi> in the profile menu, and then click <hi rend="bold">Creator Studio Classic</hi> in the sidebar to the left.  Sharing Private videos is not yet available in YouTube Studio.</item></list></item>
<item>Click .  It's in the sidebar to the left.  This displays a list of all your uploaded videos. <figure rend="Post Private Videos on YouTube on PC or Mac Step 17 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click  below the video you want to share.  The edit button is below each video in the list.  This opens the Edit Video menu in Creator Studio. <figure rend="Post Private Videos on YouTube on PC or Mac Step 18 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click .  It's on the right side of the screen below the drop-down menu that says "Private".  This displays a pop-up that allows you to add users you want to share the video with. <figure rend="Post Private Videos on YouTube on PC or Mac Step 19 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Type the email addresses of YouTube users.  Use the box to type the email address associated with any YouTube users you want to share the video with.  The user must have a YouTube account in order to be able to view a video set to private. <figure rend="Post Private Videos on YouTube on PC or Mac Step 20 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click .  This sends an email invite to the user to notify them you have shared a video with them. <figure rend="Post Private Videos on YouTube on PC or Mac Step 21 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
