<text id="autogum_whow_doc237" title="Write a Trading Plan" shortTile="write-trading-plan" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-05-11" dateModified="2019-10-31" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Write-a-Trading-Plan" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Write a Trading Plan</head><p>Writing a trading plan is an integral part of being a successful market trader. Whether trading stocks, currencies or commodities, a detailed trading plan helps to solidify a trading strategy and encourages adherence to a well-developed trading system. An effective trading plan details the steps that a trader must follow when entering and exiting trades. Without a trading plan in place, traders are more susceptible to trading mistakes, overtrading and making impulsive decisions in volatile markets, particularly when trading online. Here are the steps for writing a trading plan.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>At the very first place, you have to decide which financial instruments you will trade. You may be strictly a stock or currency trader, or you may be trading multiple markets. So, try to create a separate category in your trading plan for each financial instrument. It is necessary to check the market asset volatility before selecting a particular asset type. For example, in the forex market, if you want to trade exotic pair, then you have to pay a higher spread compared to the major pairs. <figure rend="Write a Trading Plan Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Determine which stocks, currencies or other financial instruments to trade. For example, you may be interested in a few company stocks. Or when trading currencies, you might trade only one currency pair or all pairs related to the Great British Pound (GBP). List the names of the specific companies, currencies or commodities.  <figure rend="Write a Trading Plan Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Identify your market indicators. For example, you might trade a particular currency based on a series of chart indicators related to momentum, moving averages, and trend lines. Write down the exact conditions that must be met before you can enter a particular trade. Remember, trading indicators will help you to analyze the trading market properly.  <figure rend="Write a Trading Plan Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Decide ahead of time how many shares or lots you will purchase. Thinking through the trading size ahead of time will help you to avoid taking risks that may result in tremendous loss. Record the number of shares or lots you intend to purchase. Do not overtrade.  <figure rend="Write a Trading Plan Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Set specific price entry points. Your goal may be to buy a particular stock when it reaches a specific price. Write down at which price you will buy the stock, plus or minus a few points, if applicable. <figure rend="Write a Trading Plan Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Write down the process of how you will monitor each trade. When day trading, for example, you might check the price of your stock or currency every 15 minutes. Or you might set an alarm to alert you to these time increments. Monitoring each trade can help you to avoid extra loss in trading.  <figure rend="Write a Trading Plan Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Decide on the parameters for trade exits. Documenting your exact strategy for trade exits prevents last-minute or impulsive trading decisions, such as exiting a trade too early or holding it for too long. If you have a well-tested and profitable trading system with a strict money management plan, exiting your trade based on set parameters will yield the best results.  <figure rend="Write a Trading Plan Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Write the exact conditions that must be met before you can exit your trade. This may be an exact price point, a chart indicator level or a specific time of day.</item></list></item>
<item>Include a section for trading times. If trading the 24-hour foreign exchange market, trading can be a nonstop event. Decide on a trading schedule and write it into your trading plan. When day trading stocks, you might work for 4 hours each day starting at the daily open. If you trade in longer time frames, your trading schedule may involve only a 15-minute daily commitment to check prices and read relevant market news. <figure rend="Write a Trading Plan Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Evaluate your trading plan. Include a section in your trading plan for evaluating your trades. This can be a comment box where you write down whether you adhered to your trading plan. Alternatively, it may be a list of steps you must check off while trading. The trading plan can be changed based on the market price movement. Note that your plan will help you to be a successful trader. <figure rend="Write a Trading Plan Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
