<text id="autogum_whow_doc142" title="Handle Differences of Opinion" shortTile="handle-differences" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-06-03" dateModified="2018-10-10" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Handle-Differences-of-Opinion" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Handle Differences of Opinion</head><p>An opinion is not fact, but what someone thinks or believes. Not everyone will have the same opinions on things, and some opinions are very hard to change. Since people think different, try these steps to reduce differences and see what happens.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Try to think like the other person. Sometimes, it seems hard to look at something from another perspective, but it's a good way to understand why they feel as they do. You see, if you really try to understand both sides, you can approach the issue more neutrally. Religion and love can be very debatable, but that's not the point. You can understand someone if you really want to get along with them. This is not about RIGHT versus WRONG. Consider the following examples:
<list type="unordered"><item>If you're with same sex marriage, try to understand why someone else might not approve of those of the same gender marrying. It does go against some religious rules held by some people.</item>
<item>If you are opposed to same sex marriage, try to put yourself in a position where you love someone very much, but you can't get married because other people have an issue with it.</item>
<item>Suppose your child wants to go on a vacation with a friend, but there could problems and implications without his/her guardian with them on the trip. As the parent, try to understand why your child wants to go and have fun, and why being denied permission seems unfair simply because you're working the weekend and he/she will be left with nothing to do.</item>
<item>Your mom has refused to let you go on a trip with your friend. Try to put yourself in her shoes and you'll realize your mother is going to worry about you; there's no way to stop her from it. To her, your safety is more important than how much fun you could have with your friend.</item></list></item>
<item>Give it time and see if the argument will fade away. You and your friend have a fight about something, and there is no possible way you will agree on it  - ever. Step away and give yourself time to think about it. If you really care about someone, you can set every difference aside and still be their friend.
<list type="unordered"><item>You can always try to make them understand (in a calm way) that you understand why he/she won't change their mind and why you won't either. Explain that you should just let it go and set it aside because, in all honesty, your friendship is about much more than your differences.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If talking to the person about the differences, don't be rude. Come to your friend calmly and rationally, because nobody likes someone with a rude attitude.</item></list>
</text>
