<text id="autogum_whow_doc399" title="Make a Warli Painting" shortTile="make-warli-painting" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-06-11" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-a-Warli-Painting" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make a Warli Painting</head><head>Introduction</head>
<p>Warli paintings are rudimentary wall paintings made by the Warli tribe of India. The central motif in this painting is surrounded by scenes portraying hunting, fishing, and farming,festivals, dances, trees and animals. Although these paintings were traditionally wall paintings, you can draw them on paper, pots, canvas etc. You should also not limit yourself to paints and can use other mediums such as color pencils and crayons.Warli painting depict the activities of a tribal village. So, your scene can be a bonfire with people dancing around it, or people doing their day to day activities like cooking, farming, kids playing, carrying water from the river etc. Once you decide what you want to show, paint accordingly.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Background</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Paint/Color the background evenly in a Red Ochre. This is the color used traditionally to paint the background in Warli paintings.The figures are painted in white. However, you can also use black or any dark color. In contemporary paintings, a white background with brown or black figures has also been observed. You can pick either one, as long as you have a contrast between the background and the figures.</item></list>
<head>Making a Human Figure</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Make a circle and fill it in to make the head. If the human is a female, just add another small circle on the side of the circle to indicate a bun. <figure rend="Head.jpeg"></figure></item>
<item>Add a small line under the circle, which depicts a neck. <figure rend="Neck.jpeg"></figure></item>
<item>Draw an inverted triangle attached to the line. <figure rend="Shoulders.jpeg"></figure></item>
<item>Draw an upright triangle with its tip attached to the tip of the previous triangle and make them both equal in size. <figure rend="Torso.jpeg"></figure></item>
<item>Draw a line each  from the top 2 vertices of the inverted triangle to draw the arms. If the action you are trying to show needs elbows, then just draw another 2 lines at the end of the first 2 lines to show a joint. <figure rend="Arms.jpeg"></figure></item>
<item>Standing Legs -
<list type="unordered"><item>Draw 2 parallel lines from the base of the upright triangle at an angle of 120 degrees from the horizontal.</item>
<item>Draw another set of parallel lines at the angle of 60 degrees from the horizontal at the end of these lines.</item>
<item>Draw 2 small lines aligned with the horizontal at the end of the previous 2 lines to make the feet. <figure rend="Leg1.jpeg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Running Legs -
<list type="unordered"><item>Draw 2 lines from the base of the upright triangle, first one at the angle of 160 degrees from the horizontal and the other one at an angle of 90 degrees.</item>
<item>Draw a line perpendicular to the end of the previous lines.</item>
<item>Draw a line aligned with the horizontal on the first leg and draw a line perpendicular to the leg for the second one to draw the feet. <figure rend="Leg2.jpeg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Sitting Legs -
<list type="unordered"><item>Draw 2 horizontal 'U's, facing each other, originating from each of the 2 vertices of the upright triangle.</item>
<item>Make 2 straight lines from the end of the 'U's to draw the feet. <figure rend="Leg3.jpeg"></figure></item></list></item></list>
<head>Making Animals</head>
<p>Since Warli paintings are essentially stick figures, this set of instructions is for making a general animal. You can differentiate into a specific animal by varying sizes, adding horns, distinct ears or tail. </p>
<list type="ordered"><item>Make a circle and fill it in to make the head. <figure rend="Animalhead.jpeg"></figure></item>
<item>Add a small line under the circle, which depicts a neck. <figure rend="Animalneck.jpeg"></figure></item>
<item>Draw an horizontal triangle attached to the line. <figure rend="Animalshoulders.jpeg"></figure></item>
<item>Draw another horizontal triangle with its tip attached to the tip of the previous triangle and make them both equal in size. <figure rend="Animaltorso.jpeg"></figure></item>
<item>Draw 2 lines with a 30 degree between them from each of the vertices facing downward. They make an inverted ‘V’. <figure rend="Limbs.jpeg"></figure></item>
<item>Draw a tail of appropriate size, according to your animal, from the upward facing vertex of the second triangle.</item>
<item>Add whiskers, horns, and ears to the head according to your animal. <figure rend="Stag.jpeg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Making A Dholak (Indian Drums)</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Make an oval shape. <figure rend="Oval.jpeg"></figure></item>
<item>Make another smaller oval in the center inside the oval. Fill this oval in. <figure rend="Liloval.jpeg"></figure></item>
<item>Make a semicircle using the first oval's middle as the center and the length of the oval as the diameter. <figure rend="Semicircle.jpeg"></figure></item>
<item>Make inverted triangles with their bases on the perimeter of the oval inside the semicircle. <figure rend="18.jpeg"></figure></item>
<item>Shade the area of the semicircle that doesn't have the triangles in it. <figure rend="Dhol.jpeg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Materials</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Red Ochre(or your choice of background color) and White paint(or crayons,colored pens, etc.)</item>
<item>Paper(or wall,vase, etc)</item></list>
</text>
