<text id="autogum_whow_doc308" title="Make Food That Will Help Fight Lead Exposure" shortTile="make-food-help-fight" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2017-02-07" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-Food-That-Will-Help-Fight-Lead-Exposure" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make Food That Will Help Fight Lead Exposure</head><p>Lead exposure can be prevented by changing your diet and consuming 3 important nutrients everyday. Calcium, Vitamin C, and Iron are key nutrients to help prevent lead exposure. Calcium strengthens bones, which makes it less likely for lead to be absorbed. Vitamin C helps your kidneys get rid of lead. Calcium and Vitamin C, along with Iron can prevent lead from being absorbed into your body. The specific foods listed below contain these nutrients. Consuming small meals like these throughout the day can ensure that you're receiving enough of these nutrients.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>French Toast</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Mix 1 egg, 1 teaspoon of vanilla extract, and ½ a teaspoon of cinnamon into a bowl</item>
<item>Stir in ¼ cup of milk.</item>
<item>Dip bread into the mixture, coating both sides evenly</item>
<item>Lightly grease a nonstick pan</item>
<item>Cook bread slices on medium heat until both sides are browned</item>
<item>OPTIONAL: Serve with maple syrup or top it off with banana slices or any other fruit as they provide Vitamin C and other beneficial nutrients.</item></list>
<head>Pizza Bagels</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Preheat your oven to 375 degrees</item>
<item>Slice open a bagel and place it on a pan. Breads provide iron to the body.</item>
<item>Spread 2 tablespoons of tomato sauce onto the bagels</item>
<item>Add shredded cheese (or a cheese slice) onto each bagel. Cheese is another source of calcium.</item>
<item>OPTIONAL: Add toppings such as pepperoni for taste. Any lean meat is also great source for iron.</item>
<item>Bake in oven for 10 minutes or until cheese is melted</item></list>
<head>Strawberry Banana Smoothie</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Add 2 cups of frozen strawberries and 1 peeled banana into a blender. It's best to cut the tops of the strawberries first. The fruits provide Vitamin C.</item>
<item>Add one cup of milk (almond is preferred) and one cup of ice. The ice makes for a thicker smoothie. Milk is an excellent source of calcium and strengthens bones.</item>
<item>OPTIONAL: add a dollop of yogurt (another  source of Vitamin C) or a tablespoon of honey for taste</item>
<item>Pulse in blender until all ingredients are combined</item>
<item>Pour into a cup and enjoy!</item></list>
<head>Ingredients For French Toast</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>1 Egg</item>
<item>1 Teaspoon Vanilla Extract</item>
<item>1/2 Teaspoon Cinnamon</item>
<item>4 Slices of Bread</item>
<item>Vegetable Oil</item>
<item>Bananas (Optional)</item>
<item>Maple Syrup (Optional)</item></list>
<head>Ingredients For Pizza Bagels</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>1 Bagel</item>
<item>2 Tablespoons Tomato Sauce</item>
<item>Shredded Cheese or Sliced Cheese</item>
<item>Pepperoni (Optional)</item></list>
<head>Ingredients For Strawberry Banana Smoothie</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>2 Cups Frozen Strawberries</item>
<item>1 Banana</item>
<item>1 Cup Milk (Almond preferred)</item>
<item>1 Cup Ice</item>
<item>Yogurt (Optional)</item>
<item>1 Tablespoon Honey (Optional)</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't add all ingredients for the smoothie at once, or else they may get stuck. Try adding in the ice after blending the fruit and milk if this happens.</item>
<item>Be sure to watch the bottom of bagels to make sure they don't burn.</item>
<item>Watch out for the blender blade and make sure to keep lid on when pulsing the blender.</item>
<item>Don't grease the pan for the french toast too much.</item>
<item>Yogurts and fruits are rich in Vitamin C</item>
<item>Milk and cheese are a great source in Calcium</item>
<item>Breads and lean meats contain Iron</item></list>
</text>
