<text id="autogum_whow_doc247" title="Choose Best Digital Marketing Course" shortTile="choose-best-digital" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2016-04-13" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Choose-Best-Digital-Marketing-Course" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Choose Best Digital Marketing Course</head><p>Digital marketing is evolving and changing the world like ever. Every second, a startup is launched across the globe. And the increasing need of digital marketing professionals, there is also a rise in the training institutes who are offering professional courses and making you ready for the industry needs. According to reports from various organizations, the online advertising market in India is expected to touch $ 1.2billion by the end of 2016.In the current digital advertisement market; the search and the display feature contribute the most.Thus in this competitive training industry, there is a need of institute that prepare professionals for the industry. Before going for any professional course in digital marketing whether it is online or offline, you must verify some things so that it must help you professionally in your career prospect. Here are those criteria to look for:</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>·        Course Curriculum &amp;Trainer: Before enrolling for any course in the digital marketing, look for the curriculum which is currently in demand in the market. Measure the institute for the course they offer and check the expertise of their trainers. The best way to check these all is to attend a demo class with the training institute.</item>
<item>·        Certification: A professional certification can definitely make a difference while you are a fresher. Sometimes it also helps if you have experience in a particular domain but having a certification in digital marketing ensures that you are an expert in this field too. Thus choosing a good institute giving certification in the digital marketing field will help you in getting a good job profile or a good bump in the salary package. So opt for certification courses recognized by the industry.</item>
<item>·        Reviews: Always look for reviews and go with it. It helps you giving a clear view about the course and the institute. The students who have taken training from the institute always giveright review what they have felt during the training.  So check for reviews and recommendations from the ex-students through discussion forums. Reach out to alumni of the institute oversocial media platforms and ask for the feedback, where possible.</item>
<item>·        Placements: over all, placement is the first and last thing a fresher need and thinks before joining any course. Research and look for the placement service offered by the institute and go for feedback from the ex-students.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Once you are done with the above research work then go with the best training institute. For your convenient, below are the most popular institutes offering Digital Marketing courses.</item>
<item>Delhi School of Internet Marketing(DSIM): Founded in 2011 by Kunal Choudhary. Delhi School of Internet Marketing offers advanced digital marketing training that covers 17 modules and provides both in-class and live-online classes for working professionals, business owners and job-seekers. For in-class training, the centers are available in Delhi, Bangalore and Kolkata.  The program costs Rs. 48,450 + Tax. DSIM offers 8 certifications. Placement support is good for working professionals and freshers.DSIM claims to have more than 7095 professionals trained through their ADMTP and their trainees have been placed in various renowned brands and organizations. You can check out reviews of the institute here. <ref target="http://dsimreviews.com/">http://dsimreviews.com/</ref></item>
<item>Digital Vidya: The Course/Training includes 6 core Modules and 15 specialized modules. All courses are online with no physical venue. The CDMM – Certified Digital Marketing Master Course costing is INR49, 900 + Service tax. Digital Vidya offers 8 certification courses according to the need. Placement support is good for newbies and Freshers. Digital Vidya has claimed to conduct over 700 trainingprograms for more than 12,000 participants from across Asia. You can check out reviews of the institute here: <ref target="http://coursedekho.com/2015/09/01/digital-vidya-review/">http://coursedekho.com/2015/09/01/digital-vidya-review/</ref></item>
<item>NIIT:  The first institutes to launch a comprehensive digital marketing training program in India in 2012 and  offers Professional Diploma in Digital  Marketing. The training will happen via a live video stream rather than offering fully online training. No option for online Learning and course fee is non transparent. NIIT Imperia has partnered with Digital Marketing Institute (DMI) Ireland to offer a Professional Diploma in Digital Marketing. This course is accredited by Further Education and Training Awards Council (FETAC) of Ireland. NIIT claim to train 40,000 professionals. The training centers of NIIT are spread in more than 30 cities of India, butthe lead instructor will not be physically present. You can check out reviews of the institute here: <ref target="http://www.mouthshut.com/product-reviews/NIIT-Mumbai-reviews-925002525">http://www.mouthshut.com/product-reviews/NIIT-Mumbai-reviews-925002525</ref></item>
<item>Simplilearn: Simplilearn was founded in 2009 by Krishna Kumar. The Digital marketing Training program is named as Advance online marketing certification training. The Course covers 9 Modules and provides only e learning based classes. The program costs Rs.49,999+ taxes. offers Master program certification by OMCP.org.OMCP is awarded to professionals who have completed extensive training and possess several years of online marketing experience. Initially Simplilearn was a blog with useful tips which later evolved into a training company. The course aimed at helping working professionals and aspirants. You can check out reviews of the institute here.<ref target="http://www.simplilearn.com/reviews">http://www.simplilearn.com/reviews</ref></item></list>
</text>
