<text id="autogum_whow_doc117" title="Browse Internet Websites Without Your Parents Knowing" shortTile="browse-internet-websites" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2008-03-25" dateModified="2019-10-03" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Browse-Internet-Websites-Without-Your-Parents-Knowing" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Browse Internet Websites Without Your Parents Knowing</head><p>Do you want to look at a website but don't want your parents to know? This article will help you.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Incognito Browser Method</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find a website your parents will allow you to use. Visit that website and keep the page open. <figure rend="Browse Internet Websites Without Your Parents Knowing Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find the website you want to use and open it up in a new window or tab. Make sure to watch and listen for parents or anybody else that may tell on you. If someone comes, quickly switch windows or tabs to the other website. <figure rend="Browse Internet Websites Without Your Parents Knowing Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>In Windows, you can quickly close the tab or window by pressing +.</item>
<item>In Linux, you can switch workspaces quickly using the mouse wheel. Open your System Settings and click on <hi rend="italic">Windows Manager Tweaks</hi>. Then select <hi rend="italic">Workspaces</hi> tab and check the <hi rend="italic">Use the mouse wheel on the desktop to switch workspaces</hi>.</item></list></item>
<item>Clear your history. When you're finished, delete all the history on your computer that leads to any websites your parents don't want you on. <figure rend="Browse Internet Websites Without Your Parents Knowing Step 3 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>In Firefox, there is actually an option you can select which will automatically clear your browsing history when you exit the browser. <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Automatically_Delete_Firefox_History_on_Exit">This article</ref> will guide you in setting that up.</item></list></item>
<item>Using incognito mode! This is a special window in the browser which, when used, does not record any internet data, history, or cache. Most popular browser have such an option. <figure rend="Browse Internet Websites Without Your Parents Knowing Step 4 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>In Internet Explorer, you can press ++ to enter Private browsing. To exit incognito mode, simply close the window with incognito enabled.</item>
<item>In Firefox, you can press ++. To exit this window in Firefox, press the same buttons.</item>
<item>In Google Chrome, you can press ++ to enter Incognito Mode. To exit incognito mode, simply close the window with incognito enabled.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Alternate Browser Method</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Download another internet browser such as Firefox or Safari. <figure rend="Browse Internet Websites Without Your Parents Knowing Step 5 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do not make this browser your default browser. When you install it make sure to <hi rend="italic">not</hi> set as your default browser. <figure rend="Browse Internet Websites Without Your Parents Knowing Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Clear all evidence of the installation. If you are using Windows, delete the quick launch shortcut and move it to some safe location. <figure rend="Browse Internet Websites Without Your Parents Knowing Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use this browser to surf the internet privately. Now, you can use the other browser for stuff you don't want your parents to know about. The favourites, history, cache, and cookies will be separate from your normal browser. Your parents will continue to use the other browser normally, and even if they check the history they won't find anything, but make sure they don't notice the other browser. <figure rend="Browse Internet Websites Without Your Parents Knowing Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Portable Firefox Method</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Select a device to host your portable applications. Any cell phone, MP3 player, camera, USB flash drive, or portable hard drive which comes up as a <hi rend="italic">removable device</hi> in Windows will work. <figure rend="Browse Internet Websites Without Your Parents Knowing Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Download the Portable Firefox. You can search it on Google. <figure rend="Browse Internet Websites Without Your Parents Knowing Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Install their launcher menu and then portable Firefox on your device. <figure rend="Browse Internet Websites Without Your Parents Knowing Step 11 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Restart your device. You can do this by unplugging your device and plunging it back in, or you can turn it off, then turn it back on. <figure rend="Browse Internet Websites Without Your Parents Knowing Step 12 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Unblock Windows Firewall. Windows will ask you what you want to do; let it start <hi rend="italic">PortableAppz.blogspot.com</hi>; this will open the menu. Red, looks like the Start menu, comes up on the right. <figure rend="Browse Internet Websites Without Your Parents Knowing Step 13 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the Firefox icon/name on the menu. <figure rend="Browse Internet Websites Without Your Parents Knowing Step 14 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Portable Firefox will keep all of your bookmarks, history, and settings on your device; it won't leave anything behind on the host computer.</item>
<item>You can take it to a friend's house, hook it up, and all of your stuff is there.</item>
<item>4GB and 8GB flash drives can be bought for very cheap now online and in some stores. Corsair drives tend to have the fastest speeds.</item></list></item>
<item>Be sure to exit the menu (grey circle with white arrow) when you're done using it. <figure rend="Browse Internet Websites Without Your Parents Knowing Step 15 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>VPN</head>
<p>For a VPN is the newer way to hide data online, the Incognito tab, cannot hide data from your router, but a VPN such as Tor can. They are also connected to the dark web sites, so are made to be anonymous.</p>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>It's best to be alone when searching something you don't want your parents seeing.</item>
<item>Use your instinct - it's better to be safe than sorry when it comes to things like this.</item>
<item>On Internet Explorer, delete your history by clicking tools, then click "delete browsing history" and click delete all. On Firefox, click tools, then click "clear private data" and click "clear private data" now.</item>
<item>A Windows 7 is the best computer for this because the internet tabs do not show a preview of the description of websites. If there is one in your house, use it.</item>
<item>If you're technically minded, then you can use a proxy website which will retrieve the packet data from another server, not your internet service provider, this will hide it from any parent controls installed on the router or family safety program. You could also use  a Free VPN service which will divert all internet logs to another server.</item>
<item>Don't use Google, use DuckDuckGo instead, because Google keeps a log of what you searched for that you can't erase, but DuckDuckGo does not.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If your parents find out, you may lose computer privileges or have parental controls turned on and block the sites they don't want you on.</item>
<item>Your parents do everything for your own good. It is better to obey them and not to disobey. They are much more experienced and probably won't allow anything which could harm their children.</item></list>
</text>
