<text id="autogum_whow_doc647" title="Ride a Holoholo Balance Board" shortTile="ride-holoholo-balance" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2007-12-08" dateModified="2019-04-13" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Ride-a-Holoholo-Balance-Board" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ride a Holoholo Balance Board</head><p>Using a Holoholo Board has great fitness benefits and helps you  improve your balance, making it a great cross-trainer for athletes. It's also a lot of fun!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Method 1</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Set up. Put the Pipe Roller parallel to the board.  <figure rend="Ride a Holoholo Balance Board Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Insert the pipe into the stops and under the Pipe-Lock screws. Tighten it using your fingers. <figure rend="Ride a Holoholo Balance Board Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try Skier style. This is also called the SUP (Stand Up Paddle-board) style. It is the easiest style to learn. Place your feet on the board in line with the pipe and board. Bend your knees for more of a challenge. Wheelies, hang ten, and other moves are possible, and you can get a skiing sensation when transferring weight across the roller. Balance requirements are very similar to stand up paddle boarding. <figure rend="Ride a Holoholo Balance Board Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try Boarder Style. Step onto the Holoholo board as if it were a skateboard; the board will have a slight roll and lots of tilt to challenge your balance. Once you are comfortable with the board touching the ground on both sides, you can try to stay balanced in the small amount of travel or roll that is allowed by the Pipe-Lock and stops. There is a fine line you can feel when you are centered over the pipe roller and maintaining control. That same sensation is common to most board sports. Once you have your balance, try kick turns, 360's and all kinds of skate tricks. Practice rail grabs and other surfing, snowboarding, and wake board positions. <figure rend="Ride a Holoholo Balance Board Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try SUP Style Kanoa ride. Sometimes the board is restricted from stops if you do the kanoa ride. <figure rend="Ride a Holoholo Balance Board Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Method 2: Pipe Roller riding perpendicular to the board</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Use this method to get great overall balance training and lateral movement. The board is restricted by stops, but is not locked in as it is in Method 1. Spotter or assistance is recommended for beginners. <figure rend="Ride a Holoholo Balance Board Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try Boarder Style. This will feel very much like skiing. It employs the same basic concept as the Indo and Bongo Boards. Place your feet on the board boarder-style and then shift your body weight to the raised side of the board. The board will tilt and the roller will move back and forth between the stops on the bottom of the board. This is great fun and when you bend knees and lower your body weight, it becomes even more challenging. <figure rend="Ride a Holoholo Balance Board Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>PIPE IS NOT LOCKED IN. Keep feet on opposite sides of roller, falls likely if both feet are on same side of roller. <figure rend="Ride a Holoholo Balance Board Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Skier/in-line SUP skater style is not recommended. <figure rend="Ride a Holoholo Balance Board Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Balance Board <figure rend="Ride a Holoholo Balance Board Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>SET UP Half Pipe Riding Parallel to Board <figure rend="Ride a Holoholo Balance Board Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>(REQUIRES 1/2 PIPE-Sold Separately) <figure rend="Ride a Holoholo Balance Board Step 15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Goal- Practice for advanced levels #4 and improves a Boarders Forward/ Backward tilt control that is needed when cutting or carving in board-sports. Extension and flexion of calves and centering of body weight with little risk of falls. <figure rend="Ride a Holoholo Balance Board Step 16.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Insert the 1/2 pipe into stop slot on the bottom of the board and then use one hand to hold the 1/2 pipe in lay them down as one unit. Make sure the 1/2 pipe stays in knock outs and test by placing one foot atop the board and pushing on the board. If it fits correctly the board and 1/2 pipe will move as one unit. You can ride this set up in-line skater/skier and boarder style. You can even do basic kick turns while riding boarder style by pivoting on one end of the board similar to skateboarding. <figure rend="Ride a Holoholo Balance Board Step 17.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>SET UP Half Pipe Riding Perpendicular to Board. <figure rend="Ride a Holoholo Balance Board Step 18.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>(REQUIRES 1/2 PIPE-Sold Separately) <figure rend="Ride a Holoholo Balance Board Step 19.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Goal-Build a balanced athlete conditioned for a solid "ready position" and good confidence booster before attempting other levels. Improves lateral shifting of body weight and basic sense of balance. Place the 1/2 pipe perpendicular to the length of the board, open side facing the ground or the rounded part touching the board. <figure rend="Ride a Holoholo Balance Board Step 20.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Boarder-style with feet perpendicular to the length of board board. Approach the board from the middle of the length of the board and place one foot on at a time. It will rock laterally. Try to keep the board centered or level so that neither side touches the ground. Benefits- Encourages a natural bend to knees and keeping body weight centered and lateral movement awareness. <figure rend="Ride a Holoholo Balance Board Step 21.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>In-line skater/Skier SUP Style- feel parallel to the length of board board. Place feet in the center of the board so it rocks toward your toes and heels. This has skier type feel and also helps develop a good "ready position". <figure rend="Ride a Holoholo Balance Board Step 22.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Set UP #5 ADVANCED Rider- <figure rend="Ride a Holoholo Balance Board Step 23.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>(REQUIRES 1/2 PIPE-Sold Separately) <figure rend="Ride a Holoholo Balance Board Step 24.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Goal- Simulates steep drops,inclines, foil boarding. <figure rend="Ride a Holoholo Balance Board Step 25.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Lay the 1/2 pipe on the carpet or pad with open side facing down. You can either place the board and pipe set as in method #3 on top and then step on the board or you can start riding boarder style and pivot or kickturn to basically climb on top of the 1/2 pipe. This will add challenging angles to balance on and interact with. <figure rend="Ride a Holoholo Balance Board Step 26.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Boarder style is with feet perpendicular to the length of board. Inline skater/Skier is with feet parallel to the length of the board.</item>
<item>A spotter can assist a new rider by holding their hands or hips.</item>
<item>Holoholo boards can also help you learn the basics of wakeboarding.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Parental or adult supervision of child riders is necessary at all times.</item>
<item>The Holoholo board is designed for use on a rugged/padded surface, such a durable carpet/pad, but can be ridden on concrete of you use pipe grips - rubber sleeves that add traction. Don't use a Holoholo board on hardwood, though; it will likely damage wood floors.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Holoholo Balance Board</item>
<item>Pipe Roller</item>
<item>1/2 Pipe accessory</item></list>
</text>
