<text id="autogum_whow_doc526" title="Increase Revenue in a Hair Salon" shortTile="increase-revenue" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-05-01" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Increase-Revenue-in-a-Hair-Salon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Increase Revenue in a Hair Salon</head><p>There are all kinds of ways hair salon owners can adjust their business plans in order to boost earnings. Do you happen to own or work at a hair salon? If so, you'll surely want to check out these 7 simple steps you can use to help increase revenue.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Design Gift Cards For Your Customers</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>There are all kinds of websites and companies which give you the ability to create custom gift cards for your salon. Don't necessarily have the extra funds to have personalized gift cards made? You definitely could always look at making your own salon gift certificates. If you choose to go this route, make sure you use a unique paper or design to ensure you're able to authenticate them. Creating your own cards allows room for more creativity, but professional gift cards will undoubtedly impress your customers.</item></list>
<head>Start a Customer Loyalty Program</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Another great way to increase the revenue of your hair salon is by creating a customer loyalty program. These special programs reward clients for booking multiple appointments or purchasing a certain dollar amount of services within a designated time frame. One of the best ways to create your own customer loyalty program is by designing your own cards that you can punch out a spot on each time a customer comes in for a hair service. To eliminate the expense of creating cards all together, you could even look at having your salon receptionist keep a customer log on the computer. This will ensure that each and every salon client gets their rightful loyalty rewards.</item></list>
<head>Build a Client List</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>It is extremely helpful to have an established list of regular clientele with their complete contact information. In order to begin building your client list, have stylists ask clients who come in to the salon for their email and phone number. If you have the contact information of your clients, you can then easily send out email newsletters notifying them of sales and promotions. You could also even have your receptionist occasionally give them a call to let them know about special offers.</item></list>
<head>Offer Hair Care Products</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Not every client is going to be able to make it to the salon once or twice a week. Most of them are going to want to know how he or she can create the particular look you gave them when doing their own hair. This is why you definitely want to sell the products you and other stylists use to style hair in the salon. It's recommended you set up a display case with a number of smaller bottles that your clients can purchase and take home with them.</item></list>
<head>Expand Your Services</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>To raise the revenue of your salon, you may also want to expand the services you offer. If you only offer hair services at the moment, maybe look at finding a makeup artist, masseuse, or nail technician for clients who want to purchase a complete makeover package.</item></list>
<head>Ask For Feedback</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>The best way to find out what you can do to improve the earnings of your salon is to ask your clients. You should do this by creating feedback forms and asking clients to rate specific aspects of their salon experience.</item></list>
<head>Use Social Media</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>In today's business world, the use of social media is a wonderful way to reach new potential clients and stay in touch with clients you have already serviced. You definitely want to make sure your salon has a presence on the biggest social media sites such as Facebook, Instagram and Twitter. Post a few pictures of your best hair creations to have new clients coming in and contacting you to book appointments in no time.</item></list>
</text>
