<text id="autogum_whow_doc693" title="Map Out a Travel Route" shortTile="map-out-travel-route" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2012-04-26" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Map-Out-a-Travel-Route" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Map Out a Travel Route</head><p>Long-distance travel can be an exciting prospect, but if poorly planned it can quickly become a costly and frustrating experience. Planning and organizing your directions before setting out will help you get to your destination on time and avoid getting lost. Choosing a travel route has become easier in recent years with the increased availability of GPS-enabled mobile devices and online mapping services. Listed below are some of the key steps in learning how to map out a travel route.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Determine the overall length of your trip. The total distance between your origin and destination will help you determine how long your trip will take and how many times you will need to stop. The easiest way to determine your travel distance is by entering your origin and destination in an online mapping service such as Google Maps or MapQuest. <figure rend="Map Out a Travel Route Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Break your trip into different legs if necessary. Very long trips will need to be attempted over several days. When dividing your trip into different legs, keep a few things in mind. First, ask yourself how many hours each day you'll be willing to drive; the difference between 7 and 14 hours of driving per day can double the total time of your trip. Second, consult a map to determine where you can stop to stay at a hotel. Ending each day of travel near a major city will help you find a place to stay. <figure rend="Map Out a Travel Route Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Include any interesting landmarks along your travel route. If your trip is very long, you may be able to adjust your route to pass through additional areas of interest. Look at the cursory route you have selected through an online mapping service to see if it passes near any cities, parks, or other landmarks of interest. The easiest way to adjust the route to include these landmarks is by entering them as your destination for 1 leg and as your origin for the next. <figure rend="Map Out a Travel Route Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Avoid areas that will be affected by adverse weather. If you are traveling in winter, you may need to pay attention to which roads you select. Major freeways are much likelier to receive regular snowplow service than smaller roads, for example. Mountain passes and bridges are often the most dangerous roads to use in the winter, and these types of roads are often closed. Road closures can be checked ahead of time through online mapping services and through regional transportation departments. <figure rend="Map Out a Travel Route Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Prepare a method for consulting your route during the trip. An easy way to check your directions during the trip is by using a mobile phone with a mapping application. If you don't have this available, you can print out both maps and turn-by-turn directions from an online mapping service. In either case, it is very helpful to have large pull-out maps with you in case you need to plan an alternate route or if your phone loses signal. <figure rend="Map Out a Travel Route Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Traveling with more people will often mean a slower trip. Multiple people often necessitate more stops for eating and using the restroom, and the increased weight will reduce the fuel efficiency of your vehicle, so you will have to stop for fuel more frequently.</item>
<item>If you plan on using any form of public transit during your trip, buy tickets ahead of time if possible. If using both your vehicle and public transit, make sure that you will have a place to park your car long-term.</item>
<item>If your travel will take you across national borders, make sure each person in your party has their passport and at least 1 other form of government-issued ID.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Mobile phone</item>
<item>Maps</item>
<item>Turn-by-turn directions</item></list>
</text>
