<text id="autogum_whow_doc638" title="Start a Weightlifting Workout Diet" shortTile="start-weightlifting" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2006-08-03" dateModified="2018-09-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Start-a-Weightlifting-Workout-Diet" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Start a Weightlifting Workout Diet</head><p>This arm program is for advanced weightlifters only!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Eat a meal 1 hour before your workout; 1 cup oatmeal, 1 chopped apple and three whole eggs (cook with the oatmeal). Add two tablespoons of honey and cook in 1 and half cups of apple juice. <figure rend="Start the Recommended Workout Diet Step 1 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have one half cup of raisins 20 minutes before the workout. <figure rend="Start the Recommended Workout Diet Step 2 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Prepare a big water bottle(500ml) with orange juice in it and 25 grams of whey protein; sip on this during the whole workout. <figure rend="Start the Recommended Workout Diet Step 3 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Warm up with 7 minutes of jogging. Curl your arm up and squeeze like a bicep curl and push down as if you were working your triceps. <figure rend="Start the Recommended Workout Diet Step 4 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do one set of as many Parallel Tricep dips as possible. <figure rend="Start the Recommended Workout Diet Step 5 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Go to the chinning bar and do as many pullups as possible. <figure rend="Start the Recommended Workout Diet Step 6 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Go between two benches and do as many bench dips as you can. <figure rend="Start the Recommended Workout Diet Step 7 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Go to the lat pulldown and do as many as you can. <figure rend="Start the Recommended Workout Diet Step 8 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Rest for one minute and do two sets of 21 Tricep pushdowns superseded with two sets of 21 overhead tricep extensions. <figure rend="Start the Recommended Workout Diet Step 9 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do one set of 21 barbell curls superset with as many concentration curls as possible. <figure rend="Start the Recommended Workout Diet Step 10 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Tricep pushdowns use lat pulldown bar(long bar) take a wide underhand grip do 7 reps move the hand in a little and take an overhand grip and do 7 reps move the hand close together and do 7 reps overhanded move on to barbell over head extensions and do the same 7 underhanded wide grip ,move hands in a little overhanded 7 reps , close together 7 reps.</item>
<item>Barbell curl: take a narrow grip underhanded start from the top of the movement and do 7 rep only coming down to the top of the rip cage and coming up to touch your collar bone, continue by taking an underhanded mid grip starting from the top of the rip cage down to legs, continue by taking a wide overhanded(reverse) grip and doing 7 reps through the full movement. Know go grab two light dumbbells and a incline bench place yourself on the incline bench chest first so your chest is at the very top of the bench let you arms hang down over the top of the bench and do 7 curls but only coming up halfway do another 7 reps but only coming down halfway and another 7 reps doing the whole movement.</item>
<item>Lat pulldowns: same as pull ups underhanded grip  apart ,now keep your arms out in front of you so your triceps are parallel to the floor and a 90 degree angle to your body (the same as resting your elbow on a table) keep your arms in this position and curl the lat bar down toward the top of your head until it hit the top of your forehead.</item>
<item>Pull ups: take an underhanded grip with hands about  apart, curl your self up until you eyes meet the bar only come down a little pass 90 degrees with your arms.</item>
<item>Bench dips: make sure you go all the way down until your butt hit the ground and lockout at the top Squeeze your triceps</item>
<item>Parallel Tricep dips: keep body straight come down until biceps hit forearms and lockout at the top and squeeze triceps.</item></list>
</text>
