<text id="autogum_whow_doc171" title="Think Differently" shortTile="think-differently" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2013-03-12" dateModified="2018-09-26" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Think-Differently" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Think Differently</head><p>Thinking differently is more than just a mind setup.It means approaching problems in new, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Innovate">innovative</ref> ways.conceptualizing problems differently and understanding your position in relation to any particular situation in a way you’d never thought of before. Here are some steps to find out how we can achieve this.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Study another industry. Go to the library and pick up a trade magazine in an industry other than your own, or grab a few books from the library, and learn about how things are done in other industries. You might find that many of the problems people in other industries face are similar to the problems on your own, but that they’ve developed really quite different ways of dealing with them. Or you might well find new linkages between your own industry and the new one, linkages that might well be the basis of innovative partnerships in the future. <figure rend="Think Different Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Learn about another religion. Religions are the way that humans organize and understand their relationships not only with the supernatural or divine but with each other. Learning about how such relations are structured can teach you a lot about how people relate to each other and the world around them. Starting to see the reason in another religion can also help you develop mental flexibility – when you really look at all the different ways people comprehend the same mysteries, and the fact that they generally manage to survive regardless of what they believe, you start to see the limitations of whatever dogma or doxy you follow, a revelation that will transfer quite a bit into the non-religious parts of your life. <figure rend="Think Different Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take a class. Learning a new topic will not only teach you a new set of facts and figures, it will teach you a new way of looking at and making sense of aspects of your everyday life or of the society or natural world you live in. This in turn will help expand both how you look at problems and the breadth of possible solutions you can come up with. <figure rend="Think Different Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Read a novel in an unfamiliar genre. Reading is one of the great mental stimulators in our society, but it’s easy to get into a rut. Try reading something you’d never have touched otherwise – if you read literary fiction, try a mystery or science fiction novel; if you read a lot of hard-boiled detective novels, try a romance; and so on. Pay attention not only to the story but to the particular problems the author has to deal with. For instance, how does the fantasy author bypass your normal skepticism about magic and pull you into their story? Try to connect those problems to problems you face in your own field. For example, how might your marketing team overcome your audiences normal reticence about a new “miracle” product? <figure rend="Think Different Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Write_a_Poem"> Write a poem</ref>. While most problem-solving leans heavily on our brain’s logical centers, poetry neatly bridges our more rational left-brain though processes and our more <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Creative">creative</ref> right-brain processes. Though it may feel foolish (and getting comfortable with feeling foolish might be another way to think outside the box), try writing a poem about the problem you’re working on. Your poem doesn’t necessarily have to propose a solution – the idea is to shift your thinking away from your brain’s logic centers and into a more creative part of the brain, where it can be mulled over in a non-rational way. Remember, nobody has to ever see your poem…  <figure rend="Think Different Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Draw">Draw a picture</ref>. Drawing a picture is even more right-brained, and can help break your logical left-brain’s hold on a problem the same way a poem can. Also, visualizing a problem engages other modes of thinking that we don’t normally use, bringing you another creative boost. <figure rend="Think Different Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Turn it upside down. Turning something upside-down, whether physically by flipping a piece of paper around or metaphorically by re-imagining it can help you see patterns that wouldn’t otherwise be apparent. The brain has a bunch of pattern-making habits that often obscure other, more subtle patterns at work; changing the orientation of things can hide the more obvious patterns and make other patterns emerge. For example, you might ask what a problem would look like if the least important outcome were the most important, and how you’d then try to solve it. <figure rend="Think Different Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Work backwards. Just like turning a thing upside down, working backwards breaks the brain’s normal conception of causality. This is the key to backwards planning, for example, where you start with a goal and think back through the steps needed to reach it until you get to where you are right now. <figure rend="Think Different Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Ask a child for advice. Don’t buy into the notion that children are inherently ore creative before society “ruins” them, but children can think and speak with an ignorance of convention that is often helpful. Ask a child how they might tackle a problem, or if you don’t have a child around think about how you might reformulate a problem so that a child could understand it if one was available. Don’t run out and build a boat made out of cookies because a child told you to, though – the idea isn’t to do what the child says, necessarily, but to jog your own thinking into a more unconventional path. <figure rend="Think Different Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Invite randomness. If you’ve ever seen video of Jackson Pollock painting, you have seen a masterful painter consciously inviting randomness into his work. Pollock exercises a great deal of control over his brushes and paddles, in the service of capturing the stray drips and splashes of paint that make up his work. Embracing mistakes and incorporating them into your projects, developing strategies that allow for random input, working amid chaotic juxtapositions of sound and form – all of these can help to move beyond everyday patterns of thinking into the sublime. <figure rend="Think Different Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Take_a_Shower">Take a shower.</ref> There’s some kind of weird psychic link between showering and creativity. Who knows why? Maybe it’s because your mind is on other things, maybe it’s because you’re naked, maybe it’s the warm water relaxing you – it’s a mystery. But a lot of people swear by it. So maybe when the status quo response to some circumstance just isn’t working, try taking a shower and see if something remarkable doesn’t occur to you! <figure rend="Think Different Step 11.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
