<text id="autogum_whow_doc207" title="React when Your Child Goes Missing" shortTile="react-child-goes" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2017-07-13" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/React-when-Your-Child-Goes-Missing" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>React when Your Child Goes Missing</head><p>Although true abduction cases are very rare sometimes you may find yourself in a situation where you can't find your child. In this moment it's important to stay calm, and be prepared to get help immediately.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Make important calls immediately. Dial 911 as soon as you're sure your child is not in the immediate area. Legally, they are required to enter their information into the National Crime Information Center (NCIC)'s Missing person file right away. Officers may also put out a BOLO (Be on the lookout) or AMBER alert if they feel they are in danger. <figure rend="React when Your Child Goes Missing Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be prepared to share information. You may be panicking and unable to think but it's important to give police as much about your child as you can, so they have an easier time finding them. Be prepared to give your child's: <figure rend="React when Your Child Goes Missing Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Full name</item>
<item>Height and weight</item>
<item>Age and birthdate</item>
<item>Clothing child was wearing</item>
<item>Features such as glasses, scars, birthmarks, etc.</item>
<item>Names, addresses, and numbers of child's friends/family</item>
<item>Frequently visited spots</item>
<item>Any health issues</item>
<item>A picture, so try to find several recent photos that clearly display</item></list></item>
<item>Look in your immediate area. Begin searching around where you last saw your child. On and under all beds, piles of laundry, around and inside vehicles, inside washer and dryers. Anywhere a small child could climb inside. <figure rend="React when Your Child Goes Missing Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Notify the business. If you're in a store or other business notify a manager or guard immediately. Most stores will follow a Code Adam protocol where all employees will help look and lock down the store to ensure the child doesn't leave. <figure rend="React when Your Child Goes Missing Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Look for digital clues. If a child is old enough to have a phone or online presence, look through recent Google searches, messages, and emails or ask police to. They may have left some clue as to where they were going. <figure rend="React when Your Child Goes Missing Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep yourself available. You may want to start pounding the pavement yourself, but it is strongly advised to focus on gathering information to give to police. Police may want to search the child's room and take several items as evidence. They may also need an item of clothing from your child for the search. <figure rend="React when Your Child Goes Missing Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep your phone line open. In case police, your child, or someone else attempts to call you try to keep a phone line open. <figure rend="React when Your Child Goes Missing Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Call someone to be with you. In this stressful time if you're alone you may want someone to help you out with giving information to the police or remembering information given to you, or just to provide some probably much needed comfort. <figure rend="React when Your Child Goes Missing Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Inform the National Center for Missing and Exploited Children. After calling local police enlist the help of the NCMEC by calling 1-800-THE-LOST (1-800-843-5678), a non profit dedicated to helping children. They can help you out greatly in the search. <figure rend="React when Your Child Goes Missing Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Prevent it from happening. The best way is to prevent it from happening in the first place. Easier said than done sometimes but research or ask your local police for ways to locate a missing child such as phone locator apps, alarms on doors and windows, security cameras in and around the house, whistles/portable alarms, and other security measures can be great deterrents for both would be offenders and sly children trying to sneak out! <figure rend="React when Your Child Goes Missing Step 10.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
