<text id="autogum_whow_doc683" title="Power Clean and Press Correctly" shortTile="power-clean-press" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2017-10-05" dateModified="2019-06-24" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Power-Clean-and-Press-Correctly" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Power Clean and Press Correctly</head><p>The power clean is a full body explosive workout that can greatly help athletes when done correctly. This is relevant in today's society because many individuals want to be as healthy as possible and this workout will get the job done. The muscles which are mostly involved include your core, hamstring, quads, calves, and glutes, which are used for most of the movement, while your shoulders, traps, and arms are being worked as well during the second pull.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Starting Off</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Begin with the bar on the floor, positioned close to your shins and directly over your shoelaces. Have your feet shoulder-width apart. Place your hands at shoulder width length for a comfortable grip.
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure to grab the bar with an overhand grip, not underhand.</item></list></item>
<item>Sit your butt down. Make sure your chest is up and your eyes are looking forward. Pull your shoulder blades down and slightly back and tighten your core.
<list type="unordered"><item>Your elbows need to be rotated out to the sides, with your arms completely straight.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Doing the First Pull</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Pull the bar off the floor. Do this by powerfully extending your legs and making sure to keep your chest up, eyes straight, and most important your back flat.
<list type="unordered"><item>The bar should travel vertically in a straight line, not into you as it would for a deadlift exercise.</item></list></item></list>
<list type="ordered"><item>Shift your stance. Once you have lifted the bar above your knees, shift your torso to a vertical position and re-bend your knees slightly.</item>
<item>Launch the bar straight up by forcefully extending your hips and keeping the barbell close to your body. Keeping the bar close to your body will make your next motion much smoother.</item></list>
<head>Doing the Second Pull</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Expect power from this pull, as it is the most powerful part of this motion. While violently jumping straight up towards the ceiling, extend your knees, hips, and ankles, while at the same time shrugging the bar with your shoulders.
<list type="unordered"><item>Keeping the bar as close as possible for this exercise will help make the next step (the catch) much smoother.</item></list></item>
<item>Swiftly drop into a quarter-squat position. Keep your back straight, while also bending your hips and knees slightly.</item>
<item>Drive your elbows forward while also rotating them around the bar. Catch the bar in a racked position across your shoulders with your fingertips still on the bar.</item>
<item>From this position, stand up forcefully and grip the bar tightly. It's important to bend your knees slightly in order to support your back.</item>
<item>Lift the bar forcefully from the position on your shoulders to directly up above your head.
<list type="unordered"><item>While doing this be sure to jump slightly and move either your left or right foot in front of the other to help support you.</item></list></item>
<item>From this position, bring the bar down back to your knees while also bringing the foot you put up front back to shoulder width length. It's crucial to bend your knees in order to prevent back injury.</item>
<item>Drop your butt slowly while also dropping the barbell. Repeat from the beginning.
<list type="unordered"><item>It's extremely important to fully drop the barbell on the ground to help prevent hurting your lower back.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Keeping your eyes forward helps your balance and prevents you from hurting your back in this exercise.</item>
<item>When lifting the barbell above your head, it's important to move one leg forward to again, to prevent you from hurting your back.</item></list>
</text>
