<text id="autogum_whow_doc151" title="Communicate with a Private Person" shortTile="communicate-private" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2013-01-10" dateModified="2018-08-24" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Communicate-with-a-Private-Person" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Communicate with a Private Person</head><p>Is there that person you want to know better? Do you feel like they aren't going to tell you anything? Do you want to be this person's friend? If you answered yes to any of these questions then keep reading.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>This is probably the most important step of all. It's simple too. INTRODUCE YOURSELF! You can't get close to a person or know more about them if they have no idea who you are. <figure rend="Communicate with a Private Person Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try and get that person talking. Find something they're interested in and talk about that. Helping this person feel comfortable around you will help them open up and communicate a little more. <figure rend="Communicate with a Private Person Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Hang out with this person. Spending quality time with he or she will help this person feel like you want to be their friend, which will help them open up even more. <figure rend="Communicate with a Private Person Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Continue to try Step 2 and Step 3 until this person feels comfortable around you. Once they're comfortable around you and consider you a friend then you've opened them up! Congratulations! <figure rend="Communicate with a Private Person Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you want to be more than friends with this person, then try <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Get_a_Guy_to_Fall_for_You">How to Get a Guy to Fall for You</ref> or <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Get_a_Girl_to_Like_You">How To Get A Girl To Like You</ref> <figure rend="Communicate with a Private Person Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try and be friendly. You can't be mean to this person and expect them to like you. Treat this new friend of yours like any other friend.</item>
<item>Don't try and get to know them to spill their secrets and humiliate them. It's not very fun to be humiliated in front of everyone that you know.</item>
<item>Don't expect immediate results</item>
<item>Don't give up and be persistent. If that person says "I don't want you around me" then just leave them alone. But until they do, try and get to know them better. Break them out of the shell they have.</item>
<item>If the person doesn't warm up to you right away, don't sweat it. This is a private person so they may be trying to figure out if you're friend or foe.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure you are not exceeding the person's comfort level.  Be mindful of their posture and expressions, to see if they are becoming nervous.  In the event that the person has social limitations or trust issues, it is important that they feel like you are a "safe" person to talk to, who would respect their boundaries and not try to pressure them into more conversation than they are comfortable with.</item>
<item>Some people have psychological disorders which make social interactions difficult for them.  It's rare that they will simply announce this to you.  Be aware of this possibility, ahead of time.  While the person may simply be shy, they could also just as well be suffering from PTSD or Social Anxiety.  These conditions do not necessarily mean that they will never allow you to become close to them.  However, it may be at a different pace than the one you would normally expect.  Be respectful and do not impose your pace upon them.  A gentle and slow approach will give a them a greater sense of ease, and they will be more likely to open up to you.</item></list>
</text>
