<text id="autogum_whow_doc489" title="Cope when Your Fashion Favorite Stops Being Trendy" shortTile="cope-fashion-favorite" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2010-10-05" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Cope-when-Your-Fashion-Favorite-Stops-Being-Trendy" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Cope when Your Fashion Favorite Stops Being Trendy</head><p>When a beloved fashion item you've always adored suddenly becomes fashionable, it's an amazing feeling to be ahead of the trend and suddenly hip! But what happens when your favorite fashion item goes out of fashion and becomes a real style faux pas? Do you let go with great sadness or find other solutions? Here are some suggestions for coping.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Consider not wearing the item for a period of time until the next trend is well underway. Usually there is a period of time during which an old trend is disdained and considered unworthy before it's forgotten about. By being patient, you can ride out the backlash and start wearing it again in about a year's time. <figure rend="Cope when Your Fashion Favorite Stops Being Trendy Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Enjoy the sales; stock up on this item at rock bottom prices!</item>
<item>Be aware that some fashion items remain "tainted" for a very long time, like 80s <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_Scrunchies">scrunchies</ref> or neon <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_Leggings_from_Tights">leggings</ref>. In this case, you could be waiting a long time.</item></list></item>
<item>Reconfigure your fashion item. Look to see if there is some other way you can wear your favorite fashion item that won't seem old trend. For example, if you loved a certain piece of jewelry, maybe you can wear it or use it differently from the its use during the trend, such as sewing it onto a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Knit_a_Scarf">scarf</ref>, embellishing a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_a_Cool_Belt">belt</ref> with it, wearing it on a different part of your body, or using it as a hair accessory. Try to think outside the square and find new ways to use it. <figure rend="Cope when Your Fashion Favorite Stops Being Trendy Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Stop wearing it from this point. If you feel as if the trend has spoiled its specialness for you, maybe it's time to give it up and move on anyway. If this is the case, consider donating it to charity or passing on to a friend or family member keen to have it. <figure rend="Cope when Your Fashion Favorite Stops Being Trendy Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Turn it into a pretty or useful memento. Perhaps you've decided to stop wearing it but you'd like to keep a memory of it. Think about ways you can turn it into something else, like turning: jewelry into a framed picture, a scarf into a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Choose_a_Tablecloth_Size">tablecloth</ref>, leggings into cat toys, sweaters into cushion covers, hats into a mannequin's hat, a dress into a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_a_Quilt">quilt</ref>, etc.</item></list></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Bold">Be bold</ref> and buck the new trend. If it is something that has always represented your signature style and is definitely you, consider ignoring its loss of trendy status and continue to wear it anyway. For some items, especially classic pieces, this will be fairly easy to do, and if people know you've always worn the item, they'll expect you to keep wearing it anyway. <figure rend="Cope when Your Fashion Favorite Stops Being Trendy Step 4.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Formerly trendy fashion item(s)</item></list>
</text>
