<text id="autogum_whow_doc615" title="Discover Your Authentic Self" shortTile="discover-authentic" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-10-06" dateModified="2018-09-25" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Discover-Your-Authentic-Self" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Discover Your Authentic Self</head><p>It's easy to get caught up in the values of society and, self-imposed morals then finding yourself someone completely different from how you started. You find yourself wondering who you are and, what you want to be. The problem is that you have no clue who you used to be or, how you used to think. The best way to do that is to drop everything.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>DROP EVERYTHING
<list type="unordered"><item>Forget your hobbies</item>
<item>Forget your dreams</item>
<item>Forget your past itself</item></list></item>
<item>What is right and wrong to you? Some people think killing is always wrong no matter what. They truly believe all life is sacred and should be protected at all costs. Now did you really care about the indiiduals of 9/11 or the Tsunamis that hit Japan? If you don't does that make you evil? You're true self will know the answer in an instant so don't get in it's way.</item>
<item>Discover your virtues; what do you put more stock in freedom or order? Create a list of controversies and pick a side off the top of your head then argue its morality based off of what your true self believes what is right and wrong. A list of virtues-
<list type="unordered"><item>Bravery- Opposite of cowardice a virtue of someone who desire survival above all; meaning to be with fear yet, face adversity</item>
<item>Wisdom- Opposite of ignorance a virtue of someone seeking an easy life without hard descision; meaning being able to discern an outcome when given information and, finding the best solution</item>
<item>Humility- Opposite of pride a virtue of those without shame who live with utmost care of others perceptions; meaning to withstand shame and, learn from it.</item></list></item>
<item>Find what you cannot do without. In other words, love. Be it money, family/friends, power or, even abstract concepts such as happiness and stories. Don't let anyone influence what you love absoulutely no one. Even if you do everything else if you can't find your love you'll never know who you are. Unless you love nothing in which case you should find what you hate. If you fail at both of those then find what brings you the most comfort.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you struggle with morality think about those you admire be they real or fictional but, don't copy them they'll just give you hits about what you truly believe is right and wrong.</item>
<item>With your virtues think about the kind of person you want to be in your ideal form. Look up Benjamin Franklin's virtues to see how he built his.</item>
<item>Remember that there is but one true good Knowledge and one true evil Ignorance.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Just as scientists don't allow foreign elements in their research don't let anyone influence you during this time this is and has to be a solo mission</item></list>
</text>
