<text id="autogum_whow_doc130" title="Build a Robot from Pipe Cleaners and Aluminum Foil" shortTile="build-robot-pipe" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-03-17" dateModified="2019-03-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Build-a-Robot-from-Pipe-Cleaners-and-Aluminum-Foil" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Build a Robot from Pipe Cleaners and Aluminum Foil</head><p>I grew up watching cartoons such as Voltron defender of the universe, Go-bots, Transformers, Gundam Wing and other types of shows.  There was something magical about watching these robots fight monsters and other robots. And no matter if they were on earth or in space that seemed to capture the attention of young minds, and helped to cultivate a healthy imagination.     This page caters to those individuals who have maintained a youthful imagination, and want to know how to convert a thought into reality. The instructions are simple, they are meant to serve as a compass to guide you to the finished product.#The materials required for this is a roll of aluminum foil, pipe cleaners, and a good imagination.  (Scissors and markers are optional, but not required).  One thing to note here is that the time frame for creating this robot will vary based off of the time, and materials that are readily available to the individual making the model.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><figure rend="DSCN0089 (1).JPG"></figure>Step one: Brainstorm. The most essential item anyone can ever bring to the table is a good imagination.  Create the concept for the root and also create a list the items that will be needed before hand.</item>
<item><figure rend="DSCN0092.JPG"></figure>Step two: Start connecting the pieces of pipe cleaner together. They serve as the skeletal structure of the android so it is very important to ensure that each piece of pipe is firmly connected to each other.  You will want to create a firm silhouette before moving forward.</item>
<item><figure rend="DSCN0096.JPG"></figure>Step three:  Begin the application of the first layers of aluminum foil to the silhouette. If the android is to be stationary like a statue then there is no need to be concerned about covering up the joints or movable points of the creation.   If the model is to be pose-able then it is best to keep the free from any application of foil, since it would fall off due to repeated movement. The amount of aluminum foil that can be used is at the discretion of the creator.  Applying multiple layers to the creation will allow it to be more durable.</item>
<item><figure rend="DSCN0097.JPG"></figure>Step four (optional): apply color to the foil and apply the final layer of foil to the android.   Lastly is the creation of accessories for the model.  This is also a good time to create any accessories that would be appropriate for the model, not limited to, swords, shields, animal, or vehicle.</item>
<item><figure rend="DSCN0103.JPG"></figure>Step five:  take multiple pictures and post them on your favorite social media site for your friends and can to admire your work.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Keep in mind that his is an awesome piece but pipe-cleaners rust so you will want to keep it out of water, and although it will be durable, it can still fall apart, so handle your masterpiece with care.</item></list>
</text>
