<text id="autogum_whow_doc681" title="Get Fit for Climbing" shortTile="fit-climbing" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2007-08-28" dateModified="2018-08-05" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get-Fit-for-Climbing" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get Fit for Climbing</head><p>You want to start climbing but you don't think you're fit enough?
Read on.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Improve upper body <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Perform_Strength_Training_for_Gymnastics">strength</ref>. <figure rend="Get Fit for Climbing Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Start doing <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Strengthen_Your_Pitching_Arm">arm</ref> pull ups, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Do_Sit_Ups">sit ups</ref>, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Increase_the_Weight_of_a_Pig">weightlifting</ref> and other exercises that would help.  Remember that your lower body (i.e. legs) strength is, if anything, even more important than your upper body strength. You propel yourself up the wall with your legs, and reliance on upper body strength leads to sloppy technique.  Squats, particularly one-legged squats, should feature heavily in any weights workout. <figure rend="Get Fit for Climbing Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try to make yourself more <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Improve_Agility_for_Running_Backs">agile</ref> -- seriously, it helps. <figure rend="Get Fit for Climbing Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Hand_over_Hand_Properly">hand</ref> and finger exercises so your strength in your hands get stronger. <figure rend="Get Fit for Climbing Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do your best to try to make your grip better.  Buy or build grip exercisers and learn to use them. <figure rend="Get Fit for Climbing Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Improve your cardio-vascular fitness by including exercises like running, biking, swimming or jumping rope in your exercise routine.  Not only will a cardio routine burn fat turning you into a leaner, more fit athlete, but a cardio routine will also increase your endurance. <figure rend="Get Fit for Climbing Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Include balance exercises in your training program. <figure rend="Get Fit for Climbing Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Buy a fitness ball, like those used in pilates, and learn to use it.  These help build strength and balance. <figure rend="Get Fit for Climbing Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Learn to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Walk_a_Slackline"> Walk a Slackline</ref>.  Learning to move precisely and gracefully will pay big dividends once you start climbing. <figure rend="Get Fit for Climbing Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Eat healthy foods.  Your body needs high-quality food to operate at peak performance.  Minimize junk food in your diet and increase protein and vegetable intake (see warnings below!) to provide the nutrients your body needs to build muscle and bone mass.  Include healthy, slow-burning carbs like rice, oats and sweet potatoes to provide energy during your workouts. <figure rend="Get Fit for Climbing Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Go climbing!  The best training for rock climbing is...you guessed it!  Rock climbing. <figure rend="Get Fit for Climbing Step 11.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><list type="ordered"><item>When weightlifting, do more repetitions with lighter weights -- stamina is more important than brute strength when rock climbing.</item>
<item>When you start climbing watch how more experienced climbers move over the rock.  Powering your way through climbs will work at first, but once you start climbing harder routes (5.10/V1 or better), you will plateau if you don't learn good technique as well.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><list type="ordered"><item>Check with a doctor before starting an exercise or diet program.  Sudden changes in exercise or diet can do far more damage than good, in some cases.</item>
<item>Make sure you give your body time to recover between workouts, especially when you first begin.</item>
<item>Pay attention to your body's warning signals.  If you find yourself in pain after a workout, you might need to take some time off or decrease the intensity of your workout until your body is used to exercising regularly.  While some muscle soreness indicates that you are building muscle tissue, pain is a warning sign that something is wrong.  In particular sharp pains in your muscles, joint pains or a feeling like an electric shock in your forearms during or after your workouts can indicate more serious problems that should not be ignored.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
