<text id="autogum_whow_doc111" title="Embed Pictures" shortTile="embed-pictures" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-05-18" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Embed-Pictures" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Embed Pictures</head><p>Photos and other graphical images add interest to web pages and printed materials with a minimum of effort. Embedding pictures into your written text is quick and easy, although the process differs greatly depending on the application you are using. It is possible to embed pictures and other graphical images in Word, PowerPoint, Wordpress and HTML. Start with step 1 to get graphic!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Word and PowerPoint</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Choose the type of embedded image. <figure rend="Embed Pictures Step 1 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can add a picture or insert a graphic, clip art or chart. You can also create a shape or graphic.</item></list></item>
<item>Click the Insert tab and then click the icon for the image type. <figure rend="Embed Pictures Step 2 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Clicking the Picture icon will launch the "Insert Picture" window. Place your cursor in your document where you want the picture to appear. Browse to your picture, click on its icon to select it and then click "Insert."</item>
<item>The "Clip Art" icon will launch the Clip Art selection sidebar. You can search for a piece of clip art or browse through the catalog. Click on your clip art to select it and it will appear in your document.</item>
<item>Choosing the "Smart Art" icon causes a window to pop up where you can select your Smart Art image and insert it into your document. Customize the image after it has been placed into your Word document.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Wordpress</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Place your cursor in the draft of your blog post or page where you want to upload image. <figure rend="Embed Pictures Step 3 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Upload the image by clicking the "Add an Image" icon above the text entry field. <figure rend="Embed Pictures Step 4 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can choose to upload images from your computer or from an existing URL. You can also choose to insert an image you have already saved in your Media Library.</item></list></item>
<item>Select the appropriate tab for your upload image source. <figure rend="Embed Pictures Step 5 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If uploading from your computer, browse to the image and click "OK." Add the image's title, alternate text, caption and description, if desired, and click "Insert into Post." You can also choose the image's size and alignment from this window or set those properties later.</item>
<item>If linking to an upload image from another URL, locate the image on the web page where it resides, right-click and choose "Copy URL," then paste it into the Image URL field in Wordpress. If you are linking to someone else's image, make sure to obtain permission from the owner..</item></list></item></list>
<head>HTML</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Upload the image you would like to embed in your web page using an FTP utility. <figure rend="Embed Pictures Step 6 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Create the image tag by using the &lt; img src="URL" alt="alternate text" / &gt; syntax. <figure rend="Embed Pictures Step 7 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The acronym "URL" should be replaced with the name and file extension of your uploaded image.</item>
<item>The words "alternat_text" should be replaced with the text that will be displayed on browsers not capable of showing the im age.</item>
<item>For example, your image tag may read &lt; img src="picture1. jp " alt="picture_ of_boat" / &gt;</item></list></item>
<item>Transmit the HTML file of your web page via FTP and then visit the website to check that the upload image displays correctly. <figure rend="Embed Pictures Step 8 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Only insert graphic images that are expressly yours, or that are designated free for personal use. Using someone else's images without permission and attribution is theft of intellectual property.</item></list>
</text>
