<text id="autogum_whow_doc448" title="Get Along With Roommates in Your Apartment" shortTile="along-roommates-apartment" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2007-02-08" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get-Along-With-Roommates-in-Your-Apartment" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get Along With Roommates in Your Apartment</head><p>Living with strangers, or even friends, can be challenging – especially if it’s your first time living away from home.  While you can introduce a ‘family’ atmosphere to an apartment full of strangers, it’s important to realize that new boundaries apply.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Respect each other's property. This may sound basic, but there are certain liberties people can take with their own family that they can’t with others.  While your mother had an open pantry and your siblings didn’t mind sharing their clothes, this may not fly in an apartment arrangement.  Some people are guarded of their possessions, and rightly so. Establish the boundaries early – is it acceptable to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Persuade_Your_Best_Friend_to_Lend_You_Her_Clothes">borrow clothes</ref>, browse through each other’s music collection, use somebody else’s personal computer, etc. <figure rend="Live-with-a-College-Roommate-Who-Is-Your-Total-Opposite-Step-9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Decide whether to share food or cook separately. Communal meals or dinner for one?  There are advantages to both strategies. <figure rend="Make-the-Perfect-Dinner-for-Date-Night-Step-13.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Sharing food can help you save money because you split the price of dietary staples.  However, if you aren’t a large eater you may find yourself spending above your weight.  Also, settling on a diet that everyone agrees upon can be difficult.</item>
<item>Cooking for yourself can be more convenient because you only have to please yourself. If your roommates have boyfriends or girlfriends who often hang around the apartment, buying your own groceries won’t make you worry that you’re supporting the food plan of a ‘significant other’.  Also, you can eat on your own time schedule and purchase whatever food you want regardless of others’ budgets. That’s not to say you can’t share certain foods though.  Often apartment roommates share food staples such as milk, sugar and bread.  If you run out of something, it’s nice to have an understanding with your roommates that you’re allowed to borrow something of theirs until you replenish your stock. If you all cook separately, and at different times, you might consider arranging a weekly sit-down meal together.  Dining together is one of the easiest and most satisfying ways to bring people closer.</item></list></item>
<item>Clean up after yourself.  If you make a mess don't leave it for someone else to look after. <figure rend="Clean-a-House-Step-9-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take your turn to tidy, sweep, and mop the common areas. If you share a place, you all have equal responsibility to keep it clean. <figure rend="Clean-a-House-Step-19.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure you do your fair share of household chores, such as taking out the trash and recycling, cleaning the washroom, and emptying the fridge of rotting food. <figure rend="Make Your Room Look Nice Step 3 Version 4.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Take care in choosing your roommates. Living with friends can either be a very rewarding experience or a very trying experience, depending on your relationship history. Some of the benefits of living with friends include knowing whether or not they're reliable.  You have an idea of their financial history and whether you can trust them to pay the apartment rent on time. With friends, you’re more likely to have common interests and even common friends, which can make your apartment more welcoming for visitors.  However, knowing each other well brings higher expectations, which can sometimes lead to disappointment.  Often it is better to share an apartment with acquaintances - people you know enough to trust – rather than close friends.  Seeing each other every day might grate on each other’s nerves and a once strong friendship might quickly sour.  You might also find your friendship suffers because you stop spending time together outside of the apartment.</item>
<item>Trust your instincts when it comes to living with strangers.  This type of living arrangement is a good way to expand your social network, and it also grants you more independence to do your own thing – strangers are less likely to worry about your comings and goings. But if their social skills or integrity are questionable, choose another apartment or another roommate.  Ask for personal references before making a final decision on a potential roommate.</item></list>
</text>
