<text id="autogum_whow_doc533" title="Decide if You Want to Adopt a Pet" shortTile="decide-want-adopt" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-05-19" dateModified="2018-03-14" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Decide-if-You-Want-to-Adopt-a-Pet" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Decide if You Want to Adopt a Pet</head><p>Having a pet can be a wonderful thing, but it takes a lot of commitment.  When deciding if you really want to adopt a pet, there are a few things to consider.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Do you have the time needed to take care of a pet?  Whether you are thinking of getting a fish, a dog, or even a horse, you are going to need to invest a lot of time into taking care of it.  Some pets will require more time than others so when thinking about this, consider what you will need to spend time doing.  You should set aside time for:
<list type="unordered"><item>Cleaning - Picking up messes and cleaning cages will become a big part of your life.</item>
<item>Training - Many pets will need some sort of training.   Even small, caged animals can be trained to make your life easier.</item>
<item>Exercising - All pets need time to stretch their legs and exercise.  You will need to set aside some time to walk your dog, or to make sure that the hamster doesn't fall down the stairs while running around the house in its ball.</item>
<item>Playing - Just like people, animals can get bored.  Spending some time interacting with your pet will not only help prevent boredom, but it will also give you a chance to improve your bond.</item></list></item>
<item>Are you financially equipped? Before getting a pet you need to make sure that you will be able to afford all of the supplies that are needed.  In most cases, food will be your number one pet expense. Some other expenses you may encounter are vet bills, toys, litter, bedding and vaccinations.   Do research on the type of pet you are wanting to get for a better idea of what you will need.</item>
<item>Do you have the space needed for the pet you would like?  If you are living in an apartment, a Great Dane may not be the pet for you.  If you are short on living space, a caged animal will be easier to live with than a larger animal that will need more space.  Having a larger animal in a small space will add to the time that you need to set aside for exercising your pet outside.</item>
<item>If you have considered all of the things listed above and you still want a pet, make sure to choose one that is compatible with you.  Don't get a pet just because you think they are cool looking or because you like the idea.  Choose your pet based on how much time, money and effort you are willing to put in.  Don't buy a pet on a whim.  Do your research and choose your new best friend wisely.</item></list>
</text>
