<text id="autogum_whow_doc461" title="Learn Handyman Skills" shortTile="learn-handyman-skills" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-10-31" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Learn-Handyman-Skills" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Learn Handyman Skills</head><p>On-the-job experience is one of the best ways to learn handyman skills, but if you want to start a handyman business, you'll usually need a business license and other formal certifications declaring your competency as a handyman. If you want to pursue a handyman career, start your training at home by performing simple maintenance on routine systems such as plumbing and heating. Later you can pursue formal vocational training, then go on to earn a handyman certification provided by your city or county.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Look for basic repairs needed around your house. Whether you rent or own a home, every structure requires maintenance. <figure rend="Learn Handyman Skills Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Stay ahead of seasonal repairs and maintenance by fixing problems before inclement weather occurs. Look for leaks in your roof in summer, before heavy rains occur. Check the furnace before the weather turns cold. Inspect your home for pest infestations during early spring, before the warm weather causes bugs to reproduce.</item></list></item>
<item>Acquaint yourself with home systems such as plumbing, one of the most common home systems that requires ongoing care. Learn how to use a plumber's tools to perform basic maintenance on your home's plumbing systems. <figure rend="Tell if Your House Is Haunted Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Keep drains running smoothly. Remove hair and other debris on a regular basis by employing the help of a drain snake.</item>
<item>Fix leaks. Look underneath sinks, behind toilets and around spigots to find free-flowing water. Discovering how to find a leak's source is critical for any handyman to perform simple plumbing repairs without having to hire a licensed plumber.</item></list></item>
<item>Tell friends and family that you want to help with home repairs. Although most homes have similar systems, the more experience you have on different types of homes, the more skilled you'll become at being a general handyman. <figure rend="Answer an Office Phone Call Conversation Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get handyman training at a vocational school. Many adult education schools offer courses in basic handyman training. Check community college catalogs for course offerings. <figure rend="Become an Online Freelance Writer Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Apprentice with an experienced handyman. Volunteer your services to act as an apprentice for a home repair expert. Although you won't get paid, you'll receive free on-the-job training and guidance by a more experienced professional. <figure rend="Learn Handyman Skills Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Study local building codes and contractor's requirements. Each city has different criteria for handyman contractors who work on homes. Many will prohibit anyone but a licensed general contractor to make home repairs in excess of a certain dollar amount. <figure rend="Become a Teenaged Writer Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you intend to earn money as a home handyman, know the scope of the type of projects you can work on before a contractor's license is required by your city.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Projects such as Habitat for Humanity are always in need of volunteer construction labor. Learn handyman skills by volunteering to building a home for a needy family.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Ensure that your friends and family know you are a handyman student. Don't attempt to fix problems that are beyond your skill level or you could make the problem worse, as well as more expensive.</item></list>
</text>
