<text id="autogum_whow_doc043" title="Get a Sponsor for Sound Offs" shortTile="sponsor-sound-offs" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-05-27" dateModified="2019-08-19" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get-a-Sponsor-for-Sound-Offs" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get a Sponsor for Sound Offs</head><p>If you have an affinity for cars, marketing, and audio equipment, you might be interested in learning how to get a sponsor for sound offs. Sound offs are competitions in which cars demonstrate their custom-built audio systems and compete for titles and prices. Getting a sponsor for sound offs involves a lot of research, precision, and hard work, but can pay off by getting your car a state-of-the-art sound system and the sponsors a lot of exposure. Read the following steps to find out how to get a sponsor for sound offs.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Design the sound system for your car. Unless you already have some celebrity status in the automotive or audio industry, you should approach a respected car audio store to help you select the products and design the system. <figure rend="Get a Sponsor for Sound Offs Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Research potential manufacturers of each part of the audio system. Try to find at least 2 candidates for each part. For each manufacturer, carefully list the model number of the product you need, as well as the contact details of the marketing director of each company. <figure rend="Get a Sponsor for Sound Offs Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Create visual plans of the audio system. Make them as clear as possible by drawing the layout of your car, and then creating additional layers (if you're using computer graphics) or transparencies (for paper) for the hardware and wiring. <figure rend="Get a Sponsor for Sound Offs Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Create a portfolio of your own work, including a resume, publications, awards, and other noteworthy details. If you have a logo, include it. <figure rend="Get a Sponsor for Sound Offs Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Write up a marketing plan that outlines how, when, and where the car's sound system will get coverage. Substantiate your plan with letters of interest from publishers, producers, and event managers. <figure rend="Get a Sponsor for Sound Offs Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Draft a cover letter that outlines your motivation for undertaking this project, a description of the audio system, what you want from each manufacturer, and what type of coverage they'll receive in return. Ask for a reply to your request within a time period that works for you. An acceptable time frame is 14 days. <figure rend="Get a Sponsor for Sound Offs Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Assemble a package for each manufacturer that includes a cover letter, the visual plans for the audio system, your portfolio, and the marketing plan. <figure rend="Get a Sponsor for Sound Offs Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Send a package to the marketing director of each company. To ensure timely delivery, it's recommended to use priority shipping. <figure rend="Get a Sponsor for Sound Offs Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Follow up with each manufacturer after 2 weeks to find out whether they are willing to sponsor you. <figure rend="Get a Sponsor for Sound Offs Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Negotiate the details of each sponsorship agreement to find a deal that works for both parties. <figure rend="Get a Sponsor for Sound Offs Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Sign the sponsorship agreements. If you're unsure about the terms and conditions of the agreements, have a lawyer explain them to you before you sign anything. <figure rend="Get a Sponsor for Sound Offs Step 11 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>After getting a sponsor for sound offs, follow your contract and keep the sponsor informed of your project's progress.</item>
<item>Use the names of your sponsors to get maximum exposure in the media.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Sound system design</item>
<item>List of manufacturers and product model numbers</item>
<item>Visual plans</item>
<item>Portfolio</item>
<item>Marketing plan</item>
<item>Cover letter</item></list>
</text>
