<text id="autogum_whow_doc245" title="Use New and Traditional Media to Market Your Business" shortTile="use-new-traditional" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2010-05-26" dateModified="2018-01-27" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Use-New-and-Traditional-Media-to-Market-Your-Business" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Use New and Traditional Media to Market Your Business</head><p>Right now in 2010, there is no such thing as "the right way to advertise." As technology magnifies the infinite number of possibilities to brand an idea, many businesses are confused when it comes to social media platforms. Likewise, many companies are making use of online tactics but failing to realize their significance and how to best use them. Many are also forgetting about traditional media, and this is a problem. So what's the best way to stay competitive in an ocean full of emerging media? It's simple! Every business should maintain a healthy balance of both new, online tactics as well as traditional media platforms. Contrary to popular belief, print is not dead. If you are a business owner, it's time to cross over to hybrid marketing. This is how you can use new media and traditional media to market your business.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Stay current on the web. If your website is rarely updated, be sure to stay connected to your followers through blogs and other (free) social media websites like Twitter, Facebook, YouTube, StumbleUpon, and Merchant Circle. <figure rend="Use New and Traditional Media to Market Your Business Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use new media platforms wisely. Don't sign up for social media websites if you don't know how to use them. Research how to use each tool effectively, and only involve yourself with sites that fit your company's business model accordingly. If you don't know why you are doing something, you probably shouldn't do it.. yet. Find a way to properly make use of each social platform before making random posts. <figure rend="Use New and Traditional Media to Market Your Business Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Create a conversation around your brand. Using new media platforms such as Twitter will create engagement. You want your customers, clients, business partners, and affiliates to interact with your brand as much as possible. Tweeting keeps your brand at the top of their mind. <figure rend="Use New and Traditional Media to Market Your Business Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get your audience excited. Raising brand awareness is more than putting fliers up and hoping for banner ad clicks, it's creating an environment, a user experience, or a feeling that makes everyone want more. It's all about lasting impressions. <figure rend="Use New and Traditional Media to Market Your Business Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't neglect traditional media. Even the greatest campaigns combine both online tactics with traditional advertising. You may have a great website, and an even cooler Facebook page, but how will your 9-5 workers who are stuck in rush hour until 6'oclock going to know where to find you? Think big and go bigger. Truck side advertising, billboards, guerrilla tactics, and outdoor signage are all cost-effective tactics that make a big impact and spark interest. <figure rend="Use New and Traditional Media to Market Your Business Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Print big. Right now, it's all about visibility. Why stay cooped up in a building with a tiny door logo that's hard to find? You can fully wrap your office building, design eye-popping window graphics, and maximize your space with full color murals and floor graphics. The key to brand awareness is connectivity. Why have a great logo if isn't plastered all over your walls? Why host an open house without larger than life advertising? Think big and use large format printing to your best advantage. <figure rend="Use New and Traditional Media to Market Your Business Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Stay competitive and research trends. Don't just follow trends, try to do something different and unique in the spaces you compete in. If your competitors have more tweets than you, think about an exclusive Twitter campaign to boost your own page. The more time and creativity you invest in, the more results you'll see in the end. <figure rend="Use New and Traditional Media to Market Your Business Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
