<text id="autogum_whow_doc092" title="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac" shortTile="make-notes-pdf-pc" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-01-17" dateModified="2019-05-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-Notes-on-a-PDF-on-PC-or-Mac" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac</head><p>This wikiHow teaches you how to take notes and highlight sections on a PDF text document, using your computer's stock PDF reader app. You can use Preview on Mac, and Reader on Windows.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Adding Notes to a PDF on Mac</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open your PDF document in Preview. Double-click the PDF document to open it in Mac's default PDF reader, Preview. <figure rend="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Press  on your keyboard. This will show Preview's markup toolbar at the top of your document. <figure rend="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Alternatively, you can click the toolbox icon in the upper-right corner of Preview, next to the search bar.</item></list></item>
<item>Click the notepad icon on the markup toolbar. This button looks like a square with horizontal lines in it. You can find it next to the signature icon at the top. <figure rend="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This will create a new, yellow notepad sheet. It looks like a yellow square on your PDF.</item></list></item>
<item>Click the yellow square to type. If the yellow notepad square doesn't automatically prompt you to write, click on it again to expand your note sheet. <figure rend="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Type your note into the yellow notepad. Anything you write here will be saved in your note. <figure rend="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click anywhere on your PDF. This will minimize the pop-up notepad into a yellow square with no text. <figure rend="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Drag the yellow square anywhere on the PDF. You can place your note anywhere on your document. <figure rend="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the yellow square to view your note. Clicking will expand the notepad sheet. You can view and edit your note here anytime.  <figure rend="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Adding Textboxes on Mac</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Click the  icon on the markup toolbar. You can find this button on the markup toolbar near the upper-left corner. It will add a textbox in the middle of your PDF. <figure rend="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Hold and drag the textbox anywhere on your PDF. You can place the box anywhere on the margins or over the text. <figure rend="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Double-click on the textbox. This will allow you to edit the text in it. <figure rend="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac Step 11.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The placeholder text reads "Text" in the text box.</item></list></item>
<item>Type your notes in the textbox. You can use your keyboard to enter your comments or questions here. <figure rend="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the  icon on the markup toolbar. This button is on the far-right end of the markup toolbar at the top. You can edit your text's font, size, and style here. <figure rend="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac Step 13.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Select a font from the drop-down.</item>
<item>Enter a number in the "pt" field to change text size.</item>
<item>Click the color box to select a text color.</item>
<item>Use the <hi rend="bold">B</hi>, <hi rend="italic">I</hi>, U icons for bold, italics, and underline.</item>
<item>Select a text alignment at the bottom.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Drawing and Sketching on Mac</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open your PDF document in Preview. Double-click the PDF document to open it in Mac's default PDF reader, Preview. <figure rend="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Press  on your keyboard. This will show Preview's markup toolbar at the top of your document. <figure rend="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac Step 15.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Alternatively, you can click the toolbox icon in the upper-right corner of Preview, next to the search bar.</item></list></item>
<item>Click the pencil icon on the top-right. This is the <hi rend="bold">Sketch</hi> tool. You can find it next to the dashed square icon on the markup toolbar at the top. <figure rend="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac Step 16.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Sketch a line or curve on your PDF. You can use this to mark or cross certain sections in the text. <figure rend="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac Step 17.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If Preview is not sure about your sketch, you'll see a pop-up box in the upper-left corner below the markup toolbar. You can select what you meant to draw here.</item></list></item>
<item>Click the three-lines icon on the markup toolbar. It's located next to the notepad icon at the top. <figure rend="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac Step 18.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select a line thickness. The thickness style you select here will automatically apply to your current sketch. <figure rend="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac Step 19.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can also click a line to select it, then change its thickness here later.</item></list></item>
<item>Click the color square icon next to the three-lines button. You can select a color for your sketch lines and curves here. <figure rend="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac Step 20.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the pen icon next to the pencil on the markup toolbar. This is the <hi rend="bold">Draw</hi> tool. You can use this tool to draw and sketch free-hand on your PDF. <figure rend="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac Step 21.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can select a thickness and color from the markup toolbar.</item></list></item>
<item>Draw freely with your cursor on the PDF. You can use the Draw tool to mark or cross something in the text or take notes anywhere on the page.  <figure rend="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac Step 22.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Adding Notes and Highlighting on Windows</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open your PDF document in Windows Reader. Double-click the PDF document to open it in Windows's default PDF reader app, Reader. <figure rend="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac Step 23.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you have another reader app set as your default, right-click your PDF document, hover over <hi rend="bold">Open with</hi>, and select <hi rend="bold">Reader</hi> here.</item></list></item>
<item>Select a word, sentence, line or paragraph in your PDF. Hold down your left mouse button, and select where you want to add your note. <figure rend="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac Step 24.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This will highlight your selection, and show your options in a pop-up toolbox. You can select <hi rend="bold">Highlight</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Add a note</hi>, or <hi rend="bold">Copy</hi> here.</item></list></item>
<item>Click  in the pop-up toolbox. This option looks like a speech balloon icon. It will create a small note sheet on your PDF. <figure rend="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac Step 25.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Type your note into the small note sheet. Anything you write here will be saved in your note. <figure rend="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac Step 26.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click anywhere on the PDF. This will close the pop-up notepad, and save your note. <figure rend="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac Step 27.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the highlighted section on your PDF. Your options will pop up on a toolbar. <figure rend="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac Step 28.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click  on the pop-up toolbar. This will open your saved note. You can view and edit your note here anytime. <figure rend="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac Step 29.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select any text in your PDF. You can select any word, sentence, line or paragraph with your left mouse button. This will show your markup options in a pop-up toolbox. <figure rend="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac Step 30.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click  in the pop-up toolbox. This will highlight your selection in the text. You can easily find this section next time you open your document. <figure rend="Make Notes on a PDF on PC or Mac Step 31.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
