<text id="autogum_whow_doc596" title="Keep Academic Philosophy Alive" shortTile="keep-academic-philosophy" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-03-16" dateModified="2017-05-05" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Keep-Academic-Philosophy-Alive" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Keep Academic Philosophy Alive</head><p>Academic philosophy such as the study of epistemology, ethics, logic, and metaphysics, have all but fallen by the wayside in the face of disciplines which seem to require much less analysis and contemplation and are geared towards jobs and money-making. Is academic philosophy dead? How can you help to keep it alive, given that there are no jobs in the area?  There is absolutely no need for a department of philosophy in the government or a private sector “philosophy creation” organization. Or is there? Letting the basis of all thought and knowledge become obsolete or assume that everything has been said and done is not merely sad, it is dangerous. The last time real new movement in the areas of logic and epistemology occurred was arguably with Wittgenstein. That was over one hundred years ago. Maybe it's time for a new wave now.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Stop making fun of those who major in philosophy. Encourage higher thinking children to continue to utilize their critical thinking skills in order to move all of us to a greater, and therefore better, place sociologically. <figure rend="Keep Academic Philosophy Alive Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Support true academics in the area of philosophy who stand up to the vast Internet junk philosophy attempting to call itself true academic philosophy. Basic ethics discussions are not necessarily academic philosophy. <figure rend="Keep Academic Philosophy Alive Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Remember your first ethics class in college where you were required to state your conclusion, then support it with reasonably strong premises? For example, you might be asked to create a sound argument based on the premises you've written in support of a woman's right to choose. Or, maybe you've created an argument supporting the death penalty.  At any rate, these exercises are the most basic ways of introducing students and individuals not only to ethical thinking, but to the ways of creating sound and valid argument forms; the basis of all philosophy. It is not the intention to minimize the importance of ethics or ethics courses. The problem is that if this is the last stand of academic philosophy, society is in big trouble.</item></list></item>
<item>Be familiar with logic, epistemology and avoid shallow ethics fight. Avoid base level debates. <figure rend="Keep Academic Philosophy Alive Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Encourage true academics to take a small amount of their time and educate participants on Internet sites of the basics of real philosophy, it might help to elevate the thinking and discussion of topics on these sites. <figure rend="Keep Academic Philosophy Alive Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Set a goal and strive to become the next big thinker in the universe! Why not? It is probably much more rare and certainly more difficult to become the next Stephen Hawking or Hume than it is to become the next Jay Z. And it is absolutely the case that the money and fame will come much more slowly. <figure rend="Keep Academic Philosophy Alive Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>First there will be academic accolades, literary awards that might come with honorariums, but that's not to say you won't be comfortable.</item>
<item>You'll most certainly end up with a tidy sum of prize money and a secured professorship at an excellent university of your choice! You'll be able to travel the world lecturing on your theory and motivating others to do what you've done! Young and old,' push yourselves as far as you can.</item></list></item>
<item>Do what you must to go about mastering this. Write, think, and make a complete fool of yourself. Read, get together in groups and challenge one another in every way possible.  Keep real thought alive, and keep academic philosophy alive! <figure rend="Keep Academic Philosophy Alive Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Take a course that is far above your abilities. If you have to fight to get in, do just that.</item>
<item>Join a study group with people whom you feel very comfortable with making a complete jerk of yourself. If you don't feel comfortable saying the most ridiculously wrong thing, you'll never learn, and you'll never advance.</item></list></item>
<item>Write, write, write. Write all of the time. Carry notebooks and fill them with every thought you have. If you have a particularly important thought, develop a method of referring back to those "more important" thoughts, that way they don't get lost amongst everything else. <figure rend="Keep Academic Philosophy Alive Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
