<text id="autogum_whow_doc100" title="Root the HTC Inspire" shortTile="root-htc-inspire" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-06-14" dateModified="2019-09-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Root-the-HTC-Inspire" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Root the HTC Inspire</head><p>Rooting your HTC Inspire will allow you to remove preinstalled apps, free up memory, increase battery life, and generally improve the overall functionality of your device. The HTC Inspire can be rooted using the Easy Ace Root Tool program on any Windows-based computer.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Close any antivirus programs running on your Windows-based PC. Some antivirus programs can interfere with rooting, or recognize the East Ace Root Tool program as a type of malware. <figure rend="Root the HTC Inspire Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Uninstall HTC Sync Manager from your computer, if applicable. The HTC Sync Manager may interfere with the rooting process when your HTC Inspire is connected to your computer. <figure rend="Root the HTC Inspire Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Click on “Start” and select “Control Panel.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> The Control Panel window will display on-screen.</item>
<item>Click on “Uninstall or change a program,” or “Add / Remove Programs,” depending on your version of Windows.</item>
<item>Click on “HTC Sync Manager,” then click on “Uninstall” or “Change / Remove.” Windows will uninstall HTC Sync Manager from your computer.</item></list></item>
<item>Back up all personal information you want saved on your HTC Inspire to another location. Rooting your HTC Inspire will wipe all personal data from the device. <figure rend="Root the HTC Inspire Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Back_Up_an_Android_Phone_on_the_Google_Cloud">Sync your personal data with Google's servers</ref>, copy files and folders to your computer, or use a third-party cloud storage app from Google Play Store to back up your data.</item></list></item>
<item>Navigate to the XDA Developers website at <ref target="http://forum.xda-developers.com/showthread.php?t=2169518">http://forum.xda-developers.com/showthread.php?t=2169518</ref>. <figure rend="Root the HTC Inspire Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Scroll to the “Downloads” section in the first post and click on the link next to “EasyAceRootTool_21112013.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> You will be redirected to the Dev Host file-sharing service website. <figure rend="Root the HTC Inspire Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select the option to download the Easy Ace Root Tool .zip file to your desktop. This file contains the rooting software needed for the HTC Inspire. <figure rend="Root the HTC Inspire Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Right-click on the .zip file and select the option to extract the files. <figure rend="Root the HTC Inspire Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Open the “tools” folder,” then open the “winddrivers” folder. <figure rend="Root the HTC Inspire Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Double-click on the “HTC Drivers” .exe file. This file contains updated HTC Inspire drivers for your computer. <figure rend="Root the HTC Inspire Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Follow the on-screen prompts to install the required drivers on your Windows PC. <figure rend="Root the HTC Inspire Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tap on Menu and select “Settings” on your HTC Inspire. <figure rend="Root the HTC Inspire Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tap on “Applications,” then tap on “Development.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> <figure rend="Root the HTC Inspire Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Place a checkmark next to “USB debugging.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> <figure rend="Root the HTC Inspire Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Connect the HTC Inspire to your computer using a USB cable. <figure rend="Root the HTC Inspire Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wait for the computer to recognize your device and install any necessary drivers. <figure rend="Root the HTC Inspire Step 15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Right-click on the file named “EasyAceRoot.cmd” and select “Run as administrator.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> <figure rend="Root the HTC Inspire Step 16.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Follow the on-screen prompts to finishing rooting your device. The Easy Ace Root Tool will guide you through the rooting process. <figure rend="Root the HTC Inspire Step 17.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wait for the Easy Ace Root Tool to inform you rooting is complete, then disconnect the HTC Inspire from your computer. Your device will now be rooted and ready for use. <figure rend="Root the HTC Inspire Step 18.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Rooting your HTC Inspire will void the manufacturer's warranty; however, you can <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Unroot_Android">follow these steps to unroot your Android device</ref> at any time to reinstate the warranty in the event you need to exchange or return your HTC Inspire under the warranty.</item></list>
</text>
