<text id="autogum_whow_doc165" title="Open a Trade School" shortTile="open-trade-school" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-04-28" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Open-a-Trade-School" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Open a Trade School</head><p>Trade schools or vocational schools offer hands-on, practical training for professions that require a working knowledge of a particular field. There are many different types of trade schools, ranging from esthetician and culinary schools to carpentry and auto repair schools. If you're an expert in a specific trade, and you enjoy sharing your knowledge, you may want to find out how to open a trade school. It's important to know that, in order to open a trade school, you'll need a sound business plan as well as permission from your local and state government. Planning the process properly is crucial to its success.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Determine which type of trade school you want to open. Usually, you'll want to open a school in your field of expertise so you can evaluate every aspect of the trade school's function. <figure rend="Open a Trade School Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Investigate whether there's a demand for this type of trade school in your area. Find out if there's any competition in the area and if that will hamper your startup plans. <figure rend="Open a Trade School Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find out what trade certifications you need, such as welder's, plumber's or electrician's certificate. <figure rend="Open a Trade School Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Draw up a business plan that can serve as a funding application to the state. <figure rend="Open a Trade School Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Explain the curriculum you plan to offer and the types of instructors you want to attract.</item>
<item>Define the demand for the school in the area by analyzing job statistics and educational statistics.</item>
<item>Describe the costs of starting up the school, including location, materials, educator contracts, insurance and taxes.</item>
<item>Outline your income projections for the first 2 years.</item></list></item>
<item>Register your trade school with the appropriate local and state organizations. <figure rend="Open a Trade School Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Raise the capital to open a trade school by getting a business loan from a bank or obtaining state or private funding. <figure rend="Open a Trade School Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find a location for your trade school. Make sure it's easily accessible and offers the potential to adapt it to a safe learning environment. <figure rend="Open a Trade School Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Adapt the location for your trade school. Remember to have it evaluated by your local fire department to determine whether it meets all safety requirements. <figure rend="Open a Trade School Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get insurance for your trade school. This includes insurance for the building and its contents, as well as liability insurance and any other type of insurance you deem necessary. <figure rend="Open a Trade School Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Purchase all necessary equipment. The types of equipment will depend on the trade you're teaching. <figure rend="Open a Trade School Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Draw up contracts for your staff as well as admission agreements for students. <figure rend="Open a Trade School Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Interview and hire educators. Choose applicants who are qualified and experienced in the trade and in front of a class. <figure rend="Open a Trade School Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Install a security system with armed response to protect the school and everybody in it from crime, fire and other hazards. <figure rend="Open a Trade School Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Launch a marketing plan to attract pupils. This can include advertising at schools, in newspapers, on billboards and on local television. <figure rend="Open a Trade School Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Enroll your students for the first year. <figure rend="Open a Trade School Step 15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Open your trade school. <figure rend="Open a Trade School Step 16.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always keep in contact with trade unions to stay abreast of the latest developments in your field.</item>
<item>Always consider creating a website that offers internship and job opportunities for students and alumni.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Trade certification or license</item>
<item>Business plan</item>
<item>Investment capital</item>
<item>State registration</item>
<item>Insurance</item>
<item>Equipment</item>
<item>Security system</item></list>
</text>
