<text id="autogum_whow_doc063" title="Register a Boat" shortTile="register-boat" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-02-21" dateModified="2019-06-17" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Register-a-Boat" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Register a Boat</head><p>If you’re planning to get a motorized boat, make sure you follow the law regarding registration. Just like cars, states require boats to be registered. Registration lets the authorities know who’s operating boats legally on a given waterway. States vary when it comes to boat registration rules and fees. Before you go out on the water in your boat, check with the appropriate state agency to ensure you’re in compliance.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Submitting Your Boat Registration</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Get a boat registration application from the appropriate state agency. You’re required to register your boat in the state where you keep it. States vary when it comes to the agencies that handle boat registration. Common state agencies that handle boat registration include the Department of Motor Vehicles, the Department of Fish and Game or the state agency specifically dedicated to managing waterways. <figure rend="Register a Boat Step 01.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can pick up an application from the appropriate state agency in-person or download one from the agency’s website.</item>
<item>If you just bought a brand new boat, the dealer most likely will give you a boat registration application and tell you where to send it.</item>
<item>You can also search online to find out which agency in the state where you park your boat handles registration.</item></list></item>
<item>Fill out the boat registration application. Boat registration applications are detailed and ask for information such as your name and address. You have to state truthfully that you are the owner of the boat and attach proof of ownership. You also must provide details about what the boat is made out of as well as the hull identification number. <figure rend="Register a Boat Step 02.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>On your boat registration application, be prepared to state truthfully that you have paid taxes on your boat.</item></list></item>
<item>Gather your proof of ownership documents. You’re required to show proof of ownership of your boat. A boat title in your name is the best proof of ownership, but if you don’t have one, a bill of sale, which is basically a sales receipt for your boat, works fine. If you bought the boat and haven’t yet paid off the owner, you can provide your sales contract as proof of ownership. <figure rend="Register a Boat Step 03.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be prepared to show documentation of any loans you have on your boat as part of the registration process.</item></list></item>
<item>Mail in the application, copies of supporting documents and fee. Boat registration fees vary widely among the states but are mostly affordable. In most cases, you can expect to pay less than $100 for the boat registration sticker and documents combined. You can drop off the application in person or send it to the appropriate state government agency by mail. <figure rend="Register a Boat Step 04 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Send your payment for initial registration by personal check, cashier’s check or money order. Avoid sending cash.</item>
<item>If you drop off your application in person, you might be able to pay with your credit card.</item></list></item>
<item>Affix your registration number to your boat with paint or decals. When the state processes your boat registration, you’ll get a registration number and a decal to put on your boat. With rare exceptions, you’re required to display your registration number and the decals on both sides of the front half of your boat. <figure rend="Register a Boat Step 05.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can purchase waterproof block letters at your local boating or home improvement store.</item>
<item>It’s a good idea to purchase waterproof paint and block letter and number stencils so that your registration number is in compliance and easy to read from a distance.</item>
<item>Boat registrations usually expire after two years and must be renewed.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Renewing Your Boat Registration</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Review the boat registration renewal notice that you got in the mail. States usually send out registration renewal notices two months in advance of expiration. Review the notice carefully to find out if there are any required changes you need to make to be in compliance. <figure rend="Register a Boat Step 06 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, occasionally, the U.S. Coast Guard may require certain registration numbers to be changed. Should this happen, you would be required to remove the old registration number and display the new registration number to avoid a fine.</item></list></item>
<item>Create an account and log-in to your state’s licensing renewal website. Most states require initial registration by mail or in person and allow registration renewal online. The website you’re supposed to use is listed on your renewal notice. Follow the prompts online to complete your registration renewal. <figure rend="Register a Boat Step 07.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you don’t have a laptop with you at the time of renewal, don’t worry. Most registration renewal websites can be accessed on your smartphone.</item>
<item>You can also renew your boat registration by mail or in person if you so choose, depending on the state.</item></list></item>
<item>Pay your boat registration renewal fee online with a credit card. States that process registration renewals online usually accept a variety of credit cards. You might also be able to pay the renewal fee using a service like Paypal, depending on the state. <figure rend="Register a Boat Step 08.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Pay your boat registration renewal fee by check, money order or cashier's check if you send in your renewal form by mail.</item>
<item>Your boat registration number may not change, but you’ll be sent a new decal to put alongside it.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>While waiting for your registration, your state agency or boat dealer can issue you a temporary registration which allows you to park and use your boat.</item>
<item>You don’t need to register a non-motorized boat like a canoe or kayak. You may, however, need a permit to use your non-motorized boat, depending on park or waterway regulations.</item>
<item>Remember, as long as your boat is properly registered in the state where you normally keep it, you don’t need to register your boat in another state if you’re just visiting. Most states allow visitors to bring and use their boats for a limited amount of time without registration.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<p>It’s vitally important to follow boat registration rules in the state where you park your boat and states you visit for boating. Failure to comply may result in fines.</p>
</text>
