<text id="autogum_whow_doc403" title="Paint a Candy House in Watercolor" shortTile="paint-candy-house" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2017-11-19" dateModified="2019-09-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Paint-a-Candy-House-in-Watercolor" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Paint a Candy House in Watercolor</head><p>Toward the end of the year, candy and sweets lurk around every corner.  Those visions of sugarplums can be used make art.  Doing a painting of a house made of candy is a fun way to indulge without eating too much sugar or spending a lot of cash.  The resulting painting will last for years and starts with a simple rectangle.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Assemble your candy references.  Shop in the bulk aisle at your grocery store and buy tiny amounts of various candies to use as models.  Or, cut pictures of holiday candies, cakes, cookies out of newspapers, magazines and advertisements. <figure rend="Candyrefer.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Assemble your art supplies.   An 11” x 14” piece of 140 lb. watercolor paper from a pad, a set of watercolors in a full range of colors, plus black, and an assortment of watercolor brushes.  You'll also need a pencil, eraser, ruler and a fine line Sharpie in black. <figure rend="Paintsetc..jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Lay out the beginnings of your house.  Begin by drawing, in pencil, a rectangle. Use a template if you wish, a box, disk sleeve or other rectangular item.   Place this somewhere in the center of your page.</item>
<item>Construct the roof.  Find the center of your rectangle at  and draw 3” vertical line upward.  The top end of the line will be the peak of the roof.  Construct the roof by drawing a line down each side to form a large triangle.  Use a curvy item as a template for roof edge, if you wish. <figure rend="Sketchhouse.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Return to the body of the house and draw the door.  Make it  as tall and as  wide as you wish.  On either side, draw two square windows. <figure rend="Door,windows,path.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Decorate the house with candy shapes.  Look at your references and analyze the various types and styles of candies.  These will be your building materials, so look over their various sizes and shapes.  Try to picture which candy would look best at what point on your house. <figure rend="Decwcandy.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Begin to put candy on the house.  Sketch candy of one shape in pencil, repeatedly, to fill one area of your house.  For example, for the front, you might have round candies to mimic siding shingles.</item>
<item>Imagine how you want the roof to be.  You might use long candies to edge the roof or make it piled with snow---marshmallow fluff to mimic snow.  By working in pencil, you can make changes easily if one idea doesn't work out.  Erase and try something else. <figure rend="Pencildrawing.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Create a suitably sweet environment for your house.  Use varied sizes, shapes and colors of candies to make trees, pathways, rocks, signposts, and trimming around the corners of the house and its windows.  Candy canes make good lampposts.  Green lollipops look a bit like ornamental trees.  Long, narrow candies standing in a row resemble a fence.  Pile on the candy until much of the house is covered.  The landscape ought to be a magical place where candy reigns supreme. Remember to populate the scene.  Gingerbread men, women and children look exactly right as residents of a candy house.</item>
<item>Go over the pencil drawing with fine line permanent black marker. <figure rend="Inkwsharpie.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Activate your paints with drops of water.  Begin to paint the design.  The hard work is done if you have taken time to make your drawing detailed and complete.</item>
<item>Look to see where a color can be used in another part of the design.  While you have one color on your brush, use it wherever else it is needed.</item>
<item>Wash in a solid color for a sky.  This will be a nice backdrop for the colorful candy.  With so much going on in the picture a simple sky will be nice.</item>
<item>Work until the piece looks finished.  Allow it to dry and give it another look.  If any part needs punching up do it. <figure rend="Worktofinishit.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Allow the paint to dry before attempting to put another color close to it unless you want the two colors to mingle.</item>
<item>As you paint, work the colors from one spot into other areas of the design.  Instead of working in sections and completing one area at a time aim to keep the whole painting involved.  This all over approach to color will give a sense of unity to your work, having various shades sprinkled throughout the page.</item></list>
</text>
