<text id="autogum_whow_doc107" title="Get Away With Going to a Site You Aren&apos;t Supposed To" shortTile="away-going-site-arent" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2008-07-10" dateModified="2019-09-23" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get-Away-With-Going-to-a-Site-You-Aren%27t-Supposed-To" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get Away With Going to a Site You Aren't Supposed To</head><p>Are you not allowed to go on a website, say, YouTube or Myspace?  Well, for whatever reason it may be, you want to go on that site.  Maybe a friend told you of a cool video on YouTube, or maybe your friend has a page on Myspace they want you to see.  Either way, its important you make sure you don't get caught doing this.  Someone could see you on the site, or they could tell you were there from the browser's history.  Please read on to find out how to cover your tracks when you have to go on a site you aren't allowed to visit.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open up your browser and <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Locate_Your_Instant_Message_History_in_MSN_Messenger">go to the history</ref>.  Make sure there is some history left behind you before you go to the site.  If there isn't much, go to some sites, like yahoo and just click on links to fill up the history. <figure rend="Get Away With Going to a Site You Aren't Supposed To Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Once you have some history built, go to the site you aren't allowed to.  The point of filling up history before is because the site you went to will get "blurred in" and "lost" with the other pages. <figure rend="Get Away With Going to a Site You Aren't Supposed To Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You should also get a few other windows opened up.  This way, if someone comes by, you can just change windows.</item></list></item>
<item>Look at whatever you need to look at.  Be sure you don't take long though. <figure rend="Get Away With Going to a Site You Aren't Supposed To Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Close the window.  You should do this just to be sure you don't get caught.  This is also where having multiple windows open helps, as you can now fill up more history. <figure rend="Get Away With Going to a Site You Aren't Supposed To Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Delete_Browsing_History">Delete whatever history you had</ref> on that site.  You can now begin filling up history again. <figure rend="Get Away With Going to a Site You Aren't Supposed To Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Go on another site your parents allow you to.  Once you are there, go back and forth and click on as many links as you can.  Do this quickly however so it looks like you were only there for the whole time. <figure rend="Get Away With Going to a Site You Aren't Supposed To Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try getting Firefox then go to Tools &gt; Options... &gt; Privacy and check the box "Always clear private data when I close Firefox" then go to settings and check/uncheck whatever you want to be erased or kept.</item></list>
<p>Don't use AOL 9.0 you can't delete the web history.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_a_Gentle_Person">Be careful</ref> and <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_Excuses_for_Playing_on_the_Computer">make up some excuses</ref> for what you are doing.</item>
<item>Also delete the temporary internet files and cookies.</item>
<item>If there is a web filter on your computer, use a proxy web surfer to surf the sites, and then delete the history afterwards.</item>
<item>Try downloading an internet explorer that has a porn mode were you can delete history easily</item>
<item>Search the website's name on Google instead of entering it into the address bar. If you do, the bad website's name will be in the address bar and your parent[s] will notice. Be sure to delete the Google search history too.</item>
<item>If you would like to bookmark a website add it to you favorites with an innocent looking name. For example "This History of the Airplane Telephone".</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You could get grounded if you do this.  Please do this at your own risk.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Internet browser</item>
<item>Internet history</item>
<item>A few windows open</item>
<item>Proxy web surfer (such as Proxify.com or vtunnel.com)</item></list>
</text>
