<text id="autogum_whow_doc372" title="Make Cup Holder for Using on Trees" shortTile="make-cup-holder-using" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2009-09-24" dateModified="2019-09-20" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-Cup-Holder-for-Using-on-Trees" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make Cup Holder for Using on Trees</head><p>Hi, for all those tree climbers who are too lazy to put your refreshment drink in a thermos, here's a fun, creative, and easy way to keep from spilling your drink!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find a tree in your yard. Collect 9 sticks off the ground. They must not be thin nor thick enough to not break with your knee. Four sticks need to be about  long; a little more than your elbow to finger tip. Five sticks need to be  long; from elbow to wrist. Be prepared to break them.</item>
<item>Prepare the ties for the sticks. Many things will work to hold the sticks together. pipe cleaners, fabric scraps, and yarn are just a couple of ways to hold it together. be creative. Pipe cleaners are best; they are pretty strong for such little thingies.</item>
<item>Take two of the  sticks and cross them at the top; about  from the top of each. Take one pipe cleaner and make a plus sign with it; twisting it around each space between  the X. Do the same thing again with another pipe cleaner in the same spot.</item>
<item>Repeat step 3 with 2 separate  sticks.</item>
<item>Take 1 10 inch stick and repeat steps 3, but place stick at the bottom of the 1st X stick. It should look like a triangle with edges hanging off. Don't forget to do both sides where the sticks cross.</item>
<item>Repeat step 5, except with the 2nd set of X's.</item>
<item>Connect them! At the top of both triangles, where the X's are, place  stick vertically with  of space between top triangle and bottom triangle.</item>
<item>Take 3 pipe cleaners (or as many as necessary) and just weave it around the connection. they are there to keep it from moving. use as many pipe cleaners as you need.</item>
<item>Repeat step 7 and 8 with the remaining sticks at the bottom of the triangle.</item>
<item>It should look like a 3D triangle with edges poking out and colorful pipe cleaners. now just see if your drink fits. It should be snug.</item>
<item>If it's not, then scoot the sticks together a bit more. Take of some pipe cleaners if it won't budge.</item>
<item>Take a  piece of  tall knit, spandex, or whatever fabric you prefer that doesn't catch (like a run in panty hoses) and is stretchy. Wrap it around the triangle many, many times. As many as it will go.</item>
<item>With your hand, move the fabric in the middle of the triangle up at the top and down at the bottom to fit in can. move fabric back into place after drink is secured.</item>
<item>Take a (depending on how far you are going) piece of rope and tie to a tree limb in the tree you want to climb in.</item>
<item>Tie rope to top of cup holder.</item>
<item>Pull the rope like a pulley system to the resting spot of your choice and be happy!</item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you have a bottle, then change the lengths and dimensions in which this is made.</item>
<item>Cut off the leftover edges; give it a lot of breathing room with the length.</item>
<item>Use colorful fabric and pipe cleaners to add a bit of spunk.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>This will eventually break.</item>
<item>Do not leave out in extreme weather, winds, or rain.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Pipe cleaners, yarn, fabric scraps, or other material that won't break easily</item>
<item>A decent sized tree to climb</item>
<item>Rope</item>
<item>Spandex, knit, or others stretchy fabric</item>
<item>Coke or other drink can</item></list>
</text>
