<text id="autogum_whow_doc422" title="Find Festivals and Special Events in Denver" shortTile="find-festivals-special" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-04-13" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Find-Festivals-and-Special-Events-in-Denver" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Find Festivals and Special Events in Denver</head><p>Denver residents dedicate more money to public arts funding than any other community in America. The importance that residents place on the arts is evident the large number of festivals and special events in Denver throughout the year. From the 100-year old National Western Stock Show to the Colorado Renaissance Festival, the Mile High City has an event to suit every taste, nearly every weekend of the year.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Review the Denver Convention and Visitor's Bureau (CVB) website for the most comprehensive list of major music, art, theater and sporting events in Denver. Click on the "Events" link at the top of the home page to find festivals and special events ranging from the Denver Rocky Mountain Horse Expo in February to Denver Restaurant Week in October.</item>
<item>Purchase a print edition of the Denver Post, Colorado's main newspaper. On Thursdays and Sundays you'll find an entertainment calendar in the Post that spotlights events for the coming week, as well as reviews for past and current festivals, shows and activities. The online edition is more comprehensive however and allows users to find festivals and special events in Denver and outlying suburbs up to 30 days prior to their event date. Both print and online editions also include TV shows, book and restaurant reviews.</item>
<item>Pick up a copy of Westword, the Denver metropolitan area's free weekly alternative newspaper. If you're in Denver the print edition is free and available in nearly every major retail store. Both the print and online edition feature a weekly entertainment calendar that enables users to find festivals and events everywhere from the smallest to the largest venues. Nightclubs and outdoor recreation event listings are also included.</item>
<item>Visit a Denver library for events and festivals listings. Denver libraries serve as a repository for community groups of all sizes to post fliers about their events. The online edition of the Denver Library system also has a searchable directory of festivals and events in Denver ranging from baby exercise classes at the library to on-site film festivals.</item>
<item>Shop at a local health food store to find out what's going on. Denver health food stores like Sunflower Markets are a great way to get a feel for the local community because they usually have bulletin boards where local residents can post fliers about everything from nearby meditation classes to animal rescue adoption days. Many of these Denver festivals and special events will never make it into newspapers. These bulletin boards are often the only place you'll hear about them.</item>
<item>Consider the type of event that interests you, then search online for Denver-based organizations that might host a festival or special event of this type. For example, if you are a history buff who wants to know more about Denver's past, the organization Denver History Tours offers guided walking tours with themes ranging from historic architectural monuments to gold rush history.</item>
<item>Search user-generated review websites for festival and event listings. They allow users to search for festivals and special events by city and oftentimes there are dozens of reviews posted by attendees. Keep in mind that reviews are based on the personal experience of attendees and may not accurately reflect the collective experience of everyone who was there. Search for "Denver" to find upcoming festivals and special events.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Denver freeways can become extremely congested during peak driving times. Many of Denver's most popular events will impact local freeway conditions, so always check traffic reports the day of your event.</item></list>
</text>
