<text id="autogum_whow_doc374" title="Make a Spiral Styled Gimp" shortTile="make-spiral-styled" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2006-05-02" dateModified="2019-08-09" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-a-Spiral-Styled-Gimp" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make a Spiral Styled Gimp</head><p>Gimp, also called a boondoggle, or a lanyard, is woven from plastic lacing and turned into bracelets, keychains, pulleys, and even bookmarks. Also called guimpe or guipure, gimp plaiting creates a square shape, but you can create spiral-shapes if you follow these instructions. For the sake of clarity, we will use one red lace and one green lace.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Start with two  pieces of lacing. Find the center of each length of lacing. We use green and red, but you can use any other two colors you like. <figure rend="Make a Spiral Styled Gimp Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Cross the laces. Lay the center of the green lace across the center of the red lace in a perpendicular fashion. Your project should look like a plus sign. <figure rend="Make a Spiral Styled Gimp Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Start the weaving process. Fold the ends of the red lace across the green lace, as if they are arms hugging the green lace. Hold in place. The red lace now seems to be wrapped around the green lace. <figure rend="Make a Spiral Styled Gimp Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make the first layer. Pass one end of the green lace over the first fold in the red lace. Insert the green lace into the loop formed by the second fold of the red lace. Hold in place. <figure rend="Make a Spiral Styled Gimp Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pass the other end of the green lace over the first fold in the red lace. Insert the end of the green lace into the  loop formed by the second fold of the red lace. Pull gently to tighten lace. You have completed the first layer. It should hold itself in place now. <figure rend="Make a Spiral Styled Gimp Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Fold both ends of the red lace across your project. Instead of folding directly across, position them at a diagonal. Hold in place. <figure rend="Make a Spiral Styled Gimp Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pass one end of the green lace over the fold in the red lace. Insert the green lace into the loop formed by the fold of the red lace. Hold in place. <figure rend="Make a Spiral Styled Gimp Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pass the other end of the green lace over the fold in the red lace. Insert the end of the green lace into the loop formed by the fold of the red lace. Pull gently to tighten. You have completed the first diagonal layer. It should hold itself in place now. <figure rend="Make a Spiral Styled Gimp Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Repeat the steps for diagonal plaiting until you finish your project. Consistently form your diagonal plait and your project will form a spiral with each successive layer. <figure rend="Make a Spiral Styled Gimp Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Melt the end of the gimp with a match when you are finished.  Otherwise it will unravel or become loose. <figure rend="Make a Spiral Styled Gimp Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Finished. <figure rend="Make a Spiral Styled Gimp Step 11.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Check that the gimp has not twisted after you do a stitch.</item>
<item>Pull tight or the stitch will unravel.</item>
<item>Use gimp of the the same thickness for both strands or it will affect the desired shape.</item>
<item>You can make this without plastic.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be careful when using things such as matches and super glue during this project.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Gimp lacing</item>
<item>Scissors</item>
<item>Matches</item></list>
</text>
