<text id="autogum_whow_doc437" title="Host a Party in an Apartment Without Getting Busted or Thrown Out" shortTile="host-party-apartment" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2007-09-20" dateModified="2018-03-02" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Host-a-Party-in-an-Apartment-Without-Getting-Busted-or-Thrown-Out" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Host a Party in an Apartment Without Getting Busted or Thrown Out</head><p>It's happened to everyone.  You've hosted a party, favorite lite beverage in hand, drinking games ‘round the round table, and some intense music that was carrying to the building over, when suddenly around 3:20 a.m., a knock at the door by the local “proud to protect and serve” asking you to break it up (and shut it up).
Time to think on a better party-throwing method to head off homelessness. Be sure and keep these tips from <ref target="http://www.apartmenthomeliving.com">http://www.apartmenthomeliving.com</ref> in mind before you throw another busted party.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Have a plan. This may be a bit more difficult than simply calling everyone up at 7 p.m. for a party at 9, but it's well worth it. <figure rend="Host a Party in an Apartment Without Getting Busted or Thrown Out Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Reduce_Noise_Levels_in_Your_Apartment">Keep down the sound</ref>. If you keep down the sound, you’ll keep down the citations. <figure rend="Host a Party in an Apartment Without Getting Busted or Thrown Out Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't order a lot of delivery food. If the apartment building doesn't allow parties, it's a dead giveaway when the pizza man shows up with ten large pizzas if only two people are supposed to be living in your room! <figure rend="Host a Party in an Apartment Without Getting Busted or Thrown Out Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have your party at an earlier time. Parties from 6pm to 10pm are much less likely to have the cops called than a party from 8pm to 2am. <figure rend="Host a Party in an Apartment Without Getting Busted or Thrown Out Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Prepare the neighbors. <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Avoid_Offending_Uninvited_Guests">Explain to them beforehand of the party</ref>, and if appropriate: Invite them! <figure rend="Host a Party in an Apartment Without Getting Busted or Thrown Out Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take it outside. This may seem counter-intuitive. Not necessarily. A party by the pool or a grill-out can often remain a tad calmer than a party without all the outdoor distraction. Even better-Plan a midnight <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Play_Volleyball">volleyball</ref> or dodgeball game in a park close to the homestead and bring glow sticks…only Bambi and Thumper will be kept awake, and as long as you don’t have a giant strobe light, you should be fine. Extra hint: Stay clear of glass bottles.  Most parks don’t allow them. <figure rend="Host a Party in an Apartment Without Getting Busted or Thrown Out Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Plan a dinner party. Kidding. But, it may worth taking the party to a cheap nearby Bar and Grill with live music or a juke box.  A good group of friends, great food, and a little music always means awesome times.  And the clincher of the whole thing: NO CLEANUP! (Remember to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Tip_a_Bartender">tip your servers</ref>.) <figure rend="Host a Party in an Apartment Without Getting Busted or Thrown Out Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Plan a beginning with the end in mind. Mom used to say that nothing good happens after midnight. She obviously has never been to a slamming after-party.  Like tip # 4, you want to go out on the town, but still want to play host a little at your place. Not a problem. If you really want to insure that you won’t have to lay your head next to Gary, the guy under the bridge, take mom’s advice a little and invite friends to pre-party instead of an after party. Then head out on the town around 11 p.m. What this accomplishes? An awesome start to a night out by showing off your digs, and playing host without upsetting the neighbors. <figure rend="Host a Party in an Apartment Without Getting Busted or Thrown Out Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
