<text id="autogum_whow_doc652" title="Make It to the Major League" shortTile="make-major-league" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2017-12-08" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-It-to-the-Major-League" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make It to the Major League</head><p>Making it into the Major League for professional baseball is an extremely hard task to accomplish. It takes years of hard work and dedication to get drafted by a Major League team.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Know the odds. Only 1 in 200 high school seniors who play baseball will be drafted. Only about 7% of those players will actually play in the MLB.</item>
<item>Put in the work. Making it to the MLB requires a lot of hard work. Talent alone will only get you so far. You must work hard to hone your skills and you should always look to improve.</item>
<item>Play as much as possible. The more time you spend playing baseball, the more you can work on your game. This experience can help you to perform better overall as well as in high pressure situations.  <figure rend="Play Baseball Step 11 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Play well. This is important because MLB teams and scouts will not look into a player that does not perform well. They only want the best of the best. You need to show that you belong in that category. <figure rend="Get Used to Batting Against Side Arm Pitchers Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Challenge yourself. Play against the best competition available to you. This will help you improve in more ways than one. You will not only become a better player by doing this, but you will also gain a competitive attitude. This attitude will make you want to be the best and will fuel your training and practice. <figure rend="Play Baseball Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get your name out there. Gaining positive recognition from college and MLB scouts improve your chances of being drafted. Build a relationship with these people and keep them updated with your performance and accomplishments. <figure rend="Be a Champion Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Know the rules of the MLB. The general rules are that draft eligible players are:
<list type="unordered"><item>High school, players, if they have graduated high school and not yet attended college or junior college</item>
<item>College players, from four-year colleges who have either completed their junior or senior years, or are at least 21 years old</item>
<item>Junior college players, regardless of how many years of school they have completed.</item></list></item>
<item>Once drafted, work your way up to the major league. Most drafted players begin their careers in the minor leagues. Work hard and perform well to quickly rise up the ranks in your organization</item>
<item>Major league call ups. Once your organization feels you are ready, they will move you up to the major league team. This may be temporary or permanent. Your performance will most likely decide which it will be. <figure rend="Be a New York Mets Fan Step 3.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't let the odds discourage you. Use them as motivation.</item>
<item>Find a routine that works for you and stick with it.</item>
<item>Try to play high school baseball in the spring, travel baseball in the summer, and fall/winter baseball in the offseason.</item>
<item>It is more important to play well in your travel baseball summer league season than it is during high school and fall/winter season. However, playing well all the time will greatly benefit you.</item>
<item>If you play the best competition available, you will have a better chance of getting recognized. Scouts usually attend a greater number of these games than those with lesser competition.</item>
<item>The more positive recognition you receive, the more likely you are to be noticed by an MLB team.</item>
<item>Undrafted players may enter free agency and be picked up by a team.</item>
<item>When you are called up to the major league team, do not stop working hard. You can always be demoted back down.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>MLB draft rules may differ for international players.</item></list>
</text>
