<text id="autogum_whow_doc090" title="Appear Busy While Using a Computer" shortTile="appear-busy-using" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2007-10-15" dateModified="2019-10-25" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Appear-Busy-While-Using-a-Computer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Appear Busy While Using a Computer</head><p>For people in school, at work or doing some "homework" using a computer on a daily/hourly basis, this wikiHow explains how you can look productive while not actually doing anything or just procrastinating without letting anyone know. If you have the inclination to look busy, but be doing nothing work-related, read on from step number one below.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>If you have a scheduled assignment, keep it in the taskbar and prepare to fast-click to it at a second's notice. Alt-tab can also be useful here. <figure rend="Appear Busy While Using a Computer Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Intersperse work with downtime by working for a few moments followed by IMing, Facebooking, Googling, or whatever it is you feel like doing. This way you can relax and do your job, albeit slowly, at the same time. <figure rend="Appear Busy While Using a Computer Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Write a wikiHow article on something you know about. It looks like work, and takes a good amount of typing to do. It's a perfect cover, but won't  impress your boss if you're being paid to do tasks. <figure rend="Appear Busy While Using a Computer Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you're at home with a laptop then try sitting with your back to a wall. That way no one can see what you're doing. Do a lot of typing that looks productive. <figure rend="Appear Busy While Using a Computer Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure that even if you aren't doing much work, have something that looks like work open, such as an end of quarter PowerPoint or something of the sort. <figure rend="Appear Busy While Using a Computer Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are at work, a library, or any other public place, it may be a good idea to strategically place open books, folders, or papers on and around your desk or table.  Be sure to turn the pages once in a while, or pretend to read them, to increase believability.</item>
<item>When somebody tells you something, don't answer immediately and say, 'Shhh! Can't you see I'm busy? I can't focus both at you and at what I'm doing now!'</item>
<item>In Windows, hitting the Windows and the D key simultaneously will take you to your Desktop instantly.</item>
<item>If you get caught, be prepared with an excuse. Keep it real!</item>
<item>If you're working online and using a tabbed web browser, it's simple to do anything you want in one tab while doing work in another.  Or, try installing a remote access software such as LogMeIn on your computer, which is accessible by browser, so you can access your home computer and do stuff from anywhere.</item>
<item>It's easier to appear busy if you actually are busy! Play a game or go on wikihow, it's more fun than just sitting there.</item>
<item>Using a proxy can usually bypass filters/blocking software, but it can get you in trouble with the school IT director, so try to avoid it if you can</item>
<item>Turn down/off the volume of the computer, as the bleeps and bloops of IM and other messengers will tip you off.</item>
<item>Practice using the Alt-Tab strategy. You can immediately switch to another open program without using the mouse.</item>
<item>Don't spend the whole period doing this. You need to do your work; this is just for little breaks you might need.</item>
<item>You can always keep open a work file. For instance: If you're on Myspace, or  email when you should be writing a paper, keep the paper opened but minimized.</item>
<item>Always look serious. Try not to laugh!</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You might get caught, be alert at all times.</item>
<item>Don't click out of something fast, that will draw a teacher or professors attention. Just calmly click into another page or always go to Yahoo.com or Google!</item>
<item>Don't play Solitaire/Minesweeper/any other silly game if you want to appear busy. Being caught doing something as trivial as that only shows how bored you really are.</item>
<item>Don't appear to be too interested, that is a sign that you're not doing work.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Computer</item>
<item>Time</item>
<item>Skills in covering up</item></list>
</text>
