<text id="autogum_whow_doc620" title="Become a Kurd" shortTile="become-kurd" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-06-12" dateModified="2019-03-18" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Become-a-Kurd" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Become a Kurd</head>Lots of people become Kurds and this  will give you some tips and tricks onbecoming one. Be aware that becoming a Kurd is not for the faint-hearted. <hi rend="bold">Do not</hi> become a Kurd just for the "good bits".
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Decide what kind of Kurd you want to be. There are Turkish Kurds, Syrian Kurds, Iraqi Kurds, Iranian Kurds, Sorani Kurds, Kurmanji Kurds and Hawrami Kurds.
<list type="unordered"><item>Do some internet research or find a book about Kurds at a library or bookstore to help make this decision. One should only become the kind of Kurd they can relate to the most.</item></list></item>
<item>Adhere to the religion. Some 90% of Kurds are Sunni Muslims following the Shafi legal code. Luckily, conversion to Islam is very easy, one just needs to declare their faith, either to themselves or officially in a mosque. The other 10% are Yazidis, Yarsanis and Alevis. While it is difficult to convert to Yazidism, Yarsanism and Alevism are much more accepting of converts and if you live in a big city, you should be able to find a Cemevi or a Yarsani temple.
<list type="unordered"><item>Most Kurds focus more on being Kurds than being religious, so you don't need to be overly religious or take part in all the religious rituals. It's more about being part of the group than anything else.</item></list></item>
<item>Change your name. Usually you can legally change your name if you are 18, but it depends where you live.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are a Turkish Kurd, you should choose a Kurdish first name and Turkish surname as Kurdish surnames are banned in Turkey.</item>
<item>If you are an Iraqi Kurd, choose a Kurdish first name, a religious male middle name and surname, and then a tribal or geographical designator.</item>
<item>If you are an Iranian Kurd, choose a Kurdish first name and an Iranian surname.</item></list></item>
<item>Dress and look like a Kurd.  This does <hi rend="italic">not</hi> mean wearing traditional garb all the time, even though it is a wise idea to have a brown or olive green suit (for men) or a dress (for women). You can buy these from online stores, Ebay, and specialist shops.
<list type="unordered"><item>Kurdish girls wear heavy makeup and have thick eyebrows and long lashes. If you are female, invest in some eyebrow pencil, foundation and mascara, or get your eyebrows tinted.</item>
<item>If you are female and you are an Iraqi Kurd or Iranian Kurd, you might be expected to put a scarf over most of your hair. It should be stylish, possibly designer. Don't forget the oversized sunglasses.</item>
<item>If you are male, wear baggy jeans, sports clothes, cologne or perfume, and always be clean-shaven.</item></list></item>
<item>Try to learn the lingo. While textbooks and online resources for learning Kurdish are limited, it is possible to find a private tutor or go to a group language learning class, if you live in a European city. If you live in a Midwestern hick town, you're out of luck.
<list type="unordered"><item>This isn't mandatory, but it is recommended that learn a third language depending on what kind of Kurd you are. An Iranian Kurd would learn Farsi, an Iraqi Kurd would learn Arabic, and a Turkish Kurd would learn Turkish. If you have a knack for languages, why not learn all three? Resources for these are much more abundant.</item></list></item>
<item>Meet other Kurds. Join the community. The aforementioned cities, like London, Paris and Berlin, should have Kurdish community centres where you can attend meetings, celebrations, commemorations, and protests. Meeting other Kurds can also help with learning the language and finding love. It is better for Kurds to marry other Kurds.
<list type="unordered"><item>Be prepared to go to lots of protests. Making signs and banners is a great way to bond with new friends. Just stay safe! Protests, especially at night, can be dangerous for young people on their own and could even get you arrested so make sure you stay in a group.</item></list></item>
<item>Get official documentation. Sadly, there is no such thing as a "Kurdish passport" but you can apply for an Iranian, Iraqi, or Turkish passport, and an ID card in Iraq and Turkey.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you have a passport that might make travelling to the Homeland difficult, like an American passport if you are an Iranian Kurd, that and your American citizenship might need to be renounced.</item></list></item>
<item>Consider marriage. Marrying an Iranian citizen (hopefully a Kurd) will automatically give you Iranian citizenship.</item>
<item>Develop your political views. Keep in mind that Kurdish people talk politics as often as English people talk weather.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are a Turkish Kurd, you would probably support the left-wing HDP. The leader is currently imprisoned. Disagreement with Erdogan is de rigueur. Campaign for your basic human rights.</item>
<item>If you are an Iraqi Kurd, you already have a semi-autonomous jurisdiction...and a problem with nepotism and corruption, so you would show a certain amount of distrust of the local govt. Campaign for further independence.</item>
<item>If you are an Iranian Kurd, you would generally not vote, having similar distrust for the govt. Campaign for the abolition of the death penalty.</item></list></item>
<item>Prepare to confront haters. Sadly, even in this day and age, many people won't respect your decision to live as a Kurd so you need to be able to discuss it with them in a civilised way. Don't be overly zealous with people who might not be sympathetic. Some subjects are only suitable for discussion with other Kurds. Be articulate and confident. You can practice this by joining a debate club, Model Un, or toastmasters.
<list type="unordered"><item>Be prepared to be called "other" and "enemy" and "terrorist". This may be distressing so it helps if you consistently tell yourself that you aren't.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
