<text id="autogum_whow_doc610" title="Live Two Different Lives" shortTile="live-two-different" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2012-12-03" dateModified="2018-09-27" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Live-Two-Different-Lives" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Live Two Different Lives</head><p>If you are like many people, you are a person that has many different identities, good and bad. Many people do not fulfill their several identities but instead settle for only living out one identity. Others, because they are braver, or simply more adventurous, embrace their several identities and live them out to their fullest. However, usually, out of necessity, you must separate your chosen identities and thus live multiple lives. This article should help guide you along the way to living two ( or more!) different lives in a legal manner.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Realize and accept you are a multifaceted and complex person. For some, this can be hard to realize because they have, for their entire life, felt constricted and trapped by the roles they have been forced to play in their life. The concept that you are a different person than those around you realize can be quite a liberating experience. <figure rend="Live Two Different Lives (Non Illegal Purposes) Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Discover who you really are. You are allowed to be whoever you truly are. ( Within reason of course! If you are not a brain surgeon than please don't scrub in for surgery and start operating! Please don't hurt others.)  <figure rend="Live Two Different Lives (Non Illegal Purposes) Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Figure out ways to live and be yourself. Take classes, read books, and research the identity you believe you are. Simply just be yourself. If you secretly really want to be a drag queen, then rent a hotel room, dress up, find a friendly club and go crazy out there! If you are younger ( under 18) than this is obviously where you will have the most trouble. Your parents and family may have issues with you just being yourself especially if they are strict. This is where it really helps to have at least one person who knows who your other identity is, and who you can be your true self around even just to vent. <figure rend="Live Two Different Lives (Non Illegal Purposes) Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Figure out if you need money. Some double lives require a lot of cash on hand. Such is the case if you have to travel frequently to fulfill your life. Think through this and make sure you are set financially. Get another job if you have to (this in itself can be a secret life depending on the work you do). <figure rend="Live Two Different Lives (Non Illegal Purposes) Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find ways to be yourself and have fun! <figure rend="Live Two Different Lives (Non Illegal Purposes) Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you know your job will have a problem with who you are, then you are basically in the same situation as when your parents did not approve. Thankfully, however, it is easier to hide what you are doing from your employer then it is to hide it from your parents. If you believe you may lose your employment if your boss finds out what you are doing then be very careful!</item></list>
</text>
