<text id="autogum_whow_doc377" title="Cut Vinyl Records" shortTile="cut-vinyl-records" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-08-20" dateModified="2019-06-11" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Cut-Vinyl-Records" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Cut Vinyl Records</head><p>If you have an old vinyl record that's unplayable or scratched, upcycle it instead of throwing it away. You can make art, designs, jewelry, and much more by cutting the record. By heating the record or by using a hotknife, you can easily cut your vinyl into whatever shape you need!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Heating the Record in the Oven</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Preheat the oven to . Put one of the racks in the center position. Turn on the oven and let it heat completely. <figure rend="Cut Vinyl Records Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you want to make a specific design, draw it on the record with a pencil before you heat it.</item></list></item>
<item>Put the vinyl record in the oven for 2-3 minutes. Set the record on the center rack. It can go directly into the oven or onto a baking tray. Turn on the oven’s interior light if it has one so you can watch the vinyl heat. Use oven mitts to take the vinyl out of the oven before it starts to droop or melt. <figure rend="Cut Vinyl Records Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The heat softens the vinyl, making it easier to cut.</item>
<item>Leave your oven on until you’re completely finished with your cuts in case you need to reheat your vinyl.</item>
<item>Cover a baking tray with aluminum foil before putting the vinyl record on it. This protects the baking tray from any melted vinyl.</item></list></item>
<item>Use a utility knife or pair of heavy-duty scissors to cut the record. Set the vinyl on a flat heat-safe cutting surface. Hold the record still with an oven mitt or potholder so it doesn’t move around when you cut it. Follow along with your design with a sharp knife or pair of scissors. <figure rend="Cut Vinyl Records Step 3.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure you use a sharp blade to make your cuts.</item></list></item>
<item>Put the record back in the oven if it hardens. As you work with the vinyl, it will start to solidify as it loses temperature. Set the record back on the center rack of your oven for 1-2 minutes to soften it to a workable temperature again. Repeat this as many times as you need until you’ve finished cutting your vinyl record. <figure rend="Cut Vinyl Records Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Turn off your oven when you make your last cuts.</item></list></item>
<item>Smooth the edges of the vinyl with fine-grit sandpaper. Use a 120 to 300-grit sandpaper to finish the edges where you made your cuts. This ensures they aren’t jagged or sharp so you can easily handle the record afterward. <figure rend="Cut Vinyl Records Step 5.360p.mp4"></figure></item></list>
<head>Using a Hotknife</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Buy a hot knife from an arts and crafts store. Hot knives are heated cutting tools used in crafts and woodworking to precisely cut delicate materials like vinyl or foam. Visit your local crafts store and look for a hot knife with a sharp blade attachment. <figure rend="Cut Vinyl Records Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Check a home improvement store if an arts and crafts store doesn’t carry hot knives.</item></list></item>
<item>Plug the hot knife in and let it heat up. Turn on the knife and set it so the blade is off of your work surface. Wait 2-3 minutes for the blade to heat up or else your knife won’t make smooth cuts. Do not touch the blade of the knife once it’s heated. <figure rend="Cut Vinyl Records Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Work on a wooden or heat-resistant surface so your knife doesn’t burn through it when you make your cuts.</item>
<item>Keep the knife out of children’s reach.</item>
<item>Many hot knives will have a built-in stand to hold the blade off the table.</item></list></item>
<item>Poke the knife through the record and pull it along your design. Slowly stab the tip of the hot knife through the vinyl record. Once you’re through the vinyl, pull the knife at a steady speed along the line you want to cut. Follow all of your lines until you’ve completely cut out your design. Turn off the knife and let it cool down once you finish. <figure rend="Cut Vinyl Records Step 8.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Vinyl contains chlorine gas that could escape when it’s heated. Wear a facemask while cutting the vinyl with a hotknife.</item>
<item>Don’t hold the knife in one spot for too long or else the vinyl will melt and bubble.</item>
<item>Keep the knife stationary and move the record with your other hand if that’s more comfortable.</item></list></item>
<item>Punch the vinyl pieces when you finish cutting them. Hold the cutout portion of vinyl against the table with your non-dominant hand. Start gently pulling the rest of the record off your work surface with your dominant hand to separate the pieces. <figure rend="Cut Vinyl Records Step 9.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For more intricate pieces, hold the cutouts as close to the edge as possible so they don’t break off when you try to separate the pieces.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Making Crafts</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Transform the record label into a coaster. Heat the record in the oven at  for 3 minutes. Once the oven is heated, use a pair of scissors to cut out the label in the center. Once you have the record down to size, trace it onto a piece of felt and cut it out. Attach the felt to the bottom of the record label with spray adhesive. <figure rend="Cut Vinyl Records Step 10.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure to cover the hole in the center of the record, or else the liquid could still damage your table.</item></list></item>
<item>Cut the record into decorative wall art. Draw a design on the record using a number 2 pencil before you start cutting it. Cut your design out of the vinyl using either a hotknife or utility knife. Hang the record on your wall either using adhesive strips or with a nail through the center hole. <figure rend="Cut Vinyl Records Step 11.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>To get inspiration for your art, look at the name of the record and think of a theme that relates to the song or album title.</item></list></item>
<item>Make wrist cuffs out of vinyl strips. Cut out  strips out of the record and put them on a baking tray. Place the tray in an oven heated to  for about 3-4 minutes. Once you remove the baking sheet, shape the vinyl strip to fit around your wrist by wrapping it around a rolling pin. <figure rend="Cut Vinyl Records Step 12.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you need to reshape or resize the vinyl, put it back in the oven for 1 minute to soften it again.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Vinyl releases chlorine gas when heated. Wear a facemask so you don’t inhale any of the fumes.</item></list>
<head>Things You’ll Need</head>
<head>Heating the Record in the Oven</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Oven</item>
<item>Utility knife</item>
<item>Heavy-duty scissors</item>
<item>Sandpaper</item>
<item>Baking sheet (optional)</item></list>
<head>Using a Hotknife</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Hotknife</item>
<item>Wooden work surface</item>
<item>Facemask</item></list>
<head>Making Crafts</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Oven</item>
<item>Scissors</item>
<item>Felt</item>
<item>Pencil</item>
<item>Hotknife</item>
<item>Rolling pin</item>
<item>Baking sheet</item></list>
</text>
