<text id="autogum_whow_doc395" title="Paint Helmets" shortTile="paint-helmets" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-03-15" dateModified="2019-04-15" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Paint-Helmets" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Paint Helmets</head><p>Painting a helmet is a great way to express your personality and sense of style. It can transform this important piece of safety gear into an attractive accessory. Before you start to paint your bicycle, motorcycle, or sports helmet, however, make sure that the paint you select is safe to use on your helmet. The solvents in some paints may corrode the material your helmet is made of, rendering it less effective at protecting your head. Once you’ve determined that the paint you’re using is safe, use masking tape to cover the parts of your helmet that you don’t want to get painted, sketch out your design, then get started. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Getting Ready for Painting</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Check local laws in your area to make sure painting your helmet is legal. In some jurisdictions, painting your motorcycle helmet may be a violation of road safety laws. This is because the petroleum-based solvents found in many paints may damage the helmet and reduce the protection it provides. Contact the transportation safety office in your local area for relevant information. <figure rend="Paint Helmets Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Laws regarding the modification of motorcycle helmets vary location to location and so do police officers’ interpretation of these laws.</item>
<item>Wearing a helmet that doesn’t comply with local safety laws may result in a fine.</item></list></item>
<item>Select a paint that is approved by the manufacturer of your helmet. Because the solvents in some paints may weaken the plastic of some bicycle, motorcycle, and sports helmets, the manufacturer of your helmet may recommend against painting it. Check the tags and labels that came with your helmet when you purchased it, and look for any warnings about types of paint that should be avoided. <figure rend="Paint Helmets Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you can’t find any helpful information in the material you received when you purchased your helmet, try contacting the helmet’s manufacturer, and ask if they have any recommendations about paints that would be safe to use on your helmet.</item>
<item>If the outside of your helmet is damaged, don’t paint it. The solvent in the paint may leak into outer shell and damage it.</item></list></item>
<item>Avoid sanding the painted surface of your helmet. If you try to sand existing paint off your helmet, you may inadvertently sand into the outer plastic or fiberglass shell. This can weaken the helmet’s outer shell, reducing its effectiveness in protecting the inner layer from everyday bumps and scrapes. This may diminish your helmet’s ability to protect your head in the event of an accident. <figure rend="Paint Helmets Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you’re going to buy a helmet to paint, go with a plain white or black matte helmet so that you don’t have to worry about removing any painted design or glossy finish.</item></list></item>
<item>Clean your helmet with a mixture of dish detergent and water. Removing dirt and grease from your helmet is essential if you want the paint you apply to stick to its surface. Fill a small container with warm water and household dish soap, soak a rag in the mixture, and then thoroughly wipe down the outer surface of your helmet. <figure rend="Paint Helmets Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>After washing your helmet, dry it off with a clean, lint-free cloth and let it sit for an hour so that it can dry thoroughly.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Applying the Paint</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Cover or remove any parts you don’t want to be painted or clear coated. Remove any removable fittings that you don’t want to paint, such as a visor on a motorcycle helmet or a face mask on a football helmet. Simply pull off any pieces that are attached with Velcro or fasteners. Then use masking tape to cover any parts you shouldn’t remove, like the inner shell and vents. Make sure only the area you want to paint is exposed. <figure rend="Paint Helmets Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Use paper or plastic and masking tape to shield the inside of the helmet from the paint.</item>
<item>Removing the inner shell, vents, or any other essential part of your helmet’s structure during the painting process may weaken it, so try to avoid doing this.</item></list></item>
<item>Sketch your design on the helmet with a pencil. You can also use stencils, stickers, or tape to make your design. Take your time so that your helmet design will look just like what you imagined. <figure rend="Paint Helmets Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Use thin black lines to enhance the visibility of your design from a distance.</item>
<item>To create complex geometric patterns, try cutting strips of masking tape and arranging them on your helmet.</item></list></item>
<item>Paint your design with water-based acrylic paints and brushes. These water-based paints are safe to use on helmets. Let each layer of paint dry before applying the next one so that every layer can properly bond to the surface of your helmet. This will help keep the paint from peeling off. <figure rend="Paint Helmets Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Apply your base layers first and then add shadowing, highlights, and any finishing touches.</item>
<item>If you want to spray paint your helmet, opt to use an airbrush instead of an aerosol can. An airbrush will allow you to cover your helmet in a more even coat of paint.</item>
<item>Don’t paint over any safety stickers that may be on your helmet.</item>
<item>If you applied any masking tape to make your design, remove the tape slowly and gently only after the paint on your helmet has dried to avoid inadvertently damaging your design.</item></list></item>
<item>Apply 3-4 layers of clear coat to protect the paint on your helmet. Shake the can of clear coat for 1 – 2 minutes before applying it to your helmet so that the solvent and clear coat become fully mixed together. Then position the nozzle a can’s length away from the helmet and spray. Move the can side to side and lightly coat the entire surface of the helmet. <figure rend="Paint Helmets Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Let the clear coat dry for 15-20 minutes, then repeat the process 2-3 times to ensure the helmet is evenly coated and the paint is protected.</item>
<item>Use a clear coat that is intended for use on plastic. Check what your clear coat is made of before applying it to your helmet to make sure that it is safe to use on your helmet.</item>
<item>Double check before spraying the clear coat that the inside of your helmet is completely covered. The clear coat may eat away at the foam inside the helmet.</item>
<item>Allow the clear coat to sit overnight before reattaching any of the fittings you removed.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
