<text id="autogum_whow_doc488" title="Put Spurs on Boots" shortTile="put-spurs-boots" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-05-03" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Put-Spurs-on-Boots" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Put Spurs on Boots</head><p>Spurs can help improve communication between a rider and a mount.  If you’ve selected a shiny new pair of spurs, you may be wondering how to attach them to your favorite cowboy boots.  The process is quite simple and should only take a few minutes.  Once you understand and assemble your new spurs, you’ll have them on your boots and be riding in no time.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Setting up the Spur</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Locate the spur ledge on the back of your cowboy boot.  The spur ledge is the protruding part of the boot heel that creates a small shelf where the spur heel band will rest. <figure rend="Put Spurs on Boots Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The spur ledge is a very slight ledge, just large enough so that the heel band doesn’t slip down the boot.</item>
<item>All cowboy style boots should have a spur ledge.  If you are not sure about your boots, take them with you when you go to purchase your spurs.</item></list></item>
<item>Find the heel band portion of the spur.  The heel band is the U-shaped piece of metal that wraps around the boot’s heel and is held on by a strap.  The heel band may have buttons where the straps will attach or bars for threading straps to attach. <figure rend="Put Spurs on Boots Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You will need a heel band that is approximately the same size as the heel portion of your cowboy boot.</item></list></item>
<item>Choose 1 long strap if the heel band has bars.  If the heel band has bars on both sides, you will need 1 long strap with a buckle on one end to attach the heel band to the boot. <figure rend="Put Spurs on Boots Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Take a look at your strap to see if it has a decoration, metal work, or fancy design on one side.  You want the decorative side to always be visible on the outside of your boot.</item></list></item>
<item>Get 2 small straps if the heel band has buttons.  If the heel band has buttons on both sides, you will need 2 smaller straps with buttonholes.  These will ultimately buckle together after being attached to both sides of the heel band. <figure rend="Put Spurs on Boots Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Take a look at your straps to see if either of them have a decorative, scalloped, or fancy side.  You want the decorative side to always be visible on the outside of your boot.</item></list></item>
<item>Look for the shank on the spur.  The shank is a small metal piece that extends from the middle of the heel band.  The shank should point down once the spur is in place on the boot. <figure rend="Put Spurs on Boots Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Spot the rowel on the back of the spur.  The rowel is the rotating disk with blunt points attached to the shank on the heel band.  This is the most important part of the spur because it is the part you will use to nudge your horse in the side to communicate your intentions with him. <figure rend="Put Spurs on Boots Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Exercise caution when handling the rowel so that you don’t accidentally cut yourself.  Most aren’t incredibly sharp but could still cause pain if grabbed too tightly.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Assembling the Spur</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Gather all the pieces needed to assemble your spur.  You’ll need to grab your boots, heel band (with rowel attached), and the straps you will be using.  This is a perfect time to position any decorative strap sides where you want them before attaching them to the heel band. <figure rend="Put Spurs on Boots Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Attach button straps onto heel bands with buttons.  For this type of heel band, you will need 2 small straps with buttonholes.  The straps will be attached on either side of the heel band and then buckled across the boot later. <figure rend="Put Spurs on Boots Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Hold the heel band in your hand with the shank facing down.</item>
<item>Start with one side of the heel band and place the first strap with the buttonhole over the heel band button.</item>
<item>Spread the buttonhole apart to push the button through the hole.</item>
<item>Rotate the strap around the button until it lays down flat.</item>
<item>Repeat with the other side of the heel band and attach the second strap.</item></list></item>
<item>Thread straps into a heel band with bars.  For this type of heel band, you will need 1 longer strap with a buckle.  With 1 long strap you will thread it through both sides of the heel band and buckle it across the boot later. <figure rend="Put Spurs on Boots Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Hold the heel band in your hand with the shank facing down.</item>
<item>Begin threading the strap from the inside of the outward facing heel band bar.</item>
<item>Thread the strap through the bars.  The buckle should end up on the outside of your boot.</item>
<item>Leave some strap to go under the boot and then thread the same strap into the other side of the heel band through the bars.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Attaching the Spur to Your Boot</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Fit the heel band to the spur ledge of your boot.  The heel band should rest on the spur ledge with the shank facing down.  The fit should not be too tight or too loose.  There should be a little bit of movement for the spur to fit correctly.  If the fit is off just slightly, you may be able to gently pull it apart to loosen it or squeeze a bit to tighten it. <figure rend="Put Spurs on Boots Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Attach the spur to your boot by buckling the straps.  Once the heel band is fitted in place at the back of your boot, buckle the strap or straps together over the boot to create a snug fit. <figure rend="Put Spurs on Boots Step 11.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Put the buckles on the outside of the boots.  If the buckles are facing the inside of the boots, they will rub together at your ankles and be uncomfortable.</item></list></item>
<item>Adjust the strap so that the spur fits snugly onto the boot.  If the spur is too tight or too loose once buckled onto your boot, you may need to let some strap in or out of the buckle to adjust the fit. <figure rend="Put Spurs on Boots Step 12.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Start by unbuckling the strap.  Next, adjust the length of the strap as needed to ensure a good fit.  Finish up by re-buckling the strap.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are having trouble attaching the spur to your boot while you are wearing the boots, try fitting the spur to the boot and buckling them in place before slipping the boot onto your foot.</item></list>
</text>
