<text id="autogum_whow_doc619" title="Raise a Child to Respect Religion" shortTile="raise-child-respect" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2017-04-17" dateModified="2019-07-21" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Raise-a-Child-to-Respect-Religion" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Raise a Child to Respect Religion</head>Religion and faith are both important foundations in the upbringing of many children. Teaching children to respect their own faith, as well as the beliefs of others can help them live in harmony. This article will show practical ways to do so.
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Stay neutral. If you place one religion on a pedestal or give it higher importance than another one, your child will have a hard time respecting religion and treating all beliefs as equal. Keep your explanations neutral and fact-based, and save your personal beliefs for a later discussion, if your child initiates it. <figure rend="Help an Autistic Child Cope with Change Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try not to belittle any religion or compare one to another. Let them know that all religions teach people to be good to one another.  <figure rend="Instill Discipline in Children Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Explain how people adopt their religion. It is crucial for the parent to know about his/her own religion first and how they adopted it because until we know this, we can't pass knowledge on to our children. Many parents make the mistake of pushing faith on kids without looking at the consequences of prohibiting choice.  <figure rend="Explain Bipolar to a Child Step 2 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Teach kids about faith. It can help them make a wise and informed choice regarding their own worship. You can teach kids about:  <figure rend="Appreciate People of Other Religions Step 17.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The most prominent figure of that religion</item>
<item>The place people of that religion worship</item>
<item>The holy book, and what it means to different people</item>
<item>Traditions and religious customs.</item></list></item>
<item>Teach about all religions. While many people place a focus on the religion they want their child to be or the religion that's most common where they live, it doesn't give your child a well-rounded view of religion. Talk about all major religions, not just your faith or the most common ones in your area, so they get to learn about all religions and make a decision of their own. <figure rend="Lose Your Religion Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you don't know enough about a certain religion to explain it to your child, research it with them. You could visit the library and pick out books to read together, or look it up online together.</item></list></item>
<item>Don't try to force faith on a child. Trying to force a child or teen to worship in a certain way creates much distress, so instead provide freedom of choice and experimentation. <figure rend="Instill Discipline in Children Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Take your child to many different places of worship, such as a temple, church, gurdwara, cathedral, or mosque so that he/she can actually see them and learn about them.</item>
<item>Introduce him/her to the people who belong to a different religion.</item>
<item>Explain both the positive and negative aspects of all religions.</item>
<item>Purchase or borrow books with teachings from various prophets, and discuss what they mean with kids.</item>
<item>Teach tolerance for each other. Respect the beliefs of others, no matter how much you agree or disagree with them.</item></list></item>
<item>Let your child choose a place of worship when they are of age. Be proud that you instilled values of faith and respect in them.  <figure rend="Explain Lent to a Child Step 13 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Allow them to ask questions. Answer their questions for as long as you are comfortable. When their curiosity becomes too much for your patience or time, guide them towards books, websites, speakers &amp; movies that you trust as credible sources to answer their questions.  <figure rend="Promote Physical Activity in Childcare Step 14.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Never answer them something misleading in haste. It may affect their future thoughts.</item>
<item>Encourage them to seek their own answers since religious texts have many interpretations and interpreters. They can be encouraged to reason and relate religious teachings to their daily life.</item></list></item>
<item>Accept their stance. If they choose to take time or stay without a choice, allow them. Matters of faith and religion can't be forced. Allow their life incidents and observations to turn their hearts towards a particular religion.  <figure rend="Explain Bipolar to a Child Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Let kids ask questions and try your best to provide answers.</item>
<item>Talk about faith openly and let your children know that they are free to talk to you about it.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Never speak harshly about other religions. It will give your child a negative view of those religions and push them towards religious intolerance.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Various holy books and writings</item>
<item>Access to a library or bookstore</item></list>
</text>
