<text id="autogum_whow_doc537" title="Know if You&apos;re Ready for a Pet" shortTile="know-re-ready-pet" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2016-01-16" dateModified="2016-01-16" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Know-if-You%27re-Ready-for-a-Pet" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Know if You're Ready for a Pet</head><p>A Pet is an animal kept primarily for a person's company or protection, as opposed to working animals, sport animals, livestock, and laboratory animals, which are kept primarily for performance, agricultural value, or researchAs we all know, almost people all over the world have Pets at home. They have pets for fun and companionship. But of course,having a pet offers great responsibility, Pets or Companion Animals are just the same as Humans. They need Food,Shelter and someone to take Care of them. So how will you know if youre ready for a Pet? The following steps will make you think and know if youre truly ready to have a Pet in your life.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>CHECK YOURSELF
<list type="unordered"><item>How old are you? Can you take care of yourself? Do you still live with your family? If you are old enough and can take care of yourself, you are ready to take care of someone else and adopt a pet. and you need to have enough knowledge of that certain animal youre trying to adopt so that it would be easier for you to take care of it and you would not disturb your familyfor asking them what,when,how and why about your pet.</item></list></item>
<item>CHECK YOU SURROUNDINGS
<list type="unordered"><item>Do you have a garden or a backyard? You need to have a a place for your pet ot wander around so it would not feel like a prison in its cage. Locking it in its cage or tying it in a leash everyday can make your pet depressed and it would make him feel like their in a prison rather than a Home.</item></list></item>
<item>ASK YOURSELF
<list type="unordered"><item>Do you have enough money to provide the needs of your pet? If youre still a student, i would suggest you to buy a pet that needs less attention. Like a Cat for example since it needs less food and can wander around the house without its own cage and shelter and of course it can eat anything in your house.</item>
<item>Do you have Time? “If you are too busy or not at home enough, it’s not appropriate to bring a pet into the mix,” says Bernardine Cruz, DVM, one of the veterinarians in WebMD’s pet health community. All things need Time and if youre too busy you need to give some time if you want to adopt a pet.</item>
<item>Can You Afford a Pet? Along with time commitment, money can be a major factor in owning an animal.“It doesn’t always mean spending a lot, but if you don’t have the discretionary income, then having a pet may not be the best idea right now,” says veterinarian Greg.The first expense: the pet itself. An animal can be as cheap as free, but certain prized breeds could cost thousands of dollars.</item></list></item>
<item>AGE (YOUR AND YOUR PET'S) MATTERS
<list type="unordered"><item>When considering a pet, ask yourself this question: “What am I going to be doing in 10 years?” Will you have gone off to college? Will you be retired? Moved into assisted living?When people adopt pets, they often fail to consider their long-range plans.</item></list></item>
<item>DO YOUR HOMEWORK
<list type="unordered"><item>Knowing what you’re looking for in a pet can save a lot of heartache and headache for both pet and owner.</item>
<item>There are plenty of resources to help you figure out if you’re ready and, if so - what kind of animal you should go for.</item></list></item>
<item>TALK TO AN EXPERT
<list type="unordered"><item>Talk to a veterinarian. A vet will probably ask you if you have a lot of kids in the house, which might mean you need a sturdier breed of animal. And, what are your expectations -- are you looking for a dog that can go jogging and hiking with you every weekend, or just one that’s going to cuddle at the foot of your bed? Other questions: How big is your yard? Does anyone in your home have allergies? Do you want a calm companion, or a peppy animal who lives to play chase with you?Based on these types of issues, a vet can suggest an animal to fit your lifestyle.Books and web sites can also give you a good understanding of different animals and breeds, including grooming and health issues to anticipate.Visiting a shelter, pet store, a dog show, or even talking to a breeder are other smart ways to better understand what kind of size, attitude, and breed best suits you.</item></list></item>
<item>WHY?
<list type="unordered"><item>Why? That is the question. Why would you want a pet? Why do you suddenly want to Buy a pet? Do you Love animals? If you just want to buy a pet because everyone else is doing it, wrong answer mate. Thats not how it works. Like i said earlier Adopting a pet offers a great responsibility. and if youre going to adopt a Cute Puppy, think of it. If it grows up. it will not be as cute and cuddly anymore. and if thats just what you want for a pet,I suggest you might as well just buy a Stuffed Animal.</item></list></item>
<item>YOURE READY
<list type="unordered"><item>Having a critter companion can be good for your health, too. Studies have shown being around an animal can ease depression, lower blood pressure and stress, and keep you active. Heart attack patients who have a dog can live longer than those who don’t. So, i salute you for wanting to have a pet cause youre trying to take care of someone else other than yourself. and if you think youre truly ready and you want it badly. You can adopt a pet.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
