<text id="autogum_whow_doc414" title="Deal with Sharing a Birthday with Someone Else" shortTile="deal-sharing-birthday" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2016-01-23" dateModified="2018-12-11" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Deal-with-Sharing-a-Birthday-with-Someone-Else" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Deal with Sharing a Birthday with Someone Else</head><p>Few people like having to share the limelight and it's even worse on a special day. This article contains some advice about having to share your birthday with someone else.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Embrace the joint celebration. If you share a birthday with one of your friends, it's not necessarily a bad thing. Accept that it's not just your special day, now you can share your happiness with someone else! You could consider having a joint <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Throw_a_Successful_Party">party</ref> if you have a lot of mutual friends. It might keep down the costs for both of you if you're on a budget.  <figure rend="Get Your Girlfriend a Great Birthday Present Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Schedule your celebrations so they don't clash. If you and the other person are both planing parties and you are worried about who will attend which party, don't have your parties on the same day. If you are friends, you get to celebrate twice! One of you can have your party the day or week after, or on the closest Friday or Saturday night if your shared birthday is a week day. <figure rend="Give Your Girlfriend an Unforgettable Birthday Step 3 Version 3.jpg"></figure>.</item>
<item>Try <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Stop_Being_Jealous">not to be jealous</ref> about anything to do with the other person's birthday. Being jealous they are older than you, for example, is just silly! Understand that they might get more presents, more attention, a bigger party, better presents, a huge birthday cake or more birthday cards. Remember that how much people care about you isn't shown by how much you get on your birthday. The other person with a lot of material things, may not have family at home that can't wait to celebrate; hopefully, you do! Their family may be less loving and try to compensate with things, not time, love, attention and good parenting which you will hopefully be enjoying on your birthday.  <figure rend="Handle Haters and Jealous People Step 4 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If the person you share your birthday with makes a big deal about their birthday, gently remind them that it's your birthday too. It's not a special and unique day just for them; you were born on the exact same day!
<list type="unordered"><item>Find out about some famous people that share your birthday too if you like - show the other person that you two aren't the only ones who have a birthday in common.</item></list></item>
<item>If you don't really know the person, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Calm_Down">calm down</ref>. They might not even bother you! Make sure to spend your birthday with the people that you care about, and that care about you too. There's no need to fuss about someone else you barely know having the same date of birth as you. There are about 353,000 babies born every day! No one's birthday is theirs alone. <figure rend="Handle Haters and Jealous People Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Step back if the other person's birthday is a 'big one'. If the other person is turning, 13, 16, 18, 21, 30 or another significant anniversary, and you're not, let them shine. Your turn will come when you reach these milestones. <figure rend="Celebrate Your Birthday Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Distance yourself as needed. If you don't like the person you share a birthday with, try to stay away with your friends. If the person tries bothering you, ignore them, distance yourself from the situation, and if necessary, try telling an adult or supervisor. Try not to be mean, but understand that it's your birthday, and you shouldn't have to spend it around people you don't like any more than is strictly necessary. <figure rend="Stop Being Dramatic Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If they're in your class at school, and everyone pays attention to them instead of you, be gracious and mature. Let them have the spotlight for a little bit. If it gets too much, kindly and subtly remind them that it's your birthday too.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Avoid your birthday sharer if you need to.</item>
<item>Don't act like it's all about you. Understand that the other person has feelings.</item>
<item>Don't be prissy when people greet you with a happy birthday. Be grateful, and say thank you.</item>
<item>You could even swap presents if you each get something you don't want as much as the other person's gift. Be careful not to offend the people who gave the gifts.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Even your closest friends may become irritated with you if you are incapable of dealing with the totally harmless situation of having been born on the same day as someone else. Don't get labelled a drama queen.</item></list>
</text>
