<text id="autogum_whow_doc182" title="Not Feel Alone in Your Opinion" shortTile="feel-alone-opinion" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-02-19" dateModified="2018-09-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Not-Feel-Alone-in-Your-Opinion" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Not Feel Alone in Your Opinion</head><p>Have you ever felt like you have an opinion on something, but nobody else seems to agree with you? Do you feel alienated and unconfident as a result of this? A few simple tips should help! </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Analyze your opinion. How and why did you form this opinion, why do you feel so strongly about it, and why do you feel alienated for having it? This first step is important, because once you pinpoint exactly why your opinion is so important to you, it may become easier for you to learn how to deal with your problem. <figure rend="Not Feel Alone in Your Opinion Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Think of the number of people in the world. There are well over 7 billion people on the planet, and it is very unlikely that your opinion on something is unique. It is almost certain that there is at least one other person alive today that shares your opinion. <figure rend="Not Feel Alone in Your Opinion Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Go onto Google and type in how you feel about something. To make for a better search, only use the most important keywords. You should hopefully find at least one website which features an opinion piece submitted by someone that matches yours. <figure rend="Not Feel Alone in Your Opinion Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you find a lot of websites like this, this can mean an excellent boost of self-confidence for you, as you may realise that you were not as alone as you thought you were.</item>
<item>From here, you can do extra research on the topic you have an opinion about. Read as many websites as you can in order for you to understand and possibly accept each side to the argument, as well as the history and development of the opinion topic.</item></list></item>
<item>Make an opinion collage. This involves taking screenshots of the opinions you find online on things and pasting them into a Microsoft Paint document. <figure rend="Not Feel Alone in Your Opinion Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>It can be very handy to have an archive of paragraphs that you agree with, because when you feel alone once again, you can always view your opinion collage to remind yourself that there are people out there that agree with you.</item>
<item>Alternatively, you can add webpages featuring opinions you agree with, to your favourites for quick reference.</item></list></item>
<item>Join a website, such as a forum, based upon the topic you have an opinion of (i.e. music, television, religion, politics). Here, you can start a thread where you can discuss your opinion and why you feel strongly about it. Hopefully, you will find that there are people who feel the same way and agree. And if no-one agrees, it is still good to give your viewpoint regardless. If it is unique, it may interest and fascinate people. <figure rend="Not Feel Alone in Your Opinion Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Smile">Smile</ref> with satisfaction. It always feels good to know that there are others out there who feel the same way you do about something important to you, and this can be very reassuring. <figure rend="Not Feel Alone in Your Opinion Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Remember that it is good to have an unpopular opinion. It is all too easy to jump on the bandwagon and let others choose your opinion for you, so feel proud to have a viewpoint that differs from the norm. It shows you have an analytical mind.</item>
<item>When making an opinion collage, make sure to only crop the most important parts of what you find. That way, reading and referring to it becomes a lot easier.</item>
<item>Do not feel like your opinion on something is wrong if you find no one else who agrees with you. Your opinion is your opinion, and that is all that matters in the end. You should not let an opinion define you as a person or make you feel inferior for having it.</item>
<item>If you post your opinion on something online and someone responds negatively to it, do not argue with that person. Arguing on the Internet is a waste of time, and could cost you a bad reputation.</item></list>
</text>
