<text id="autogum_whow_doc673" title="Create a Fitness Goal" shortTile="create-fitness-goal" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-02-20" dateModified="2019-06-12" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Create-a-Fitness-Goal" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Create a Fitness Goal</head><p>Many individuals struggle to create and commit to a fitness goal, we lose motivation and forget the reason we make them. This article has 12 steps to determining a workout plan based on factors such as your current state and where you want to be.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Determine your body type. Being able to identify your body is important because a physical structure or genetic makeup may respond differently to certain workout, routine, or diet changes. Your body type shouldn't limit you to what you can and can't workout, it just gives you a better idea of how your body might respond. The three body types include:
<list type="unordered"><item>Ectomorph - lean and long, with difficulty building muscle.</item>
<item>Endomorph - big, high body fat, with a high tendency to store body fat.</item>
<item>Mesomorph - muscular and well-built, with a high metabolism and responsive muscle cell.</item></list></item>
<item>Determine your own health and family history. Understanding your own health, including your family background of illnesses or diseases, can help you determine the type/amount of exercise you need to reduce the risk of disease.
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, your heart rate and blood pressure are popular factors to look at. If your blood pressure and heart rate are high, you may look into more aerobic exercises. High blood pressure and heart rate can eventually decreases with physical exercise, which reduces your risk of disease.</item></list></item>
<item>Determine your current abilities. Determining a starting point is very important in this process. When beginning your fitness routine, it is important not to do more than what your body can handle. If your body is not used to a large amount of physical activity, you can be more prone to injury or muscle soreness. This is a distraction and can lead to failure of your goal, it could potentially stop you from continuing/finishing your goal.</item>
<item>Choose a goal. Based on the information you have gathered about yourself, you should put together a reasonable goal for yourself. I suggest using "SMART" goal setting. SMART starts for specific, measurable, attainable, relevant, and timely. Setting a SMART goal allows you to gain control through structure and traceability, physically writing it down makes your goal official and seeing your accomplishments/progress will motivate you to keep at it.</item>
<item>Determine your lifestyle. Once you have chosen a goal for yourself, you need to take a look at your habits and daily schedule. Decide how you are going to find time to complete your workout so you are able to succeed. Again, physically looking at a calendar can also help plan your schedule and motivate you to stick to it.
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, some individuals have a busy schedule, analyzing your daily schedule allows you to find time to exercise.</item></list></item>
<item>Determine a budget. Depending on your goal, whether that be to gain muscle, tone your body, or to lose weight, some activity requires equipment. Determining a budget allows you to pick how you are going to workout. A budget also allowed you to achieve a long-term goal, planning and being smart with your money is an important step in this process.
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, you could buy a gym membership, purchase exercise equipment for you house, or find body weight/alternative exercises (such as biking, swimming, running, etc).</item></list></item>
<item>Choose a social setting. A specific workout setting encourages you to become motivated to workout, whether that be with a partner, a group, or a trainer. It can push you to perform with more intensity and become better. For some, competition or instruction influences performance. Another option also includes being by yourself, some individuals prefer it.</item>
<item>Choose a type of activity. The type of activity you choose to perform is dependent on your goal, budget, and social setting. Types of activity include:
<list type="unordered"><item>Aerobic - continuous movement.</item>
<item>Strength - increase muscle power and strength.</item>
<item>Calisthenics - basic body movements done without gym equipment and at a medium aerobic pace.</item>
<item>High-Intensity Interval Training (HIIT) - includes repetitions of short bursts of high-intensity exercise followed by low-intensity exercises or rest periods.</item>
<item>Boot Camps - time-based, high-intensity circuits that combine aerobic and resistance exercises.</item>
<item>Balance and Stability - strengthens muscles and improves body coordination.</item>
<item>Flexibility - aides muscle recovery, maintains range of motion and prevents injuries.</item></list></item>
<item>Choose your environment. Once you have decided on a type of activity and your social setting, secure a location or an environment within your budget. Your environment should supply you with appropriate materials/equipment you need. Most importantly, your environment should make you feel comfortable. Appropriate environments include:
<list type="unordered"><item>Gym.</item>
<item>Home.</item>
<item>Outdoors.</item></list></item>
<item>Create a schedule. Designing a schedule allows you to be reminded of your goal and how you are going to reach it. Your schedule should consist of when, where, and what:
<list type="unordered"><item>When am I going to perform my physical activity? (Time with a specific day).</item>
<item>Where am I going to perform my physical activity?</item>
<item>What am I going to do? (Figure out the kind of activity and create a workout routine).</item></list></item>
<item>Commit. Committing is the most important phase of this process. Signing up for any memberships, creating a physical layout of your schedule, and attending your workouts can help finalize and allow your to fully commit to your goal. Commitment proves to yourself and others that you are invested. The hardest step to completing your goal is to commit.</item>
<item>Reflect and keep track of your progress. Reflecting is a great tool to look back and see what worked and what didn't. It is an easy tool to use to be able to detect failure and work off of that in order to achieve success. It can help improve your psychological health and increase your overall motivation.
<list type="unordered"><item>Writing in a journal is a good example of keeping track and reflecting, it allows you to view your progress numerically and to express your emotions.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
