<text id="autogum_whow_doc402" title="Paint Cleanly" shortTile="paint-cleanly" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-06-10" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Paint-Cleanly" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Paint Cleanly</head><p>You can transform a room with a simple paint job, but painting can be messy and leave stains. Careful preparations can help you avoid spillage and paint splatter. If you want to paint cleanly, follow these tips.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Protect the area you want to paint. Preparation is an important part of your plan to paint cleanly. You should take certain steps each time you paint to reduce the chance of mishaps. <figure rend="Paint Cleanly Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Spread heavy drop cloths over the entire floor area. Don't substitute plastic covering to protect floors; it tends to bunch up when walked on.</item>
<item>Move lighter furniture out of the room you're painting.</item>
<item>Move heavy furniture to the center of the room and cover it completely with plastic covering.</item>
<item>Remove all wall decorations and area rugs.</item>
<item>Take down curtains and curtain rods.</item>
<item>Use masking tape to protect the trim and windows, door frames and baseboards. Also tape off fixtures that you can't remove.</item>
<item>Remove wall plates from electrical outlets and light switches.</item>
<item>Keep the area around the surface you're painting clear of all obstructions.</item></list></item>
<item>Paint with care. You can take steps to greatly reduce the number of accidental spills. These steps differ depending on the method you use to paint. <figure rend="Paint Cleanly Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Roll off excess paint on the roller grid. Drops of paint can go unnoticed and set in on surfaces.</item>
<item>Don't allow the roller to spin after each stroke. Spinning rollers often splatter paint in all directions.</item>
<item>Use a can roller grid instead of a separate pan. Grids that attach inside the paint can reduce paint splatter and also eliminate the need for pans. Pans tip over easily and people may accidentally step in them.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Painting With an Airless Sprayer</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Use care when painting near ceilings or windows. Airless sprayers don't use compressors. A pump forces the paint through a high-pressure hose and out the nozzle. Although they produce less overspray than a compressed air sprayer, an airless sprayer will produce paint mist that can travel on air currents to areas you don't want to paint. <figure rend="Paint Cleanly Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Reduce spillage. <figure rend="Paint Cleanly Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Use a nail to punch a hole in the rim of the paint can. Paint tends to collect on the rim of the can after it's been poured. When the lid is closed, paint seeps outside the can. Creating the hole in the rim allows the paint drip back into the can.</item>
<item>Place the lid back on the paint can, drape a cloth over the can and tap the lid down with a hammer. This keeps excess paint from splattering as you tightly close the lid.</item></list></item>
<item>Clean up paint spills immediately. Accidents will happen, but their effects can be ameliorated if you act quickly. <figure rend="Paint Cleanly Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Oil-based Paints</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Hard floor and carpets. <figure rend="Paint Cleanly Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Spill on hard floor: Dampen paper towels with mineral spirits and blot the spill before it dries.</item>
<item>Spill on carpeting: Use the same method as you would use on a hard floor. It is important to have mineral spirits or paint thinner available beforehand when working with oil-based paints.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Water-based Paints</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Hard floor and carpets. <figure rend="Paint Cleanly Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Spill on hard floor: Use damp paper towels to sop up the spill.</item>
<item>Spill on carpeting: Position paper towels around the spill. Drench the stain with water and soak up the mixture with clean paper towels. Continue to douse and blot the stained area until the towels show no sign of color. Consider using a carpet-cleaning product to remove the last remnants of paint.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Drop cloths</item>
<item>Plastic covering</item>
<item>Masking tape</item>
<item>Can roller grid</item>
<item>Hammer and nail</item>
<item>Mineral spirits or water</item>
<item>Paper towels</item></list>
</text>
