<text id="autogum_whow_doc072" title="Have Fun Paddle Boating" shortTile="fun-paddle-boating" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-08-02" dateModified="2018-09-24" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Have-Fun-Paddle-Boating" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Have Fun Paddle Boating</head><p>Are you going paddle Boating? Think it's going to be <hi rend="bold">boring</hi>? Don't worry, this article will show you how to have a fun and memorable time.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find a park or lake that rents out paddle boats. If you own a paddle boat, skip this step. Before renting one check the place you're renting out from in advance. Check for ducks (they can carry swimmer's itch), dead fish, etc. Check the paddle boats to make sure they're not falling apart and are in good condition. <figure rend="Have Fun Paddle Boating Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find friends or loved ones to go with! It's never fun to paddle boat alone. Talk to them about their schedules, and when they're open. Consider splitting the price. Tell them what they need to bring - bathing suit, towels, sunscreen, etc. <figure rend="Have Fun Paddle Boating Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Before going paddle boating, gather the supplies you'll need. Water bottles, towels, etc. Make sure to bring more than you need in case someone's forgotten to bring it. Go and pick up your friends and or loved ones and drive to your destination! <figure rend="Have Fun Paddle Boating Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>When you get there, have one person pay for renting or place your boat near the water. It's generally considered polite for you to do this. Now get dressed and put on some sun screen. <figure rend="Have Fun Paddle Boating Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Choose the two people that are going to be paddling first. Decide how you're going to rotate through the seats. Let the people sitting in the back go first, then the paddlers. <figure rend="Have Fun Paddle Boating Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have the people in the front back up and head for the <hi rend="bold">middle</hi> of the lake. If you're the people in the back, look for fish, go leach searching, let your feet drag in the water, just have <hi rend="italic">fun</hi>! Soon you'll be paddling, so enjoy the time that you have to kick back and relax! <figure rend="Have Fun Paddle Boating Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Switch every every ten minutes or so, and stay fair. An argument would ruin your boating trip. If you're the person in the front, ask everybody where they want to go. If there are children on the boat, pretend you're a pirate captain, and say things like "Land ho!" or other pirate sayings. <figure rend="Have Fun Paddle Boating Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Chat! Even if your paddling. if you don't know what to say, say something like, "Isn't it hot out?" or "How was it at work today?" However, make sure to let everybody talk, so no one feels left out. <figure rend="Have Fun Paddle Boating Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If possible, bring a <hi rend="bold">waterproof</hi> camera with you. You can make a scrapbook! If you don't have a <hi rend="italic">waterproof</hi> camera with you, don't bring it. If you drop it, and it's not waterproof, it will break and possibly sink. <figure rend="Have Fun Paddle Boating Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have fun paddle boating! <figure rend="Have Fun Paddle Boating Step 10.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always wear a life jacket, even if you can swim. In some places it isn't legal to paddle boat without a life jacket, and it's safer anyway.</item>
<item>If someone wants to stop paddling, let them walk out of the boat. <hi rend="bold">Never</hi> move the boat when their walking, or they'll fall in and might be hurt or upset.</item>
<item>Make sure you tell somebody where you're going first just in case something happens.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">Always</hi> keep a close eye on children.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Never</hi> bring any electronics with you, unless they're waterproof.</item></list>
</text>
