<text id="autogum_whow_doc242" title="Create a Targeted Advertisement on Facebook and Instagram" shortTile="create-targeted-advertisement" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-02-07" dateModified="2019-01-21" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Create-a-Targeted-Advertisement-on-Facebook-and-Instagram" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Create a Targeted Advertisement on Facebook and Instagram</head>Advertising is the best way to display and deliver products and services to the right people. What better way of advertising is there than through social media, particularly Facebook which has 1.86 billion active users and Instagram with 800 million active users. Since Instagram is owned by Facebook, advertising on both simultaneously is a seamless process.
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Setting up the Campaign</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><figure rend="Capture433.jpg"></figure> Click on the link titled ads from the Facebook.com dashboard. This will load the Facebook Ads Manager.</item>
<item>Press close in the left tab. You could technically start creating the ads from here. However, for simplicity's sake, we'll start the ad creating process in a more efficient way.  <figure rend="Capture3FB.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on the <hi rend="bold">Campaigns</hi> tab if it isn't displayed by default. Then click on <hi rend="italic">Create Campaign.</hi> <figure rend="Capture5FB.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Name your advertisement and select the campaign objective. This will decide how the ad's funds will be spent and will help you keep track of your advertisement campaign. Once you're done, click on <hi rend="italic">save to draft.</hi> <figure rend="Capture6FB.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can create a generic name for your advertisement. This will not be displayed publicly so don't worry about it.</item>
<item>Here you can also select the campaign objective. By default Facebook has selected gaining traffic. This is the most optimal form of advertising but it is important to select whichever one fits your needs. You can change this later.</item></list></item>
<item>Select your country, currency, and time zone under the tab: Ad Account.</item></list>
<head>Beginning the Advertisement</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Click on the dashboard select the tab titled <hi rend="bold">Ads.</hi>, and click on <hi rend="bold">Create Ad.</hi> <figure rend="Capture7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select the campaign you have created under <hi rend="bold">Use Existing'<hi rend="italic">. Then, select </hi></hi><hi rend="italic">Use Guided Creation.</hi> if the option appears. Otherwise, just move on.</item>
<item>Select the marketing objective. There are three broad categories to choose from, select the one relevant to your goal. At this point, the one you chose will determine the structure of your advertisement. Once done, select <hi rend="italic">Continue.</hi> <figure></figure></item></list>
<head>Creating the Ad Set and Targeting an Audience</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Choose where you want your advertisement traffic will be driven.<figure></figure></item>
<item>Under the <hi rend="bold">Audience</hi> section, select who you will see your advertisement done, which is achieved through Facebook's advertising algorithm.<figure></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Custom Audience</hi> is used to target individual users by their username from outside sources such as a third party website. This is mainly for large companies.</item></list></item>
<item>Under <hi rend="bold">Locations</hi>, choose where your advertisement is displayed. You can select multiple towns, cities, states/provinces, and countries.<figure></figure></item>
<item>Select the age range of users that will see your advertisement as well as the gender of these users.<figure></figure></item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Detailed Targeting</hi> is the most important aspect of a well-designed advertisement. Here you can select from a near infinite amount of subgroups you want to see your advertisements, each demographic will also display how many users fall under the category. You can also exclude certain demographics.<figure></figure></item>
<item>You can click <hi rend="bold">Save This Audience</hi> so you don't accidentally lose your progress.<figure></figure></item>
<item>Under Placements select the option <hi rend="bold">Edit Placements</hi>. Here you can select where on Facebook and Instagram your advertisement will appear.<figure></figure></item>
<item>Under <hi rend="bold">Budget and Schedule</hi> you can decide how much you want to spend on your advertisement daily. The more money you spend the more users will be projected to see your advertisement, but there's no guarantee that that amount will see it daily.<figure></figure></item>
<item>Once done, select <hi rend="bold">Continue</hi></item></list>
<head>Creating the Displayed Advertisement for Facebook and Instagram</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>For <hi rend="bold">Identity</hi> select the Facebook page you created that you want displayed with the ad.<figure></figure></item>
<item>Under <hi rend="bold">Format</hi> and Imaged you can choose whether you want one image, multiple images, or a video displayed as your visual advertisement.<figure></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Upload an image you wish to be displayed in your advertisement.</item>
<item>You can upload up to six photos that will be displayed.</item></list></item>
<item>Under the <hi rend="bold">Links</hi> section you will decide what headline and description you want displayed with the picture(s)/video. Be original, but most importantly, draft something that will grab the attention of your audience. <figure rend="Capture20.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Here you also paste the link you want your advertisement to go to. This can be a product, a website, an affiliate marketing link, another social media account, etc.</item>
<item>As you finish up your advertisement, an example of your ad will start to render in the left panel.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Finishing Moves</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Link a payment method that Facebook will charge monthly (until it is canceled).</item>
<item>Before your advertisement goes live, Facebook will first analyze it for errors, false advertising, or for violating their terms of service. This usually won't take longer than a day. <figure rend="Capture21.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Facebook account</item>
<item>Facebook page</item>
<item>Debit or credit card with enough balance to pay for a one time or recurring payment</item></list>
<head>Video</head>
</text>
