<text id="autogum_whow_doc227" title="Get a CKYC Number" shortTile="ckyc-number" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-01-09" dateModified="2019-09-14" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get-a-CKYC-Number" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get a CKYC Number</head><p>A Central Know Your Customer (CKYC) number is required by law in India if you plan to invest in mutual funds or other financial assets. Having a CKYC number will show financial regulators that you are a legitimate investor and help to verify your identity. The process for getting a CKYC number is relatively easy and once you have it, you do not need to apply for it again. With a few key personal documents and the right information on the application form, you can get your CKYC number and start investing right away.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Applying for a CKYC Number</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Download and print the CKYC application form. Access the application form here: <ref target="https://www.sebi.gov.in/sebi_data/commondocs/KYC_ApplForm_p.pdf">https://www.sebi.gov.in/sebi_data/commondocs/KYC_ApplForm_p.pdf</ref>. You can also get a copy of the form through your financial broker or mutual funds provider. <figure rend="Get a CKYC Number Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Provide basic personal information on the form. You will need to provide your full name, as well as your father’s or spouse's full name. You will also need to list your date of birth, your gender,  your occupations, and your marital status. <figure rend="Get a CKYC Number Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You will also need to note your citizenship level and your residential status.</item></list></item>
<item>Include your Permanent Account Number. Your PAN is a 10-digit number given to you by the federal Income Tax Department. You can apply for a PAN if you do not already have one through the government’s Income Tax Department. <figure rend="Get a CKYC Number Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Provide proof of identity and address information. You will need to list at least 1 of the following for the proof of identity section and the proof of address section: your passport number and the expiry date, your driver’s license number and the expiry date, your voter ID card number, or an AADHAR card number. <figure rend="Get a CKYC Number Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You will also need to provide copies of your passport or driver’s license to prove your identity and address. You may need to provide the originals of your passport and your driver’s license, if requested during the application process.</item></list></item>
<item>Include a recent passport size photograph of yourself. The photograph should be well-lit and standard passport size, which is  in India. You can get a passport photograph taken at a local photography studio or at a passport services kiosk. <figure rend="Get a CKYC Number Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Submit the completed form to your broker or mutual funds provider. Sign the signature line on the form. Then, bring the completed form, the passport size photograph, and a copy of your passport or driver’s license to your financial representative. They can then process your application properly. <figure rend="Get a CKYC Number Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can also go to a local financial registrar office in your area to submit the application.</item></list></item>
<item>Provide a completed investment application form, if required by your broker. Some financial representatives require you to also submit an investment application, where you specify which investments you would like to pursue once you receive your CKYC number. This will help them to get a sense of how you plan to use your CKYC number and to analyze your finances in detail. <figure rend="Get a CKYC Number Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Ask your broker for an investment application form that you can complete.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Receiving and Using Your CKYC Number</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Wait up to 2 weeks for your application to process. You cannot pursue any investments legally until your application is approved. However, you can discuss possible investments and mutual funds you are interested in with your financial broker or advisor while you wait. <figure rend="Get a CKYC Number Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get your 14-digit CKYC number by email or text message. Once your application is approved, you will receive an email or a text message that lists your CKYC number. The message will appear as: “Your KYC details have been registered with Central KYC Registry. Your CKYC identifier is 10088756711997.” <figure rend="Get a CKYC Number Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>After you have saved the CKYC number in a safe place, delete the email or text message so your number cannot be stolen. A stolen CKCY number can lead to identity fraud, as others can try to use your number to make investments.</item></list></item>
<item>Apply again if your application is rejected. If your application is rejected, you may have failed to provide the proper documentation. You can apply again for the number by filling out the application form again and following the proper guidelines. Make sure you double check your documentation to ensure your application is approved. <figure rend="Get a CKYC Number Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can also talk to your financial broker or advisor for guidance to ensure your application is approved on your second try.</item></list></item>
<item>Use your CKYC number to invest in mutual funds and other financial products. Having a CKYC number will allow you to invest your money through a broker or a financial advisor. Providing your CKYC number on financial applications and forms will streamline the process. <figure rend="Get a CKYC Number Step 11.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
