<text id="autogum_whow_doc536" title="Teach Disabled People to Take Care of a Pet" shortTile="teach-disabled-people" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-12-16" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Teach-Disabled-People-to-Take-Care-of-a-Pet" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Teach Disabled People to Take Care of a Pet</head><p>Pets make great friends for anyone, especially people who have difficulty relating to others.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Considering Whether to Get a Pet</head>
<p>Not all people with disabilities are able to care for pets. Carefully consider the person and their situation when making a decision about whether to buy a pet, and what type of pet to buy.</p>
<list type="ordered"><item>Notice how the person interacts with other animals. If they are afraid of animals, then a pet is probably not a good idea. If they respond positively to animals, and know how to be gentle, then a pet might be a good idea.
<list type="unordered"><item>Getting over a fear of animals takes time and care. A pet should only be gotten once the person is pretty comfortable around animals.</item>
<item>Extremely fearful people might become afraid of a pet if they have a bad experience.</item></list></item>
<item>Consider how rough or gentle a disabled child is. A child that breaks toys or hits others is not ready for a pet. They may upset the pet and get scratched or bitten.
<list type="unordered"><item>Some disabled children are very tough. Because hitting doesn't hurt them, they don't realize that it hurts others. They need someone to explain this to them, and to set rules.</item></list></item>
<item>Consider whether the disabled person understands personal space. If they don't, they may upset the pet, and get bitten/scratched. The disabled person should be able to set boundaries (and have others listen to those boundaries), and should know how to respect others' boundaries.
<list type="unordered"><item>Does the disabled person respect other people's boundaries? If so, they will probably respect a pet's boundaries.</item>
<item>Do other people routinely violate the disabled person's boundaries (including personal space)? If so, the disabled person will think it's okay to violate boundaries.</item>
<item>Is the person in compliance therapy? If so, they may not realize that people and animals are allowed to set boundaries, much less that these boundaries need to be honored.</item></list></item>
<item>Evaluate the person's self-care abilities. If they struggle to take care of themselves, then they may not be able to handle a pet. Don't put extra responsibilities on an overtaxed person. Alternatively, if they are handling things well, and they say they could handle a pet, then they are probably ready.
<list type="unordered"><item>Consider how much care other household members can contribute. For example, if a disabled girl's dad is willing to clean up after it, her brother will feed it, and her sister will walk it, then she may not need to be responsible for it.</item>
<item>Talk to them, and see how much care they might think they would be able to handle.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Teaching the Disabled Person</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Talk about personal space and pets. Just like people, pets have personal space and don't always want to play or be petted. Encourage the person to pay attention to the pet's body language, and to leave the pet alone if it wants to be alone.
<list type="unordered"><item>Encourage the person to call a pet by holding out their hand and/or making kissy sounds. Explain that if the pet wants to come, it will come. Otherwise, it wants alone time, so let it be.</item></list></item>
<item>Explain how to avoid scaring a pet. Pets have slightly different social norms than people do, so it's important that all household members learn how to interact appropriately with a pet.
<list type="unordered"><item>Be gentle.</item>
<item>Never sneak up on a pet.</item>
<item>Use your indoor voice. Don't shout or scream at a pet.</item>
<item>Leave a sleeping pet alone.</item>
<item>Don't chase a pet. If a pet walks or runs away and wants to be alone, don't pester it.</item>
<item>Don't tease or take away a toy the pet is playing with.</item>
<item>Leave the pet alone when it is eating.</item></list></item>
<item>Explain how to tell if a pet wants to be alone. Different animals</item>
<item>Encourage the person to help with feeding/walking the pet. Teach them how to fill the pet's bowl and store the food. If teaching about dogs, especially show them to never let a dog off of the leash, unless in a secured area. Walking and feeding pets is an important bonding experience.</item>
<item>Teach the person how to tell if a pet is angry. Tell them that growling/hissing are signs of anger, and to slowly walk away. Also, show the person not to touch the food bowl while they're eating, or take a toy away. Tell them to never pull a pets tail.</item>
<item>Teach the person how to pet an animal gently. Show them how to rub a dog's belly, or pet a cat's ears.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Have patience.</item>
<item>Don't force the person to help if they're afraid/upset.</item>
<item>Have the disabled person give treats to the new pet. This will help the pet like them.</item></list>
</text>
