<text id="autogum_whow_doc396" title="Do Spring Flowers in Puff Paint and Watercolors" shortTile="spring-flowers-puff" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-04-12" dateModified="2019-09-08" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Do-Spring-Flowers-in-Puff-Paint-and-Watercolors" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Do Spring Flowers in Puff Paint and Watercolors</head><p>Tulips, daffodils, hyacinths and other flowers know when it is time to spring onto the scene and enliven the outdoors.  The beautiful, delicate flowers announce that warm days have arrived.  This art project encourages “topsy-turvy tulips,”  “dancing daffodils” and “hip-hopping hyacinths”---all of them determined to make the blank page their stage.  Puff paint is an easy drawing medium and watercolors can flow fast to cover big areas of the paper.  What a fun way to cure the woes of winter and spread joy to the doer---and the viewer.</p>
<head>Steps =</head>
<head>Preparing and Drawing</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Prepare your supplies.  Open a pad of any size 140 lb. watercolor paper and give the page stability by keeping it attached to the binding.  Open a box of watercolors, wet each pad of color and set it aside.  Have at least a small, round, pointed brush, a bigger round brush and a ½ inch flat brush.  You will also need a pencil, water container and tissues to mop of excess water.</item>
<item>Purchase a colorful array of puff paints.  They are readily available at the craft or discount store.  If you haven’t tried them, experiment doing lines on scrap paper by squeezing the paint through the dispenser top.  You will quickly learn that they take a little time to dry so you will need to keep your hands from rubbing through and smearing a wet area.  A hairdryer will hasten the wait time for drying.</item>
<item>Draw some common spring flowers lightly. in pencil, on your watercolor paper.  Try a tulip, daffodil, hyacinth, daisy, dandelion, pansy, petunia, etc.  Do them different sizes and at many angles so they look as though they are dancing over the page.  Don’t forget to add the leaves to each flower.</item></list>
<head>Painting</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Draw over the lines with puff paints.  Soon you will gain confidence and you won’t even have to draw the guide lines first.  Let your flowers gain new personalities by keeping the drawing loose and rhythmic.  Use the hairdryer often to make sure the flowers are completely dry to avoid smearing them as you continue to work.  When satisfied with how it looks, prop up the paper and stand back.</item>
<item>Think how you might finish the work.  Will you link the flowers with watercolor shapes and lines?  You can also use the watercolors to fill in the flowers and leaves or simply to draw more flowers.  Might you add directional arrows or numbers?  Footprints?  Let you imagination go free and when you have decided, start painting with your watercolors.</item>
<item>Finish the background.  You could just paint the flowers and use a green line to string them all together.  You could do the entire background in appropriate colors.  You could paint an abstract background of colors and shapes.  You could paint a fence around the flowers. You could bring in clouds and pieces of blue sky. The possibilities are endless.  Do the watercolor painting part of this project to the point where you are happy with it.  Allow the piece to dry.  Evaluate it and punch up areas that need it.</item></list>
<head>Extending the Activity</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Try the lesson again.  Turn to a fresh piece of paper, but this time, set a whole new plan into action.  Keeping spring flowers as your theme, think about how you might do them differently.  Perhaps this time, make the flowers more realistic and put them in a garden setting.  Put the flowers in pots and have them in a sunny window.  Use you imagination and try to make this art piece very different and perhaps more formally organized than the last one.</item>
<item>Make wearable art.  Before putting this project behind you, go out and purchase a plain white t-shirt.  Use the puff paints to, once again, draw flowers.  This time use other colors of puff paint to fill in the blossoms and leaves.  This paint is designed to work on cotton fabrics.  (Be warned, though, save the watercolors for work on paper.)  Wear your art piece as you go through your day, knowing that you have brought the flowers front and center for all to see and enjoy.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>The key to this project is the energy captured in the drawing of the flowers.  Bear in mind that the flowers are trying to show their happiness at surprising us by blooming. Imagine that they take great pride in making people happy.</item>
<item>If you make a wrong line or mark with puff paints, there is no removing it, so try to incorporate it into your design.  A mistake can sometimes open a new direction of thought and make something better than it might have otherwise been.  In other words, embrace your mistakes and strive to turn them into success.</item></list>
</text>
