<text id="autogum_whow_doc275" title="Make Chor Muang" shortTile="make-chor-muang" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-03-08" dateModified="2019-07-27" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-Chor-Muang" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make Chor Muang</head><p>Chor Muang is very delicious and a portion of colorful food. Below this, is an amazingly delicious recipe!</p>
<head>Ingredients</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Dough</hi></p>
<p>(Yields 24 dumplings)</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>180g wheat starch</item>
<item>50g tapioca starch</item>
<item>310ml Butterfly pea blue water-boiling, 212F</item>
<item>4 tsp avocado oil</item>
<item>80g chicken thigh</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shrimp Filling</hi></p>
<p>(Boneless, or combination of chicken and seafood, minced)
(Yields 24 dumplings)</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>1 tsp garlic fresh, minced</item>
<item>1/2 tsp white pepper freshly ground</item>
<item>1 tsp coriander stems finely diced</item>
<item>3 tsp palm sugar</item>
<item>2 tsp fish sauce</item>
<item>2 tsp avocado oil</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">Butterfly Pea Blue Water</hi></p>
<p>(Yields 24 dumplings)</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>4 tsp Butterfly pea flowers dry</item>
<item>320ml water-boiling, 212F</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">Serving</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>4 tsp garlic fresh, minced</item>
<item>4 tbsp avocado oil</item>
<item>8 leaves lettuce</item></list>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Making the Wrappers</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>In a teapot, measure 1 tbsp of dry Butterfly Pea flowers and add 1 cup of boiling water.</item>
<item>Steep for about 10-15 minutes. While the tea is steeping, prepare the stuffing and caramelize garlic for serving.</item>
<item>Mix well. In a bowl, mix all wheat starch and 15g of tapioca starch with a whisk. Stir the blue teat and strain, lightly squeezing the flowers in a strainer.</item>
<item>Measure 155ml of blue water into a teacup and bring it to boiling in a microwave. Immediately pour it all at once into the bowl with starches and combine into a paste using chopsticks. Cover the bowl with plastic wrap and let it rest for 5 minutes at room temperature. # Add the rest of tapioca starch and knead the dough until all well combined and soft. Add oil and knead until the blue dough is smooth, soft, and pliable.</item>
<item>Shape the dough into a cylinder 1" D and divide into 12 portions 1" long. Shape each portion into a ball.
<list type="unordered"><item>Keep them covered with a damp towel or plastic wrap to prevent drying.</item></list></item>
<item>Line bamboo baskets with lightly oiled parchment paper. Shape dumpling one by one and place into the baskets. Flatten each portion of dough into a round wrapper.</item>
<item>Place 1 tsp of filling in the center, and shape it into a ball. Using flat tongs, pinch petals.</item>
<item>Steam dumplings for 5-6 minutes over medium heat.</item></list>
<head>Making the Stuffing</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Peel and mince 3 tsp of fresh garlic. Ground white (or black and white) peppercorns. Finely chop cilantro stems.</item>
<item>Mince chicken (and prawns or scallops, if using). Combine 1 tsp of garlic, 1 tsp of cilantro stems, and 1/3 tsp ground pepper and make a paste using a knife or mortar and pestle. Do not mix them. Measure fish sauce and palm sugar.</item>
<item>Heat 2 tsp of oil in a small skillet over medium heat. Saute garlic-cilantro-pepper paste for a few seconds, stirring, until sweet fragrance. Add chicken and stir-fry it for a minute, breaking clumps, until white.</item>
<item>Season with fish sauce and sugar and continue cooking until caramelized, for about 1-2 minutes. Transfer into a small bowl and let cool to the room temperature.</item></list>
<head>Serving</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Heat oil. In a small skillet or saucepan, heat oil over low heat. Add minced or sliced garlic and slowly caramelize it until lightly golden. Strain oil and use for other recipes.</item>
<item>To serve, arrange green leafy vegetables and hot steamed dumplings on the plate and top them with crispy and sweet caramelized garlic.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Butterfly pea flowers used for this recipe came from a family-owned farm in Thailand.</item></list>
</text>
