<text id="autogum_whow_doc650" title="Play Kubb" shortTile="play-kubb" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-04-08" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Play-Kubb" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Play Kubb</head><head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Determine the aim of the game.: The aim of the game of Kubb is for one team to knock over the King after having knocked over all the Kubbs on the opposing side of the pitch. Should a team knock over the King before knocking over all the opposing Kubbs, they lose!step here and then click "Add Step"</item>
<item>Set up the game. The game consists of the following pieces: 1 King 10 Kubbs 6 BATONS 4 Corner Markers The Typical Kubb field is 26 feet long and 16 feet wide. The rectangular Kubbs are set up at each end 1 baton length away from the corners, and then evenly spaced. The  KING is placed in the middle.</item>
<item>Decide how many people can play and who starts?The players are divided into two teams with between 1 and 6 players on each side. You don't have to have the same number of players on each team, but it helps. To choose which team starts, one player from each team stands behind the same base line and they each throw a BATON underarm towards the King. The starting team (Team A) is the team whose stick lands closest to the King without actually touching it.</item>
<item>Learn basic game play.   Team A starts by standing behind their own base line and throwing the six BATONS at the Kubbs lined up on Team B’s base line. The aim is to try to knock over as many of these as possible. The Kubbs lined up on the team's base line are known as Base Kubbs.
<list type="unordered"><item>The BATONS must be held at either end (not in the middle) and thrown underarm and end over end. “Helicopter Throws”, where the BATON is spun horizontally, is NOT allowed.   Once Team A has thrown all its BATONS, Team B takes its turn. Standing behind its base line, Team B throws the Kubbs, knocked over by Team A (if there are any), into Team A’s half of the field, i.e. the area between the King and Team A’s base line and between the Corner  toppled Kubb into the opposing half of the pitch.   </item>
<item>Should any Kubb land outside this area more than once. Team A may place any such Kubb(s) anywhere on their own half of the pitch, but not closer than the length of one BATON from the King or a Corner Marker. Once all the toppled Kubbs have been successfully thrown onto the opposing side of the pitch, Team A stands these up, wherever they have come to rest. These are now known as Field Kubbs.</item></list></item>
<item>Note: Should Team B have failed to knock over all of the Field Kubbs on Team A’s side of the pitch, Team A may stand in line with the Field Kubb closest to the King when throwing the BATON. This does not apply when throwing the Kubbs as these must always be thrown underarm from behind the team's baseline.
<list type="unordered"><item>The game continues in this way with the two teams taking turns until one team knocks over all the Field and Base Kubbs on the opposing side of the pitch. They may then attack the King with any remaining BATONS.  </item>
<item>When attacking the King, the thrower must always stand behind the base line. If the team then succeeds in knocking over the King, that team wins the set. Remember - should a team knock over the King before knocking over all the opposing Kubbs, they lose!</item></list></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Remember, these are wooden Batons and can hurt, so be careful!</item></list>
</text>
