<text id="autogum_whow_doc692" title="Navigate New York City" shortTile="navigate-new-york" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2008-04-22" dateModified="2018-08-04" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Navigate-New-York-City" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Navigate New York City</head><p>Navigating New York City may seem difficult to accomplish. After all, it is one of the world's largest and busiest cities. So if thick crowds, gridlock traffic and loud noises make you uncomfortable, this guide will help you out.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Always have a pocket-sized map of Manhattan with you at all times.</hi> This always comes in handy when you're trying to determine the distance between, say, Wall Street and <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Visit_Times_Square">Times Square</ref>, or if you just want to know exactly where you are. However, looking at a map too frequently will make you <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Avoid_Looking_Like_an_American_Tourist">look like a tourist.</ref> <figure rend="Navigate New York City Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Wear good walking shoes if you plan on walking.</hi> If, however, you plan traveling further distances around the city, buy a Metro card - similar to something like a bus pass but more flexible - that will allow you to take the subway or bus transportation for however long you need at a price you pay when you purchase the card. If you are unsure about the amount left on the Metro Card, slowly slide your Metro Card at a amount checker. These are usually next to a Metro Card machine.
<list type="unordered"><item>Keep in mind that you'll need a receipt as a proof of purchase of an active Metro Card to actually board the bus. <figure rend="Navigate New York City Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Set aside a certain amount of cash for dining, shopping, sightseeing and transportation. This will make organizing your finances much easier and will help you <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Visit_New_York_City_on_a_Budget">avoid overspending</ref>. <figure rend="Navigate New York City Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Know where you are heading to. Don't just stand around in the middle of the sidewalk and gawk at all the tall buildings.</hi> Keep moving, like the rest of the crowd. <figure rend="Navigate New York City Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Buy a MetroCard for access to the subway and bus.</hi>  You can put enough money on the card for all the people in your party or you can buy a weekly pass for yourself. When you're done with the card (if it still has a few rides left on it), give it as a tip to the bellman at your hotel. <figure rend="Navigate New York City Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Buy a ticket for the City Sights Double Decker Sightseeing Bus.</hi> It stops at all the major attractions and landmarks. You can buy a Hop-on Hop-off all day pass to get you to and from all the attractions that you can see in a day.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Only hail a taxi when absolutely necessary.</hi> They tend to be expensive on long distance drives and do charge for waiting at a red light. The best way to get around the city is by bus, subway, or by walking.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">If you don't have a map, most subway stations have one displayed on the wall near the entrance to the station.</hi> Generally, they have a subway map and a local street map. Be sure to look for the Green lamp that signifies that the station entrance is open. A red lamp indicates that the station entrance is closed. A sign should tell you how to get to the station entrance that is open.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Try not to look like a tourist.</hi> This will have a small negative impression among other people.</item></list>
</text>
