<text id="autogum_whow_doc659" title="Play Korfball" shortTile="play-korfball" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-03-21" dateModified="2017-05-05" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Play-Korfball" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Play Korfball</head><p>Korfball, originated in the Netherlands in 1902, is a fun, social and fast-paced ball sport with similarities to basketball and netball that is played by teams of four male and four female players. The objective of the game is to score more goals than your opponent; this is done by shooting the ball through a basket, also known as a 'Korf'.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Have the right equipment. The primary step is making sure you have all the essential things needed to play a game of Korfball. First, you'll want two teams of 8, made up of 4 boys and 4 girls. Next you need somewhere to play, so a Korfball court, indoor or outdoor is a must. Then finally, you have to have a Korfball to play with. <figure rend="Play Korfball Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Position yourself. Before the match starts, players must be in position. Four players, two male and two female of each team are in one zone, and the others play in the other zone. Also at the beginning of the match, one team will choose one end of the court. That end will be their defending zone, with that team's Korf inside it. <figure rend="Play Korfball Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Start the game. Now the game can begin, one team starts the game with a pass from the centre line to kick things off. This happens every time a goal is scored, with the team who just conceded taking the pass. <figure rend="Play Korfball Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Score goals. Teams score by a player shooting the Korfball through the opponents' Korf. Once two goals are scored, the teams swap ends: defenders become attackers and attackers become defenders. In between those zone-changes, defenders cannot step into their attacking zone or vice versa. <figure rend="Play Korfball Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Follow the rules. Always follow the rules of the game. The rules of Korfball stop physical power controlling the match. <figure rend="Play Korfball Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Tackling, holding and blocking are all forbidden, along with kicking the ball.</item>
<item>When a player has the ball, one cannot run, walk or dribble with it, although, one can move one of their feet as long the other foot stays in the same position. Therefore efficient and tactical play between teammates is best, because players will need one another to keep the game flowing.</item>
<item>A player may not attempt to shoot while being defended, which occurs when the defender is between the opponent and the Korf, is facing his or her opponent, is within arm's reach and trying to block the ball.</item></list></item>
<item>Play the correct time. The game is played with two halves of 30 minutes, with a 10 minute 'half time' break. <figure rend="Play Korfball Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Finish. Once the game has ended, the team with the most goals has won! Unless the game has ended with the score level, in which case the game usually goes to overtime where the next goal (Golden Goal) wins. <figure rend="Play Korfball Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Buying a Korfball to practice at home with, can really help your game.</item>
<item>If you are struggling or find it hard, don't give up! You'll get there eventually.</item>
<item>The game is almost always played with 4 male players and 4 female players on a team. But that doesn't mean you can't play a game if you don't have the exact numbers of each.</item>
<item>Join a nearby Korfball team; clubs are always kind and welcoming as well as happy to have new players</item>
<item>There are variations of Korfball such as Beach Korfball, so check them out.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try to warm up before the game and warm down afterwards to prevent injury.</item>
<item>Always remember to keep hydrated when playing sports.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>A Korfball</item>
<item>A Korfball Court (With 2 goals)</item>
<item>Other people to play with</item></list>
</text>
