<text id="autogum_whow_doc436" title="Decorate a Basement Apartment" shortTile="decorate-basement" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2013-03-04" dateModified="2019-08-07" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Decorate-a-Basement-Apartment" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Decorate a Basement Apartment</head><p>A basement apartment is often an affordable way to live in the city, but what you get in location you pay for with space and natural light. While many people find basement apartments charming, they can also be small, dark and because they are underground, a little claustrophobic. Decorate a basement apartment by focusing on light, color and the appropriate placement of furniture.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Using the Right Materials</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Determine humidity control factors. Basements in some regions often have little air flow and high humidity. If your apartment has central heat and air and relatively good return, you have all options for materials. If humidity and little air flow are issues, consider using humidity-resistant, or rust, mildew resistant materials.</item></list>
<head>Basement Apartment Lighting</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Place artificial light sources around the apartment. You will have little, if any, natural light, so take advantage of artificial light where you can. <figure rend="Decorate a Basement Apartment Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use lamps. This will provide softer light than harsh overhead lighting. They will also keep your place looking larger since light that is too bright can make a space look smaller. <figure rend="Decorate a Basement Apartment Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Take advantage of different lamp sizes and wattages. Use floor lamps in corners with brighter bulbs and smaller lamps on tables and surfaces with dim bulbs.</item></list></item>
<item>Include track lighting. The contrast in track lighting and lamps will give your basement apartment a mood that reflects its cozy appeal and urban location. <figure rend="Decorate a Basement Apartment Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep windows accessible if you do have them. Open blinds or curtains during the day will allow a bit of natural light. <figure rend="Decorate a Basement Apartment Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Maximize light in your kitchen area. Whether you have a kitchenette, a full kitchen or a microwave and a mini fridge, you will want to be able to see everything you are doing in the kitchen. <figure rend="Decorate a Basement Apartment Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Using Color</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Mix light and bright colors on your basement apartment walls.
<list type="unordered"><item>Use dark splashes of color on wall sections if the majority of your walls are kept white. <figure rend="Decorate a Basement Apartment Step 6Bullet1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Paint walls bright colors such as burgundy, green or chocolate brown and complement those colors with lighter furnishings or light trim. <figure rend="Decorate a Basement Apartment Step 6Bullet2.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Choose different paint colors to separate your living spaces. For example, paint the living room area brown and your bedroom or sleeping area light blue. <figure rend="Decorate a Basement Apartment Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take advantage of color, texture and patterns in other places. You can utilize color with your furnishings, accessories and carpets as well as your walls. <figure rend="Decorate a Basement Apartment Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Select throw rugs that contrast with your carpet or walls. For example, a bright red rug against a white or beige floor will really get attention.</item></list></item>
<item>Utilize drapes and window treatments. A dark set of curtains or drapes against a light wall can create a beautiful, well put together effect. <figure rend="Decorate a Basement Apartment Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Include mirrors. Not only will mirrors make your basement apartment look bigger, they will reflect the colors you have in your place. <figure rend="Decorate a Basement Apartment Step 10.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Placing Furniture</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Do a little space planning before you move in. Measure the rooms and decide if your current furniture will fit, or if you will have to acquire new pieces. <figure rend="Decorate a Basement Apartment Step 11.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Create separate living areas. This is especially important if you have one large living space instead of a separate bedroom, kitchen and living room, place. Use your furniture to divide up the area.</item></list></item>
<item>Use furniture that has multiple uses. This will save you space. For example, use ottomans or benches that open up and provide storage or a bed with drawers underneath. <figure rend="Decorate a Basement Apartment Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Allow for empty space. There is no need to have a piece of furniture in every empty spot. <figure rend="Decorate a Basement Apartment Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Utilize corners. Put a chair in a corner to create a reading space or get a desk that fits a corner so you have a work area. <figure rend="Decorate a Basement Apartment Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep clutter out of your basement apartment. Use all of your available storage and if necessary, borrow space in a friend's basement, attic or spare room to keep whatever you cannot fit. <figure rend="Decorate a Basement Apartment Step 15.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Work with an interior designer if you have the budget. If you cannot afford a professional, see if a college student or design intern would be willing to help you decorate your basement apartment to earn the experience and hands-on training.</item></list>
</text>
