<text id="autogum_whow_doc266" title="Manage Risk when Trading Stocks" shortTile="manage-risk-trading" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2010-09-15" dateModified="2017-07-14" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Manage-Risk-when-Trading-Stocks" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Manage Risk when Trading Stocks</head><p>Every successful business has a risk-management plan. Stock trading is a business. Here is how to manage risk when trading stocks.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Cover your expenses every month. Then concentrate on achieving a steady growth in earnings. <figure rend="Find Tax Exemptions for Your Small Business Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Rather than striving for the big hit, protect your capital first and work for consistent returns. You can take more aggressive risk with a portion of profits.</item>
<item>The big hits and "home runs" will still come along, but let them arrive without taking  excessive risk.</item></list></item>
<item>Base your stock-trading business philosophy on three principles (in order of importance): <figure rend="Get Commercial Lawn Accounts Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Preservation of capital</item>
<item>Consistent profitability</item>
<item>Pursuit of superior returns</item></list></item>
<item>Preserve capital in the interests of money management. This is the cornerstone of stock trading. Risk is the prime concern. <figure rend="Follow the Mortgage Accelerator Plus Program Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Before asking, "what kind of profit can I make?", ask first, "what potential loss can I suffer?" This is astute stock-trading risk management.</item>
<item>A storekeeper takes a risk every time s/he stocks new merchandise. If it does not sell, s/he will lose money. A smart businessperson takes only risks that will not put him/her out of business, even if s/he makes several mistakes in a row.</item></list></item>
<item>Define your risk. As a stock trader, you are in the business of trading. You need to define your business risk, the most money you are willing to risk (or lose) on any single trade. Here are some basic risk-management principles:  <figure rend="Manage Risk when Trading Stocks Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>There is no standard amount of money to risk, just like there is no standard business. Your acceptable risk level depends on the size of your trading account, your trading method and your tolerance for "pain."</item></list></item>
<item>Beware of emotional trading. Trading can be so exciting that it leads to emotional highs and lows in rapid succession. It rarely happens that a trader will make serious money while riding an emotional roller coaster. Emotional trading is the enemy of success. Fear and greed can undo a stock trader. A real professional  does not get too ecstatic or too depressed about specific wins or losses. This is a good mental state for stock trading and for life in general. If you're thinking about a past opportunity, you'll miss the next one to come your way.  <figure rend="Get Coupons and Free Samples from Most Companies Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Focus on being the best. The goal of a successful professional in any field is to reach his/her personal best. You need to concentrate on trading right. Each trade has to be handled like a surgical procedure: seriously, soberly, without sloppiness or shortcuts. This is a stock-trading risk-management plan. A loser cannot cut his losses quickly. When a trade starts going sour, the loser may hope and hang on while the losses pile up; or he may sell his position just before the market comes roaring back.  <figure rend="Negotiate a Short Sale Step 11.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Trends emerge because most losers are alike. They act on their gut feelings instead of using their heads. Personal emotions don't follow cultural backgrounds or educational levels.</item>
<item>Emotional traders go into risky gambles to avoid taking certain losses. It is human nature to take profits quickly and postpone taking losses. Emotional trading destroys otherwise intelligent traders. Good money management and timing techniques will keep them out of the hole. Losing traders look for a "sure thing", hang on out of hope, and irrationally refuse to accept small losses.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
