<text id="autogum_whow_doc022" title="Start Your Own Music Venue" shortTile="start-music-venue" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2010-07-10" dateModified="2015-08-27" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Start-Your-Own-Music-Venue" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Start Your Own Music Venue</head><p>If you went to a club one night and didn't like the music, atmosphere or the people and thought about creating your own music venue but just don't know where to start, here is your guide to how to start your own music venue.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Make A Budget. Your budget should be reasonable, affordable, and definitely not all your pocket money even if you plan to do this professionally. <figure rend="Start Your Own Music Venue Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have An Idea of What The Venue Is Going To Be Like.  If you want a jazzy smokey kind of venue then you want a bar and a bit of attitude to go along so you're not going to have kids running around and pop music which will come in to be very important. <figure rend="Start Your Own Music Venue Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Buy Property. Unless you're running a household venue then your going to need property in a central and/or visible location, i.e. downtown, where a lot of people visit. Remember: if you're running a pop style venue DO NOT put your venue in a shadier part of town who don't have the same taste of music. Get the property next to young places like Mrs. Tiggley Wiggles.( Very very sorry this was a horrible example but it is a smart idea.) <figure rend="Start Your Own Music Venue Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Start A Design - Very important. This is where your personality comes in and your budget. No matter what kind of place your running you don't want it to be bare. You want style, friendly outgoing style that reflects the music and feel of the bar. Draw what you want the bar to look like and then purchase the items according to what space you have of the venue. <figure rend="Start Your Own Music Venue Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Advertise You still want advertisements even if your downtown. Put out advertisements through street poles, by word, or even television. Also have a very bright entrance to your venue. people will notice the lights and automatically look and feel the vibes. <figure rend="Start Your Own Music Venue Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Start Hiring. You want bartenders, custodians and all of those. remember that there has to be a contract made legally. You might even want to do this all yourself or get help from friends. And Make sure everyone you hire is easy-going so the people who enter are more comfortable. <figure rend="Start Your Own Music Venue Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Hire Musicians. This is the time to hire musicians. Hire musicians that reflect the feel of the rest of the venue. ONLY hire bands that you have heard or seen before so when you do ask for or get asked for always ask for a press kit. Also only hire bands that are trustworthy. No heavy drinkers or druggies. This will of course will be bad business and you will have to guess when they're coming. <figure rend="Start Your Own Music Venue Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep Track Of Everything. This is what you will have to do because you will have less chance of getting sued or have any other accidents happen. You will also see where the money is going and also keep track of trends that are happening so you can put them in the advertisements. <figure rend="Start Your Own Music Venue Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take Lots Of Pictures And Videos And Sponsor Events. This will help support your venue by creating a way for people to feel connected. <figure rend="Start Your Own Music Venue Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Go there yourself And With Friends. This will help you see the outlook of your venue and see what other people see. <figure rend="Start Your Own Music Venue Step 10.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be Nice To Other Venue Managers And Ask Them On Tips</item>
<item>Always Be Willing To Go To Your Own Venue</item>
<item>Never Let the Venue Take Over Your Life</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't Let Money Get In The Way Of Any Thing</item>
<item>You will never get the best location due to other venues</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>A Location Downtown</item>
<item>A Good Attitude</item></list>
</text>
