<text id="autogum_whow_doc250" title="Enhance Customer Support via Marketing Techniques" shortTile="enhance-customer" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-04-30" dateModified="2016-01-08" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Enhance-Customer-Support-via-Marketing-Techniques" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Enhance Customer Support via Marketing Techniques</head><p>In the modern day business scenario, the sales and marketing departments are disintegrating and the entire sales procedure has changed. Unlike what used to happen in the past, these two departments i.e. marketing &amp; sales are now working together to boost up business revenue. The sales representatives of your company today have just as much responsibility as your marketers since they not only have to entertain the customers’ queries but also have to upsell and cross-sell, as a necessary part of their jobs. Many tools are used by customer support and sales reps these days, which are made for personalizing the experience of your customers. So, you should take time to look into the practices, which can help you enhance your customer support department. Here are a few marketing techniques to help you out:</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Use Marketing Automation. You can make use of a tool like marketing automation, which can help you gather behavioral data from your prospective customers. Doing this will help you creating a comprehensive file of your prospects. With the help of marketing automation tool, you can enhance your sales intelligence, which will let you equip your customer support and sales agents to refine their communication with your customers, a communication which is purely focused on the customers’ expectations and needs. <figure rend="Enhance Customer Support via Marketing Techniques Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tap into Social Data. Apart from collecting behavioral data via tracking tools and marketing automation, you should also lookup social profiles of your prospective customers to find more business for your organization. There are many profile lookup tools, which help you tap into social data. You can conduct in-depth survey which may include a company’s size, revenue and much more. Tapping into social data helps you find a method to personalize the sales pitch and keep your sales process streamlined. <figure rend="Enhance Customer Support via Marketing Techniques Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Respond instantaneously. Unlike customers from the past, today’s customers are more demanding, the reason being they have too many options to choose from. If you are not efficient enough in providing them information regarding your products and/or services, they will never give you a second chance to market. Earning customers’ loyalty has become the most difficult task in the modern era for the entrepreneurs, since brand switching has become common due to countless competitors offering special rates and packages to their customers. According to WebGreeter®, a leading online chat service provider, 30-50 percent of overall sales are a result of instantaneous response from the vendor. <figure rend="Enhance Customer Support via Marketing Techniques Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Let Facebook help you. You can enhance your customer support by asking help from Facebook. You can create your company’s page on Facebook and advertise about your products, services, promotions, special packages, discount offers and much more. This will help your customers know closely about what you have to offer, and will make them trust you more. The leading online chat service and software vendors such as WebGreeter® also offer integration of live chat with your Facebook page in order to entertain your online visitors and give them a purely personalized feeling. <figure rend="Enhance Customer Support via Marketing Techniques Step 4.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
