<text id="autogum_whow_doc487" title="Wash LuLaRoe Leggings" shortTile="wash-lularoe-leggings" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-07-23" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Wash-LuLaRoe-Leggings" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wash LuLaRoe Leggings</head><p>LuLaRoe leggings are cute and are a great way to express your unique style. Wearing them is exciting, but making the choice to wash them may cause nervousness. While washing your leggings may seem difficult, there are tricks to keeping them clean while maintaining their appearance. Learning to wash your leggings safely will help you get more use out of them and keep them in your closet longer.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Washing Your Leggings in the Washing Machine</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Separate your leggings from the rest of your clothing. If possible, separate all your leggings into a different laundry basket to ensure that none of your leggings get washed with your regular clothes. <figure rend="Wash LuLaRoe Leggings Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Turn your leggings inside out. This will help to preserve them. Watch for stains so that you can to pay more attention to the stain-affected areas.  <figure rend="Wash LuLaRoe Leggings Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Purchase a gentle detergent. Non-concentrated detergent is also safe to use. Good detergent options include Tide, Gain, and Arm &amp; Hammer. <figure rend="Wash LuLaRoe Leggings Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you use a generic detergent, make sure to check the ingredients against a brand name gentle detergent to ensure you are getting the best value. </item></list></item>
<item>Add laundry detergent. Laundry softener is also recommended to keep your leggings soft and smelling fresh, but it is not required. <figure rend="Wash LuLaRoe Leggings Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are unsure of how much detergent to put in, use the mantra 'less is more'. Remember that adding too much detergent will stain your leggings and leave undesired residue. </item></list></item>
<item>Wash your leggings. Be sure to wash them in cold water on the gentle cycle. Any other setting will likely be too harsh and may damage your leggings or ruin the coloring.   <figure rend="Wash LuLaRoe Leggings Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Put your leggings on clothes hangers or a drying rack to dry. This will help them to last longer than putting them in the dryer. <figure rend="Wash LuLaRoe Leggings Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you choose to dry them outside, keep them inside out to keep from getting sun damage.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Cleaning Your Leggings in the Sink</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Separate your leggings from the rest of your dirty clothing to prevent color damage. If possible, put all your leggings into a different laundry basket to ensure that you do not accidentally wash them with all your other clothes.  <figure rend="Wash LuLaRoe Leggings Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use a cold water laundry detergent. Gentle detergent is a great choice, but it is also okay to use non-concentrated detergent. If you do not have either of these detergents, it would be best to purchase one. <figure rend="Wash LuLaRoe Leggings Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>To determine which brand to buy, it may be helpful to look into a website like Consumer Reports or ask advice from someone you trust. </item></list></item>
<item>Prepare your sink for clothes washing. Remove any items nearby that may catch on your leggings and make sure the sink is free of food stains, grease, and grime. <figure rend="Wash LuLaRoe Leggings Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Clean your sink if necessary, fill at least halfway with water, then add 2 oz of laundry softener and 1/4 of a cup of laundry detergent.</item>
<item>Adding too much detergent will discolor your clothing by leaving light spots, so remember that when it comes to detergent, less is more.</item>
<item>Mix the water until both the laundry softener and the detergent completely dissolve. </item></list></item>
<item>Turn your leggings inside out and put them in the water. Avoid putting more than 4 or 5 pairs of leggings in the water together at one time. If you are not sure if your leggings will bleed color, wash each pair individually to save your clothing from discoloration. <figure rend="Wash LuLaRoe Leggings Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Clean your leggings. Remember to be gentle so the fabric is not strained. <figure rend="Wash LuLaRoe Leggings Step 11.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Let them soak in the water for about 5 minutes.</item>
<item>Swish them around to shake off dust and dirt particles and gently scrub them with your hands to remove any stains, then let them soak for another 10 to 15 minutes to remove any additional dirt or grime.</item>
<item>Swish your leggings once more to ensure they are 100% clean and fresh, then remove them one by one. </item></list></item>
<item>Drain all the water out of the sink. Rinse it out so that no soapy residue remains, then fill the sink with water. Rinse the leggings in the sink. Gently swirl them in the water to remove all the soap. <figure rend="Wash LuLaRoe Leggings Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Put your leggings on a drying rack or hang them on a clothes hanger to dry. This will eliminate any damage that would occur from putting them in the dryer. If you are drying your them outside, keep them inside out to prevent fading or other sun damage. <figure rend="Wash LuLaRoe Leggings Step 13.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Add one cup of vinegar to one gallon of water and soak your clothes in this mixture for up to 30 minutes before washing them normally. This will help to preserve their coloring.</item>
<item>Wear your leggings multiple times before washing to preserve their life and color.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not put your leggings into the dryer. This will cause unnecessary wear and tear.</item></list>
</text>
