<text id="autogum_whow_doc426" title="Improve Your Luck" shortTile="improve-luck" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2008-10-18" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Improve-Your-Luck" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Improve Your Luck</head><p>Feeling a little unlucky lately? Want the secret to being lucky? You have it already - it's <hi rend="italic">you</hi>. The secret to improving luck is about perspective, self-belief and <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Optimistic">erring on the side of optimism</ref>. It isn't about winning huge pots of cash - it's about making the most of the wonderful blessings already surrounding you. See Step 1 below for some thoughts for making your own luck grow.
</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Prepare.  "Luck is when preparation meets opportunity", said Seneca, Roman dramatist, philosopher and politician, 5 BC - 65 AD.  If you have the groundwork in place you can take advantage of the opportunities that come your way. <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Proactive">Be proactive</ref>. <figure rend="Improve Your Luck Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Network">Network.</ref> Lucky people know people, lots of people. They don't have to be everyone's bosom buddy but it is the art of being open to many new people that counts. Practice feeling comfortable <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Mingle_With_Strangers_at_Parties">talking to strangers</ref> at events that you attend. And actively listen to them when you <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Start_a_Conversation_When_You_Have_Nothing_to_Talk_About">strike up a conversation</ref> because you will have a lot to learn and they will remember that you appreciated what they had to say. This can translate into opportunities; the more people you meet and the more people you display genuine interest in, the more likelihood of you meeting the right person at the right time who has an opportunity at hand that you want to be a part of. <figure rend="Improve Your Luck Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Follow_Your_Intuition">Trust your instincts.</ref> That little inner voice is often right and lucky people know this. You will also know when your "common sense" or "reason" are trying to override the lucky hunch. When this happens, take a moment aside to sit and think things through clearly and uninterrupted. Consider whose voices are speaking to you when you are faced with overriding intuition - is it your own trustworthy voice or is it <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Stop_Being_a_People_Pleaser">the voices of others' expectations</ref> - a spouse, a boss, a friend? <figure rend="Improve Your Luck Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Laid_Back">Take it easy.</ref> Anxiety and worry are enemies of luck. They introduce a factor that says "Be very risk averse" and "Whoa there! Hold back now!" You won't be stumbling across luck while you are too busy hiding out. When opportunities come, you need to notice them and you need to seize them. A lucky person <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Live_in_the_Moment">believes in now as being as important</ref> as tomorrow and much more so than yesterday. Don't be held back by ghosts of failure - they were just learning experiences. And tomorrow will always come whatever happens, so do your best to enjoy today so that tomorrow has a standard to match! <figure rend="Improve Your Luck Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Exercise_an_Open_Mind">Be ready for new opportunities.</ref> The more open you are to novel ideas and new ways of doing things, the more likely it is that you will strike it lucky. Lucky people don't plod along methodically; while that guarantees a safe and secure path, lucky people take the path less known and meet all sorts of amazing opportunities along the way. Put your foot on that path now... try something you have never done before, try something you have convinced yourself you would hate, try something that someone else has suggested you try. <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Bold">Be bold.</ref> <figure rend="Improve Your Luck Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Optimistic">Be an eternal optimist.</ref> <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Expect</hi></hi> the best. Yes, anyone <hi rend="italic">can</hi> do this and why not? It isn't about living with the fairies. It is about <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Positive">being positive</ref> and creating the outcomes that you want most. Lucky people are optimistic and they expect that good things will happen to them. Heard the <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Perform_Mantra_Meditation">mantra</ref> "only good things happen to me"? Well, probably not, as most of us tend to whine "why do all the bad things happen to me?!" Stop it right now and start expecting the best. Instead of choosing to wallow and feel rotten about things that go wrong, look for life's lessons in the experience and look for new solutions that grow out of the bad experience. Dwelling on horrible events in your life gives them great power over you, stifling your growth and stomping on your luck. And when you view the world in this manner, even if Lady Luck does call, you're likely to sabotage it because that suits your negative mindset. <figure rend="Improve Your Luck Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Self_Learning">Never stop learning.</ref> This is related to staying open to new opportunities. Unlucky people think their learning stopped at school or university. Lucky people realize that that was just the beginning and that life is one huge university. Soak it all up; even the stuff you find hard, boring, or uncomfortable. It really makes your life a whole lot more exciting and helps you to understand where others are coming from. Aiming to understand a wide range of perspectives makes it easier for you to forgive people and to see their points of view. Knowing this enables you to weave others' motivations into how you approach life and treat them with respect. Which leads to the next point... <figure rend="Improve Your Luck Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Use <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Use_Affirmations_Effectively">affirmations</ref> daily. "I am going to have a lucky day today." "I am going to have good fortune today." "I am going to help enable my luck today by helping others to be lucky today."</item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Humble">Be humble.</ref> Luck favors the humble; this doesn't mean you can't stand out there and enthuse others to find their luck but you mustn't toot your horn of arrogance or luck will start to shy away as you become too self-certain. And this quickly steps into the realm of disrespecting others and closing yourself off to more learning. Remember balance and you'll be fine.</item>
<item>Luck is made, not found. And the luck that is "stumbled across" is very often fool's gold in the hands of a person who doesn't know what to do with it. If you believe in yourself and your abilities, and follow the ideas outlined above, you will be in a great position to take advantage of lucky breaks.</item>
<item>Use techniques such as <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Improve_Your_Visualization">visualization</ref> and <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Accomplish_a_Goal">goal-setting</ref> to create your luck. These are not over-used mantras; they are proven techniques to ensure that you remain directed and focused on the things you want for yourself in life.</item>
<item>Use your subconscious mind. Have a total picture of the success you would like. Bring it into mind for 3 seconds, and then leave it. It will come true with a strong intent.</item></list>
</text>
