<text id="autogum_whow_doc319" title="Eat Bread at a Dinner Party" shortTile="eat-bread-dinner" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2009-08-10" dateModified="2016-08-18" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Eat-Bread-at-a-Dinner-Party" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Eat Bread at a Dinner Party</head><p>The bread! Often it's the first source of sustenance for a starving dinner guest but wait! Not so fast! Is it rude to start breaking it open and chowing down before you're even seated?! There is basic etiquette attached to eating bread at the dinner table. This article only deals with etiquette relevant to some anglophone cultures. It is possible other cultural requirements exist for eating bread in other parts of the world - asking first is a good idea if you don't know!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Wait before breaking bread. It is quite possible that you're starving, but it is ill-mannered to eat the bread without respite before the first course arrives at the table. If bread is sitting on the table already, wait until the first course is served before helping yourself to it. If bread is handed out by a waiter, allow the waiter to use bread tongs to place it on the plate. Do not be tempted to stick your hand into the waiter's basket and grab more! Ask instead. And again, wait until everyone has started eating. <figure rend="Eat Bread Dinner Party Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Eat the bread carefully. A dinner party is not the time to display breakfast table bread habits. Instead, break apart the bread into small pieces using your fingers. Do not cut the bread or bite into the large part of the bread. If you wish to add butter to your bread, add it to each small piece after you have broken it. <figure rend="Eat Bread Dinner Party Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Place the broken bread onto the bread and butter plate. This small plate is found just above the dinner plate and is used to hold the bread and butter. Using your bread, place a small bit of butter onto the bread and butter plate next to your bread. Do not "double dip" into the butter dish. Take only what you need from the butter dish and place that onto the plate. Carefully add neatly spread butter onto your hand broken pieces of bread with your hands. <figure rend="Eat Bread Dinner Party Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Beware the bread bloat. While some people are very careful not to overdo the bread, others consume too much at the dinner table and cannot eat all of their meal. Avoid this by remembering that bread is the support cast and not the star. If you're still starving later, you can raid the fridge at home, out of sight. <figure rend="Eat Bread Dinner Party Step 4.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Note that many functions such as weddings, conferences, etc., will only cater for enough bread to go around per person once. If you ask for additional bread and it is refused for this reason, don't despair (and equally, don't take it out on the poor waiter). The best thing to do is to ask if the waiter can return to you with more bread if any is left over. There are always people on low-carb diets, etc., who refuse their share of bread.</item>
<item>If you have special dietary needs, allergies, etc., such as not consuming dairy or gluten, ask the waiter quietly at an opportune moment if the bread ingredients are known; be clear that you have an allergy or dietary issue with certain ingredients. If it cannot be ascertained with certainty or ease, simply refuse the bread politely.</item></list>
</text>
