<text id="autogum_whow_doc435" title="Decorate an Apartment Office With Limited Space" shortTile="decorate-apartment" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2009-02-18" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Decorate-an-Apartment-Office-With-Limited-Space" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Decorate an Apartment Office With Limited Space</head><p>Perhaps you’re in a student apartment and stay up late at night finishing essays. Or perhaps you’re a young entrepreneur who works in their apartment in their pajamas. Whatever you use your apartment office for, you don’t want it to be boring, and you don’t want to waste any space. Use these apartment decorating ideas to ensure that you’re apartment office is a comfortable, relaxing, and fun place to work.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be careful with colour. Dark colours will definitely make your room appear smaller. Light neutral colours will give off the greatest appearance of space in your apartment office, but at the same time, they can get boring. However, there are many fun <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Bring_Color_Into_Your_Home">colours</ref> out there, and you can always get them in a lighter shade. <figure rend="Decorate an Apartment Office With Limited Space Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use large decorations A lot of small decorations everywhere can give the appearance of clutter. A few larger decorations, such as a large <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_a_Wall_Poster_Using_Rasterbator">wall poster</ref>, can create wonderful focal points for your apartment office while opening the room up. <figure rend="Decorate an Apartment Office With Limited Space Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Clean_Up_Your_Desk">Keep your desk clean</ref>. Whatever size desk you need for your apartment, keep it clean. Don’t add decorative clutter to it if you’re goal is to open up space. If you have a computer, try to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Organize_Computer_Wires">hide</ref> as many wires as you can. <figure rend="Decorate an Apartment Office With Limited Space Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use smart apartment storage. Don’t just leave everything out in your apartment office. Look into trendy storage solutions to keep all your apartment clutter in a small space and out of the way. If you have stuff that you traditionally keep in your apartment office but hardly ever use, consider storing it elsewhere in your apartment. <figure rend="Decorate an Apartment Office With Limited Space Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use smart layout. If you have a smaller apartment office, do not put your desk in the centre of the room. Keep it in the corner, so that you have as much open space as possible. <figure rend="Decorate an Apartment Office With Limited Space Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don’t buy large plants. A small <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Grow_a_Cactus">cactus</ref> or other plant can give any room more life without taking up lots of space in your apartment. Think of strategic ways to place it where it’ll give the greatest illusion of <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_a_Small_Room_Seem_Larger">lots of space</ref> (as the only decoration in the centre of a large table, for example). The trick is to contrast one small item with something much larger. <figure rend="Decorate an Apartment Office With Limited Space Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Only keep what you need. Often apartment offices don’t have a lot of space, even while the rest of the apartment does. If this is the case, you might put a few office items in other places around your apartment. If you don’t print a lot but you own a printer, there’s might be a place somewhere else in your apartment that’s out of the way. <figure rend="Decorate an Apartment Office With Limited Space Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
