<text id="autogum_whow_doc656" title="Make the Soccer Team" shortTile="make-soccer-team" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-06-22" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-the-Soccer-Team" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make the Soccer Team</head><p>If you want to show that you've got what it takes to be part of the team or simply want to take up a new hobby, soccer can be a great pursuit. These steps will help make sure you have the best chance of <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_a_Sports_Team">getting into the team</ref>. Follow them one by one, or just pick those you think are most relevant to you. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Making Amateur to Professional Teams</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Improve_Physical_Fitness">Improve</ref> and <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Keep_Your_Fitness_Plan_in_Place">maintain</ref> your fitness. This is very important; if the coaches see you out of breath after a light jog they'll think you don't have the stamina to perform well for a full 90 minute game. If you are getting ready for trials make sure to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Create_a_Personal_Fitness_Plan">start a fitness program</ref> roughly 2 months before to improve your muscular and cardiovascular endurance, or just try to maintain a good level of fitness all year round.  <figure rend="Make the Soccer Team Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>good training is good for simulating the different intensities of a soccer match, it involves working at different intensities and/or across different terrains. Although, you should progress gradually and always perform a warm up and cool down with your workouts to reduce the risk of injury.</item></list></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Eat_Right_for_a_Fitness_Program">Eat right</ref>. Reduce the amount of fat and sugar in your diet. Try to eat foods with more carbohydrates, to give you a long-lasting energy supply, and protein, to help your muscles grown and recover quicker. <figure rend="Make the Soccer Team Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>An example of a good pre-match or pre-training meal would be tuna and pasta.</item></list></item>
<item>Add in your own training sessions. This is especially useful if you are struggling to perform a specific skill, such as long passing. The more you practise, the more natural and fluent the movements will become. It will help to develop muscle memory if you repeat skills over and over again. Practise really does make perfect. <figure rend="Make the Soccer Team Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure you seem really enthusiastic and enjoy yourself. If the coaches see you sulking or complaining they will be concerned about your attitude and work ethic. <figure rend="Make the Soccer Team Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Show just the right amount of aggression. You need to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Confident">be confident</ref> enough to go in for the ball, even when you might get hurt, but equally the coaches and manager won't want you making wild challenges or getting into fights. You need good sportsmanship and compassion whilst still being driven to win. <figure rend="Make the Soccer Team Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Confident">Be confident</ref>, on and off the pitch. On the pitch you need to communicate effectively and make important, split second decisions. Off the pitch, try to get to know the other people in the team/trial and ask the coaches questions if you want useful tips or don't understand something. This will make you seem <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_More_Enthusiastic">enthusiastic</ref> and it will show you can work well as part of a team and inspire others if you can both get on with your team and work together effectively on the pitch. <figure rend="Make the Soccer Team Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure you are confident playing in a number of different positions and roles. Don't limit yourself to only being able to play in one position. Coaches and managers like to be able to use players in several positions. So, if you are normally a striker try to develop your game as a centre forward and attacking midfielder as well. Same for defenders; if you normally play as a centre back, try out the roles of a full-back and defensive midfielder. This shows you are <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Become_Flexible">adaptable</ref> and the manager will be able to use you in more positions. <figure rend="Make the Soccer Team Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Build_Self‐Control">Show good restraint</ref> on and off the pitch. There are times where other players or people may taunt you or try to cheat, but as a good player, you need to show that you are in control and you are above retaliation. Managers want players who will positively reflect on the entire club. <figure rend="Make the Soccer Team Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Making the High School Team</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Behave_In_Class">Behave</ref>. Many schools will not allow you to play if you are regularly misbehaving in class. This applies on the pitch as well, play fair and be a good sportsperson. <figure rend="Make the Soccer Team Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Study">Study hard</ref>. If you are failing any subjects, the school may ban you from participating because they think it may be affecting your grades. Make sure you always have time to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Finish_Your_Homework">complete homework</ref> and any catching up you need to do. <figure rend="Make the Soccer Team Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Listen">Listen</ref> to the coach. High school coaches often pick players for the team that they know will listen to their instructions and can be trusted to do their best. <figure rend="Make the Soccer Team Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Show commitment. Turn up to as many training sessions as you can, the coach will get a better idea of your abilities and you will improve more. <figure rend="Make the Soccer Team Step 12.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Joining a Casual Team</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Get_Someone's_Phone_Number">Get contact numbers</ref> for your potential teammates. This will help a lot with communication if the team doesn't have an designated manager and doesn't play in an official league. <figure rend="Make the Soccer Team Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Socialize_Smoothly">Socialise and be friendly</ref>. In casual teams, one of the most important things is that you all get on with each other and can work well together as a team. <figure rend="Make the Soccer Team Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Turn up regularly. It is accepted that you will miss some training and possibly even matches due to work or school commitments and the odd special occasion, but you should try to turn up as often as possible. This will send a message, that you are committed and <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Reliable">reliable</ref>. <figure rend="Make the Soccer Team Step 15.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure to have at least one rest day between training and the trial(s) if possible to reduce the risk of injury.</item>
<item>You should have rest days in between training days to allow your body to recover and positive effects to take place.</item>
<item>Participate in other sports as well, maintain your fitness without getting bored of constantly repeating the same exercises.</item>
<item>Be friendly towards your teammates and try to socialise away from soccer as well. The more you get to know each other, the better you will be able to play, as a team.</item>
<item>If the team doesn’t have any goalies then try out for it. Anyone can be good at it!</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Dehydration can lead to sickness. Make sure you drink plenty of water to keep you cool and hydrated.</item></list>
</text>
