<text id="autogum_whow_doc565" title="Test a Dog&apos;s Intelligence" shortTile="test-dogs-intelligence" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2009-12-19" dateModified="2019-06-10" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Test-a-Dog%27s-Intelligence" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Test a Dog's Intelligence</head><p>In animal intelligence research, even defining the subject of study can be difficult. Many basic questions remain unanswered, and people argue endlessly over what the results of tests mean. So remember, if your dog scores low, you can still say he's the smartest dog in the world.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Intelligence Tests</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find a stopwatch. You'll need a clock that measures seconds for these tests. They're intended to measure problem-solving and adaptation to the environment. <figure rend="Test a Dog's Intelligence Step 1 Version 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Toss a towel over the dog's head. Let the dog smell a large towel or a small blanket. Toss it over the the dog's head, covering it completely. Start the stopwatch and see how long it takes your dog to get free. Write down the score: <figure rend="Test a Dog's Intelligence Step 2 Version 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>30 seconds or less: 3 points</item>
<item>31–120 seconds: 2 points</item>
<item>Tries but doesn't succeed within 120 seconds: 1 point — and take off the towel for him!</item>
<item>Doesn't try to get free: 0 points.</item>
<item>You might want to practice tossing the towel over a chair beforehand. It should land in one, smooth motion.</item></list></item>
<item>Hide a treat under the towel. Show the dog a treat. While the dog is watching, put the treat on the floor. Lay the towel over it. Start the stopwatch and see how long the dog takes to reach the treat: <figure rend="Test a Dog's Intelligence Step 3 Version 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>30 seconds or less: 3 points</item>
<item>31–60 seconds: 2 points</item>
<item>Tries but fails within 60 seconds: 1 point</item>
<item>Doesn't try: 0 points</item></list></item>
<item>Set up a low opening. For this test, you need a gap low to the ground, that the dog can reach with its paws but not its muzzle. A couch might work, or you might need to make one yourself out of a pair of books and a wide plank. Weigh down the top of the plank so the dog can't easily knock it over. <figure rend="Test a Dog's Intelligence Step 4 Version 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Test the dog with the puzzle. Place a treat underneath the plank or couch, while the dog is watching. Push it far enough underneath that the dog can't reach it with its muzzle. Encourage the dog to get the treat while you time it: <figure rend="Test a Dog's Intelligence Step 5 Version 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Succeeds within 2 minutes (using its paws): 4 points</item>
<item>Succeeds within 3 minutes (using its paws): 3 points</item>
<item>Fails within 3 minutes, but uses its paws: 2 points</item>
<item>Fails, only uses its muzzle: 1 point</item>
<item>Doesn't try: 0 points</item></list></item>
<item>Teach your dog to find a hidden treat. The next test is designed to challenge the dog's memory, not its problem-solving skills. To do this, the dog needs to understand what's going on. Put a treat underneath a plastic cup, then tell the dog to find it. Lift the cup to show the dog where it is. Do this about eight or ten times, until the dog learns that treats go underneath cups. <figure rend="Test a Dog's Intelligence Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Test the dog's memory. Place three plastic buckets or cups upside down on the floor, a foot apart. Put a treat underneath one of the cups, while the dog is watching. Lead the dog out of the room for 30 seconds, then back. Urge the dog to find the treat. <figure rend="Test a Dog's Intelligence Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Checks under the right cup on the first try: 2 points</item>
<item>Finds it within two minutes: 1 point</item>
<item>Doesn't find it: 0 points</item></list></item>
<item>Score the dog's results. Add up all your dog's points and see how it did: <figure rend="Test a Dog's Intelligence Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>11–12 points: Canine Genius</item>
<item>8–10 points: Obedience School Honor Student</item>
<item>4–7 points: Just an Average Rex</item>
<item>1–3 points: I'm a Barker, Not a Thinker</item>
<item>0 points: You might have just tested a mop.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Getting Better Results</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Treat it like a game. This is no time to be an impartial observer, your dog's college admissions are on the line! But seriously, if the dog isn't interested, she won't even try to complete the challenges. Encourage the dog with gestures or smiles, keeping it interested but not so excited it forgets what to do. <figure rend="Test a Dog's Intelligence Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pick a special treat. The dog has to cooperate to be tested. Pick a special, smelly treat to bribe it with. Soft, smelly treats are best, since the dog will notice them and eat them quickly. Cut them into small, pea-sized pieces if you plan to do all of these tests at once. <figure rend="Test a Dog's Intelligence Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Pieces of hot dog, cooked chicken, or cheese are all good options.</item>
<item>Use a dry, non-smelly treat when you're testing memory.</item></list></item>
<item>Have the dog's owner conduct the test. This test works best if the dog spends a lot of time with the person testing him. A dog might not live up to its full potential if it's been living with the test-giver for less than three months. <figure rend="Test a Dog's Intelligence Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Test a puppy again after it matures. A puppy under one year old probably won't be as "smart" or obedient as an adult dog. <figure rend="Test a Dog's Intelligence Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Train the dog with treasure hunts. Tell the dog to stay while it watches you "hide" a treat in a box or under a table. Once it finds the treat, hide the next one in a harder to find location. As your dog gets better at this, you can hide the treat while the dog isn't looking, and put it behind several barriers. <figure rend="Test a Dog's Intelligence Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Teach the "new trick" command. This is a great way to challenge your dog. It works best if you've <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Clicker-Train-Your-Dog">clicker trained</ref> your dog with several tricks already. Use the clicker and say "new trick," then reward it for any trick it does. Repeat immediately with another "new trick" and only reward it if it does something <hi rend="italic">new</hi>. Keep going until the dog runs out of tricks or gets confused. <figure rend="Test a Dog's Intelligence Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get brain-testing puzzle toys for your dog. You can't always be around to tutor your dog. Give it some homework in the form of an interactive dog toy. These have treats hidden inside that won't fall out unless the dog solves a puzzle. Some of them even have an electronic voice to give commands, although be careful giving those to dogs with a constant chewing habit. <figure rend="Test a Dog's Intelligence Step 15.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can find dog intelligence games online or on mobile devices, for you and your dog to play together.</item>
<item>Don't get frustrated if your dog can't do it at first. Keep working on it!</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Only use a light blanket that the dog can easily move under. Don't suffocate a puppy or small dog with a heavy quilt.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>A dog</item>
<item>A stopwatch</item>
<item>A blanket or towel</item>
<item>Treats or a toy</item>
<item>3 buckets or cups - preferably matching.</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
