<text id="autogum_whow_doc419" title="Enjoy the Ice Festival in Harbin, China" shortTile="enjoy-ice-festival" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-03-23" dateModified="2018-01-23" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Enjoy-the-Ice-Festival-in-Harbin%2C-China" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Enjoy the Ice Festival in Harbin, China</head><p>The Ice and Snow Festival in Harbin, China is the 2nd largest ice and snow festival in the world. People come from all over the world to participate and see the results of this snow and ice competition. Here's how to enjoy your trip to this northern Chinese city.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Choose the right timing:
<list type="unordered"><item>The ice festival usually begins in early January. (This may begin earlier depending on the weather that year).</item>
<item>It is best to go earlier in the season, because the larger structures will be closed off as the warm weather compromises their structure.</item></list></item>
<item>Be Prepared:
<list type="unordered"><item>Harbin is the coldest city in China, located near the border with Russia.</item>
<item>Expect temperatures well below freezing, usually between 0 and 10 degree Fahrenheit.</item>
<item>Wear warm clothes! Wear many layers and cold weather gear (such as hats, scarves, gloves, etc.) You will also need warm, waterproof, winter boots for the snow.</item></list></item>
<item>Know where to go:
<list type="unordered"><item>The Ice and Snow Festival is not limited to one area. There are several places you can go.</item>
<item>The largest, and by far the most popular, are the Ice and Snow World and the International Snow Sculpture Exhibition on Sun Island.</item>
<item>The Zhaolin Gardens are also popular.</item></list></item>
<item>Buy tickets:
<list type="unordered"><item>The entrance tickets for the different Ice and Snow Festival areas are extremely expensive. They usually cost upwards of 300 RMB.</item>
<item>If you have a student ID for an undergraduate degree at a Chinese university (study period lasting approx. a year) you can get half-price.</item>
<item>Children's tickets are usually based on height not age. Your child's age may not guarantee a free ticket.</item>
<item>Elderly and Military ID's can also result in a discount, but this may be only for Chinese people.</item>
<item>Cheaper tickets can be purchased online or through the Harbin Tourist Center on Zhongyang St. (中央大街).</item></list></item>
<item>Know when to go:
<list type="unordered"><item>Sun Island's Snow Sculpture Exhibition closes before sunset.</item>
<item>The Ice and Snow World is open almost all day. It is best to go just before sundown and stay while it's dark. This is where the famous 冰灯 are located.</item>
<item>Zhaolin Gardens is best viewed after sundown as well.</item></list></item>
<item>Find convenient transportation:
<list type="unordered"><item>Ice and Snow World and the Snow Sculpture Exhibition are both located on Sun Island, which is farther from the city center (and most likely even farther from your hotel).</item>
<item>There are bus lines that go to the exhibitions and Snow World on Sun Island. These cost a measly 2 RMB and are direct lines.</item>
<item>Some hotels offer free shuttles.</item>
<item>You can hire a bus or a taxi. Note that taxis do not use meters in Harbin. You will have to agree on a price before you arrive.</item>
<item>For the adventurous, the river separating Sun Island and the main area of Harbin has a gondola which will take you to the other side. From there, it's just a short walk.</item></list></item>
<item>Follow these steps when you get there:
<list type="unordered"><item>Bring a camera! There are many beautiful hand-carved ice and snow sculptures you won't want to forget.</item>
<item>Try sledding! Several places, particularly the Ice and Snow World, have several ice slides. You don't even need a sled!</item>
<item>The biggest ice slide is in Ice and Snow World. They provide sleds and it's free.</item>
<item>Take pictures with winter animals like snow foxes, or ride in a carriage pulled by horses, reindeer, or dogs.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>There are very few places to eat in these places so it may be a good idea to eat beforehand. Otherwise, there are candied fruits and other snacks available.</item></list>
</text>
