<text id="autogum_whow_doc571" title="Find a Dog by AKC Registration Number" shortTile="find-dog-akc-registration" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2017-09-15" dateModified="2019-06-04" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Find-a-Dog-by-AKC-Registration-Number" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Find a Dog by AKC Registration Number</head><p>The American Kennel Club (AKC) keeps a lot of information on dogs registered with the organization. From a dog’s competition wins and losses to its pedigree, the AKC can help you learn a lot about your furry friend. If you know your dog’s AKC registration number, you can use the Club’s website to search for information about your dog, and even getting full reports on its pedigree and dog show participation. All you need to do is register online for a free AKC account, and use the tools they provide.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Running a Free Search</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Register with www.akc.org. To research a dog on the AKC site, you will need to register for a free account with them. Click the Sign Up link on the homepage in the upper right corner, and input your email address, your first and last name, and a password for your account. You may need to verify your email from a link provided by the AKC website. <figure rend="Find a Dog by AKC Registration Number Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The AKC website is the only accurate, up-to-date source for looking up AKC registration numbers.</item>
<item>You can also search as a guest, but registering for an account is a good idea.</item></list></item>
<item>Hover over the AKC Shop in the menu bar. Once you have registered, navigate to the ‘shop’ tab on the top-of-page menu bar. Hover over the link to produce a drop-down menu. <figure rend="Find a Dog by AKC Registration Number Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select the Competitor Reports option. Competitor Reports will take you to a table of reports and searches that let you look for your dog. Click on this link, and look under the Search Tools section. <figure rend="Find a Dog by AKC Registration Number Step 03.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This will be under AKC Services &amp; Reports when accessed from the mail page.</item></list></item>
<item>Click on Free Dog Lookup. Clicking directly on this link will generate a pop-up where you can search for a dog by its AKC number. Enter the number, and click search to run your query. Select your dog to see its information. <figure rend="Find a Dog by AKC Registration Number Step 04.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This search generates a limited amount of information about your dog including their birth date, sex, breed, group, breeders, owners, and some awards. More comprehensive information may still require buying a report.</item>
<item>You can also search from the dog's breed and registered name.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Finding a Dog’s Pedigree</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Register for an AKC account. Before you can pull up any AKC reports, you need to register for an account on the AKC website. Accounts are free, but registration will require some contact information including your name and email address. <figure rend="Find a Dog by AKC Registration Number Step 05.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Navigate to the AKC Shop in the menu bar. Once you have registered with the AKC site, navigate to the ‘Shop’ tab on the top-of-page menu bar. Hover over the link to produce a drop-down menu. <figure rend="Find a Dog by AKC Registration Number Step 06.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select the AKC Certified Pedigrees option. Under the ‘Shop’ drop-down menu, click on the ‘AKC Certified Pedigrees’ option. This link will take you to a page where you can look up your dog’s pedigree by their AKC number. <figure rend="Find a Dog by AKC Registration Number Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This report will show your pet's family tree including championships, health certifications, and countries of origin for up to 4 generations.</item></list></item>
<item>Add the report to your cart. To generate the search, you need to add the report to your cart. A certified pedigree report from the AKC cost $34. <figure rend="Find a Dog by AKC Registration Number Step 08.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can choose to purchase a framed version of the report for an additional cost.</item></list></item>
<item>Input your dog’s registration number in the search. Once the report is in your cart, it will produce a pop-up that will allow you to search for your dog by its AKC number. Run the search to select your dog and order the proper report. <figure rend="Find a Dog by AKC Registration Number Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Purchase your report. Select the ‘check out’ option on the report page. Input your credit card information and complete your purchase. Your certified pedigree will be printed and mailed to you within a few weeks. <figure rend="Find a Dog by AKC Registration Number Step 10.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tracking Your Dog’s Awards</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Register your AKC online account. Before you can access your dog's award records, you will need to register for an AKC online account. Use your name and email address to sign up, and login to you account to get access to the report. <figure rend="Find a Dog by AKC Registration Number Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Go to the AKC Shop in the menu bar. Just like looking up your dog’s pedigree, you need to register for an AKC account before looking up your dog’s awards. Once you have registered, navigate to the ‘shop’ tab on the top-of-page menu bar. Hover over the link to produce a drop-down menu. <figure rend="Find a Dog by AKC Registration Number Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on the Competitor Reports option. This will be under the AKC Reports option. Competitor Reports will take you to a table of reports. Select this link, and look under the Custom Reports &amp; Products for Your Dog section on the table. <figure rend="Find a Dog by AKC Registration Number Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Choose the Individual Dog Award Record and Points Progression. This will take you to the report page, where you will be able to search your dog. The report is an online deliverable, and costs $8. <figure rend="Find a Dog by AKC Registration Number Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the button to add the report to your cart. This will generate a pop-up where you can search for your dog by their AKC number. Input your dog’s number to generate their individual report. <figure rend="Find a Dog by AKC Registration Number Step 15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Purchase the report. Once you have confirmed your dog’s registration number, you will need to purchase the report. Select the ‘check out’ option on the report page and input your payment information. The report will be delivered to you electronically. <figure rend="Find a Dog by AKC Registration Number Step 16.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This report will show any awards and points progressions from any AKC partner dog show or agility event.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you don’t know your dog’s full AKC registration number, you can also run any of these searches using their breed and registered AKC competitor’s name.</item></list>
</text>
