<text id="autogum_whow_doc593" title="Understand Plato&apos;s Cave Theory" shortTile="understand-platos" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-05-15" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Understand-Plato%27s-Cave-Theory" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Understand Plato's Cave Theory</head><p>Plato's Cave Theory is a fundamental component of philosophy - from a historical and epistemological perspective. Recently, it has also been popularized in the Mumford and Sons hit: the Cave. Plato's Cave Allegory provides a visual representation of how Plato believed "reality" exists.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>A Summary of the Cave Allegory</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>The Cave Allegory is presented in Plato's book, The Republic. Through a dialog, a story begins to emerge: A group of people have lived their entire lives in a cave, chained to a wall.  In front of them is a blank wall upon which they watch shadows move.  The people are constrained and cannot see that the shadows are made from various objects passing in front of a fire that is located behind them.  They do not see the source of light, and believe the shadows on the wall are "real things."The story becomes more complex, as Plato paints a detailed picture of how these people know nothing besides the shadows on the wall. Any noises they hear are mere echos that bounce off the wall of the cave. If someone, chained from his earliest memories, were to be freed, Plato reasons, he would prefer what he believes is reality to noticing anything else. The light from the fire would hurt his eyes. Walking would hurt.If he were to run back to the group to tell him his discovery, he would not be believed.  Some people would try to kill him for "insanity"However, this particular freed prisoner would still be missing "true reality." He would not want to go outside, since the light would be blinding and painful. He would have to be dragged outside, and would not be able to see anything while his eyes adjusted.  First he would see vague shadows of people and objects.  Next, he would be able to see reflections in water.  As his eyes grew accustomed to the light, he would be able to look directly at the sun itself. By this point, the freed prisoner would no longer want to return to the cave.</item></list>
<head>What Plato Was Illustrating</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>The Cave is an allegory for the world we live in.  Plato believed that true reality and knowledge resides only in the realm of pure universals (or, as he called it "the world of forms").  For example, when we look at a tree, we see only a reflection of tree-ness - the universal standard of what a tree is.  Our eyes see a physical representation of something that our mind grasps metaphysically.  To Plato, contemplating the world of forms is the highest state of being.  It is like stepping out of the darkness and living in true knowledge of reality.</item></list>
<head>The Implications of Plato's Cave</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>The implications of Plato's epistemological theory is this: our bodies are not "real".  A body is only a reflection of human-ness, that exists in the metaphysical world of forms. To Plato, a human is composed of a soul trapped in a body.  The soul is always fighting against the body, and will only truly be freed when it is unencumbered by physical things and is permitted to freely reside in the world of forms. To oversimplify:  physical = not good ; thoughts/metaphysical/universals = good</item>
<item>Unfortunately, Plato never fully details and develops how he believes his theory fits together (unlike Kant, centuries later, who developed an entire realm to fit in his epistemological theories.).  He is, however, clear in promoting the form as the ultimate reality.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>To read the Allegory of the Cave on your own, locate a copy of Plato's Republic</item>
<item>Plato is one of the fundamental fathers of modern philosophy. Many modern theories of reality and metaphysics are based on his thoughts.</item>
<item>Aristotle, Plato's pupil, came up with a more integrated approach to reality and being.  Using scientific methodology and analytics, his epistemology is still in use today.</item></list>
</text>
