<text id="autogum_whow_doc102" title="Avoid the Urge to Upgrade Your Computer" shortTile="avoid-urge-upgrade" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2010-04-25" dateModified="2018-08-08" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Avoid-the-Urge-to-Upgrade-Your-Computer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Avoid the Urge to Upgrade Your Computer</head><p>Have you been feeling your PC isn't enough lately, maybe you read an article in a PC magazine in which a writer boasts of his $3000 computer, with water cooling, and neon-lights running through the casing? Or maybe you're having trouble resisting the urge to buy that featured video card at the Newegg Online Store? Sometimes upgrades aren't worth it, you may only appreciate them for one game, then wish you had the money back. This article will help you resist the urge to constantly upgrade your computer every time you get money.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Tweak your operating system. There are many ways to increase the performance of your current computer without having to pay for an upgrade. <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Tweak_Vista">Here's a good article to refer to for Windows Vista users.</ref> Many of the tips in that article will also work for both Windows XP and Windows 7 users <figure rend="Avoid the Urge to Upgrade Your Computer Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Think about the reasons you want to upgrade. Did you see a game like Crysis, and you were drooling over the quality of the visuals? If so, try games known for their storyline or multiplayer gameplay, not their graphics. Some good examples would be: <figure rend="Avoid the Urge to Upgrade Your Computer Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Half Life 2, a game set in post-apocalyptic Europe, it's known for an amazing storyline.</item>
<item>Team Fortress 2, this game is an extremely popular multiplayer game, well known for its excellent class design.</item>
<item>Thief: The Dark Project and Thief 2, both are very old 3D games, don't expect good visuals, but they too have an amazing storyline, set in a Victorian-Steampunk world in which you are a thief.</item>
<item>Age of Empires 1 and 2, amazing strategy games in which you lead civilizations to expansion and conquest of either computer players or people online!</item>
<item>Plants vs Zombies, an extremely addictive tower-defense style game in which you build plants to protect your backyard from zombies, this game will even run on Netbooks!</item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Overclock_a_CPU">Overclocking is another way</ref>, albeit risky, to improve your computer's performance. It involves forcing components (usually the CPU, but video cards can be overclocked as well) to perform calculations at higher speeds than their factory defaults. This can put your computer at risk though, especially if you mess around with voltages. <figure rend="Avoid the Urge to Upgrade Your Computer Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Whatever you do, don't attempt to overclock a laptop CPU as your computer will overheat quickly.</item></list></item></list></item>
<item>If you do end up upgrading, don't bother upgrading components that won't show a significant improvement in performance. An example of a component that won't drastically improve speed is the motherboard. Unless your existing motherboard is the lowest of low-end hardware, it should have good performance. <figure rend="Avoid the Urge to Upgrade Your Computer Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find a hobby that doesn't require a high-performance computer. <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Become_a_Programmer">A good example is computer programming</ref>, not only will it provide huge job opportunities if you become good at it, it will also provide a constructive use of your time. <figure rend="Avoid the Urge to Upgrade Your Computer Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>When you make a decision to buy a computer component (i.e Video card), make sure that it is what you want and will be good enough to last at least a year. Sometimes when you find a deal on a computer component, you rush to buy it and in your excitement, you don't realize that maybe it doesn't have a DVI port, and you were planning on buying a new monitor this year. Now, when you go to buy the monitor, and it needs a DVI connection, you will have to buy a new video card. <figure rend="Avoid the Urge to Upgrade Your Computer Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't torture yourself by browsing online stores for parts when you don't need them. You might end up buying something you don't need, like a gold-plated DVI cord.</item>
<item>Don't feel bad about upgrading if your computer seriously needs it, this article assumes you already have a decent computer, if your computer is 10 years old or is a slow laptop, go ahead get a new one.</item></list>
</text>
