<text id="autogum_whow_doc538" title="Wait to Bring Home a New Pet" shortTile="wait-bring-home-new" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-04-14" dateModified="2017-10-20" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Wait-to-Bring-Home-a-New-Pet" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wait to Bring Home a New Pet</head><p>A pet can mean so much to a family. Whether you are going to be getting a bird, fish, dog, cat, unicorn, or whatever it is, you can love them so much! Waiting to bring them home can be excruciating, nobody wants to wait and leave their new best friend in a shelter, or wherever they are when they could be home and bonding with you. Sometimes you just have to wait though, this article should help with that.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Make sure everything is prepared for your pet. You want everything to be perfect for when they come into their new home, so while you're waiting, optimize your environment, and get all the stuff they'll need. A small dog might need you to fill any holes under the fence so they can't escape, come up with where you're going to put dishes,cages,beds.so on. You don't  want there to be a little confusion and problems when you bring them home, so make sure everything is ready! <figure rend="Wait to Bring Home a New Pet Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Bake some treats for them! Everyone loves some delicious home-made food, why wouldn't your pet? A new bird might love some pudding for birds, or maybe your dog would enjoy some fresh baked dog bones. Google some recipes for whatever animal you are getting, and you'll probably find something you'll love to make, and your new friend will love to eat! <figure rend="Wait to Bring Home a New Pet Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Draw pictures, write, or create something depicting them. Whatever you like creating, be it traditional art or Minecraft building, you could try putting together something like your pet, or are excited to do with your pet. Don't worry about being accurate, just enjoy yourself! <figure rend="Wait to Bring Home a New Pet Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do homework, or something else you have due soon. Rather than just waiting, finish up one of your projects you have due. Its important in your life to get this done, you'll also have more spare time for when the pet does come home! <figure rend="Wait to Bring Home a New Pet Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Play and video game, or watch YouTube. Near everyone is entertained this way. If you watch a video maybe one about the type of pet you're bringing home. <figure rend="Wait to Bring Home a New Pet Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Look at images of the pet. Do a Google image search of maybe 'cool fish tanks' or 'cat houses' maybe even 'clothes for turtles' you'd be surprised what comes up. Maybe what you find will help inspire something you can do for your animal. Adding how to into the search will help you find a variety of cool things to do. <figure rend="Wait to Bring Home a New Pet Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep in mind: they'll be home soon! Just keep waiting and being patient. It will be incredible once they finally are with you. Good luck, and have fun! <figure rend="Wait to Bring Home a New Pet Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>When waiting to bring home a new pet, our minds are focused on them. So whatever you're doing, it's best if it relates to the pet as well, because whatever you do, your mind will probably be preoccupied by them anyway.</item></list>
</text>
