<text id="autogum_whow_doc564" title="Sell Puppies" shortTile="sell-puppies" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-05-18" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Sell-Puppies" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Sell Puppies</head><p>Did your dog just have puppies and you need to sell them? Well don't worry or be sad you'll know how to sell your dog in no time!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>So you want to sell a puppy at the proper age. 1 month or 12 weeks is best. <figure rend="Hound.png"></figure></item>
<item>Once the pup is at the proper age you want to sell it. You should start making attractive ads up for the pup such as "Young Stout female bird hound for sale!" Or "Daughter of a champion pup for sale best bird hunting dog!" Like that but only if it's true! Make sure to add her personality to make people see their sweet side. <figure rend="Hound 3.png"></figure></item>
<item>Once you are done you should post the ad where people congregate most. Online is best as people are always on the outlook to adopt baby animals there. Then once your ad is up you want the pup to be ready. You'll need to deworm the dog and make sure she has got all her shots and is properly bathed. Make sure to put their medical info in the ads to let people know what they need before going to the veterinarian. <figure rend="Hound 2.png"></figure></item>
<item>Now you need to clean up any dirty areas the people will be walking in and make sure the puppies bedding area is clean and where you'll be when your selling the puppy. <figure rend="Hound 4.png"></figure></item>
<item>Now you wanna make a sign preferably on cardboard and sit it on the ground, post it on a pole, or put it on the cage your puppy is in and write on it that your selling a puppy unless the puppy already has a request from someone who saw your ad. <figure rend="Hound 5.png"></figure></item>
<item>So make sure you style the pup up with one simple accessory its always something nice to do, like put a collar on her but don't name. <figure rend="Hound 6.png"></figure></item>
<item>Now its time to prepare for saying bye to your pup rub her but only for a very short bit for you might become too attached. And get any tears out if needed in a bathroom privately then make yourself strong again and remember your making another family happy by giving. So keep that in mind. <figure rend="Hound 7.png"></figure></item>
<item>Once the family or person arrives greet them and introduce yourself then show them the puppy! They will interact to get to know each other before the sell is made. The puppy may be scared at first but over time may warm up then be able to leave without much trauma. <figure rend="Hound 8.png"></figure></item>
<item>Once the puppy is with her new owner, don't forget to get the money. The owner will have to pay what the puppy costs before leaving with the puppy. <figure rend="Hound 9 1.png"></figure></item>
<item>After you've dealt with everything you've needed to deal with, wave bye to your puppy and remember you did something good! The puppy is gonna love her new home! <figure rend="Hound 10.png"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Talk to the future owners of your puppy and let them get know the pet through you such as personality traits, allergies, and medical records so  the owner is well prepared to care for the pet and the pet will get used to its new home easier.</item>
<item>If the owner is new to pet ownership, let them know the basics and whatever knowledge you have. You want to make sure the puppy goes to a safe and long lasting home.</item>
<item>If the puppy is still within a young age where it still needs special food and milk, let the future know and what exactly what you feed in order for the puppy to continue its diet in their new home.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Never ever leave the guest unattended in your house. Some people rob in these situations. <figure rend="Hound 13.png"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure the future owner knows their stuff about dogs so your puppy is safe and doesn't potentially get hurt due to lack of proper knowledge.</item>
<item>Make sure the person who visits is safe to be around. If they are unfit or cruel as a potential owner do not sell your puppy to them. If they seem unsafe to be around, do not let them in your house or go through with meeting at the designated place of sale.</item></list>
</text>
