<text id="autogum_whow_doc518" title="Create a Drop Shipped T Shirt Website" shortTile="create-drop-shipped" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2016-09-28" dateModified="2018-03-05" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Create-a-Drop-Shipped-T-Shirt-Website" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Create a Drop Shipped T Shirt Website</head><p>Have you ever wanted to start your own T-Shirt company, but didn't have enough money to purchase inventory? Well drop-shipping is right for you! Drop-Shipping takes all the production and shipment out of your hands, so you can focus on creating your T-Shirt designs and promoting your brand.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Create your Brand Name
<list type="unordered"><item>Many people will gloss over this step thinking it's not that important, but when it comes to clothing and design. Branding is actually <hi rend="italic">very</hi> important!</item>
<item>Come up with a unique name that fits your niche.</item>
<item>If you are having trouble, try writing down all the characteristics of your designs, potential customers, and of yourself. Then just start combining words and see what you come up with!</item></list></item>
<item>Create your website
<list type="unordered"><item>Head to shopify.com</item>
<item>Create an account; You start with a 14 day risk free trial, and you can upgrade at the end of it. 2 weeks should give you enough time to expirement around with shopify, and see if there is any demand for your T-Shirts</item>
<item>You start with a 14 day risk free trial, and you can upgrade at the end of it. 2 weeks should give you enough time to expirement around with shopify, and see if there is any demand for your T-Shirts</item></list></item>
<item>Customize your website
<list type="unordered"><item>In the navigation pane, under "Sales channel", click "Online Store"</item>
<item>Click on "Visit Theme Store"</item>
<item>Click the dropdown menu and select "Clothing &amp; Fashion"</item>
<item>If you aren't looking to pay 180$ for a theme, any free theme will do just fine. (You can always change this later)</item></list></item>
<item>Visit App Store
<list type="unordered"><item>Start by pressing Apps, located in the bottom corner of the sidebar right above settings</item>
<item>Click "Visit Shopify App Store"</item></list></item>
<item>Install Printful
<list type="unordered"><item>Search "Printful"</item>
<item>Install the app by pressing "Install this app" and follow through the registration process</item>
<item>Make sure the email used for registration is the same used for your shopify</item></list></item>
<item>Create your designs
<list type="unordered"><item>No matter what program is used make sure the output is a PNG file</item>
<item>Required dimensions for a normal T-Shirt Design on Printful is 3000 x 3000 with 300 DPI</item>
<item>Below are settings that can be used on PhotoShop and Illustrator. Other programs may have a different layout or different wording but the concept remains the same.</item></list></item>
<item>Upload your designs
<list type="unordered"><item>Select PrintFul on the "Apps" page to begin uploading your first design</item>
<item>Begin by pressing "Add Product" at the top of the page</item></list></item>
<item>Select the products you would like your design on
<list type="unordered"><item>Select whatever style T-Shirt or tank you would like (Be sure to select matching colors)</item>
<item>Although this is a write up on how to DropShip T-Shirts, you can also select other products to put your designs on other products</item></list></item>
<item>Finalize the upload
<list type="unordered"><item>Adjust the positioning accordingly, make sure your design is centered!</item>
<item>Select "Proceed to pricing" when you are done</item></list></item>
<item>Pricing
<list type="unordered"><item>At this point, you could select how much profit you would like to receive from each shirt</item>
<item>Don't be afraid to higher the prices, especially if the designs are high quality</item>
<item>Edit your title &amp; description so that it looks as professional as possible</item>
<item>Once you are done, select "Submit to store"</item></list></item>
<item>I have my first designs uploaded, now what?
<list type="unordered"><item>Now comes the hard part: Getting customers</item>
<item>Try showing your friends your designs and getting feedback on how to improve your site</item>
<item>We live in a very social age, use it to your advantage. Social media advertising is the most effective way to advertise your brand/product.</item>
<item>Research how to improve your search rankings on Google and other search platforms.</item></list></item>
<item>Don't give up
<list type="unordered"><item>This is the most important step of all.</item>
<item>Everything you have done would be for nothing if you give up after 2 weeks of no sales.</item>
<item>It may take days, weeks, or even months to get your first sale. This is normal. Stay Calm and trust in your designs.</item>
<item>Keep your site updated! Keep pushing those designs, and advertise them on social media.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
