<text id="autogum_whow_doc674" title="Get a Little Healthier While Staying Just as Lazy" shortTile="little-healthier" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2010-08-07" dateModified="2019-08-23" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get-a-Little-Healthier-While-Staying-Just-as-Lazy" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get a Little Healthier While Staying Just as Lazy</head><p>Being healthier can be a huge challenge, especially if you don’t have the time or the energy. But there are small changes you can make to your life where you can improve your health and still be lazy. Eat differently, exercise just a tiny bit more, and make a few other small changes to your life to improve your health without making huge changes to your everyday life.
</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Eating Well</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Eat your meals with your nondominant hand. If you’re right-handed, put your fork in your left hand at meals. Using your nondominant hand as your fork hand makes you eat more slowly. Stop eating when you feel full, but not bloated. You’ll eat more slowly and probably consume less food. <figure rend="Gain-Weight-and-Muscle-Step-10-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Add in healthy food. Buy those Milano cookies, but also make an effort to buy frozen fruit for smoothies and snap pea crisps to snack on, too. Over time, try to eat fewer cookies and more of the healthy snacks you have on hand. <figure rend="Lose Weight Quickly and Safely (for Teen Girls) Step 8 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Drink a glass of water before every meal. Water will fill you up a little bit, so you won’t overeat at your next meal. Make it a habit to keep a water bottle near you at all times, whether you’re in your house or on the go. <figure rend="Get Faster at Running Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Drink coffee. People who drink three to five cups of coffee a day are less likely to show early symptoms of heart disease. Don’t skip out of your morning cup of coffee or that afternoon pick me up. <figure rend="Get-Veins-to-Pop-Out-Step-7-Version-4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Eat on smaller plates. People who eat on smaller plates end up eating less food. Buy a few inexpensive smaller plates and bowls if yours are large. You’ll think you’ve eaten more than you have. <figure rend="Lose-Weight-in-3-Days-Step-11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Eat spicy foods. Spicy foods may help to decrease your appetite. Go for extra hot salsa, some chili peppers, or cayenne pepper. Add it to your food for extra flavor and a health boost! <figure rend="Get-Veins-to-Pop-Out-Step-14-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Exercising</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Walk for two minutes every hour. Just two minutes...you can do it! You can even walk in circles around your couch while you watch TV. Walking will help you burn extra calories that would have been stored as fat, had you stayed sitting. <figure rend="Boost-Your-Energy-Level-in-the-Afternoon-Step-7-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Walk backwards. Be sure to look behind you. Walking backwards, even in short bursts, may have huge health benefits. Walking backwards will also work different muscles than walking forwards. <figure rend="Control-Your-Emotions-Step-3-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get your metabolism started early. If you have things to do, such as laundry, taking out the trash, or other chores, do them earlier rather than later. This will kickstart your metabolism. <figure rend="Have-Fun-at-Home-on-a-Saturday-Night-Step-5-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Stand instead of sit. You can still play video games or watch TV, but try to stand for at least half of the time you’re doing so. You can burn up to 750 more calories every week if you stand for 3 hours a day! <figure rend="Have-Fun-with-Your-Girlfriend-Step-2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Making Other Healthy Choices</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Hit the snooze button. Getting plenty of sleep boosts your <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Develop_a_Strong_Immune_System">immune system</ref>, reduces your risk of inflammation, depression, and stress. Plenty of sleep also helps to keep down your weight. It also improves your daily mood, making sure you're taking care of your <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Have_Good_Mental_Health">mental health</ref> as well. <figure rend="Lose-Weight-Quickly-and-Safely-(for-Teen-Girls)-Step-18.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Hang out with your friends. Spending time with friends reduces your stress level and could help you prevent inflammation and keep your blood pressure and heart rate down. Find time to hang out with a friend on weeknights, too, even if you’re exhausted from work or school. It’s healthy! <figure rend="Hang-Out-with-Your-Best-Friend-Step-5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Watch a funny video during work. Take a break from your normal workday to watch a funny video of a cat or a puppy. You will have more energy and be happier in the long run! <figure rend="Enjoy Each Day Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pet your dog or cat. You get the “love hormone,” oxytocin, from just looking at your animal’s face. Spend some quality time with your pet and get a boost of happiness in return. <figure rend="Convince Yourself That You're Happy Being Alone Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Park far away. Even if you go to get fast food, park at the far end of the parking lot so you have to walk. Walking will burn some more calories and help you exercise even a little bit. <figure rend="Overcome-Boredom-Step-12-Version-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Play more active games. Instead of playing games that require sitting, like Xbox or PlayStation, try playing a more active game, like Wii Tennis or Dance Dance Revolution. You can also venture out of the house to play paintball or laser tag.  <figure rend="Be-a-Good-Hiphop-Dancer-Step-5-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try to put aside healthy snacks instead of unhealthy ones. Choose some cherry tomatoes over potato chips, or trail mix over a candy bar.</item>
<item>Eat only half of a hefty portion at a restaurant. Set aside the other half for your lunch the next day.</item>
<item>Pack your lunch at school or work instead of buying it. It’s less expensive and usually healthier!</item>
<item>If you want to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Improve-Your-Health">improve your health</ref> even more, try to exercise for 150 minutes per week and include more fruits and vegetables in your diet.</item>
<item>Drink water.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always consult your doctor for specialized medical advice about your diet and exercise.</item></list>
</text>
