<text id="autogum_whow_doc214" title="Have Great Conversation at Family Dinners" shortTile="great-conversation" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-11-02" dateModified="2017-06-27" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Have-Great-Conversation-at-Family-Dinners" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Have Great Conversation at Family Dinners</head><p>Many sons and daughters have dreaded coming home from either school or work because of the inevitable family dinner conversations. Who knows, you might end up next to your great-aunt Kate who blabs on and on about her cats or next to cousin Joey who rightfully earned his title of prank king. Read this article to have an easier time, and you might find yourself enjoying these dinners!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Review the Seating</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Consider whether there is some rivalry in the family. Or, do some people just not fit together? If that is the case, make sure they sit on opposite sides of the table! <figure rend="Have Great Conversation at Family Dinners Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try to steer the mood towards being a happy one. Who likes to chat with a nemesis for a whole night? Also, it might turn out to be dangerous... <figure rend="Have Great Conversation at Family Dinners Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Sit in a comfortable environment. Put yourself next to friends and people you have no problem being yourself with. <figure rend="Have Great Conversation at Family Dinners Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have a corner for children. It's very annoying when little kids bug you for the whole dinner, so make sure that they have toys to play with and other kids to scream with. <figure rend="Have Great Conversation at Family Dinners Step 4.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Always Have an Escape</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Plan the escape. Inevitably, there are the casualties, so make sure that if you end up with a very boring or annoying person as your side person, that you have an escape. Some ideas are offered next, to help you. <figure rend="Have Great Conversation at Family Dinners Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Fake a call. You can say that your friend is in a homework crisis, or be even less confidential and simply say it's important. <figure rend="Have Great Conversation at Family Dinners Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Say you want to check on your 3-year-old cousin, or in certain cases, your son. Kids are a great diversion from family dinners, because they need so much care and attention. Watch out though, you might find yourself spending the rest of the night with little Johnny! <figure rend="Have Great Conversation at Family Dinners Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use the restrooms. If you desperately need to go to the bathroom, nobody could force you to stay. Just make sure you don't stay away for too long. <figure rend="Have Great Conversation at Family Dinners Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Bring Another Person in the Conversation</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>If you are having trouble keeping the conversation going, include someone else. Group chats can be so much easier and enjoyable, because you can just lay back and listen (or not). <figure rend="Have Great Conversation at Family Dinners Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Being properly engaged</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Make eye contact. Many people expect you to be making eye contact, so do that. <figure rend="Have Great Conversation at Family Dinners Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Stand up straight. This basically shows the person respect. <figure rend="Have Great Conversation at Family Dinners Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't be the one to end the conversation if you don't have a proper excuse. The person might come back later and won't give up until you've heard it all. <figure rend="Have Great Conversation at Family Dinners Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be funny. It is so much more enjoyable to talk to a funny person! Make jokes and laugh when necessary, but make sure you don't overdo it. <figure rend="Have Great Conversation at Family Dinners Step 13.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Laugh even when you don't get the joke, it makes people feel appreciated.</item></list></item>
<item>Be a good audience. Nod when you have to, cry when you have to, and even yell if necessary! The talker needs a confidence booster to keep his or her story interesting on both sides. <figure rend="Have Great Conversation at Family Dinners Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be polite. Don't interrupt unless the speaker asks you a question. <figure rend="Have Great Conversation at Family Dinners Step 15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find a good topic to talk about. It's so much easier to speak if both parties are interested and involved in the conversation. <figure rend="Have Great Conversation at Family Dinners Step 16.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't be negative. Don't try to see everything at a bad angle, it makes the environment worse for you and the other guests. Try to enjoy yourself, and most of the time you will. <figure rend="Have Great Conversation at Family Dinners Step 17.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be yourself! Don't brag about something that's not true, because it's hard to keep up a lie with your family. Plus, nobody judges or hates you at family dinners, it's your family!</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't be too loud or evasive. Don't draw too much attention to yourself, but not too little either, it's rude in both ways.</item></list>
</text>
