<text id="autogum_whow_doc654" title="Play Elimination Nukem" shortTile="play-elimination" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2008-04-23" dateModified="2019-09-05" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Play-Elimination-Nukem" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Play Elimination Nukem</head><p>Elimination Nukem (or Nukemball) is similar to volleyball; however, you catch the ball and throw it over the net rather then hit it. The object is to get all the other team's players out by throwing the ball over the net and getting it to land on their side. If the other team fails to catch it, the player who touched the ball or is closest to the ball when it hits the ground is out.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Set Up</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Get 10 players together; five for each team <figure rend="Play Elimination Nukem Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find a volleyball court or put one together yourself. <figure rend="Play Elimination Nukem Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get a ball that is similar in size to a volleyball or basketball. <figure rend="Play Elimination Nukem Step 3.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Rules</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>To start the game, one player throws it over the net to the other team. <figure rend="Play Elimination Nukem Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>After a player catches the ball, they have 3 seconds to throw it to the other team <figure rend="Play Elimination Nukem Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Once the ball is caught, the player who caught it can't move their feet until they have thrown the ball back. <figure rend="Play Elimination Nukem Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If the ball lands on your side without anyone catching it, the player that touches the ball, or is closest to it when it lands is out. <figure rend="Play Elimination Nukem Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Game play goes until all the players on one side of the court are out. <figure rend="Play Elimination Nukem Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>In order to get back in someone on your team must catch the ball with one hand. This rule sometimes creates controversy; if so, you can always play with standard catches. <figure rend="Play Elimination Nukem Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Golden Arrow</head>
<p>This is an alternative version to the regular game.  One player is chosen to try to earn the title of "Golden Arrow".</p>
<list type="ordered"><item>This player, the arrow, starts on one side of the net by themselves against all other players.</item>
<item>If a player in the opposing team is put out, they join the arrow.</item>
<item>If a player in the arrow's team is put out, they are eliminated from the game.</item>
<item>If the arrow is put out, someone in his/her team must sacrifice themselves for him/her.</item>
<item>If the arrow is put out when by himself, they lose and the game is over.</item>
<item>Should all players in the opposing team be put out, the arrow wins and is officially awarded the title of "Golden Arrow".</item></list>
<p>To make the game more interesting, teams can be given names of goodies and baddies from films, with the arrow being the goody, e.g. The Rebel Alliance.</p>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try to place the ball in an area where the other team is not.</item>
<item>Don't throw the ball very high because this will give the other team more time to run under the ball and catch it.</item>
<item>Keep your eye on the other team, they may try something tricky.</item>
<item>If it's a sunny day throw the ball high so that the other team can't see where the ball is going to land because of the sun.</item>
<item>Make sure you throw the ball really hard so it goes over the net. This can be really hard though.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Getting hit in the head may hurt so try to avoid that.</item>
<item>Running into your own teammate will definitely hurt.</item>
<item>Running into the net may also hurt so don't do that.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Volleyball court</item>
<item>Ball similar in size to a volleyball or basketball</item>
<item>An even number of players</item></list>
</text>
