<text id="autogum_whow_doc585" title="Be Human (Philosophy)" shortTile="human-philosophy" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2017-01-25" dateModified="2018-10-04" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be-Human-%28Philosophy%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be Human (Philosophy)</head>Being human is a lot more complicated than just surviving long enough to reproduce. We all seek a purpose in life and hope to thrive. This will show you step by step what you have to do to be human. These steps/parts don’t need to be followed in any particular order (with the exception of part 0 being first). *Written for a school project*
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Sustain Long Term Survival And Security</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Before you worry about the semantics of the human condition,  make sure you can take care of your physical and safety needs first. These requirements are the first two levels of Maslov’s Hierarchy of Needs, which is another important aspect in being human. You need to make sure you are able to get sufficient daily nutrients and water, along with appropriate shelter for you environment. Once you physical needs are taken care of you need to make sure you are as safe as possible. Living in an area plagued with crime or war will jeopardize your survival, so it’s important to live in a safe and stable place.</item></list>
<head>Establish A Sense Of Self</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Begin to worry about being not just another animal, but a human being. And to be a human you need to have an identity. Being human is a lot more than just being another member of a group of animals working together for survival, it’s about being your own individual person. Figuring out exactly who you are can be tricky though, and is often something that takes a long time. It is important not to rush in deciding who you are. Always remember that people can change, it’s very likely you will be a different person at different times in your life and that’s okay. The step below outline how you can go about finding out who you are</item>
<item>Figure out what you like and potentially what you want to do with your life. Find something your passionate about and ask if it’s something you could gear your life towards. Spend time reading and explore different environments to see what you like. For example, if you know you love food and preparing food, maybe consider taking some cooking classes, and if you’re still young, consider studying culinary arts after high school.</item>
<item>Travel. Travel is very important in developing a sense of self because it exposes you to a large variety of cultures and environments. After seeing different cultures and areas, you can decide where you think you belong. Maybe a certain country would be a more appropriate place for you to live in than the one you currently reside in.</item>
<item>Find role models. It’s hard to figure out who you want to be from scratch, having role models can help you to understand who you might want to be.</item></list>
<head>Develop Relationships</head>
<p>Relationships are incredibly important and one of the most fundamental parts of the human experience. No Man is an island, it’s important to have people you can trust and have fun with.</p>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find like-minded people who share your interests. One of the best ways to start a friendship is to find something to do together. This allows for bonding and can make an activity a lot more enjoyable. A good way to meet people with similar interests is to join a club or sports team.</item>
<item>Develop strong relationships with your family. Your family is a good place to develop lasting relationships since most people are very close with their families and live with them. Find something you like to do or something you like to talk about with someone in your family. For example, if your grandfather likes to play the same kinds of board games you do, set some time aside to create a game night.</item>
<item>Find love and consider starting a family. Friends and family are great, but it’s also important to have someone in your life that you love romantically and can share your life with. Love is a very important part of the human experience, and people who are married often have benefits that other people do not.</item></list>
<head>Find Your Purpose In Life</head>
<p>Finding purpose can be a difficult thing to do, especially when there’s the possibility that we live in a purposeless world. It’s important to find a reason for your existence, and something that fulfills you as a person.</p>
<list type="ordered"><item>Think about how you want to be remembered. A good way to figure out what your purpose should be is to think about how people will view what you’ve done after you’ve died. This will give you an idea of what you should gear your life towards. For example, if you think the most important thing you could do for society is to contribute to scientific understanding, then find some way to work in a setting devoted towards scientific progress.</item>
<item>Find something that’s fulfilling and enjoyable. Everyone doesn’t need to be or aspire to be the man who cures cancer, or solves world hunger, your purpose can be found in what you love to do. For example, if you love computers and video games maybe consider making a blog or writing reviews.</item></list>
<p>_</p>
</text>
