<text id="autogum_whow_doc561" title="Celebrate National Dog Day" shortTile="celebrate-national" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-08-22" dateModified="2019-08-24" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Celebrate-National-Dog-Day" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Celebrate National Dog Day</head><p>The national dog day, celebrated on August 26, is a celebration of dog owners to inspire the spirit of dog-loving and respecting, showing gratitude and honoring our special pet – the dog.  This furry friend is not only our playmate or guide but a lively friend who can inspire people with disabilities.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Understand the celebrations. National Dog Day was first coined by  Colleen Paige, an animal lover, in 2004. It is celebrated by dog lovers to create awareness about adopting dogs and to show concern about the unsafe conditions of some dogs.</item>
<item>Advocate for dogs rights. Although this can be done at any time of year, we can take specific actions to make the day more colorful and important. Some ideas are:
<list type="unordered"><item>Take care of rescued dogs. You can do this by heading to your local animal shelter and volunteering. You might end up deciding to volunteer on a permanent basis.</item>
<item>Buy treats or make homemade treats for rescue dogs. Many animal shelters will accept these as donations, but check on their website to be sure.</item></list></item>
<item>Send dog-related gifts to friends or family members. You could even buy gifts for your dog! For example, a new toy, or a water bowl. Look online for dog-related gifts, and buy them for friends, family, or even their dogs!</item>
<item>Go to dog-related events if they are being held in your area. Community groups or individuals may throw a dog party for all the dogs in the area. If there aren't, why not set one up yourself? You could advertise on social media, and buy treats and toys for all the dogs.</item>
<item>Write about your furry friend, either on a blog or on social media. You could post funny pictures, videos or jokes about your dog, or just write about how much you love them.</item>
<item>Treat your dog. You know your dog best, do something you know they will like. You could give your dog a spa day, go to the park and play ball, there are loads of options! Try to either buy or cook something delicious for your dog and make the day enjoyable for him.</item>
<item>Understand the danger some dogs are in. Most dogs are lucky to have a home and good food, but we should do best for those furry friends who have no home and are without care. They are in the shelters or languishing in the wilderness and are prone to serious risk of starvation, sickness, suffering from severe disease, and even death. Consider ways to help these dogs.
<list type="unordered"><item>Consider donating to a charity that helps animals if you can.</item>
<item>If you can't adopt or donate, spread the message in person and online. One of your friends or family members might be able to help.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
