<text id="autogum_whow_doc640" title="Sport Stacking" shortTile="sport-stacking" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-09-30" dateModified="2018-09-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Sport-Stacking" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Sport Stacking</head><p>Sport Stacking is a sport where you stack 12 special designed cups (the only brand that's recognized by the World Sport Stacking Association is the Speed Stacks) in several different stacks of pyramids. Competitive stacks includes the 3-3-3, the 3-6-3 and the Cycle.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Before the lesson</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Understand the terminology. Your leading hand is called <hi rend="italic">Hand #1</hi>, your other hand is called <hi rend="italic">Hand #2</hi>. When you stack your cups into pyramids, it is called <hi rend="italic">Upstack</hi>. When you slide down your cup, it is called <hi rend="italic">Downstack</hi>.
<list type="unordered"><item>For teaching purposes, these instructions are written for a right-hand dominant stacker. Left-hand dominant stackers can reverse the instructions for left and right hand. Be sure to practice each step several times before moving on to the next step.</item></list></item>
<item>Keep the stacking movement smooth and light. Stacking with force doesn't make you stack faster, and it is bad for your cups.</item>
<item>Start slow and take your time to learn each step. Once you've got each stack mastered, you can speed it up, practice, practice, practice and shoot for record times.</item></list>
<head>The Basis to Competitive Stack - 3</head>
<head>Upstack</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Start with 3 cups staked on top of each other.</item>
<item>Lift the top cup with hand #1 and set it next to the bottom cup.</item>
<item>Lift the middle cup with your hand #2 and place it on top. You now have a pyramid made from three cups.</item></list>
<head>Downstack</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Place hand #1 around the side of the top cup and your hand #2 around the side of the bottom left cup.</item>
<item>Slide the top cup down to the bottom right cup.</item>
<item>Bring the cup in hand #2 up, over, and down onto the middle cup. You are now back to your original stack of 3 cups and ready to go again.</item></list>
<head>The Basic Stack: The 3-3-3 Stack.</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Make three stacks of three three cups.</item>
<item>Upstack each stack, working from left to right. You can only upstack one stack at a time.</item>
<item>Go back and downstack from left to right. You must <hi rend="italic">always</hi> go back to the beginning to downstack.</item></list>
<head>The Six Stack</head>
<p>The fastest way to build a 6 is called the 3-2-1 method. Learn this method and practice it over and over.</p>
<head>Upstack</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Start with 6 cups. Pick up 3 cups with your right hand and two cups with your left hand, leaving 1 cup in the center.</item>
<item>Put the bottom cup from your right hand to the right of the center cup.</item>
<item>Put the bottom cup from your left hand to the left of the center cup. You now have three cups next to each other; this is the base for the stack.</item>
<item>Put the now-bottom cup in your right hand on top of the center and right cups of the base.</item>
<item>Put the cup in your left hand next to it. You now have a stack with two layers.</item>
<item>Put the last cup from your right hand on top of the stack.
<list type="unordered"><item>In short, the order for putting down the cups is <hi rend="italic">Right - left - right - left - right</hi> if you're right-handed, or <hi rend="italic">Left - right - left - right - left</hi> if you're left-handed.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Downstack</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Place your right hand on top of the 6 stack and your left hand on the left cup from the middle layer.</item>
<item>Slide down the right with your right hand and the left with your left hand at the same time.</item>
<item>Pick up the 3 cups in right hand and the 2 cups in left hand.</item>
<item>Put them back in one stack of 6.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always grab and hold cups with your hands on the sides of the cups, never on top of the cups.</item>
<item>Use a "light, soft touch". Slide the cups down, don't slam them down.</item></list>
</text>
