<text id="autogum_whow_doc131" title="Make a Walking Robot" shortTile="make-walking-robot" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2016-06-06" dateModified="2019-05-13" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-a-Walking-Robot" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make a Walking Robot</head><p>If you want to make a robotic animal a four legged walking robot is a good place to start. This DIY robot can be made out of a sheet of polycarb or other durable material, small machine screws, small eye screws, rubber bands, string, batteries, and a dc motor. This project will require some electronics experience. These directions are just a place to start, you can make adjustments as you go.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Cut polycarb into multiple one centimeter wide strips</item>
<item><figure rend="Capture 71.png"></figure>Cut strips into 8-7 cm pieces, 4-3 cm pieces, 2-10 cm pieces, 2-5 cm pieces and 4-4 cm pieces.</item>
<item><figure rend="Pic3x1.png"></figure>Drill holes slightly larger than your string in both ends of the 3 cm pieces and in the middle of 4 of the 7 cm pieces (thigh) <figure rend="Pic2 5.png"></figure></item>
<item><figure rend="Pic4 4.png"></figure>In the same 4 1x7 cm pieces (thigh), in one corner cut diagonally from halfway across the short side to 1 cm up the long side.</item>
<item>Choose a drill bit that would allow your machine screws move freely through the hole but not wobble.
<list type="unordered"><item><figure rend="Pic5 5.png"></figure>In the same 4 pieces (thigh) drill holes 1.5 cm from both sides</item>
<item><figure rend="Pic6 4.png"></figure>In the other 4 1x7 pieces (calf) drill holes 0.5 cm from one end</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Pic7 9.png"></figure>Use 4 machine screws to attach, but do not tighten, each type of 1x7 pieces (thigh and calf) with the diagonal cut in the center</item>
<item><figure rend="Pic8 7.png"></figure>Using super glue, glue the 1x3 cm pieces on the calf so the long edge lines up with the end of the thigh piece, this should be 3 cm from the edge. The legs should be able to move freely in one direction, similar to a person's leg.</item>
<item>To make feet:
<list type="unordered"><item><figure rend="Pic9 5.png"></figure>cut 8 4x2 cm pieces with a slight curve in one of the long sides</item>
<item><figure rend="Pic10 5.png"></figure>glue one to the end of each leg with the curve down</item>
<item><figure rend="Pic_a2.png"></figure>use machine screws with multiple nuts on them to connect the other foot pieces so there is a space between them, they should be able to stand on their own</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Pic12 4.png"></figure> <figure rend="Pic11 4.png"></figure>At the top of your legs, 0.5 cm from the edge, drill a hole that your eye screw will tightly slide into then with a slightly smaller drill bit drill holes 1 cm from the ends of the 1x10 cm pieces(body). Use the eye screws to attach each leg to the body, they should move freely and all knees should be facing one direction.</item>
<item>Modify two servo motors
<list type="unordered"><item>remove the 4 screws holding it together</item>
<item>remove electrical components</item>
<item>unclip potentiometer</item>
<item>remove foam block</item>
<item>put everything except the potentiometer and foam block back together</item></list></item>
<item>Using more strips of polycarb attach the motors to the underside of the body in the center.</item>
<item>Add the round gear accessory to the servo and place eye screws at the top and bottom of the motors</item>
<item>Drill a hole for a machine screw 0.5 cm from the end on one side of the 1x4 cm pieces, on the other side drill a hole for a eye screw 0.5 cm from the end</item>
<item>With a machine screw attach one 1x4 cm piece to the remaining large holes in each leg. Use a eye screw to attach the other end to an off center hole in the gear of the motor, both pieces should be stacked on the same screw.</item>
<item>Cut a rubber band and run it through the hole in the 1x3 piece that is in the front, and the remaining small hole in the thigh, tie so the leg stays straight, and repeat for all the legs.</item>
<item>Tie the string to the eye screw connected to the motor, run it through the eye screw above the motor, through the eye screw at the top of the back leg, and tie the other end to the other hole in the 1x3 piece, make sure the string is tight enough that it just barely starts to pull on the leg when the leg is all the way back. Repeat using the eye screw above the motors for back legs and the eye screw below the motors for front legs</item>
<item>Glue the 1x5cm pieses to the front and back of the body pieces to connect both sides</item>
<item>Connect a battery holder to the motors</item>
<item>Add rubber bands to feet for traction as needed</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can skip step 10 and use another dc motor but servo motors have convenient housings and accessories.</item></list>
</text>
