<text id="autogum_whow_doc408" title="Use an Oekaki" shortTile="use-oekaki" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2006-11-23" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Use-an-Oekaki" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Use an Oekaki</head><p>Drawing on the computer is hard, but an oekaki (doodling and painting program) can make it more simple than it appears. This can help you use an oekaki so you can stop using that horrible MS-Paint!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find an oekaki that seems fitting to your level. <figure rend="Use an Oekaki Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Go to draw, if that is what it is under. <figure rend="Use an Oekaki Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pick out which program you want to use. Shi-painter is a tricky one, but in a way it's easy. In Shi-painter, you can have a rainbow of colors that you pick out, and you have a new tool called pen. Pen makes it seem like a real pencil drawing. If you get the hang out this, then try Shi-painter Pro. <figure rend="Use an Oekaki Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If Shi-painter isn't for you, try PaintBBS. Palette is good for it because it gives you more colors. <figure rend="Use an Oekaki Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>OekakiBBS is a good one, and it has a different way of sizing the point of the pen. Usually, oekakiBBS won't allow you to submit your art, so I would avoid using this one. <figure rend="Use an Oekaki Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pick whatever one you want, and start sketching. For sketching, use a different color other than black. Such as, for the eyes use orange, or for the head use green. Switch colors often so you will know where a part ends. <figure rend="Use an Oekaki Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Now go over the lines with a darker color, or just use black. <figure rend="Use an Oekaki Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Add detail. <figure rend="Use an Oekaki Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Color using And or Div. <figure rend="Use an Oekaki Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you feel like you are finished send it. Type out a comment about your drawing, and type out a title. <figure rend="Use an Oekaki Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Ask for crits if you want to improve. <figure rend="Use an Oekaki Step 11 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you want to find an oekaki of your level, and are a beginner, go to an oekaki without try-outs. Suta Raito Sketch oekaki is a good one, and so is EP oekaki.</item>
<item>If someone says such things as, 'Your art sucks!' don't let it get to you!</item>
<item>If you want 'crits' then say so, but if you don't say so too, because in a normal oekaki they WILL give crits.</item>
<item>The bezier tool helps!</item>
<item>Get your own style, so people notice you!</item>
<item>If you want help on your figure for drawing, ask for a redline.</item>
<item>Mask is good for going over lines in black. And is good for coloring, and so on. These are simple tools.</item>
<item>If you feel as though your drawing isn't great, then don't send it! But if you really want to do.</item>
<item>You can Safety save, or S.S. your unfinished works.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are trying out for a normal or advanced oekaki and are just a beginner in oekakis, then you should wait, because they will crit you.</item>
<item>If you spam, you will have a warning.</item>
<item>Crits can be harsh!</item>
<item>Sometimes your drawing might close, so use PRT SCR (print screen) button often!</item>
<item>Your artwork might get bumped off quickly, so save it!</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>A computer.</item>
<item>A basic skill of drawing and coloring.</item>
<item>Internet.</item>
<item>Not needed, but helps: Tablet.</item></list>
</text>
