<text id="autogum_whow_doc455" title="Spot a Bad Contractor" shortTile="spot-bad-contractor" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2008-07-03" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Spot-a-Bad-Contractor" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Spot a Bad Contractor</head><p>When you're planning on doing up, changing or fixing a part of your home or garden, it pays to know who is likely to do a good job for value. And that means knowing who might be a bad bet as a contractor. Many people have had a bad contractor experience. These experiences come in all sorts of flavors, from bad workmanship to unfinished work to "unforeseen" cost over-runs, or in the worst case, the contractor skips town with your money and does no work. This article aims to point out the problem signs <hi rend="italic">before</hi> you sign on the dotted line.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be wary of a deal that's too good to be true. Watch out if the contractor in question's bid was far below all of the others. This is a sure sign that the contractor is either unfamiliar with the work in question (and therefore also probably new to the work), or has underbid on purpose because he intends to have cost over-runs later. Another play on this theme is if the contractor offers a great bargain in order to use "your project" as an example, such as featuring it on a website or in a brochure. <figure rend="Spot a Bad Contractor Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Ask for references. Beware the contractor who has questionable or no references and or no fixed business address. Always ask for references; if the contractor does good work, he will have many, many examples of this through his references. Any contractor that does not have a fixed business address could be a fly-by-night operation. If you are suspicious of any address provided, turn up to see if it exists before you sign up. <figure rend="Spot a Bad Contractor Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have a written agreement. Be very cautious when the contractor does not want to go through the formalities of signing a contract. When you are doing any major work, a contract that spells out what the scope of work is, and what the contractor's responsibilities are, is standard business practice and any person who does not want to follow that is suspect. <figure rend="Spot a Bad Contractor Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Trust your gut instinct. When you get a bad feeling, trust your gut feeling; the guy who seems like a sleazy sales man probably is. High pressure sales tactics such as "This price is only valid until I walk out of that door, you have to sign this right now..." are a very bad sign. If you feel hassled, pushed, intimidated or bullied, this isn't the contractor for you. <figure rend="Spot a Bad Contractor Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Seek another opinion. Be very cautious of the contractor who uses scary scenarios to get you to buy more expensive options or more extensive work than what you initially wanted. If problems are uncovered during a project, they should be obvious. Like a doctor, you can always get a second opinion. <figure rend="Spot a Bad Contractor Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do your own research. Use the internet to learn as much as possible about the product or services that you want for your home or garden. If you are fairly knowledgeable about the product or service, you will be familiar with the lingo, you will be able to ask pertinent questions, and it will be clear to the contractor that you know what you want and this will scare off a bad contractor or can lead them to say things that you know are wrong or poorly informed. <figure rend="Spot a Bad Contractor Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Ask people whose advice you value. The best way to find a good contractor is to ask your friends, family or neighbors. More often then not, they have used somebody with a good result. Be extremely wary of the guy who pulls up in front of your house out of the blue and tells you that you need a new roof (or something else). Best to tell that person to be on his way. Additionally, many locations require contractors to have licenses. If you live in one of those locations, it is perfectly reasonable to ask for a copy of the contractors license and insurance certificate. No show, no go. <figure rend="Spot a Bad Contractor Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Guard yourself against possible retaliation. If you have fired a contractor who you provided a key to access your home, change your locks as soon as possible. Best to leave temptation at the door rather than let it through. <figure rend="Spot a Bad Contractor Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you feel that you have been ripped off, call the local authorities. Blatant theft, such as a contractor took your money and left town, should be reported to the police. Other situations may need to be handled through civil courts, The Better Business Bureau or other organizations.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Sighting of license or other professional standards documents</item>
<item>Contract</item>
<item>References, word-of-mouth</item>
<item>Examples/samples of work done elsewhere</item>
<item>Second opinions (consider at least 2 or 3 contractors for any major home job)</item></list>
</text>
