<text id="autogum_whow_doc197" title="Handle Parenting Criticism" shortTile="handle-parenting" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-10-10" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Handle-Parenting-Criticism" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Handle Parenting Criticism</head><p>Often times as parents, we feel as though we are trying our best, and criticism from other parents can trigger a parent to become self-conscious and lower their self-esteem as a parent. It can be very tough being a parent in and of itself, however, there is more to parenting than just being a mother or a father. Parents often need ways to handle harsh criticism on their parenting skills. This article will hopefully help with how to deal with this obstacle in a parent's life. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Educating Yourself</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Prepare yourself mentally of responsibilities of parents. Know that becoming a parent is a big step in one's life. It comes with responsibilities and changes we should become familiar with. These changes can begin from the moment a mother is pregnant until the child has grown up. Often times we become overwhelmed with the responsibilities. Therefore, mental preparation is important  <figure rend="Forgive an Abusive Parent Step 15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Research daily parenting skills. As parents, we are a significant part of a child's life. It is important that we are aware of the skills we should obtain in order to provide a stable life for our children. <figure rend="Choose a Paper Topic Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Apply each skill in your daily life. In order to become better at parenting, we need to apply the research we have done to enhance our skills further. This step allows us to see the pros and cons and the way children react to certain things we often implement. We need to try new things in order to make lasting changes as parents. <figure rend="Use Psychology to Win Chess Games Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Allow yourself to understand that it is okay not to be perfect. Applying skills you have already researched (mentioned in the previous step) may not always go as planned. Parents and children are similar but they also vary from family to family. At times like this, it can become frustrating, so try not to compare yourself to others, because no one is perfect at parenting.  <figure rend="Survive Overthinking Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Being Proactive About Criticism</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Ask for advice from other parents. Often times those that are experienced parents can offer advice that can help you. Every parent tries different methods. Therefore, it's important to try new methods if old ones do not work.  <figure rend="Deal with Homework Frustration As a Parent Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Listen to other parents that harshly criticize you. Sometimes parents are faced with criticism that can be really cruel. This can affect parents' mental strength and self-esteem as parents. However, it is important to listen to these criticisms. Not to let people walk all over you, but to use the criticism to better yourself as a parent.However, it is important that you know yourself as a parent. This way you can take out the advice or criticisms that do not pertain to your idealistic parenting skills or who you are. Your goal and values are also very important. <figure rend="Develop Listening Skills Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Turn the criticism into advice. Even though it might have appeared harsh, remember what your goal is. Turning criticism into advice shows a positive attitude and a strong mind. Always remember,  <figure rend="Control Your Mind Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do further research and reevaluate. This time around, use research you have already done and include the advice and criticism you have received. Reevaluate your actions and find ways to make them better. Parenting is a process of learning and adapting to change. Therefore, reevaluating your actions can result in success.  <figure rend="Take Notes on a Book Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Apply what you now know. Each skill you have obtained as a parent can now be exercised using different methods when you reevaluated.</item></list>
<head>Staying Focused on Your Kids</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be confident. As a parent, it is vital that we show our children we are confident. We need to stay motivated and have courage. Effectiveness as a parent can be related to self-confidence. When you are confident, you can carry out solutions to obstacles as parents. <figure rend="Build Self Confidence Step 2 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be consistent. By this step, you should have a significant change in your attitude. You are well aware of the mistakes, and you have corrected them. If not, repeat step 8. Implement and exercise the skills you have obtained with your children consistently. This can result in adaptability to newer changes. Our judgments, when we are introduced to a new obstacle, will become better because of our consistency with other skills we implement. This also helps your children understand what role you play and build their trust in whatever you do because it is consistently implemented.  <figure rend="Be Consistent Step 10 Version 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be driven by your self-improvement as a parent. This allows you to build self-confidence, a stronger mentality, and a positive energy for your children and yourself. <figure rend="Build a Positive Attitude Step 3 Version 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Watch your offspring grow as you improve as a parent. This is a rewarding feeling as you grow closer to your children.  <figure rend="Be Loved by Your Family Step 14.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
