<text id="autogum_whow_doc605" title="Face Your Shadow" shortTile="face-shadow" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2013-05-14" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Face-Your-Shadow" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Face Your Shadow</head>          In Jungian psychology, the "Shadow" is an archetype that represents the unconscious "dark side" of an individual or group. This side is often composed of repressed, disowned, unrecognized, or unexpressed needs, feelings, and personality traits. Sometimes, in the process of stuffing things away (to either cope with a trauma or become more acceptable to others), we bury positive things about ourselves as well as negative - like a talent, etc. The longer we continue to repress or refuse to acknowledge or integrate this side into our conscious ego, the meaner it gets. From there, it begins to affect our relationships with others by causing us to project our negative (or even positive) qualities onto them. The "Shadow" is similar to the "id" in Sigmund Freud's model of the psyche.
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Figure out who in your life you project on the most - this may be the closest person to you, whom you spend a lot of time with or it can be your "epitome of evil" in society. <figure rend="Face Your Shadow Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>List all the qualities about this person or group of people that you despise or feel jealous, judgmental, or afraid of. <figure rend="Face Your Shadow Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Think of the ways that you display those same qualities or traits. It can be in different contexts or to a lesser degree, or maybe you even wish you could be like that. <figure rend="Face Your Shadow Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep acknowledging and taking responsibility for your Shadow. <figure rend="Face Your Shadow Step 4.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Use The Arts to create "dark" stories, poetry, music, drawings, paintings, movies, etc. Start with a conscious decision to do it for the purpose of Shadow Work. That means you'll need to go back and read, listen, or look later.</item>
<item>Pay attention to the "shadowy" creatures and themes as well as any "villains", if applicable. What are they like? How are they similar to you? Do you wish you could do the things they do if you knew you'd get away with it?</item>
<item>Pay attention to your dreams; write them down if you remember them.</item>
<item>Pay close attention to the feelings and thoughts involved and how you act on them.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Shadow Work isn't easy and you may feel very uncomfortable with what you find lurking there. The more you resist accepting that it is a part of you, the stronger and longer 'it' will fight with you.</item>
<item>Individuals with certain "high conflict" personality disorders are prone to projection and will often accuse their targets of the same. Everyone projects to some degree, but a disordered mind usually won't take any steps to integrate their Shadow as they're content to let others to carry that baggage for them.</item>
<item>Once you start, there's no going back.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Courage</item>
<item>Objectivity (maybe a trusted friend can help with this)</item>
<item>Supplies/Equipment for writing, art, or music</item></list>
</text>
