<text id="autogum_whow_doc088" title="Dismantle a Computer" shortTile="dismantle-computer" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-10-14" dateModified="2019-10-14" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Dismantle-a-Computer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Dismantle a Computer</head><p>This is a step-by-step guide for people to follow when completely taking a computer apart.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>You are going to start off by removing the side panels on the computer case. These panels are often secured by a few screws on the back of the case. Unscrew the screws then slide the side panels off.  <figure rend="Back of computer case1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>After the panels are off, you will see the motherboard. There will be multiple cables coming off of the motherboard that run back to the power supply, hard drive(s), fan(s), and possibly more depending on the computer. Go ahead and unplug all of these cables from the motherboard.  <figure rend="Inside of the computer.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>After you unplug all of the cables that are attached to the motherboard, go ahead and unplug any cables that attached to the drives towards the front of the computer.  <figure rend="Inside of the computer2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Now that all of the power supply cables are unplugged, you can now remove the power supply. On the back of the case, there will be at least four screws holding the power supply in place. Go ahead and start unscrewing those screws. If the power supply is mounted in the top section of the case, be sure to hold it as you are unscrewing so that it does not drop!  <figure rend="Back of computer case2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>After the power supply is removed, look to see if there is anything plugged into the motherboard's PCI slot(s). If so go ahead unscrew the screw holding the card in place. Once you do that, you can push the tab in on the PCI slot to remove the card.  <figure rend="Inside of the computer3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>After the PCI card(s) is removed, you can now take the motherboard out of the case. The motherboard is screwed onto the multiple case stand-offs. Go ahead and unscrew all of these screws. (It is recommended to lay the computer on its side for this step.)  <figure rend="Inside of the computer4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>After you remove the motherboard, go ahead and remove all of the drives from the drive cage at the front of the computer case. These drives are going to be held in tray that will just slide straight out of the drive cage. If you wish, you can remove the drives from the tray by unscrewing the four screws that secure the drives to the tray.  <figure rend="Inside of the computer5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>At this point, all components should be removed from the computer case. The only thing remaining is the RAM and the CPU still attached to the motherboard. To remove the RAM, just push on the tabs found on the end of the sticks and it will just pop out.  <figure rend="Inside of the computer6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>The last thing to do is to remove the CPU from the motherboard. The CPU is under the CPU cooler. In order to remove the CPU cooler, pull up on the four tabs around the fan and it should just pop off.  <figure rend="Inside of the computer7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>The CPU will just lift out of its socket and then all the components to the computer will be disassembled.</item></list>
</text>
