<text id="autogum_whow_doc087" title="Install a Virtual Machine on Your Computer" shortTile="install-virtual-machine" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-10-07" dateModified="2019-10-20" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Install-a-Virtual-Machine-on-Your-Computer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Install a Virtual Machine on Your Computer</head><head>Steps</head>
<head>Create Space on Computer</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Make enough space. If you don't have enough storage to install a VM machine, consider uninstalling any programs that aren't currently being used. <figure rend="PicNo1.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Having enough space on your laptop or pc will make visualBox run smoothly without any lag.</item></list></item>
<item>Restart the computer. <figure rend="PicN2.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>After uninstalling unused apps restart your computer.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Downloading Virtual Machine Apk</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open a web browser and go to your selected virtual machine providers website.  <figure rend="Prospect4.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Search for download links.</item></list></item>
<item>Before installing link ensure that the website has a secure icon on the web browser. <figure rend="Prospect6.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Ensure that a website is secure before installing anything unto your computer</item>
<item>Installing applications from an unsecured website might make your laptop vulnerable for hacks or trojan virus.</item></list></item>
<item>Follow the instructions. If the web page is a secure process to the download link and accepts any additional instructions that come up. <figure rend="VirtualBox234.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If web pages are secure click on the download link and at the bottom of your laptop screen, you will see the file downloading.</item>
<item>Never install a file from an unsecured website, because it could make your computer vulnerable for hacks and virus</item></list></item></list>
<head>Installing a Virtual Machine</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Launch the installer. After the download completes, start the installer. The installer will be located in the location specified when it was downloaded. <figure rend="PicNo4.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>On your web browser search for downloads and you will be able to see your file.</item></list></item>
<item>After launching the installer, setup procedures will appear <figure rend="Annotation 2019 10 18 150014.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>keep clicking next on the installer.</item></list></item>
<item>Accept Network Interfaces. <figure rend="Annotation 2019 10 18 150014567889.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Accept any form of network prompt that pops up.</item></list></item>
<item>Create icons. Be sure to create a desktop icon and start menu icon for easy access to the virtual machine. <figure rend="Pictures897.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Allows you to easily access the applications on your home screen.</item></list></item>
<item>Accept any other installation and Click Finish. <figure rend="Prospect899.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Depending on your computer, you might get extra options, but after that click Finish.</item></list></item>
<item>Restart.
<list type="unordered"><item>Restarting your computer will make all the changes you have made to be applied quickly</item></list></item></list>
<head>Running an Operating System on a Visual Machine</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Download your Desired Operating system ISO File. <figure rend="PicNo5.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Different operating systems that could be used would be Windows,macOS, Mint, chrome os, ubuntu, arch Linux, etc.</item></list></item>
<item>Once Download is complete, Launch VirtualBox. <figure rend="Toolsl.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Once you have downloaded your desired operating system, Launch VirtualBox or any other virtual machine that you have chosen to run your OS on.</item></list></item>
<item>Once VisualBox is launched click on New. <figure rend="Pictures344567.png"></figure></item>
<item>Provide a name for the Operating system. <figure rend="Napmespcs.png"></figure></item>
<item>Choose Operating system space. <figure rend="Slection.png"></figure></item>
<item>Select VirtualDisk Type. <figure rend="Disk.png"></figure></item>
<item>Attach OS File to visualBox. <figure rend="Svaefile788.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Click on settings and choose storage.</item></list></item>
<item>On Storage attach your operating system file. <figure rend="770.png"></figure></item>
<item>Select ubuntu and Click Start. <figure rend="Debo4ir.png"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure your operating system can support the programs that you intend to install</item>
<item>Ensure that you have enough space on your laptop or pc to avoid storage errors while installing the virtual machine and other components</item></list>
<head>Things you'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Computer running Windows 7, 8, or 10</item>
<item>Internet Connection</item>
<item>Enough Storage Space</item>
<item>Laptop or PC</item></list>
</text>
