<text id="autogum_whow_doc061" title="Rock out in a Car" shortTile="rock-out-car" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2008-03-09" dateModified="2015-11-11" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Rock-out-in-a-Car" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Rock out in a Car</head><p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/rock%20out">Definition</ref></hi>: To totally enjoy a song, especially rock and roll
</p>
<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=rock+out">Definition</ref></hi>:   Where you are compelled by the total arse-kicking-ness of a song (mainly rock and metal) to go ballistic. This can include air guitaring, jumping around, showing the horns and generally making an arse out of yourself. But it's alright, cause you're Rocking Out!
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">The "Rock Out"</hi> has history going back hundreds of thousands of years.  It is well documented in cave paintings and clay tablets that even the most early of humans rocked out to a mean beat. At the time, this was done by means of crude animal skin drums, clubs, and howls; not unlike the street performers of today's metropolises. Luckily, in this day and age there are more sophisticated methods for creating that head-banging musical miracle, particularly useful for mobile rockin' outage. This wikiHow will guide you on your way to an epic rock out in the most common form of mobile transportation, the Automobile.
</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Learn as much as you can about Rocking Out from <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Rock_Out">How to Rock Out</ref>.</item>
<item>Be in a car. <hi rend="italic">Caution:</hi> This is not for the novice driver. Attempting and engaging in rock outs as a vehicle is in motion should be reserved for the master driver/rocker combo. Besides stop lights are where the magic happens. <figure rend="Rock out in a Car Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Blast some rocking music. Music choice is pivotal so be sure to select a track that you fully enjoy and that allows you to thoroughly immerse every fiber of your being in the rock out experience. <figure rend="Rock out in a Car Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Capture the essence of your music choice in your rock out. Thugging it? Lean back a bit. Get your pimp hand ready. Throw them bows. Initiate the cool thug head bob. Angrily thrashing? Don't hit your head on the steering wheel. Whimsically singing along? Sway. Engage side to side head tilt. Whatever your soundtrack, try to express and capture its essence, its flavor in your rock out. Most importantly, be creative and own it! <figure rend="Rock out in a Car Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>You're confined but not inhibited. Because you are in a confined space and limited in your range of moves, perfecting the auto rock out is truly an art. Don't let the confines of the steel enclosure inhibit your rock out! The rock out need not be bound to the upper body (e.g., head, arms, &amp; shoulders). 'Wiggle dat ass', shake them hips...like a Polaroid picture (typically a move best reserved for forced breaks in motion e.g., stoplights) <figure rend="Rock out in a Car Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Share. Typically most rock outs take place in the comforting arms of solitude which is nice but don't deprive the world of your rocking out capabilities. Recruit friends to participate in a group rock out session a la automobile. At stop lights, engage your audience - point at, sing to, gesture (politely) to, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Smile">smile</ref> at, invite your fellow road warriors to the rock out. Most importantly, demonstrate that you enjoy and are perfectly alright with making an ass out of yourself and inspire someone else to do the same. Rock outs are contagious and addictive. <figure rend="Rock out in a Car Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Utilize these gestures to enhance the rock out:</hi><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corna">Corna</ref></hi> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fist_pump">Fist-Pump</ref> </hi> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Headbanging">Headbanging</ref></hi> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=gangsta+lean">Gangster Lean</ref></hi> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=hip+check">Hip Check</ref></hi> (Generally reserved for dual vehicle occupancy and bench seating) <hi rend="bold">Toe Tap</hi><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.ehow.com/how_15104_play-air-drums.html">Air Drumming</ref></hi></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Proceed with caution when fully utilizing that sound system you put in your car that one weekend with the buddies which is actually worth more than your car's Kelly Blue Book value. The results can include bodily injury, blown stereo equipment, or even involvement of city and state fire protection agencies. If you rock out too hard, things can go wrong so raise it up to eleven at your own risk.  Watch <ref target="http://break.com/index/air-bag-knocks-driver-out.html">this</ref> to see what could potentially occur.</item></list>
</text>
