<text id="autogum_whow_doc410" title="Respond when Someone Wishes You Happy Birthday" shortTile="respond-someone-wishes" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2012-08-20" dateModified="2019-09-12" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Respond-when-Someone-Wishes-You-Happy-Birthday" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Respond when Someone Wishes You Happy Birthday</head><p>It's your birthday! It's great to see that your friends care about you, but what's an appropriate way to respond? In person, just say "Thank you!" If the well-wishes are sent over social media or physical mail, the etiquette can be a little different, but it's not difficult to learn.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>On Social Media</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Post one thank you message. If you use social media frequently, you might get birthday wishes from acquaintances, old friends, and people you don't even remember. Even your friends are probably not waiting anxiously to receive a personalized response. One message to your wall thanking everyone for the birthday wishes is common practice, and unlikely to offend anyone. Here are some example responses: <figure rend="Respond when Someone Wishes You Happy Birthday Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Thank you everyone for the birthday wishes! I'm having a great time!</hi></item>
<item><hi rend="bold">One man. One birthday. So many great birthday messages.:)</hi></item>
<item><hi rend="bold">IT'S MY BIRTHDAY SO I GET TO USE CAPS LOCK. Thank you for the kind thoughts everyone!</hi></item>
<item>Check out the examples section for more ideas.</item></list></item>
<item>Post a picture instead (optional). If you want to thank people in a more visible way, take a photo of your smiling face in a party hat, a birthday cake, or another birthday symbol. Post it along with a comment thanking everyone for their birthday wishes. This shows that you put a little effort into making your thanks special, but is still fairly simple to do. <figure rend="Respond when Someone Wishes You Happy Birthday Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Reply to messages that go the extra distance. If someone posts a long, heartfelt birthday wish over social media, reply to it in person. Post a reply at least three sentences long. You can reply directly to the comment, or in a private message. There's no need to respond with a new post on the other person's wall. <figure rend="Respond when Someone Wishes You Happy Birthday Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Older relatives, "low tech" people, and people who don't use social media much are all more likely to expect an individual response.</item>
<item>You can use the opportunity to reconnect with friends you haven't seen in a long time, even if they only posted a short message for your birthday.</item></list></item>
<item>Respond briefly to other posts (optional). As mentioned above, there is no need to respond to every person individually. However, if you'd like to take the extra time, you could "Like" each Facebook post, or reply to any social media post with a short comment such as "Thanks for thinking of me!" or "Thanks, I appreciate it!" <figure rend="Respond when Someone Wishes You Happy Birthday Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>In Person</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Thank someone in person. When possible, thank someone in person after he gives you a birthday present, or puts extra effort into a birthday wish. Give each friend or group of friends your full attention, smile, and make eye contact while delivering your thanks. Here are some ideas on how to do it: <figure rend="Respond when Someone Wishes You Happy Birthday Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Your card meant a lot to me. It really cheered me up.</hi></item>
<item><hi rend="bold">That was the perfect birthday gift! You know me so well.</hi></item>
<item>See the example section below for more ideas.</item></list></item>
<item>Send a card, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Respond_to_a_Thank_You_Email">email</ref> or letter. Relatives and friends older than yourself tend to appreciate receiving a thank you card in the mail. Always add a handwritten message. A short thank you message is fine, but adding a heartfelt message is recommended for people who have been unusually generous or kind. <figure rend="Respond when Someone Wishes You Happy Birthday Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Look at the examples section if you need ideas on what to write.</item></list></item>
<item>Be specific. Make your friend feel special for her contribution to your birthday celebration, and to your life. Mention the specific gift she gave you, or the card she sent. Tell her how you will use the gift, or that you will "enjoy it for a long time." <figure rend="Respond when Someone Wishes You Happy Birthday Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Say what your friend wants to hear. Never criticize the gift your friend sent you, bring up something embarrassing, or do anything else that might upset him. If you dislike the gift, try to find something about it that you do enjoy, or thank him for taking the time to pick out (or create) such a thoughtful gift. <figure rend="Respond when Someone Wishes You Happy Birthday Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Example Responses</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Give out compliments. Let the well-wishers know how wonderful they are, and how much you appreciate them. You can use more specific compliments that match your friends', or use these examples: <figure rend="Respond when Someone Wishes You Happy Birthday Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Thank you, that's such a kind thing to say!</hi></item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Thank you, you've been a bright and wonderful part of my life.</hi></item>
<item><hi rend="bold">I'm so lucky to have a group of friends like you.</hi></item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Give yourselves a pat on the back for being such great friends this past year.</hi></item></list></item>
<item>Tell everyone how much the wishes meant to you. Let your friends know you appreciate the positive effect they have on your life. Here are a couple examples: <figure rend="Respond when Someone Wishes You Happy Birthday Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Your message gave me a smile that lasted all day.</hi></item>
<item><hi rend="bold">It was so wonderful to hear from you. You made my birthday so special.</hi></item></list></item>
<item>Post something unique. If you're posting a mass thank you message on social media, sometimes you want to stand out a little. Try one of the following ideas: <figure rend="Respond when Someone Wishes You Happy Birthday Step 11.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Say something funny, like "<hi rend="bold">It feels great to have so many friends wishing me a happy birthday. You can all have 1/207 of my birthday cake."</hi></item>
<item>Say "Thank you!" in different languages. Try <hi rend="bold">Salamat!</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Foole tunk!</hi>, or pick your favorites by searching online.</item>
<item>Link to a video. There are many "thank you" videos available online, or you can find a clip from your favorite movie, band, or cute animal acting excited.</item></list></item>
<item>Give a serious, meaningful thank you. Sometimes, it feels great to communicate your sincere, deep appreciation for a full year of kindness and support. Tweak these examples to include specific events in your life for greater effect:<figure><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Special:FilePath/Respond_when_Someone_Wishes_You_Happy_Birthday_Step_12.jpg">Image:Respond when Someone Wishes You Happy Birthday Step 12.jpg</ref></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">I feel blessed every day, but most of all on the day when my friends send a flood of support and smiles. Thank you everyone for reminding me what matters on my birthday this year." </hi></item>
<item><hi rend="bold">It's been a difficult year, but the support of my friends and family made all the difference. My heartfelt thanks to all of you who helped get me back on my feet and face the next year with a smile instead of a frown.</hi></item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can treat birthday texts the same way you treat social media posts. Reply to the long, thought-out birthday wishes, and let your one social media post serve as thanks for the rest. (A mass text is another option, but make sure you know how much you'll be charged for it.)</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
