<text id="autogum_whow_doc496" title="Look Fabulous All the Time" shortTile="look-fabulous-time" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2009-07-25" dateModified="2019-10-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Look-Fabulous-All-the-Time" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Look Fabulous All the Time</head>
<p>Hey, have you ever wished you could look fabulous all the time? Whatever you're doing, going to school, going to work, on a date, out shopping, hitting the beach or hitting the gym - You can be constantly fabulous! Just read this guide.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Confident">Be confident</ref>! Stand tall and smile, or all of your hard work will go to waste. Never stand in a corner or try to avoid attention or no one will notice how fabulous you look. <figure rend="Dress-Hipster-Grunge-Step-1-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have a clear face. Use a product like Proactive if you have zits. Make sure to wash your face daily, and that you are free of acne before attempting the next step, or you could cause a break-out. Wash as often as you need, daily showers are the norm. No one will care how fabulous you look if you smell like sweat! <figure rend="Achieve-Smooth-Skin-on-a-Budget-Step-6-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Carry around a little make up pouch with you with your favorite products. In your make up pouch, you should have at least your eyeliner, blush, lip gloss and mascara. A comb or hairbrush helps too. Also keep some deodorant and chapstick just in case. <figure rend="Organize-Your-Purse-Step-14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tie up your hair into a nice, cute ponytail or smooth it out before you step out of your house. Change your hairstyle every once in a while. Having the same hairstyle for the whole year can become a little dull and boring. Try a bun or braid to jazz things up. You can even go to the stylist and ask for a snip. <figure rend="Do-an-Ariana-Grande-Ponytail-Step-3-Version-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't leave home without checking yourself in a mirror. Check the mirror every few hours - you could just use your make-up mirror. Don't try this during class, or you could get into trouble. <figure rend="Choose-a-Foundation-for-Dark-Skin-Tones-Step-5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Carry a big bag to put all of your essentials in. It's easier to carry just one bag, except for your make up pouch, which can be put into your big bag, and it looks more stylish, too. <figure rend="Wear-White-Step-8-Version-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you do not need to wear a uniform, you don't need to wear the same outfits to school. Look at <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Create_a_Capsule_Wardrobe">making a capsule wardrobe</ref> - a few pieces that can mix and match to many different outfits. <figure rend="Look-Like-a-Confident-Teen-Step-8-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try accessories. Something simple like earrings, bangles, or a belt can change up a look from good to fabulous. <figure rend="Look-Boho-Chic-Step-10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be true to yourself and <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Have_Your_Own_Style">your own style</ref>. Don't listen too much to other people's advice especially if it doesn't sound like it will work. <figure rend="Be-a-Pretty-Teenage-Girl-Step-32.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get a good night's sleep every night . This way you'll look fresh in the morning. Sleep also will reduce dark spots under the eyes. <figure rend="Be-a-Pretty-Teenage-Girl-Step-14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Smell nice. Shower in the morning and at night and wear perfume that you think smells great. <figure rend="Detangle-African-Hair-Step-2-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't forget to smile. It makes you feel fabulous, even on bad days.</item>
<item>Make sure your hair and skin aren't oily.</item>
<item>Try not to put hair gel as when it dries up, it looks like hair lice!</item>
<item>Don't use foundation; this causes break outs which is what you really want to avoid.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always be yourself. Do not change yourself for others.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>At least 14 sets of good clothes</item>
<item>Makeup</item>
<item>Proper bags</item></list>
</text>
