<text id="autogum_whow_doc185" title="Think out of the Box and Find Alternative Solutions" shortTile="think-out-box-find" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2010-01-06" dateModified="2016-08-18" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Think-out-of-the-Box-and-Find-Alternative-Solutions" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Think out of the Box and Find Alternative Solutions</head><p>Every now and then, someone will tell you to start thinking outside the box. You instantly realize they are calling your ideas stale or redundant. But what exactly is this box and how do you think outside of it? Well, here are a few pointers.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Figure out the problem you are trying to solve. It helps if you know what you want to accomplish. <figure rend="Think out of the Box and Find Alternative Solutions Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Think of all the solutions you can. Anything you think of, write it down; preferably on separate sheets of paper. <figure rend="Think out of the Box and Find Alternative Solutions Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Look at your current solutions. Take them to other people and ask for their opinions. Listen to them and keep notes. <figure rend="Think out of the Box and Find Alternative Solutions Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Go back through all of your solutions. See if you can improve them with the opinions you received. <figure rend="Think out of the Box and Find Alternative Solutions Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Now grab a blender... well, actually, grab anything you have near you. Think about this item in terms of how it could help you solve your problem. Maybe the item as a whole cannot help, but one specific part can. Take notes on your current solutions if something you think of may help that solution be better. <figure rend="Think out of the Box and Find Alternative Solutions Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>READ. Read everything you can on the topic of your problem, preferably from websites. Look for strange ways of doing things and keep them in mind. Take notes on your current solutions if something you read may help that solution be better. <figure rend="Think out of the Box and Find Alternative Solutions Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Invent something that does not (or cannot) exist. Make up an item which solves your problem. Think about how this item works. Maybe it uses principles from your current solutions, the opinions you've received, the objects you've looked at, and the articles or books you've read or videos you've watched. <figure rend="Think out of the Box and Find Alternative Solutions Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Put it all together. You want to think outside the box, but you still need to be organized. Solutions happen when everything comes together. <figure rend="Think out of the Box and Find Alternative Solutions Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Think like a Science Fiction writer. Make something up and let the scientists explain how it works. Just make sure it can actually work that way in the real world.</item>
<item>Don't be afraid to enlist the help of others. Brainstorming with other people is one of the best ways to think outside of the box. Often, no matter how creative you are, someone else will have thought about something you would have never thought.</item>
<item>KISS. No, not the band. It's an acronym which stand for Keep It Simple, Stupid. Don't make things too hard on yourself, nor on the people who will use your solution.</item>
<item>Keep notes. These notes may help you with other tasks later on.</item>
<item>If all else fails pretend nothing exists to even help you obtain your goal. You have to invent everything. If nothing else, this will help you relax as you realize there's already solutions to parts of your problem.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don' steal other people's work. You'll likely get sued and labeled as a fraud.</item>
<item>Make sure you don't violate a confidentiality agreement by sharing ideas with the wrong person. You could get fired.</item>
<item>Make sure you share with a trusted friend (as long as the above does not apply) who you know will not steal your ideas.</item></list>
</text>
