<text id="autogum_whow_doc459" title="Prevent Major Home Repairs" shortTile="prevent-major-home" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2012-03-17" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Prevent-Major-Home-Repairs" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Prevent Major Home Repairs</head><p>Just as a routine maintenance schedule helps prevent major repairs to your car, and just as regular visits to a doctor can help prevent illnesses and afflictions from developing, routine maintenance of your home can help you ward off major, costly repairs. Paying for home repairs out of pocket is one of the unpredictable and less glamorous aspects of home ownership. Major repairs, up to and including structural damage, can be inaccessibly expensive. To help prevent major home repairs, it helps to practice routine maintenance of your home. The guide below highlights some of the important aspects of this maintenance.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Clean your gutters regularly. This is one of the most important tasks in warding off major home repairs. Gutters are designed to direct water safely away from your home. When they are clogged with leaves and debris, water overflows out of the gutters directly onto the ground surrounding your house. This can quickly saturate the soil against your home's foundation, which can lead to leaky basement walls and even cracked concrete foundations. <figure rend="Prevent Major Home Repairs Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Change your home's air filters regularly. Dirty air filters not only impede the flow of air through your home; they can cause major damage to your air conditioning unit. Inadequate air flow across the unit's evaporator coil can cause the temperature to drop enough for ice to form on the coils. This ice can eventually crack or collapse the tubing in the evaporator coil, which would require a costly visit from an HVAC technician. <figure rend="Prevent Major Home Repairs Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep a vigilant eye out for mold growth. Mold and mildew growth is fairly common in homes, as mold only needs some organic material and a bit of moisture to proliferate. In areas where moisture levels are high (typically bathrooms and kitchens), regularly scrub walls, ceilings, and fixtures with bleach, vinegar, or another disinfectant. Letting mold growth proceed unchecked can quickly cause damage to the studs in your walls, which will require major and costly structural repairs. <figure rend="Prevent Major Home Repairs Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Replace aging or malfunctioning appliances or fixtures. Aging and faulty electrical wiring can pose a risk of fire. Old appliances should be inspected by an electrician and replaced or reconditioned when no longer in safe condition. Any wiring in your home with stripped or frayed insulation should be replaced immediately. Small fixtures like lamps can usually be completely rewired with little trouble. An electrical fire can very easily get out of control and cause major structural damage. <figure rend="Prevent Major Home Repairs Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take precautions against insect infestations. Insects can cause major damage to your home, but even when they do not cause structural damage, they can be very expensive to eliminate. Insects such as termites, roaches, and bed bugs can be kept ay bay by making sure that your house is cleaned regularly. Avoid eating food throughout your home, instead eating only in your kitchen or dining area. Being vigilant about water damage will also help prevent termites and other insects that feed on water-softened wood. <figure rend="Prevent Major Home Repairs Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Purchasing comprehensive homeowner's insurance is another effective strategy for mitigating the out-of-pocket cost of major home repairs. Remember that fire and flood damage may need to be covered through a separate policy.</item></list>
</text>
