<text id="autogum_whow_doc625" title="Defend Your Religion" shortTile="defend-religion" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2017-11-17" dateModified="2017-11-17" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Defend-Your-Religion" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Defend Your Religion</head><p>"But sanctify the Lord God in your hearts, and be ready always to give an answer to every man who asketh you a reason for the hope that is in you, with meekness and fear." 1 Peter 3:15It is estimated that there are roughly 4200 religions in the world right now. Some of those religions are bound to contradict and many people are intolerant of certain religions. It is inevitable that at some point in your life your religion will be criticized and you will have to defend your beliefs. This article will show you the most important tips.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Preparation</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Develop a deep understanding of your religion for yourself before arguing with anyone. You cannot successfully explain or defend something that you do not know. If you do not understand your religion yourself, you may end up giving out the wrong information and misrepresenting it. No matter how good your debating skills are, the most important ingredient for any debate is knowledge. It is essential to familiarize yourself with the doctrine and teachings of your religion.
<list type="unordered"><item>Attend sermons or lessons frequently to familiarize yourself with the teachings of it.</item>
<item>Always ask questions whenever there is anything you do not understand. Be sure to ask someone who is knowledgeable in your religion (Minister, Imam, Priest, etc.)</item>
<item>Familiarize yourself with your religion's texts (Bible, Torah, Quran, etc.), this is important because it is likely that critics will cite this text as evidence against the validity/morality of your religion.</item></list></item>
<item>Learn the most common criticisms. It is likely that certain criticisms against your religion are used more often than others. If you familiarize yourself with the most common criticisms used against your religion, you will be prepared to rebut most criticisms against it.</item>
<item>Understand what is literal and what is metaphorical. When Jesus said, "if your eye offend thee, pluck it out," he was not telling you to literally gouge out your own eye; it was figurative language, which is common in many religious texts. It is important to learn the whether or not certain passages of text are symbolic or literal, because certain metaphorical texts may be found to be objectionable by critics if interpreted literally.</item>
<item>Learn what the apologists say. This is one of the quickest ways to learn many defenses against criticisms of your religion.
<list type="unordered"><item>Search online and see if there are any apologetic sites dedicated to defending your religion.</item>
<item>Go to your local bookstore or library and get books dedicated to defending your religion</item></list></item>
<item>Watch Debates. Check YouTube or other video sites to see if there are any debates where your religion is being defended. Analyse the apologist and the critic and ask yourself:
<list type="unordered"><item>Did the apologist do a good job of defending your beliefs? Why/why not? What would you have done differently?</item>
<item>What points did the apologist bring up? How would you modify them?</item>
<item>What points did the critic bring up? How would you respond to them?</item></list></item></list>
<head>Discussion</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Watch out for strawman arguments.</item>
<item>Watch out for ad hominem fallacies. An ad hominem fallacy is when someone's argument is dismissed because of who they are or some fact about them, when the argument should be evaluated on its own merit. There are several different types of ad hominemAbusive: Note that some instances of ad hominem are not fallacious, such as situations when the argument directly has something to do with the person being criticized.</item>
<item>Watch out quotations out of context.</item>
<item>Watch out for appeals to ridicule.</item>
<item>Watch out for loaded language.</item>
<item>Honestly answer all honest questions. It shows integrety and credibility if you are able to answer the critics questions.</item>
<item>Watch out for misinterpreations</item></list>
<head>Civility</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Stay calm</item>
<item>Avoid insults.</item>
<item>Avoid interrupting and ask that the critic do the same.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Understand that there are some people who simply will not listen to your defense no matter what. If it is obvious that that is the case, it may be a better idea to simply leave them alone.</item></list>
</text>
