<text id="autogum_whow_doc393" title="Paint Corners" shortTile="paint-corners" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-06-28" dateModified="2019-07-08" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Paint-Corners" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Paint Corners</head><p>Whether it's a large or small project, there's a good chance that most painting tasks will involve corners. Although it can be a tricky process at first, any corner can be painted with the proper taping preparations and short, careful brush strokes. With a little bit of patience, you will be able to work through your home painting projects with efficiency!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Protecting and Sealing the Paint Site</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Set up a step stool next to the painting site. Before you start painting, you will want to make sure that the spot you plan on painting is easily accessible. If necessary, set up a small step stool or ladder to help you reach the area that you'll be painting. Being closer to the corner will allow you to make steadier, more confident strokes. This can help make your paint job look more professional. <figure rend="Paint Corners Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you're using a ladder, always have a person nearby to spot you. This can help to prevent any potential injuries.</item></list></item>
<item>Wipe the corner baseboard with a moist cloth to remove any dust. You will be applying painter’s tape to prevent any paint from dripping into unwanted areas, so you want to make sure that there is no lingering dust. Wait for the wiped surface to dry before applying any painter's tape. <figure rend="Paint Corners Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Painter's tape will have a smoother application along a clean surface.</item>
<item>Wipe with a phosphate-free detergent product if the wall or corner area appears to be greasy. This solution can be found at most hardware and home improvement stores.</item>
<item>If you are working on a ceiling area, wipe down wherever you expect to be placing painter’s tape.</item></list></item>
<item>Cut a long strip of painter's tape. The length of this strip will depend on the length of your wall. Place the tape along the floor baseboard. Choose a starting point along the edge and ensure that the piece of tape is long enough to reach the corner.  Make the piece of tape longer than necessary to ensure that the corner’s edges are completely covered. <figure rend="Paint Corners Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Medium adhesion painter’s tape is a good choice for painted walls, and will help prevent any damage to the wall during the tape removal process.</item>
<item>Using a painter's tape applicator can help to make the taping process much more efficient. They are available at most stores that sell painting supplies.</item>
<item>When painting a ceiling corner, secure the painter’s tape along the edge where the ceiling meets the wall.</item></list></item>
<item>Secure the painter's tape to the wall with a putty knife. Drag the putty knife along any loose sections of painter’s tape so that they adhere tightly to the wall. Once you have securely bonded the tape to the corner, use a utility knife or other small blade to cut off anything extra.  <figure rend="Paint Corners Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>A one and a half inch wide putty knife is a good size for most painting projects.</item></list></item>
<item>Repeat the taping and sealing process. Using another long strip of painter's tape, cover the other adjoining edge of the wall with painter's tape. Secure this piece of tape with the putty knife. <figure rend="Paint Corners Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Since you already cut the extra tape off of the first strip, the second strip will be easier to secure to the wall and corner.</item>
<item>Apply long strips of painter’s tape around nearby moldings as needed. This process will be identical to the rest of the taping process.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Applying the Paint</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Begin to fill the corner with paint. Use a two-and-a-half inch wide brush and liberally dip into the paint.  Start by using your brush to apply paint from the innermost crevice. This will make it easier to paint the areas immediately surrounding the corner. <figure rend="Paint Corners Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are painting near a baseboard, be sure to have drop cloths or plastic sheeting laid out to prevent any paint from spilling on the floor.</item>
<item>If you prefer to use a roller in your painting, consider using a square paint edger. This tool is a mix of a brush and a roller, and will help you reach the inner parts of the corner. Use an extension pole if necessary.</item></list></item>
<item>Spread the paint in outward strokes. You will want to keep your brushstrokes short so that you can spread the paint evenly across a small area. Aim to paint at least five short strokes from your initial paint placement. <figure rend="Paint Corners Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Edge rollers can also be effective in providing consistent paint coverage along a straight line.</item></list></item>
<item>Keep brushing in short strokes to hide any brush marks. Given the small amount of painting space in a corner, there is a chance that you have lingering brush marks that are visible to the naked eye.
<list type="unordered"><item>Give extra care to even out parallel strokes of paint with perpendicular ones.</item></list></item>
<item>Switch to a roller to get consistent paint coverage. While a roller may not be able to reach a corner’s crevice, it can help to flatten and level out the existing paint that you have already applied with a brush. Using a roller also eliminates any worry of lasting brush strokes. <figure rend="Paint Corners Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take off the painter's tape. Once the paint has dried, press down on the top of the tape with the thin edge of a putty knife. You will then want to pull the tape off in a clean, steady motion. Ideally, you will want the tape to be forming a 45-degree angle as you remove it from the wall. <figure rend="Paint Corners Step 10.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Wet wipes</item>
<item>Painter's tape</item>
<item>Paint brush</item>
<item>Paint roller</item>
<item>Paint roller extension pole (optional)</item>
<item>Square paint edger</item>
<item>Putty knife</item>
<item>Utility knife</item>
<item>Paint</item>
<item>Disposable gloves (optional)</item>
<item>Drop cloths (optional)</item>
<item>Plastic sheeting (optional)</item>
<item>Step stool (optional)</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Wear a mask if you plan on painting for an extended period of time.</item></list>
</text>
