<text id="autogum_whow_doc677" title="Revamp Your Fat Burning Exercises" shortTile="revamp-fat-burning" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2009-10-27" dateModified="2018-09-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Revamp-Your-Fat-Burning-Exercises" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Revamp Your Fat Burning Exercises</head><p>A handful of straightforward changes to your boring regime of fat burning exercises can take you to a whole new level in your fitness and increase your ability to burn more fat. Here are some tips to add some zing to your regular training regime and keep you looking forward to exercising.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Take a new route. It is imperative to keep your body constantly challenged if you would like to enhance your fitness, decrease your body fat, or increase your muscle strength. It is relatively simple to achieve any or all of these without having to change your regime too much. If you walk or run regularly, try including some extra hills. Alternatively, if you use cardio equipment at the gym or at home such as a Treadmill, increase the incline or the speed. <figure rend="Revamp Your Fat Burning Exercises Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Add supersets to your weight training. Bringing supersets to your weight training routine will not only enhance your muscle mass, it is superb for adding some extra muscle definition. Supersets are also good if you're in a rush, as there is less resting time between the exercises, making your routine quicker to get through. A superset is when you complete one set of an exercise then immediately go on to the next exercise. <figure rend="Revamp Your Fat Burning Exercises Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Go hard! Sometimes with exercise and weight training, you can experience feeling a bit overwhelmed with all of the technical jargon you need to bear in mind - reps, sets, maximum heart rate, and so on. Try not to focus on all of that for a change and simply train hard at whatever exercise you are doing for the day. If you're cycling choose a totally different route than you would normally pick and just go hard! Don't monitor your heart rate if you normally do, instead keep going with a high intensity until you need a break. After a short break, do it all again. <figure rend="Revamp Your Fat Burning Exercises Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Incorporate intervals into your regime. This is an exceptional way to increase your fat burning exercises. Try including one minute bursts into some of your cardio exercises such as treadmill work, running, spinning, cross-trainer, or swimming. If you're used to walking, try running for one minute bursts. There are workouts going under the name of HIIT workout (High Intensity Interval Training), which is a great way to improve your fat burning workout!  <figure rend="Revamp Your Fat Burning Exercises Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Join a new class. If you belong to a gym that has many different classes, experiment with one you've never done before, even if it means getting out of your comfort zone and experimenting with something different. Some excellent fat burning classes are cycle, body combat, basic training, or body pump. <figure rend="Revamp Your Fat Burning Exercises Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pick fun exercises. It's not difficult to quit your fat burning exercises routine when it feels monotonous and you lose all motivation. Experiment with some enjoyable activities such as going for a bike ride, joining a local sports team such as soccer or netball, belly dancing, or walking along the beach. <figure rend="Revamp Your Fat Burning Exercises Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>With any luck these ideas will arm you with some new thoughts if you choose to change your exercises to keep yourself energized and raring to go with your next session.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are determined to lose weight, please do not starve yourself! This is something a lot of people do wrong, and they end up hurting their bodies. Be sure to get enough of all the needed nutrients, but stay under the limit of needed calories.</item>
<item>Don't forget to drink a lot of water when losing weight! Hydrating your body may help you to boost your metabolism and keep your body going.</item></list>
</text>
