<text id="autogum_whow_doc144" title="Contribute to the Story Project" shortTile="contribute-story" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2008-03-31" dateModified="2018-09-13" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Contribute-to-the-Story-Project" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Contribute to the Story Project</head><p>The Story Project is non-profit organization that fosters reading, writing and communication skills in middle schools. If you look around, there are so many that seem to complain that they feel alone in the world and misunderstood. Some feel unloved and abandoned, or uncared for. The story project is here to make that difference. You can be a part of that difference!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Look approachable. Have a smile on your face. Be presentable, focused, and calm. Try smiling with your eyes. Be aware of your body language and look open and understanding by uncrossing your arms and keeping a genuine gaze. <figure rend="Contribute to the Story Project Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Ask “what is your story?” This question comes across as very powerful. As human beings, we often wonder if anyone is interested in knowing who we truly are. With the stereotypes we have, so many get lost in this image. Those 4 words are the most amazing words you can say to someone. It shows how much you care. These “life stories” are extremely powerful gifts and tools. They show how everything fits together in life to create this bigger picture. They reveal what truly matters. They can give comfort and support. Looking back on the lives we have, with every detail of our life, feelings, and beliefs, and everything that ever happened to us, it’s all so beautiful. Just combining those things together to make a person shows us how empowered we can become. We can learn so much from each other. We can learn love, acceptance, and peace when we are at peace with ourselves and everyone around us. Do your part and ask a simple question. You might just make someone’s day. <figure rend="Contribute to the Story Project Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be prepared to listen. Attend the conversation by leaning slightly foreword while listening, keep your hands and feet quiet and still, and look interested (and be interested), nodding at the appropriate times. Keep sufficient eye contact. Look at the person, however, avoid staring. Offer feedback. Repeat what the other person is saying in your own words. Do not do this for every sentence. Act natural while following your heart. Look and be comfortable, and the other person will as well. <figure rend="Contribute to the Story Project Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Put yourself in the shoes of the other person. Avoid judging him or her. <figure rend="Contribute to the Story Project Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Evaluate. Look at the prospect of the life story of the person. Take the lessons that need be learned from the story, as well as the person. Identify the strengths of him or her and compliment accordingly. Thank them for sharing. <figure rend="Contribute to the Story Project Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be prepared to share your story. The story project is about sharing. It means making someone feel understood and less alone in the world. In order to accomplish this, it is important to understand the other person by listening and being attentive; then sharing some things about yourself and your life, your struggles, and rising above those obstacles. <figure rend="Contribute to the Story Project Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not worry if someone does not share there story. Not all persons would feel comfortable doing so. Do not hesitate to ask.</item></list>
</text>
