<text id="autogum_whow_doc060" title="Easily Increase Your Gas Mileage" shortTile="easily-increase-gas" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-02-01" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Easily-Increase-Your-Gas-Mileage" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Easily Increase Your Gas Mileage</head><p>Not everyone can go out and buy the latest hybrid model. However, you can learn how to easily increase your gas mileage with your current car. Driving well and taking good care of your vehicle are all it takes to go further on a tank of gas.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Drive the speed limit. Experts estimate that you lose 20 cents for every  you go over the highway speed limit. <figure rend="Easily Increase Your Gas Mileage Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use your vehicle's cruise control for highway driving. The cruise control keeps the accelerator even and prevents sudden surges from stepping on the gas. <figure rend="Easily Increase Your Gas Mileage Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Cruise control won't work in favor of your gas mileage if you live in a mountainous area, as the accelerator will be constantly surging going up frequent steep hills.</item></list></item>
<item>Shut the car off if you'll be idling for longer than 15-30 seconds. <figure rend="Easily Increase Your Gas Mileage Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Drive moderately and don't rev the engine. Anticipate having to stop and slow down way ahead of traffic. <figure rend="Easily Increase Your Gas Mileage Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Change your oil regularly and rotate or replace your tires when needed. A dirty air filter or worn-out spark plugs can also seriously drain your gas mileage and should be fixed or replaced. <figure rend="Easily Increase Your Gas Mileage Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Use the motor oil recommended in your vehicle owner's manual. Motor oil additives can also make a difference. Look for an oil in your car's recommended grade that advertises energy conservation or uses the API performance logo.</item></list></item>
<item>Check your vehicle owner's manual to see what octane of fuel is recommended for your vehicle; for most cars, regular octane is ideal. <figure rend="Easily Increase Your Gas Mileage Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Reduce engine speed by using the highest gear available. Not only will this easily increase your gas mileage, it will also reduce the wear and tear on your engine.
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't use a gear that is too high.</item></list></item></list>
<list type="ordered"><item>Take luggage and racks off the exterior of your car when you're not using them. Anything extra on the outside of your vehicle increases drag. <figure rend="Easily Increase Your Gas Mileage Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remove unnecessary junk from your trunk, as extra pounds will weigh a car down. It's estimated that for every 250 pounds hauled, you lose  per gallon. <figure rend="Easily Increase Your Gas Mileage Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Travel when you know traffic will be lighter, if possible. Combine trips to run several errands at once in certain areas of town. <figure rend="Easily Increase Your Gas Mileage Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try not to use your four-wheel drive if possible. The drive components increase fuel consumption.</item>
<item>Keep your tires inflated at optimum levels. Not only is this good for the wear of your car and safety, you may be able to get a modest increase in gas mileage. <figure rend="Easily Increase Your Gas Mileage Step 12.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>On the highway, always keep your revs below 3000rpm, this will reduce the amount of gas being used to move the vehicle.</item>
<item>Keep track of your fuel savings by saving receipts and calculating your fuel economy over distances traveled. Make notes about which gas mileage saving methods you tried and their result.</item>
<item>Avoid any fuel additives that claim it can easily increase your gas mileage. The Federal Trade Commission warns that any savings from these products will be minimal.</item>
<item>Rolling down the windows and forgoing air conditioning made no difference in tests of gas consumption.</item></list>
</text>
