<text id="autogum_whow_doc660" title="Join a Korfball Team" shortTile="join-korfball-team" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-03-18" dateModified="2016-08-18" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Join-a-Korfball-Team" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Join a Korfball Team</head><p>People of all ages play Korfball to keep fit, make new friends and have fun. If you aspire to play Korfball, joining a team is the best thing to do. New players are always made welcome and will usually be taught the basics of the game free of charge. All you need to join is a normal sports kit and some trainers; everything else will be provided by the club.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Become familiar with the game. This isn't a must but it'd be good to understand how the game is played. Korfball is a mixed sex ball sport similar to basketball, that is played by 2 teams of 4 boys and 4 girls, the aim of the game is to score more goals than your opponent by the end of the match, this is achieved through throwing the ball through your opponent's Korf (basket).</item>
<item>Pick a team. Once you're sure you want to join a Korfball club, you will first need to pick a team to join. The best way to find one is to search the internet for a team in your area, there are many websites online dedicated to helping you do just that.</item>
<item>Get in touch. Once you've decided which club you would like to join, contact them for more details such as training times. This will make you more clued up on important things like what you will need to participate and where to go. Along with making them aware of your intent to get involved.</item>
<item>Attend training sessions. Attend training as it is great practice to be playing with other players who have experience and will be able to help you with your skills and technique. It will also show your commitment to the Club. When attending the sessions, make sure you have the right clothing.</item>
<item>Keep at it. Now you've joined a team and you're playing matches, it does not stop there. You should keep practicing to stay fit and become a better player. Also look towards the future, as one day you could be playing Korfball at a higher level, abroad or even internationally.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are nervous about joining a team on your own, get a friend or family member to come along with you to play or for support</item>
<item>Buy a Korfball to play at home with, this can be a good way to improve your skills</item>
<item>Attend a Korfball game to see how it is played and to decide whether you'd like to try it out.</item>
<item>If the club has a social media account, follow them for updates.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Remember to warm up before exercise and warm down afterwards to avoid injury</item>
<item>Always stay Hydrated during exercise</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Suitable Clothes and Trainers</item>
<item>A bottle of water</item></list>
</text>
