<text id="autogum_whow_doc405" title="Do a Speed Paint" shortTile="speed-paint" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2016-11-05" dateModified="2017-02-04" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Do-a-Speed-Paint" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Do a Speed Paint</head><p>Have you ever wanted to do a speed paint? Have you seen so many and thought " I wish I could do that!" ? Well here you go.  If you are just here to find a good painting program than go to the Preparing Section.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>If you want to do a speed paint you first need to get a painting program. Don't worry its free. My favorite ones to use are youidraw and the animal jam art studio.file:///Users/jasmine/Desktop/Screen%20Shot%202016-11-05%20at%202.21.21%20PM.png( thats a picture of youidraw )file:///Users/jasmine/Desktop/Screen%20Shot%202016-11-05%20at%202.21.02%20PM.png( thats a picture of the A.J art studio.)</item>
<item>Once you have chosen a drawing site or app, try to draw something. Remember you're not going to be picasso on your first try. Keep on drawing things and using picture references to help you if you'd like. Once you get the hang of drawing test your limits try something you haven't done before. Also don't just draw online, try it on paper too. Remember to qualify as a speed paint it doesn't necessarily have to be on the computer. Remember practice makes perfect!</item>
<item>Once you have been practicing drawing and like how you are doing you're probably going to want to be able to record it. To record your screen on a mac simply hold down Command then hit space. This will activate spotlight. Once spotlight is open type in quicktimeplayer this will bring up the application ( it comes with the computer so every one has it) now this is the confusing part. go up to the bar with the apple symbol and the battery percentage and what time it is and what not and click the button that says 'file'. from there you want to click ' new screen recording' it will bring up a gray bar on your sceen. then just click on the red button on the gray bar and select the area of the screen you would like to record ( or just click the screen to record the whole screen).</item>
<item>Once you are done making the recording you may want to upload it to youtube. Most likely your video will be to long to upload. To fix this you can go to imovie ( or which ever editor you want to use) and click the clock button this will bring up a small menu of if you want it to go in reverse slow or fast. Click fast and select the speed at which you would like it to play. Then click the upload button which is a box with an arrow pointing up. Once you have clicked that it will bring up a menu select YouTube ( or where ever you want to upload) now add a title and maybe a description. also if you would like to add music you can select it from your itunes media or ad it in later in the YouTube editor. once you select upload to YouTube you will see an empty circle on your screen this shows you how much longer it will take to upload the video.</item>
<item>Once you are done with all that go to your video and watch it! here is an example of a finished speed paint I did!<ref target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Cqa9hluBtvA">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Cqa9hluBtvA</ref></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>DO NOT DOWNLOAD FIRE ALPACA!!!!! I TRIED AND IT GAVE ME MALWARE!!!!! I REPEAT DO NOT DOWNLOAD FIRE ALPACA IT GAVE ME MALWARE! I don't know if what I downloaded was really fire alpaca considering i've seen speed paints with it but it was all in Japaneese so yeah just don't download it.</item></list>
</text>
