<text id="autogum_whow_doc123" title="Find Your Apple ID" shortTile="find-apple-id" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-06-20" dateModified="2017-12-24" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Find-Your-Apple-ID" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Find Your Apple ID</head><p>This wikiHow teaches you how to locate or recover your Apple ID.
</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Using iPhone or iPad</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open Settings. It's a gray app that contains gears (⚙️) and is typically located on your home screen. <figure rend="Find Your Apple ID Step 1 Version 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tap . It's at the very top of the Settings menu. <figure rend="Find Your Apple ID Step 2 Version 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you're already signed in to your device and you see your name at the top instead, tapping on your name will take you to a page that displays an email address bellow your name. That email address is your Apple ID.</item>
<item>If you are running an older version of iOS, instead tap  and check to see if you are signed in to your device at the top. If you are signed in you will see an email address displayed under your name. That email address is your Apple ID.</item></list></item>
<item>Tap . It's below the password field. <figure rend="Find Your Apple ID Step 3 Version 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are running an older version of iOS, instead tap </item></list></item>
<item>Tap . It's in the center of the pop-up menu. <figure rend="Find Your Apple ID Step 4 Version 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tap . It's below the "Apple ID" field. <figure rend="Find Your Apple ID Step 5 Version 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Enter your information. Type your first name, your last name, and your email address into the labeled fields. <figure rend="Find Your Apple ID Step 6 Version 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tap . It's in the upper-right corner. <figure rend="Find Your Apple ID Step 7 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Enter your phone number. Type in the phone number associated with your Apple ID, ending in the last two digits displayed on the screen. <figure rend="Find Your Apple ID Step 8 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tap . It's in the upper-right corner. <figure rend="Find Your Apple ID Step 9 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tap . It's at the bottom of the screen. <figure rend="Find Your Apple ID Step 10 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>A verification code will be sent by text message to your number. If the verification code doesn't autofill, enter it on the screen and tap .</item>
<item>If you don't have access to the phone number, tap <hi rend="bold">Don't have access to your trusted number?</hi> at the very bottom of the screen and follow the on-screen prompts to recover your Apple ID.</item></list></item>
<item>Enter your passcode. Enter the passcode you use to unlock your phone's screen. <figure rend="Find Your Apple ID Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Enter a new password. Type a password into the labeled space and re-enter on the next line. <figure rend="Find Your Apple ID Step 12.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Your password must have at least 8 characters (including a number and an uppercase and lowercase letter) with no spaces. It also shouldn't have three consecutive characters (ggg), be your Apple ID, or a previous password you've used in the last year.</item></list></item>
<item>Tap . It's in the upper-right corner of the screen. <figure rend="Find Your Apple ID Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tap . If you're not automatically signed into iCloud, enter your new password into the labeled field. <figure rend="Find Your Apple ID Step 14.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Your Apple ID will be displayed in the field labeled "Apple ID."</item></list></item>
<item>Tap . It's in the upper-right corner of the screen. <figure rend="Find Your Apple ID Step 15.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The screen will intermittently display the message "Signing into iCloud" as it accesses your data during the sign-in process.</item></list></item>
<item>Enter your iPhone's passcode. This is the unlock code you established for your device when you set it up. <figure rend="Find Your Apple ID Step 16.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Merge your data. If you'd like any calendars, reminders, contacts, notes, or other data already stored on your iPhone to be merged with your iCloud account, tap <hi rend="bold">Merge</hi>; if not, tap <hi rend="bold">Don't Merge</hi>. <figure rend="Find Your Apple ID Step 17.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Your Apple ID, which is an email address, will be displayed under your name at the top of  the screen.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Using Desktop</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open the Apple menu. Do so by clicking on the black Apple icon in the upper-left corner of the screen. <figure rend="Find Your Apple ID Step 18.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on . It's near the top of the drop-down menu. <figure rend="Find Your Apple ID Step 19.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on . It's an icon containing a blue cloud on the left side of the window. <figure rend="Find Your Apple ID Step 20.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you're signed into your Mac with your Apple ID, your Apple ID will be the email address under your name in the left pane of the window.</item>
<item>If you're not signed in, you'll be prompted to enter your Apple ID and password.</item></list></item>
<item>Click on . It's below the password field in the dialog box. <figure rend="Find Your Apple ID Step 21.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on . It's located near the bottom of the dialog box. <figure rend="Find Your Apple ID Step 22.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on <ref target="https://iforgot.apple.com">iforgot.apple.com</ref>. It's in the text of the dialog box or enter iforgot.apple.com into your browser. <figure rend="Find Your Apple ID Step 23.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Enter your information. You will need to enter your first name, last name, and email address associated with the Apple ID. You can enter in any prior email addresses as well, but this isn't required. <figure rend="Find Your Apple ID Step 24.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Click on <hi rend="bold">Next</hi> when you've finished filling out the form.</item>
<item>There is a very good chance that your Apple ID is your current email address.</item></list></item>
<item>Verify your birthday. You will need to enter in your birthday before you can proceed with retrieving the Apple ID. <figure rend="Find Your Apple ID Step 25.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Choose how you want to retrieve the Apple ID. You are given two options for retrieving your Apple ID: you can receive your login information via email, or you can answer a couple security questions and have it displayed in your browser. <figure rend="Find Your Apple ID Step 26.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you choose to have the information sent to your email, it will be sent to your current email address as well as any other email addresses you have associated with the account.</item>
<item>If you choose to answer security questions, you will be asked two of the questions you set up when you created the ID originally.</item></list></item>
<item>Reset your password. If you chose to answer the security questions, your Apple ID will be displayed on the next page. You will be asked to create a new password for your Apple ID. If you asked to retrieve your Apple ID via email, you will receive an email with a password reset link. The email address you received the message on is your Apple ID. <figure rend="Find Your Apple ID Step 27.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
</text>
