<text id="autogum_whow_doc520" title="Become an Avon Consultant" shortTile="become-avon-consultant" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2012-06-08" dateModified="2019-03-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Become-an-Avon-Consultant" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Become an Avon Consultant</head><p>Becoming an Avon consultant will give you the opportunity to promote and sell Avon products to individuals in your local area and everywhere else in your country. As an Avon consultant, you can connect with people to sell product face-to-face, or sell Avon products on your own personal blog or website. To become an Avon consultant, you are required to sign up for the sales program with another Avon consultant in your area, or online at Avon's website. After you have paid the applicable registration fees and received training materials, you can begin selling Avon product and start earning commission on sales. Continue reading this article to learn more about the steps you must take to become an Avon consultant.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Sign Up Process</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find a local Avon consultant in your area. To find an Avon consultant, you can either call Avon's customer service center at 1-800-367-2866, or email Avon at "dearavon [at] avon.com." <figure rend="Become an Avon Consultant Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Sign up online to become an Avon consultant. You should only apply for the consultant program online if you cannot locate another Avon consultant in your local area. <figure rend="Become an Avon Consultant Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Go to the "Your Avon" website displayed in the Sources section of this article, then click "Apply Now."</item>
<item>Type your personal information into the fields provided, then click on "Submit." The nearest Avon consultant in your region will contact you and provide you with the next steps for becoming a consultant.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Registration Process</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Arrange a meeting with your local Avon consultant. To fully register for the consultant program, you must meet with another Avon consultant to complete paperwork and discuss the program in more detail. <figure rend="Become an Avon Consultant Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Ask the Avon consultant about the materials you should bring to the meeting; such as identification, and registration fees. The fees for becoming an Avon consultant will vary depending on the region and country in which you live.</item></list></item>
<item>Fill out the Avon consultant paperwork. During your meeting with the local Avon consultant, you will be provided with the necessary registration paperwork for becoming a consultant. <figure rend="Become an Avon Consultant Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Speak with the Avon consultant about any questions or concerns you have about the program. The Avon consultant will address your concerns, and answer any questions you have about the consultant program in its entirety. <figure rend="Become an Avon Consultant Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Start Selling Avon Products</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Receive your first Avon kit in the mail. After meeting with the local Avon consultant, your registration paperwork will be sent to the Avon office for processing. After you have been accepted into the program, you will be sent an Avon kit with brochures, training materials, and various Avon product samples. <figure rend="Become an Avon Consultant Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Determine how you want to sell Avon products. As an Avon consultant, you can sell Avon products using any method you choose; including hosting Avon parties, selling Avon products online, distributing brochures throughout your local community, and more. <figure rend="Become an Avon Consultant Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Review the Avon training materials and resources to find additional tips and strategies for getting started with selling Avon products. For example, if you want to sell Avon on the Internet, consult with your training materials to learn when you can attend an Avon training course for selling products online.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Network with and recruit other Avon consultants in your area. By meeting with other Avon consultants, you can share sales tips and best practices; plus, you can potentially earn extra commission if you recruit new Avon consultants.</item>
<item>Use social media outlets for help with promoting and selling Avon products. For example, if you use Facebook to socialize with friends and family, place an Avon widget on your Facebook page that allows your friends and family to purchase Avon products from you online.</item>
<item>Sell Avon products using more than one sales method to boost your income potential. For example, if you enjoy using Avon products yourself, start a personal blog that features reviews on various Avon products, then publish links on the blog that drive visitors to your Avon sales page.</item></list>
</text>
