<text id="autogum_whow_doc622" title="Decide Between Religion and Atheism" shortTile="decide-between-religion" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-03-27" dateModified="2019-02-22" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Decide-Between-Religion-and-Atheism" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Decide Between Religion and Atheism</head><p>Beliefs and spirituality are an important part of our lives. Not only to get answers to spiritual questions, but also to identify in a group, to not feel rejected. How to decide when you don't know your own beliefs?</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Understanding the Difference Between Religion and Atheism</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Know the definitions. Most of the time, we look for answers without even understanding the question. What does it mean to be religious? To be an atheist? You will notice that the definitions of these words aren't as clear as they may seem, and everybody has their own opinion on what they actually mean. Clearly understanding the meanings of these words will help you understand exactly what you are looking for.
<list type="unordered"><item>Religion: 1. The belief in and worship of a superhuman controlling power, especially a personal God or gods. 2. A particular system of faith and worship. 3. A pursuit or interest to which someone gives supreme importance.</item>
<item>Religious: Relating to or believing in a religion.</item>
<item>Atheism: 1. Disbelief or lack of belief in the existence of God or gods. 2. Skepticism, being unsure about whether or not a god or gods exist.</item>
<item>Atheist: 1. A person who disbelieves or lacks belief in the existence of God or gods. 2. A person who has no spiritual beliefs.</item></list></item>
<item>Learn about your subjects. Knowing is good, but learning by yourself is better. Do research on atheism, on the religion that interests you, get the definitions clear in your mind. Understand what it means to choose a religion, to choose to be atheist, or even to create your own beliefs. Because a religion is made to understand things we can't explain better, and if you have your own beliefs, you don't have to pick a religion. The research will also help you see all the sides of the medal, so you don't have prejudice and you can stay open-minded.</item>
<item>Note your impressions. Get a notebook and write everything about religions that interest you, about being an atheist, about anything you need. That way, you will stay organized.</item></list>
<head>Learning Your Own Beliefs</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Do it logically. Make a list of pros and cons for each religion (including atheism) in your notebook. Write as many arguments as you can. Try to see if one religion comes out more frequently, has more pros or more cons, or has more interesting pros or cons. You can also compare them with categories, such as holidays, restrictions, general beliefs, etc. You can also ask your family and friends what they think, and see if they come up with pros or cons you didn't think of. Basically, try to get a visual representation of what happens in your mind to help you get your ideas clear.</item>
<item>Do it spiritually. Do meditation before going to bed, and think about your most profound beliefs. Let your heart guide you. Check out videos on YouTube on how to meditate. Plus, if you do it before going to sleep, your subconscious will work on it during the night and you will have clearer ideas in the morning. The basic concept here is to see where your mind tells you to go, to follow your guts and to be open-minded.</item>
<item>Try it out! If one religion comes out more, always pops up in your mind, or you have any feeling this could be what you want, try adopting the religion for a year. If you think this is how you want to live, if you think this is what you believe in, then good job! You have made your choice. If not, try again from the beginning. Maybe you would prefer a religion that you didn't yet think of, or maybe you prefer not knowing and simply following the flow of life, seeing where it will lead you. In the end, it all comes to you.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always remember that you can switch if you don't like the religion you chose.</item>
<item>Talk to people of the religions that interest you. Nothing is better than talking to someone who lived it to tell you more about that religion!</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Never base your decisions on what others may think of you.</item>
<item>Never base your decisions on prejudice. Not being open-minded will hide great opportunities from you.</item>
<item>Base your decisions mostly on beliefs. If you love your religion but don't believe in the god of that religion, you should quit and search for what you really believe in.</item></list>
</text>
