<text id="autogum_whow_doc154" title="Use a Communications Degree" shortTile="use-communications" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2014-10-25" dateModified="2018-08-22" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Use-a-Communications-Degree" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Use a Communications Degree</head><p>Communications degrees can be used in many ways to obtain work in a variety of areas. The field of communications is broad and you can "tailor" your degree to something that truly fits your interests.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Training in communications</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find a college that best suits you. Many colleges offer degrees in communications, but some programs are considered to be better than others. Consider many different things when seeking out a college that offers communications degrees, such as the location of the school, the price of the schooling, and how prestigious the program is considered to be. Bear in mind that just because a school offers communications, this does not mean that it is a strong program.</item>
<item>Select a specialization. When you seek a degree in communications, you must often choose an area of or focus. Many colleges offer different areas of specialization, such as journalism, advertising, or public relations. Often you won't have to decide your focus in your first year or two of college or even your major, so take this time to explore the different areas by taking classes that relate to your own communications interests. You can always talk to your advisor about the classes you can take, to help you make your decision.</item>
<item>Get involved. Many colleges have communication related clubs, such as an advertising club or the school newspaper. Not only are these great ways to get involved and meet new people, they are often a great way to get real world experience and maybe even some extra money. However, some of these things can add to your workload, so don't let it take precedence over your studies.</item></list>
<head>Getting employed in the communications field</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Put your qualifications to good use. Colleges are often able to help you get internships to get you on your way. This is a great place to start, as internships are a good way to get more real world experience and get your name out there. Sometimes, internships can lead to job offers.</item>
<item>Start looking for job openings online in a field you desire. Use your degree to show employers that you know your field inside out. Use your prior college work experience to show that you know how to work in your field. Don't give up, and remember you may not make a million dollars overnight, but hard work pays off!</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always work hard and don't get down on yourself if you don't find work right away.</item>
<item>Always have a "learning attitude" you can learn a lot about communicating simply by watching TV or talking to people in everyday situations.</item>
<item>Have good grammar. It is unhelpful to read work written by students and workers in the communications field that shows a lack of good grammar and spelling, which is the foundation of the very tool that they have chosen to work with, language. If you are weak in this area, do something about it.</item></list>
</text>
