<text id="autogum_whow_doc305" title="Check an Internal Meat Temperature" shortTile="check-internal-meat" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-09-17" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Check-an-Internal-Meat-Temperature" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Check an Internal Meat Temperature</head><p>A meat thermometer checks the internal temperature of cooked meat to ensure that the meat is thoroughly cooked and hot enough to kill any harmful bacteria that might be present, without overcooking the meat. A meat thermometer is also used to check the temperature of casseroles containing meat, meat loaves and egg dishes. How to check an internal meat temperature depends on the meat and how you're cooking it.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Buying a Thermometer</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Read the label to make sure you're buying a meat thermometer and not a candy or oven thermometer. If you think you may have difficulty operating a digital thermometer, buy one with a needle gauge. However, digital thermometers do have a distinct advantage. They provide a more precise temperature reading in a matter of seconds. This will keep less heat from escaping your oven or outdoor grill while your are checking the meat's temperature.  <figure rend="Check an Internal Meat Temperature Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Buy an instant-read thermometer for meats such as ground beef patties, pork chops or grilled chicken. An instant read thermometer is inserted into the meat at the end of cooking time to check the internal temperature. <figure rend="Check an Internal Meat Temperature Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Purchase a probe thermometer for meats such as whole birds, ham, beef or lamb roasts. A probe is designed to be inserted in the meat before the meat is placed in the oven, and allows you to monitor the temperature and know when the meat has finished cooking. <figure rend="Check an Internal Meat Temperature Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use a meat thermometer specially designed for microwave use if you cook meat in the microwave. <figure rend="Check an Internal Meat Temperature Step 4.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Inserting the Thermometer</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Insert a probe thermometer into the thickest part of the meat, being careful not to touch the bone, which will be hotter than the meat around it. Don't allow the thermometer to rest on the roasting pan or dish. <figure rend="Check an Internal Meat Temperature Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>When cooking whole birds, insert the thermometer into the thickest part of the thigh with the readout or gauge toward the wing. Be careful that the thermometer doesn't touch the bone.</item></list></item>
<item>Test steaks, ground beef patties and other thinner cuts of meat by inserting an instant-read thermometer 1.3 cm (0.5 inches) into the meat. Be careful not insert the thermometer completely through the meat, and avoid touching the grill, pan or plate. If you're using a needle gauge, wait a few seconds for the needle to stop moving before reading the temperature. <figure rend="Check an Internal Meat Temperature Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remove the thinnest cuts of meat from the stove-top or grill and test by inserting the thermometer from the side to prevent touching the thermometer to the pan or grill. <figure rend="Check an Internal Meat Temperature Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Temperatures</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Grill or roast beef and lamb to different temperatures depending on the desired term. These cuts of meat will have contaminating bacteria only on the outside, so it's safe to leave the center less than thoroughly cooked. <figure rend="Check an Internal Meat Temperature Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Medium rare (bright pink center): 63°C (145°F)</item>
<item>Medium (light pink center): 71°C (160°F)</item>
<item>Well done (no pink): 77°C (170°F)</item></list></item>
<item>Cook ground beef, pork, chicken or turkey to a temperature of 74°C (165°F). Because the meat is ground, contaminating bacteria might be present throughout the meat. It's therefore never safe to serve ground meat that's less than well done. <figure rend="Check an Internal Meat Temperature Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Roast whole birds or breasts to a temperature of 74°C (165°F). <figure rend="Check an Internal Meat Temperature Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You should also cook the stuffing to 74°C (165°F), since many stuffing recipes incorporate juices or other parts of the bird.</item></list></item>
<item>Roast, fry or grill pork to a temperature of at least 64°C (145°F). It's not safe to serve undercooked pork because the meat may contain parasites that cause trichinosis. <figure rend="Check an Internal Meat Temperature Step 11 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Heat a cooked ham until the internal temperature is 60°C (140°C). An uncooked ham should be roasted until to 63°C (145°F). <figure rend="Check an Internal Meat Temperature Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Cook most fish to a temperature of 60°C (140°F). Game fish such as tuna or marlin should only be cooked to an internal temperature of 52°C (125°F) or it will dry out and become unpalatable. <figure rend="Check an Internal Meat Temperature Step 13 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Reheat all leftovers until they reach a temperature of 74°C (165°F)  <figure rend="Check an Internal Meat Temperature Step 14 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remove egg dishes and casseroles from the oven when the temperature reaches 71°C (160°F) and casseroles when they reach 74°C (165°F). <figure rend="Check an Internal Meat Temperature Step 15 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>When roasting meat, remove it from the oven when it reaches the desired temperature, but don't remove the thermometer. Leave it in place, and let the meat rest until the internal temperature stops rising. The meat will continue to cook for up to 90 minutes, depending on its size. It will be more tasty if allowed to rest.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't rely on pop-up thermometers, which are not accurate, or on the color of the center of ground beef to determine the term.</item>
<item>When placing meat dishes on a buffet or otherwise allowing them to sit, use a thermometer to make sure the internal temperature stays above 60°C (140°F). If it cools to below 60 degrees, contaminating bacteria may start to grow.</item></list>
</text>
