<text id="autogum_whow_doc221" title="Plan and Organize a Family Reunion" shortTile="plan-organize-family" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2005-10-11" dateModified="2019-09-13" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Plan-and-Organize-a-Family-Reunion" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Plan and Organize a Family Reunion</head><p>Since the advent of the personal computer and network technology, genealogy research by family members has become an addictive pastime that has contributed to many happy family reunions. But what if you were asked to organize the next event? Where would you start? When should you start? Should you hire a family reunion planner, form a reunion committee or do it all yourself?</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Ask for other family members to help with planning activities and choosing the time and place. Get the word out - let others know you're planning a family reunion event. Give family members plenty of notice. Usually three or four months advance notice will allow attendees to plan vacation time or make adjustments in scheduling. <figure rend="Plan and Organize a Family Reunion Step 01.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Assign each member of your newly formed reunion committee a specific task. This could be tasks such as T-shirts and memorabilia, genealogy presentations including memorials and historic tours, entertainment, dining events, Reunion Book, entertainment, photography, etc. <figure rend="Plan and Organize a Family Reunion Step 02.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Give each member written instructions regarding how to execute his or her task. Create a time line reminder. Make good use of Family Reunion Planner organizers that feature schedulers and time line reminders. Make use of Event Planning Software with editable worksheets and templates. <figure rend="Plan and Organize a Family Reunion Step 03.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Schedule the next meeting one or two months away and follow up on all action items. Keep the lines of communication wide open. <figure rend="Plan and Organize a Family Reunion Step 04.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Hold each person responsible for their assignment. <figure rend="Plan and Organize a Family Reunion Step 05.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Decide some of the main things that will occur at the reunion. For example, you may wish to honor the elders and accomplished members of the family, acknowledge those who are going through something, etc. Be sure to encourage each other. <figure rend="Plan and Organize a Family Reunion Step 06.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>During the gathering have food and drink available.</item>
<item>Share stories and anecdotes. Don't gossip or spread rumors; keep everything positive and friendly.</item>
<item>Bring lots, and lots of love. Even for people you usually clash with!</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>There are many family reunion planning tools online. Make use of planning material that features the following: a time line, preparation reminders, scheduling worksheets, committee assignment sheets, reunion needs lists, meal planners and checklists and T-Shirt Rosters.</item>
<item>There are many ways to do your family reunion on the cheap. You can get free stuff from your local Chamber of Commerce, museums and tourist centers, find free spots to congregate at universities, and get free invitations and eCards online.</item>
<item>You might like to consider holding a small family gathering to plan and organize a committee for starting annual or regular family reunions. It depends on how much effort you wish to put in.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't settle for services simply because they are cheap and local. Get recommendations from folks who do not stand to profit.</item>
<item>Don't procrastinate.</item>
<item>Delegate tasks according to skill and competence.</item></list>
</text>
