<text id="autogum_whow_doc128" title="Play with a Sphero 2.0" shortTile="play-sphero-" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-09-19" dateModified="2018-09-27" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Play-with-a-Sphero-2.0" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Play with a Sphero 2.0</head><p>A Sphero 2.0 is fun toy for anybody, but it can seem complicated to set up and drive your Sphero. This wikiHow will teach you the essentials of using and having fun with your toy.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Setting Up Your Sphero</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Download the Sphero app. Open the App Store or Google Play and search for the Sphero app. Install it.</item>
<item>Charge your Sphero. Place the Sphero into the charging cradle. The light on the base of the charging cradle will begin blinking blue, and turn solid when it is fully charged. For more information on charging your Sphero, go to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Charge_the_Sphero">How to Charge the Sphero</ref>. <figure rend="Charge the Sphero Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wake your Sphero up. To wake your Sphero up, double tap with your hand or a hard surface. Often it will only respond to tapping on a hard surface - don't worry about harming it.
<list type="unordered"><item>The Sphero will begin flashing colors when successfully woken up.</item></list></item>
<item>Pair your Sphero. On iOS, open Settings &gt; General &gt; Bluetooth. When the Sphero is detected, it will begin to pair with your device. On Android, open Settings &gt; Wireless Controls &gt; Bluetooth. When the Sphero is detected, click on its name to begin pairing.  <figure rend="AFF7C3FA E88D 4030 A3A5 35A8270B4601.jpeg"></figure></item>
<item>Open the Sphero app. The app will automatically connect with the Sphero each time it is opened. <figure rend="D778A1AD CD16 43D8 911A E62A2CD709F4.png"></figure></item>
<item>Name your Sphero. After the app connects with the Sphero, it will open to a screen asking for a name. <figure rend="807D222A 449D 4B6A A02F 5560E591FE67.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can always change its name by opening settings in the app (located on the left side of the circle) and tapping on the Sphero icon three times. This will take you to advanced settings, and at the top of the page you will have to option of renaming it.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Driving Your Sphero</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open the Sphero app. The app will automatically detect the Sphero. <figure rend="D778A1AD CD16 43D8 911A E62A2CD709F4.png"></figure></item>
<item>Aim your Sphero. On the bottom left corner of the controlling screen, you will see a circle with two arrows pointing opposite directions. Face the Sphero, then press and hold on this button, and rotate your finger around the circle until the blue tail light is pointed at you. <figure rend="3EF50784 0207 450C AE44 B2583D0F8CC9.jpeg"></figure></item>
<item>Move the Sphero. In the center of the screen, there is a control pad with a four-pronged arrow in the middle. To move the robot, move the arrow in the direction you wish it to go in. <figure rend="2B768D3B CADC 4B73 9F4F F8F086D3E8A4.jpeg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can change the controlling method to tilt by clicking the icon of a phone and two arrows facing different directions on top of it.</item></list></item>
<item>Go on missions. Directly to the right of the control pad is a curved rectangle with 3 dots, and a number representing the number of challenges you have, followed by the word "Missions." Click on this for a list of challenges to complete, such as driving your robot a certain distance in a certain amount of time, making sure it doesn't crash after it has been "hacked," even shaking it.  <figure rend="7CA175CC 2476 4B5C A346 891773FE424C.jpeg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Doing these challenges will result in level-ups, which grant you cores (Sphero's arm of "currency") and tricks. You can also buy tricks with the cores.</item></list></item>
<item>Level up. Above the control pad, a curved bar with a number represents your progress in levels. Doing missions will help you level up, as will driving the Sphero around.  <figure rend="04FF3271 0ECE 405F A0F5 85DA19D1E5FD.jpeg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>A line of black bars spreading along the level-up bar represents how close you are to leveling up. When you have leveled up, the bar will glow white. Click to it to receive gifts, but remember that 20 is the max level.</item></list></item>
<item>Perform tricks. In the bottom right corner, there will be an icon of a Sphero, though its activity and position varies, with six square dots in two rows at the bottom. Click on the dots to scroll through your list of tricks. Click on a trick to read its description, then press "Select". To do it, tap on the icon of the Sphero performing the trick.  <figure rend="A0F0B009 E40D 4E16 BD82 91D924B0AFEB.jpeg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Some tricks require the Sphero to move or require the icon to be held down.</item></list></item>
<item>Change your Sphero's color. Beneath the level-up bar directly on the left side, there is a pallet button. Press that, then tap the color on the color wheel that you would like. When you have chosen a color, click the green arrow in the top left corner. <figure rend="F6BE6E37 B97A 48EA 9D92 D17336AA6E2C.jpeg"></figure></item>
<item>Change the speed of your Sphero. Situated directly beneath the control pad there is a curved bar, a turtle button on one side, a rabbit button on the other, and a percentage just to the left of the rabbit button. Click the turtle button to make the Sphero go slower, and the rabbit button to make it speed up. <figure rend="D60CD11F 24C2 4753 8F04 82CD2D37A882.jpeg"></figure></item>
<item>Boost the Sphero. Above the trick button, there is a rectangle featuring the Sphero going at high speeds. Click on this to make the Sphero temporarily speed up.  <figure rend="7536C648 9B66 4E7D BB26 AB4358BDD8E1.jpeg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The boost bar will automatically fill up by driving around.</item></list></item>
<item>Go on core drops. Just to the right of the speed bar, there is a circle with three plus signs surrounding it. Pressing this will enter a mode where you can collect cores by driving around. Where the challenges button typically is, there is a new button Sphero icon with a bar a the bottom. When you are far away from a core collection, the button will be blue. Drive in any direction until the bar begins to become yellow. When the bar is green, press the button to 'warp' and gain cores. Your goal is to get as many cores as possible within a time limit. <figure rend="FE2847B4 0DD4 4BB9 A193 CF8CE7B1BF20.jpeg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The Sphero will rotate and make noises when warped.</item></list></item>
<item>Play other games. There are a wide variety of other apps that you can play with the Sphero, available on the App Store and Google Play, such as Color Grab and Chromo Drive. There is also an educational app that teaches coding, like Sphero Edu. <figure rend="2B93EEAB 0008 4E66 BFEA C0D223728344.png"></figure></item></list>
</text>
