<text id="autogum_whow_doc418" title="Enjoy a Vietnamese Traditional Martial Arts Festival" shortTile="enjoy-vietnamese" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2010-11-17" dateModified="2018-07-22" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Enjoy-a-Vietnamese-Traditional-Martial-Arts-Festival" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Enjoy a Vietnamese Traditional Martial Arts Festival</head><p>The three-day Vietnamese traditional martial arts festival in central Binh Dinh Province, father land of the “Viet Vo Dao”, is not only a way to popularize the Viet’s martial arts, but also a reflection of its prestige in the world.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Coming to Binh Dinh and attending the festival, you can join local teams and witness the showcase for their talent in martial arts, as well as Binh Dinh’s scenic beauty and distinctive, appealing culture. Participants demonstrated their various performances at the villages, allowing everyone to imbibe the unique aspects of martial arts in different cultures. <figure rend="Enjoy a Vietnamese Traditional Martial Arts Festival Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Visit the province’s martial arts villages such as An Thai and An Vinh, where you can learn about the time-honored arts from successors of martial arts forefathers. The festival features enthralling events including battle drumming, international martial arts competitions and a beauty pageant with some of Vietnam’s most dangerous women. <figure rend="Enjoy a Vietnamese Traditional Martial Arts Festival Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Listen to the battle drum. Tay Son battle drumming has always been close to locals hearts. It is said that during battle, Nguyen Hue, who later became Emperor Quang Trung, used a 12 drum system, which symbolized Asia’s 12 zodiac signs, to give battle commands, boost his soldiers’ morale and convert his enemies to good causes. According to Tran Dinh Ky, director of King Quang Trung museum in Quy Nhon Town, Tay Son battle drumming is a special genre which blends military and artistic elements and is based on the traditional sound systems such as ho, xang and xe. It is extremely difficult to express the “soul” of Tay Son battle drumming, which explains why few artists can perform it well. <figure rend="Enjoy a Vietnamese Traditional Martial Arts Festival Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Enjoy the beauty pageant. In the festival, beauties from martial arts schools in almost 40 countries participate in a beauty pageant titled “Hoa hau nhung mien dat vo” (Beauties from the Lands of Martial Arts). <figure rend="Enjoy a Vietnamese Traditional Martial Arts Festival Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Tuong (Vietnamese classical drama) and particularly tuong from the province’s Dao Tan tuong theater, one of Vietnam’s tuong cradles, is also a part of the contest. In Binh Dinh tuong and martial arts share some of the same movements giving them a close connection.</item></list></item>
<item>The festival begins with a procession and flower offering, at King Quang Trung museum at 8 a.m, to honor Emperor Quang Trung, a shrewd king and a great national hero. <figure rend="Enjoy a Vietnamese Traditional Martial Arts Festival Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>On the next day, ride in 22 sailboats, which symbolize 22 years of “doi moi” (economic reform), and let loose flower garlands and colored lanterns at Thi Nai Bay and Thi Nai Bridge. <figure rend="Enjoy a Vietnamese Traditional Martial Arts Festival Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Attend the fireworks shows and traditional musical performances by local and international artists throughout the festival. <figure rend="Enjoy a Vietnamese Traditional Martial Arts Festival Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Visit the traditional handicraft fair, with many stalls at the central park in Quy Nhon Town. <figure rend="Enjoy a Vietnamese Traditional Martial Arts Festival Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Relish specialties such as the very strong Bau Da wine and Phu My nem (fermented pork roll) at the fair. An ornamental plant fair and competition featuring a wide variety of rare plants and bonsai from across the country is organized at the province’s Labor Cultural House. <figure rend="Enjoy a Vietnamese Traditional Martial Arts Festival Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
