<text id="autogum_whow_doc158" title="Attract Parents to Your Daycare" shortTile="attract-parents-daycare" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-03-06" dateModified="2019-03-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Attract-Parents-to-Your-Daycare" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Attract Parents to Your Daycare</head><p>Keeping your daycare or preschool at maximum enrollment is essential for the overall success of your center. Word of mouth and positive reviews are powerful tools for attracting parents to your daycare. However, you need to reach parents and grow your enrollment before you can take advantage of these assets. When starting a new childcare center, use these steps to attract parents to your daycare.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Know your audience. You may work with infants, toddlers and school-aged kids all day, but growing your center means seeking out parents. Understanding the parents you’re trying to reach will help you offer services and features that matter to them. More than three-quarters of babies are now parented by millennials, the generation born between 1980 and 2000. To fill your daycare, you need to appeal to this new generation of parents.
<list type="unordered"><item>Millennial parents love personalization, technology, and experiences (rather than things). Both moms and dads are more involved in decision-making when it comes to raising kids than in the past, so you need to create services that appeal to both parents.</item>
<item>More than ¾ of dads research parenting topics on YouTube.  Dads also rely on websites, social media, apps, and blogs to be better parents. These are all places where your childcare center can connect with today’s dads, using content marketing and digital ads.</item></list></item>
<item>Find your competitive advantage. Nearby centers are competing to connect with the same audience. To stand out, you need to identify what makes you different. Why should moms and dads looking for the right daycare option choose you?
<list type="unordered"><item>First, take a look at what nearby centers are doing both on- and off-line. Drive by local daycares and note what they look like from the outside. Are they inviting? Does their sign make it easy for parents to find them? Is their playground protected from busy streets and passersby?</item>
<item>Then, turn to Google. Search using phrases parents would use, like “daycare centers near me.” Go through the first few pages of search results for approximately 10 unique phrases you think parents would search with. Click on websites and make notes of what first impression your competitors are leaving online. You should also spend some time brainstorming the strengths and weaknesses of businesses that aren’t direct competitors but could still appeal to local parents looking for childcare. Examples include summer camps, nannies and in-home daycares.</item>
<item>After reviewing the competition, think about what makes your childcare business different from these other local businesses. These are the features you should highlight when looking to attract parents to your daycare. Whether you’re focused on education, offer extended hours or have highly-qualified teachers, own it!</item></list></item>
<item>Build your brand. Build a brand around your competitive advantage and the audience you want to connect with. Your brand, or “personality,” includes a logo, colors, fonts, tone of voice, tagline and other elements that help parents immediately recognize your center. Use these brand elements consistently in every place you are connecting with parents, like your physical center, business cards, flyers, social media profiles, and website.</item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Advertise_a_Preschool">Advertise your daycare</ref>. Advertising helps you put your daycare in front of parents who may be looking for childcare. Consider where your audience (identified in Step 1) spends time. Millennial parents search for parenting advice and service reviews online, so this is one of the first places you should advertise.
<list type="unordered"><item>A website is a great starting point. All of your other advertising, both online and off, should point toward your website, where you have unlimited space to talk about what makes your center great.</item>
<item>Online advertising tools include paid and organic social media (Facebook, Twitter, LinkedIn, Instagram, Pinterest, YouTube, etc.), content marketing, search engine optimization, email marketing, search ads, and display ads.</item>
<item>Offline, consider flyers, lawn signs, car magnets, and community partnerships and events. Make sure all of your advertising, both traditional and digital, includes your competitive advantages and brand elements.</item></list></item>
<item>Turn leads into customers. Your advertising will encourage parents to call to learn more, fill out a contact form on your website or sign up for a tour. Once you have contact information for a family interested in your center, they are considered a lead. To fill your daycare or preschool, you need to turn these leads into enrollments.
<list type="unordered"><item>You want to attract parents to your daycare and reassure nervous moms and dads that you are the right place for their child. A thorough tour, friendly and knowledgeable staff, open communication, modern facility and positive reputation are what it takes to turn leads into customers.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
