<text id="autogum_whow_doc582" title="Understand Life" shortTile="understand-life" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2016-12-24" dateModified="2018-10-12" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Understand-Life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Understand Life</head><p>So far, I have finished one way to develop life and universe understanding. More are coming. Please comment on anything you think is a good method. Or, put you method into the comments box. Which way? Who knows? Do you even understand the questions you are asking about questions? But is the question really about questions? Dig deep, always deep. Unless, it's digging you in deep. Understand the universe and all it's life, let it understand you.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Yoga</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>I also at a point thought that yoga was pointless. Then, I realized how much it it helped me and gave me a way to stay peaceful and calm the rest of the day. However if this doesn't work for you, then there are other ways. However, I encourage trying it at least once.</item>
<item>Find a wide and spacious area where you can set up. This is a very important step, because small areas can do the opposite of give you meaning, and instead just make you feel stuck and unimportant. This is not what you want.</item>
<item>Lay down several mats, even if it is just you. Having more room than you need is a good thing, and maybe even essential, depending on the person. Make sure that the mats are both thick, and soft, as if you could dig into the endless meaning of life through it.</item>
<item>Turn on some soothing music. Now, when I say "soothing music", I mean soothing to you. If rock and roll or heavy metal are your favorite kinds of music, go for it! It does not have to be slow, or quiet.</item>
<item>Create a motivation. Do not buy therapy cards, or any kind of idea givers. Think of one yourself, otherwise you'll find that you are convincing yourself that something someone else said is you. That is not always true, and it takes a lot to figure out what exactly is real, and what is just a mindset.</item>
<item>Either do poses, or lie down thinking. Ask yourself questions like,How important to me is my motavation?What would change in the world without me?Suppose I put all my effort into improving the world. How would it change? How much am I capable of?Do I have any beliefs or religions? How do they effect how I think or act?This should lead to more questions, unless you aren't really thinking. Don't think too hard, or it will tire you and distract you from obvious answers. If this takes you hours, it is OK. Don't worry about work, or appointments, anything you are late for. It is just you. What is more important? Full Meaning or Jobs?</item></list>
</text>
