<text id="autogum_whow_doc356" title="Perform an Orbital Transfer" shortTile="perform-orbital-transfer" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-12-16" dateModified="2019-05-08" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Perform-an-Orbital-Transfer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Perform an Orbital Transfer</head><p>An orbital transfer is a maneuver used to change the height of your orbit around a planet, moon or other body. Although you'll probably never need to use this knowledge in real life, it comes in very handy if you're using a simulator like the Kerbal Space Program.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Raising Your Orbit with a Hohmann Transfer</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Decide if you should use a Hohmann transfer. In general, you should use a Hohmann transfer if: desired radius/current radius &lt; 11.95.</item>
<item><figure rend="Hohmann transfer 1.png"></figure>When you reach your periapsis (the lowest point of your orbit), burn prograde (in the direction of travel). This has the effect of raising your apoapsis (the highest point of your orbit). Burn until your apoapsis reaches the height of your desired orbit. You can calculate the delta-v for this burn using the formula in the picture.</item>
<item><figure rend="Hohmann transfer 2.png"></figure>When you reach apoapsis, burn prograde until your periapsis reaches the desired height. This should cause your orbit to circularise. Again, you can use the equation to calculate the delta-v for this burn.</item></list>
<head>Raising Your Orbit with a Bi-Elliptical Transfer</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Decide if you should use a bi-elliptical transfer. You should use this method if: desired radius/current radius &gt; 11.95</item>
<item><figure rend="Bi elliptical transfer 1.png"></figure>When you reach periapsis, burn prograde until your apoapsis is near the edge of the planet's sphere of influence.</item>
<item><figure rend="Bi elliptical transfer 2.png"></figure>When you reach apoapsis, burn prograde until your periapsis reaches the height of the desired orbit. Use a low thrust for this, it won't need much delta-v.</item>
<item><figure rend="Bi elliptical transfer 3.png"></figure>When you reach periapsis, burn retrograde (opposite the direction of motion) until your apoapsis falls to the height of the desired orbit.</item></list>
<head>Lowering Your Orbit with a Hohmann Transfer</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>When you reach apoapsis, burn retrograde until your periapsis reaches the height of the desired orbit. You can use the equations from method one to calculate the delta-v for this and the next step.</item>
<item>When you reach periapsis, burn retrograde until your apoapsis falls to the height of the desired orbit.</item></list>
<head>Lowering Your Orbit with a Bi-Elliptical Transfer</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>When you reach periapsis, burn prograde until your apoapsis is near the edge of the planet's sphere of influence. You can use the equations from method two to calculate the delta-v needed for these steps.</item>
<item>When you reach apoapsis, burn retrograde until your periapsis reaches the desired height.</item>
<item>When you reach periapsis, burn retrograde until your apoapsis falls to the height of the desired orbit.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Periapsis: the lowest point of your orbit</item>
<item>Apoapsis: the highest point of your orbit</item>
<item>Prograde: the direction in which you are moving (not necessarily the direction in which you are facing)</item>
<item>Retrograde: opposite the direction in which you are moving</item>
<item>Sphere of influence: the zone of space in which the gravity of a body is dominant over other gravity sources.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>When performing a bi-elliptical transfer, make sure that your apoapsis doesn't leave the planet's sphere of influence! If it does, you'll escape the planet's gravity and go flying off into space.</item></list>
</text>
