<text id="autogum_whow_doc176" title="Think Like a Businessman" shortTile="think-businessman" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2016-02-04" dateModified="2016-12-15" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Think-Like-a-Businessman" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Think Like a Businessman</head>
<p>We all need to do to business at some point in life, whether it's a small trade or a huge business one.
It is important to think like a businessman for many reasons like to avoid fraud, earn a little cash, or stay out of debt, and this article will teach you how to think like a real businessman!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Do cost benefits analysis of things. this is the basis of most profitable decisions. here you are weighing up what you expect to lose in comparison to what you expect to gain and what benefits you will get from taking certain pathways.</item>
<item>Figure out the usefulness and benefit of products. usefulness and benefit of things often transcribe to whether or not the product is sell-able. when you analyse things look to see how much use it provides.</item>
<item>Have a vision. A vision of what you aim to create is what draws people to you and inspires others to your cause. A good vision will gain you many supporters and investors. it is useful to look at the visions of others to determine which visions are worthwhile.</item>
<item>Value your time. Time is something you never get back and valuing it makes you spend it well. Old age and death creep up on people before they are aware and they live with lots of regrets. managing your time well also makes people respect you.</item>
<item>Look to see how you can best organise people. The organisation of people for a purpose is the fundamental aspect of a company. if you can organise people for a reason you can form a company and begin.</item>
<item>Pay attention to where things are going to waste. A sense of wastefulness is paramount to reorganising your resources in a way that is best for you. If you have no sense of where things are going to waste then you will dwindle accumulated wealth little by little. Look at what is going to waste - energy, time, resources, skills and then find ways to use them.</item>
<item>Pay attention to innovative ideas and methods. In this way, you develop a means to do things in ways that are more efficient. many people have it in their heads that the only way to do things is the way that it has been done for a long time, however, this is not based in reality and can be very time consuming for little reward.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you're not sure whether a trade is good or not be sure to ask a friend or family member to avoid getting ripped off!</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you aren't careful you may lose a lot of cash and/or items!</item>
<item>Do <hi rend="bold">NOT</hi> make illegal trades/business deals!</item>
<item>You may not start thinking like one right away, but remember practice makes perfect!</item></list>
</text>
