<text id="autogum_whow_doc694" title="Take a Shortcut" shortTile="take-shortcut" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2009-06-17" dateModified="2018-08-03" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Take-a-Shortcut" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Take a Shortcut</head><p>Taking shortcuts is often considered an awful idea. Everyone has seen the cartoons where a sign saying "Shortcut" often leads unaware travelers off a cliff. Most have also attempted to take a shortcut, only to become disoriented and lose more time than it was worth. However, with ample planning and forethought, you can cut travel time in half, leaving you with more time to do things you enjoy.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Think about your common travel routes, and how bothersome each one is. Are any of them busy, dangerous, or just unpleasant? If so, then a shortcut may be in order. <figure rend="Drive Through a Ghetto Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Acquire a map of some kind. Try <ref target="http://earth.google.com">Google Earth</ref>; it's free and allows you to see buildings, where a regular map usually does not. <figure rend="Get Away from the Computer Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Look at the path between your starting location to the end</hi>. Find the most efficient driving path, then see how much closer it would be "as the crow flies." Basically, draw a straight line between Point A and Point B. Then, see how closely you can follow this line on foot. The image below displays an effective example. The yellow line is the path that would be taken by a car. It isn't very efficient, and you feel a shortcut could be found. The green line is "as the crow flies", and the red line is the actual path. With this example, you'd save only a minute or two, at the most. However, by applying the same techniques, you can complete a 20-minute round trip in a fraction of the time. <figure rend="Pass Safely on a Two Lane Road Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If traveling by foot is not an option, a shortcut may still be possible. Try taking a new route to work every day, skipping the busiest roads and using a residential road. While the speed limit may be lowered, you can avoid traffic jams and stop lights by using less occupied roads.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Plan out your path before you need to travel. After that, make sure you are clear on the exact path you mean to take. You don't want to have to re-orient yourself and end up late for an appointment.</item>
<item>Parking lots, especially large ones, often have multiple exits. Use these to skip busy intersections, or avoid a red light.</item>
<item>Biking or rollerblading often allows you to go many places a car cannot, and you travel faster than on foot. Additionally, you can walk through the woods, then put on your roller blades when you reach the street.</item>
<item>There are roads that, for one reason or another, do not end up on any maps. Keep an eye open for these, as they are often made for the purpose of being shortcuts. Even a small field could be crossed with a car, shaving lots of time off your traveling. (Obviously, don't drive across a soccer or baseball field; those require maintenance and you may damage the field.)</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Crossing busy streets or walking at night can be risky. Judge for yourself if your shortcut is safe, and always have a flashlight when walking at night.</item>
<item>Cutting through private property is rude and should be avoided. Some homeowners are very sensitive about their lawns or privacy and do not want either violated. Talk to the owner before entering their yard.</item></list>
</text>
