<text id="autogum_whow_doc326" title="Eat Neatly" shortTile="eat-neatly" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2007-07-05" dateModified="2016-05-13" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Eat-Neatly" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Eat Neatly</head><p>Eating neatly is a sign that you care about the appearance you are presenting at the table and that you appreciate your food and the effort that someone has gone to in putting the food together. Unless you suffer from a disease or you are under the age of 12 years old, you should be able to overcome messy eating habits.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Use your silverware properly. Except for some foods (sandwiches, pizza, etc;) you have to use your fork and knife. If you are at a fancy restaurant, the salad fork is the small fork and the larger one is for the main course. If you are uncertain of these utensils, just watch the host, they should know what they are doing.  If you are eating certain foods, (steak, etc;) you will have to use a knife. Hold the fork in your left hand and the knife in your right. <figure rend="Eat Neatly Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Eat slowly. This way you can actually have have a conversation with the person you are eating with. It also helps you to digest your food properly, which makes you feel more full, so you eat less and become fitter, <figure rend="Eat Neatly Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Stay polite throughout the meal. Don't hog the conversation, chew with your mouth <hi rend="italic">closed</hi> and finally, don't pick at your food. <figure rend="Eat Neatly Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use your napkin. Always keep it in your lap, and if somebody tells you that you need to wipe your mouth, don't get mad about it. Just say, "Thank you." When you eat with your napkin, either stuff it down your shirt so you don't get it on yourself or put it on your lap and lean more closely to the table when you eat. <figure rend="Eat Neatly Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>When you're full, stop. It's not impolite to leave food on your plate, and if you are finished you could just save it and warm the rest up for your supper. Eat as much as you can until you feel full, but there is an easy way to eat it all. Chew it into tiny pieces and take smaller amounts and also after every three mouthfuls stop for a bit to let the food go down. If everyone else grabs desert, and you're not hungry, don't give into "Social Snacking." Instead, keep drinking water in between chats. <figure rend="Eat Neatly Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Turn off your mobile phone. However tempting it may be to send a text to everyone about your new pair of shoes, it's very impolite and distracts the entire dinner party.</item>
<item>When eating a food that drips or has crumbs, bring your plate closer to the edge of the table or your mouth closer to the plate. This allows your plate to catch any drips or crumbs and avoids a mess.</item>
<item>Keep your posture from slouching because it kind of is impolite.</item></list>
</text>
