<text id="autogum_whow_doc235" title="Use Bollinger Bands" shortTile="use-bollinger-bands" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-03-23" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Use-Bollinger-Bands" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Use Bollinger Bands</head><p>Bollinger Bands are a relatively recent invention within the sphere of technical analysis to help investors assess holdings and plan for future capital gains. Developed by financial analyst John Bollinger, the idea of Bollinger Bands establishes detailed future price probability data based on moving averages and fundamentals for a stock or fund. For those who want to use Bollinger Bands for any kind of investment strategy, here are some critical steps for succeeding with analysis that includes these pricing tools.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Start with a time frame. Like other analytical stock tools and moving averages, the Bollinger Bands are really only meaningful when applied to a specific timeline. Choosing a window will help the investor more accurately describe what he or she sees in the activity of Bollinger Bands around an equity.</item>
<item>Understand the triple band setup of Bollinger Bands. The basic explanation from established sources is that the middle band represents a simple moving average that impacts the upper and lower bands. What all of this leads to is a projection of price probabilities based on established price movements.</item>
<item>Read about the use of the "envelope" for Bollinger Bands. Traders often use Bollinger Bands to figure out relative highs and lows within a specific price environment. The envelope represents a region within the parameters laid out by the bands that can help traders evaluate various prices.</item>
<item>Use Bollinger Bands within a good visual context. The best uses of Bollinger Bands often include software designed to display equity prices to analysts, investors or others.
<list type="unordered"><item>Include candlestick charting. Candlestick charting, with its daily candle and wick design, provides all of the dynamic price movement in a market day (or longer time period) at a glance. Mixing in Bollinger Bands with candlestick charting can provide more detail on which to base market decisions.</item></list></item>
<item>Apply Bollinger Bands to diversified holdings. An investor who fails to develop a diversified portfolio is playing with fire no matter how analytical he/she gets. Bollinger Bands and other tools will not guarantee you protection in a volatile market environment. Be sure you have correctly weighted your portfolio among several asset classes.</item>
<item>Use Bollinger Bands with an overall trading strategy. In addition to diversification, investors will want to have a specific trading philosophy and master plan in hand. Without a desired goal, it's hard to know when to sell equities for profit. Bollinger Bands can help individuals get closer to identifying price movements, but gaining from them usually requires a good set of strategic plans.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Keep an international perspective. Bollinger Bands can be applied to equities  regardless of where they're traded. Learn to trade in international markets, including foreign currency exchanges.</item>
<item>Keep reading the opinions of various analysts. With Bollinger Bands, it's often how they are interpreted that counts. Single investors should not base all of what they do on the opinions of others, but knowing how analysts view the use of Bollinger Bands in a given  instance can be helpful.</item></list>
</text>
