<text id="autogum_whow_doc216" title="Survive a Family Reunion" shortTile="survive-family-reunion" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2013-03-25" dateModified="2019-08-13" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Survive-a-Family-Reunion" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Survive a Family Reunion</head><p>Family reunions sound different to all of us. Some Tweens would think, yay family time! Most tweens would think, OMG, worst night of my life, the kids are annoying, old people are scary-that sort of thing. Well, here is how to survive it.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Bring a pad of lined paper, a book, or iPod touch. Then before you leave, print out hard math sheets [but make sure you have the answers] to pretend to do. Other types of worksheets or real homework is acceptable. If your parents say no, bring a book and pretend is it class reading. <figure rend="Survive a Family Reunion Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>When you arrive, you will probably receive over excited hellos and hugs. One subtle way to show you do not want to be bothered is to stand in a pencil position and do not open your arms. <figure rend="Survive a Family Reunion Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Amusing yourself. First, inform someone where you are going. Do not inform a young kid, and old person or your parents. Maybe a cousin, or a more childish adult. The go to the sitting area and read[or play on your iPod touch, or draw]. Do not barricade yourself behind a chair, or on the floor in the corner. That will make you more conspicuous. <figure rend="Survive a Family Reunion Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>When dinner is called GO TO THE TABLE.  If you have a choice, it is best to sit a t the corner, near a baby, a quiet teenager, anyone who knows what you are doing. If the dinner is started with prayers bow your head and mumble. Under the table read, draw, or play iPhone with the VOLUME DOWN. Take small portions of food to have another excuse to get more. You can also use napkins as an excuse. <figure rend="Survive a Family Reunion Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Dessert is sometimes the only enjoyable part. Again, take small portions or messy food. If you get messy and small portions, this will give an excuse to get up to get napkins or seconds. <figure rend="Survive a Family Reunion Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>In my family, we read stories form the bible before and after dinner. If you cannot read, Hebrew, Chinese, or your religious language, mention it to the host quietly during dessert. If you then are asked to read English, DO NOT MUMBLE in the vain hope you will not have to read it. Speak clearly. If there are words you do not feel comfortable saying, simple skip them by 'accident' or say them wrong. Do not change t he word. <figure rend="Survive a Family Reunion Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If games are played, play quietly and do not be competitive. If you can worm your way out of playing, good for you. If you win say something like. "Yay!" or "Wow! I did not think I would". Do  not say it was fun, or that you liked it, because then you will have one less excuse next time. <figure rend="Survive a Family Reunion Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>As you leave find a large cluster and clearly say goodbye. The wave to your hostess and the old people. <figure rend="Survive a Family Reunion Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If some has died DO NOT SMILE, but DO NOT FROWN. Keep a straight face.</item>
<item>Dress appropriately. As we all know it a real challenge to appear fashionable to children and seniors at the same time.</item>
<item>Know your family. Some families have no problem with "high fashion" clothing.</item>
<item>Boys, the usual. Slacks,loafers, but wear a t-shirt. If you have dyed hair wear a hat.</item>
<item>If you have a tattoo, or piercings, try to cover them up/take them out.</item>
<item>Girls should wear a soft cotton top, ballet or long sleeve. No neon. I recommend baby's bedroom colors. Where colored jeans. Not brights, but black, rust, and other dark colors. Where Toms or sandals. Old people think high heels can only be worn by people 30 and over.</item>
<item>Basic Dress Rules: No skinny jeans, no shorts, no short skirts, no crop tops, no netted shirts, no off the shoulder, no tank tops, no tees with objectionable slogans. In short don't wear anything high fashion.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Have something minimized such as a math site like IXL, a vocabulary web site or a typing practice game. If someone starts coming over, open it up.</item>
<item>Before hand memorize these excuses if someone sees your amusement activity:            1. We'll you know how hard this work is. These are hard math problems, so they require a lot of thinking.                                                                                              2. Everyone gets tired from work. Anyway, I should get back to work. I need complete silence.                                                                                                    3. If it is not a common game, like temple run is, say it is a quick thinking exercise.</item></list>
</text>
