<text id="autogum_whow_doc552" title="Transport Animals" shortTile="transport-animals" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-07-21" dateModified="2019-10-17" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Transport-Animals" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Transport Animals</head><p>Transporting or moving animals can be worrisome and even stressful to most animals. By following these steps for your pets, they will be much calmer, and some may even enjoy the ride!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Horses and Cows</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Obtain a horse or livestock trailer. This can be quite expensive, so instead of buying a new one, purchase a used trailer and save money. <figure rend="Horse_trailer2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Put a halter on the animal. To do this, take the hole in the end of the halter and slide it over the animal's nose. Fasten the strap.</item>
<item>Lead the animals into the trailer one at a time. Pull on the lead, don't be shy with it. These are large animals and halters will not hurt or choke them. Stand in the trailer and if they do not come into the trailer, tempt them with grain.</item>
<item>Tie them in using a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Tie_a_Quick_Release_Knot_(Highwayman's_Hitch)">quick release knot.</ref></item></list>
<head>Dogs and Cats</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Put the dog or cat in a crate or kennel designed for cats and dogs. If you have a car, a dog can be placed inside the car in a seat belt harness.</item>
<item>Carry the cage to the back of the truck or utility vehicle. Make sure the cage is secure and will not slide around during your trip.</item></list>
<head>Small Animals, Birds, and Reptiles</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Place the cage into the vehicle. Just leave them in their cage and put it in the back of your car or truck. Make sure that their cages will not slide around during your trip, as this will frighten them.</item>
<item>Use a box. Line the box with shavings and some food and place the pet in there for the car ride.</item>
<item>Use a crate. If you have a dog or cat crate, that will also work. Make sure they can't slip out.</item></list>
<head>Fish</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Place fish in bowls. Pour some of the water out carefully: when doing this make sure you do not dump out the fish. There should be about half the amount there was before. Put the bowl on the floor of the vehicle where the passengers' feet go. Drive carefully and avoid large bumps.</item>
<item>Transport fish in bags. Put the fish in bags that are half-filled with water, blow air into the bags and tie a knot at the top. You can also keep the fish in the tank and dump some water out or you can get a large tupperware container and put water and the fish in it.</item></list>
<head>Goats, Sheep, and Medium Livestock</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Use livestock trailers. If you have a livestock trailer, let them go in there or put halters and collars on them and tie them up in there.</item>
<item>Use extra large dog kennels. You may also put one goat per extra large dog kennel.</item></list>
<head>Chickens and Livestock Birds</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Use a dog kennel or cage.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>It is best to hold your small animal while traveling.</item>
<item>Line your livestock trailer with shavings.</item>
<item>Feed the animals grain and treats while traveling; it will calm them.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be careful when you are driving, and avoid large bumps or potholes!</item>
<item>Bags of water containing fish will only last so long, as the air may run out.</item>
<item>Try to avoid long unnecessary trips with pets.</item></list>
</text>
