<text id="autogum_whow_doc164" title="Start Your Own Private Lesson Business" shortTile="start-private-lesson" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2007-12-14" dateModified="2019-10-03" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Start-Your-Own-Private-Lesson-Business" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Start Your Own Private Lesson Business</head><p>Have you ever wondered how to make a profit from a private lesson business?   If you have expertise in almost any area, there is a good chance someone else will want to learn from you.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Decide what skill or area of expertise you wish to market. The private lesson business is most certainly not limited to teaching just a few subjects. There are hundreds of different skills which may be marketed for private lessons.  Whether you know how to perform martial arts, cook gourmet meals, embroidery, day trade, understand currency exchange, or know yoga, someone else is bound to want to learn from you.  One teacher started her private lesson business by offering lessons in the Japanese language, while a musician used his skills and talents to teach private music lessons.  Focus on some talent or skill you enjoy.  If you are passionate about the subject you teach, you will enjoy giving private lessons and your enthusiasm will inspire your students. <figure rend="Start Your Own Private Lesson Business Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do your "Homework".  Research the market to determine what competition you will encounter.  What does your competitor charge? <figure rend="Start Your Own Private Lesson Business Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make a "Lesson Plan".  Decide how you will do business.  Knowing who will be doing the teaching, where lessons will be taught, the types of payments you will accept, what your bookkeeping or accounting needs look like, and what  your licensing and liability insurance needs will be, are some important items to address before opening the doors to your students. <figure rend="Start Your Own Private Lesson Business Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>"Ring the Bell".  Devise a marketing strategy to get students into your classes, (space ads, direct mail, promotions, online presence, and word of mouth), and set your marketing budget.  Consider using flyers or offering free seminars to groups where you might encounter prospective students. This can be very helpful if you have a small marketing budget.  Space ads, a webpage, direct mail, special promotions and word-of-mouth advertising can also bring your new business to the attention of prospective students. <figure rend="Start Your Own Private Lesson Business Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>"Class is in Session".  Having a successful private lesson business can be rewarding and fulfilling.  Deciding on the type of lessons you want to teach, doing your homework and market research, making a lesson plan that will be your guide through the everyday details of your business, and finally, marketing yourself to prospective students, may seem like a lot of work to do before you ever begin teaching, but once you have mastered the basics, you can relax and enjoy sharing your knowledge and, even better, get paid for it! <figure rend="Start Your Own Private Lesson Business Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Obtain the proper licenses and certifications required for operating a business in your area.</item>
<item>Become certified or accredited by organizations that specialize in your service.  For instance, if you offer scuba lessons, become certified in your profession, and offer the classes and training for others to become certified scuba divers or instructors.</item>
<item>Contact the Small Business Personal Banker at your local bank to obtain a credit card machine or credit forms for your student's payments.  It may cost a little upfront to take credit cards, but by offering the option, you may find your students will also be more inclined to purchase back end merchandise from you, (for example:  music books, cook books or specialty utensils, language tapes, etc.) or even extend their lessons beyond the basics.  Also consider accepting Pay Pal as an alternative payment method.</item>
<item>Offer "Grand Opening" discounts.  By initially charging less than your competitors, you may grab some of the market share.</item>
<item>Consider discounting lesson prices or services at first, if you are in direct competition with other private lesson providers.  After you have adequate clientele, you can always increase your charges to the current market prices.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Never place your students in danger without their knowledge and signed consent and waiver releasing you from responsibility for accidents.  This applies even if they say they cannot sign that waiver for whatever reason. Always explain the possible risks associated in learning a new skill, and do all you can do to alleviate the chances of an accidental injury or death.</item></list>
</text>
