<text id="autogum_whow_doc116" title="Think of a Username" shortTile="think-username" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2006-11-22" dateModified="2019-09-05" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Think-of-a-Username" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Think of a Username</head><p>When you are creating a new account on the Internet it is important to not only think of an original username, but one that is memorable as well. There are a few simple tricks to creating a unique username, like adding numbers and symbols, but creating a memorable one is entirely up to you. Here are a few tips to creating the perfect username for your online accounts.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Identifying an Appropriate Username</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Recognize what kind of username your are creating. In a lot of cases, your username only appears to you as the account holder. However, if you are creating an account on an online forum, a shared account, or are creating a username in a work environment, it is important to remember that the other users in your community will be able to see your username. <figure rend="Think of a Username Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't make it too complicated. While a complicated username can be great for privacy reasons, it is important to remember that you will most likely need to recall this information on a regular basis. <figure rend="Think of a Username Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Recognize the site's specifications. Some websites require your username to meet specific guidelines, like a capital letter and at least two instances of numbers or symbols. Make sure you meet these requirements when designing your username. <figure rend="Think of a Username Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Understand that you may have this username for a long time. It is incredibly important to make sure that your username will be appropriate in the future because you may be using it for a long time. For instance, a username that you find appropriate as a student or young adult may not be appropriate when you enter the workforce. <figure rend="Think of a Username Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Avoid using too much personal information. In a lot of situations it is important to maintain anonymity, especially when posting to forums and comment sections on the internet. You probably don't want that comment you left on YouTube to lead to someone messaging you through Facebook! <figure rend="Think of a Username Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Thinking of a Unique Username</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Think of something unique to you. It often helps to think of a unique characteristic about yourself, like your eye color or a particular passion you may have. This does not mean the last four digits of your Social Security Number! Be vague! A good example may be "GreenEyedBiker" if you love to bike and have green eyes. <figure rend="Think of a Username Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep it simple. If you are creating an account at your school or business, sometimes it is best just to keep it simple by making your username your first initial and your last name. For example, if your name was Jane Smith, you could use "jsmith." <figure rend="Think of a Username Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>To make this name more unique, add your middle initial or a number that bears significance to you.</item></list></item>
<item>Add numbers or symbols. A great way to make your username more unique is to add numbers and symbols in the place of more complicated names. For instance, you can jazz up "jsmith" by turning it into "j_smith35." This is also a simple way to get that username you initially wanted but you were told that name has already been taken. <figure rend="Think of a Username Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you do decide to include a number in your name, don't make it too complicated! You don't want to forget it.</item>
<item>Write down your username somewhere safe and nearby incase you forget it and need it for reference.</item>
<item>f you find that you can't seem to think of a unique and secure username, there are some username generators out there. However, be careful when doing this as this could be an easy way for your information to be stolen.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be sure not to put anything too personal in your username. You don't want strangers on the site you are on seeing your name or birth date.</item></list>
</text>
