<text id="autogum_whow_doc624" title="Distinguish Mennonites from Amish" shortTile="distinguish-mennonites" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2016-01-25" dateModified="2019-08-31" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Distinguish-Mennonites-from-Amish" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Distinguish Mennonites from Amish</head><p>Both the Amish and Mennonites stem from similar cultural and religious heritages, making it tricky to distinguish between the two. Luckily, there are several ways to figure out whether someone is Amish or a Mennonite without having to straightforwardly ask them. By looking at their clothing or asking them questions about things like their education or religious meeting places, you'll soon know whether they're Amish or a Mennonite. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Examining Their Lifestyle</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find out if they’re interested in higher education. The Amish usually don’t allow any type of higher education because they think it gets in the way of their faith. However, Mennonites do accept higher education. Ask the person if they’re in school or getting a degree to find out if they’re Amish or a Mennonite.
<list type="unordered"><item>If they’re young you might ask, “Are you planning on going to college?”</item>
<item>Ask an older person a question like, “Did you choose to earn a degree?” to see if they’re Amish or a Mennonite.</item>
<item>Ask about their beliefs on going to college too, if desired.</item></list></item>
<item>Check whether they use technology or electricity. Amish people don’t use technology, and instead of using cars, they prefer to use horse-drawn carriages instead. They also avoid using electricity. Mennonites are more accepting of technology of all kinds, and they do use cars as well as electricity. Asking or finding out if they drive cars or use electricity is an easy way to figure out if they’re Amish or not.
<list type="unordered"><item>Mennonites allow electricity and telephones in the home.</item>
<item>Some Amish groups may have one telephone that they use collectively.</item></list></item>
<item>Look at their clothing to figure out if they're Amish or Mennonites. Amish people tend to dress more conservatively in plain clothing, with women wearing dresses or head coverings. Mennonites don’t have a strict dress code and are often dressed like everyday people. If you see people dressed very modestly, it’s likely that they’re Amish as opposed to Mennonites. <figure rend="Distinguish Mennonites from Amish Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The Amish wear solid-colored clothing in blues, grays, whites, and blacks. Men wear black suits and straw or felt hats, while the women wear dresses and prayer caps.</item></list></item>
<item>Find out how much they interact with the outside world. The Amish are a tight knit community and tend not to get involved in everyday society. Mennonites are close to the opposite—they're well-integrated into modern society and have lots of involvement with other people. <figure rend="Distinguish Mennonites from Amish Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Because the Amish are so isolated, their jobs often include agricultural work in their communities.</item>
<item>Mennonites live among regular communities and often have regular jobs as well.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Evaluating Their Religious Practices</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Ask where they have their church services. Mennonites have their church services in meeting houses while Amish people meet in smaller places like homes, barns, or shops. By asking the person where they meet for church, you’ll be able to figure out whether they’re Amish or a Mennonite.
<list type="unordered"><item>You could also ask them what language they use during the service—German or Pennsylvania Dutch is often used by the Amish, while English is primarily used by the Mennonites.</item></list></item>
<item>Use the size of their worship group to help you decide if they’re Amish or Mennonites. The Amish tend to worship in smaller groups because of space limitations—they’re expected to host church services in their houses. Mennonites worship in large meeting spaces, meaning their groups can get quite large. While an Amish worship group might have 15-20 people in it, a Mennonite group could have 50-100 people.</item>
<item>Find out if they do missionary work or only stay in their communities. Mennonites are known for their outreach in the community, going on missionary trips around the world to actively help others. They use this as a way to spread their religious beliefs while assisting those in need. The Amish do all of their charitable giving close to home and don’t tend to stray from their community.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you think someone might be a Mennonite, ask them if they do any missionary work to find out for sure.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Know that there are always exceptions, so ask several different types of questions to find out for sure whether the person is Amish or a Mennonite.</item>
<item>If all else fails, politely ask them. It's likely that they'll be glad to tell you and happy that you're interested in learning about their lifestyle.</item></list>
</text>
