<text id="autogum_whow_doc669" title="Stay Fit Without Going to the Gym" shortTile="stay-fit-without" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-10-20" dateModified="2019-10-24" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Stay-Fit-Without-Going-to-the-Gym" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Stay Fit Without Going to the Gym</head>We all hate the hassle of putting on workout clothes and driving to the local gym where it feels like everyone is judging you while you work out. Not to mention the time and money it feels like you're wasting by doing so. Well, in this article I will provide tips on how to shed a few extra pounds without going to the gym.
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Daily Diet</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Replace unhealthy snacks with fruits and vegetables. Eat carrots, or an apple.
<list type="unordered"><item>Refrain from buying processed fruits and veggies as these can have additives as well as a lesser nutritional value.</item></list></item>
<item>Drink at least half your body weight in fluid ounces everyday. Drinking more water each day holds several health benefits. It keeps skin more clear, it gives you energy, and it aids in the digestion process.
<list type="unordered"><item>Keep a 20 ounce water bottle with you at all times, figure out what half your weight is and then determine how you are gonna break it up throughout the day and drink what amount of water by what time.</item></list></item>
<item>Eat smaller portions during meals.
<list type="unordered"><item>Use smaller plates and cups</item>
<item>Make half your plate fruits or veggies</item>
<item>Drink a full glass of water with your meal</item></list></item>
<item>Portion out snacks. Eat snacks out of a small bowl or place a cup of whatever you want to eat on a plate and leave the snack container in the cabinet.</item>
<item>Plan out meals. Create a spreadsheet or write out in a daily planner what you intend to cook on each day. Try to get your body on a schedule (pasta on Mondays, steak on Tuesday, etc). Research recipes and try new things to keep it interesting.</item>
<item>Eat a good breakfast. You want to start your day off right, choose foods that are going to give you that extra boost of energy to start your day. Stray away from sugary cereals, or eating pancakes too often. Include at least a fruit or veggie, a grain, and a protein.</item>
<item>Eat high protein foods with low fat. Incorporate lean meats, eggs, seafoods, and nuts into your diet. Stray away from sausages, these contain a lot of sodium and saturated fats.</item></list>
<head>Getting Daily Exercise</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Do some body weight exercises upon waking up. Do push-ups, sit-ups, or planks in the morning to get the blood moving throughout the body and to wake yourself up for the day.</item>
<item>Go for a cardio workout. Get outside and bike, run, or walk at least 3 times a week.
<list type="unordered"><item>Taking the dog for a walk is a great excuse to get outside.</item>
<item>Taking the longer route to walk from place to place is also a great way to get extra steps in.</item></list></item>
<item>Always do what will burn a few extra calories without too much extra effort.
<list type="unordered"><item>Take the stairs instead of using the elevator.</item>
<item>Take the long route to the bathroom at work.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Refining Daily Habits</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Decrease time in front of electronics. Eat your meals without a screen. Do not watch movies or TV while laying in bed. Cut down on computer socializing.</item>
<item>Get at least eight hours of sleep a night. Go to bed 30 minutes earlier each week to slowly get your body on a regular sleep schedule.
<list type="unordered"><item>Develop a night time routine.</item>
<item>Meditate before bed a few times a week.</item></list></item>
<item>Develop a mindset of positivity and growth. Read books, learn new things.
<list type="unordered"><item>View your failures as growth and expanding your mind.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Keep an optimistic mindset. Ditching old habits is never easy for anybody.</item>
<item>You’ll receive out of it what you put into it.</item></list>
</text>
