<text id="autogum_whow_doc254" title="Run a Sweepstakes" shortTile="run-sweepstakes" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-10-11" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Run-a-Sweepstakes" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Run a Sweepstakes</head><p>A <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Avoid_Sweepstakes_Fraud">sweepstakes</ref> can really help your 'bottom line', by adding to your mailing list and your contacts. Read this article to learn how to do one properly.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Have the infrastructure to support it. You will need to have a server that can handle the load. The world is full of people who want something for nothing and a lot of those people invest a lot of time in it! Infrastructure would be: <figure rend="Run a Trucking Business Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Server</item>
<item>Mail list support</item>
<item>Database support (for the information received when they fill out entries)</item></list></item>
<item>Do some research into various organizations that do <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Do_Qualitative_Research">data collection</ref>. Learning, and utilizing, the demographics is one of the many uses of data received in a sweepstakes. Be sure the one you get will work for you. <figure rend="Segment Customers Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Understand that when you offer prizes, (usually offered by a third party), that you may be limited as to who can enter. <figure rend="Retire Early by Building Residual Income Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be prepared for the fallout from the rest of the world!</item></list></item>
<item>Understand, and accept, that it will never be easy enough. Some people just won't get it. Be prepared to either have a bunch of FAQs for every problem they have, or ready to answer all of their emails. <figure rend="Remove Collections From a Credit Score Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't have there be just one method of entering it. Some methods that you can use are: <figure rend="Remove Collections From a Credit Score Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Form entry</item>
<item>A hard-coded link to the form</item>
<item>Have a way for them to enter manually, as in the terms and conditions</item></list></item>
<item>Understand what compliance is and how it varies from state to state. And then <hi rend="bold">Be Compliant</hi>. <figure rend="Segment Customers Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>One things you can do is '<hi rend="bold">borrow'</hi> the terms and conditions from a similar contest and adopt it to your purposes.</item></list></item>
<item>Know that your email list will not be <hi rend="italic">exactly</hi> the goldmine you are expecting. When you start sending out emails, you will get many unsubscribe requests. Especially, if it gets picked up by a sweepstake offering site. You will come out ahead, but be prepared to be narrowing it down for a while. <figure rend="Run a Sweepstakes Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure your selection will be <hi rend="bold">random</hi>.  There are sites online that will generate a random number for you. Each entry will have a number, so choose a random number from there. <figure rend="Run a Sweepstakes Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be able to manage the costs. The costs will come from the infrastructure mentioned before as well as other costs you might incur. <figure rend="Remove Collections From a Credit Score Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Most companies pass off the tax liability to the winners. Be sure they understand, or the opportunity is there for them, that when entering your contest.</item>
<item>If you are not incorporated, it is not a good idea to hold a sweepstakes. You will be opening yourself to lawsuits. Contact your local tax authority so that they can tell you how to deal with the value of the prize being offered.</item></list>
</text>
