<text id="autogum_whow_doc406" title="Do the Wash Painting Effect" shortTile="wash-painting-effect" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2012-09-22" dateModified="2019-02-22" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Do-the-Wash-Painting-Effect" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Do the Wash Painting Effect</head>
<p>the wash painting has great effects and looks great. It's easy once you know how and after a bit of practice. ^.^ happy painting</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Step One- get a hold of some watercolour paints or pencils. the wash technique is much easier with water colours as they look better diluted then poster paints or acrylics, you can still try it with these types though, it may look more like what you're looking for. <figure rend="Do the Wash Painting Effect Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Step Two- dilute the paints and fill in an area of an outline (its best to draw a very faint outline of your scene so you get the exact shape you're looking for). don't dilute your pain too much, you don't want the water flowing the paint out of the lines and ruining your painting (unless this is the effect you wish to achieve). This is why it's best to to a few practice runs before you make your real masterpiece. &gt;.&lt; <figure rend="Do the Wash Painting Effect Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Step Three- this is the tricky part. Grab some paper towel. it cannot be tissue or Kleenex or even toilet paper, those will get soggy and fall apart all over you artwork. it needs to be like in the picture to the right. Fold it neatly(!) and gently press on top of the water colour you have just applied. it will  soak up the excess water that hasn't already soaked into the paper (you need to act quickly or all the water will soak up and its ruined). <figure rend="Do the Wash Painting Effect Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Step Four/ Congrats-Magic! you have completed the wash effect for the first time!   ... well not quite. you still need to do the rest of you painting... if the colour hasn't turned out clear enough just do another layer on top ( wait for it to dry). don't take this as a reason to add more paint to your watercolour solution, it's better this way because you can see weather it should be a little darker without it already being too dark, ruining your painting and the point of wash effect anyway. Also, if the colour goes a little out of the lines that's okay, it gives a nice affect but if you don't like it that's okay too. it all depends on your style. you shouldn't be able too see the lines if you've done them right but if you can see them, that's fine. It enhances the out f the lines effect because there ARE lines. This doesn't mean you should go outlining the drawing while pressing VERY hard on your pencil (probably the best outlining tool but don't restrict yourself to graphite- experiment with chalks and charcoal as well), pressing too hard can damage your paper/canvas. IF YOU ARE USING A CANVAS don't have it on an easel. The water colour will slide down. You can do this if you want, as i said before, FIND YOUR PERSONAL STYLE. <figure rend="Do the Wash Painting Effect Step 4.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>I have included tips throughout the article, i think it works better that way.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Warnings are also in the article</item></list>
</text>
