<text id="autogum_whow_doc662" title="Order Custom Uniforms for Sports Teams" shortTile="order-custom-uniforms" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2013-11-25" dateModified="2017-05-14" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Order-Custom-Uniforms-for-Sports-Teams" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Order Custom Uniforms for Sports Teams</head><p>Your sports team can get motivated with new uniforms and it can help the players perform better. However, there are a few things that you need to consider when ordering custom uniforms. The process may sound simple, but it requires a little bit of effort, and this will ensure you get exactly the kind of uniform you have envisioned for your team.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Choose the uniform manufacturing company. There are many companies that manufacture sports uniforms/kits. Decide your budget and choose a company that matches all your requirements. <figure rend="Order Custom Uniforms for Sports Teams Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Choose the material. You can get an array of materials, such as polyester, jersey-style, cotton and jacquard. Depending on the kind of sport your team is into, you should select the material. Also, the weather in your area has a say in the kind of material you select. If players are required to run and sweat, you should be looking for a material that is comfortable to use and also has the ability to dry moisture quickly, so that it doesn't become heavy from the sweat. Weigh all options before zeroing in on the material for the uniforms. <figure rend="Order Custom Uniforms for Sports Teams Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Choose the color of the uniform. The color of the uniform should be carefully selected. Usually, sports teams don their team color.This is fine if the colors are in harmony, but if the colors do not match, the uniform can look outrageous. So spend some time selecting uniform colors by involving the team members. It is best to select a color that you can claim as your own rather than picking colors that other teams in the area are already wearing. <figure rend="Order Custom Uniforms for Sports Teams Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Design a team logo. A sports uniform is incomplete without a logo. This too requires careful consideration. While most teams prefer to have the logo on the front, it may not be the ideal spot. Sometimes, having the logo on the back can look much better. If you want a professional looking logo, opt for an embroidered one rather than a screen printed one. <figure rend="Order Custom Uniforms for Sports Teams Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Personalize the uniform. Every team member is an important part of the team and the best way to ensure that each player feels wanted and important is through sports uniform personalization. This means printing the player’s name and number on the uniform. This can be done through screen printing or embroidery, but there are other options as well. <figure rend="Order Custom Uniforms for Sports Teams Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take measurements. When you select custom uniforms for your sports team, it is crucial the uniform fit players perfectly. They should not be too big or small, or too loose or tight. This means that measurements of every team member should be taken carefully and the uniform should be created to fit each member, as per his or her measurements. Remember, this also includes getting the hat measurement right, so be sure to measure the brow line correctly. <figure rend="Order Custom Uniforms for Sports Teams Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Decide on hats. There are many sports where hats form an integral part of the uniform. If your team is into a sport where hats matter, be sure to color coordinate the hat with the rest of the uniform, and make sure the logo is properly embroidered on the front of the hat. You can customize hats by embroidering the player’s name on the back. While it is not challenging to customize sports uniforms, it does require certain amount of planning and forethought. So be ready to use some gray matter and you should be able to have unique and customized uniform for your sports team within no time. <figure rend="Order Custom Uniforms for Sports Teams Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
