<text id="autogum_whow_doc057" title="Protect a Convertible" shortTile="protect-convertible" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-05-25" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Protect-a-Convertible" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Protect a Convertible</head><figure rend="1961 Cadillac Convertible.jpg"></figure>As a convertible owner, you relish the time spent driving with the top down. You may even brave the road on those cooler days, or live in a climate that has hard winters that may eventually put wear on your convertible top. Whether it's hot or cold outside, it's important to protect your convertible from the elements, and there are several ways to achieve this. Begin with proper maintenance, which is the key to keeping your car in good condition, regardless of whether your top is constructed of cloth or vinyl.
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Cleaning Convertible Tops</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Wash your convertible regularly. It is recommended that you clean your convertible top at least once every 4 weeks to keep dirt from sinking into the fabric or vinyl. <figure rend="Organize a Charity Car Wash Step 9 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wet the top of the convertible with a hose. Use a gentle car shampoo or one made specifically for convertible tops, which can be found in any automotive or home improvement store. Apply the cleaner with a sponge as you would to the rest of your vehicle. <figure rend="Clean Tinted Car Windows Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Allow the cleaner to sit for 15 minutes for stubborn dirt or stains. <figure rend="Maintain-a-Convertible-Step-13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Scrub the top gently with a bristled brush <figure rend="Maintain-a-Convertible-Step-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Rinse thoroughly with water.. <figure rend="Maintain-a-Convertible-Step-14.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Protecting Cloth Tops</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Begin with a top that is dry and free of dirt and debris. <figure rend="Maintain-a-Convertible-Step-16.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Apply a fabric convertible-top protectant. Spray the product directly onto the vehicle from a distance of approximately 16-18 inches. <figure rend="Maintain-a-Convertible-Step-6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Allow the top to dry completely. <figure rend="Maintain-a-Convertible-Step-13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Dry thoroughly with a clean, microfiber towel. <figure rend="Maintain-a-Convertible-Step-1.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Protecting Vinyl Tops</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Ensure your vinyl top is clean and dry. <figure rend="Maintain-a-Convertible-Step-12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Using sweeping motions, spray a vinyl convertible-top protectant at a distance of 8-12 inches from the top, or spray the product onto a clean, microfiber cloth and wipe the convertible top. <figure rend="Maintain-a-Convertible-Step-5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wipe the top thoroughly with a fresh cloth until it's completely dry. <figure rend="Maintain-a-Convertible-Step-17.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Repeat this process up to three times if dirt or stains remain. <figure rend="Maintain-a-Convertible-Step-15.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Avoid washing your convertible in direct sunlight.</item>
<item>Always wash your convertible top all at once rather than washing in spots, as this will cause certain areas of the top to be discolored.</item>
<item>If in doubt, determine whether your convertible top is vinyl or fabric by dropping 1/8 tsp. of water on the top and working it into the material. If it begins to soak in, the convertible top is most likely made of cloth. A vinyl top would allow the drop to pool up and remain. A cloth top will also gather small particles such as lint more easily than vinyl will.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Avoid washing your convertible top with common household cleaners such as bleach, which can cause the fabric or vinyl to deteriorate.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Convertible-top cleaner</item>
<item>Vinyl convertible-top protectant</item>
<item>Fabric convertible-top protectant</item>
<item>Microfiber cleaning cloths</item></list>
</text>
