<text id="autogum_whow_doc524" title="Buy Wholesale Leather Coats" shortTile="buy-wholesale-leather" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-05-06" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Buy-Wholesale-Leather-Coats" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Buy Wholesale Leather Coats</head><p>When you run an online business or own your own clothing store in your city, it is often less expensive to buy items in bulk. It is also convenient, since you will receive coordinating items in an array of sizes. Another benefit when you buy wholesale leather coats online is having them delivered directly to your place of business. In addition, you will receive most, if not all of the items all at one time. Learn what to look for when purchasing wholesale leather coats.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Apply for a wholesaler's license. This license allows you to buy items at wholesale prices. It also ensures that you pay taxes on the merchandise you purchase. Fill out the required paperwork and wait to receive your wholesaler's license in the mail. <figure rend="Buy Wholesale Leather Coats Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Check prices online and through wholesalers in your area. Compare the prices to see which wholesaler offers the most competitive prices. Also, take into account shipping charges when ordering wholesale products online. <figure rend="Buy Wholesale Leather Coats Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Ask about the quality of the leather coats. What type of leather are they made from? Find out whether the leather jackets have a protective coating on them to protect them from moisture and rain. Also, ask what sizes they come in. Most wholesalers send bulk items in predetermined sizes. Some will supply you with more mediums and larges and fewer smalls and x-larges; however, you need to ask them ahead of time what sizes you will receive with your order. <figure rend="Buy Wholesale Leather Coats Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Determine if they offer a money back guarantee. Ask the sales representative in person or on the phone about the return policy and whether you can return your order when you are not happy with the quality of the merchandise. Make sure to ask this question, as you don't want to spend money and not have any recourse when the jackets are not up to your standards. <figure rend="Buy Wholesale Leather Coats Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>See if they come in different styles. Having a variety of leather coats is important because people have different style preferences. What is an appealing style to 1 person may not be an appealing style to another person. <figure rend="Buy Wholesale Leather Coats Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pay for your items. You can also use COD if the wholesaler offers this service. Make sure to give the customer representative the proper address, telephone number and credit card information to process your order. <figure rend="Buy Wholesale Leather Coats Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Let the customer service representative know when you have any special delivery requests, such as delivering the box to the back door or placing the box in a special place when it rains. Also, let the representative know if someone else will be receiving the jackets and tell them the name of this person. <figure rend="Buy Wholesale Leather Coats Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wait for your items to arrive in the mail, which will take from a week to a couple of weeks. Open the box of the leather jackets and inspect each one carefully and thoroughly. <figure rend="Buy Wholesale Leather Coats Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure to inspect the items as soon as you receive them. Waiting to inspect the jackets a few days or weeks later can pose a problem when attempting to return them.</item>
<item>Make sure you read the return guidelines and adhere to the store's guidelines. Depending on the company you purchased them from, you may have to pay the shipping charges to send them back; make sure to check this information before you purchase from this company.</item>
<item>When you cannot locate leather jackets online or in the area you live, try networking with other people in the retail industry to find out how they obtain their wholesale catalogs and how they buy wholesale. You can also read books or magazines about owning your own business and locating wholesalers off-line.</item></list>
</text>
