<text id="autogum_whow_doc443" title="Accommodate Guests in Your New Apartment" shortTile="accommodate-guests" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2007-01-23" dateModified="2019-03-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Accommodate-Guests-in-Your-New-Apartment" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Accommodate Guests in Your New Apartment</head><p>Apartment-living is an attractive option for seniors who no longer need a big family home, or want to get the most out of their retirement savings by reducing extra costs.  But downsizing your home doesn’t prevent you from throwing successful family parties in your apartment!  With simple planning, you can still bring everyone home for the holidays.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Plan your space.                                  Furnish your apartment with pieces that serve multiple purposes. Stools and pillows look great and can be used for extra seating. Tables that fold or expand can temporarily double your serving space. <figure rend="Accommodate Guests in Your New Apartment Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Clear the Clutter.                                   Put away any knickknacks, counter clutter, and small decorative furniture. Your valuables will not only be safe, but you will have more surface space and the room will seem bigger and more inviting. <figure rend="Accommodate Guests in Your New Apartment Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Delegate.                                        Once your children have grown out of calling peanut butter and pickles a dinner, ask them to help with the preparations! If each adult prepares an appetizer, desert or entrée, your preparation time will be cut significantly, your kitchen will stay cleaner and everyone will be able to contribute to the day. <figure rend="Accommodate Guests in Your New Apartment Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make after-party arrangements.                    Are people coming from out of town? Will alcohol be served? Is transportation available? If any of your guests will need overnight accommodation, make sure arrangements are made before the big day. A smaller home means less space for unexpected overnight guests. <figure rend="Accommodate Guests in Your New Apartment Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't forget the children.                         If children are coming, make sure there is a safe space away from the excitement of the party available. In an apartment, a bedroom or office can be used for this purpose. Young children may become overwhelmed or tired before the day is through and having a 'children's only' area will make sure that they enjoy the day as much as the adults. <figure rend="Accommodate Guests in Your New Apartment Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Eat simply.                                     Unless you are planning a formal dinner, serve simple food that won't stain clothes. If everyone can't fit around a single table, skip the dinner time ordeal and allow your guests to mingle and graze the food. <figure rend="Accommodate Guests in Your New Apartment Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Watch the clock.                                    Know when your guests are coming and leaving. If your first guest arrives early and the last guest leaves late, the day can quickly become long and overwhelming. Set a start and finish time for your gathering and you and your guests will get the most out of your time with each other. <figure rend="Accommodate Guests in Your New Apartment Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Moving into a rented apartment doesn't mean you have to give up your family traditions.  With just a bit of planning, you can still find room to accommodate everyone when celebrating family occasions.</item>
<item>Welcome your guests with a drink and offer to take any coats or bags. This will help them feel more comfortable and integrate with the party sooner.</item>
<item>Save a room for coats and bags, such as a spare bedroom. This will help your guests feel more safe that their belongings aren't next to the door.</item>
<item>If your guests haven't met before the party, introduce them to the others as they enter.</item>
<item>Have a list of taxi companies on standby for your guests leaving after consuming alcohol.</item>
<item>Don't be afraid to cool the party down. When it's getting late and you feel the party should come to an end, politely tell them that they should think about how they're going to get home. It's your home after all!</item></list>
</text>
