<text id="autogum_whow_doc112" title="Enable NSFW Content on Reddit" shortTile="enable-nsfw-content" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2017-08-09" dateModified="2019-09-23" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Enable-NSFW-Content-on-Reddit" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Enable NSFW Content on Reddit</head><p>This wikiHow teaches you how to enable adult and Not Safe for Work (NSFW) on Reddit using a computer, phone, or tablet. Though there's no option to allow NSFW content in the official Reddit mobile app, your preferences from Reddit.com will carry over. Due to Google and Apple Store restrictions, some NSFW may remain unavailable in the mobile app, even after adjusting your settings.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Using Reddit on a Phone or Tablet</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open a web browser on your phone or tablet. Although there's no way to change your NSFW content preferences in the official Reddit app, you can get the job done in your web browser. Changes you make to your account settings on Reddit.com will carry over to the official mobile app. <figure rend="Enable NSFW Content on Reddit Step 1 Version 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you use one of the non-official Reddit apps on your phone or tablet, you can likely still use this method to enable NSFW content for that app.</item></list></item>
<item>Go to <ref target="https://www.reddit.com">https://www.reddit.com</ref>. This takes you to the Reddit mobile site. <figure rend="Enable NSFW Content on Reddit Step 2 Version 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tap the  menu. It's at the top-right corner of the page. <figure rend="Enable NSFW Content on Reddit Step 3 Version 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tap . It’s at the top of the menu. <figure rend="Enable NSFW Content on Reddit Step 4 Version 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you’re already signed in, you can skip to step 7.</item></list></item>
<item>Enter your login information and tap . This logs you into your Reddit account and takes you back to the Reddit mobile site. <figure rend="Enable NSFW Content on Reddit Step 5 Version 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tap  again. The drop-down menu will re-appear. <figure rend="Enable NSFW Content on Reddit Step 6 Version 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If asked to install the Reddit app, just tap the <hi rend="bold">mobile site</hi> link at the bottom of the screen.</item></list></item>
<item>Tap . It's the gear icon in the menu. This opens the same version of the settings page that you'd see if you were using a computer. <figure rend="Enable NSFW Content on Reddit Step 7 Version 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remove the checkmark under “NSFW Content.” It’s under the “media” header in the first section of the page. As long as this box is unchecked, adult content will appear in your Reddit feed and search results. You’ll still have to change a few more settings, however. <figure rend="Enable NSFW Content on Reddit Step 8 Version 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Scroll down to the "content options" heading. It’s near the bottom of the page. <figure rend="Enable NSFW Content on Reddit Step 9 Version 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Check the boxes next to the first two "Content options." Both of these options should be selected if you want unrestricted access to NSFW content on your phone or tablet: <figure rend="Enable NSFW Content on Reddit Step 10 Version 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>“I am over eighteen years old and willing to view adult content.”</item>
<item>“Include not safe for work (NSFW) search results in searches.”</item>
<item>If you’d like adult/NSFW posts to be labeled as “NSFW” in the feed or search results, you can also check the box next to “label posts that are not safe for work (NSFW)."</item></list></item>
<item>Scroll down and tap . It's at the bottom-left corner of the page. NSFW content will now be accessible on Reddit. <figure rend="Enable NSFW Content on Reddit Step 11 Version 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>It may take a little while for the changes to take effect in the mobile app. You can try logging out and back into the app if you still can't view NSFW content.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Using Reddit.com on a Computer</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Go to <ref target="https://www.reddit.com">https://www.reddit.com</ref> in a web browser. If you’re not already signed in to your Reddit account, click the <hi rend="bold">LOG IN</hi> button at the top of the page to sign in now. <figure rend="Enable NSFW Content on Reddit Step 12 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This method is for redditors who haven’t reverted back to the old Reddit design. If you’ve chosen to switch back to the old design, see <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Main_Page#Using_the_Old_Version_of_Reddit.com">this method</ref> instead.</item></list></item>
<item>Click your Reddit username. It’s at the top-right corner of the page. A menu will expand. <figure rend="Enable NSFW Content on Reddit Step 13 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click  at the top of the menu. <figure rend="Enable NSFW Content on Reddit Step 14 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the  tab. It's near the top-center part of the page. <figure rend="Enable NSFW Content on Reddit Step 15 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Slide the "Adult content" switch to On . This allows NSFW content to appear in your feed and search results. <figure rend="Enable NSFW Content on Reddit Step 16 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Slide the “Safe browsing” switch to Off  (optional). If this switch is On (blue), NSFW/adult thumbnails and previews will be blurred in the feed and on the search page. If you want these images to be clear, turn the switch Off (white/gray). <figure rend="Enable NSFW Content on Reddit Step 17 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Due to regulations by the Apple App Store and Google Play Store, some NSFW content may appear blurred in the search results, even after changing these settings.</item></list></item>
<item>Scroll down and click . It’s the gray button near the bottom-left corner of the page. Your Reddit options are now updated, and you will see NSFW content all across the website.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you use the Reddit app on an Android, iPhone, or iPad, you may need to force-close the app and then re-open it before your settings take effect.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>The Reddit app prevents certain types of NSFW content from displaying on the mobile app. This is because both the iOS App Store and the Google Play Store have restrictions on the kind of content that apps can display.</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
