<text id="autogum_whow_doc535" title="Be a Responsible Pet Owner As a Muslim" shortTile="responsible-pet-owner" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2016-09-02" dateModified="2019-03-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be-a-Responsible-Pet-Owner-As-a-Muslim" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be a Responsible Pet Owner As a Muslim</head><p>What is pet? Based on Merriam Webster dictionary, pet is defined as a domesticated animal kept for pleasure rather than utility. Nowadays, people tend to keep pet in their house. These animals can form very close bond with their human owners and in fact, cats are even known as man’s best friend. But, most of the owners did not know the right ways to take care of their pets. In Islamic views, there are a few ways on how to take a good care of pets. In order to be a responsible owner, people should know and implement the right steps to make sure their pets are in a good condition including treating them kindly, train the pets to be good in house and only own pet that is admissible in Islam.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Treating them kindly</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>First and foremost, Islam expects humankind to treat all animals with respect and dignity and not cause it any harm nor injury. Treating animals with kindness and mercy is just one of the responsibilities embedded in Allah’s creation. It is stated in the Quran, “And We have sent you O Muhammad not but as a mercy for all of humankind, jinn, and all that exists.” (Quran 21:107). From this verse, we could acknowledge that treating every creations including animals with warmth and care is highly encouraged. Furthermore,according to one of the hadith narrated by Abu Hurayrah, it was stated that:  The Prophet (peace and blessings of Allah be upon him) said; “Whilst a man was walking on the road, he became very thirsty. He found a well so he went down into it and drank, then he came out. There, he saw a dog that was panting and biting the ground out of thirst. The man said: this dog is feeling the same thirst that I felt. So he went back down into the well and filled his shoe with water, then he held it in his mouth until he climbed back up, and he gave the water to the dog. Allah appreciated (his action) and forgave him. (The Hadith, n.d.) Therefore, we as a Muslim must show kindness towards animals notably our pets and that we must also have mercy on animals and not for human beings alone.</item></list>
<head>Train the pets to be good in house</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Secondly, pet owners also have to train their pets to be good. Just like humans, animals should also be trained so that they can behave well and bad behaviours like attacking people who happens to visit our house or even not knowing where to pee could be avoided. This is vital in order to ensure our house to remain organized and clean from any dirt and unwanted waste. We, as a Muslim should always keep our house clean because in the Quran it was stated that “truly Allah loves those who turns to Him constantly and He loves those who keeps themselves pure and clean.” (Quran 2:22). From this verse, it is apparent that Islam really places a great emphasis on cleanliness and those who would do as He say surely will be blessed by Allah. Apart from that, purity could ensure one’s prayers to be answered. Besides training animals to behave well in distinct environment may require a huge effort but if consistent commitment were given, success could be achieved. The pet owners too must invest their time in acquiring knowledge on how to train their pets effectively and this could be done in several ways. For example, they could purchase books on relevant topics at the bookstore or according to Regan (2012), they could ask for some advice from the professionals. Thus, pet owners should train their pets so that their pets could live successfully in the human world.</item></list>
<head>Only own pet that is admissible in Islam</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Thirdly, animals that are kept must be animals that are permissible to be kept according to Islamic point of view. In Islam, we are forbidden to pet animals like dogs, foxes and snakes. This is because keeping it would do us nothing but only could bring harm to us and there is no guarantee that will not get loose and harm us. Apart from that, keeping them is considered as splurging our money and something unnecessary and it is a waste of money. The Scholars of the Standing Committee for Issuing Fatwas were asked about the shar‘i ruling on dealing in or keeping animals that are used to fulfil whims and desires, including predators such as wolves, lions, foxes and so on. Then, they replied:  It is not permissible to sell predators such as wolves, lions, foxes and other wild animals that have fangs, because the Prophet (blessings and peace of Allah be upon him) forbade that. And because it is a waste of money, and the Prophet (blessings and peace of Allah be upon him) forbade wasting money. (Fath al-Wahhaab, 1/273). Moreover, any other animals that falls within this category such as pigs are impure and could bring along several diseases such as cancer. According to Abu Ishaaq ash-Shiraazi (may Allah have mercy on him) said: “With regard to pigs, they are impure because they are worse than dogs, and because it is recommended to kill them even if they are not harmful, and it is stated in the texts that they are haraam. If dogs are impure, then pigs are even more so.” In Homotoxins and Homtaxicoses, Fundamentals of a Synthesis of Medicine (1955) it was stated that, “The mice fed on pork developed a marked tendency towards cannibalism. As they grew older (ranging from a few months. to about a year) many developed cancer in various parts of their bodies.” From this scientific research, we can conclude that pigs are dirty and one who consumed it is prone to suffer from diseases. Therefore, we should follow Allah’s commandments that is to only own a pet that is permissible in Islam.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>In conclusion, there is a myriad of alternatives in the way to be a responsible pet owner from Islamic perspectives. As stated earlier, the owners should treat their pets kindly, know how to train their pets to behave well and also to pet animals that is admissible in Islam. By following all of these alternatives, we could also attain Allah’s pleasures and blessings because according to the Quran, “And those who believe and do good works and believe in that which is revealed to Muhammad, and it is the truth from their Lord, He removes from them their ill-deeds and improves their state.” (Quran 47:2).</item></list>
</text>
