<text id="autogum_whow_doc333" title="Look After Your Mind and Body" shortTile="look-mind-body" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2009-08-28" dateModified="2019-11-04" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Look-After-Your-Mind-and-Body" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Look After Your Mind and Body</head><p>Being Healthy and living a long happy life is important for each of us. The key is looking after both your mind and body. A healthy body can carry an even healthier mind. Read the article below for help!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Hair</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Keep hair looking shiny by rinsing it with cold water for two minutes after conditioning it. <figure rend="Be-Good-Looking-Step-6-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't use too much conditioner, it will pull your hair down and give it less volume. <figure rend="Grow-Thick-Curly-Hair-Step-13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wash your hair at least every-other day or it will get greasy and increase the chance of spots on your face. <figure rend="Do-Two-Strand-Twists-Step-2-Version-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>When you wash your hair, do not brush it as this upsets the natural pattern of your hair and makes it frizzy. Instead, comb it with a wide-tooth comb for tangles. <figure rend="Be-Good-Looking-Step-13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>When wearing a hair bobble don't put it in too tight as this damages your hair and slows down hair growth. Instead when you go to tie your hair up leave a fingers width of space between your scalp and the bobble this will look cool as well as it will decrease the chance of hair loss. <figure rend="Style-Shoulder-Length-Hair-Step-12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>To prevent hair breakage when sleeping, sleep on a satin pillow or wear a scarf. <figure rend="Do-Two-Strand-Twists-Step-12-Version-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do not get armpit wet. <figure rend="Stop-Armpit-Sweating-Step-1-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try different styles everyday if you have long hair there is an endless amount of possibilities, if you have short hair try extensions for a really different look. <figure rend="Look-Good-in-a-School-Uniform-(Girls)-Step-10-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Face</head>
<p>Here's a recipe on how to make an aloe Vera face mask:</p>
<list type="ordered"><item>Mix the milk and sugar together until sugar is not as grainy. <figure rend="Get-a-Chemo-Patient-to-Eat-Step-11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Choose an aloe vera leaf size according to how much juice is within the leaf. <figure rend="Use-Aloe-Vera-to-Treat-Burns-Step-5-Version-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Mix aloe vera juices from leaf with sugar/milk combo. <figure rend="Get-Rid-of-Acne-Scars-with-Home-Remedies-Step-20.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Spread over face leave for five minutes. <figure rend="Get-Rid-of-Acne-Scars-with-Home-Remedies-Step-10-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wash off with a wet washcloth. <figure rend="Have-a-Smooth-Face-Step-4-Version-5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wash your face every day in the morning and in the night. <figure rend="Have-a-Smooth-Face-Step-1-Version-5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Always make sure to wash all your make-up off before you go to bed. <figure rend="Have-a-Smooth-Face-Step-3-Version-5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>To <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Get_Rid_of_Blackheads">get rid of blackheads</ref> hold your face in the steam of hot water and stay like that for up to 20 minutes then squeeze the blackhead up NOT down as this will only make them worse. <figure rend="Cure-a-Cold-Fast-Step-13-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't ever squeeze spots or blemishes downwards, as this pushes the infection further into the skin making the blemish or spot worse. <figure rend="Get-Clear,-Smooth-Skin-Step-3-Version-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Moisturise your face every day. <figure rend="Hide-Pimples-Step-16-Version-4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Exfoliate with face scrub every night before bed. <figure rend="Get-Rid-of-Acne-Scars-with-Home-Remedies-Step-16.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you have open pores on your face then lemon or citrus fruit is a good way to close them. <figure rend="Combat-Stress-with-Good-Nutrition-Step-10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you would like longer eye lashes then try putting Vaseline they make your eyelashes longer and fuller. <figure rend="Look-Like-Rihanna-Step-15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Vaseline is also a good substitute for lip gloss or eye shadow, it makes your lips more moist and gives your eyes a shiny natural glow. <figure rend="Get-Angelina-Jolie's-Lips-Step-2-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Always wear chap stick in the winter, you don't want dry <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Get_Rid_of_Painful_Cracked_Lips">cracked lips</ref> do you. <figure rend="Look-Good-in-a-School-Uniform-(Girls)-Step-7-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Never leave make up on overnight, your neglecting your own skin if you do! <figure rend="Have-Flawless-Skin-in-a-Week-Step-5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Put spot removing face cream on every day even if you don't have spots because it helps stop any forming. <figure rend="Get-Clear,-Smooth-Skin-Step-1-Version-3.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Body</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Drink at least 8 glasses of water a day or 10 glasses of fluid a day to hydrate your body and leave you feeling refreshed. <figure rend="Care-for-Your-Skin-As-a-Guy-Step-14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Eat 5 portions of fruit or veg a day to keep your body healthy. Some suggestions of yummy but healthy food is fruit smoothie or milkshake, as long as you check they have the '1 of your 5 a day' symbol on them or even better make them yourself. <figure rend="Lose-Weight-Quickly-and-Safely-(for-Teen-Girls)-Step-4-Version-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Every morning when you get up say, “I am beautiful, no one can take that away from me.” This will boost your confidence. <figure rend="Start-a-New-Day-Step-8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Smile, even by just smiling you will be  more happy and so will the people around you. <figure rend="Be-Attractive-Step-7-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Everyone is self conscious about some part of their body, but many girls are particularly unsatisfied with their breasts. Here are some exercises you can do to speed up the growth of your boobs: <figure rend="Stuff-Your-Bra-Step-18.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Massage your boobs before bed every night. <figure rend="Identify-a-Lump-in-a-Breast-Step-4-Version-2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Press your fists against your boobs then push your elbows as far back as they will go.</item></list></item>
<item>Try wearing a push up or water bra. <figure rend="Naturally-Increase-Breast-Size-Step-9-Version-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do more exercise, join clubs, walk to school or go jogging with your friends. <figure rend="Start-a-New-Day-Step-15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>You could even start your own exercise club with your friends on the weekend. <figure rend="Heal-Your-Life-Step-6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>A good way to get fit and have fun while doing it is to get a Wii fit and keep track of your progress. <figure rend="Have-Fun-with-Your-Girlfriend-Step-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Love yourself and don't care what others think, they are probably just jealous about your beautiful body any way! <figure rend="Feel-Awesome-Step-12-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wear fake tan and moisturise your legs regularly it is a better way of getting a tan that a sun bed as it doesn't harm you skin! <figure rend="Get-Pale-Skin-Step-8-Version-3.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Make up</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Put moisturizer on before your foundation as it helps the make up go on more smoothly giving it a more natural look. <figure rend="Get-Pale-Skin-Step-7-Version-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Put concealer onto you eyes/spots not rub, rubbing makes the area go red and draws more attention to your spots! <figure rend="Hide-Pimples-Step-9-Version-5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wear foundation that matches your skin tone no one will like you if your orange. <figure rend="Hide-Pimples-Step-11-Version-6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wash your face before putting make up on. <figure rend="Clear-Under-the-Skin-Pimples-Step-1-Version-3.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<p>For the face mask:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>1 tbsp sugar</item>
<item>Aloe vera leaf</item>
<item>1/2 tbsp milk</item></list>
</text>
