<text id="autogum_whow_doc486" title="Wear White Booties" shortTile="wear-white-booties" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-08-14" dateModified="2019-09-19" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Wear-White-Booties" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wear White Booties</head><p>White booties are versatile and easy to style. Pair them with blue, black, or white jeans for an easy outfit. To mix it up, wear your white booties with skirts and shorts. You can even wear your white booties on nicer occasions with dresses, skirts, or suits. White booties go with every color and so many different styles of clothing, so get ready to enjoy experimenting with different outfits. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Styling with Jeans</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Pair your white booties with blue jeans for a casual look.  Blue jeans will be the most casual look, great for hanging out with friends or running errands. You can pair your blue jeans with a white top if you want to coordinate with your booties, a black top for contrast, or a colorful top to mix it up. <figure rend="Wear White Booties Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>A long gray cardigan can make this outfit perfect for fall.</item></list></item>
<item>Wear <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Wear_Black_Jeans">black jeans</ref> with your booties for slightly more formal occasions. If your work lets you wear black jeans, pairing them with white booties is a great way to make the outfit a little bit fancier. Black jeans and white boots go well with a blue or white button-down. <figure rend="Wear White Booties Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Keep in mind that straight-cut black jeans are dressier than faded, cropped, or skinny black jeans.</item></list></item>
<item>Create a bold, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Wear_White">all-white</ref> look with white jeans, booties, and a top. You have to be fairly confident to pull this one off, and make sure it’s a day where you won’t really be outside much so there’s no chance of getting your white outfit dirty. Try pairing a loose white blouse with skinny white jeans, or a tighter white top for looser jeans. <figure rend="Wear White Booties Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Consider adding a pop of color to your all-white outfit with a colorful handbag.</item></list></item>
<item>Wear white booties with cropped jeans that end above your boots. Cropped jeans are a great item to style with white booties. You can get cropped jeans that just brush the top of your booties, or ones that show a little bit of ankle – it’s up to you. <figure rend="Wear White Booties Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Wide-leg crop jeans will give you a more dramatic look, while skinny cropped jeans will look cute and playful.</item></list></item>
<item>Try double cuffing your full-length jeans above your boots. Roll up the jeans at the bottom hem twice in crisp folds. Make the folds wide enough that your cuffs reach the top of your booties or a little higher to show a bit of ankle. <figure rend="Wear White Booties Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You may have to unroll and try again a few times before you find a height that you like.</item></list></item>
<item>Go for a more casual single cuff look as an alternative. Single cuff your jeans by rolling up the bottoms . Your cuffed jeans should end just at or above the tops of your white booties. <figure rend="Wear White Booties Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The single cuff isn’t for everyone, so if seeing the hem of your denim bothers you, you can always go back to double cuffing.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Keeping it Casual with Shorts and Skirts</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Wear white booties with jeans shorts or dress shorts. While it’s most common to see people wearing boots with full length pants, wearing jean shorts or dress shorts with boots is a fun way to change up your normal summer outfit. If you’re wearing short shorts, pair them with a loose top for a balanced outfit, but if your shorts are on the longer side, you can wear a tighter top. <figure rend="Wear White Booties Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Wearing shorts with high-heeled boots can visually elongate your legs.</item></list></item>
<item>Try a colorful <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Wear_a_Mini_Skirt">mini skirt</ref> with white booties. Wear a skater mini that flares out, a bodycon mini, or even a denim mini skirt. When wearing a mini skirt, you might want to pair it with a looser, longer top to balance how much skin you are showing. Mini skirts look great with crop tops or graphic tee shirts. <figure rend="Wear White Booties Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Wear tights under a mini skirt in the winter to stay warm and stylish.</item></list></item>
<item>Pair a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Style_a_Denim_Skirt">denim skirt</ref> with white booties for a flirty look. Denim skirts are a cute option for spring and summer outfits. Your favorite denim skirt will look great with white booties, whether it’s a pencil skirt, a mini skirt, or even a full length denim skirt. <figure rend="Wear White Booties Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Wear a crop top with your denim skirt for a more casual settings, or tuck in a nice blouse to step it up a notch.</item></list></item>
<item>Avoid wearing white booties with athletic shorts. Athletic shorts are comfortable and can even be fashionable, but they look better when paired with running shoes, sneakers, or flip-flops. Sweatpants and athletic shorts are just a little too informal to look good with booties. <figure rend="Wear White Booties Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Dressing Up with Dresses and Suits</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Dress up a short summer dress with white booties. White booties go well with all kinds of short summer dresses, from colorful floral prints to all-white dresses. The booties will instantly make a sundress look just a little bit fancier, and perfect for a date. <figure rend="Wear White Booties Step 11 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don’t wear your white booties if you’re going to the beach though – they’ll be a real pain on the sand and will probably get dirty.</item></list></item>
<item>Try a long, flowing <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Wear_a_Maxi_Dress">maxi dress</ref> with heeled white booties. Heeled booties instantly make your maxi dress seem classier. For a smooth look, wear a maxi dress that extends beyond the tops of your booties, so that you can’t see any ankle. <figure rend="Wear White Booties Step 12 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Maxi dresses look great with lots of accessories like beaded necklaces, bangles, and earrings.</item>
<item>Wearing booties instead of sandals with your maxi dresses means you can wear them in the winter, too.</item></list></item>
<item>Pair your favorite <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Style_Jumpsuits">jumpsuit</ref> with white booties. Different kinds of jumpsuits are good for different occasions– a cotton printed jumpsuit is great for casual wear, while a linen jumpsuit is dressier. Dress up your jumpsuit with a formal blazer or dress it down with a leather or denim jacket. <figure rend="Wear White Booties Step 13 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>White booties with heels can also lengthen your legs if your jumpsuit is a little too long when you wear flats.</item></list></item>
<item>Wear white booties with a colorful pantsuit for powerful business attire. White booties are great to pair with pantsuits, because white goes with every color, from the brightest reds to the softest purples. White booties and a colorful pantsuit is a bold look – so try it on before at home before wearing it to an important meeting. <figure rend="Wear White Booties Step 14 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For a job interview, you should probably stick to a more conventional black pantsuit with black shoes.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
