<text id="autogum_whow_doc025" title="See Life Through the Eyes of an Artist" shortTile="see-life-through" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2010-03-03" dateModified="2018-09-23" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/See-Life-Through-the-Eyes-of-an-Artist" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>See Life Through the Eyes of an Artist</head><p>How do you see life through the eyes of an artist? An artist is a person young or old with a gift to see the world discovered and undiscovered in different ways.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Observe someone who's interested in art and point out unique things in the room or setting. What is the first thing that comes to your mind? what is the first thing that comes to their mind? An example would be if you see a black and white flower. Would the artist notice the positive and negative space and shading and angle of the flower whereas you just think its pretty? Art museums are a great place to go to try to see the world through the eyes of an artist because that's where artists have portrayed what they've seen through their eyes. <figure rend="See Life Through the Eyes of an Artist Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try drawing what you see when you look at an irregular or odd object. Drawing helps to let you focus and break down line, shape, space, and mass when looking at everyday objects. if you don't have paper draw the item in your mind line by line and see how it adds up to create the object. <figure rend="See Life Through the Eyes of an Artist Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>When looking at an everyday object, memorize it in a familiar way then try looking at the space around the object or looking at it in a different way that someone else might see it. <figure rend="See Life Through the Eyes of an Artist Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Artists see life in a different way. Literally. Something that looks like one thing to a normal person looks completely different to an artist. If you aren't sure you think quite that way, relax! Most people weren't born that way! The brain is built to be wired and rewired so you can most certainly begin to think differently. The next time you see an ordinary object like a chair, don't think 'chair' think something new, something completely different, something a little weird, but don't be afraid of weirdness, embrace it! <figure rend="See Life Through the Eyes of an Artist Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Play that game with yourself where you say the first thing that comes to your mind. If at first you get average results, challenge yourself to think something completely different. It'll be fun! <figure rend="See Life Through the Eyes of an Artist Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't be afraid of weirdness. Its part of what makes artists so creative! Being able to think of something that no one else does makes you completely artsy and cool! Just think, if people like Salvador Dali or Picasso were 'normal' would they be quite so famous? <figure rend="See Life Through the Eyes of an Artist Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try new things. Artists do new things all the time, the unconventional the uncool, the odd, the eclectic. If you see something you've never seen before, pick it up. If you see an old place you've never been to, go inside. You might be amazed at what you find. Even if you don't, you should be willing to take the risk. <figure rend="See Life Through the Eyes of an Artist Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't think of things as having only one solution. Or one anything! No object has only one use, no words only mean one thing. The possibilities of anything are only as limited as you imagine them to be. <figure rend="See Life Through the Eyes of an Artist Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you see something cool, draw it. Or do whatever it is artsy that you like to do. Feel a perfect breeze? Write a poem about it. See a funky outfit? Draw it. Hear a melodic sound, write a song about it. Do a bit of what you do every single day. If you do, by the end of this year you will have at least 365 pieces of artwork. You will boost your talent and also be quite prolific. <figure rend="See Life Through the Eyes of an Artist Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Imagine you are someone, or better yet something, for an entire day. Pretend you are them, speak like them, walk like them, behave like them. True, you may raise some eyebrows but let them rise! The more you do, the more quirky and individual you will become and then you will be able to have a deeper connection with that person or thing! <figure rend="See Life Through the Eyes of an Artist Step 10.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Creativity and artistic talent don't necessarily come naturally but if you would like to possibly have a career in the field of art.</item>
<item>try to look at the world from someone else's perspective-someone you know</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>don't get crazy...well, not too crazy</item></list>
</text>
