<text id="autogum_whow_doc689" title="Become an Au Pair in China" shortTile="become-au-pair-china" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2011-09-29" dateModified="2018-07-27" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Become-an-Au-Pair-in-China" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Become an Au Pair in China</head><p>An Au pair is a young adult who goes abroad for a longer time to live with a local family. The Au-pair gets full board and lodging in exchange for taking care of the children and doing some light chores.</p>
<p>The Au pair program in China started in 2009 and is slightly different than the normal program in other countries. First of all it is not necessary to know the Chinese language. The only condition is to be fluent in English. Second, Chinese parents find it very important that their child starts to learn a second language from early age on, that's why a foreign Au pair who speaks English is most welcome in China. Third, the Au pair program in China is more aimed at language tutoring and playing with the children than doing chores. And finally, you can choose to stay 3, 6 or 12 month as an Au pair.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find an agency online that places foreign Au pairs in China. There might be agencies in your country who work together with Chinese agencies, but you can also apply directly at some agencies in China (and save the service fee). <figure rend="Become an Au Pair in China Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Read the information carefully. Before you apply for the program please make sure you meet all the requirements to become an Au pair in China. <figure rend="Become an Au Pair in China Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Contact the agency. Fill out the application documents and provide them with all the needed documents, e.g. copy of your valid passport, photos, dear family letter, etc. <figure rend="Become an Au Pair in China Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Prepare for an interview with the agency. Mostly it will be via Skype, so if you haven't got an account yet its the perfect time to get one. In the interview you have to convince the agency that you are a suitable candidate as an Au pair in China. <figure rend="Become an Au Pair in China Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wait for a suitable host family. If you have passed the interview the agency will start to match you with one of the families. <figure rend="Become an Au Pair in China Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>First contact with the family. The family will write you an email and you can decide if you want to get in touch with them. You will also have to do a video-chat via Skype. <figure rend="Become an Au Pair in China Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Prepare the last needed documents. When you and the family are a match, you have to prepare the remaining documents, e.g. health declaration, criminal background check, etc. <figure rend="Become an Au Pair in China Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Sign the contracts. To be an Au-pair in China you have to sign two contracts, one between you and the agency and one between you and your future host family. <figure rend="Become an Au Pair in China Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Apply for your Visa. Your agency will provide you with all the information you need to apply for your visa in China. <figure rend="Become an Au Pair in China Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Apply for health insurance. Some Chinese agencies offer free health insurance in China, but I would not recommend that, as they only cover the costs for local Chinese hospitals, whereas the international health insurance in your country also covers the costs for international hospitals with western standards. <figure rend="Become an Au Pair in China Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Book your flight ticket. You can decide if you buy a one-way flight first or a return flight already. Many air ticket sites offer good deals, also it is cheaper to fly on weekdays as on the weekend. <figure rend="Become an Au Pair in China Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get ready to start your Au-pair stay in China. The agency will provide you with useful information about China and life in China, you should also read as much as possible about it before you go. You can ask your family what you should bring and what you don't have to bring. <figure rend="Become an Au Pair in China Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Check on the Airport transfer. The family will arrange your airport pick-up after you tell them when you will arrive. <figure rend="Become an Au Pair in China Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If any problems or misunderstanding should occur during your Au-pair stay in China your agency is always the first to contact. They will help you <figure rend="Become an Au Pair in China Step 14.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Photos: You should choose photos where one can identify your face and you look friendly. Also send in some photos with you and your family, friends, pets, etc. as well as photos showing you interacting with children to show you have experience in child care</item>
<item>Write a friendly and interesting letter where people can identify your personality and get to know about your life. Also write about all your talents, Chinese parents want their children to learn as much as possible (e.g. musical instrument, sports, arts, etc.)</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>As you might not be used to the food and drinks in China, you might want to take some local medicine from your home country for your stomach</item>
<item>Even if it is not necessary to know Chinese it would be safer to travel with a travel guide where you can find useful information</item>
<item>Cultural shocks are nothing uncommon, but you should make sure before you decide to be an Au-pair if you can take it and if you think you can adapt to a totally different culture</item></list>
</text>
