<text id="autogum_whow_doc661" title="Call Plays As an Offensive Coordinator" shortTile="call-plays-offensive" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-02-05" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Call-Plays-As-an-Offensive-Coordinator" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Call Plays As an Offensive Coordinator</head><p>A lot of people think that calling plays as an offensive coordinator is easy. It's not; it takes a combination of intelligence, time, and practice in order to become a good offensive coordinator. You have to have a good coaching staff and good players on your team in order to be successful.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Know your football. In order to call plays as an offensive coordinator, you have to know football. Not just the basic rules, but the more advanced knowledge, such as knowing how to put in place the different defensive coverage. The more you know, the better you will be at calling plays. <figure rend="Call Plays As an Offensive Coordinator Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Design good plays. A good play is any play that gains four or more yards. You can have some basic plays but overall, seek to have good plays in your playbook. This is where your football knowledge comes in handy. You can create plays that will beat different coverages (cover 1, cover 2, cover 3, etc.). You can be as creative as you can be and as talented as your team is. <figure rend="Call Plays As an Offensive Coordinator Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Study tape. Besides calling plays, study your opponent. The tape can be from anything, it can be tape from a game or from practice. Try to get multiple games or practice on tape in order to get more information. By studying your opponent you can learn their weaknesses.("Football Offensive Strategy - Tactics - Strategies - Offense." Football Babble. Web. 12 Mar. 2015.) By learning their weaknesses you can call specific plays to expose it. <figure rend="Call Plays As an Offensive Coordinator Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Practice. Now that you know your opponent's weakness and have selected plays to expose it, you have to practice them. Practice because you are going to call it in the game, and you want your players to know the play. Also, practice the rest of your plays because you may call 40 to 50 plays in the game. <figure rend="Call Plays As an Offensive Coordinator Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure that you and the rest of the coaches are on the same page before the game. Now that you have done everything you can to prepare for the game, you have to make sure everyone is on the same page. Make sure that the coaches know the game plan. Also make sure the players know the game plan as well, and go over the plays during warm-ups. <figure rend="Call Plays As an Offensive Coordinator Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be able to execute in the game. Now it is time to trust your players to be able to execute. Being able to execute means to do or perform the play (Dictionary.com. Dictionary.com. Web. 12 Mar. 2015.) that you and your team have practiced. Depending on the situation, call specific plays to put your players in the best situation and call the plays that expose the opponent's weakness and work to your team's advantage. <figure rend="Call Plays As an Offensive Coordinator Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try to watch some documentaries on good offensive coaches. By watching these, you can learn a thing or two.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can't be a good offensive coordinator without putting the work in. It's not like a part time job. You have to put a lot of time and effort.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Notebook for your plays</item>
<item>Video of players and coaches (tape)</item>
<item>Time</item>
<item>Patience</item>
<item>Good players</item>
<item>Other good coaches</item></list>
</text>
