<text id="autogum_whow_doc630" title="Understand the Christadelphian Religion" shortTile="understand-christadelphian" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2016-08-26" dateModified="2017-01-03" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Understand-the-Christadelphian-Religion" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Understand the Christadelphian Religion</head><p>The Christadelphian religion is a religion in which people come together to read the Bible. The people in this community do not believe in the trinity, but that Jesus was God's son sent down from heaven to preach the word and the hope of his father. Christadelphians do not go to a church, they meet at an ecclesia, a normal-looking building and is considered more as a hall than anything strange. This religion is extremely rare. It is approximated that only about 50 000 believers of this religion remain on this earth at present. We believe that the earth is breaking down, the governments can't change it and neither can scientific theories prove what the purpose of creating humans would be. I (personally) believe in the big bang theory, but opinions differ taking beliefs into consideration. We do not believe in people's spirits going to heaven when they die, we believe in resurrection. Only Jesus The Christ can resurrect. God specifically said in the Bible that his one and only son would come down from heaven to set up His kingdom upon earth. Think logically about this, if people's spirits went up to heaven, then why would Jesus come down to earth to rule Israel and restore peace and judgement to His followers? This quote from the Bible explains it, "The Kingdom of Heaven will be established on earth as it is in heaven." The kingdom of God will be established on earth, not in heaven, so why are people's spirits going to heaven? In this day and age, people have clearly misunderstood this. Another thing to remember, we believe that crosses and idols used as a form of worship are wrong. We become so absorbed in thinking that we are speaking to and praying to a statue or cross and ultimately this is idolatry and not worshiping the actual living God in heaven. We do not portray crosses on walls, jewelry and  any materialistic objects. The cross that Jesus died on symbolizes His death, the spitting on His face, the holes in his hands and feet, the thorn crown and all the pain He went through. Why would we want to remember the pain that He went through for us? Wouldn't we want to remember His resurrection and the hope that we could be resurrected after death by this Savoir? God has given us existence, Jesus has given us His life, the only way we can be more like Jesus everyday is if we remain constant in our daily readings of the one and only book God gave us to study, the Bible.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Do some research on the Christadelphians and they're beliefs. Out of the many religions there are in the world today, this real belief has all the facts and really makes sense. Speak to people, ask them if they've ever heard of such a religion. If not, show them what you have researched. Do not get confused between Christianity and Christadelphians, although they have similar names and both study the Bible, the beliefs are actually very different.</item>
<item>Look around yourself, observe the world and it's actions. Ask yourself about resolutions mankind could make to stop the chaos with war break-outs, strikes, natural disasters, bombings, racial inequalities and so on. Hopefully you should come to the conclusion that only these things can be solved by the creator, God, and in order to realise this you have to become a true follower of Him.</item>
<item>Remember, nobody is perfect. Only Jesus was, so in order to be like Him we should do everything in our power to be like him. Do not worry with this, come to the realisation that if you have had a bad backround or committed really serious sins, it is not over. There is always hope from God. He is forgiving as long as you ask for forgiveness from Him through prayer. No matter what situation you are in, God will always offer you hope. The wages of sin is death, but the gift of God is eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord.</item></list>
</text>
