<text id="autogum_whow_doc018" title="Make a Carrot Clarinet" shortTile="make-carrot-clarinet" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-10-03" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make-a-Carrot-Clarinet" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make a Carrot Clarinet</head><p>Clarinets are a musical instrument from the woodwind family. The clarinet is classified by its cylindrical shape and the type of mouthpiece used to play it. Traditional clarinets are made from plastic or wood in a factory, but you can make one at home for fun, using just a carrot!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Buy a large carrot. It should be quite large (190mm or longer).
<list type="unordered"><item>This carrot should be sturdy and not soft.</item></list></item>
<item>Gather other supplies.
<list type="unordered"><item>Get a clarinet or saxophone mouthpiece, reed, and ligature.</item>
<item>Get a kitchen knife, vegetable peeler, and funnel.</item>
<item>Get a tube that is 12mm in diameter cut to 35mm long and some electrical tape.</item>
<item>Get an electric drill with a 12mm spade bit and a 7mm drill bit.</item></list></item>
<item>Cut the ends of the carrot off. The length of the carrot should come to about 187mm.</item>
<item>Mark 6 holes on the front of the carrot.
<list type="unordered"><item>The 1st hole should be 39mm from the top of the carrot.</item>
<item>The 2nd hole should be 54mm from the top of the carrot.</item>
<item>The 3rd hole should be 74mm from the top of the carrot.</item>
<item>The 4th hole should be 97mm from the top of the carrot.</item>
<item>The 5th hole should be 123mm from the top of the carrot.</item>
<item>The 6th hole should be 140mm from the top of the carrot.</item></list></item>
<item>Mark one hole on the back for your thumb.
<list type="unordered"><item>The thumbhole should be 22mm from the top of the carrot.</item></list></item>
<item>Drill through the center of the carrot.
<list type="unordered"><item>Use the 12mm spade bit and drill straight down the center of the carrot from top to bottom.</item>
<item>As you drill, dump the contents of the inside of the carrot into the bowl.</item>
<item>Drill until there is a clear path from one end of the carrot to the next.</item></list></item>
<item>Drill the 6 holes on the front of the carrot.
<list type="unordered"><item>Use the 7mm drill bit to drill each of the marked 6 holes through to the center of the carrot.</item></list></item>
<item>Drill the 1 hole on the back of the carrot.
<list type="unordered"><item>Use the 7mm drill bit to drill the 1 marked hole through to the center of the carrot.</item></list></item>
<item>Use a vegetable peeler to peel off a layer over the holes on the carrot.
<list type="unordered"><item>This created a slightly flat part of the carrot that will home the finger and thumb holes for the clarinet.</item></list></item>
<item>Attach a 12mm tube to the bottom of the mouthpiece.
<list type="unordered"><item>If the tube does not stay in the mouthpiece, wrap a piece of electrical tape around the end of the tube to widen the wall of the tube. (Some mouthpieces will fit differently from others.)</item></list></item>
<item>Attach the 12mm tube and mouthpiece to the top of the carrot.
<list type="unordered"><item>The opposite end of the tube should fit inside of the top of the carrot.</item></list></item>
<item>Add a funnel to the bottom of the carrot, if desired.
<list type="unordered"><item>The funnel makes the carrot look more like a clarinet and amplify the sound a little bit.</item>
<item>The carrot is playable without the funnel.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
