<text id="autogum_whow_doc205" title="Stop Your Child from Lying (Homework Related)" shortTile="stop-child-lying" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-01-14" dateModified="2018-11-04" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Stop-Your-Child-from-Lying-%28Homework-Related%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Stop Your Child from Lying (Homework Related)</head><p>Many children lie to their parents about completing their homework. When your children lie to you, they may break your trust in them. In order to give them your trust back, a series of steps must be followed in order to prevent your child from lying about their homework in the future.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Talking with Your Child</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find out why your children lie about their homework. Take time to listen to their feelings without being overly negative about them lying. Just let them talk. They may actually have a good reason that you haven't listened to before.</item>
<item>Explain to them that lying is not acceptable. Tell them that it is okay they didn't finish, but remind them that instead of lying, they should ask for help. <figure rend="Parent Adolescent Children Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Help them if they are having trouble. Talk your way through the concept, work a problem with them, and ask questions to make sure they are comprehending.</item>
<item>Be supportive of your children. If they are having trouble, help them as much as you can and be understanding if they don't make as good grades as they could. Instead. encourage them to do better and focus on their strengths. <figure rend="Parent Adolescent Children Step 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Preventing future fibs</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Ask your child to bring you their homework for you to check. This is the best way to resolve the problem. When they bring you homework, you can see if they've finished or not and whether they have been lying to you.
<list type="unordered"><item>Give them a time when they should be done with their homework. At the set time, you will check their homework. Remind them they can ask for help at any time. <figure rend="Excuse Yourself from Unfinished Homework Step 7 Version 6.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Be ready to punish lying if this continues to happen. Take away a favorite toy or electronic if they lie again. <figure rend="Make Up a Good Excuse for Your Homework Not Being Finished Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Talk with your child's teacher. Many schools have a great way of allowing parent connection with the teacher. The teacher may send e-mails regarding your child's troubles with homework. Then you can try to find a time to meet up with their teacher to address the issue. You can also arrange with your child's teacher a tutoring schedule or having an aide come to the house to tutor your child. <figure rend="Talk to Parents When You Babysit Their Kids Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try turning off the television in the living room to help your child focus on homework. If you still want to watch television, maybe you can go to your bedroom instead.</item>
<item>Confiscate your children's electronics until their homework is complete. This ensures they are not wasting time while they should be doing their homework</item>
<item>Ask your child to do their homework in a common area (such as the kitchen or living room) so you can monitor them while they complete their homework.</item>
<item>Show genuine care and interest in your child's life.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't be too hard on the punishment, as your child may get discouraged and not try at all to improve.</item></list>
</text>
