<text id="autogum_whow_doc155" title="Communicate Freely with People" shortTile="communicate-freely" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2015-05-31" dateModified="2018-08-22" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Communicate-Freely-with-People" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Communicate Freely with People</head><p>Communication is the basic asset of human beings. It's our ability to speak and communicate freely that makes us a superior race. But most people fail to harbor the courage to talk open minded with people they have first met or strangers in any place. We often feel alone inside metro, buses, parks or a new institution. Being able to approach new persons saves us from that awkward times that we often face when we don't know anyone we are looking at. Communication for some is like Maggie noodles; we just need 2 minutes a top. But, it can also become a tedious task for introverts and shy persons. It's very rewarding instead, if you have the guts to make the first move.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Keep your attitude right. Your first impression is not the last impression. When you enter a new place, say, your school or college, or even your workplace, its obvious to feel nervous. Don't worry so are the others. you just need to show that you're scared too. They have seen you for the first time so try not to flaunt yourself, instead; be yourself. Think them as already your friends. <figure rend="Be-Single-and-Happy-Step-12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make yourself comfortable. Relations are not sent by God, so try to adjust in whichever seat you get. Making access to other's choices is also important to show you care. You need not argue with someone for the best seat. If you want a particular place for yourself like the front seat or the middle one then just be sure to come a little early the next day. Making tantrums the very first day isn't a good idea to present yourself. <figure rend="Be-a-Better-Girlfriend-Step-6-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be the first to approach. The person beside you or in front of you is seeing you for the first time. Just act normal and introduce yourself, like "Hi, I'm Sasha and you?" or focus on his/her notebook or mobile phone and say, "Good choice, its very trendy." You could just simply comment on his/her dress or shoes or even hairstyle. show that you like him/her. Sometimes there are certain common things that initiate conversation, like the classroom you are in or the boss you are working for. Either way, feel free to voice your opinion. <figure rend="Approach-Women-Anywhere-Step-11-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Carefully listen to what others say. Rushing with your rambling is always not a good idea; you should also pause and listen his/her response. Try to engage more in their topics and views. When they find you reliable and easier to talk, you will too, find them interesting. Don't think for any topics beforehand. Let the conversation lead you. you will see one topic leads to another. It often becomes smooth when you act natural. Pretence is not necessary unless you didn't enroll for an acting course. <figure rend="Be-a-Better-Girlfriend-Step-12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be helpful. Make sure to offer help when they need one. It's up to them to trust you or not, but you could show concern and interest in them. Who knows, you might get help in return. When you're alone in a new place, you won't know what you need and when. So instead of regretting later, you could just ask for some help too unless its very personal. A helping hand once in a while saves from embarrassment. <figure rend="Convince-Yourself-That-You're-Happy-Being-Alone-Step-13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Stay in touch after leaving. It's very rude to not ask for the contact number, especially after the other person has helped you. Even if you do not intend for further communication, just an occasional 'Hi!' or 'Hello! How you're doing?' sums it up. Remember the first person you met saved you from boredom and has at least been a friend to you. Just for the sake of that, drop a message sometimes to show that you remembered. Always be thankful. <figure rend="Be-Friends-with-Everyone-Step-2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Airing yourself is sometimes the hardest thing to do. Even if you're an extrovert and an expert communicator, you have to remember that people are here for your own self worth. If you do not respect yourself, others won't too. while approaching, you must be clear of who you truly are and what are you here for. Friends and peers are always secondary.</item>
<item>Remember, your attitude should be right only for those who are right. Trying to be one of them is okay but sacrificing the real you for becoming a part of something completely different is not going to buy you friends. You will end up being a total nobody. Choose yourself before anybody. Confirm your base first, and try to stick to your origins. Then make friends who suits you best. Everyone has a unique inborn quality, make sure you don't dump yours.</item>
<item>Always be honest to yourself and the others around you. Sometimes it becomes hard to cope up with colleagues and peers, specially when they are popular. But don't you worry. your day will come too. The most important factor is your honesty, hard work and righteousness that will bear fruit. No one has ever gone away  with betrayal, treason and slyness. The only way to stay put is to work well with others.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't befriend too loud and rude people. The best way to avoid trouble is to stay away from them.</item>
<item>Don't be miserable all the time. Feeling low and depressed is a common human behavior, but try to include in some fun too. After all that's the only point of communication, right?</item>
<item>Granted, be rude to get rid of annoying friends. After all, smiles can't conquer the world.</item>
<item>Don't push yourself far enough for attention. Just wait for the right time.</item>
<item>Offering for help is very charming but only if you do not get involved in their personal matters. You don't want controversies about yourself.</item></list>
</text>
