<text id="autogum_whow_doc590" title="Read Plato’s Gorgias" shortTile="read-platos-gorgias" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2018-02-05" dateModified="2018-08-19" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Read-Plato%E2%80%99s-Gorgias" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Read Plato’s Gorgias</head><p>This how-to instruction set will guide any student, either at the high school or undergraduate level, on reading Plato’s Gorgias.  As a student of any level in English one will run into classical texts at some point. Plato’s Gorgias is a text that is relevant to the field of Rhetoric and Composition Studies, as it debated the uses and misuses of rhetoric as a verbal/written genre.  The following sections (supplies, before you read, while you’re reading, and after you read) will slowly guide the reader of this how-to in understanding the text at hand.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Pre-Reading for a Platonic Dialogue</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Go to a workspace with all of the supplies. This will limit the number of times you will have to stop reading the text. The dialogue in the Gorgias is unfamiliar and therefore may require you to re-read and focus. This is why having a workspace that is comfortable for you will help to limit frustration and distractions. When choosing a workspace pick somewhere that you are able to study and focus. This could be done in a library, home or coffee shop where ever is best for you.</item>
<item>Practice Active Reading Strategies.  Active reading is employing different methods to help understand a text before and while you read. Using active reading methods before you begin reading will help to ease the frustration that can follow reading a difficult text.
<list type="unordered"><item>Here are a few links for more information on pre-reading strategies
<list type="unordered"><item>Study Guides and Strategies</item>
<item>7 Pre-Reading Strategies that Increase Comprehension</item></list></item></list></item>
<item>Understand why the text is valuable for your field (English, Rhetoric and Composition, Communications, Media studies, Philosophy...). Plato’s Gorgias is important because it is a core text use to define the function of Rhetoric. As a student studying in the field of English as a BA or an MA, this understanding is fundamental to how the genre is understood. Many scholars use this text as a way to argue within their own works. If you have a good base understanding of this text, you will be able to read others with less frustration. Especially, if you are a student in the field of Rhetoric and Composition Studies as the piece helped to define the field in which you study.</item></list>
<head>Reading Strategies for the Gorgias</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Do background research into the Ancient Greek Scene. This should be the history the scholar Plato and settings, themes, and characters of Gorgias to gain context via a quick online search. This will help you to read the text easier because you will be familiar with this writing style, base themes and limit frustration at unfamiliar concepts and jargon. For example, virtue and the functions of rhetoric are themes discussed within this text.</item>
<item>Write focus questions about why the concepts or ideas in this text matters. This can be typically 3-4 questions bases on your research you have conducted on the text. These will help you to center your reading of this text.
<list type="unordered"><item>Some sample questions you may ask are:
<list type="unordered"><item>What take does Plato have in terms of the use of rhetoric in society?</item>
<item>What other characters are involved? Do they have the same viewpoints as Plato or are they different?</item>
<item>How does Plato differ from the sophists?</item>
<item>Does Plato's position on rhetoric make sense in modern studies of rhetoric?</item></list></item></list></item>
<item>Take notes in the margins. They can come in the form of comments or questions, but actively engaging with the text allows you to retain what you are reading.</item>
<item>Mark any unfamiliar jargon while reading. Look up unfamiliar jargon after reading the text completely as this will help to keep a focus on reading.This will limit frustration because of unfamiliar words.
<list type="unordered"><item>Some unfamiliar jargon that you may come across could include:
<list type="unordered"><item>sophist</item>
<item>harangue</item>
<item>techne</item>
<item>oratory/orator</item>
<item>nomos</item></list></item></list></item>
<item>Mark any main themes around the function/defining of Rhetoric. In this piece, Plato is discussing, through Socrates, the meaning, and uses of rhetoric. Socrates is engaged in an argument with Gorgias who believed that rhetoric is the art of persuasion. Gorgias is a sophist. The sophists are teachers that instruct others to make a living, and not just for the pleasure of having knowledge. The art of persuasion that Gorgias is speaking is used to make money and other reasons that Socrates deems immoral.Therefore, Socrates deems rhetoric as a skill, unlike philosophy which is an art form. This piece is one of the first known sightings of the word “rhetoric” and it gives an insight into the functions and uses of rhetoric as a genre.</item>
<item>Take notes on characters stances. This piece is centered around a debate going on between Socrates and Gorgas about what function of rhetoric. All characters involved have different stances on the definition of rhetoric. This idea will inform your core understanding of the meaning of Plato’s Gorgias.
<list type="unordered"><item>The characters you will most likely come across are:
<list type="unordered"><item>Socrates</item>
<item>Gorgias</item>
<item>Polus</item>
<item>Callicles</item>
<item>Chaerephon</item></list></item></list></item></list>
<head>Reflecting on Reading the Gorgias</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Look up any jargon you did not understand.</item>
<item>Answer the focus questions that you wrote before reading. Being able to answer these questions can assess how much is taken away from the work from the initial read.</item>
<item>Ask yourself how this text relates to the goals of the course you are currently enrolled in or how it relates to other texts you have read so far.</item>
<item>Assess your understanding of the text. Did you understand the work? Remember that this text is not easy to understand and can be confusing for first time readers. But, this is okay and expected, because reading as a process is not linear, but recursive. Meaning that it may take more than one attempt to begin understanding a text.</item>
<item>Reread the text. Take your time and read through the piece once more to help gain a better understanding of the material.</item>
<item>Read additional summaries. If you are still having issues understanding this text go back and read a summary or book review.</item>
<item>Talk it over with others in your class.</item>
<item>Ask your teacher or professor some questions regarding the text to help gain some insight.</item></list>
</text>
