<text id="autogum_whow_doc330" title="Write About Mental Illness" shortTile="write-mental-illness" type="whow" dateCollected="2019-11-06" dateCreated="2019-04-10" dateModified="2019-10-26" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Write-About-Mental-Illness" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Write About Mental Illness</head><p>Writing about serious topics is difficult for those who may have never experienced them. Subjects like mental health can be sensitive for many, making addressing them in an informative essay or a work of fiction a hard thing to do. Here, we discuss what to do when writing about mental health.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Educate yourself. Find information about the mental illness you want to write about from reputable, authoritative sources in the psychology field.
<list type="unordered"><item>Ideally, going to professionals who specialize in the mental illness you choose to pursue can help to make your writing factual and understandable for your audience, while still being able to keep an audience hooked on your writing.</item>
<item>Talk to real people with mental illnesses, if possible. People with the ability to give firsthand accounts of mental health experiences are amazing resources for making your piece respectful for those who suffer from the illness. It also can help bring a more personal feeling in your character if you write with the people you talk with in mind. Be respectful of their privacy and any identifying traits or personal stories they share with you.</item>
<item>Don't be afraid to ask questions. Many people are comfortable talking about the mental disorders they have and will give you a sense of what living with a mental health issue is like. Just be respectful of the person and understand that not everyone wants to share information about this sensitive of a subject.</item></list></item>
<item>Figure out what your motive is for incorporating mental health issues in your work. This is particularly important if you're writing a fictional piece; remember why you plan to address mental illness.
<list type="unordered"><item>Many people use mental illnesses to emphasize character traits. For example, a character that is supposed to be angsty might be given depression, but only because it emphasizes the stereotypical depressed individual that the author wants. However, this is an inappropriate use of the illness and isn't seen as respectable in the mental health community.</item>
<item>Don't let the mental health issue define your character. While someone may suffer from bipolar disorder, that doesn't mean that is all they are. Writing a character that is only notable for their illness is a very forced way of incorporating mental health into your book. Characters with mental disorders need to maintain the same level of depth as every other character.</item></list></item>
<item>Be precise with your language. Avoid inaccurate or inflammatory words.
<list type="unordered"><item>Never use words like "retarded". Words like this often get used a lot in situations where it's inaccurate and offensive. As an author, you need to be sure to use appropriate terminology and not to use certain words that are seen as offensive. Language evolves as our society changes, and this is especially true for terminology surrounding mental health and disability.</item>
<item>Learn what terms are accepted in the community. Often there are slight nuances to speaking on mental health, and while the distinctions may seem small, they can make your writing less respected by the community. For example, it's generally not acceptable to say "a schizophrenic" or "a schizophrenic person". Instead, say "a person with schizophrenia" or "a person who has schizophrenia".</item></list></item>
<item>Be open to changing things. Take feedback from others, including those better versed in the subject you're writing about or who are directly affected by it.
<list type="unordered"><item>Even if your overall writing is sound, you may have certain sentences that come off wrong and need fine-tuning. Keeping an open mind on improving things in your writing will make writing a respectful piece much easier.</item>
<item>Understand that people may get upset. Mental health is often a controversial topic, and not everyone agrees on certain aspects. Be understanding, but also know that it is tough to please everyone and that sometimes you can't change who gets offended by what.</item>
<item>Always take into account that if you write about discrimination, there may be controversy in whether that should be talked about. However, this controversy isn't necessarily something that you, as an author, need to take personally, as this is an issue bigger than your writing.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't take judgment to heart, but do try to keep multiple perspectives in mind, particularly that of the groups depicted in your work.</item>
<item>Learn to be open to changing things in your writing.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Trigger warnings may become necessary if you write on subjects of harassment or discrimination based on mental health.</item>
<item>Controversy can lead to a lot of hate against your writing.</item></list>
</text>
