<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc99" title="Flash Xiaomi Qualcomm Devices" shortTile="flash-xiaomi-qualcomm" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2017-04-19" dateModified="2019-09-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Flash_Xiaomi_Qualcomm_Devices" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Flash Xiaomi Qualcomm Devices</head>Many Xiaomi device users will have some trouble on their devices like annoying adware, hang on Mi Logo (boot loop), battery drain, and many more. it because their devices were on Rom called 'distributor' Rom. This tutorial will bring to you how to fix flashing Xiaomi devices powered by Qualcomm processor. Don't try this if your device has a MediaTek processor.
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Turn on USB Debugging and OEM. You can unlock this on your device by going to your settings. Then, select "additional settings" before tapping on the "developer option." However, if the developer option is missing, choose "MIUI Version 5x."</item>
<item>Install Xiaomi Flashtool. In addition, install Minimal ADB and Fastboot. Be sure to run Xiaomi Flashtool and follow the step when you run .exe files until Xiaomi Flashtool is installed.
<list type="unordered"><item>Run Minimal ADB and Fastboot and follow the step when you run .exe files until Minimal ADB and Fastboot installed.</item></list></item>
<item>Boot your device into Emergency Download Mode (EDL).
<list type="unordered"><item>Open minimal ADB and Fastboot</item>
<item>Type this command on the app: 'ADB devices' (if your device still alive, if your devices were stuck on Mi Logo, the command is 'Fastboot devices).</item>
<item>Then, your device will be shown as 'xxxxxxxxxx ADB' or 'xxxxxxxx Fastboot' if your devices stuck on Mi Logo.</item>
<item>Type 'ADB reboot EDL' or 'Fastboot reboot EDL' if your device stuck on Mi Logo.</item>
<item>after this, your device will reboot to EDL Mode and your devices will red blinking. repeat this tutorial if your devices rebooted on the system again.</item></list></item>
<item>Extract the Fastboot Random Access Memory(ROM) to C:<hi rend="bold">(Local Disk) directory.</hi></item>
<item>Flash your devices. Open Xiaomi Flashtool and tap the "select" button. Choose the rom folder where you extracted (C: &gt; xxxx_images_x.x.xxxxxxxx.xxxx.xx_x.x_xx &gt; xxxx_images_x.x.xxxxxxxx.xxxx.xx_x.x_xx ). Then, refresh the page, and your devices will be shown as 'COM XX' depend on your USB Port.
<list type="unordered"><item>On the right bottom of the Xiaomi Flashtool, select 'clean all'.</item>
<item>Select 'Flash' button.</item>
<item>Wait until status shown as 'Flashing Done'.</item>
<item>Reboot your device to the system by holding the power button until your devices rebooted to the system.</item></list></item>
<item>Set up your device(s). Once flashing is done, you can set up your devices like new devices again.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>For booting the device into EDL Mode, many devices will have a different step. You can search by yourself on a search engine for a tutorial.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Important: this tutorial will erase your internal storage data! so back up your files to PC before trying to flash. I am not responsible for bricked devices, dead SD cards, thermonuclear war, or you getting fired because the alarm app failed. so please be careful and follow the step by steps correctly.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Xiaomi Flashtool from <ref target="https://androidmtk.com/download-xiaomi-mi-flash-tool">https://androidmtk.com/download-xiaomi-mi-flash-tool</ref>.</item>
<item>Fastboot ROM from <ref target="http://en.miui.com/a-234.html">http://en.miui.com/a-234.html</ref> (please choose the ROM to depend on your devices, for example, I choose Redmi note 3 Qualcomm)</item>
<item>Minimal ADB and Fastboot from <ref target="https://forum.xda-developers.com/showthread.php?t=2317790">https://forum.xda-developers.com/showthread.php?t=2317790</ref> (depend on your devices, for example, my device is Redmi Note 3 Qualcomm and I need this tool).</item>
<item>PC with Windows 7 - 10.</item>
<item>USB Data Cable.</item></list>
</text>
