<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc37" title="Run the Motion Offense in Lacrosse" shortTile="run-motion-offense" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-06-09" dateModified="2019-05-14" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Run_the_Motion_Offense_in_Lacrosse" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Run the Motion Offense in Lacrosse</head><p>The Motion Offense is a critical part of both the men and women's lacrosse game. Implementing the Motion Offense sets up a solid foundation for your team's offense. The Motion Offense organizes the offense and creates movement of the ball until players create an opportunity to score. The key point of the Motion Offense is to never stop moving. The constant motion of the offense confuses the opposing defense and creates situations that are difficult to defend. When the offense is constantly moving, the defense does not have time to rest.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Label disc cones with the numbers 1-7. <figure rend="Run the Motion Offense in Lacrosse Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Set up your offense. Each position in the Motion Offense is assigned a number. Facing the middle of the field: The left of the goal is #1, the right of the goal is #2, then numbers increase  from 3 to 7 counter-clockwise balancing around  the 12-meter arch. <figure rend="Run the Motion Offense in Lacrosse Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Place a cone to mark the 7 starting spots of the Motion Offense. <figure rend="Run the Motion Offense in Lacrosse Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Inform players of the following options that the ball carrier has in the motion offense: <figure rend="Run the Motion Offense in Lacrosse Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Going to goal</item>
<item>Passing to an adjacent</item>
<item>Switching Positions</item></list></item>
<item>Start with the play setup. During a transition from midfield to offense, the ball carrier should look to go to goal as her first option. If the opposing defense is not set up yet, she could have an easy opportunity to shoot or draw a shooting space foul. <figure rend="Run the Motion Offense in Lacrosse Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If the ball carrier does not have a clear path to goal, she stall the play by getting into one of the seven spots and wait for her teammates to set up Motion. <figure rend="Run the Motion Offense in Lacrosse Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Explain to the ball carrier that the next option should be a look to pass. The ball carrier has 2 options when passing. Those two options include passing to the player to her left or passing to the player to her right. Passing to any player other than an adjacent is a risky pass and could be intercepted or deflected by the opposing defender. Passes should be quick, clean and direct. Lobbed passes could also be intercepted by a defender. <figure rend="Run the Motion Offense in Lacrosse Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are a player who does not have the ball and is not directly adjacent to the ball carrier, you should be paying attention to the location of the ball. Keep the offense balanced around the 12 meter arch to create space for passing, movement and cuts.</item></list></item>
<item>After the ball carrier has passed it to an adjacent, have the previous ball carrier make a cut towards goal. They now become "the cutter". The cutter should be running close to full speed into the 8-meter arch in front of the goal, looking for a pass from the now-ball carrier. <figure rend="Run the Motion Offense in Lacrosse Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If the ball carrier does not have a clean pass to the cutter, the cutter will continue running to the outside of the 8 meter arch. They will find a new spot in the Motion while the other players balance out the rest of the set-up.</item></list></item>
<item>Have the ball carriers continue to pass to their left or right adjacent, then cutting towards the goal. The ball should be moving fast, only staying with one player for 3-5 seconds before being passed to the next adjacent. <figure rend="Run the Motion Offense in Lacrosse Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If a player is having a hard time getting the ball to her adjacent, she can also switch her location in the motion offense. Communication is key within the offense, so let your teammates know by yelling "switch". Your teammates will know that you are moving and will be looking out for opportunities to receive a pass. <figure rend="Run the Motion Offense in Lacrosse Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Off-ball players can switch places with other off-ball players as well. Any movement that the offense does requires the defense to focus attention on the motion offense. <figure rend="Run the Motion Offense in Lacrosse Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be the first player to all ground balls. If you or a teammate drops the ball while in motion, make sure you hustle the hardest to win back the ground ball. <figure rend="Run the Motion Offense in Lacrosse Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be patient. Working the Motion Offense can take time. Do not rush and force passes or shots, as bad shots and bad passes are easily recovered by the opposing team. <figure rend="Run the Motion Offense in Lacrosse Step 13.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Have your midfielders set up at the top of the arch. These players will have to run a shorter distance when they need to get back and help on defense.</item>
<item>Before moving to Step #3, have players pass around while calling out the numbers of the positions in the motion offense. If the ball is in spot #4, all players should be shouting "4!"</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure each player is wearing protective goggles and a full mouth-guard. Goalies should also be equipped with proper padding prior to starting the instruction of the Motion Offense.</item></list>
</text>
