<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc146" title="Make Your Younger Cousin Jealous" shortTile="make-younger-cousin" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-10-13" dateModified="2019-06-01" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make_Your_Younger_Cousin_Jealous" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make Your Younger Cousin Jealous</head><p>Ever thought your little cousin is/thinks they are better than you? Do they brag all the time to try and be cool? If they do, then this article is for you!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Looking Presentable</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Work on your hair. Your hair will complete your outfit. How you do your hair depends on the vibe you want to give out.
<list type="unordered"><item>Some "vibes" include cutesy, sporty, girly, dancer, formal, trendy, and casual.You can find many articles discussing what would look best for each of these looks for both genders.</item></list></item>
<item>Opt for good attire. Your outfit is the main focus. It should match your hairstyle, shoes, makeup, jewelry, or anything else you plan to present yourself with.</item>
<item>Think good shoes. Shoes can make or break your entire outfit. Choose wisely for the season and your style.
<list type="unordered"><item>Some ideas for your shoes could include, uggs, flats, wedges, flip-flops, heels, or boots.</item>
<item>Remember to pick shoes that look good and that you will be comfortable wearing. In the moment, nothing can seem worse than having to walk around in shoes that don't fit you right.</item></list></item>
<item>Pick the right accessories. Accessories are essential to a complete outfit.
<list type="unordered"><item>For both genders, you can wear hats, watches, shoes, etc.</item>
<item>For girls, you can wear different types of jewelry or heels.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Working On The Personality</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Up your talent. You should be better than them at something/everything.</item>
<item>Be mindful. Become more mature than them, such as being more alert, nicer, smarter, etc. Always look on the bright side (when appropriate).
<list type="unordered"><item>When they confront you about this, they’ll seem very immature.</item></list></item>
<item>Act cool. Act like you really don’t care when they are around. Text your friends, discreetly roll your eyes, etc.</item>
<item>Be outgoing. Be a social butterfly at school and in the family.
<list type="unordered"><item>Be able to socialize with everybody in the family. This can be made easier through more interactions with people so that you can find out their interests and hold better, more meaningful conversations with them.</item>
<item>Make a lot of friends at school, and you could possibly date someone if you want to up your chances of making them jealous.</item>
<item>Before going to see your cousin, text all of your friends. When you’re there, your phone will be ringing off the hook and they may become jealous.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Taking Care Of The Extras</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Maintain a nice looking room. Keep it clean and organized. Your bed should have a nice black, white, or your favorite color sheet/comforter/pillowcases. Set up trophies, ribbons, medals, etc. in your room to show off your achievements.</item>
<item>Have things that your cousin wants. Do you have something they are very into, like a toy or a game? Let them know you have it, but never give it to them. This will make them seem immature when they ask for them.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try to have fun. Let this jealous cousin inspire you to live life even better.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't forget yourself and your interests. There may be many that provoke you but you have to balance between living for others and for yourself.</item>
<item>Don't take this too far, unless you want to get in trouble. Opt to make your cousin a bit envious, but don't outright bully them.</item></list>
</text>
