<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc82" title="Copy Drivers from One Computer to Another on PC or Mac" shortTile="copy-drivers-one" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-08-16" dateModified="2019-09-25" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Copy_Drivers_from_One_Computer_to_Another_on_PC_or_Mac" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Copy Drivers from One Computer to Another on PC or Mac</head><p>This wikiHow teaches you how to copy device drivers from one Windows or macOS computer to another. This is useful for when you need an older version of a driver that is no longer available from the manufacturer.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Windows</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open the Windows File Explorer. A fast way to do this is to press the Windows  on the keyboard. <figure rend="Copy Drivers from One Computer to Another on PC or Mac Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Navigate to driver repository. Windows stores a copy of each installed driver at C:\Windows\System32\DriverStore\FileRepository. Each driver is located within its own folder. <figure rend="Copy Drivers from One Computer to Another on PC or Mac Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>To access this folder, click your <hi rend="bold">C</hi> drive in the left panel, double-click <hi rend="bold">Windows</hi>, then <hi rend="bold">System32</hi>, then <hi rend="bold">DriverStore</hi>, and then <hi rend="bold">FileRepository</hi>.</item></list></item>
<item>Locate the folder with the driver you want to copy. Scroll down the right panel until you find it. Folders names begin with the name of the actual driver (e.g., ″xboxgip.if_amd64_x″), and are listed in alphabetical order by default. <figure rend="Copy Drivers from One Computer to Another on PC or Mac Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Copy the folder to a flash drive. If you don’t have a flash drive, you can <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_a_Zip_File">zip the folder up</ref> and upload it to a cloud server, such as <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Add_Files_to_Google_Drive_Online">Google Drive</ref>. Otherwise, here’s how to copy the folder to your flash drive: <figure rend="Copy Drivers from One Computer to Another on PC or Mac Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Insert your flash drive into the computer.</item>
<item>Click the folder you want to copy once to select it, then press  to copy it.</item>
<item>Scroll down the left column of the File Explorer and double-click your flash drive.</item>
<item>Right-click a blank space in the right panel and select <hi rend="bold">Paste</hi>.</item>
<item>Once the files are copied, safely remove your flash drive.</item></list></item>
<item>Insert the flash drive into the second PC. If the contents of the flash drive do not display immediately, press  to open the File Explorer, then click the flash drive to open it. <figure rend="Copy Drivers from One Computer to Another on PC or Mac Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you uploaded the folder to a cloud account, sign into that same account on this computer, then download the file.</item></list></item>
<item>Drag the driver folder to the desktop. You can drag it to a different location on the computer if you prefer. <figure rend="Copy Drivers from One Computer to Another on PC or Mac Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you downloaded a zip file, double-click it to open it, then drag the folder inside to the desktop).</item></list></item>
<item>Open the Device Manager. Here’s how to find it: <figure rend="Copy Drivers from One Computer to Another on PC or Mac Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Click the search icon (a circle or magnifying glass next to the Start menu).</item>
<item>Type .</item>
<item>Click <hi rend="bold">Device Manager</hi> when it appears in the search results.</item></list></item>
<item>Expand the group that contains the device you want to install. Depending on the device, the correct group may already be expanded because the driver needs to be installed. <figure rend="Copy Drivers from One Computer to Another on PC or Mac Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, if you’re installing the driver for a sound card, expand ″Sound, Video, and game controllers″ group.</item></list></item>
<item>Right-click the device and select . This opens the Properties window. <figure rend="Copy Drivers from One Computer to Another on PC or Mac Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the  tab. It’s at the top of the window. <figure rend="Copy Drivers from One Computer to Another on PC or Mac Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . It’s the second option. <figure rend="Copy Drivers from One Computer to Another on PC or Mac Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . <figure rend="Copy Drivers from One Computer to Another on PC or Mac Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Double-click the location where you copied the driver folder. For example, if you dragged the folder to the desktop, double-click <hi rend="bold">Desktop</hi>. <figure rend="Copy Drivers from One Computer to Another on PC or Mac Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select the driver folder and click . This adds the selected folder to the ″Update Drivers″ dialog. <figure rend="Copy Drivers from One Computer to Another on PC or Mac Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . Windows will now scan the folder for the driver. <figure rend="Copy Drivers from One Computer to Another on PC or Mac Step 15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Follow the on-screen instructions to install the driver.  <figure rend="Copy Drivers from One Computer to Another on PC or Mac Step 16.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>macOS</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open Finder . It’s the first icon on the Dock, which is usually at the bottom of the screen. <figure rend="Copy Drivers from One Computer to Another on PC or Mac Step 17.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Press  as you click . <hi rend="bold">Go</hi> is a menu in the bar at the top of the screen. <figure rend="Copy Drivers from One Computer to Another on PC or Mac Step 18.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . <figure rend="Copy Drivers from One Computer to Another on PC or Mac Step 19.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Double-click the device’s folder. For example, if you need to copy printer drivers, double-click <hi rend="bold">Printers</hi>. <figure rend="Copy Drivers from One Computer to Another on PC or Mac Step 20.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Copy the folder to a flash drive. If you don’t have a flash drive, you can <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_a_Zip_File">zip the folder up</ref> and upload it to a cloud server, such as <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Add_Files_to_Google_Drive_Online">Google Drive</ref>. Otherwise, here’s how to copy the folder to your flash drive: <figure rend="Copy Drivers from One Computer to Another on PC or Mac Step 21.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Insert your flash drive into the computer. In a few moments, the flash drive will show up under ″Devices″ in the left column of Finder.</item>
<item>Drag the driver from its original location to the flash drive.</item></list></item>
<item>Insert the flash drive into the second Mac. If you uploaded the folder to a cloud account, sign into that same account on this computer, download the zip file, and then unzip it to the computer. <figure rend="Check-USB-Ports-on-PC-or-Mac-Step-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Open Finder  and click the flash drive. The contents of the drive will appear. <figure rend="Copy Drivers from One Computer to Another on PC or Mac Step 23.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Drag the folder to the hard drive. It’s usually called <hi rend="bold">Macintosh HD</hi> unless it’s been renamed. This installs the driver to the appropriate Library folder. <figure rend="Copy Drivers from One Computer to Another on PC or Mac Step 24.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
