<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc136" title="Plant the Seeds of Knowledge" shortTile="plant-seeds-knowledge" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-03-06" dateModified="2017-10-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Plant_the_Seeds_of_Knowledge" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Plant the Seeds of Knowledge</head><p>Learning should be a lifelong endeavor, and planting the seed of attaining knowledge will help your children and others gain knowledge throughout their life.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Encourage curiosity. Teaching someone to want to know why, how, or what something is or does is a gateway to learning. If the child asks you something that you don't know about, or it isn't related to things you know about, assist your child in searching for the answer instead of providing it yourself. <figure rend="Plant the Seeds of Knowledge Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This will increase their curiosity as well as help them understand that things need to be found out sometimes and that the answer isn't always given.</item></list></item>
<item>Teach the person how to read critically.  Reading is an effective tool for learning, and reading critically will help the person discern truth and value in what they read.Try to read books to a child from a young age. That will prove to be effective as they grow. <figure rend="Plant the Seeds of Knowledge Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Children are sharper and more observant at the ages of 11 months to 2 years. They take a deep effect of everything that is happening around them and the effect, good or bad, influences them when they grow.</item></list></item>
<item>Show the student how to observe. Looking closely, watching for varying time intervals, and looking for the source or origin of observed phenomena will enhance understanding of what is seen and increase curiosity. <figure rend="Plant the Seeds of Knowledge Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You might take them to walk through various streets and ask them what they observed in them.</item>
<item>Give them pictures or stamps of countries or states and ask them to describe what they noticed about any particular stamp that inspired them. Start with two to three colorful and highly detailed pictures that would catch the child's attention.</item></list></item>
<item>Provide tools for learning. This may include books, a camera, an audio recorder, and tools like a magnifying glass or microscope. Aside from these, there are guides and booklets of various subject which are specially designed to teach a child about something particular. <figure rend="Plant the Seeds of Knowledge Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Before getting the accessories, be well acquainted about your child's likes and things that they enjoy.</item></list></item>
<item>Provide opportunity for learning. Trips to museums, science displays, parks, zoos, farms, or anywhere else that exposes a fertile mind to a learning experience can be very valuable to the learner. Visiting places far away from your locality, like a countryside if you live in a town, shall also help in opening your child's mind. <figure rend="Plant the Seeds of Knowledge Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try taking the child to trips when you are visiting a foreign country or a city you've never been to before. Taking them to places they don't know of will get their mind used to understanding and knowing that there are other places aside from his/her birthplace as well as increase their knowledge.</item>
<item>Before, however, you take the child to a new community, be well-informed about it, since your child is likely to ask you a lot of questions about the region. Know its history, culture, geography and traditions.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
