<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc60" title="Change the Language on Your Computer" shortTile="change-language-computer" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2013-12-06" dateModified="2019-11-02" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Change_the_Language_on_Your_Computer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Change the Language on Your Computer</head><p>This wikiHow teaches you how to change your computer's language. This will affect the text used in menus and windows. You can do this on both Windows and Mac computers. Changing your computer's default language will not <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Change-Your-Browser's-Language">change your internet browser's language</ref> or other programs.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>On Windows</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open Start . Click the Windows logo in the bottom-left corner of the screen. <figure rend="Change the Language on Your Computer Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can also press the Windows key on your keyboard to open Start.</item></list></item>
<item>Click Settings . This gear-shaped icon is in the lower-left side of the Start window. <figure rend="Change the Language on Your Computer Step 2 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . It's in the middle of the Settings window. <figure rend="Change the Language on Your Computer Step 3 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the  tab. You'll find this on the far-left side of the window. <figure rend="Change the Language on Your Computer Step 4 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . It's next to a large <hi rend="bold">+</hi> sign in the middle of the page, below the "Languages" heading. <figure rend="Change the Language on Your Computer Step 5 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select a language. Click the language you want to use on your computer. <figure rend="Change the Language on Your Computer Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select a dialect. If clicking your preferred language brings you to a page with different regional dialects available, click a dialect to select it. <figure rend="Change the Language on Your Computer Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This may not be available for your selected language.</item></list></item>
<item>Click your added language. It should be below your current default language in the "Languages" section of the window. Doing so will expand the language's box. <figure rend="Change the Language on Your Computer Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . This button appears below the language. Doing so opens the language's Options window. <figure rend="Change the Language on Your Computer Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Download the language pack. Click <hi rend="bold">Download</hi> below the "Download language pack" heading in the upper-left side of the page. <figure rend="Change the Language on Your Computer Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click Back . It's in the top-left corner of the screen. <figure rend="Change the Language on Your Computer Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the language again, then click . You'll find this button below the language. Doing to will move the language to the top of the "Languages" section and set it as the default for all built-in menus, apps, and other display options. <figure rend="Change the Language on Your Computer Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Restart your computer. Open the Start menu, click <hi rend="bold">Power</hi> , and click <hi rend="bold">Restart</hi>. Once your computer restarts and you sign back into your account, your selected language will be in place. <figure rend="Change the Language on Your Computer Step 13.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>On Mac</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open the Apple menu . Click the Apple logo in the top-left corner of the screen. A drop-down menu will appear. <figure rend="Change the Language on Your Computer Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . It's near the top of the drop-down menu. <figure rend="Change the Language on Your Computer Step 15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . It's a flag-shaped icon near the top of the System Preferences window. <figure rend="Change the Language on Your Computer Step 16.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . This icon is below the bottom-left corner of the "Preferred language:" box on the left side of the Language &amp; Region window. Doing so prompts a pop-up window with different languages. <figure rend="Change the Language on Your Computer Step 17.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Scroll to select the language you want, then click . <figure rend="Change the Language on Your Computer Step 18 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click  when prompted. This is the blue button in the bottom-right corner of the window. Doing so will set your computer's default display language to the added language. <figure rend="Change the Language on Your Computer Step 19 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you miss this step, just click and drag the language you added from the bottom of the "Preferred languages" box to the top.</item></list></item>
<item>Restart your Mac to complete the language change. <figure rend="Change the Language on Your Computer Step 20 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Changing your computer's language won't change the language for all apps, programs, menus, and so on. When downloading software, you'll still have to select your preferred language as part of the installation process.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be sure not to change the language on your computer to something you don't understand or can't easily backtrack through.</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
