<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc285" title="Stay Healthy when You Have a Desk Job" shortTile="stay-healthy-desk" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-01-23" dateModified="2019-06-02" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Stay_Healthy_when_You_Have_a_Desk_Job" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Stay Healthy when You Have a Desk Job</head><p>Having a desk job is no reason to start gaining weight. Some people may find that the combination of a desk job, a poor diet and a lack of exercise may lead to them becoming fatter, year after year.  A desk job isn’t an excuse to get fat and consign yourself to buying clothing of XXXL size. You can easily stay healthy, or get healthier, even working '9:00-5:00' at a desk. Read on from step one for how.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Change your eating habits. Consider what you commonly eat for lunch. Many office workers and desk jockeys buy fast food, such as Chinese takeaway, burgers and other kinds of unhealthy food that may damage their health and cause weight gain at lunchtime. <figure rend="Stay Healthy when You Have a Desk Job Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Choose a healthy lunch option. Don't eat a lot of red meat, white bread, mayonnaise, fatty cheese, baked goods and refined sugar. Avoid carbonated drinks, too. Many people believe that the best lunch choices are vegetable soup, boiled or stewed meat or fish, fresh vegetables and porridge, especially brown rice and buckwheat. Try to eat five portions of fruit and vegetables today, incorporating different colours of these, and avoid consuming more than 2000 calories.</item></list></item>
<item>Get regular physical exercise. It is up to you what kind of exercise you choose. You can go to the gym after work or walk to work. Try zumba, circuit training, dancing, jogging, yoga, pilates, box-ercise or aerobics. <figure rend="Stay Healthy when You Have a Desk Job Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>There are lots of activities that are not healthy, but also fun. Aim to be active for 30 minutes at least every day. You will be healthier, have a better body and feel more energetic.</item></list></item>
<item>Walk as much as possible at work and get up from your desk often. You can walk to your office if it's practical, or at least get of the bus a stop early and walk. Park at the rear of the car park if you can. Don’t use the elevator for less than three flights; even better, never use the elevator! <figure rend="Stay Healthy when You Have a Desk Job Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Going up stairs is an excellent exercise that can help you to burn a lot of calories. You shouldn’t sit all day long during your working day. Walk, even in the office. Stretch at your desk, walk to toilets a floor away and get a small drink several times a day rather than sitting still drinking from a large cup or bottle all day. Go talk to colleagues instead of sending an e-mail or calling them. Consider standing in meetings, rather than sitting.</item></list></item>
<item>Don't get dehydrated. <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Drink_More_Water_Every_Day">Drink water throughout the day</ref>. <figure rend="Stay Healthy when You Have a Desk Job Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get your work station assessed by a health and safety officer. Sitting isn't a natural position for the human body so make sure your chair is suitable. Get your keyboard, monitor and computer checked to make sure you're using them safely. Consider an ergonomic keyboard, using a wrist rest, getting a foot rest, using a mouse pad with a wrist rest and any other equipment that will help you feel comfortable and avoid W.R.U.L.D. (Work Related Upper Limb Disorder) type injuries. <figure rend="Stay Healthy when You Have a Desk Job Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be aware of noise. Printers, phones ringing, office chatter, etc. can all lead to a noisy workplace. Make sure you take advantage of any hearing tests offered if your workplace qualifies. <figure rend="Stay Healthy when You Have a Desk Job Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Look after your eyes. Don't get eye strain using a monitor all day, but have frequent micro breaks. If you get dry eyes in the office, try eye sprays washes, especially if you were contact lenses. Ensure products are compatible. <figure rend="Stay Healthy when You Have a Desk Job Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Dietitians recommend eating small portions (7-7.5 ounces) several times a day. Don’t think that it is too little. You will get used to such eating habit very soon and notice changes on the scales.</item>
<item>It is also advised to forget about snacks that contain mostly fats and starches – crisps, sweets, buns, chocolate bars and other foods that are commonly used by people to lay stomach for a while.</item>
<item>Don’t abuse sugar, salt and spices.  Too much salt may cause water retention (and weight gain consequently) and too much sugar often become an addiction. Bear in mind that drinks like Coca-Cola contain much sugar.</item>
<item>It is enough to exercise 3 times a week and observe healthy eating habits to stay fit and strong even if you work 10-12 hours a day.</item>
<item>All depends on you. It isn’t difficult to stay slim and slender even if you have a desk job. All you need is a little patience, a dab of will power and some efforts.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don’t exclude any group of products from your menu for quicker results. Only a balanced diet can help you to lose weight and stay fit for years without extreme dieting.</item>
<item>Avoid taking alcohol. When people drink hot beverages, they often forget about “rules” and consume everything they see. If you take alcohol, it may affect your results.</item></list>
</text>
