<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc306" title="Celebrate Gurpurb" shortTile="celebrate-gurpurb" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-11-23" dateModified="2016-08-18" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Celebrate_Gurpurb" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Celebrate Gurpurb</head><p><hi rend="bold">Gurpurbs</hi> are festivals in the religion of Sikhism. It is celebrated in honour of the birthdays, guruship dates and deaths of the Gurus. One of the most important festivals is celebrating the birth of Guru Nanak Dev, the founder of the Sikhs. This is how to celebrate this festival.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>In November the <hi rend="italic">Akhand</hi> paths are performed in <hi rend="italic">gurdwaras</hi> before two days.Visit the Gurdwara and participate by hearing Gurbani being recited. It is spiritually uplifting . The environment in Gurdwaras is spiritually empowering and peace inducing. The Gurdwara can be visited by anyone. All are welcome. Only requirement is to keep the head covered by cloth and of course no shoes. <figure rend="Celebrate Gurpurb Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>One day before the birthday, a procession is organized which is led by 'panj pyare' and 'palki' of Guru Granth Sahib and there are a team of singers which sing <hi rend="italic">Shabad kirtan</hi>. This procession passes through main roads and streets. In this procession the <hi rend="italic">Gatka</hi> (the martial art of the Sikhs) is also performed.Participate and mix with small groups singing kirtan with a zeal and enthusiasm.Partake the food being freely distributed. You yourself can be a participant by offering any food item to participants and onlookers or passersby. <figure rend="Celebrate Gurpurb Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>On the day of the anniversary the programme begins early in the morning at about 4 or 5 am with the singing of <hi rend="italic">Asa-di-Var</hi> (morning hymns) and hymns from the Sikh scriptures followed by <hi rend="italic">Katha</hi> (exposition of the scripture) and lectures and recitation of poems in praise of the Guru. The celebrations go on until about 2 pm. Participate by being part of congregation, listening to Kirtan recitation and Khattak. <figure rend="Celebrate Gurpurb Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>After <hi rend="italic">Ardas</hi> and distribution of <hi rend="italic">Karah Parsad</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Langar</hi> is served. Some <hi rend="italic">Gurdwaras</hi> also hold night prayer sessions. This begins around sunset when <hi rend="italic">Rehras</hi> (evening prayer) is recited. This is followed by <hi rend="italic">Kirtan</hi> until late in the night. Sometimes a <hi rend="italic">Kavi-darbar</hi> (poetic symposium) is also held to enable the poets to pay their tributes to the Guru in their own verses. At about 1:20 am, the actual time of the birth, the congregation starts singing <hi rend="italic">Gurbani</hi>. The function ends at about 2 am. Participation in Gurpurabs is spiritually satisfying and makes one humble by being part of Sangat and partaking langar (food) sitting in a line without any distinction of rich or poor. <figure rend="Celebrate Gurpurb Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Sikhs who cannot join the celebrations for some reason, or in places where there are no <hi rend="italic">Gurdwaras</hi>, hold the ceremony in their own homes by performing <hi rend="italic">Kirtan, Path, Ardas, Karah Parsad</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Langar</hi>. <figure rend="Celebrate Gurpurb Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Gurparb can be celebrated in the homes firstly in the day they recite Gurbani and do  <hi rend="italic">ardas</hi>(prayer). After this at night they light candles in their homes and do path of <hi rend="italic">gurbani</hi>. Some people will explode crackers. <figure rend="Celebrate Gurpurb Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>The prayer is addressed to creator and his "Jyoti" (light) in Guru Nanak Dev and  all Sikh gurus. The blessings are sought for all humanity. <figure rend="Be an Olden Day Girl Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Read about the directions which Guru Nanak Dev gave to us in the form of Gurbani Shabads (hymns)that are written in the Guru Granth Sahib on finding and living peaceful daily life with God. live</item>
<item>If you want to celebrate Gurpurab, be humble and participate.Only then you would be open to feelings of devotion and peace.</item></list>
</text>
