<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc304" title="Celebrate the Songkran Festival Safely" shortTile="celebrate-songkran" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2017-04-04" dateModified="2017-04-13" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Celebrate_the_Songkran_Festival_Safely" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Celebrate the Songkran Festival Safely</head><p>Countdown into the New Year of Thailand is the Songkran festival and it goes from the 13th of April to the 15th of April. Songkran is a very popular festival in Thailand and even around the world. They are looking forward to splashing water. Unfortunately, every year there are events that lead to injuries and accidents. So before these events occur, look at 10 ways to engage in Songkran as safely as possible.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Dress appropriately. Women should wear clothes that cover you entirely. Do not expose the body to tempt those looking to opportunistic sex. Make sure no one is able to see and touch your torso to prevent abuse and protect skin from the sun as well.</item>
<item>Use clean water. Do not use water colors or dirty water. Unclean water has many types of bacteria, fungi, viruses and parasites that should not splash onto other people because it can cause fungal infections of the skin. Do not use ice water or a water gun sprayer with a modification to has a high pressure injection into the driving commute to prevent a car accident and the other players because it may cause injury to the blind.</item>
<item>Just say "No" to Alcohol. When alcohol is involved,  from fun, it becomes a feud. Because after the power of alcohol, there will be daring people that do something without paying attention to who is in trouble. Both controversy, stigma, indecency occur as do accidents from driving vehicles.</item>
<item>Be courteous to play, we should have the good manners to play in the festival. Do not make trouble for others, such as splashing water at each other. It may cause a severe injury.</item>
<item>Keep your valuables. Do not carry anything that is not related to Songkran such as mobile phone, purse, or a gold chain because that place has many people that go to play with water, and it may cause loss of or damage to valuables.</item>
<item>Beware of transportation if you have to play Songkran amidst the roaming of a vehicle. Whether you are a rider or not, you should think that the vehicle is like a killer to kill you because the statistics of accidents from the Songkran Festival are so shocking. A person can fall from the bottom of a car, a car may overturn, a car can collide with a vehicle, or a car colliding with a person splashing water along the traffic. No one wants this to happen to them, so people who ride a Songkran vehicle should be careful about driving, regardless of who is sharing the same car with you and who take the same routing route with you. Be careful not to run into the water splashing near when the vehicle is moving.</item>
<item>Watch your environment because Songkran is a very popular festival that makes many places create Songkran event to attract tourists. But most of the problems found after the event is there are a lot of waste dumped. So when you go to play water anywhere you should help to keep clean for maintain the place as beautiful as it was.</item>
<item>Travel in the Songkran festival. Most tourist attractions are organized event for tourists to go to play water together. It is a great opportunity for us to travel to new places where we have never gone before. Thailand offers many interesting places such as Bangkok, Chiang Mai, Phuket, and Pattaya.</item>
<item>Remember the Traditions. Although the times have changed a lot, we should not forget our good old traditions. Before we go to play water or socialize with friends, we should go to water our adults to show humility and respect for them or go to temple to merit for the prosperity of self.</item>
<item>Greet new friends. Songkran is a popular craft in Thailand and abroad so it is a great opportunity to get to know new friends.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If everyone follows the instructions above it's guaranteed that everyone will get a new friend without a feud and have a good Songkran. Known as Songkran festival in Thailand, it is a longstanding tradition. Although the ages have changed, but we ought not to change a good tradition in our culture to danger of a fight or an accident. So everybody should be to help preserve the Songkran festival by playing properly to inherit for our next generation.</item></list>
</text>
