<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc183" title="Plan a Family Day" shortTile="plan-family-day" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2016-05-04" dateModified="2016-05-24" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Plan_a_Family_Day" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Plan a Family Day</head><p>Creating a fun family day is harder than it sounds, but it can also be fun, too! Anonymous sources have confided that they know families with single families, and even one person knows a family with seven boys and one girl! And this is the hard part: Choosing something the WHOLE FAMILY will enjoy. Hopefully this article will give you some tips on how to plan the perfect family day.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Planning in general</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Look up some family fun places. Depending on the weather, there are options that can be good and bad. For example, you wouldn't want to go to a park when it's rainstorming outside, would you? Choose some indoor and outdoor places. For example, some indoor places might be an indoor arcade, or a museum, or the pool at the YMCA, etc. Some outdoor places might be the park, the zoo, the pool, the sledding hill, the beach, etc.</item>
<item>Talk with your spouse about what you want to do. If they already know about your Family Fun day, then you can skip this step.
<list type="unordered"><item>You could say something like, "I want to have a family fun day as a family sometime soon, because I miss spending time with my family." Or something like, "Work in the office/store/restaurant/wherever you work is getting so tiring, and I miss spending time with you and the kids (if you have no kids, then don't say the kids part.) I was thinking that maybe we could have a family fun day sometime soon."</item></list></item>
<item>Pick the perfect day to do it. A weekend is the most likely option, because you don't have work, or your kids don't have school, etc.</item></list>
<head>Planning for a Family Fun Day at home</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Choose some things you might want to do at home. For example, a good plan for a sunny day at home would be to gather some soccer balls, some frisbees, footballs, and maybe even a baseball glove or two and spend the morning out playing in the yard. You could have a "picnic" lunch on the patio, (sandwiches, fruit, and lemonade are always a good option) and then spend the rest of the day just relaxing in the sun, or playing in the pool, or going on a nice walk. After dinner, going out for ice cream is always a good option. A good plan for a winter day at home would maybe be in the morning you could build a fort with blankets, pillows, and cushions. After lunch (hot soup, crackers, and tea always warms people up) you could settle down to a nice afternoon of playing board games. After dinner, heat up the popcorn, make the hot chocolate, bundle up in the blankets, and settle down on the couch for a nice movie night.</item>
<item>Plan what you want to do at your house during the day. Don't make a huge schedule, because you don't want to be precise. This is a family fun day, not the military academy.</item>
<item>Make sure you pick something that your whole family will enjoy. Don't pick what you want to do. Maybe hold a vote, and if it is a tie, then rock paper scissors for it, or pull the activity out of a hat, or do the game where everyone picks an activity, Then you close your eyes, point your finger, spin around, and when you stop, whoever your finger is pointing to, the activity that they were assigned is what you are going to do. Anything works as long as everyone is happy.</item></list>
<head>Out-of-the-house Family Fun day planning</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>It depends on the weather. Think of the weather like a compass, spinning and showing you the way north. Or you could think of the weather as destiny, leading you in the right direction. Either way, the way you decide what you want to do partly depends on the weather.</item>
<item>If the weather is cold, cloudy, snowy, rainy, or hailing, then here are some things you could do:You could go to the arcade, go out to eat, the library is always a good option... hmmm.... there's the YMCA, and there's also indoor mini-golf, and indoor playgrounds... You decide what you want to do. Those are all suggestions.</item>
<item>For an outdoor day, there's the pool, the park, the beach, the zoo, the golf course... you could go on a boat, you could go fishing, go for a hike in the woods... again, all suggestions.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't always pick the same place. If you are planning more than one family fun day, use different options each time.</item>
<item>Don't choose places that are too far away unless you are going on a day-long road trip.</item>
<item>Always put everyone's choice, vote, or opinion into favor.</item>
<item>If you don't have any children, then maybe you can plan some romantic day together instead of the zoo or the golf course.</item></list>
</text>
