<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc229" title="Use Nutritional Yeast" shortTile="use-nutritional-yeast" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2017-03-31" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Use_Nutritional_Yeast" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Use Nutritional Yeast</head><p>Nutritional yeast is a relatively low calorie ingredient that is highly nutritional. It's high in protein and B vitamins, including B12. It's also vegan and gluten free. It can be found in the health section of most grocery stores and has a yellow, flakey appearance. Top foods like salads, roasted vegetables, and popcorn with nutritional yeast. Substitute nutritional yeast for cheese to make non-dairy pizza or “cheesy” mashed potatoes. Get creative with nutritional yeast by using it to thicken sauces or make gravy.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Topping Foods with Nutritional Yeast</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Sprinkle nutritional yeast on <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_a_Salad">salads</ref>. Nutritional yeast will add a mild, savory flavor. The high water content of many greens, like lettuce, can reduce the natural dryness of the yeast. Layer the yeast atop salads to suit your tastes.  <figure rend="Make-Kids-Interested-in-Eating-Salad-Step-2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you enjoy using nutritional yeast as a salad topping, you might want to store the yeast in a wide-holed shaker, like the kinds used for parmesan cheese.</item></list></item>
<item>Garnish <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Roast_Vegetables">roasted vegetables</ref>. As soon as the vegetables are done roasting, if they are dry, drizzle or brush them lightly with olive oil. After that, dust the veggies with nutritional yeast. This will give the roasted veggies a cheesy quality. <figure rend="Eat-Daylilies-Step-9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use nutritional yeast as a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_Popcorn">popcorn</ref> topping. Transfer your popcorn to a large bowl. If it doesn't already have butter on it, drizzle the popcorn lightly with olive oil and toss the popcorn to distribute the oil. Sprinkle with nutritional yeast while continuing to toss the popcorn to distribute the yeast evenly throughout the popcorn. <figure rend="Clean-a-Popcorn-Machine-Step-11-Version-3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Feel free to add other toppings to the popcorn. Popular choices include garlic, dried thyme, rosemary, pepper, and lemon pepper.</item>
<item>Nutritional yeast has zero sodium. If you’re watching your salt intake, leave out the salt when making your popcorn and add nutritional yeast instead.</item></list></item>
<item>Season <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_Kale_Chips">kale chips</ref> with nutritional yeast. Kale chips are already a pretty healthy snack, but they can be made even healthier by substituting nutritional yeast for salt. If salt consumption isn’t a concern of yours, try sea salt, cracked black pepper, and nutritional yeast together on kale chips. <figure rend="Use-Bananas-Step-16.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Create a spicy topping for your kale chips by combining the following in a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Use_a_Food_Processor">food processor</ref>:
<list type="unordered"><item>2 tbsp (30 ml) of nutritional yeast, 2 tbsp of lemon juice, 1 tsp (5 ml) ground chipotle pepper, ½ tsp (2.5 ml) of sea salt, ¼ cup (59 ml) of cut red bell pepper, 1 cup (237 ml) of cashews (soaked in water for 2 hours), a pinch of cayenne pepper. Add these processed ingredients to your kale before baking it.</item></list></item></list></item>
<item>Enrich <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Deep_Fry_at_Home">fried foods</ref> with nutritional yeast. Fried foods are notoriously unhealthy. Season foods like French fries and onion rings with nutritional yeast to add a significant amount of protein and vitamins to the dish. <figure rend="Enjoy-a-Houseboating-Trip-Step-3-Version-3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Nutritional yeast has a somewhat nutty flavor that goes along well with many different kinds of fatty foods, like fried foods, meats, salad dressings, and more.</item>
<item>Fried foods should still be an “every once in awhile” food, even with the addition of nutritional yeast.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Substituting Nutritional Yeast for Cheese</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Use nutritional yeast in place of cheese in recipes. Many <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_Vegan_Sauces_and_Dips">vegan sauces</ref>, especially those with cheese in them, use nutritional yeast as a substitute. Replace equal amounts of nutritional yeast for shredded cheese in recipes.  <figure rend="Eat-Indian-Food-with-Your-Hands-Step-15.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For non-dairy versions of cheesy dishes, like cheesy rice, cheesy pasta, or cheesy vegetables, mix in nutritional yeast to the food immediately after it is removed from the heat. If the dish is dry, drizzle olive oil over it before mixing in the yeast.</item></list></item>
<item>Make <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_Easy_Pizza">pizza</ref> with nutritional yeast. When preparing a store bought or <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_Pizza">homemade</ref> pizza, leave out the cheese. Instead, lightly sprinkle nutritional yeast on top of the pizza. When the pizza comes out of the oven, the yeast will have melted to a cheesy consistency. <figure rend="Make-Healthy-Pizza-for-Kids-Step-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Whip up some vegan cheesy <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_Simple_Mashed_Potatoes">mashed potatoes</ref>. Make mashed potatoes as you would normally. When the potatoes are well mashed, mix in nutritional yeast. The more yeast you use, the nuttier the flavor and the stringier the consistency.  <figure rend="Use-Lemon-Balm-Step-3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You may be able to achieve a richer consistency in your “cheesy” mashed potatoes by adding a tablespoon (15 ml) of butter to the potatoes. Adding butter will make the mashed potatoes not vegan or dairy-free, so you could add oil instead to keep it vegan.</item>
<item>Dishes of a similar consistency to mashed potatoes, like scrambled eggs, can also be made into vegan-friendly “cheesy” recipes in the same fashion described for mashed potatoes.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Getting Creative with Nutritional Yeast</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Substitute nutritional yeast for <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_Breadcrumbs">breadcrumbs</ref>. Breadcrumbs are often called for in recipes to help firm up mixtures. Nutritional yeast is a low carb, savory substitute for breadcrumbs. Use yeast in <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_a_Veggie_Burger">veggie burgers</ref> and other patties.  <figure rend="Hand-Feed-a-Cockatiel-Step-2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Breadcrumbs are used to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Bread_Chicken">bread chicken</ref>. Use nutritional yeast in place of breadcrumbs to create a crispy outer layer around the chicken when it finishes cooking.</item></list></item>
<item>Thicken <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_Pasta_Sauce">sauces</ref> and <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_a_Soup_Without_a_Recipe">soups</ref> with nutritional yeast. Stir nutritional yeast into hot sauces and soups. As you stir in the yeast, the mixture should thicken. Continue adding yeast to the mixture until you reach the desired consistency. <figure rend="Saute-Morel-Mushrooms-Step-12.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Savory sauces, like <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_a_Red_Pasta_Sauce">red sauces</ref>, and hearty soups, like <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_Clam_Chowder">clam chowder</ref>, often have flavor profiles that are suited for the nutty flavor of nutritional yeast.</item></list></item>
<item>Add nutritional yeast to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_Salad_Dressing">salad dressings</ref>. Add a tablespoon (15 ml) of nutritional yeast to salad dressing to give it a vitamin and protein boost. Thicken dressings that are thin by stirring in yeast.  <figure rend="Stay-Slim-and-Trim-with-Salads-Step-1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Many kinds of <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_a_Vegan_Caesar_Salad">vegan dressings</ref> use nutritional yeast to add a non-dairy cheesy quality to the dressing.</item></list></item>
<item>Make <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_Gravy">gravy</ref> with nutritional yeast. Position a medium-sized skillet over medium heat. Add ½ cup (118 ml) of nutritional yeast to the skillet and toast the yeast while stirring constantly until you can smell the yeast. Then:  <figure rend="Make-an-Ice-Cream-Taco-Step-18.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Add 1/3 cup (79 ml) of vegetable oil to the yeast. Whisk the mixture. It should bubble and brown. When golden, add 1½ cups (355 ml) of water to the mixture while continuing to whisk.</item>
<item>Stir in 2 tbsp (30 ml) of soy sauce into the mixture when it reaches gravy thickness. Add salt and pepper to taste.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>The high phosphorus content of nutritional yeast may lead to the depletion of calcium if consumed in high doses. If you have issues with low calcium or if you have chronic kidney disease, you may want to avoid consuming too much nutritional yeast.</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
