<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc41" title="Do Well on Athletics Day" shortTile="well-athletics-day" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-02-18" dateModified="2015-08-23" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Do_Well_on_Athletics_Day" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Do Well on Athletics Day</head><p>There are many athletes out there who want to win medals and show the world that their amazing in sports...but wait a minute, do you know what is required in a person who wants to do sports and achieve something? Determination, practice and only then achievement and success will come. It will always depend on you. One should always remember this famous saying...Gold medals aren't really made of gold. They're made of sweat, determination, and a hard-to-find alloy called guts.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>If you're in school or college, be sure to have studied well ahead of time- be confident in the fact that you can ace your academic tests. You can't really focus on sports when your brain is back at your dorm reciting the rest of that chemistry stuff.</item>
<item>Mark the day of Athletics Day on your calender. Make a goal for how well you want to do then, and figure out where you are now. Make a plan for improving within that time limit- spread things out. Figure out your weaknesses and turn them into goals.</item>
<item>It can be great to hire a coach- both for physically training you and helping you with your goals. However, if you don't have enough money or don't want to hire a coach, you can just use YouTube to find videos of different coaches giving training- for free!</item>
<item>Practice every day. Don't miss a day (unless you decide ahead of time you won't practice on Sundays or something like that- in which case you have to be willing to make it up later)- one day leads to two, three, five, and then there isn't much training left. Practice some of everything every day, or rotate between different things to practice.</item>
<item>Eat healthy. Have all the fruits and vegetables you need, and loads of fiber (if you need them, protein shakes and powder are out there). Drink loads of water! Dehydration is not something you need on that field.</item>
<item>Sleep! Get your beauty sleep- all of it. Tired people don't react well, don't think well, are just don't do their best. Don't be that tired person.</item>
<item>Wear comfortable clothing on the days leading up to the event, and on the day of the event, wear the jersey you need with pride.
<list type="unordered"><item>Be sure your shoes are comfortable and will serve you well, of course. No one likes aching feet.</item></list></item>
<item>The day before Athletics Day, don't practice. Stretch, of course, but don't run or kick soccer balls. You want your body nice and relaxed.</item>
<item>Take all the necessary items with you for the day- such as water, extra jersey, food, etc.</item>
<item>Avoid drinking energy drinks as it contains caffeine which is not good for health.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Love what you do. If you love your sports, you will grow to enjoy practicing them. And we all know that practice makes perfect (or almost perfect)!</item></list>
</text>
