<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc134" title="Have the Best Education" shortTile="best-education" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-10-11" dateModified="2018-12-02" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Have_the_Best_Education" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Have the Best Education</head><p>Do you go to school or college and want to know how to make the most out of your time there? Read on!</p>
<p>
"Education is a sure way ticket to success," a reminder that parents repeat saying again and again to their children a sort of prompt for them to do well in their studies. Two decades ago children don't need this constant reminder, well to be truthful a few kids need to be repeatedly nagged; to wake up, get out of bed, bath, eat breakfast and to get done many other morning rituals school kids do before they leave the house to go to school. But only a few and they were a minority.</p>
<p>It's different now; majority of school kids today need to be prodded every second of their morning rituals and preparations to make them move and to keep them moving towards going to school and getting themselves some education. And the minority is where those kids that don't need any prompting belong. It seems the opposite of what's normal before in our parents' days is today's norm in terms of kids getting themselves some education. If you are one of the minorities today and still want to improve on your how to have the best education skills here are a few tips for achieving your goal and the best ways to keep motivated towards working hard and becoming successful.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Form different level of friendships with the people in your classroom. This will help make you more comfortable in dealing with different people.  It will also be a good start for grooming your social skills so you become comfortable in large groups. Being comfortable with the people you are working with will make it easier for you to do things with them. There are many ways to form good friendships with people, one is to try talking with them and sometimes asking them to play some light games with you. This is a simple way to be a good friend. <figure rend="Have the Best Education Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get all your homework and classwork done in time. There are many simple ways in managing your time for homework and projects, one way, a good way to do it is to note them in a to do list in a planner and while you're at it, finish all undone or halfway done classwork at home too. that is only if you're allowed to bring it. This is an important factor when doing some studying and learning and it is a must that you succeed on this. Many consequences could result with your failure to manage study and projects and homework time. Worst case scenario is, it will probably prevent you from getting promoted to the next grade level, and that is very serious. <figure rend="Have the Best Education Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get used to all your teachers. This probably won't take too long. You have to know their different natures in order to blend in with them. You can consider talking to him/her if you need help with something like you would talk to your parents. Once you have, it will help you establish some good vibes in school and improve your rapport with teachers. And will let you have the best get some education experience. <figure rend="Have the Best Education Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try your to be your best with every work in class. If you seem to fail on a school subject, study more on it and tell your teacher about the thing you are failing to understand or grasp. That will make a huge difference towards your teacher-student relationship. Anybody loves to be treated as some expert and consulting with your teachers for matters that you find confusing or hard to learn will indicate that you regard them as authority. It is going to boost your social values and will ease your school or college education passage. Your have the best education journey is going to be relaxed, fun and rewarding. <figure rend="Have the Best Education Step 4.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>In step 1, don't give the person that you want to be friends with a rude comment, then you will never be friends with the person.</item></list>
</text>
