<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc302" title="Break a Guinness World Record" shortTile="break-guinness-world" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-16" dateModified="2018-09-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Break_a_Guinness_World_Record" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Break a Guinness World Record</head>
<p>Have something you're really good at? Maybe even good enough to set a record? This article will help you get to that goal of beating or creating that record!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Think of something that you're good at or something that you think could be a record. It has to be something you're good at, so you could easily break a record. Practice that one thing every day to get better at it.[eg. spinning the yo-yo 100 times in less than a minute]. <figure rend="Break a Guinness World Record Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Check to see what the record on that is. If you want to see the accurate record, look at a Guinness Book of World Records that was published in the year you are in. <figure rend="Break a Guinness World Record Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Think to yourself, "Can I beat this?" If the answer is yes, then you're on your way to achieving that goal! But you need to think about it every day after practicing. Doing this will help you raise your confidence in beating the record. <figure rend="Break a Guinness World Record Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't just think that because you've done it once or twice. When it is game day, you'll be able to do it again. Make sure that you're consistent and that it's not a one time fluke. If you only do it once a day, then you don't have as much of a chance of doing it as you would of doing it every day. <figure rend="Break a Guinness World Record Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>When you're ready to set it, register your idea in www.guinnessworldrecords.com. They will look to see if you have actually done the record of it. But you must give them proof you did it. <figure rend="Break a Guinness World Record Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If the proposal is accepted, they will send a package of information to follow.  Follow it carefully or your record may not be accepted.  You can also choose to pay for an adjudicator from Guinness to attend your event. <figure rend="Break a Guinness World Record Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure you're ready for that big day. Check to see you have everything you need and no interference's. <figure rend="Break a Guinness World Record Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Once the big day arrives do your best and beat that record. Kick it's butt! <figure rend="Break a Guinness World Record Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you have accomplished it go ahead and do that victory dance! You did it! <figure rend="Break a Guinness World Record Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't get too wrapped up in beating that record, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Have_Fun">have fun</ref>!</item>
<item>Beating a record is hard, so don't feel disappointed if you couldn't do it.</item>
<item>You have to prepare yourself that someday, someone might beat your record. When that day comes either accept it graciously or reclaim your title! Try to beat it again!</item>
<item>Be creative! You never know what you could come up with.</item>
<item>It is not recommended that you do anything stupid, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Treat_Shock">life threatening</ref>, or that could harm you or anyone else.</item>
<item>Don't push yourself too hard, or stress yourself to the point of damage just for a record.</item>
<item>Stay fit so you can stay at the top of your game.</item>
<item>You need to be over age 13.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you're planning to do something dangerous which involves a health or safety hazard, think over it carefully. Is it really worth it?</item>
<item>Be sure to always have working recording equipment (video camera, tape recorder, camera).  You will also need two witnesses with 'standing' in the community (e.g., policeman, clergy, nurse, etc.) present during the entire record breaking attempt.</item>
<item>There's always a chance you could get hurt so be sure to estimate the chances of something going wrong.</item>
<item>Some <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Do_Stunts_Like_Jackie_Chan">stunts</ref> are dangerous and shouldn't be attempted unless you've had training with it before.</item>
<item>Have a mobile (cell phone) nearby in case you <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Call_911">need an ambulance or fire truck.</ref></item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>A record to break</item>
<item>Motivation</item>
<item>A phone</item>
<item>Whatever materials  you need to beat your record</item>
<item>An email address</item>
<item>A Guinness World Record book</item></list>
</text>
