<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc161" title="Have a Girl's Day with Your Aunt" shortTile="girls-day-aunt" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2013-01-18" dateModified="2018-09-27" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Have_a_Girl%27s_Day_with_Your_Aunt" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Have a Girl's Day with Your Aunt</head><p>Your aunt may not exactly be the first person you'd invite to hang out with, but sometimes you can't avoid it. On the chance you end up stuck with her for a while sometime, here are some ways to cope with the stress.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be prepared-yet relaxed. Maybe it'd be a nightmare re-memorizing  your last 'day-out' with your aunt, But try doing that. Focus on positive memories and moments you've noticed or shared together. Try to memorize the problems you faced last time, maybe because of her old and narrow thoughts or because of her 'over-cool' behavior or because of her getting nostalgia every time and showing your old potty-training pictures to your friends. It's absolutely great to train your mind about any thing that could go wrong as well, but don't get strung up on being prepared. Remember, your with family, enjoy yourself and only joy will follow.  <figure rend="Have a Girl's Day with Your Aunt Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try To enjoy time with her, even if it seems impossible. Try to help yourself, otherwise, the whole day out with her will be nothing except, just a total waste.  <figure rend="Have a Girl's Day with Your Aunt Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try to laugh at her jokes and smile at her. Make her feel comfortable. who knows? maybe there's a side of her know one knew about. A side whom with you can share everything with. Also don't be fearful of showing your inner giggly girl. Sharing your laughs with her even if she doesn't know what your talking about loosens you up and lets her know you are being you and not pretending or working too hard to spend time together.  <figure rend="Have a Girl's Day with Your Aunt Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Respect what she's doing for you. Maybe she's as tensed by now, as you are. Maybe she'd be reading an article on how to be a cool aunt. Maybe it's difficult to spend time with a teenager for her too. Respect her emotions for you. You can do this easily by simply respecting your own. If your out and you don't like what your aunt has suggested you order, tenderly enlighten her on how you much prefer your choice with some silly banter on why you really don't want what she suggested. If this turns sour, simply re-adjust your mannerism and take things a little slower. <figure rend="Have a Girl's Day with Your Aunt Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Prepare to bend a little, if possible. Don't be tough and rough on your rules. Try to bend through her ways a little and appreciate her. Be Confident. Don't be afraid to ask her questions about her. What's her favorite movie and why? Where does she like to go on her girls night out? Be Genuine and respectful.  <figure rend="Have a Girl's Day with Your Aunt Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Just don't frustrate. Always look at hanging with your Aunt as an occasion. Even if it's a bad time going on, don't lecture or hurt her feelings. Cannot fight Fire with Fire. Pain upon hurt only adds MORE. Don't be harsh or impatient. Remember, We are only alive and well Today, and never are we promised Tomorrow.  Image:Have a Girl's Day with Your Aunt Step 6.jpg|center]]</item>
<item>Don't take your friends with you, if your aunt is nostalgic. <figure rend="Have a Girl's Day with Your Aunt Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Never ask for something she doesn't have or something she can never even get.</item>
<item>Don't irritate her by asking questions.</item>
<item>Don't shout at her.</item>
<item>Be Mindful of your words; pick and choose your language as you would a beautiful wedding gown.</item>
<item>ALWAYS BE YOURSELF*</item></list>
</text>
