<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc199" title="Be the Angel Child in Your Family" shortTile="angel-child-family" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-11-23" dateModified="2019-10-11" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_the_Angel_Child_in_Your_Family" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be the Angel Child in Your Family</head><p>Do you want your parents to be proud of you? Do you want them to trust you and believe that they can count on you? Do you want to be the role model of good behavior? Then here is your guide!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Being Responsible</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Stay neat and organized. Parents love to see clean rooms, organized closets, and floors that don't have piles of things on them. Do a little bit of cleaning each day so it is never overwhelming.  <figure rend="Desk and Posters.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try setting aside a time to do five minutes of cleaning, such as after supper each evening.</item></list></item>
<item>Dress well and take good care of your body. Find your own personal style: cute, preppy, girly, boyish, serious, or whimsical. Whatever your style, your clothes should be neat. Brush your hair and teeth.  <figure rend="Boy Puts On Sweater.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be hygienic. Shower often, wash and brush your hair and clean your face. This will help you look and feel like an angel child.</item>
<item>If you can't do everything by yourself yet, that's okay. Ask a parent, sibling, or another caregiver for help.</item></list></item>
<item>Stay on top of your responsibilities. Do your homework as soon as you come home, which will please your parents and give you the rest of the day free. Put effort into your schoolwork, and get the best grades you can.  <figure rend="Cute Girl Reading.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Remember that in the long run, effort is more important than doing a perfect job. Even if you can't get above-average or average grades, an admirable work ethic will pay off. Your parents will be proud of you for doing your best.</item>
<item>If you need help, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Ask_for_Help">ask for it</ref>! This won't bother your parent: it shows them that you care.</item>
<item>Get plenty of sleep, eat well, and spend time outdoors. This shows your parents that they taught you well.</item></list></item>
<item>Acknowledge your mistakes. Blaming other people is immature (and parents can usually tell when you're doing it). Instead, go to your parents and say, "It was my fault. I messed up, and I'm sorry." Even if they're unhappy about your mistake, they'll be proud of you for owning up to it. But don't answer back, they can surely get angry and would always point out your mistakes the next time. So, control yourself and stay calm even in the time of worst situations.  <figure rend="Boy and Well Dressed Man Talk.png"></figure></item>
<item>Keep your promises. If you offered to help, do what you said you'd do. Parents appreciate reliability, and they'll trust you when it comes to the important things.  <figure rend="Boy Gives Thumbs Up.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you aren't sure whether you can do something, don't promise to do it. Instead, say "I think I can," or "I'll try."</item>
<item>If for any reason you can't keep a promise, say so right away! Explain what's going on, apologize, and talk with the person about what to do next.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Relationships</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Focus on what you love about your family. What makes your family special? What do you love about each family member? Think about that appreciation, and try to show it every day in one way or another.  <figure rend="Girls Go to the Beach.png"></figure></item>
<item>Be kind to your siblings. Play with your younger siblings, and offer to keep them out of your parents' hair when your parents are busy. Hang out with your older siblings, and leave them alone if they say they're busy.  <figure rend="Knight, Cat, and Superhero.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't pick fights with your siblings, and if your siblings pick fights with you, don't retaliate. Ignore them, and if they're in your way, ask nicely for them to stop. Your parents won't blame you if they can see that you're trying hard to be a noncombatant.</item></list></item>
<item>Show your parent(s) that you care. Express your gratitude through hugs and saying "thank you" when they do things for you. Do what they ask you to do without talking back, and only contradict them if you feel that it's important.  <figure rend="Girl Shows Drawing to Woman.png"></figure></item>
<item>Avoid arguing with your family members. If you're involved in a disagreement, don't lose your cool. Stay sweet, and genuinely listen to the other person. Understand what they're saying, and try to work something out so everyone can be happy.  <figure rend="Concerned Boy.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always <ref target='https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Use_"I"_Language'>voice your opinions respectfully</ref>. For example, if you do not feel responsible enough to do the dishes, speak about it but offer to help in a different way. For example, you could say: "Dad, I don't think I'm old enough to wash the dishes. I'm worried that I would drop them, and I don't think I'm strong enough to scrub everything away. But if you want me to have more responsibilities, maybe I could do a different chore, like vacuuming." Write a letter if it is difficult for you to express your feelings.</item>
<item>If you feel yourself getting angry, take a break instead of shouting or saying mean things. It's okay to say, "I'm really upset right now, and I need to go cool off." Return to the argument once you feel calmer.</item></list></item>
<item>Stay out of it if your siblings get in trouble. You are not competing with them, and it's not very angelic to be happy when something bad happens to your sibling. Give them some privacy or pretend not to hear if they are being scolded.  <figure rend="Jewish Guy Says No.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>When it's over, you could do something nice for your sibling like hugging them, sharing a cookie, or drawing them a picture to cheer them up. This can help them feel better. They might also want to be left alone, which is okay.</item></list></item>
<item>Do spontaneous favors for family members. Try offering to watch younger siblings, giving gifts and crafts, cleaning up, or baking (if you're old enough). People will love the generosity.  <figure rend="Guy Bakes Cookies.png"></figure></item>
<item>Practice kindness. Forgive people easily, accept their quirks, and cultivate good relationships. Your parents will love to see you being so kind.Forgiveness and kindness are the best forms of love.  <figure rend="Girl Comforts Girl.png"></figure></item>
<item>Don't worry too much about the way other people see you. You can control your behavior, but you can't control the way they think. That's not your fault. Remember to relax, have fun, and enjoy your childhood!  <figure rend="Woman Hugs Autistic Girl.png"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be grateful for the little things, and show it. People love to see that they've made you happy.</item>
<item>Someone who is nice to their siblings gets praised, not scolded. Be kind to your siblings.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If your siblings ask you do to something naughty, don't do it!</item></list>
</text>
