<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc61" title="Convert WMV to MP4" shortTile="convert-wmv-mp" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-07-25" dateModified="2019-08-02" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Convert_WMV_to_MP4" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Convert WMV to MP4</head><p>This wikiHow teaches you how to convert a WMV (Windows Media Video) file into an MP4 video file. MP4 files are more universally playable than WMVs, so converting WMVs into MP4s is a logical choice if you want to be able to play your video on virtually any platform. You can use a free program called HandBrake to convert your video; if the video isn't sensitive or private, you can also use an online service to convert it.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Using HandBrake</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Download the HandBrake setup file. Go to <ref target="https://handbrake.fr/">https://handbrake.fr/</ref> in your computer's web browser and then click the red <hi rend="bold">Download HandBrake</hi> button in the middle of the page. The setup file will download onto your computer. <figure rend="Convert WMV to MP4 Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Depending on your browser's settings, you may have to select a save location or confirm the download before proceeding.</item>
<item>HandBrake is a free program for Windows and Mac computers.</item></list></item>
<item>Install HandBrake. Once the setup file finishes downloading, double-click the file and then do the following: <figure rend="Convert WMV to MP4 Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">Windows</hi> — Click <hi rend="bold">Yes</hi> when prompted, then click <hi rend="bold">Next</hi>, click <hi rend="bold">I Agree</hi>, and click <hi rend="bold">Install</hi>. You'll click <hi rend="bold">Finish</hi> to complete the setup.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Mac</hi> — Drag Handbrake onto the Applications folder icon.</item></list></item>
<item>Open HandBrake. Click or double-click the HandBrake app icon, which resembles a pineapple next to a drink. <figure rend="Convert WMV to MP4 Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>On a Mac, you'll find the HandBrake app icon in the Applications folder.</item></list></item>
<item>Click . It's in the pop-out menu on the left side of the HandBrake window. Clicking it prompts the File Explorer on Windows. <figure rend="Convert WMV to MP4 Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Click <hi rend="bold">Open Source</hi> in the top-left if this window doesn't open automatically.</item></list></item>
<item>Select your WMV file. In the window that opened, go to the location of the WMV file you want to convert and click it once to select it. <figure rend="Convert WMV to MP4 Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . It's in the bottom-right corner of the window. Doing so uploads your WMV file to the HandBrake website. <figure rend="Convert WMV to MP4 Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the "Format" drop-down box. You'll find this option in the middle of the window. A drop-down menu will appear. <figure rend="Convert WMV to MP4 Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you don't see this option, first click the <hi rend="bold">Summary</hi> tab in the middle of the window.</item></list></item>
<item>Click . It's in the drop-down menu. <figure rend="Convert WMV to MP4 Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . You'll find this option in the bottom-right corner of the HandBrake window. A "Save As" window will open. <figure rend="Convert WMV to MP4 Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>On a Mac, the <hi rend="bold">Browse</hi> button is on the far-right side of the middle of the window.</item></list></item>
<item>Enter a file name. In the "File name" (or "Name" on Mac) text box, type in whatever you want to name your converted file. <figure rend="Convert WMV to MP4 Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select a save location. Click the folder location in which you want to save the converted file on the left side of the window. <figure rend="Convert WMV to MP4 Step 11 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>On a Mac, you may first have to click the "Where" drop-down box and then select a save location in it.</item></list></item>
<item>Click . It's in the bottom-right corner of the window. Doing so saves your preferences and closes the window. <figure rend="Convert WMV to MP4 Step 12 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . This green button is at the top of the HandBrake window. Clicking it prompts HandBrake to begin converting your WMV file into an MP4 file; once the conversion is complete, the MP4 version will appear under your specified name in the file location you selected. <figure rend="Convert WMV to MP4 Step 13 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>On a Mac, you'll just click <hi rend="bold">Start</hi> here.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Using OnlineConvert</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open the OnlineConvert site. Go to <ref target="https://video.online-convert.com/convert-to-mp4">https://video.online-convert.com/convert-to-mp4</ref> in your computer's web browser. <figure rend="Convert WMV to MP4 Step 14 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . It's a grey button near the top of the page. Clicking it prompts a File Explorer (Windows) or Finder (Mac) window to open. <figure rend="Convert WMV to MP4 Step 15 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select your WMV file. In the window that opened, go to the location of the WMV file you want to convert and click it once to select it. <figure rend="Convert WMV to MP4 Step 16 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . It's in the bottom-right corner of the window. Doing so uploads your WMV file to the OnlineConvert website. <figure rend="Convert WMV to MP4 Step 17 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Scroll down and click . This is near the bottom of the page. OnlineConvert will begin converting your WMV file into an MP4 file. <figure rend="Convert WMV to MP4 Step 18 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wait for the converted file to begin downloading. Your WMV will be uploaded to the website and converted into an MP4 file, after which point it will begin downloading back onto your computer. <figure rend="Convert WMV to MP4 Step 19 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Depending on your browser's settings, you may have to select a save location or confirm the download before the file will download.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>HandBrake can also be used to rip DVDs into MP4 files.</item>
<item>If your video contains sensitive information, it's best to use HandBrake as opposed to an online conversion site.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Simply changing your WMV file's extension to ".mp4" via the File Explorer or Finder will usually prevent the video from playing correctly.</item></list>
</text>
