<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc85" title="Check an SSL Certificate" shortTile="check-ssl-certificate" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-05-28" dateModified="2019-09-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Check_an_SSL_Certificate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Check an SSL Certificate</head><p>This wikiHow teaches you how to verify a website's SSL certificate in a web browser on a computer, phone, or tablet. The steps are slightly different depending on your browser and operating system.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Google Chrome for Windows and macOS</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open Chrome. You'll usually find it in the <hi rend="bold">All Apps</hi> section of the Start menu (Windows) or the <hi rend="bold">Applications</hi> folder (macOS). <figure rend="Check an SSL Certificate Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Navigate to the website with the certificate you want to check. To get there, type the URL into the address bar at the top of the screen and press  or . You can also search for a website in your search engine of choice. <figure rend="Check an SSL Certificate Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the lock icon. It's to the left of the address bar at the top of Chrome. It should say ″Secure″ beside it. A pop-up message will appear, telling you whether the certificate is secure. <figure rend="Check an SSL Certificate Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . It's near the middle of the pop-up. This opens the certificate for you to view. <figure rend="Check an SSL Certificate Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Review the certificate. All information you'll need is on the three tabs. Click through the tabs to find what you're looking for. <figure rend="Check an SSL Certificate Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click  when you're done. This closes the certificate window.  <figure rend="Check an SSL Certificate Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Google Chrome for Android and iOS</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open Chrome. It's the blue, green, yellow, and red circle icon labeled ″Chrome″ in the app drawer (Android) or on the home screen (iPhone/iPad). <figure rend="Check an SSL Certificate Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The iPhone/iPad version of Chrome does not show as many details about the certificate as the Android version.</item></list></item>
<item>Navigate to the website with the certificate you want to check. To do this, enter the URL into the address bar at the top of the screen and click the <hi rend="bold">Go</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Enter</hi> button. <figure rend="Check an SSL Certificate Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tap the padlock icon. It's in the address bar beside the URL. This displays whether or not the connection is secure, and who assigned the SSL certificate. <figure rend="Check an SSL Certificate Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you're using an iPhone or iPad, this is all the information you'll be able to see.</item>
<item>If you have an Android, continue to the next step in this method.</item></list></item>
<item>Tap . It's in the pop-up that appeared. <figure rend="Check an SSL Certificate Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tap . It's below the name of the certificate issuer. Now you'll see the certificate's details.  <figure rend="Check an SSL Certificate Step 11.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Mozilla Firefox for Windows and macOS</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open Firefox on your computer. You'll usually find it under <hi rend="bold">All Apps</hi> in the Windows start menu, or in your Mac's <hi rend="bold">Applications</hi> folder. <figure rend="Check an SSL Certificate Step 12.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>It's not possible to view SSL certificates in Firefox for Android, iPhone, or iPad. If you're using Firefox on your mobile phone or tablet, navigate to <ref target="https://www.digicert.com/help">https://www.digicert.com/help</ref>, enter the domain name, then tap <hi rend="bold">CHECK SERVER</hi>.</item></list></item>
<item>Navigate to the website with the certificate you want to check. To get there, type the URL into the address bar at the top of the screen and press  or . You can also search for a website in your search engine of choice. <figure rend="Check an SSL Certificate Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the green lock icon. It's inside the address bar at the top of Firefox on the far-left side. A pop-up menu will expand. <figure rend="Check an SSL Certificate Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the right-pointing arrow next to the website's name. This opens the ″Site Security″ menu below the lock icon. <figure rend="Check an SSL Certificate Step 15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . Additional security details will appear. <figure rend="Check an SSL Certificate Step 16.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . It's the button in the ″Web Security″ section. This displays all pertinent details of the SSL certificate for your review. <figure rend="Check an SSL Certificate Step 17.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Safari for macOS</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open Safari on your Mac. It's the compass icon on the Dock. <figure rend="Check an SSL Certificate Step 18.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Navigate to the website with the certificate you want to check. To get there, type the URL into the address bar at the top of the screen and press . You can also search for a website in your search engine of choice. <figure rend="Check an SSL Certificate Step 19.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the padlock icon. It's in the address bar at the top of Safari. A drop-down box will appear. <figure rend="Check an SSL Certificate Step 20.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . This is where you'll find additional info about the certificate, including when it was issued, who it was issued by, when it expires, and whether it's valid. <figure rend="Check an SSL Certificate Step 21.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click  to close the window. It's in the bottom-right corner of the certificate window. <figure rend="Check an SSL Certificate Step 22.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Safari for iPhone and iPad</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open Safari on your iPhone or iPad. It's the compass icon that's typically found on the home screen. <figure rend="Check an SSL Certificate Step 23.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Safari for iOS does not come with a built-in way to view an SSL certificate in the app, but you can use a certificate verification website as a workaround.</item></list></item>
<item>Navigate to <ref target="https://www.digicert.com/help">https://www.digicert.com/help</ref>. This opens a website that can check SSL certificates for any accessible site. <figure rend="Check an SSL Certificate Step 24.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Enter the URL of the site you want to check. You can type just the domain (e.g. wikihow.com). <figure rend="Check an SSL Certificate Step 25.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tap . It's right below the blank. <figure rend="Check an SSL Certificate Step 26.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Scroll down to see the results. You'll find all of the certificate's information, including its issuer, expiration date, and other pertinent details.  <figure rend="Check an SSL Certificate Step 27.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Microsoft Edge for Windows</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open Edge. It's the ″e″ icon in the Start menu. You may also find it on the desktop. <figure rend="Check an SSL Certificate Step 28.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Navigate to the website with the certificate you want to check. To get there, type the URL into the address bar at the top of the screen and press . You can also search for a website in your search engine of choice. <figure rend="Check an SSL Certificate Step 29.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the black and white padlock. It's on the left side of the address bar at the top of the screen. A menu with information about the website will appear. <figure rend="Check an SSL Certificate Step 30.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . The certificate information will appear on the right side of the screen. Some browsers may not require this step. <figure rend="Check an SSL Certificate Step 31.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
