<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc138" title="Find Loan Officer Classes" shortTile="find-loan-officer" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-05-20" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Find_Loan_Officer_Classes" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Find Loan Officer Classes</head><p>Loan officers work with consumers as well as business owners in processing loan applications to purchase items such as a home, get a college student loan, or obtain funding to start a company. Loan officers can specialize in several areas including consumer loans in addition to mortgage loans and business loans. Educational training, licensing and certification requirements for becoming a loan officer may vary depending on the region where you live. Here are some helpful tips and suggestions on how to find loan officer classes.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Know that loan officer training classes can be intensive and will focus on teaching many federal laws and regulations that you will be required to learn and remember. You will not only learn how to process a loan but also learn about topics such as lending practices, consumer ethics and real estate procedures, in addition to privacy protection. <figure rend="Memorize French ER Present Tense Verbs Using Visual Imagery Mnemonics Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Realize that some positions as a loan officer, particularly one that works with mortgages, will likely require that you pass an examination, become licensed and engage in continuing education on an annual basis. This is a requirement for mortgage loan officers working within the United States. <figure rend="Learn German by Immersion Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Browse the Internet to explore the many loan officer classes that are available. Consider the reputation of the organization that offers loan officer classes. Before you invest your time and money, it is important to conduct some background research. <figure rend="Learn Arabic Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Review the information provided about the organizations that offer loan officer classes including how long they have been in business. Find out if the organizations offer a money-back guarantee and provide students with a way to contact either the instructors or a customer service representative in the event of any potential problems during the training. <figure rend="Minimize Student Loans Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Check to see if the organizations that are providing the training are accredited or if the loan officer classes are part of an accredited program. For example, many loan officer training programs within the United States are accredited by the Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry (NMLS). NMLS has guidelines that maintain national standards for continuing education testing and pre-licensing. <figure rend="Learn Classical Mechanics (Physics) Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Know that there is a listing available on the Internet for NMLS approved educational programs within the United States that includes loan officer classes. It can be viewed at Mortgage Nationwide Licensing System online, the link of which is provided at the end of this article.</item></list></item>
<item>Realize that many educational training programs for loan officer classes are available in online format. These types of training programs are accessible worldwide regardless of where you reside. Be aware that on-site loan officer classes may also be available in your area. <figure rend="Learn Arabic Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Explore several college websites that may offer loan officer classes. A position as a loan officer usually requires that the applicant has a bachelor's degree that includes a focus on finance and economics. Additional preparatory coursework includes mathematics and banking, as well as computer and communication skills. <figure rend="Make a Webquest Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Consider a work study program through either an internship or job shadowing if you are currently a college student to gain some valuable experience and skills while in school. Meet with your college career counselor to discuss your options and make arrangements. <figure rend="Find Loan Officer Classes Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Apply to your chosen program for taking loan officer classes. Keep a record of your receipts and all details about your loan officer class. Register early and obtain any necessary study materials and textbooks required for the coursework. <figure rend="Minimize Student Loans Step 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
</text>
