<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc33" title="Put on an Athletic Cup" shortTile="put-athletic-cup" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-10-17" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Put_on_an_Athletic_Cup" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Put on an Athletic Cup</head><p>Wearing an athletic cup is important if you play contact sports. The key to successfully wearing an athletic cup is finding one that’s comfortable and fits properly. Whether you’re wearing the cup underneath a jockstrap or a pair of compression shorts, you should make sure the cup is firmly in place before you head onto the field. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Wearing a Cup and Jockstrap</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Get a cup-style jockstrap that fits snugly. Check the packaging on the jockstrap to make sure it’s suitable for wearing a cup. Most jockstraps come in kid and adult sizes that are based on waist size. Don’t get a jockstrap that’s too large; an oversized jockstrap will prevent the athletic cup from being held firmly in place. <figure rend="Put on an Athletic Cup Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Put on the jockstrap. Slide each leg through one of the elastic leg straps and pull the jockstrap up to your waist. The waistband should rest on your waist and your genitals should be securely tucked into the front pouch on the jockstrap. <figure rend="Put on an Athletic Cup Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Slide the cup into the pouch at the front of the jockstrap. The narrower end of the cup should be facing downward, with the wider end up just below the waistband. Your penis and testicles should be completely inside the athletic cup; if they’re not, the cup may be too small. <figure rend="Put on an Athletic Cup Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure the cup is firmly held in place by the jockstrap. Do some squats, lunges, or other movements to see if the cup is secure. If you feel your penis or testicles shifting around a lot in the cup, or the cup feels too loose, the cup may be too big. Don’t use an athletic cup that doesn’t fit. <figure rend="Put on an Athletic Cup Step 4.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Wearing a Cup and Compression Shorts</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Get cup-style compression shorts. Compression shorts are thin, mid-thigh length shorts that can be worn underneath your uniform in place of underwear. Measure your waist size to determine which size you should get. <figure rend="Put on an Athletic Cup Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure the packaging on the compression shorts says they’re compatible with an athletic cup.</item></list></item>
<item>Put on the compression shorts. Compression shorts should be worn like regular underwear or biking shorts. Make sure the cup pouch on the shorts is facing forward and covering your genitals. <figure rend="Put on an Athletic Cup Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pull the shorts waistband outward and slide the cup into the pouch. The narrow end of the cup should be facing down toward your feet, with the wider end of the cup resting below the waistband. Adjust the cup inside of the pouch so your penis and testicles are completely inside of it. <figure rend="Put on an Athletic Cup Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Check to see if the athletic cup is fit snugly in the pouch. Move around a bit or jog in place. The cup should feel like it’s being held firmly in place by the compression shorts; not so tight that it’s causing pain, and not so loose that your genitals and the cup are shifting around a lot. If the cup feels too tight or too loose, get a different size cup or a different size pair of compression shorts. <figure rend="Put on an Athletic Cup Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Choosing an Athletic Cup</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Get an athletic cup made of polymers or carbon fiber for protection. Check the packaging to see what the cup is made out of. Find a cup that lists polymers or carbon fiber as one of the main materials; they’ll help soften any blows to the groin by transferring the shock elsewhere. <figure rend="Put on an Athletic Cup Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find an athletic cup that has gel-padded edges for a comfortable fit. Check the label to see if there are gel pads present on the cup; they’ll prevent the edges of the cup from scratching and irritating the skin. <figure rend="Put on an Athletic Cup Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Choose a machine-washable athletic cup for convenience. It should say right on the label whether the cup can be machine washed or not. Using a cup that can be washed in a machine will let you keep the cup clean and fresh without having to wash it by hand and air dry it. <figure rend="Put on an Athletic Cup Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get an athletic cup in a size that corresponds with your waist size. Athletic cups are measured in waist sizes, so make sure you know your waist size before buying one. Use measuring tape to measure your waist if you’re not sure. <figure rend="Put on an Athletic Cup Step 12.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
