<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc297" title="Build a T Shirt Cannon" shortTile="build-t-shirt-cannon" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2017-02-20" dateModified="2018-04-04" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Build_a_T_Shirt_Cannon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Build a T Shirt Cannon</head><p>T-shirt cannons are a great source of fun and can be a great promotional tool at sports games, rallies or just for your own fun. These instructions will inform you on how to safely build and operate and operate your T-shirt cannon.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Building the Cannon</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Cut the boards needed for your cannon.
<list type="unordered"><item>Take your 10ft section of 3-inch diameter PVC and cut it in half to get two 5-ft sections. One of these will become the muzzle of your cannon and the other the air tank.</item>
<item>Take one of the 5-ft sections and cut it in two areas to get three segments (one 6-inches long, one segment 2½-ft long, and one 2-ft long). The 2-ft section will not be needed. The 2 1/2-ft segment will become the air tank.</item>
<item>Take your 2-inch diameter tube and cut two 4-inches long segments from it, the rest will not be needed.</item></list></item>
<item>Build the muzzle.
<list type="unordered"><item>Take your 5-ft segment and cement it to one of the 2-inch or 3-inch adapters. <figure rend="IMG_5708.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Test your valve. Try turning your ball valve now. If you find it hard to turn, you may want to attach a handle to it, to make it easy to turn. (<hi rend="bold">NOTE:</hi>Do not oil the valve as it may damage the seal on the valve.<hi rend="bold">)</hi></item>
<item>Build the valve assembly. Take your 2-inch ball valve and cement both of the 4-inch and 2-inch diameter tubes to either end.<figure><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Special:FilePath/IMG_5712_1.jpg">Image:IMG 5712 1.jpg</ref></figure></item>
<item>Connect the valve to the top of the muzzle. Find a comfortable direction that you like to turn the valve by looking through the valve while turning it. Label the side facing away from you as the front and the side facing towards you as the back.
<list type="unordered"><item><list type="unordered"><item>When doing this, be sure to direct the valve handle towards your dominate hand.</item></list></item>
<item>Take the side labeled as front and cement it to the adapter on the muzzle.<figure><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Special:FilePath/IMG_5713_1.jpg">Image:IMG 5713 1.jpg</ref></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Turn the cannon-elbows 180 degrees.
<list type="unordered"><item>Take both of your 90-degree elbows and cement them together so that the slim side of the spigot elbow is inside of the other elbow.</item>
<item>Make sure that they are facing the same direction.<figure></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Assemble the valves. Cement the adapter on to the back side of the valve.</item>
<item>Connect the 180-degree turn to the cannon.
<list type="unordered"><item>Cement the 6-inch and 3-inch diameter segments into the second 2-inch to 3-inch adapter.</item>
<item>Cement the 180-degree turn onto the cannon making sure that the turn is parallel to the ball valve handle.<figure></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Form the end cap.Take your end cap and drill a hole in it using the 21/64-inch drill bit (<hi rend="bold">NOTE:</hi>Be sure to use a vice or some other means to securely hold the end cap when drilling.<hi rend="bold">)</hi>
<list type="unordered"><item>You will now need to force-turn the 1/8-inch male adapter into the cap.</item></list></item>
<item>Assemble the compressor connections. Wrap the fitting threads in Teflon tape to ensure that they won't leak. Assemble the remaining fittings so that the ¼-inch compressor connector joins with the ¼-inch to ½-inch adapter and that the adapter joins with the valve. <figure rend="IMG_5723.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Attach the air tank.
<list type="unordered"><item>Cement the end cap to the 2 ½ft segment of 3-inch diameter tube.</item>
<item>Cement the air tank to the 180-degree turn. <figure rend="IMG_5724.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remember to let the PVC cement cure for at least 15-20 minutes before using your cannon.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Using the Cannon</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Insert a rolled-up t-shirt.</item>
<item>Close the ball valve and open air tank valve.</item>
<item>Fill with compressed air to 80-100psi.</item>
<item>Close the air tank valve then disconnect from the compressor.</item>
<item>Launch T-Shirt. When firing, make sure that you are not firing directly at someone.
<list type="unordered"><item>Arcing your shots ensures that you will not hit someone directly.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If there are any leaks, find the leak by pressurizing the tank and find it by either listening for, feeling for, or submerging to find bubbles. Once the leak is found, apply primer and cement to that area liberally. If issues continue, sections or parts may need to be replaced.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Only properly trained personnel should use the tools necessary.</item>
<item>Cannon does shoot projectiles and should only be fired in the company of adults.</item>
<item>Wear eye and hand protection when constructing and operating your cannon.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>PVC</item>
<item>1, 3-inch diameter Schedule-40 10ft long tubing (<hi rend="bold">NOTE</hi>: the tube will have “NOT FOR PRESSURE” printed on it. This is ok 40 Schedule PVC has a maximum working pressure of 58 psi and will not be exceeded in this design)</item></list>
2, 3-inch to 2inch adapters
<list type="unordered"><item>At least 1ft of 2inch Schedule 40 diameter tubing</item>
<item>1, 2-inch Ball valve (without threading)</item>
<item>1, 3-inch end cap</item>
<item>1, 3-inch 90 degree elbow</item>
<item>1, 3-inch Street L 90 degree elbow</item>
<item>PVC Cement and Primer (consult label on application Instructions</item>
<item>1, 1/8-inch valve</item>
<item>1, 1'8-inch male-male connector</item>
<item>1 adapter male 1/8-inch, female 1/4-inch</item>
<item>1, 1/4-inch male compressor connector</item>
<item>Teflon Tape</item>
<item>Saw (hand or powered)</item></list>
Power drill and 21/64- inch drill bit
<list type="unordered"><item>Measuring tape</item>
<item>Marker or pencil</item></list>
</text>
