<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc135" title="Find Support in Online Communities" shortTile="find-support-online" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-03-16" dateModified="2019-07-09" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Find_Support_in_Online_Communities" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Find Support in Online Communities</head><p>Finding support in online communities, or support groups, can be a convenient way to deal with any type of personal issue you may be facing in your life. There are many benefits to joining an online support group; including the ability to participate and seek support at a time that works best with your schedule, anonymity, and the convenience of never leaving your home if you suffer from a disability or other situation that prevents you from being mobile. Many online communities exist on the Internet from which you can find support, depending on your particular situation. Continue reading this article to learn about the best methods for finding support in online communities.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Determine the type of support you need. Online communities exist for nearly every type of support group for any issue; including health issues, family issues, phobias, addictions, and more. <figure rend="Find Support in Online Communities Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Seek names of groups or organizations that support your issue. Most groups and major organizations can make recommendations on online communities you can join to receive support, or have an online community of their own. <figure rend="Find Support in Online Communities Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Ask your doctor or health care provider for names of organizations that support your personal issue. For example, if you need support to overcome an addiction to gambling, you may be able to find online support from Gamblers Anonymous.</item>
<item>Visit the "NMHA" website listed in the Sources section of this article to review a full list of links to organizations with specialized support groups.</item></list></item>
<item>Search for online communities for your specific group on the Internet. Online support groups may exist in the form of chat rooms, blogs, forums, email lists, or may have their own profiles on social networking sites such as Facebook or Twitter. <figure rend="Find Support in Online Communities Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Perform an Internet search for online communities using keywords that include the name of your specialized support group. For example, if you are seeking divorce support, enter keywords into your search engine such as "divorce support forum," "online divorce support group," or "divorce chat room."</item>
<item>Visit the websites of organizations that support your issue to find links to forums and similar online communities. For example, if you need support for your mental illness, visit the website for the National Alliance on Mental Illness, then link to and join their Facebook discussion group.</item></list></item>
<item>Join major social networks that cater primarily to support groups of every type. In addition to common social networks such as Facebook and Twitter, there are numerous social networking websites dedicated solely to support groups. <figure rend="Find Support in Online Communities Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Visit the "Read Write Web" website provided to you in the Sources section of this article to review a full list of large-scale social networking communities you can join to receive support for a particular personal issue.</item></list></item>
<item>Read through the content posted within the online support community to measure the level of support provided by other members. An online community that truly offers support will demonstrate compassion and understanding about issues and topics posted by members. <figure rend="Find Support in Online Communities Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Verify that the online community is active and current. A strong online support community will contain updated news and information about your issue, and be comprised of numerous members that engage in discussion on a daily basis. <figure rend="Find Support in Online Communities Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Examine the dates and frequency of posts and discussions to verify that the community is active.</item></list></item>
<item>Join more than one online support community. Depending on your support needs and personality, joining several online support communities can help you find the support group that is most helpful to you. <figure rend="Find Support in Online Communities Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be careful when sharing personal information about yourself with online support communities; such as your real name, telephone number, and address. Some predators use online support communities to prey on people during the most vulnerable times in their lives.</item>
<item>Do not participate in online support communities whose members encourage you to stop treatment, purchase their products or services, or are judgmental about your choices. These types of behaviors may not provide you with the type of healthy support needed to overcome your issue.</item></list>
</text>
