<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc44" title="Understand Soccer Positions (Roles)" shortTile="understand-soccer" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-01-02" dateModified="2015-08-15" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Understand_Soccer_Positions_%28Roles%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Understand Soccer Positions (Roles)</head><p>The eleven players on the soccer pitch achieve one goal by playing differently in terms of roles and positions. Here's how to comprehend the theory of roles and positions and their interrelationship.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Goalkeepers</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Goalies play in between the posts, and are mostly confined within the 18 yard box.Goalkeepers:
<list type="unordered"><item>prevent the ball from finding the net.</item>
<item>continue play by initiating goal kicks.</item>
<item>reduce pressure from up field players by receiving back passes.</item>
<item>command the defense and team in general.</item></list></item>
<item>In some formations, goalkeepers may act as sweepers, clearing loose balls from the defending half.</item></list>
<head>Defenders</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Defenders mainly prevent the opposition from scoring and possessing the ball near their net. Mostly based on their defending half, defenders are differentiated into:
<list type="unordered"><item>Fullbacks, that is, a right back and a left back who play wide depending on their respective sides. Fullbacks prevent opposition from attacking via the wings(flanks) and assist centre backs and midfielders (mainly those who play wide)</item>
<item>Centre backs play at the heart of a team's defense. These are the main defenders. Centre backs consist of a sweeper, who plays as the last man, and a stopper, who marks the main striker. Centre backs also help midfielders reduce pressure by receiving passes, and sometimes play long passes to more upfield players.</item></list></item>
<item>Defenders may also change a team's defense into attack by initiating counter attacks or playing long balls.</item></list>
<head>Midfielders</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>The midfield consists of the most dynamic players: midfielders. They play in the middle third, and depending on formations and strategies, they have different positions hence different roles. Midfielders may be:
<list type="unordered"><item>defensive midfielders. These play deep, much closer to defenders, and they supplement the defense as well as aid the rest of the midfield. They play a central position.</item>
<item>central midfielders, who play at the centre of the midfield. Central midfielders roam the entire pitch and are the main possessors. Passing and marking are their main roles, and sometimes goal scoring can be part of it depending on the occasion.</item>
<item>wingers(wide midfielders) play on the flanks, either right or left. They attack through the flanks and provide crosses. In defensive situations, they help the fullbacks. Wide mids may be more offensive, or play in the middle third.</item>
<item>attacking midfielders play a more offensive role. They may be wide or central, and mainly supply the forwards and score goals.</item></list></item>
<item>Midfielders take set pieces, throw-ins and are mainly involved in recovering possession.</item></list>
<head>Forwards</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>These are the most offensive players, also called strikers or finishers. Their main role is to find the back of the net.</item>
<item>Forwards may be wide or central, depending on formation. Wide forwards mainly attempt from wide and provide crosses and assists.</item>
<item>Some forwards initiate counter attacks after picking up the ball from deep. A good example is Cristiano Ronaldo.</item></list>
<head>Positions according to numbers</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Numbers may define positions depending on formations: 1-Goalkeeper 2-Right back 3-Left Back 4-Centre back 5- Centre back 6-Defensive midfielder (or central midfielder) 7-Right winger (or right forward) 8-Central midfielder (or attacking midfielder) 9-Centre forward 10- Attacking midfielder(central) or secondary striker 11-Left midfielder (or left forward)</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>In the modern game, jersey numbers may not accord to player roles.</item>
<item>Even if positions are meant to be guidelines to roles, tactical changes may assign players new roles irrespective of position.</item></list>
</text>
