<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc279" title="Educate Others on the Importance of Injury Prevention" shortTile="educate-others-importance" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-09-13" dateModified="2019-06-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Educate_Others_on_the_Importance_of_Injury_Prevention" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Educate Others on the Importance of Injury Prevention</head><p>Every year, nearly 1 million children die from injuries. Tens of millions more require hospital care for non-fatal injuries. Many are left with permanent disabilities or brain damage.</p>
<p>Injuries affect children of all ages. Girls and boys under 5 years of age are at particular risk. More boys than girls die from injuries.</p>
<p>The most common injuries are traffic injuries, non-fatal drowning (sometimes referred to as near drowning), burns, falls and poisoning.</p>
<p>Traffic injuries and drowning are the leading causes of injury-related death.</p>
<p>The most common place for young children to be injured is in or around their homes.</p>
<p>Almost all injuries can be prevented.</p>
<p>Families, communities and governments have an obligation to ensure children's right to live in a safe environment and be protected from injury.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Understand the importance of injury prevention. In order to spread the message, it is important to know the facts. The basics are: <figure rend="Educate Others on the Importance of Injury Prevention Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Many serious injuries can be prevented if parents and other caregivers supervise children carefully and keep their environment safe.</item>
<item>Young children are at risk on or near roads. They should not play on or near the road and should always have someone older with them when they are near or crossing a road. They should wear a helmet when on a bicycle or motorcycle and should be securely strapped into an age-appropriate child restraint when being transported in a vehicle.</item>
<item>Children can drown in less than two minutes and in a very small amount of water, even in a bathtub. They should never be left alone in or near water.</item>
<item>Burns can be prevented by keeping children away from fires, cooking stoves, hot liquids and foods, and exposed electric wires.</item>
<item>Falls are a major cause of injury for young children. Stairs, balconies, roofs, windows, and play and sleeping areas should be made secure, using barriers with vertical bars to protect children from falling.</item>
<item>Medicines, poisons, insecticides, bleach, acids and liquid fertilizers and fuels, such as paraffin (kerosene), should be stored carefully out of children's sight and reach. Dangerous substances should be stored in clearly marked containers and never in drinking bottles. Child-resistant closures, where available, should be used on the containers of poisonous products.</item>
<item>Knives, scissors, sharp or pointed objects and broken glass can cause serious injuries. These objects should be kept out of children's reach. Plastic bags, which can cause suffocation, should be kept away from young children.</item>
<item>Young children like to put things in their mouths. To prevent choking, small objects, such as coins, nuts and buttons, should be kept out of their reach. Children's foods should be cut into small pieces that can be easily chewed and swallowed.</item></list></item>
<item>Learn the basics of what to do with certain basic injuries, such as broken bones, cuts, etc. <figure rend="Educate Others on the Importance of Injury Prevention Step 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
