<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc144" title="Detect Developmental Dysplasia of the Hips in Infants" shortTile="detect-developmental" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2019-09-21" dateModified="2019-10-26" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Detect_Developmental_Dysplasia_of_the_Hips_in_Infants" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Detect Developmental Dysplasia of the Hips in Infants</head><p>Developmental Dysplasia of the Hips, or Hip Dysplasia (DDH) is a congenital condition and occurs when the ball and socket of the hip are not formed properly in babies and children. It is most common in first-born children and occurs mostly in the left hip. This wikiHow will help you determine whether or not your child may have the condition.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Looking Out for Signs of DDH</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Research the condition to gain a better understanding.  <figure rend="Research Step 12.jpg"></figure>Hip dysplasia is where the hip does not form properly and the hip socket is too shallow to keep the hip joint stable. This can cause the hip to subluxate or dislocate if left untreated.
<list type="unordered"><item>About 1 to 2 in 1,000 babies are diagnosed with the condition every year.</item></list></item>
<item>See if you meet the risk factors of your child developing hip dysplasia.  <figure rend="Turn a Breech Baby Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure>Hip dysplasia can occur if a baby was born breech, or if the child was born with any other physical conditions. It is also common in females. Other risk factors include:
<list type="unordered"><item>Being your first pregnancy.</item>
<item>If the condition runs in your family.</item>
<item>Giving birth to a larger baby or multiple babies.</item></list></item>
<item>Look out for signs of DDH in your baby  <figure rend="Handle a Newborn Baby Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure>. If your doctor does not notice hip dysplasia or have any concerns straight away, it is still important to be aware of the symptoms so that your baby can be checked out and diagnosed if there are any indicators of hip dysplasia being present. Signs to look out for include:
<list type="unordered"><item>One leg being slightly shorter than the other leg.</item>
<item>A hip may be more mobile and movable than the other.</item>
<item>A baby might show a limp when they start learning to walk.</item>
<item>If the child experiences any discomfort when mobilising the hip.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Getting a Professional Diagnosis of DDH</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Ask your doctor to perform a physical hip exam if they haven't done so already <figure rend="Massage a Newborn Baby Step 16 Version 3.jpg"></figure>. Most doctors will do a hip check soon after a baby is born as part of their protocols when checking the overall health of the baby. They will feel the baby's hips to determine if they feel solid or not.
<list type="unordered"><item>This should not cause any pain to your baby and does not take long to complete.</item>
<item>If they do not feel solid, further tests will be carried out to see if your child has hip dysplasia.</item></list></item>
<item>Get an ultrasound of your baby's hips. <figure rend="Prepare for a Pelvic Ultrasound Step 18.jpg"></figure> A doctor might recommend an ultrasound if they feel that your baby's hips are not as solid as they should be at the time of birth. An ultrasound involves a probe being placed on the hips and analysing whether or not the hip joint and sockets are fully formed or not. If they are not, your child may be diagnosed with developmental hip dysplasia.{{Greenbox: <hi rend="bold">Tip</hi>: Sometimes a baby's hip can fix itself overtime before an ultrasound is done; however, it's still best to have the ultrasound to rule out any underlying conditions or signs of DDH.}}</item>
<item>See an orthopaedic surgeon.  <figure rend="Recover from Eye Surgery Step 24.jpg"></figure>If your paediatrician or midwife recommends, it is a good idea to see an orthopaedic consultant to officially diagnose Developmental Dysplasia of the Hips in your baby and to agree on an appropriate treatment plan.
<list type="unordered"><item>If the condition is severe in your baby's case, then a brace or cast (known as a hip spica) may be applied to the hip to help correct the position of your baby's hips and help them to heal correctly.</item>
<item>Your baby may require surgery in later life, but this is usually done once the hip bones are fully formed.{{Greenbox: <hi rend="bold">Did you know?</hi>: If treated early, and if successful, a baby may grow up to have no further complications or issues with their hip and may even regain full mobility in their hips.}}</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't be frightened if your baby is diagnosed with DDH. With a good surgeon and treatment program, your child will be able to have equal opportunities and will grow up to be independent.</item>
<item>You can't cause the condition, so don't feel bad if your child is diagnosed with DDH, as you could not have prevented it.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure you follow your doctor's advice when caring for your baby, as incorrectly swaddling your baby or holding your baby could worsen the outcomes of the treatment.</item></list>
</text>
