<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc8" title="Tape a Knee" shortTile="tape-knee" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-02-21" dateModified="2019-08-22" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Tape_a_Knee" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Tape a Knee</head><p>Coping with an injured or painful knee is hard, but taping it can provide some relief. Not only that, but taping your knee also adds support for your knee. To tape your knee, you'll need to first place crossing strips on either side of your leg, framing your knee. Then, anchor your straps by wrapping more tape around your knee. If you have a tape allergy, you should apply a hypo-allergenic base, first.  </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Placing Crossing Strips</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Sit down on a flat surface. Great options include the floor or an elevated table, depending on what's available to you. Although a table may make it easier for someone else to wrap your knee, you need to make sure it's stable. <figure rend="Tape a Knee Step 2 Version 3.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Elevate your knee with a rolled towel or similar item (optional). This should put your knee at a 30 degree angle. Although you don't have to do this, it makes it easier to hold your knee in place during the wrapping. <figure rend="Tape a Knee Step 3 Version 3.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Without the support of a towel or similar object, you may find it too tiring or painful to hold your knee in place.</item>
<item>If you don't want to use a towel, you could try a water bottle or a round foam massaging roller.</item></list></item>
<item>Apply a hypo-allergenic base, if you're allergic to sports tape. The base layer, which goes under your tape, will protect you from an allergic reaction. Make sure that your entire knee is covered in a base layer before you start wrapping your knee. <figure rend="Tape a Knee Step 1 Version 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>It's best to wrap your knee with the base layer using the same method as you're using for your actual sports tape. Simply follow the procedure for wrapping your knee, but use the base layer instead of your sports tape.</item>
<item>Once your base layer is in place, apply your sports tape.</item></list></item>
<item>Cut  strips of sports tape. Use scissors to cut your tape. If you're using pre-cut tape, simply pull the strips off the roll, as they're needed. This will be the standard strip length for this procedure. <figure rend="Tape a Knee Step 4 Version 3.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Most pre-cut rolls have  strips.</item></list></item>
<item>Apply the strip to your knee. Place one end of the strip about  above the knee, in the center of the thigh. Then, slowly smooth it down along the outside of your leg, crossing over the side of your knee. <figure rend="Tape a Knee Step 6 Version 3.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The strip should finish in the center of the calf, below the back of the knee.</item>
<item>All strips should be placed so that circulation will not be cut off.</item>
<item>It is best to always have a little tension when placing each strip. Do not pull hard or let the strip hang loose.</item></list></item>
<item>Add the next strip, starting below the knee and moving up. Place one end of a second strip of cut tape about  below the knee, in the center of the shin. Slowly smooth the strip up the outside of your leg, crossing over the side of the knee and intersecting the first strip on the side of the knee. The strip should finish in the center of the thigh, above the back of the knee. <figure rend="Tape a Knee Step 7 Version 3.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Apply the strips to the inside of your knee. Repeat steps 2 through 5 on the inside of the knee to mirror the first two strips. <figure rend="Tape a Knee Step 9 Version 3.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This should create an X on each side of the knee.</item>
<item>The ends of both X’s should start and stop in the same place.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Placing Anchors</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Cut out a strip of tape that will go around your whole thigh. This length will vary person to person. You may want to measure your thigh before you cut the tape so that you don't waste any. <figure rend="Tape a Knee Step 10 Version 3.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Apply the first anchor strap. Place one end of the strip on top of the ends of the two strips already placed, which should be  above the knee. This will be the top of your "X." <figure rend="Tape a Knee Step 11 Version 3.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Wrap the piece around the leg. Go slowly so that your application is even. Cover the ends of the two strips on the back of your thigh. Finally, finish where you started. <figure rend="Tape a Knee Step 12 Version 3.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This anchors the crossing strips down.</item></list></item>
<item>Cut out a strip of tape that will go around your whole calf. This length will vary person to person. You may want to measure the tape before you cut it so that you don't risk wasting a piece. <figure rend="Tape a Knee Step 13 Version 3.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Start this anchor at the lower points of your "X." Place one end of the strip on top of the ends of the two strips already placed, which should be  below your knee. Slowly wrap the piece around the leg, covering the ends of the two strips on the back of the calf. You should finish in the same place where you started, creating a circle around your leg. <figure rend="Tape a Knee Step 14 Version 3.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This serves as another anchor.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Although these steps can be performed by yourself, best results occur when another person does the taping.</item>
<item>If you have leg hair, and would like to keep it, a base tape or other type of pre-wrap should be laid down. Shaving beforehand also works.</item>
<item>This is a basic strategy for reducing pain. There are other, more complex ways to tape a knee.</item>
<item>This method uses standard non-stretch sports tape. Kinesio tape can be used to tape a knee, but the steps are different.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you experience an increase in pain, or numbness, stop what you are doing. If the symptoms persist, seek medical help.</item>
<item>Please do not attempt this if you have a fracture or other serious injury, or have circulatory problems.</item>
<item>If you have a skin allergy, consult your doctor before choosing this method of treatment.</item>
<item>Taping depends on the nature of your injury, and/or your anatomy. Consult a medical professional for advice before you begin.</item>
<item>Taping your knee does not guarantee absolute protection or support for your knee</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Sports/athletic tape - roll or pre-cut (adhesive, non-stretch, hypo-allergenic)</item>
<item>Rolled up towel, large water bottle, or similar object to place under your knee</item>
<item>Scissors (if your tape is not pre-cut)</item>
<item>Hypo-allergenic base tape or pre-wrap (optional)</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
