<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc164" title="Apologize to Your Family" shortTile="apologize-family" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-06-14" dateModified="2019-09-10" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Apologize_to_Your_Family" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Apologize to Your Family</head><p>If you have hurt your family, it is important to identify what you did wrong and that they are feeling hurt. An apology takes a lot of thought, reflection and planning, if you need to know how to apologise to your family read the steps down below. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><figure rend="Say You're Sorry Step 10.jpg"></figure> Lay off for a while. Your family may need some time away from you after what has happened, it is good for your whole family to have some reflection time before your apology.</item>
<item><figure rend="Control Your Thoughts Step 10.jpg"></figure> Think about their point of view. After a great mistake, it is important to acknowledge that your family will need time to heal. Be sure to give them space and time and try to look at this situation from their point of view. How would they feel? Why are they feeling this way?</item>
<item><figure rend="Control Your Thoughts Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure> Understand what you did. To truly apologize to your family you need to understand exactly what you did wrong. Instead of just knowing that you got angry and said bad things, damaged something, hurt someone, wasted money or whatever else it was you're apologising for, think about the words you used or what you did and how it affected them. Write down some key things that you did to help when you apologize.</item>
<item><figure rend="Control Your Thoughts Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure> Write down your apology. Write your apology down on a peice of paper or your phone, you can read directly from it or memorise the words. Keep in mind that your family may appreciate an apology that isn't read from a note more than one that is. Remember the last two steps while writing your apology and go over it a few times imagining it is you being apologised too. Change anything that sounds blaming, insincere or excusing your own behaviour.</item>
<item><figure rend="Control Your Thoughts Step 11.jpg"></figure> Prepare to apologize. Before you apologize make sure you are in a calm but apologetic mood, if you feel angry or blaming it is best to wait for another time. Take some deep breathes if you need help to calm yourself or if you are nervous.</item>
<item><figure rend="Say You're Sorry Step 4.jpg"></figure> Ask your whole family to sit down together. Tell your family that you have something important to say to them and you'd like them to sit down together and listen. Try to do this at a time they aren't busy, if they still have things to do ask to arrange it for another time.</item>
<item><figure rend="Say You're Sorry Step 5.jpg"></figure> Ask for your families point of view. Ask them to tell their side of the story, it helps the apology go better and shows that you want to listen. Make sure you do listen to your family's point of view and the whole story. Don't interrupt them to add details, remember it's their turn to tell their side.
<list type="unordered"><item>Listening will show your family you care.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Say You're Sorry Step 2.jpg"></figure> Look at them. Making eye contact only further shows that you care about this and want to fix things. Don't daze off even if they are giving you a long lecture. While it may seem boring, your family is trying to benefit you; even if it may not feel like it.</item>
<item><figure rend="Say You're Sorry Step 6.jpg"></figure> Don't fall back into old habits. This makes your apology invalid and your family will be less likely to trust you again. Part of an apology is a promise to not make the same mistakes again.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't over-crowd them. Realize you have hurt your family and they will need time to fully trust you again and heal.</item>
<item>While apologizing, listen to your family and how they feel.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Watch your tone of voice, even if you're not angry, your tone may make it seem like you are.</item>
<item>Be sure to look at your situation from your family's point of view.</item></list>
</text>
