<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc185" title="Be a Favourite Niece or Nephew" shortTile="favourite-niece-nephew" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-03-24" dateModified="2017-07-19" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_a_Favourite_Niece_or_Nephew" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be a Favourite Niece or Nephew</head><p>Aunts and uncles are an integral part of your parent's lives and thus become an important part of your life as well. Maintaining a healthy relationship with aunts and uncles is very important for our family life. Below are some points which will explain how you could endear yourself to your aunt and uncle.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be respectful. This is a crucial part of being a good niece or nephew. Be respectful of your aunt/uncle's beliefs and personality. It is also important never to argue rudely with them. Show acceptance of their opinions by not rebelling. If you disagree, say your opinion and listen calmly to their viewpoints. No need to yell or scream; it doesn't do good to any of you. <figure rend="Be a Favourite Niece or Nephew Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be friendly. If you have cousins younger than yourself, try to bond with them by offering to babysit them, teach them, advise them or by playing with them. If you have older cousins, be respectful and honor their philosophy and way of life. Ask for guidance and appreciate all that they do for you. If they tell you to do something, be obedient unless it is immoral, unlawful or harmful to yourself.  <figure rend="Be a Favourite Niece or Nephew Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be considerate and helpful. If they are incapable of doing something themselves, offer to help. For example, walk their dogs, run errands, fix small things around the house. If they are ill, make some vegetable soup and offer it to them. Traditionally, it is a very good deed to bring tea or coffee to one's loved elders every morning and ask if they need anything every night. Try doing this with sincerity, and do not stop unless you feel like it is a terribly dreaded part of your life.  <figure rend="Be a Favourite Niece or Nephew Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be generous. Whenever you visit your uncle/aunt take something for them. Homemade or baked items are a good idea. If you aren't yet able to make things yourself, a hug or a warm compliment are great things to give. Otherwise, be thoughtful. Think of what they like and bring to them. For instance, if your aunt loves jewelry, bring her a pearl necklace and say, "For the shining pearl in your soul."  <figure rend="Be a Favourite Niece or Nephew Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be pious. If your aunt/uncle are religious and share a religion with you, go to your holy site with them and worship reverently. If they don't share a religion with you, visit their worship sites and see some of the rituals, and have them do the same for yours. If they are not religious, take them to tours, seeing different buildings where people worship.  <figure rend="Be a Favourite Niece or Nephew Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be accepting. If your aunt/uncle has a pet, be friendly with it, even if you don't like it. If they like something that you hate, accept their likes but don't force yourself to take them up. Cherish any shared hobbies and enjoy them together. Meanwhile, be obedient and follow the rules of the family. If you feel the rules are unjust, try to get them changed in an orderly manner rather than disobey them rebelliously.  <figure rend="Be a Favourite Niece or Nephew Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be kind. Do random acts of kindness. Try not to forget a holiday or birthday. If you do, then make it up with a kindly gift and an affectionate smile. Never lie to your aunt/uncle, and be as kind and respectful as possible.  <figure rend="Be a Favourite Niece or Nephew Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be grateful. Be thankful for the moments you have together. Watching old films or photo collections, playing golf, swimming in the sea, reading together...whatever it is, if you and your aunt and uncle like it, cherish each moment.  <figure rend="Be a Favourite Niece or Nephew Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make your every visit a memorable one for your uncle/aunt by making them feel important and loved. <figure rend="Be a Favourite Niece or Nephew Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Ensure that you don't overdo being involved with them; respect their boundaries.</item></list>
</text>
