<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc142" title="Transfer Educational Materials from the Internet to Your Computer Through Your Mobile Bluetooth Handset" shortTile="transfer-educational" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-07-21" dateModified="2017-02-01" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Transfer_Educational_Materials_from_the_Internet_to_Your_Computer_Through_Your_Mobile_Bluetooth_Handset" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Transfer Educational Materials from the Internet to Your Computer Through Your Mobile Bluetooth Handset</head><p>Yes it is possible to transfer useful materials from the internet to your computer through your mobile telephone. This fact could be more appreciated by students at any level be it tertiary or secondary.Now before one proceeds it should noted that the mobile telephones that are useful for this purpose are only those with Blue-tooth. So mobile telephones not having Blue-tooth may not be able to carry out this function described here  that is transfer of word documents from the internet to your computer using your mobile telephone.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Now to send a word document or PDF file to a desktop computer through a Blue-tooth mobile phone. You go to a cybercafe or where there is an internet connection with your Blue-tooth mobile phone and your Blue-tooth USB Dongle. <figure rend="Transfer Educational Materials from the Internet to Your Computer Through Your Mobile Bluetooth Handset Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Attach your USB Dongle to the online system you are using through the USB Port of the system. <figure rend="Transfer Educational Materials from the Internet to Your Computer Through Your Mobile Bluetooth Handset Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wait until the system has indicated that the it has recognized the Blue-tooth Dongle when it shows Blue-tooth at the bottom right corner of the screen of the monitor. <figure rend="Transfer Educational Materials from the Internet to Your Computer Through Your Mobile Bluetooth Handset Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Then you can put on the Blue-tooth of your mobile phone. <figure rend="Transfer Educational Materials from the Internet to Your Computer Through Your Mobile Bluetooth Handset Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>You can then proceed to send your downloaded word or PDF file by right clicking on it. Then a list of commands are shown out of which you will see send. Then click on send. When you click on send, out of the many functions you will Blue-tooth devices. Click on Blue-tooth devices. <figure rend="Transfer Educational Materials from the Internet to Your Computer Through Your Mobile Bluetooth Handset Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Then when you click on Blue-tooth devices, the system will search for any Blue-tooth device. If the Blue-tooth of your mobile phone is on it will indicate that it has seen your phone by writing the Blue-tooth name  of your mobile phone on the screen.(Please, make sure you know the Blue-tooth name of your mobile phone). <figure rend="Transfer Educational Materials from the Internet to Your Computer Through Your Mobile Bluetooth Handset Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Then you click on next when you do this. You will receive a signal on your mobile phone that you have a message. <figure rend="Transfer Educational Materials from the Internet to Your Computer Through Your Mobile Bluetooth Handset Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click OK and if you want to view it, click on show. If not scroll away but the document would have been saved under received files. <figure rend="Transfer Educational Materials from the Internet to Your Computer Through Your Mobile Bluetooth Handset Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Then finish up on the online system. <figure rend="Transfer Educational Materials from the Internet to Your Computer Through Your Mobile Bluetooth Handset Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Now to transfer the material from your Blue-tooth mobile phone to your desktop computer at home, attach the Blue-tooth USB Dongle to your desktop through the USB Port and wait till your desktop computer has indicated that it has seen or recognized the USB Dongle.It will indicate this by showing the Blue-tooth icon at the bottom right corner of the screen of the monitor. <figure rend="Transfer Educational Materials from the Internet to Your Computer Through Your Mobile Bluetooth Handset Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Then you right click on the Blue-tooth icon.When you do this a list of commands are shown out of which you will see Receive file. <figure rend="Transfer Educational Materials from the Internet to Your Computer Through Your Mobile Bluetooth Handset Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on Receive file and the computer will indicate that it is waiting to receive a file from another Blue-tooth device. <figure rend="Transfer Educational Materials from the Internet to Your Computer Through Your Mobile Bluetooth Handset Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Then go to where your material is stored on your mobile phone. The material will be saved under received files if your mobile phone is Nokia.You do this after the Blue-tooth of your mobile phone is on <figure rend="Transfer Educational Materials from the Internet to Your Computer Through Your Mobile Bluetooth Handset Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Then you click on the material you want to send and click send under the options presented.When you click send it will present you with 2 options. Send by message or send by Blue-tooth. <figure rend="Transfer Educational Materials from the Internet to Your Computer Through Your Mobile Bluetooth Handset Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Choose the send by Blue-tooth option. Then your mobile phone will search for other Blue-tooth devices and since your desktop computer is waiting to receive, it will find your computer. <figure rend="Transfer Educational Materials from the Internet to Your Computer Through Your Mobile Bluetooth Handset Step 15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>After finding click select on your handset. <figure rend="Transfer Educational Materials from the Internet to Your Computer Through Your Mobile Bluetooth Handset Step 16.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Then you finish up. <figure rend="Transfer Educational Materials from the Internet to Your Computer Through Your Mobile Bluetooth Handset Step 17.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Go back to your desktop and if you like, you can rename your file and indicate where you want it to be saved on your desktop and click finish. <figure rend="Rename-a-File-on-a-Computer-Step-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Then you have your material on your desktop computer. <figure rend="Rename-a-File-on-a-Computer-Step-1.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>please don't pair your Blue-tooth mobile device with the online system to prevent your mobile phone from being infected with virus.</item>
<item>Note that while the material is still, in your Blue-tooth handset, you may not be able to view it if it is in PDF or Microsoft Word format. Don't be afraid when you observe this. Once you have transferred it to your computer you will be able to view it.</item></list>
</text>
