<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc22" title="Get Ready for Any Sports Tryouts" shortTile="ready-sports-tryouts" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-04-18" dateModified="2019-09-19" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get_Ready_for_Any_Sports_Tryouts" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get Ready for Any Sports Tryouts</head><p>Getting ready for your tryouts? Need a little help? Well follow these steps and you're bound to be prepared</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Plan. The day you find out about the tryouts check to see how much time you have before the tryouts and prepare. Make a list of stuff you'll need (if you need anything) and check your schedule to see when you'll have time to practice. <figure rend="Get Ready for Any Sports Tryouts Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Practice. You know that practice makes perfect so practice! Practice your weak points but don't forget to practice your strong aspects either! Remember there is always room for improvement! <figure rend="Get Ready for Any Sports Tryouts Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Exercise. Exercise before practicing and before the tryouts.  Remember you don't want to get hurt.  <figure rend="Get Ready for Any Sports Tryouts Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't overwork. Overworking yourself is counterproductive. Remember everyone gets tired. Take breaks. <figure rend="Get Ready for Any Sports Tryouts Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Relax. After a nice long practice. Relax, it's good for your body and your soul. Stuff like taking a shower, listening to music you like or just unwinding and watching T.V are all ways you can relax. Do whatever relaxes you. <figure rend="Get Ready for Any Sports Tryouts Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Eat Healthy. You need to eat healthy. Your body will be working so it will need a lot of healthy nutrients. Avoid any Junk food. Here are the stuff you should eat on the day of the tryouts: <figure rend="Get Ready for Any Sports Tryouts Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Breakfast: Egg Sammy, a Sandwich made up of some eggs, a slice of cheese and a little ham. This sandwich will give you all the protein you need for the tryout.</item>
<item>Lunch: If your tryouts are after lunch here's what to eat, if not ignore this step. A Turkey sub with a side of Fruits and Pretzels. Stay away from greasy foods but don't skimp on calories you'll need them for the tryout.</item>
<item>Pregame snack: A low fat blueberry muffin and some milk will give you all the boost you need.</item></list></item>
<item>Get rest. Remember to rest, you will need a lot of energy for the game so go to bed early. <figure rend="Get Ready for Any Sports Tryouts Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Day Before Tryouts</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Prepare all your sports equipment that you'll need and don't forget to bring a water bottle! <figure rend="Get Ready for Any Sports Tryouts Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you have a tryout form, don't forget to include that too. <figure rend="Learn Quickly Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Rest that day. Practicing the day before the tryouts won't help you so just Relax instead. <figure rend="Get Ready for Any Sports Tryouts Step 10.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Keep yourself hydrated</item>
<item>Be Confident</item>
<item>Rest</item>
<item>Eat Healthy</item>
<item>Don't overwork yourself</item>
<item>Relax and take breaks</item>
<item>Don't forget to bring all your items!</item>
<item>Don't be nervous, be positive!!</item>
<item>Tell yourself you are good at this sport and that you WILL make the team. This will give you a huge confidence boost!</item>
<item>Practice makes perfect!</item>
<item>Get to the tryout location early, to get mentally prepared.</item>
<item>Wear any safety equipment you need and follow the rules</item>
<item>Have Fun!</item>
<item>Prepare well for the game</item>
<item>Exercise before the game</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always stay hydrated</item>
<item>Be careful you are playing sports and you might get hit</item></list>
</text>
