<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc74" title="Connect PC Internet to Mobile via WiFi" shortTile="connect-pc-internet" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-05-04" dateModified="2019-10-31" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Connect_PC_Internet_to_Mobile_via_WiFi" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Connect PC Internet to Mobile via WiFi</head><p>This wikiHow teaches you how to broadcast your Windows computer's Wi-Fi connection to your smartphone. You can do this on any computer that has a network hosting-enabled Wi-Fi adapter installed, meaning that you won't be able to use many desktop computers for this process. Keep in mind that this process is different than <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Connect-to-the-Internet-On-Your-Laptop-Through-Your-Cell-Phone">using your smartphone's data as a Wi-Fi network on your computer</ref>. If your computer's Wi-Fi adapter doesn't allow you to create a hotspot, you can <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Main_Page#step_2_1">use Connectify</ref> to broadcast your Wi-Fi.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Using Windows 10 Settings</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open Start . Click the Windows logo in the bottom-left corner of the screen. <figure rend="Connect PC Internet to Mobile via WiFi Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Open Settings . Click the Settings gear in the lower-left side of the Start menu. The Settings window will open. <figure rend="Connect PC Internet to Mobile via WiFi Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click  Network &amp; Internet. It's the globe-shaped icon in the middle of the Settings window. <figure rend="Connect PC Internet to Mobile via WiFi Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the  tab. This is on the left side of the window. <figure rend="Connect PC Internet to Mobile via WiFi Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the grey "Mobile hotspot" switch . It's at the top of the page. Clicking the switch turns it on  which signifies that your computer is now broadcasting your Internet connection. <figure rend="Connect PC Internet to Mobile via WiFi Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Review the network name and password. In the middle of the page, look at the "Network name" and "Network password" headings to determine the name and password for your mobile hotspot. <figure rend="Connect PC Internet to Mobile via WiFi Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The network name should be your computer's name, and the password should be your network's usual password.</item></list></item>
<item>Connect your smartphone to your Wi-Fi network. Now that your Wi-Fi hotspot is set up on your computer, you can connect to it via your smartphone's Wi-Fi menu: <figure rend="Connect PC Internet to Mobile via WiFi Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">iPhone</hi> — Open your iPhone's  <hi rend="bold">Settings</hi>, tap <hi rend="bold">Wi-Fi</hi>, tap your hosted hotspot's name, enter the password, and tap <hi rend="bold">Join</hi>.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Android</hi> — Swipe down from the top of the screen, long-press the Wi-Fi icon, tap your hosted hotspot's name, enter the password, and tap <hi rend="bold">JOIN</hi> or <hi rend="bold">CONNECT</hi>.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Using Connectify</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Make sure that you have a wireless adapter installed. You can check to see if your computer has a built-in Wi-Fi adapter by doing the following: <figure rend="Connect PC Internet to Mobile via WiFi Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Open Start .</item>
<item>Type in , then click <hi rend="bold">Command Prompt</hi>.</item>
<item>Type in  and press .</item>
<item>Wait for your adapter's information to appear. If you instead see "The Wireless AutoConfig Service is not running" appear, you don't have a wireless adapter installed.</item></list></item>
<item>Download the Connectify setup file. Connectify is a free app that you can use to broadcast your computer's Wi-Fi over short distances: <figure rend="Connect PC Internet to Mobile via WiFi Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Go to <ref target="https://www.connectify.me/">https://www.connectify.me/</ref> in your computer's web browser.</item>
<item>Click the purple <hi rend="bold">Download</hi> button.</item>
<item>Click <hi rend="bold">Continue to Download</hi>.</item></list></item>
<item>Install Connectify. Once the Connectify setup file finishes downloading, you can install it by double-clicking it and then doing the following: <figure rend="Connect PC Internet to Mobile via WiFi Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Click <hi rend="bold">Yes</hi> when prompted.</item>
<item>Click <hi rend="bold">I Agree</hi>.</item>
<item>Click <hi rend="bold">Agree</hi></item>
<item>Check the "Reboot now" box.</item>
<item>Click <hi rend="bold">Finish</hi>.</item></list></item>
<item>Wait for your computer to finish restarting. Once your computer boots back up, you can proceed. <figure rend="Connect PC Internet to Mobile via WiFi Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Open Connectify if necessary. Double-click the "Connectify Hotspot 2018" icon on your computer's desktop. <figure rend="Connect PC Internet to Mobile via WiFi Step 12.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Skip this step if the Connectify window opens automatically.</item></list></item>
<item>Click . It's a purple button at the bottom of the Connectify app window. <figure rend="Connect PC Internet to Mobile via WiFi Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the  tab. This is at the top of the Connectify window. <figure rend="Connect PC Internet to Mobile via WiFi Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Change your password if necessary. In the "Password" text box, delete the existing text and type in the password you want to use for your network. <figure rend="Connect PC Internet to Mobile via WiFi Step 15.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You cannot change the network name in the free version of Connectify.</item></list></item>
<item>Click . It's at the bottom of the window. <figure rend="Connect PC Internet to Mobile via WiFi Step 16.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wait for your computer's hotspot to start. Once Connectify alerts you that the hotspot is enabled, you can proceed. <figure rend="Connect PC Internet to Mobile via WiFi Step 17.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Connect your smartphone to your Wi-Fi network. Now that your Wi-Fi hotspot is set up on your computer, you can connect to it via your smartphone's Wi-Fi menu: <figure rend="Connect PC Internet to Mobile via WiFi Step 18.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">iPhone</hi> — Open your iPhone's  <hi rend="bold">Settings</hi>, tap <hi rend="bold">Wi-Fi</hi>, tap your hosted hotspot's name, enter the password, and tap <hi rend="bold">Join</hi>.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Android</hi> — Swipe down from the top of the screen, long-press the Wi-Fi icon, tap your hosted hotspot's name, enter the password, and tap <hi rend="bold">JOIN</hi> or <hi rend="bold">CONNECT</hi>.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>The Connectify method will work for any Windows 10, 8.1, or 7 computer that has a network hosting-enabled Wi-Fi adapter card installed.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Not all USB Wi-Fi adapters come equipped with network hosting abilities. If you decide to use a Wi-Fi adapter, make sure that yours supports network hosting.</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
