<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc46" title="Use Nike Plus With an iPod Touch" shortTile="use-nike-plus-ipod" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-09-25" dateModified="2015-11-13" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Use_Nike_Plus_With_an_iPod_Touch" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Use Nike Plus With an iPod Touch</head><p>If you have just bought Nike Plus, it can be a bit confusing to set up, but, luckily, help is at hand!
</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>If you don't see the Nike + iPod app in your home screen, you will have to enable it <figure rend="Use Nike Plus With an iPod Touch Step 1 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Go to the home screen</item>
<item>Tap Settings.</item>
<item>Scroll down and tap Nike + iPod.</item>
<item>At the top of the screen you will see an on/off switch next to "Nike + iPod". If this is set to off, tap it to turn it on.</item></list></item>
<item>Once you have it enabled, you can change the settings to your preference: <figure rend="Use Nike Plus With an iPod Touch Step 2 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">PowerSong</hi>: Scroll through your list of <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Put_Music_on_an_iPod_Touch">music</ref> to choose the song that really motivates you to run!</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Spoken Feedback</hi>: Choose the gender of the voice of Nike Plus.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Distances</hi>: Choose between imperial and metric distances.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Weight</hi>: Set your current weight to accurately calculate calories burnt.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Lock Screen</hi>: Choose the orientation of the screen during your exercise.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Sensor</hi>: Use this to calibrate your Nike Plus sensor. See the separate instructions below to link the sensor to your iPod.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Remote</hi>: Use this to calibrate the remote, which is not included with your sensor usually.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Setting up the sensor</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Navigate to the Nike Plus settings window in the Settings app. <figure rend="Use Nike Plus With an iPod Touch Step 3 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tap <hi rend="bold">Sensor</hi>. <figure rend="Use Nike Plus With an iPod Touch Step 4 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You will hear a voice saying "Walk around to activate your sensor".</item>
<item>You don't need to walk about, just shake the sensor for a few seconds until "Linked to sensor" appears.</item></list></item>
<item>Tap "Done". <figure rend="Use Nike Plus With an iPod Touch Step 5 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Putting the sensor in the shoe</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Look for the Nike Plus logo on the insole of the shoe. This is the shoe that will contain the space to put the sensor in. <figure rend="Use Nike Plus With an iPod Touch Step 6 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pull out the insole. <figure rend="Use Nike Plus With an iPod Touch Step 7 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You should see the small space where the sensor goes.</item></list></item>
<item>Insert the Nike Plus Sensor into the space and replace the insole. Now that you have everything set up, you can now run using Nike Plus! <figure rend="Use Nike Plus With an iPod Touch Step 8 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Running using Nike Plus</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Tap the Nike + iPod app in your home screen. <figure rend="Use Nike Plus With an iPod Touch Step 9 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Choose the type of workout you want to do: <figure rend="Use Nike Plus With an iPod Touch Step 10 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Basic</hi>: A workout with no goals</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Time</hi>: A workout with a time goal</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Distance</hi>: A workout with a distance goal</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Calorie</hi>: A workout with a calorie burning goal – <hi rend="italic">this will only work if your weight is set properly in settings.</hi></item></list></item>
<item>Choose the goal of your workout. The screen will vary dependent on what you have chosen. <figure rend="Use Nike Plus With an iPod Touch Step 11 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Choose what music you want to accompany your workout. You may wish to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_a_Playlist_on_an_iPod">create a playlist</ref> at this point. <figure rend="Use Nike Plus With an iPod Touch Step 12 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Choose your playlist or shuffle songs and the Sensor screen will appear. <figure rend="Use Nike Plus With an iPod Touch Step 13 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Put your trainers on and jog on the spot to activate the sensor. <figure rend="Use Nike Plus With an iPod Touch Step 14 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>The following screen will come up. Put your headphones in and tap <hi rend="bold">Play</hi> to begin your workout. <figure rend="Use Nike Plus With an iPod Touch Step 15 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Start running and you will periodically hear voice feedback from the iPod. If you wish, you can change the music, pause the workout and  end the workout from this screen. <figure rend="Use Nike Plus With an iPod Touch Step 16 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>To end the workout tap <hi rend="bold">End Workout</hi> and a screen like this will come up: <figure rend="Use Nike Plus With an iPod Touch Step 17 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Congratulations! You have just completed your first workout using Nike Plus! <figure rend="Use Nike Plus With an iPod Touch Step 18 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>The <hi rend="bold">My Workouts</hi> screen is where you can create custom workouts so you can quickly get into running without having to go through the selection screens every time.</item>
<item>These steps may vary dependent on what IOS you are using. This article uses the IOS 4.0 series.</item>
<item>To get the Nike + Sensor, you can go to any major sports shop or retailer or go online.</item>
<item>To get the trainers compatible with Nike sensors, go to any reputable sports shop and you can buy compatible trainers for about £40 ($60). Or, you can buy them online from a reputable retailer if you're sure of your shoe size.</item>
<item>The <hi rend="bold">History</hi> screen is where you will see the best time you have done a mile/kilometre in, the total distance you have ran and a list of all the workouts you have done.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't over-strain yourself when running. Do a little at a time, getting progressively higher every time. If you're serious about running, consult a professional.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>An iPod touch running IOS 4.0 or later</item>
<item>A Nike + Running Sensor</item>
<item>Nike + compatible trainers</item>
<item>In-ear headphones</item></list>
</text>
