<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc168" title="Look Like a Twin" shortTile="look-twin" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-08-25" dateModified="2019-03-30" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Look_Like_a_Twin" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Look Like a Twin</head><p>Do you and your friend want to win a 'Twin Day' contest at school, or do you just want to have some fun and see if you can trick anybody into think you're twins? Either way, you've come to the right article!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Decide on who's 'twin' you want to be. It should probably be a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_a_Good_Friend">friend</ref> who has a similar <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Build_the_Foundations_of_a_Wardrobe">wardrobe</ref> and <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Develop_a_Good_Fashion_Sense">fashion sense</ref> as you. This will make it a lot easier to look like you are a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Survive_Being_a_Twin">twin</ref>. <figure rend="Look Like a Twin Step 1 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure that the person you've chosen <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_Someone_Agree_to_Something_They_Didn't_Mean_to_Agree_With">agrees</ref>. Otherwise, if you try to copy their look and they don't know what's going on, then they may get mad at you or think that you're being creepy. <figure rend="Look Like a Twin Step 2 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Look at what clothes are in each other's wardrobe and choose  outfits that are similar to each other. Choose a few outfits/clothing items and focus on choosing an outfit to wear out of those choices. <figure rend="Look Like a Twin Step 3 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Look in your closet, shoe rack, and jewelry box and pull out EVERYTHING you have two of. For example: If you have 5 silver bracelets, then bring in two of them, or better yet four. <figure rend="Look Like a Twin Step 4 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find a way to go above and beyond everyone else if its a contest. Get two pairs of long knee socks, and each person wears one of each. <figure rend="Look Like a Twin Step 5 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make simple name tags. Write twin one and twin two on two separate half sheets of paper and then tape yarn to both ends of each one, like a necklace! <figure rend="Look Like a Twin Step 6 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure that the clothing have the same <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Change_Your_Style">style</ref>, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Choose_What_Color_to_Wear">colour</ref>, and shade for best results.</item>
<item>Consider <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Design_Your_Own_T_Shirt">designing a shirt</ref> to wear on the days that you want to dress up as twins. To do this, get a plain white T-shirt and using fabric markers, write something on the shirts like, 'Twins!' or 'Twin Day!' Make sure that the marker colours are the same and that the shirts both say the same thing. You can also look for two of the same <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Do_Iron_on_T_Shirts_and_Make_Designs_on_the_Computer">iron-on designs</ref> to iron onto your shirts.</item></list></item>
<item>Choose similar <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Accessorize">accessories</ref>. You don't have to wear accessories, but if you want to, then make sure that they are the same accessories (Basically, if one wears a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Clean_Gold_Jewelry">gold necklace</ref>, the other wears a gold necklace. If one wears earring studs, the other wears earring studs and so forth). <figure rend="Look Like a Twin Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have the same <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Choose_a_Hairstyle">hairstyle</ref>. Here are some ideas (for girls mostly): <figure rend="Look Like a Twin Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you both have fairly long hair, both of you pull your hair up into a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Do_a_Professional_Ponytail">ponytail</ref>.</item>
<item>If one of you has short hair and the other's hair is significantly longer, then the one with short hair can wear hair extensions that are the same colour as their <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_Your_Natural_Hair_Color_Last_Longer">natural hair colour</ref>.</item>
<item>If you have different coloured hair, then one of you <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Find_Hair_Dye">use temporary hair dye</ref> to dye their hair the other person's hair colour or don't bother with having the same hair colour and just focus on having the same hairstyle.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are a girl (or a boy) and you and/or your friend use makeup, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Wean_Yourself_from_Wearing_Makeup_(for_Teens)">go natural</ref> that day and ditch the makeup unless one of you doesn't have any acne and the other does (in that case, if the person with acne wants to, they can cover up their pimples with foundation).</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you don't do this on a contest day like 'Twin Day' then you may get laughed at/looked down at.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Similar clothes as your friend</item>
<item>Plain white T-shirt and fabric markers/iron-on design (for 'twins' T-shirts)</item>
<item>Similar accessories as your friend (optional)</item>
<item>Similar hairstyle as your friend</item></list>
</text>
