<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc213" title="Make a Finance Chart in Numbers" shortTile="make-finance-chart" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-04-08" dateModified="2016-01-09" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make_a_Finance_Chart_in_Numbers" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make a Finance Chart in Numbers</head><p>Making and maintaining your finances is a good way to track where you're spending your money, and also what opportunities are earning you a lot. Creating a finance chart in Numbers can be difficult at first, but it's a breeze once you get the hang of it!
</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Setting up the Table</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open Numbers and choose the Blank template. <figure rend="MakeFinanceChartinNumbersOpenNumbers.png"></figure></item>
<item>Rename the Table Name to a suitable chart title. Include your name, the chart's purpose, and the year. <figure rend="MakeFinanceChartinNumbersTitleChart.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Want to change the font or font size? Look at the Styling the Table section (below).</item></list></item>
<item>Start adding information to the header column cells. Don't forget the date, description, from/to, earnings, and costs. <figure rend="MakeFinanceChartinNumbersAddHeaderInfo.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The date column should be the column farthest to the left.</item>
<item>You may need to adjust the columns' widths as you add information. Find the letter (A, B, etc.) for the column you want to widen or shrink. Select that letter's box and drag the edge the desired direction.</item>
<item>To sub-divide a column (like the earnings or costs one) you'll need to add another header row. Click on any cell, go to the Table tab on the right, find the header options drop-down, and add another header row. Add a column directly before or after one of the sub-divided columns. Select the new header column cell and the one with the text and merge them.</item></list></item>
<item>Format the date column. This lets you enter a date however you like (for example, either April 17, 2014 or 4/17/14) and then re-formats the date to the specified format. <figure rend="MakeFinanceChartNumbersDataDateFormat.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Select all the date cells.</item>
<item>Go to the Cell tab and select Date &amp; Time for the data format.</item>
<item>Set the date and time formats according to your preference.</item></list></item>
<item>Format the earnings or expenses columns. <figure rend="FinanceChartinNumbersDaMONEYYZ.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Select all the cells for money data.</item>
<item>Go to the Cell tab.</item>
<item>Select the Currency setting. Change the settings to your currency type or preferences.</item></list></item>
<item>Delete any extra columns. Selecting the cells, then choose Table &gt; Delete Columns. <figure rend="MakeFinanceChartinNumbersDeleteColumns.png"></figure></item>
<item>Add two footer rows. Click on any cell, go to the Table tab on the right, and find the footer options drop-down. <figure rend="Make a Finance Chart in NumbersAddFooters.png"></figure></item>
<item>Add up the costs and earnings into the first footer column. Select the top footer cell of the earnings, then hit the Function &gt; Sum button. Do the same for the costs cell. <figure rend="MakeaFinanceChartinNumbersSumTopFooter.png"></figure></item>
<item>Calculate your net gain into the lowest footer. Read <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Calculate_the_Difference_Between_Two_Cells_in_Numbers">Calculate the Difference Between Two Cells in Numbers</ref> to learn how. <figure rend="MakeFinanceChartNumbersNetGain.png"></figure></item>
<item>Save your file. Numbers usually autosaves, but it's always better to have your work saved. Use a descriptive file name, preferably including the same information as the chart's title. <figure rend="FinanceChartNumbersSave.png"></figure></item></list>
<head>Recording Information</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Double click on the cell you want to edit, then add in the information.
<list type="unordered"><item>Is a cell too short for all the information you want to add? Adding a note on a cell is easy, just select the cell and then click the Comment button near the top of the app. <figure rend="FinanceChartinNumbersDATAAA.png"></figure></item></list></item></list>
<head>Styling the Table</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Change the font size. Select the cell(s), go to the Cell tab, then enlarge or shrink the font size. <figure rend="FinanceChartNumbersChangeFontSize.png"></figure></item>
<item>Change the font. Every typeface has a personality and can clarify your text while also making the table beautiful and attractive. <figure rend="FinanceChartinNumbersFontz.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Select the cell(s), go to the Cell tab, and choose your new font family.</item></list></item>
<item>Change a cell's background color. You may want to keep it neutral, but you can be wild if you keep the text readable. <figure rend="MakeFinanceChartNumberzChangeCellColor.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Select the cell.</item>
<item>Go to the Cell tab.</item>
<item>Click on the color palette and choose a color.</item></list></item>
<item>Change the text's color! <figure rend="FinanceChartNumbersFontColour.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Select the text.</item>
<item>Go to the Text tab.</item>
<item>Click on the color palette and choose a color.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
