<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc307" title="Find Festivals and Special Events in Chicago" shortTile="find-festivals-special" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-11-19" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Find_Festivals_and_Special_Events_in_Chicago" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Find Festivals and Special Events in Chicago</head><p>Several special events in the city of Chicago have earned a reputations nationwide, if not internationally. You may be familiar with the Taste of Chicago or the Air and Water Show, but the city hosts a multitude of fairs and other events all year long. This article will tell you how to find festivals and special events in Chicago.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Discovering Events Through The City</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Go to www.cityofchicago.org. This is the official website of Chicago with various links for residents and visitors. <figure rend="Find Festivals and Special Events in Chicago Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on the button on the left side of the screen entitled "visitors." The page showcases 2-to-6 events in the center of the screen that are ongoing or are scheduled to start within the week. Each one has its own icon. <figure rend="Find Festivals and Special Events in Chicago Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Point your mouse over the tab on the top of the screen and click "attractions" on the drop-down menu. This brings up a page entitled "Event Search." <figure rend="Find Festivals and Special Events in Chicago Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you know the event you wish to attend, you can use the "keyword" search box to locate the event. Alternatively, if you know you will be in Chicago on a certain date, you can use the "dates" box below the "keyword" box to search for events in the timeframe you specify.</item>
<item>You can also use the drop-down menus to find events by type, such as art or sporting events, by "special interest", or by location. There is also an option below all these menus to indicate if you're only interested in free events.</item></list></item>
<item>Clicking the "Browse Events" icon on the left of this screen will bring you to a calendar menu. You can look through the pages to search for Chicago's upcoming events. <figure rend="Find Festivals and Special Events in Chicago Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Scroll through the calendar and select a specific day on the left side of the screen if you don't want to look through pages of results. If you find something you like on either option, you can click on the link to find out more information. <figure rend="Find Festivals and Special Events in Chicago Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Finding Events Through Special Events Management</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Go to the "Special Events Management" website at chicagoevents.com. This company produces many of the fests in Chicago and the metropolitan area. <figure rend="Find Festivals and Special Events in Chicago Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on one of their "Upcoming Events" on their main page. These events are  their attractions for the following year. There is a link for more information for each event. <figure rend="Find Festivals and Special Events in Chicago Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Attraction Special Events</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Look up an expo center or museum in Chicago. Many times there are special exhibits or events occurring at one or more of these locations that you can attend. <figure rend="Find Festivals and Special Events in Chicago Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>On a museum or expo website look for a tab or icon that says "calendar" or "events." Occasionally you may also find it under "programs." These links will give you information about limited time exhibits or programs.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
