<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc177" title="Be a Distant Relative" shortTile="distant-relative" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2016-02-29" dateModified="2017-02-02" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_a_Distant_Relative" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be a Distant Relative</head><p>Sometimes family just sucks and we all wish we could get away from them for a while. Now some of you may love your family, and just get tired of them; but if you're anything like me, you cannot stand your family. The thought of being naked in front of your highschool sounds a million times more appealing than five minutes with the family. I am the best black sheep and if you want to get away from yours for good.. Just look below. Find the category  of your family and follow the steps. At least consider it.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>If your family is the type that loves to kick you when you're down, I am sorry. I understand that its not right and the truth is, its not you. Its them. First thing you need to do is evaluate. Do you really want to disconnect yourself with them? Are you ready for that?If yes, then good. Not going to say it'll be easy but it'll probably get you some self-esteem that has long been lost.</item>
<item>First thing is first, slowly stop calling them. You're always working. Trying to "make them proud" and doing something with your life. Even if you're not, or you are....be the busy body. Naturally, I forget things. Like calling them back after five texts and seven missed calls. Just so busy working. Working up a sweat at a dance club, or working my thumbs to the nub trying to pick a show on Netflix with a bag of potato chips in my mouth.</item>
<item>If you live close to them, move. Move to a new place with more opportunities. Or just say you did because they'll believe you and are not the type to actually come over.  Whatever works. Moving creates a distance. A distance that some may not want to travel. This is great if you want to stay distanced. If you have a family that won't move for you in the kitchen, its better. They won't come to your home, I promise.</item>
<item>If you're in a relationship, this works better. Wether you want distance from one side or both sides, you can use this. Spend holidays with your partners family. Or not and just say you did. There are PLENTY of excuses not to go do things or spend holidays with them. Use each other to your full potential. But make sure its a mutual agreement between you and your spouse. No secrets.</item>
<item>If you want to know how your family is doing, pick a relative that feels almost as equally about them as you do but still suffers through all their bullshit. One you get along with. Mine is my sister. That way you are in the loop of who is doing what and be at ease in your mind. Hate and love come hand in hand.  I really hate my family but I love them too and I would like to know their health status.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you want to "stay connected" send birthday cards. Dollar store has cheap ones. Stock up and set a reminder on your phone to mail it out.</item>
<item>If they have done you wrong multiple times, don't go back. You deserve better.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>May ruin relationships</item></list>
</text>
