<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc23" title="Get Your Kids Involved in Noncompetitive Sports" shortTile="kids-involved-noncompetitive" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2017-03-22" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get_Your_Kids_Involved_in_Noncompetitive_Sports" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get Your Kids Involved in Noncompetitive Sports</head><p>Competitive sports can be a little too much for some kids, especially younger ones. If you want to get your child started in sports but want to avoid the competitive nature of the activity, you do have a few options, such as looking into noncompetitive leagues or having your child join a noncompetitive class. You can also help your child to be more active by doing things like taking walks as a family and encouraging them to go outside.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Finding Noncompetitive Team Sports</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Pick a sport. If your kid is very young, you can try them out in whatever sport you feel comfortable with to see if it's a good fit. It's also a good idea to think about what would be a good fit for your child; if they don't seem to like playing catch, maybe t-ball isn't for them. If your kid is a bit older, you might ask them or let them try a few different sports to see what they enjoy the most. <figure rend="Get Your Kids Involved in Noncompetitive Sports Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Look for noncompetitive leagues. Many cities have leagues that aren't competitive, especially for younger kids. Look at the parks and recreation department, for instance, or contact your local YMCA. You'll likely be able to find a noncompetitive league in your area that places the emphasis on fun and fitness rather than competition. <figure rend="Get Your Kids Involved in Noncompetitive Sports Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Encourage your child to join a sports club instead. Many schools have sports clubs for kids who don't want to play on the school team. These clubs offer a way for kids to be involved in a sport without competition being as much of an emphasis. <figure rend="Get Your Kids Involved in Noncompetitive Sports Step 3.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Playing Individual Sports</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find a sports class. Another option for a noncompetitive is to choose a sport that is noncompetitive by nature and find a local class. For instance, your child could take recreational gymnastics, martial arts, or dancing. You can find classes through your parks and recreation department, or through local studios, martial arts centers, and gyms. <figure rend="Get Your Kids Involved in Noncompetitive Sports Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Keep in mind that the competitiveness of many sports depends on how you play them. For instance, dancing can be competitive, but your child can also just take a class for fun.</item>
<item>Golf is another sport your kid could try.</item></list></item>
<item>Try rock climbing. Rock climbing may strike a bit of fear in your heart as a parent, but it can help kids build confidence. Plus, they are only in competition with themselves. Each climb is a chance to learn something new and to gain new skills. Check your area for rock climbing walls that offer classes to kids. <figure rend="Get Your Kids Involved in Noncompetitive Sports Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Offer yoga. Yoga is another great athletic activity that your child can get involved in. It increases flexibility, and it is completely noncompetitive. It can also help with focus and balance. Many studios offer classes for kids, so check in your area to see what's being offered. <figure rend="Get Your Kids Involved in Noncompetitive Sports Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Your kid might not like the idea of going to a new class by themselves, so why not take a class together? Many studios offer kid and parent yoga classes, for instance. You'll both have fun and increase your activity level at the same time.</item></list></item>
<item>Sign your kid up for swimming lessons. Another option for an individual sport is swimming. While of course swimming can be competitive, it can also just be something fun your kid learns to do. Start with swimming lessons, and then check to see if there is a noncompetitive league in your area. Plus, learning to swim gives your kid a necessary life skill. <figure rend="Get Your Kids Involved in Noncompetitive Sports Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get the equipment for sports like skating and biking. If you want your kid to try other sports, such as skating and biking, you'll need to get them the necessary equipment. Your kid can rent skates if they only skate at a rink, but if they're going to skate elsewhere, they'll need the skates to do it. Similarly, biking can be a good sport for kids, but they need the bikes to do it. Also, check if your area has any clubs for kids that focus on these sports.  <figure rend="Get Your Kids Involved in Noncompetitive Sports Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Encouraging Other Fitness Activities</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Emphasize having a good time. No matter what sport your child is playing, the key is to emphasize having fun. Let them know how proud you are of them for trying and sticking to a sport, and encourage them to have fun while doing it. <figure rend="Get Your Kids Involved in Noncompetitive Sports Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For instance, you could say, "It's great that you're trying yoga! You're doing a great job, and it's so good that you're having fun doing it!"</item></list></item>
<item>Stay fit as a family. If you're trying to encourage more exercise, you need to model it to your child. Go on nightly walks together, or check out local hiking trails. You can also take bike rides together or go swimming. In the house, you can have dance parties, where kids likely won't even realize they're getting exercise in. <figure rend="Get Your Kids Involved in Noncompetitive Sports Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You may also want to look into parent and child classes. These may be available at local gyms, dance studios, and martial arts centers.</item></list></item>
<item>Buy active games. If your kid loves being inside gaming, start buying games that encourage them to get up and move. Many video games encourage things like dancing, for instance, which engages your child in exercising without them even realizing it. <figure rend="Get Your Kids Involved in Noncompetitive Sports Step 11.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For non-screen games, go old-school with games like Twister.</item></list></item>
<item>Send your kids outside. One way to encourage fitness is to limit screen time and send kids outside to play with siblings and other neighborhood kids. It helps to provide outdoor activities, such as a swing set, jump ropes, hula hoops, and water guns. <figure rend="Get Your Kids Involved in Noncompetitive Sports Step 12.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always clear it with your child's pediatrician before your kid starts a sport.</item></list>
</text>
