<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc36" title="Overcome Fear of Being Hit by a Ball" shortTile="overcome-fear-being" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-08-08" dateModified="2018-09-24" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Overcome_Fear_of_Being_Hit_by_a_Ball" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Overcome Fear of Being Hit by a Ball</head><p>It's not uncommon for people to be afraid of getting hit by a ball in any sport, whether it be baseball, football, or even soccer. The flinch response is a natural reaction to what the body senses as danger and can be triggered by distance anticipation and how fast the ball is traveling. Here are a few ways to work with that fear and make the flinch response go away all together.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Start off throwing with a partner at a short distance. Generally you will notice that your flinch response will come into play at large distances where you have too much time to anticipate the landing. These throws will be simulating pop-flys or punts for football. 
<list type="unordered"><item>Find out what distance you are comfortable with and increase it slightly every few catches and returns. </item>
<item>If you find that you have gone too far and start flinching again, return to a closer distance and throw from there for awhile until you are comfortable enough to try again.</item></list></item>
<item>Keep your eye on the ball. It may just be another term you hear too often but there's a reason for that (it works). When you take it literally and focus on the ball as it is travelling at you, you can better grasp the situation and train your body to react to what you see. If you look away from the ball, you reduce your chances of catching it to almost zero.</item>
<item>Increase throwing speed over time. Have your partner gradually increase how fast they throw the ball to you and throw straight to each other.
<list type="unordered"><item>This exercise should really only be increased in speed every few throwing sessions and will help you over time. Don't rush yourself to try to do it all and get rid of your flinch response all in one afternoon. It won't happen and you could get hurt.</item></list></item>
<item>Practice. Although it seems cliché, it's the most important step. You should be throwing with your partner or a range of partners every day for at the very least, an hour. You won't just get it over night, so the more you practice, the better you will become. Remember to take it easy on yourself and never overthrow your arm because it will catch up to you later on. Take your training slow but steady and you will get rid of your flinch response in a matter of weeks.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try different types of balls to throw at first, then work your way up to the one for your sport.</item>
<item>Take your time, people grow and adapt at different rates and it can take awhile for the flinch response to completely go away</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Never overthrow your arm. If you do, make sure to ice it and relax it for a few days until the pain subsides.</item></list>
</text>
