<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc88" title="Determine Your Dell Service Tag" shortTile="determine-dell-service" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-12-17" dateModified="2019-05-23" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Determine_Your_Dell_Service_Tag" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Determine Your Dell Service Tag</head><p>This wikiHow teaches you how to find the service tag for a Dell computer. The service tag is exclusive to your computer, and can be used to look up information about your computer or identify the computer to Dell customer support.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Using the Dell Website</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open Dell's <ref target="http://www.dell.com/support/home/us/en/19/Products/?app=drivers">Drivers and Downloads page</ref>. This is the page from which you can allow Dell to identify your computer's service tag. <figure rend="Determine Your Dell Service Tag Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . It's in the middle of the page. <figure rend="Determine Your Dell Service Tag Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>In some cases, you'll click <hi rend="bold">Detect Product</hi> here instead.</item></list></item>
<item>Wait for the website to detect your computer's information. This may take a few minutes. Once the "Support" page opens, you can proceed. <figure rend="Think-Like-a-Graphic-Designer-Step-6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Review your service tag. You'll see the seven-digit service tag to the right of the "Service Tag" heading at the top of the page. <figure rend="Determine Your Dell Service Tag Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Using Command Prompt on Windows</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Consider looking for the service tag number on the label. If your Dell computer's label is still readable, you may be able to find the service tag on it. You'll find the seven-digit service tag on a label in one of the following places depending on your computer: <figure rend="Determine Your Dell Service Tag Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">Laptops</hi> — On the bottom of the laptop housing, or inside the battery compartment.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Desktops</hi> — On the back of the tower. You may also find a black service tag sticker with white letters on the top of the tower.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">All-in-Ones</hi> — On the back of the monitor.</item></list></item>
<item>Open Start . Click the Windows logo in the bottom-left corner of the screen. <figure rend="Determine Your Dell Service Tag Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Search for Command Prompt. Type in  to do so. <figure rend="Determine Your Dell Service Tag Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click  Command Prompt. It's at the top of the Start window. Doing this opens the Command Prompt window. <figure rend="Determine Your Dell Service Tag Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Enter the service tag command. Type in  and press . <figure rend="Determine Your Dell Service Tag Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Review the service tag. Below the "SerialNumber" text output, you'll see the seven-digit service tag listed. <figure rend="Determine Your Dell Service Tag Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Using Terminal on Linux</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Consider looking for the service tag number on the label. If your Dell computer's label is still readable, you may be able to find the service tag on it. You'll find the seven-digit service tag on a label in one of the following places depending on your computer: <figure rend="Determine Your Dell Service Tag Step 11 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">Laptops</hi> — On the bottom of the laptop housing, or inside the battery compartment.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Desktops</hi> — On the back of the tower. You may also find a black service tag sticker with white letters on the top of the tower.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">All-in-Ones</hi> — On the back of the monitor.</item></list></item>
<item>Open Terminal. Click or double-click the  <hi rend="bold">Terminal</hi> app icon, or press  to open the Terminal window. <figure rend="Determine Your Dell Service Tag Step 12 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Enter the service tag command. Type in  and press . <figure rend="Determine Your Dell Service Tag Step 13 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Enter your password. Type in the administrator password you use to log into your computer, then press . <figure rend="Determine Your Dell Service Tag Step 14 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You won't see the password's characters or asterisks appear in Terminal as you type.</item></list></item>
<item>Review the service tag. You'll see the seven-digit service tag displayed below the password entry. <figure rend="Determine Your Dell Service Tag Step 15.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you're attempting to find the service tag for a printer, tablet, or other Dell item, look for the service tag's sticker. You'll typically find it on the back of the item (or on the scanner tray in a Dell printer/scanner), though Dell tablets may require you to open the physical panel on the back of the tablet in order to see the service tag.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you have Linux installed on your Dell PC, the Dell website's <hi rend="bold">Detect PC</hi> service may not work due to interference from the Linux software.</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
