<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc38" title="Get Started in Women's Lacrosse" shortTile="started-womens-lacrosse" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-06-09" dateModified="2016-12-22" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get_Started_in_Women%27s_Lacrosse" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get Started in Women's Lacrosse</head><p>The road to get into women's lacrosse is a long one. Do you have the drive and the desire? You have to know going into any sport that it is tough work, but it will pay off in the end. Maybe you are uncertain about the journey that would lie ahead of you. If you have that drive and desire, then these steps can help you get started with women's lacrosse.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Learning the Sport</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Buy or borrow someone's lacrosse stick and ball. They can be expensive, so look at thrift stores, Craigslist, secondhand sports shops, or just buy a cheap stick from your local sports store. <figure rend="Get Started in Women's Lacrosse Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Learn to cradle the ball. Put the ball in the net on the end of your stick. Place your dominant hand at the neck of the stick and your other hand at the bottom of the lacrosse stick. Now you need to rotate your dominant hand up and down. Once you have mastered this process, do so with your non-dominant hand. As you practice this, switch back and forth from hand to hand. Now you can then go to a one handed cradling. <figure rend="Get Started in Women's Lacrosse Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Learn to pass. This is done just as you would throw a ball. Raise your non-throwing arm up to point where you throw. Raise your throwing arm up. Reach back and throw. To catch the ball, you need to do so with soft fingers. Imagine you are a coil and let the net absorb the ball's energy. Do not reach for the ball. Finally, finish with a cradle and pass. <figure rend="Get Started in Women's Lacrosse Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Play catch with a partner. Anyone will do. Ask your sibling, your girlfriend or a neighbor. If you do not have a partner, then play wallball. To play wallball, find a brick wall and throw a ball at the wall. On the rebound of the ball, catch and cradle it. Repeat this several times. <figure rend="Get Started in Women's Lacrosse Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Learn how to scoop a groundball. First, choke up on the head of the stick. Have your back hand on the bottom of the stick. Make sure your back leg is planted. Then step through with your front leg and scoop the ball through. Cradle, then tuck the stick. <figure rend="Get Started in Women's Lacrosse Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Learn all the rules. Once you have played the game it is important to learn the game fully. You should go to uslacrosse.org and download the rules. Knowing the game on every aspect helps you to learn not only what you can and can't do, but it also helps you understand the game better. <figure rend="Get Started in Women's Lacrosse Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Work out. Cardio is a crucial part of women's lacrosse, or any sport for that matter. So running is a big part of the game. Being in shape and fit is crucial to the game. When it comes to strength training, upper body workouts are very important for shot speed. Core work is vital for shots and defense. <figure rend="Get Started in Women's Lacrosse Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Joining a Team</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find a team. Once you have the fundamentals down, you can start playing on teams. <figure rend="Get Started in Women's Lacrosse Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Once you are on a team, you should practice your fundamentals. The team that wins is the team that can pass and catch the ball, and who can scoop a groundball. It is important to keep improving your skills.</item>
<item>Once you get to high school, try out for your school's Girl's Lacrosse team. The main goal is for you to make it onto the team. Two important side pieces will be your grades and staying out of trouble. Remember that you are always a representative of your school and community. Depending on how good your high school team is, the greater the honor to be a freshman that makes varsity.</item></list></item>
<item>Look for competitive travel teams once you're good enough. This will provide you greater experience and interaction with other girls you may play with or against in high school. <figure rend="Get Started in Women's Lacrosse Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Pursuing College Team Opportunities</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Go to camps. They can teach you new things that you haven't learned before. They also give expose you to the college recruitment process. When you come back home, you can share your new skills with girls who didn't have the same opportunity to attend those camps. This is always a benefit to your team and will help you become more valuable as a team member. <figure rend="Get Started in Women's Lacrosse Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Talk to your coach. Tell him you want to play at the college level and that you would like him to start helping you get to the next level. Ask him/her to critique your current level of play. Learn from the suggestions that the coach can provide. <figure rend="Get Started in Women's Lacrosse Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make a highlight tape. This will be handy for college coaches looking for film footage. It is important to highlight your technique, effort, and good characteristics. <figure rend="Get Started in Women's Lacrosse Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Investigate your college options. Once you have gotten an offer, you should look at the school. You should visit and see what they have to offer and whether you like the campus. If you do not like it, then do not accept. You have to remember that this will be where you could spend the next four or five years of your life, so it is important you are happy there. <figure rend="Get Started in Women's Lacrosse Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Understand the commitment. Once you have accepted your offer, then it is important to understand what you are committing to. Your hard work and dedication has finally paid off, but your hard work has only just begun. Once you get to the collegiate level, playing lacrosse becomes more of a job than a hobby. You are expected to train vigorously all the time while keeping up with your academics. If you don't do well in school, you'll end up not having a school to play for. Therefore, it is important to keep it fun. If you do not keep it fun, then you will quit because it is a job. <figure rend="Get Started in Women's Lacrosse Step 14.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Grades and the ACT are crucial to playing women's lacrosse. Without these you cannot go anywhere no matter how good you are.</item></list>
</text>
