<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc314" title="Be Content Living in a House You Don't Like" shortTile="content-living-house" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-04-29" dateModified="2018-11-05" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_Content_Living_in_a_House_You_Don%27t_Like" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be Content Living in a House You Don't Like</head><p><hi rend="italic">Oh, I hate this place.</hi> Find yourself saying this about where you live? Examine why and what can be done to improve your comfort level since this is where your life is happening for now!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Ask the right questions. Owning or leasing this property? Can you make changes? Whose approval do you need and have you approached them about it? Even a small budget will allow for some creature comforts which can distract from more unpleasant facets. If you own it, a bank may help finance the improvements, if you rent and can improve the property by contributing labor in exchange for returning receipts for materials deducted from your rent check, there may be bigger opportunities. <figure rend="Be Content Living in a House You Don't Like Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Note pros and cons. Write on one column or sheet of paper what attracted you to the property first or what have you grown to love and on the other what seems to trouble you or depress you the most. Be specific as possible. Take your time and then prioritize the top few for what to reinforce and what to change. <figure rend="Be Content Living in a House You Don't Like Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>What have you noticed about other peoples flats or apartments or homes that seems most attractive to your personal style? Was it the stark simplicity? The warm colors? The crowded coziness that seemed to cuddle you in? Bright colors and lighting? Indirect lighting and lots of fabric contrast? Feminine touches?</item>
<item>What do you need to change in your appointments to be satisfied with your space reflecting your ambitions? Did someone cut down all the nice trees nearby? Is your office or your child's school now a longer travel distance? Noise? Pollution? What? Narrow it down by numbering the priority of the projects and setting a weekly budget.</item></list></item>
<item>Work on what you feel to be trouble areas. Ask friends for ideas and consult wikiHow. Can't afford 5 gallons of paint yet, maybe those pallets behind the building next door to work would make a great accent wall on one end of the room if the wood was installed diagonally? Clean up the details of the lawn and yard. Plant a tree or hedge. The bigger projects may be a bit farther off, but the rope lights under your sofa while watching a movie are great! Could have done that years ago! <figure rend="Be Content Living in a House You Don't Like Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You could spice up the place with a lick of paint, or some wall paper.</item>
<item>If you don't have the money for that, buy key decorations that bring out the colour/style in your existing walls. Be mindful, however, because you don't want to cause clutter.</item></list></item>
<item>Improve your attitude about your living space. Effort pays off not only in improving it. Once you start to invest your time and energy into attention to the details, your pride will return which will reflect in the space itself. Knowing it may not be everything yet, but is moving that direction brings contentment. <figure rend="Be Content Living in a House You Don't Like Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find things you like about your home. Even if you don't enjoy living there, there must still be a few things you like about it. Whether it is someone you like, or something nearby, every place has something good about it.</item></list>
</text>
