<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc67" title="Install the Unity Web Player on PC or Mac" shortTile="install-unity-web" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2019-04-12" dateModified="2019-05-13" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Install_the_Unity_Web_Player_on_PC_or_Mac" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Install the Unity Web Player on PC or Mac</head><p>This wikiHow article shows you how to install the Unity Web Player on your PC or Mac. The Unity Web Player makes it easy to play browser-based games made with the Unity platform. While the Unity Web Player is no longer supported or updated by Unity, it can still be downloaded and used to play games.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Downloading Unity Web Player for PC</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Go to the <ref target="https://unity3d.com/webplayer">Unity Web Player</ref> download page. To download the Unity Web Player, you must visit this URL: <ref target="https://unity3d.com/webplayer">https://unity3d.com/webplayer</ref> <figure rend="Install the Unity Web Player on PC or Mac Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the blue  button. You should see the download button under “Unity Web Player for Windows.” <figure rend="Install the Unity Web Player on PC or Mac Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Note that this web player requires Windows XP/7/8/10 to work properly. If you don’t have a compatible version of Windows, you won’t be able to run the Unity Web Player.</item></list></item>
<item>Click  to download the file. A window will pop up allowing you to choose where on your computer you want to save the file. You can use the default “Downloads” folder or use the navigation to select a different location. <figure rend="Install the Unity Web Player on PC or Mac Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Once you are ready, click “Save” in the bottom right corner of the window to download the application.</item></list></item>
<item>Double click on the downloaded file. The file will be titled “UnityWebPlayer64.” This action will start the installation process. <figure rend="Install the Unity Web Player on PC or Mac Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click  to allow the installer to run. A window will pop up asking, “Do you want to allow this app to make changes to your device?” You must click “Yes” in order to install Unity Web Player. <figure rend="Install the Unity Web Player on PC or Mac Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . The first part of the Unity Web Player Setup asks you to agree to their “License Agreement.” You must agree to install the app. <figure rend="Install the Unity Web Player on PC or Mac Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wait for the Unity Web Player to install. The Unity Web Player should only take a minute to install. <figure rend="Install the Unity Web Player on PC or Mac Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . After the installation is complete, you will see a “Finish” button in the lower right corner of the window. Click on this to complete installation of the Unity Web Player. You will now be able to play games from Unity in your web browser. <figure rend="Install the Unity Web Player on PC or Mac Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Downloading Unity Web Player for Mac</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Go to the <ref target="https://unity3d.com/webplayer">Unity Web Player</ref> download page. Here’s the direct link to the download page: <ref target="https://unity3d.com/webplayer">https://unity3d.com/webplayer</ref> <figure rend="Install the Unity Web Player on PC or Mac Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the  tab. The page has two download tabs: Windows and Mac OS X. Click on the one for Mac, or you will download the wrong file. <figure rend="Install the Unity Web Player on PC or Mac Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on the blue  button. Beneath the text “Unity Web Player for Mac OS X,” you will see a download button to click on. <figure rend="Install the Unity Web Player on PC or Mac Step 11.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Note that this web player requires Mac OS X 10.7 or newer, or it will not work for you. If you have an older version, you can use this article to fix that: <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Upgrade_Mac_System_Software">Upgrade Mac System Software</ref>.</item></list></item>
<item>Open the  folder on your desktop. After the file has downloaded, locate it in your “Downloads” folder. <figure rend="Install the Unity Web Player on PC or Mac Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Double click on the file to open the installer. The downloaded file should be titled “webplayer-mini.” <figure rend="Install the Unity Web Player on PC or Mac Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on  to begin installation. A window will open with a “License Agreement” that you must agree to before installation can begin. You should see the “Agree” option in the bottom right corner of the app. <figure rend="Install the Unity Web Player on PC or Mac Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wait for the Unity Web Player to finish installing. The web player should only take a minute to install. <figure rend="Install the Unity Web Player on PC or Mac Step 15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . Once installation is complete, you will see a “Finish” button in the bottom right corner of the window. Click on this and the Unity Web Player will now be installed, allowing you to play Unity games in your web browser. <figure rend="Install the Unity Web Player on PC or Mac Step 16.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
