<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc293" title="Make Pinball Games Out of Cardboard" shortTile="make-pinball-games" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2017-08-18" dateModified="2019-10-17" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make_Pinball_Games_Out_of_Cardboard" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make Pinball Games Out of Cardboard</head><p>Pinball is a classic arcade game. When it comes to making your own pinball machine, there are tons of options. You can keep it simple, like putting together a cardboard shoe box machine that's great for kids, or you can restore or even build a complex pinball machine for more advanced use. Whichever project strikes your fancy, you're guaranteed to have fun!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Creating a Pinball Machine From a Cardboard Shoe Box</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Gather your materials. This is what you will need: <figure rend="Pinball-game-2340087_640.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Shoe box. You can also use the top</item>
<item>Clear tape</item>
<item>2 cups from an egg carton</item>
<item>Duct tape for decoration (optional)</item>
<item>Scissors</item>
<item>Straws</item>
<item>Brass paper fastener (1/2" or 3/4")</item>
<item>Thin cardboard (the cardboard from a cereal box or tissue box etc.)</item>
<item>Marble or other small ball</item>
<item>Odds and ends to create obstacles in the playing field (optional). Examples include:
<list type="unordered"><item>Small paper cups</item>
<item>Bottle caps</item>
<item>Pipe cleaners, markers, aluminum foil, popsicle (craft) sticks</item></list></item></list></item>
<item>Paint and decorate the shoe box if desired. Let dry overnight.</item>
<item>Set the box on an angle.
<list type="unordered"><item>Tape or glue the two egg carton cups to one end of the shoe box.</item></list></item>
<item>Create a ball-launching lever.
<list type="unordered"><item>Fold a two-inch strip of cardboard lengthwise.</item>
<item>Attach the cardboard to the lower left hand corner of the shoe box using a brass fastener.</item>
<item>Test the lever by flicking it with your finger to see if it can shoot the marble. Adjust the lever as needed.</item></list></item>
<item>Design the playing field. <figure rend="PinballBox.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>PBS Kids recommends making a path on the left side of the box by taping down a straw to lead your marble to the top of the box.</item>
<item>Add a curved piece of paper to the top left corner of the shoe box to enable your marble to roll smoothly to the right.</item>
<item>Create an obstacle course with miscellaneous objects on the right side of the box.</item></list></item>
<item>Try it out! Keep testing the playing field until you are satisfied with how the pinball machine works.</item></list>
<head>Creating a Pinball Machine from a Larger Cardboard Box</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Create a ball launcher to start with.
<list type="unordered"><item>Materials needed:
<list type="unordered"><item>Pencil</item>
<item>Thumbtack</item>
<item>Washer wide enough to place around the pencil</item>
<item>Spring wide enough to thread around the pencil</item></list></item>
<item>Stick the thumbtack in the pencil eraser.</item>
<item>Slide the washer up next to the thumbtack.</item>
<item>Thread the spring onto the pencil.</item></list></item>
<item>Install the ball launcher <figure rend="IMG_0028 (2).jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Cut a hole just big enough to fit the pencil.</item>
<item>Thread the launcher through the hole.</item>
<item>Use a small piece of cardboard to create a chute next to the launcher for the marble.</item>
<item>Use your imagination and create more obstacles.</item></list></item>
<item>Add flippers to your pinball table.
<list type="unordered"><item>Determine where you want to locate the flippers.</item>
<item>Cut slits in the cardboard box big enough to insert craft sticks.</item>
<item>Insert craft sticks. Reinforce the slits with duct tape.</item></list></item>
<item>Add obstacles to the playing field.
<list type="unordered"><item>Attach the cardboard bat to a craft stick or other type of stick.</item>
<item>Place the marble on top of the thumbtack, pull back the launcher, and let it go!</item>
<item>The Scientific Mom has many suggestions for creating playing field obstacles, including setting up ramps, bells, and flaps.
<list type="unordered"><item>Create tunnels and ramps out of toilet paper tubes.</item>
<item>Create flaps using a skewer and cut paper.</item></list></item></list></item>
<item>Start playing and having fun!</item></list>
<head>Things You’ll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>For a cardboard pinball table:
<list type="unordered"><item>Clear tape</item>
<item>2 cups from an egg carton</item>
<item>Duct tape for decoration (optional)</item>
<item>Scissors</item>
<item>Straws</item>
<item>Brass paper fastener (1/2" or 3/4")</item>
<item>Thin cardboard (the cardboard from a cereal box works well)</item>
<item>Marble or other small ball</item>
<item>Odds and ends to create obstacles in the playing field.  Examples include:
<list type="unordered"><item>Small paper cups</item>
<item>Bottle caps</item>
<item>Pipe cleaners, markers, aluminum foil, popsicle (craft) sticks</item></list></item></list></item>
<item>For a restored machine:
<list type="unordered"><item>Cotton swabs</item>
<item>Isopropyl alcohol</item>
<item>Screwdrivers</item>
<item>Allen wrench set</item>
<item>Replacement pinball machine bulbs</item>
<item>400-grit sandpaper</item>
<item>Non-toxic cleaner like Simple Green</item>
<item>Lint-free cloth</item>
<item>Glass cleaner</item>
<item>Paper towels</item></list></item></list>
</text>
