<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc182" title="Improve Your Marriage Through the Law of Attraction" shortTile="improve-marriage" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2016-06-15" dateModified="2016-06-15" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Improve_Your_Marriage_Through_the_Law_of_Attraction" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Improve Your Marriage Through the Law of Attraction</head><p>Do you want to fix/improve your relationship with your spouse? No matter how your current relationship is you can always improve it by using the law of attraction to your advantage! Read on for getting the dream relationship that you have always wanted in your life.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Loving Yourself</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>You need to know that there are two people in a marriage. When you want a marriage to work then you must remember that you can only "change", one person which is you. So before you start working on the other person, work on yourself. You must love yourself and give to yourself what you want your partner to give you.</item>
<item>Take a sheet of paper and write down all of the things that you want your partner to say to you. Every romantic line and every promise that you want to hear, no matter how stupid it seems. Write every single word that you wish your partner said to you! Write it in first person. For eg- " I love you baby and I will always keep you happy no matter what." Once you write that letter, read and evaluate it for the things that are promised in the letter. In the case above, love and happiness are promised/said. Now you must give to yourself whatever is promised. In the case above  the person should give love to him/herself love and make him/herself happy.</item>
<item>Stand in front of the mirror and say to yourself, "I love you." Feel as much as love as you can as you say this. You can extend this and have a full talk with yourself but remember to tell yourself that you love you every single day</item>
<item>Affirm to yourself that you deserve love and a loving relationship. For this you can write a list of all the things that you genuinely love about your self and your qualities. Say to yourself over and over again and believe that 'I am worthy of great love.'</item>
<item>Be grateful for yourself and take the time to do things that make you happy every day.</item></list>
<head>Loving your Spouse</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Write a love letter to your spouse stating all of the things that you love in him/her and all things that you are grateful for. It is not necessary to give the letter to your partner but it is important to write it.</item>
<item>Forgive your spouse. Forgive him/her for whatever big or small thing done by them has hurt you. This will help you to focus on the things that you love in him/her.</item>
<item>Every day write down 3 things that you love and are grateful for in your partner. Do this for a minimum of 21 days.</item>
<item>Imagine that you and your partner in a perfect relationship doing things you love and enjoy together. Believe that you can have that relationship and when you get that impulse or intuitive nudge from within, act.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try to make the best of time you have together and try your best to make it positive. Try to feel good, be happy and enjoy as much as you can.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not think about what you don't want in your partner and do not think about how the relationship will improve. Only focus on the end result which is a happy marriage.</item></list>
</text>
