<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc234" title="Win the World Food Prize" shortTile="win-world-food-prize" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-01-19" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Win_the_World_Food_Prize" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Win the World Food Prize</head><p>Informally called the "Nobel Prize of Food and Agriculture," the World Food Prize recognizes exceptional achievements that have increased the quality, quantity or availability of food in the world. This is the process for nominating an individual for this highly prestigious award, founded by Nobel Peace Prize Laureate Dr. Norman E. Borlaug.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Perform a specific, monumental achievement that has increased the quality, quantity or availability of food in the world. This achievement can be at any point along the food production or distribution chain, so long as it has benefited large numbers of people. <figure rend="Become-an-Anger-Management-Coach-Step-1-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Read The World Food Prize Call to Nominate (.PDF) booklet and review The World Food Prize <ref target="http://www.worldfoodprize.org/en/nominations/">nomination page</ref> to ensure the accomplishment of the nominee is consistent with the objectives of The World Food Prize. <figure rend="Become-the-Executor-of-an-Estate-Step-7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Send a nomination to the World Food Prize Secretariat from any academic or research institution, private or public organization, corporate entity, or governmental unit. This nomination must include: <figure rend="Become-Involved-in-Medical-Research-Studies-Step-2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Biographical information about the nominee.</item>
<item>A statement of achievement of up to 800 words detailing the specific, monumental breakthrough the nominee has accomplished.</item>
<item>A statement of impact of up to 800 words detailing how the achievement has increased the quality, quantity or availability of food in the world. This statement should include information detailing the number of people affected, the geographical regions impacted, and the effect of the accomplishment over time in either enhancing health, nutrition and quality of life, or reducing levels of poverty, hunger and malnutrition.</item>
<item>A letter signed by the head of the nominating organization.</item>
<item>Supporting documents including articles about the impact of the nominee's work, or pieces by or about the nominee discussing the accomplishment.</item></list></item>
<item>Obtain two or more letters seconding the nomination. These should be from individuals or organizations familiar with the nominee's work but not associated with the nominating organization.  <figure rend="Take-Legal-Action-for-a-Player-Contract-Breach-Step-1.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Provide electronic copies of the statement of impact and statement of achievement in Microsoft Word Document (.doc) or Rich Text Format (.rtf) to The World Food Prize Secretariat, even if the nomination is submitted via the mail.</item>
<item>The World Food Prize was founded by 1970 Nobel Peace Prize Laureate Dr. Norman E. Borlaug to recognize achievements similar to those for which he won the Nobel Prize. Read <ref target="http://www.worldfoodprize.org/en/dr_norman_e_borlaug/about_norman_borlaug/">Dr. Norman Borlaug's biography</ref> before submitting a nomination to review his achievements.</item>
<item>Nominations are valid for 3 years once successfully submitted.</item>
<item>The nomination period opens on October 16, World Food Day, and ends on April 1 of the year for which they are to be considered.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>The World Food Prize is not awarded for culinary ability-- do not submit nominations for food products or dishes.</item>
<item>All nominations must be received in the English language.</item>
<item>Nominees must be living and healthy enough to receive The World Food Prize in Des Moines, IA. They also must deliver an acceptance speech and participate in World Food Prize week activities.</item>
<item>The World Food Prize Council of Advisors holds the ultimate authority in determining the winner of The World Food Prize, based on recommendations from the Selection Committee chaired by Dr. Norman E. Borlaug.</item></list>
</text>
