<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc267" title="Search the Internet for Health Information" shortTile="search-internet-health" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-10-16" dateModified="2019-06-15" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Search_the_Internet_for_Health_Information" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Search the Internet for Health Information</head><p>One of the commonest complaints patients have about doctors is that they do not provide enough information about their medical problem. As a result, many patients turn to the Internet to become better informed, but quite often they are met with frustration. For one thing, there is too much information – and this information overload causes patients to get lost. Another risk is that some of the facts can be quite scary, and not all patients are willing to confront the truth or their own mortality; and because some of it is in technical jargon, it may be incomprehensible. This is why many patients prefer not doing a search at all. To help prevent all this, here’s a short and simple guide to help you find reliable information on the Internet.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Get organized by first identifying the purpose of your search. Is it a simple search, where you just want to find out information about the side effects of the medications your doctor has put you on? The internet is great for this – and it’s often just a question of typing in the generic name of the drug and scanning the results. However, your search could be far more complex. You may want to find out why your child has had fever for many days. Do you have a diagnosis? Or is this still uncertain? <figure rend="Search the Internet for Health Information Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Write down the keywords your doctor has used even if it is in medical jargon you cannot understand. <figure rend="Search the Internet for Health Information Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Learn to scan information quickly. Just because you get 1 million hits on Google does not mean you need to scan all of them! Most of these sites will have the same information, so you are very unlikely to gain much by visiting more than 3-4  sites. Open 4-5 windows and scan them quickly to determine which seems the best. Fortunately, most of the best information is on the first page of your  search. You can also focus your search by providing more specific keywords. <figure rend="Search the Internet for Health Information Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use specialized health search engines such as <ref target="http://www.healia.com">Healia</ref> which provide focused results. Your other option is to visit specialized health websites such as <ref target="http://medlineplus.gov">MedlinePlus</ref>, <ref target="http://www.mayoclinic.com">Mayo Clinic</ref>, or <ref target="http://www.mercksource.com/pp/us/cns/cns_home.jsp">MerckSource</ref>. These are great for providing basic background information  and they are very reliable and up-to-date. <figure rend="Search the Internet for Health Information Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Trust your intelligence and remember that the secret is repetition. Don’t worry if you can’t make sense of the initial results. This is bound to happen because this is unfamiliar territory for you. You will get better with time, and this will help you get to the gold very quickly. If you cannot make sense of some of the medical terms, there are excellent medical dictionaries and encyclopedias online. Just think of yourself as a detective who is trying to unearth elusive clues! <figure rend="Search the Internet for Health Information Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>What if you do not know what your diagnosis is? A great site to find out about some of the diagnostic possibilities is <ref target="http://www.freemd.com">FreeMD</ref>. You just need to answer the basic questions, and the talking head will help you figure out what your diagnosis is. Another good site is Wrong Diagnosis.</item></list></item>
<item>Ask for help if you get stuck. If you have a teenager at home, ask them! They are great with using the internet and can provide useful tips. Librarians can be a very useful source of guidance, and the HELP library provides a free Ask-the-Librarian service to help you get started on your search. <figure rend="Search the Internet for Health Information Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remember that your Internet search is just the starting point in your quest for knowledge. Your doctor is your guide and may be able to refer you to useful websites. Many doctors today have their own websites and provide specialty links and other information you can use. <figure rend="Search the Internet for Health Information Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can use the Internet for other health related activities. Use it for: getting a second opinion; talking to your doctor (virtual web visits), so you don’t need to go to his clinic; finding hospitals and doctors which provide the services you need; storing and organizing your medical records; forming support communities with others with a similar problems and to shop for medical equipment and supplies.</item></list>
</text>
