<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc217" title="Understand the Role of Bank Bailouts in the American Economy" shortTile="understand-role-bank" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-11-22" dateModified="2019-09-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Understand_the_Role_of_Bank_Bailouts_in_the_American_Economy" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Understand the Role of Bank Bailouts in the American Economy</head>
<p>In 2008 Wall Street investment Bankers and the insurance company American International Group (AIG) received bailouts from the federal Troubled Asset Relief Program (TARP) because their derivative investments based on real estate mortgages went sour. This article will help you understand the negative effects of bank bailouts on the American economy.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Study the role of the Federal Reserve Bank through American history. The Federal Reserve Bank worked out the bank bailouts with the help of the Department of Treasury. Congress passed the Federal Reserve Act on December 23, 1913 creating the central bank we now call the FED. <figure rend="Understand the Role of Bank Bailouts in the American Economy Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The Fed is not federal, a reserve or a bank. It is not even subject to an audit or accountable to anyone. Who owns it?  The shares are not traded on any exchange. It is more like a private corporation.  Now, after QE1 we get Ben Bernanke now starting QE2 (quantitative easing #2). This means the FED will buy large amounts of newly made government bonds with just a computer entry and credit the U.S. government with the newly created money.  This is called monetizing money.  It is a form of fiat money creation or money with no backing.  Likewise, all paper currencies these days are fiat since they have no direct gold backing.  The French word fiat means "let it be made."  Historically currencies with gold backing kept governments more honest and helped rein in their borrowing and paper money printing.</item>
<item>The Federal Reserve Bank is not a reserve of anything.  They are not even a bank.  You can't walk in and open an account.  It is actually a cartel and monopoly based on political privilege and theft by increasing the money supply.  This is harmful to the elderly on fixed incomes and to those that save.  Inflation means loss of value of the money.  Plain government counterfeiting!  This means free markets are distorted by profligate governments and their bank and corporate bailouts.</item></list></item>
<item>Ask who will end up paying the bill for the bailouts the Fed and the federal government engineer.  The taxpayers - you and I - that's who. <figure rend="Understand the Role of Bank Bailouts in the American Economy Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Study the success or failure of bailouts in other countries. Some of the strongest European countries are implementing austerity measures and loaning money to tide the weaker countries over.  Yes, more worldwide bank bailouts.  This is nothing new.  It has been going on internationally for years with the help of organizations like the International Monetary Fund and the World Bank.  Many third world countries are deep in debt. <figure rend="Understand the Role of Bank Bailouts in the American Economy Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Portugal, Italy, Greece and Spain (PIGS) are reducing workers' pay and pensions due to stress over high unemployment rates choking off tax revenue causing them to catch the bank bailouts disease.  Now, even France is extending the age for retirement.</item></list></item>
<item>Consider the effect of government run deposit insurance banks on the behavior of lenders. Many American Banks have failed in the last few years - the last time we had so many bank failures was during the 1930's depression.  The FDIC, Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, has been privatized.  Remember when FDIC only covered the first $100,000 of your money?  Now most accounts are completely covered by our government.  Taxpayers now become the insurers of last resort for all they deposit in all the banks and credit unions.  That's another one of the big bank bailouts.  With government run deposit insurance banks, lenders have no risk.  Therefore they make unwise money decisions. <figure rend="Understand the Role of Bank Bailouts in the American Economy Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Just look what happened to the Federal National Mortgage Association, Fannie Mae.  Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac were GSE's, government sponsored enterprises that bought home mortgages.  They were listed corporations on the New York Stock Exchange.  Not anymore.  With the federal government to back them up, they made unwise lending decisions leading to bankruptcy.  Now, taxpayers own them.  Right they are privatized now also.  Both of them along with the FDIC.  Just another one history's recent bank bailouts. <figure rend="Understand the Role of Bank Bailouts in the American Economy Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Deflation is the de-leveraging of the 100 years of credit inflation and bank bailouts.  Credit Inflations always crash.  The credit deflation goes much faster.  It picks up speed and size the way a snowball rolls down a hill.</item></list>
</text>
