<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc152" title="Get over the Fact Your Dad Was Not the Person You Thought" shortTile="over-fact-dad-person" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2013-04-14" dateModified="2018-10-12" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get_over_the_Fact_Your_Dad_Was_Not_the_Person_You_Thought" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get over the Fact Your Dad Was Not the Person You Thought</head><p>A father is the first male relationship we have in our lives and so is an integral part of who we are. As children, we grow up thinking our parents are heroes and perfect but as time goes on we find out who they really are and find out that they are just as human as we are. Sometimes they have secrets or things about them that you didn't know that changes your perception of them but a change in your knowledge of him doesn't have to be the end of your relationship or emotional connection.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Acknowledge the shock. For a long time you have believed you knew exactly who your father was and the role he played in your life. When something comes along and changes that, there is going to be an immediate sense of loss and shock. It may seem like your father's place in your life will never be the same again, and the loss of what he was to you before can hurt. Ignoring the pain may help you feel better for the short term, but if you want to be happy and repair your relationship with your father in the long term, you need to take steps to move forward. <figure rend="Get over the Fact Your Dad Was Not the Person You Thought Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Confront the anger. When the shock of this change in perception wears off, you may feel angry. Your anger may be directed at your father or at something or someone you blame for bringing this change into your life. Feeling angry at this point is natural but it is important to deal with it appropriately and constructively. Being destructive with your anger is only going to damage other relationships and create new problems. <figure rend="Get over the Fact Your Dad Was Not the Person You Thought Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Look in the mirror. This is a time for self-reflection. Has your father really changed? Or has he been the person you think he changed into for a long time and you haven't seen it? If he has changed, then why is this change so hard for you to accept? Would you react as strongly if a different person in your life changed in a similar way? Are you still holding on to the childhood ideal that he is a perfect hero? <figure rend="Get over the Fact Your Dad Was Not the Person You Thought Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't cut him out of your life. A natural human reaction when something is causing such emotional turmoil is to distance ourselves from it or remove it completely so we don't have to feel the emotions. Dealing with the loss of the relationship altogether seems better and easier than dealing with this change. Acknowledge that these feelings are natural, but like all feelings they will fade in time and if you do cut him out of your life you may regret it later. If this is something you are considering, before you do anything speak to an impartial 3rd party like a friend and get a different point of view. <figure rend="Get over the Fact Your Dad Was Not the Person You Thought Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Communicate. When you have a firm hold on your emotions, you need to communicate with your father in any way you can. Tell him about the change in your perception and how you feel about it. Explain to him that this has changed your relationship with him. Remember to listen to him too. He may not even realize you are feeling this way, because in his mind he has been this way for a long time. <figure rend="Get over the Fact Your Dad Was Not the Person You Thought Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Rebuild. The relationship you had with your father as a child and right up until the change in perception is gone. The longer you cling to it and try to force it, the worse you will feel. Accept what is gone and set about rebuilding a different relationship with him. A different relationship doesn't mean it will be negative.  It can be just as positive for you if you allow it to be. <figure rend="Get over the Fact Your Dad Was Not the Person You Thought Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Your father is a precious thing in your life. You only have a short period of time in life with him, is what has changed your perception worth throwing away this gift? Being rash and making a decision driven by natural emotions is a dangerous ledge and could result in long-term pain you may never rid yourself of.</item></list>
</text>
