<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc159" title="Write a Family Member's Life Story" shortTile="write-family-members" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2013-12-23" dateModified="2018-10-11" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Write_a_Family_Member%27s_Life_Story" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Write a Family Member's Life Story</head><p>The lives that people lead are as varied and unpredictable as their own personalities.  While the topic of a person's life can seem mundane to that person, it's often much more interesting to others.  This is especially true when it comes to our family members.  </p>
<p>There are many reasons to want to record a family member's life story: to share their accomplishments with others, to record their adventures for future generations, or perhaps to honor them after their passing away.  In any of these cases, you want to capture the unique attributes of the person and their path through life in a way that will be worth sharing and saving for the future.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Decide what format and length you want.  This is the most important step as it will shape the rest of the process.  If a blog post is what you have in mind, you have more leeway in the length of the article and the informality of your writing.  A book-length biography, however, would almost certainly call for more formality and structure, and would involve much more research. <figure rend="Write a Family Member's Life Story Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Research everything you can about the individual and their background. <figure rend="Write a Family Member's Life Story Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Interviews: An interview even with someone you've known your entire life can reveal all kinds of surprising facts and engaging anecdotes.  If they are still living, you should conduct at least one interview.  If they have passed away, then interview any other surviving family members.  Record the interview if possible and try to cover as many of the topics below as you can.</item>
<item>Public records: Using search engine results and genealogy websites you can find out a lot even about long deceased relatives.  Things to look for include birth (and death) places, marriages, divorces, number and names of children, military service, and any employment information you can discover.</item>
<item>A sense of time and place.  If you want to do justice to a family members' story, you really need to understand where they came from in order to give your readers that information.  While you may have grown-up in 21st century America, a family member who was born in pre-WWII Bulgaria comes from a very different culture than your own.  Even family members from the same town as yourself may have lived through times whose mindsets and outlooks are very different.</item></list></item>
<item>Outline your project before you begin writing.  This may be superfluous if your project is only two paragraphs long, but if you're planning anywhere from a page to a book-length, you won't want to skip this step.  Organizing your thoughts now will let you spend your writing time focusing on your real interest: the family member you want to honor. <figure rend="Write a Family Member's Life Story Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Write it!  Now's your chance to finally tell your family member's story in your own words.  Make sure to stay true to the research you've gathered, and always respect the confidentiality of anything the family member doesn't want shared. <figure rend="Write a Family Member's Life Story Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have the family member or other surviving relatives read it first.  Before you share this story with anyone else, you want to make sure it's acceptable to the family member if they're still alive.  If not, then run it by their parents, siblings, or whatever nearest of kin you can find.  If you happen to be the only person closely related to them, then make sure that you're not sharing something the family wouldn't appreciate. <figure rend="Write a Family Member's Life Story Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Share their story with the rest of the world.  Honoring the achievements and qualities of a family member on a blog or other forum is a great sign of respect for them.  Similarly, you might want to share the story of a deceased loved one on any of the online memorial sites out there.  These not only honor the family member, but can also inspire friends and family as they reflect on this person's life. <figure rend="Write a Family Member's Life Story Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Speak with as many people as you can before you begin writing.  Even a little bit of research can produce plenty of interesting details for your account.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always make sure that you have permission to share any details you're publishing, even if they're documented elsewhere.</item>
<item>Avoid negative remarks and low points in the person's life.  Unless you're writing a professional biography, there's no need to discuss negative details just for the sake of appearing objective.</item></list>
</text>
