<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc268" title="Improve Your Health and the Health of Your Family" shortTile="improve-health-health" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-10-15" dateModified="2018-10-01" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Improve_Your_Health_and_the_Health_of_Your_Family" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Improve Your Health and the Health of Your Family</head><p>A well balanced meal and good nutrition are important to your health and the health of your family.  As we know, our body is designed to repair and to heal itself over time. By changing some of your eating habits to improve your life now, you can sometimes activate your body's own healing system to improve your life over time. Good health and eating habits are essential and can be improved through just a few easy changes.   </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Set up a regular family mealtime.  This will begin to help your body conform to your schedule as opposed to “wanting food” whenever. Keep three times for a meal---breakfast, lunch and dinner. Take the meals at the exact time which you set, so that the body grows used to it. <figure rend="Improve Your Health and the Health of Your Family Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are taking breakfast early, then you can have a light snack between the duration of these two meals.</item></list></item>
<item>Eat slowly and pay attention to your food. You can digest food better when you eat with full attention and enjoy the eating process. However, for weight gain, it is better if you eat in a larger plate, fill it up more and eat quickly. <figure rend="Improve Your Health and the Health of Your Family Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Eat a variety of foods.  By eating a variety of foods you can make sure to get the nutrients you need and not too much of what is not good for you. Organize your plate before the meals. A little bit of everything is perfect. <figure rend="Improve Your Health and the Health of Your Family Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The quantity of food doesn't necessarily have to be vast if you are eating a number of different foods.</item>
<item>Include meat, vegetables, grain, fruit and salad in the food category. Don't forget that drinks are just as important---they can range from juices and milkshakes to simply water and smoothies.</item></list></item>
<item>Consume less. The general portions that we are given to us in restaurants is usually enough to feed more than one person.  As you train your body to need a proper portion, it will begin to only receive a proper portion and you will be “full” quicker. <figure rend="Improve Your Health and the Health of Your Family Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Exercise more. When you include a regular exercise regimen in your life, your body will begin to “want” and “need” exercise.  Try to include at least 30 minutes of some type of exercise into your day and you will improve your immune system and your emotions. <figure rend="Improve Your Health and the Health of Your Family Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Add soy, garlic, fish oil, and antioxidants to your diet.  All of these natural products have been proven to greatly increase your immune system, blood circulation, and overall health.  Easy ways to introduce and include soy in your family’s meals are to snack on edamame beans and to drink soy milk.  Another easy way is to put tiny undetected dices of tofu in your meals like spaghetti, meatloaf, etc. <figure rend="Improve Your Health and the Health of Your Family Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Eliminate or at least drink less soda and drink more water. <figure rend="Improve Your Health and the Health of Your Family Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Add herbal teas to your diet.  Trying not to add sugar, honey, or milk to your tea is best. But, if you must add for now, add honey. <figure rend="Improve Your Health and the Health of Your Family Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Detox. Detoxification basically means cleaning the blood. It does this by removing impurities from the blood in the liver, where toxins are processed for elimination. Your body needs regular cleaning just like anything else in your life. A regular detox will eliminate toxins, improve your immune system and give you energy. Consult your doctor on ways that you can set up a regular detox program specific for your body. <figure rend="Improve Your Health and the Health of Your Family Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Breathe deeply.  Unlike shallow breathing, deep breathing allows oxygen to circulate completely through your body.  Here’s how:  Sit in a relaxed pose, either on the floor or in a chair. Inhale through the nose to a slow count of four. Pause before exhaling through your mouth to a count of four. Let the air completely out take a moment to pay attention to how that breath made you feel. <figure rend="Improve Your Health and the Health of Your Family Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get regular checkups and keep vaccinations up to date. Many people skip their checkups and shots because they think that it is not important. But it is. Many a life has been saved by going in when you weren't sick and making sure you're doing great.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Having a healthy body and a healthy family begins with you.  Your body will give you what you give it!</item>
<item>Using essential oils (making sure that they are pure and certified good) and keeping your mental health strong can help lead to a long, happy life.</item></list>
</text>
