<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc66" title="Contact Microsoft" shortTile="contact-microsoft" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-05-07" dateModified="2019-05-25" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Contact_Microsoft" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Contact Microsoft</head><p>Occasionally, you may need help with your Microsoft operating system, product or device. Microsoft has several convenient customer support channels to help you troubleshoot various issues. You can reach out by phone, email or online chat to get your problem resolved with the help of a Microsoft professional in no time.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Contacting Microsoft by Phone</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find your product key number. Your product key number is specific to your product or device and can provide your representative with additional information about your item. The key is 25 alphanumeric characters long, written as 5 groups of 5 characters separated by dashes. It is usually located on a label on the original box of your product. <figure rend="Contact Microsoft Step 1 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you can’t find your product key, don’t worry. A Microsoft representative can talk you through where to find it depending on what type of Microsoft product or device you have.</item>
<item>If you aren't calling about a product that you payed for, such as Windows or Office, then you can skip this step.</item></list></item>
<item>Locate your warranty if you have it. If you purchased a warranty on your product or device, locate it. Write down any relevant details such as the length of the warranty or level of coverage so you can relate it to the Microsoft representative. <figure rend="Contact Microsoft Step 2 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you did not buy a warranty, then you can skip this step.</item></list></item>
<item>Call 1-800-Microsoft (642-7676) to reach a representative. This phone number is just for U.S. callers. Microsoft accepts calls at this number from 9am-5pm PST. If you live internationally, consult the Microsoft <ref target="https://support.microsoft.com/en-us/help/13948/global-customer-service-phone-numbers%7C">customer service directory</ref> to find the appropriate phone number for support in your country. <figure rend="Contact Microsoft Step 3 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>State the issue to the representative. When you are connected with a representative, describe the nature of the problem you’re having. Be sure to let them know how long it’s been going on and the version of the product you’re using, if applicable. It can also be helpful to provide your phone number at the beginning of the call in the event that you unexpectedly get disconnected. <figure rend="Contact Microsoft Step 4 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Contacting Microsoft by Email</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Draft an email to wehelp@microsoft.com describing your issue. Describe how long the problem has been going on and whether the issue has been consistent or intermittent. Be sure to describe any relevant circumstances about when your issues began, if the troubles began after a new install or the move to a new product, for example. <figure rend="Contact Microsoft Step 5 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Include the product key number and any relevant warranty information. Be sure to include all relevant details of your Microsoft device or product in your email, including the product key number if you have it. It should be located on the original packaging. Add any warranty information, if applicable, as well as the version of the product or program you’re using. <figure rend="Contact Microsoft Step 6 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Bold your contact information so the support person can follow up. It is critical to include your contact information, so your Microsoft support technician can reach you to discuss the problem. Indicate in your message whether you’d like to be contacted back by email or phone, and if by phone, a good time for them to reach you. <figure rend="Contact Microsoft Step 7 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Contacting Microsoft by Online Chat</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Browse to <ref target="https://support.microsoft.com/en-us/contactus/">Microsoft’s online chat portal.</ref> Hit the blue “Get Started” button in the middle of the page to launch a chat dialog box. Be sure you enable pop-ups from the website, so you’re able to use chat. <figure rend="Contact Microsoft Step 8 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Describe the nature of your problem. The chat first launches a virtual assistant, which attempts to connect you with existing trouble-shooting content online. If you feel confident you might be able to fix your own issue with the right online guide, describe your problem fully. This will help the virtual assistant direct you to the best content available for common issues. <figure rend="Contact Microsoft Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You could say, “Windows isn’t loading,” or “I can’t create a new document in Microsoft Word.”</item></list></item>
<item>Say, “I want to talk to a live representative.” The virtual assistant will immediately connect you with a live Microsoft representative if you simply ask to. When connected, provide your product key, any relevant warranty information, and the details of your problem. <figure rend="Contact Microsoft Step 10.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
