<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc298" title="Get Started with an Art and Crafts Hobby" shortTile="started-art-crafts" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2016-01-08" dateModified="2019-10-14" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get_Started_with_an_Art_and_Crafts_Hobby" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get Started with an Art and Crafts Hobby</head><p>Arts and crafts describes a wide variety of activities involving making things with one's own hands. It is usually a hobby built upon your interest and passion for the DIY. But if you do not have interest in art and craft, you can cultivate one and get started with arts and crafts.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Make time for your new hobby. This is very important as art and crafts is something which requires your hard work, dedication and time. Many crafts take multiple days to complete, and in order to avoid ending up with half-finished projects all over your house, you need to make time to craft your final product. <figure rend="Get Started with an Art and Crafts Hobby Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Explore types of crafts and project ideas. There are many types of art and crafts. Look at some craft blogs, how-to articles and videos, and sites like Pinterest to get ideas. You can pick between drawing, pottery, quelling, weaving, origami, and more. <figure rend="Get Started with an Art and Crafts Hobby Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Many artists get inspired by their environment, as well as by reading books, watching movies, interacting with people and spending time alone with their thoughts.</item>
<item>YouTube and wikiHow are the two most commonly used websites to explore anything.</item></list></item>
<item>Learn the technique. Whatever project you're working on, you need to observe and practice. If you're making an origami projects, you'll need to practice the common folds; if you're getting into sewing, you'll need to master the basic stitches. Watch YouTube videos, and search for tutorials related to your respective artwork. <figure rend="Get Started with an Art and Crafts Hobby Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>There are many books published which tell beginners how to get started with arts and crafts.</item>
<item>You can also join the clubs or take classes in your chosen craft.</item></list></item>
<item>Organize.  Having a clean space can help you focus and get your work done with much more concentration. Remove anything that may distract you from your work and isn't relevant to the task. <figure rend="Get Started with an Art and Crafts Hobby Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can be organized with creations, too! You can plan them out step by step to make sure you only get the supplies you need.</item>
<item>You can use the link <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/Organize-Craft-Supplies">https://www.wikihow.com/Organize-Craft-Supplies</ref> for reference.</item></list></item>
<item>Be inspired but original. As a beginner, you're going to take inspiration from other crafts and tutorials; that's okay. But try to build upon them and make something unique. <figure rend="Get Started with an Art and Crafts Hobby Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take breaks. Some crafts take a lot of concentration; sure, they're supposed to be fun, but if you want your final product to look great,you need to take a break and then continue making your craft because this helps your body more relaxed and concentrated. <figure rend="Get Started with an Art and Crafts Hobby Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Think twice before starting long projects. If you are a beginner, you may not want to take multi-day or even multi-week projects on right away. Instead, start small projects that are capable for you. As you master these, you'll build your skills and your interest to prepare for longer projects.Then you can move on to harder and advanced crafts. <figure rend="Get Started with an Art and Crafts Hobby Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Enjoy it! The whole point of arts and crafts for a non-professional beginner is to enjoy it. Create a habit and a hobby of your crafts. Work on it in your free time, and hopefully you'll not only create some neat projects but also enjoy your new hobby. <figure rend="Get Started with an Art and Crafts Hobby Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try to clean up supplies from one project before moving on to the next.</item>
<item>Clean things out regularly to avoid a buildup of mess.</item></list>
</text>
