<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc70" title="Download App Store Apps for Free" shortTile="download-app-store" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-10-01" dateModified="2019-07-01" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Download_App_Store_Apps_for_Free" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Download App Store Apps for Free</head><p>This wikiHow teaches you how to search for and download free iPhone and iPad apps using the App Store. You cannot download paid apps for free via the App Store.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open the App Store . Tap the App Store app icon, which resembles a white "A" on a blue background. <figure rend="Download App Store Apps for Free Step 1 Version 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tap . It's a magnifying glass-shaped icon in the bottom-right corner of the screen. <figure rend="Download App Store Apps for Free Step 2 Version 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>On some iPads, the <hi rend="bold">Search</hi> section is a search bar in the top-right corner of the screen. If so, tap the search bar and then skip the next step.</item></list></item>
<item>Tap the search bar. This is at the top of the <hi rend="bold">Search</hi> screen. Doing so will bring up your iPhone's or iPad's keyboard. <figure rend="Download App Store Apps for Free Step 3 Version 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Enter an app's name or function. If you have a specific app in mind, type in its name; otherwise, type in a keyword or phrase that will help find an app to suit your needs. <figure rend="Download App Store Apps for Free Step 4 Version 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, if you're looking for a drawing app, you might type in  or  here.</item></list></item>
<item>Tap . This blue button is in the keyboard. Doing so will search the App Store for your entered word or phrase and bring up a list of matching/related apps. <figure rend="Download App Store Apps for Free Step 5 Version 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select an app. Scroll through the list of apps until you find one that you want, then tap the app's title to open the its page. <figure rend="Download App Store Apps for Free Step 6 Version 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tap . It's a blue button on the right side of the page. <figure rend="Download App Store Apps for Free Step 7 Version 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Enter your Touch ID when prompted. If you have Touch ID enabled for the App Store, scanning your Touch ID will immediately prompt the app to begin downloading onto your iPhone or iPad. <figure rend="Download App Store Apps for Free Step 8 Version 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you don't have Touch ID enabled for the App Store or your iPhone/iPad doesn't support Touch ID, you'll enter your Apple ID password and then tap <hi rend="bold">Install</hi> when prompted.</item></list></item>
<item>Wait for the app to download. As the app begins downloading, you'll see a square with a progress circle appear on the right side of the screen. Once the circle is complete, the app has successfully been download. <figure rend="Download App Store Apps for Free Step 9 Version 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can stop the app from downloading by tapping the square icon.</item></list></item>
<item>Tap . It's in the same place as was the <hi rend="bold">GET</hi> button. Doing so will open your app. <figure rend="Download App Store Apps for Free Step 10 Version 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can also open your app by tapping it on your iPhone's or iPad's Home Screen.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>There are some other methods of downloading apps that require <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Jailbreak-Your-iOS-Device">jailbreaking your iPhone</ref>; however, since the release of iOS 10.3 and the iPhone 7, jailbreaking has become less reliable. If you're running an operating system for which a jailbreak is available, you can still <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Get-Free-Apps-on-Cydia">use Cydia to search for and download free apps</ref>.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>While some paid apps will become free after a certain amount of time, most paid apps remain as such. It is illegal to download paid apps for free by using a source other than the App Store.</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
