<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc295" title="Build a Vacuum Former" shortTile="build-vacuum-former" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-01-28" dateModified="2018-03-22" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Build_a_Vacuum_Former" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Build a Vacuum Former</head><p>Do you have a need to create molds, masks, or other shapes out of plastic? Make your own 5-inch square vacuum former in just a few hours!  The instructions below are based on materials that you might have around the house already or can be modified to use what you do have.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Making the Vacuum Former Box</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><figure rend="Vacuum former box frame sketch.png"></figure>Measure and draw your guidelines.
<list type="unordered"><item>On 3/4 inch plywood, draw three squares, 5 inches on a side.</item>
<item>Draw another, smaller 4 inch square centered inside each square.</item></list></item>
<item>Cut along the inner squares on all three frame pieces.</item>
<item>Cut along the outer guidelines to finish each frame piece.  <figure rend="Vacuum former box frame pieces.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Build the main box by stacking and gluing the three frame pieces together.</item>
<item>Clamp all four sides of the box and allow the glue to dry.  <figure rend="Vacuum former clamped box.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Drill a hole on one side using the hole saw so the vacuum hose (or adapter) will fit snugly.  <figure rend="Vacuum former completed inner box.png"></figure></item></list>
<head>Making the Platen</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><figure rend="Vacuum former platen sketch.png"></figure> Measure and draw outside frame.
<list type="unordered"><item>On the 5mm MDF, draw a 5 inch square.</item></list></item>
<item>Measure and draw a grid.
<list type="unordered"><item>Start in from a corner at 0.5 inches from each side, draw straight vertical lines every 2/3 inches for a total of 7 lines.</item>
<item>Repeat the pattern for horizontal lines creating an intersecting grid pattern.</item></list></item>
<item>Drill 3/32 inch holes at each intersection.</item>
<item>Cut the final platen out of the MDF along the outside frame lines drawn earlier. <figure rend="Vacuum former completed platen.png"></figure></item>
<item>Glue the platen to the top of the former box created in the previous step, clamping all four sides until the glue dries.</item></list>
<head>Making the Bottom / Mount</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><figure rend="Vacuum former bottom sketch.png"></figure> Measure and draw cutting guidelines.
<list type="unordered"><item>On the 5mm MDF, draw a 5 inch by 9 inch rectangle.</item></list></item>
<item>Cut frame from MDF.</item>
<item>Glue this final piece to the bottom of the vacuum former box, clamping the two flush sides until the it is fully dried.</item></list>
<head>Making the Sheet Holder Frame</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><figure rend="Vacuum former sheet frame sketch.png"></figure> Measure and draw guidelines.
<list type="unordered"><item>On the 5mm MDF, draw two 7.5 inch squares</item>
<item>Centered inside each square draw another, 5.5 inch square.</item></list></item>
<item>Cut out the inner square of each frame piece.</item>
<item><figure rend="Vacuum former completed sheet frame.png"></figure> Cut along the outer guideline to finish the frame pieces.</item></list>
<head>Using Your New Vacuum Former</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><figure rend="Vacuum former mounted.jpg"></figure> Mount the box.
<list type="unordered"><item>Set the box on a sturdy table.</item>
<item>Using the clams / quick clamps, firmly clamp the box to the table.</item></list></item>
<item>Attach the vacuum.
<list type="unordered"><item>Firmly push the vacuum hose or adapter into the hole on the side of the former.</item></list></item>
<item>Gather your materials.
<list type="unordered"><item>Cut your desired thermoplastic into 6 inch square sheets.</item>
<item>Choose or 3d print shapes to be formed.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Vacuum former parts on platen.jpg"></figure> Place the objects to be molded on the platen (top). Take care to space the part around the holes to maintain clean edges.</item>
<item><figure rend="Vacuum former clamped sheet.jpg"></figure> Clamp the thermoplastic sheet between the frame pieces with the binder clips.</item>
<item>Hold frame with grips to keep heat away from your hands.</item>
<item>Heat plastic using slow, even motion with the heat gun. Keep going until until the plastic sags about 1.5 to 2 inches</item>
<item>Turn on the vacuum.</item>
<item>Lower the heated thermoplastic onto former over objects.</item>
<item>Continue to heat the thermoplastic around edges and fine details to ensure a clean mold. <figure rend="Completed vacuum former.png"></figure></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always adhere proper safety precautions (masks, safety glasses, etc).</item>
<item>Use former in a well-ventilated area as some thermoplastics emit toxic fumes when heated.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>3/4 inch plywood (a little over 75 square inches)</item>
<item>5 mm MDF (a little over 127 square inches)</item>
<item>Wood glue</item>
<item>Hole saw (sized to fit vacuum hose/adapter) - Typical adapter size is 1-1/2 inch</item>
<item>3/32 inch drill bit</item>
<item>Clamps / Quick Clamps</item>
<item>Drill</item>
<item>Jigsaw / Skill saw / Circular saw (whichever is small enough and easy to use)</item>
<item>Pencil (for drawing guidelines)</item>
<item>Thermoplastic (Try PETG as it is food safe)</item>
<item>Heat gun with enough power for your chosen thermoplastic</item>
<item>Binder clips (x4) to hold sheet inside frame</item>
<item>Grips to hold frame while heating</item>
<item>Vacuum cleaner / Shop vacuum with accessory hose</item></list>
</text>
