<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc277" title="Prevent Stairway Accidents" shortTile="prevent-stairway" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-05-21" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Prevent_Stairway_Accidents" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Prevent Stairway Accidents</head><p>Preventing accidents on stairways is a necessary undertaking, especially in the workplace. Preventing stairway accidents takes effort and time, but it is necessary if you want to avoid someone getting hurt and you getting sued. If you are looking for ways to prevent stairway accidents, consider the following list of suggestions.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Ensure that all stairwells conform to safety standards. Research building code standards and any other legal requirements for stairwell designs. By following certain codes, you can avoid being responsible in the event that someone is injured falling down the stairs. <figure rend="Prevent Stairway Accidents Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep stairways clear to prevent accidents. Don't pile items anywhere near a stairway. <figure rend="Prevent Stairway Accidents Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Mark the edge of the steps a different color so as to avoid stairway accidents. Make sure that the paint does not wear out. <figure rend="Prevent Stairway Accidents Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Attach treads to the edges of your steps. This will add a grip to them and help prevent accidents.  Again, ensure that the treads are secure and not loose. <figure rend="Prevent Stairway Accidents Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Install handrails on both side of the stairway. Select rails that are curved and smooth so that clothing and bag straps don't get caught on them causing stairwell injuries. Check that the handrails are not unsteady or detached from the wall. <figure rend="Prevent Stairway Accidents Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Post notices on oddly designed stairwells. If there is an odd step at the bottom of the stairwell or narrow steps, let people know. Post signage at that top and bottom of the stairwell that explains the oddity. Make sure that these signs are posted in a very visible spot. If you do have the means, get the oddity fixed. In some places having a sign may work against you if someone does have an accident. Find out what the law is in your area.</item>
<item>Make sure that the stairway is well lit during the day and the night. Install light switches at the top and bottom of the stairway for both safety and convenience. Check periodically that the bulbs are all working. <figure rend="Prevent Stairway Accidents Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Inspect the stairway regularly and make sure that it is maintained. Make sure that none of the steps are loose or rotting. If you have carpeting on the stairway, ensure that there are no pulls or openings that would cause someone to trip. Be proactive about correcting accident-causing issues. <figure rend="Prevent Stairway Accidents Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>On rainy or snow days, make sure that the stairwells are dried off. Don't put cloth or carpet down at the top of stairs. Someone may trip and fall down the stairs and hurt themselves badly. Just dry the area. If you need to mark the area with a wet floor sign, make sure the sign is visible but not obstructing the path. Another option would be to treat the floor with a non-slippery coating. <figure rend="Prevent Stairway Accidents Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make it a house rule to hold the handrail when using the stairs and make it natural to remind those who do who forget. <figure rend="Prevent Stairway Accidents Step 10.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Put up a notice with contact information. Should someone notice a stairway hazard, provide a way for that person to contact you. The sooner you correct the issue, the sooner you prevent an accident occurring.</item></list>
</text>
