<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc178" title="Be the Cousin That Your Family Want You to Be" shortTile="cousin-family-want" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2016-01-22" dateModified="2016-12-13" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_the_Cousin_That_Your_Family_Want_You_to_Be" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be the Cousin That Your Family Want You to Be</head><p>Being a cousin is a not a task. You can be born one, if your mother or father has a sibling that already has children, you're a cousin. Or, your aunt or uncle may have a child after you are born. If you believe that there's a role defined by your family for someone who simply happens to have a parent, who's got a sibling that has children, you can be nice, loving, caring and forgiving. This is hard because no one is all of those things all the time. Reading this article may just lift a weight off your shoulders. If your family constantly nag you to be a good cousin, or, just to be good, here is the answer to your problems.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Show you care as a cousin. To do this you must listen to the advice your family give. Ask what kind of cousin they were and show your cousin how you care by doing the small things that matter. If you have a young cousin take them to the park or buy them icecream. Or if you have an older cousin maybe ask to hang out with them or share your interests. But a cousin your own age is the easiest one to bond with as you just seem to have a special connection. All of this will help you achive the main goal being a good cousin and doing what your family asked you to do.</item>
<item>Do research. Find out what your cousin likes and maybe try it out. This way you can share interests. If they be the opposite gender of you find an activity that both male and female enjoy. Maybe find out their contact details and talk to them on social media. Find out what they like, who their friends are,  if they even like you but most importntly who they are and what there personality is. This way you have backup and if a conversation gets awkward you can bring up one of these subjects and you conversation will be back on track. Also its just nice to know your cousins details so you know how to react around them and just how to impress them. This will also show your family how hard you have worked and you can be the shining star in the family</item>
<item>Listen to your family! If they constally tell you to be a good cousin just be a good cousin as it's NOT had apart from being annoyed and putting up with the occasional fall out being a cousin is a joy and just try to accept it!! When ever your cousin comes round or when you see them make the most of it. Just show your love and tell them how much they mean to you. Doing things like this creates a bond between you both that could last a life time.</item></list>
</text>
