<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc220" title="Turn Stress Into Success" shortTile="turn-stress-success" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-07-07" dateModified="2019-06-09" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Turn_Stress_Into_Success" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Turn Stress Into Success</head><p>Many of us get stressed all the time, which may affect our career and our academical achievements.
So What is the best way to turn this to a huge success?!
These are the steps of the most successful people in the world.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Know that everyday in your life is a new life. You have to know this very well and no one can judge you, so start everyday with embracing yourself and embrace everybody around you &amp; know that you will start a new life in that day. <figure rend="Turn Stress Into Success Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Start to meditate for only 5 minutes think of the most beautiful things you want to accomplish in your life. <figure rend="Turn Stress Into Success Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have a good breakfast &amp; drink some fresh juice, start putting a plan for ONLY today...not tomorrow not the week after...just today. <figure rend="Turn Stress Into Success Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Start your schedule smiling and feel good about yourself, because you are much better than a lot of people in the world. <figure rend="Turn Stress Into Success Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Focus on your daily schedule. Just forget about the whole world, forget about your past,future or any distraction that makes you think even for a moment. KNOW that the time is stopped just for you in that moment. KNOW that you are the king of your world. So act like a King! <figure rend="Turn Stress Into Success Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Embrace every moment after finishing your schedule as if it's your last moment...greet as much as you can people that you know and that you don't know. <figure rend="Turn Stress Into Success Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do some light exercise and have a good dinner...when you get to the bed at night DO NOT think what's going to happen tomorrow... Just think very positively &amp; feel good about yourself and congratulate yourself for doing a good job and finishing your schedule. <figure rend="Turn Stress Into Success Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>DO NOT wait for others to congratulate you, cheer you or even thank you for something you've done...Remember that all you want from life is to finish your daily schedule and to get happy at the end of the day...that's all! <figure rend="Turn Stress Into Success Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>BELIEVE that you will accomplish all things you want and all your dreams will come true because not all the people can sustain their strength and keep their daily schedule without breaking it! <figure rend="Turn Stress Into Success Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Put your hundred percent in what ever work you do. <figure rend="Turn Stress Into Success Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>No work is small,big,Superior or inferior... <figure rend="Turn Stress Into Success Step 11.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Remember if you stick to the previous plan you will be on the top of this world in any field of life</item>
<item>Do not get distract from the planed task for the day.</item>
<item>Don't lose control on yourself.</item>
<item>While doing the day to day or official task you may fail, but try to minimise the failure by adopting new ways or by staying calm.</item>
<item>Don't care about what people say or what they think of you &amp; don't get jealous from others who had success..they are not better than you</item>
<item>DO your daily schedule with complete focus</item>
<item>Incidents and situations are not in our hands.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Just make plan to everyday regardless you succeed or not!</item>
<item>Don't be distracted by your success or failure because you have a mission everyday to do "The Schedule"</item>
<item>If You succeed don't be so happy for long time!</item></list>
</text>
