<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc190" title="Make Adjustments for Difficult Close Family Members" shortTile="make-adjustments" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-03-24" dateModified="2015-05-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make_Adjustments_for_Difficult_Close_Family_Members" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make Adjustments for Difficult Close Family Members</head><p>Almost no one is exempt from difficult family members - whether your own, or your spouse's. The only thing you can control in life is yourself and your reactions. Finding the way to do that can be tough at first, but once you master it, you will be free from their drama forever.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>DECIDE THAT YOU WILL NO LONGER BE PULLED INTO ANYONE'S DRAMA. Once you make up your mind that you will no longer be subject to anyone else's anger, insecurities, or unhappiness, you are free to love them for their positive qualities and to refuse to let their problems become your problems. Whether it is a sister, a brother in law, or a mother in law, you can only control your life. Refuse to respond to negative actions by withdrawing from them. Interact and support positive qualities. If questioned why you refuse to enter a debate with someone who is trying to draw you into battle, simply respond with "I will not entertain negativity any longer. Life is too short. I am here for you when you are ready to move on from this."</item>
<item>PUT OUT THOSE QUALITIES YOU WISH TO SEE IN OTHERS. In other words, practice what you preach. If you have a set of siblings who argue every time they sit down for a family get together, interrupt the disruption before it takes hold of the occasion. Don't allow anyone to hijack what should be a memorable moment. Instead, stand up and announce that this is a happy event and you will not allow it to be ruined by pettiness. Ask if anyone would like to: take a walk, play a game, think of a funny family memory, bring out some photographs, make coffee together; etc. In short, don't give energy to the negative but reverse it and try to move everyone along in a different direction.</item>
<item>WE DON'T CHOOSE OUR FAMILY. If family, whether in laws or your own, are constantly making your life miserable, simply reduce the amount of time you spend with them. You are not a bad person for choosing to surround yourself with positive people. Most people can't stomach the thought of being surrounded by angry people month after month, but if you reduce it to once or twice a year, you can handle it. If questioned why you don't socialize more with difficult family members, state the truth: you will rejoin them whenever they are ready to enlighten those around them with joy and happiness.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Sometimes people aren't ready to abandon their negative ways. It fuels them, and after a while it becomes habit. They may feel you are taking their power away from them, which, let's face it, you are. If the people in question don't wish to change direction, all you can do at that point is to leave the situation. Take a walk by yourself or enlist another person there who also doesn't wish to engage in that sort of unpleasant behavior. Remember, all you can control is yourself.</item></list>
</text>
