<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc287" title="Improve Your Memory with Exercise" shortTile="improve-memory-exercise" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-01-06" dateModified="2019-04-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Improve_Your_Memory_with_Exercise" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Improve Your Memory with Exercise</head><p>Scientists have found a direct link between cardiovascular exercise and healthy brain matter. Studies have shown that the body's ability to correctly regulate glucose levels may help to regenerate tissues and have healthy gray matter. They also show that exercise increases oxygenation to the brain, which maintains healthy brain cells. The best thing you can do to increase your memory is to maintain a healthy weight and do cardiovascular exercise for at least 150 minutes per week. There are many ways you can do this that can help to trigger memories and avoid dementia. Read more to find out how to use exercise for a better memory.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Have a physical fitness examination to find out if you are overweight. People who maintain a healthy weight maintain healthy glucose levels, which then help to regenerate tissues. A physical trainer in a gym or a general practitioner can come up with an exercise routine to help you obtain a healthy weight. <figure rend="Consistently Run if You're Overweight Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Create a weekly aerobic exercise routine. Aerobic exercise has been shown to increase the hippocampus, which in turn increases spatial memory. Aerobic exercise can include walking, cycling, running, flow yoga, swimming and more. <figure rend="Train Like a Fitness Model Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Aerobic exercise is the amount of physical activity where your body can produce enough oxygen to allow you to work your heart. The number of heartbeats per minute to achieve aerobic activity changes with age, but is generally listed as exercise that increases your heart rate but still allows you to keep up a light conversation. <figure rend="Use TV Exercise Games to Get Fit Step 3Bullet8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Understand that the longer that you maintain an aerobic exercise routine in your life, the easier it will be to maintain a good memory. However, it is never too late to start. People between the ages of 55 and 88 have been shown to diminish the likelihood of dementia by starting an aerobic exercise routine.</item></list></item>
<item>Do several aerobic exercise activities per week, or walk on different paths. Breaking away from the same pattern helps exercise the brain and allows it to make new memories. Your intelligence increases as you form new memories. <figure rend="Break Your Push Ups Personal Record Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Learn to juggle or play ball with friends and family. The act of throwing the ball and focusing on catching it helps to improve hand-eye coordination. Try this combination of exercise and hand-eye coordination by playing catch, baseball, squash, racquetball, football, basketball, tennis, badminton or ping pong. <figure rend="Use Exercise For A Better Memory Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Use your weaker hand to play catch. Using a subordinate hand will help to increase the use of neurons. It helps to increase brain power and will have long-term positive effects on brain function.</item></list></item>
<item>Walk or hike on uneven ground. Scientists believe that walking on rocky or uneven surfaces can help the vestibular system, which helps with balance. This connects with the brain's ability to remember and cope with obstacles. <figure rend="Choose Comfortable Walking Shoes Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Increase your physical activity as you get into shape. Straying away from your comfort zone will increase concentration, allowing you to remember and stay focused for longer. Also, stray from your comfort zone with hobbies, conversations and intellectual pursuits to increase your memory. <figure rend="Break Your Push Ups Personal Record Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Doctors suggest you get at least 150 minutes of aerobic activity per week, or 30 minutes of aerobic activity 5 days per week. Increase your workouts to 40 minutes or do them 6 to 7 days per week.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are unable to keep up a conversation while you are exercising, this usually means you are engaging in anaerobic activity, where your body requires other body fuels to keep up with your pace. This intense exercise is also good for your body, but is not necessarily deemed necessary for memory improvement.</item>
<item>Sleep has been found to be equally essential in maintaining your memory. Aim to achieve 7 to 9 hours of sleep per night, according to what your body requires. This should aid both short term and long term memory.</item>
<item>It is a good idea to seek a doctor's approval before starting an exercise routine, if you have a health condition. The doctor may be able to direct you toward the best exercises for your body.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Physical fitness examination</item>
<item>Walking shoes</item>
<item>Ball sports</item>
<item>Aerobic exercise routine</item>
<item>Rocky paths</item>
<item>Doctor's recommendations</item></list>
</text>
