<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc110" title="Create Subtitles Using Aegisub" shortTile="create-subtitles" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-12-09" dateModified="2016-03-11" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Create_Subtitles_Using_Aegisub" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Create Subtitles Using Aegisub</head><p>Have you ever wanted to create your subtitles, but didn't know how to? If so, this article is for you! We will help you step-by-step in using the open source software called Aegisub to create your own subtitles.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Setting Up Aegisub</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Prepare the movie file on which you want to create subtitles. If you want to create subtitles for a DVD, you will need to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Rip_a_DVD">rip the DVD</ref> first. Store the movie file in a permanent location, such as in a specially created folder. In this article, we will be using the movie Transformers for our examples in the above screenshots. <figure rend="Create Subtitles Using Aegisub Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Load the movie file into Aegisub. Open up Aegisub, then click on the Video menu and select <hi rend="italic">Open Video...</hi> Browse for your video file and click . Depending on the size and length of your video, this process could take quite a while. <figure rend="Create Subtitles Using Aegisub Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>After the video loading process completes, you should see the video display located at the upper left of Aegisub.</item></list></item>
<item>Load the soundtrack from the video. Click on the Audio menu and select <hi rend="italic">Open Audio from Video</hi>. This will automatically rip the audio from your video soundtrack and import it into Aegisub. Again, depending on the size and length of your video, this process could take quite a while. <figure rend="Create Subtitles Using Aegisub Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>After the audio loading process completes, you should see audio waveform display to the upper right of Aegisub.</item></list></item>
<item>Save your changes. Click on the Save icon located in the toolbar, or simple press + to save your work. <figure rend="Create Subtitles Using Aegisub Step 4.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Creating the Subtitles</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Type in the text. Under the audio waveform, there is a text box. Type the desired text in this box. <figure rend="Create Subtitles Using Aegisub Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Choose where in the video your text will show up. As you might have already seen, there are two frames in the audio window; one is red, and the other blue. The red simply signifies when the text will appear, and the blue signifies where the text will end. Hold the left mouse button down and drag the red frame to the beginning of the waveform; then drag the blue frame to the end of the waveform. <figure rend="Create Subtitles Using Aegisub Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Edit the text appearance. If you don't like the way the subtitles appear on the video, you can always edit the size, font, or color using the Styler Manager, located under the Video menu. <figure rend="Create Subtitles Using Aegisub Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Move the text to the desired position. Yes, you can move the subtitles to anywhere you want on the screen. In the vertical toolbar to the left of the video, click the second icon from the top. A square box will appear underneath the videos; just drag and drop the subtitles wherever you like. <figure rend="Create Subtitles Using Aegisub Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Exporting the Subtitles</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Export your subtitles. Under the <hi rend="italic">File</hi> menu, click <hi rend="italic">Export Subtitles...</hi>. Then select the four options in the <hi rend="italic">Filters</hi> window. Then click . <figure rend="Create Subtitles Using Aegisub Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Save your subtitles as a .srt file. SubRip is probably the most common subtitle format, so it would be a good idea to save it in that format. Give your subtitle a name, for example: <hi rend="italic">Transformers_2007_720p.srt</hi>. Be sure to include the .srt extension in the file name. <figure rend="Create Subtitles Using Aegisub Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Add your subtitles to a video file. In this article, we will be using VLC. Open the movie file, then right-click the screen, and under the <hi rend="italic">Subtitles</hi> menu, click <hi rend="italic">Add Subtitle File...</hi>. Then navigate to your subtitle's location and click . <figure rend="Create Subtitles Using Aegisub Step 11.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you want to permanently imprint your subtitles onto a video, use a Transcoder that supports adding subtitles.</item>
<item>There are several template you can use in Aegisub. For example, when you insert \N into a subtitle line, the line will be split into two lines.</item></list>
</text>
