<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc49" title="Reach Your Mental Peak in Sports" shortTile="reach-mental-peak" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-02-08" dateModified="2018-05-16" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Reach_Your_Mental_Peak_in_Sports" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Reach Your Mental Peak in Sports</head><p>In this article, you will learn seven important key steps to reach your mental peak and play with greater concentration, composure and confidence. As a result, you will become a more positive, productive and proactive athlete.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Know what you want to do or learn. Be mentally clear about what you want to accomplish with regards to a specific maneuver or play - like shoot a foul shot in basketball, catch a ball in football or how to dodge in lacrosse. When you focus on what you want, you play with more enthusiasm and energy. <figure rend="Reach Your Mental Peak in Sports Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Athletes who focus on what they don't want create more stress and anxiety, and end up making more and more mistakes.</item></list></item>
<item>Practice visualizing what you want to do. Close your eyes and take yourself through every step in a particular play or maneuver. Use all your senses, including self-talk, in developing a picture of your performance. See it, hear it, feel it, say it, replay it. <figure rend="Reach Your Mental Peak in Sports Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Too many athletes only think about what they don't want to happen and thereby become reserved and hold back in a game.</item></list></item>
<item>Create a highlights film of all the times you successfully perform a specific maneuver or play. Keep a list, with date and location, to help you create a mental movie of what you were doing at that particular moment in a practice or game. <figure rend="Reach Your Mental Peak in Sports Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Many athletes only replay their mistakes and therefore, create a negative image of themselves.</item></list></item>
<item>Know what you control. Successful athletes know the difference between what they can control as a player and what they can't control. You control yourself - your attitudes, your actions  on and off the field, time you put into practice, taking care of your equipment, etc. <figure rend="Reach Your Mental Peak in Sports Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Athletes who worry about what they can't control - like the weather, refs, other team - lose control of themselves.</item></list></item>
<item>Learn from each mistake. When you make a mistake, immediately take a deep breath. As you inhale, ask yourself what did you see and as you exhale, ask yourself what did you learn. The message is that if you see clearly, you can learn, and if you can learn, you will become a smarter and better player. <figure rend="Reach Your Mental Peak in Sports Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>An athlete who negatively judges himself or puts himself down learns nothing and will probably make the same mistake...many times.</item></list></item>
<item>Avoid the mental minefields of complaining, blaming, doubting, resigning or questioning yourself or others. Once you step on one of these minefields, you become mentally wounded and disabled. You have raised the white flag and surrendered. <figure rend="Reach Your Mental Peak in Sports Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Celebrate your strengths. Identify and acknowledge any personal strengths that can make you a better player - positive outlook, hustle, desire to compete, ability to study and learn quickly, focus and concentration, proper timing, speed, intensity, supporting your teammates, etc. <figure rend="Reach Your Mental Peak in Sports Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
