<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc11" title="Hang Clean and Press" shortTile="hang-clean-press" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-06-21" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Hang_Clean_and_Press" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Hang Clean and Press</head>
<p>Hang clean and press is a great exercise to put into any workout plan you want.   This lift allows you to build stamina and cardiovascular endurance, as well as muscular endurance and even strength. This exercise is broken down into four different parts; half deadlift, hang clean, front squat (which is taken while in the motion of the clean), and the shoulder press. The three parts target muscles such as shoulders, traps, triceps, lower back, quadriceps, etc. High reps can be used for more endurance and cardio as low reps and heavier weight can be used to build strength. It takes time to get comfortable with the motion so it is highly recommended that you do not add additional weight to the bar when first starting.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Use a standard barbell for this exercise. <figure rend="SARPyubiQMeXG3TVD65aOQ.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Barbells come in different shapes and sizes.</item>
<item>A standard barbell is a 45-55-pound bar.</item>
<item>This weight is recommended because it is more substantial to handle for males and females.</item></list></item>
<item>Stand with your feet shoulder-width apart and centered with the bar.
<list type="unordered"><item>This is the beginning of your startup position.</item>
<item>One of the most important steps in a clean and press movement is your initial position.</item>
<item>If this step isn’t done right, it can result in an unbalance movement and possible injury.</item></list></item>
<item>Bend your knees and grip the barbell at the grooves. <figure rend="HFdSOn6wSJuaI2174vq2NA.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Both hands should be in the overhand gripping position.</item>
<item>While bending over, make sure your back is flat.</item>
<item>Your grip should be slightly wider than your shoulder width.</item>
<item>This will be useful for the hang clean motion.</item>
<item>You can verify if this step is done correctly if your knees are inside your arms, fully extended arms, elbows facing outside and an inclined back posture.</item></list></item>
<item>Move the bar close to your shins and lift it by extending your legs. <figure rend="86rBy6C4HSDCIq1NcXEnX%A.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Stand straight up while pushing the from your feet.</item>
<item>Your hips and shoulders should move forward and raise in a fluent motion as you pick the bar up.</item>
<item>The bar should remain close to your body as you’re doing this.</item></list></item>
<item>As the bar is passing over your knees, shrug your shoulders and use your momentum to get the bar as high as possible. <figure rend="ACpVeMGIQoyRi5jAqCXAvA.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>As you are guiding the bar, extend your hips and knees.</item>
<item>This is the hanging portion in hang clean.</item>
<item>In simple terms, the goal of a hang clean is to get underneath the bar.</item>
<item>This is one of the most important steps because this will get you in position to shoulder press correctly.</item></list></item>
<item>As the bar reaches maximum height, quickly rotate your shoulders around and under the bar. <figure rend="%vhFj3FyT CihHpn3OSGdQ.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This is the cleaning portion of a hang clean.</item>
<item>To get maximum momentum, use your legs in a jumping motion to get the bar higher.</item>
<item>It is normal for your feet to come off the ground while doing this motion because you are trying to elevate the bar.</item>
<item>The height of the bar is focused on to make it easier to get underneath the bar.</item>
<item>At this point the bar should be resting on across the front of your shoulders.</item></list></item>
<item>Within the fluent motion of the bar rotating underneath you, flex your hips and knees to absorb the weight of the bar.
<list type="unordered"><item>This is perceived as a semi front squat. This step is different for everybody.</item>
<item>The squatting motion is used to regain a balance and more strength for your shoulder press.</item>
<item>You should have a slight bend at the knees, feeling most of the tension in your legs.</item>
<item>Start to slowly rise. After this step is done, you have fully completed the hang clean portion of the exercise.</item></list></item>
<item>Use the power from your strong base to press the bar over your head while exhaling. <figure rend="3zqjg71iTrOPJ48xbXDBTA.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You should continue to have a strong base with a tight core and steady feet.</item>
<item>Make sure you can get to maximum height with the bar and lock out your elbows.</item></list></item>
<item>Slowly lower the bar back to your shoulders while inhaling.
<list type="unordered"><item>This is the descending shoulder press.</item>
<item>To secure the optimal range of the full workout, the descending exercises should be done.</item>
<item>This motion will continue to stimulate your shoulders, upper and lower back, and arms.</item></list></item>
<item>As the bar is resting on your shoulders, quickly rotate your elbows from under the bar and lower the bar to the floor.
<list type="unordered"><item>This is the descending Hang Clean.</item>
<item>This motion should be done quick to prevent injury in your elbow.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Use light weight to understand the form.</item></list>
</text>
