<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc205" title="Rebuild a Dying Business" shortTile="rebuild-dying-business" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-10-07" dateModified="2018-10-09" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Rebuild_a_Dying_Business" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Rebuild a Dying Business</head><p>Are you a business man, woman, or entrepreneur? Is your business showing signs of distress? Or is it straight-up tanking? There are simple measures you can take to bring it back from the brink. Your business might be dying, but that doesn’t have to mean it’s over. This wikiHow will help you get on the path to resurrecting your business.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Evaluate your situation. Most of us are aware that before physicians treat a patient, they perform a multitude of tests and make a diagnosis. In a like manner, when you realize that your business is in serious trouble, stop and take a good, hard look at your company.
<list type="unordered"><item>Carefully evaluate your situation and assess what is going wrong.</item>
<item>You can’t take action without knowing where to start.  <figure rend="Evaluate .jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Replan your strategy. The way you think about your failures is the key to your success. After re-evaluating your company, chances are you have found where you went wrong and are ready to redefine and rethink your strategy. You have decided to not give up and are determined to succeed. This is a great step in reviving your dying business — but also a hard one. <figure rend="Strategy1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>A good example for entrepreneurs is Steve Jobs who was constantly rethinking his products to service the world better. Apple went from being nearly shut down to giving us the iPhone just a decade later, according to Forbes.</item></list></item>
<item>Focus on your team. Often, you may think that the problem is in your software, hardware, or your data, but the problem is most likely to be in the individuals you have in place. Your most important assets are your people—your employees.
<list type="unordered"><item>When your company seems to be failing, re-evaluate not just your strategy, but those who are tasked to execute it. If necessary, get rid of those who are slowing you down and hire those who can help revive your dying business. Remember: The best businesses are the ones that run with soul. <figure rend="Team1 .jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Mark Zuckerberg, the CEO of Facebook, is known for his unconventional approach to hiring and selecting a team. He often bases his choice on a person’s talents and attitudes rather than their skills or diplomas. A similar mindset might help your business.</item></list></item>
<item>Get rid of pride and fear. Rather than playing the blame game—which will get you nowhere—successful CEOs and business leaders know that admitting their faults and showing genuine humility will help them rebuild and boost their organization.</item>
<item>*When business leaders are unwilling to change, or stick to preconceived ideas of what they think will work, it is often a fast means for disaster.  <figure rend="Fear &amp; pride .jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Pride is also a form of fear. If you’re unable to admit you don’t have all the answers and are unwilling to delegate tasks to others who are more capable of completing those tasks, you are at high risk of causing your entire organization to fail.</item>
<item>If you still fear failure, take a lesson from billionaire Richard Branson, who said, “Failure is one of the secrets to success, since some of the best ideas arise from the ashes of a shuttered business.”</item></list></item>
<item>Be eternally persistent. No matter what happens, never give up.
<list type="unordered"><item>Passion is what made you start your business in the first place and it will help you to keep it going.</item>
<item>Passion may not always come with the voice of reason, but it may be the fuel you need to reignite that fire. <figure rend="Never quit .jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Nick Woodman, who invented the GoPro camera and was a billionaire at 36, said his success came only after he created a business that brought his passion for surfing to life. He had already failed at two businesses before his passion launched him to global success.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Your business difficulties should never bring you down. Turn those difficulties into opportunities.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>The end begins the moment you decide to quit.</item></list>
</text>
