<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc202" title="Work Together As a Group or Family" shortTile="work-together-group" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-09-24" dateModified="2017-05-05" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Work_Together_As_a_Group_or_Family" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Work Together As a Group or Family</head><p>Working together as a group or family is beneficial to everyone within the group.  It boosts moods and helps everyone feel more welcome and at peace.  And when tough times come, families that already know how to work together will be able to pull together quickly and efficiently.  If working together as a group or family sounds good to you, start at step one.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Set aside your stubbornness. Stubbornness getting in the way of success is a theme in literature and story-telling for a reason; it happens in real life, too. In Disney's classic "Sleeping Beauty" two of the three good fairies, Flora and Merryweather are happily watching the two lovers dance until they get into an argument over what the ideal color for Princess Aurora's wedding dress should be.  While this effectively closes the plot and story, it is not a good way for the three of them to grow closer together. <figure rend="Work Together As a Group or Family Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are being stubborn about something, for example, letting your sister borrow your hairbrush, then take a breather and step back.  How does this argument affect your relationship?  How important is it to you to keep the hairbrush for yourself?  Weigh your options, along with the pros and cons of each choice, and make a decision (this doesn't work at all if you aren't completely calm, however).  On the other hand, if whatever you are being stubborn about is really important to you, like attending a specific activity, than it's okay to hold your ground.  If you are usually very nice and agreeable, the times when you do choose to stand up for your decisions will be all the more powerful.</item></list></item>
<item>Always be there to lend a hand to family or group members who need help.  If you're the one who is always reaching out to others, you'll gain a better reputation and people will have a harder time being angry with you (don't gloat, however, as this completely offsets the good choices being made).  People may choose to repay your actions, or they may not.  Don't let the reason for your helping out be to get gain in return.  What you really want is for everyone to be closer together, and good deeds and random acts of kindness really help. <figure rend="Work Together As a Group or Family Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Believe in each other.  Verbal support is one of the most important things in a family.  Even if you think that dress really does make your sister look fat, don't say so (unless your relationship is already very strong, in which case, do so gently and cautiously).  Tell her it looks gorgeous and wish her a great night.  If your brother decides to try out for the baseball team, even if he can't pitch and has never made a home run in his life, tell him he'll do amazing and keep your doubts to yourself.  Whether or not you agree with people's decisions is probably not the point. <figure rend="Work Together As a Group or Family Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>However, if you are the parent and they are the child, or you think what they are doing could really hurt them, carefully express your concerns.  If the decisions concerns you greatly as well, like moving into your bedroom or changing jobs, then of course you have a right to express your opinion!  Just keep in mind what exactly is yours to give and hold back and what is not.</item></list></item>
<item>Be nice to each other. The often-quoted guideline "If you can't say something nice, don't say nothing at all" is a very good rule of thumb.  Watch your tongue, or you will regret it.  Also, be sure to compliment your friends, siblings, children, spouse, and parents regularly.  This can really brighten someone's day, and brings you closer together. <figure rend="Work Together As a Group or Family Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be a good listener.  If your sister comes home in tears from a bad breakup, just listen.  Dig out some ice cream from the fridge or grab some cookies, if you think that would help.  Pay attention to what she has to say!  Don't interrupt her, but if she asks for your opinion, give it (in a kind way, of course).  Sometimes the best thing you can say is absolutely nothing. <figure rend="Work Together As a Group or Family Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Follow all group/family rules.  If you aren't listening to each other, then how are you supposed to work together?  If you don't like the rule about not eating outside of the dining room and kitchen, talk to your parents.  But carrying your nachos around the house with you is probably not going to prove to your parents that you are responsible enough to not drop crumbs.  If you can't change the rules, weigh your options, as mentioned above.  How important is it?  Then either drop the subject all together or patiently and responsibly continue to ask for a change.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try to be a good example.</item>
<item>If you need help, ask.</item></list>
</text>
