<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc151" title="Get Rid of Tensions in Family Life" shortTile="rid-tensions-family" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-09-19" dateModified="2018-10-12" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get_Rid_of_Tensions_in_Family_Life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get Rid of Tensions in Family Life</head><p>The World is going through the deepest of changes in history and has become more competitive than ever. Although this is a pretty good sign, the affection between the family members is affected a lot due to the busy lives of it's members. But, you can always remove the tensions in your family life if you want to.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>As soon as you reach home, try to forget your office work and the tensions caused by your duty. Concentrate on your family and its members. Do not let your office tensions spoil your family life. You can apply for another jobs and post, but not apply for a new family and a time - machine.  <figure rend="Get Rid of Tensions in Family Life Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Invest more time on spending with your family members. Share your everyday experiences with them. You will get closer to one another and there is something like bone will grow stronger and stronger. <figure rend="Get Rid of Tensions in Family Life Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Show your love towards your spouse and children. Greet them often. Kiss and hug them anytime you have the chance. Buy them something occasionally. Take them out and spend some time with them. <figure rend="Get Rid of Tensions in Family Life Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Hug and Kiss your family members often, even for small things. This will enormously increase the bond between you and your family. <figure rend="Get Rid of Tensions in Family Life Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Reminisce the happy moments you had in the past with your family members. Recall those days where you had fun and notice the changes that took place. See that such a congenial atmosphere must be created in your family. You can talk to them about this, purposely accidentally, obviously, and somehow they will beware that they are also responsible for the peace in the family. <figure rend="Get Rid of Tensions in Family Life Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Visit a peaceful place along with your family at least once in a month. It can be a church, or a park or the lakeside. Any place that is peaceful and harmonious will do. Sometimes, maybe a traditional place of the family - gravestone, etc. This will remind the kid(s) and your partner about how important family is to them. <figure rend="Get Rid of Tensions in Family Life Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Whenever there is a decision to be made, take the opinion of all the members. This will show that you respect their opinions as well. <figure rend="Get Rid of Tensions in Family Life Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you have small children, play with them, tell them stories, buy them some playthings. Take turns with your partner to spend time with the baby. <figure rend="Get Rid of Tensions in Family Life Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Never boss over your family members, even if you are the head of the family. Remember that a tree would look ugly if  there are no branches. Hence, everyone must be treated well. The boss things can make everyone frustrated and tired, and they never feel like going home when they have to 'serve orders'. You may not, and intend to think that way, but to them it is. <figure rend="Get Rid of Tensions in Family Life Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do not argue or fight with your spouse for petty issues. See that there are no rifts in your family. However grave the situation is, sit and talk to them regarding the problem and the solution for it. <figure rend="Get Rid of Tensions in Family Life Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Family is more important than anything else for any person. Hence, give utmost priority to your family.</item></list>
</text>
