<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc264" title="Use Fulvic Acid to Improve Health" shortTile="use-fulvic-acid-improve" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-08-02" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Use_Fulvic_Acid_to_Improve_Health" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Use Fulvic Acid to Improve Health</head><p>You might have heard of people taking fulvic acid and are wondering about potential health benefits. Some people claim that it can help with a variety of issues, from brain health to aging. However, it’s important to understand that medical science does not back up these claims. There’s very little reputable research to show that fulvic acid is helpful, and in some cases, it might even be harmful. If you do choose to take a supplement, make sure to talk to your doctor first.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Taking Supplements for Mind and Body Benefits</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Choose liquid or powdered fulvic acid to add trace minerals to your body. You can purchase either form online or at many stores that sell vitamins. The powdered form should be pure black, and you should make sure to buy from a reputable retailer. You can mix  of powder once a day with water or juice. <figure rend="Use Fulvic Acid to Improve Health Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you choose the liquid form, you will take 1 oz. in the morning and evening. You can mix it with either water or juice if you don’t like the taste.</item>
<item>Some manufacturers claim that taking this product will improve digestion and neutralize acidity in the body. Remember to talk to your doctor before trying any supplements.</item></list></item>
<item>Combat aging with fulvic acid. Some suggest that fulvic acid has properties that can slow or reduce the signs of aging. You could try taking a supplement to see if you notice signs of greater vitality. You might find yourself with more energy and glowing skin! <figure rend="Use Fulvic Acid to Improve Health Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Improve brain function by taking fulvic acid. Another purported benefit of fulvic acid is improved cognitive function. Some people have experienced having a better memory and more mental clarity after adding this supplement. <figure rend="Use Fulvic Acid to Improve Health Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Others suggest that fulvic acid may be helpful in controlling some cognitive disorders, such as Alzheimer’s.</item></list></item>
<item>Add supplements for immune-stimulating and antioxidant effects. Another possible benefit of adding fulvic acid to your routine is that it could boost your immune system. In addition to keeping you from becoming sick, you could also notice less symptoms of allergies. <figure rend="Use Fulvic Acid to Improve Health Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Some believe that antioxidants can help protect the body from cancer. Just remember that there is not sound evidence to support that for fulvic acid.</item></list></item>
<item>Choose foods rich in fulvic acid for the safest approach. While there may be some risks involved with supplements, it’s likely safe to add more fulvic acid to your diet. Blackstrap molasses contains fulvic acid, and you can buy it by the bottle at many grocery stores. The best sources of fulvic acid are organic vegetables. <figure rend="Use Fulvic Acid to Improve Health Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Check before buying produce to make sure that it is <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Eat_Organic">organic</ref> to get the most impact.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Using Caution with Fulvic Acid</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Talk to your doctor before taking any supplement. Since supplements can greatly impact your health, you should always check with your doctor before starting one. Every individual has different needs, too, so what’s right for some might not be the best choice for others. Your doctor will be happy to answer your questions about fulvic acid. <figure rend="Use Fulvic Acid to Improve Health Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Understand that there is not comprehensive research on fulvic acid. It is possible that there might be benefits to taking fulvic acid. However, it is important to know that comprehensive, substantive research has not been conducted. You can always ask your doctor to let you know if they hear of any updates in research. <figure rend="Use Fulvic Acid to Improve Health Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Avoid taking fulvic acid if you are taking certain medications. Like all supplements, fulvic acid can have negative interactions with certain medications. Do not take fulvic acid if you are taking any of the following medications: <figure rend="Use Fulvic Acid to Improve Health Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Aspirin</item>
<item>Blood thinners such as warfarin or heparin</item>
<item>NSAIDs such as ibuprofen or naproxen</item></list></item>
<item>Learn how fulvic acid can interact with herbs and supplements. For example, many people take ginkgo biloba, which can act as a blood thinner. Since fulvic acid can possibly increase bleeding, that could lead to a negative interaction. If you use natural anti-histamines or anti-inflammatories, those could also interact with the fulvic acid. <figure rend="Use Fulvic Acid to Improve Health Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Tell your doctor about any herbs or supplements you take so that they can warn you about possible interactions.</item></list></item>
<item>Do not take fulvic acid if you are pregnant or have an autoimmune disease. Since the research is limited, it is not possible to know if fulvic acid is completely safe. If you are pregnant or breastfeeding, play it safe and don’t take it. <figure rend="Use Fulvic Acid to Improve Health Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>It is possible that fulvic acid could potentially worsen some autoimmune diseases. Avoid taking it if you have multiple sclerosis, lupus, or rheumatoid arthritis.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Benefits of and Foods Rich in sFulvic Acid</head>
<p><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Doc:Health_Benefits_of_Fulvic_Acid,Foods_Rich_in_Fulvic_Acid">Doc:Health Benefits of Fulvic Acid,Foods Rich in Fulvic Acid</ref></p>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Talk to your doctor about natural remedies that are right for you.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>There is not scientific evidence that fulvic acid can benefit your health. There may actually be negative effects from taking it. Consult your doctor.</item></list>
</text>
