<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc246" title="Set Up a Commercial Kitchen" shortTile="set-up-commercial" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-06-14" dateModified="2019-08-30" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Set_Up_a_Commercial_Kitchen" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Set Up a Commercial Kitchen</head><p>The layout and design of a commercial kitchen will have a significant influence on the functionality and the potential success of any food service operation. Careful planning and research is required in order to ensure cost efficiency and avoid cost overruns. This article provides a comprehensive list of the equipment needed to design a profitable commercial food service operation.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Purchase and Install Refrigeration</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Purchase and install a walk-in cooling unit. A walk-in cooling unit is a cold storage room designed to maintain the standard refrigeration temperature of 28 to 40 degrees (-2 to 4 ℃). Although some small food service operations may not require a walk-in cooler, the majority of commercial operations will. Walk-in coolers can be custom built to fit any location. Speak to several HVAC contractors and refrigeration specialists to get the best bid. <figure rend="Set Up a Commercial Kitchen Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Purchase an industrial freezer. Commercial kitchen operations typically require freezer space. Commercial freezer units are usually categorized by the number of doors. Purchase a single, double or triple-door freezer, depending on the size and scope of your food service operation. <figure rend="Set Up a Commercial Kitchen Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Purchase a refrigerated line station and supplemental refrigeration units. Adequate refrigeration is a necessity in the commercial kitchen. Food service workers need to keep prepared foods cool prior to preparation and service. A refrigerated line station will be required for the majority of commercial operations. <figure rend="Set Up a Commercial Kitchen Step 3.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Purchase and Install Storage</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Buy storage shelves for perishable and nonperishable foods, dry storage and equipment storage. <figure rend="Set Up a Commercial Kitchen Step 4.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Purchase and Install Cooking Equipment</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Purchase and install an industrial range hood and H-VAC ventilation system. Any commercial operation that prepares food over an open flame, such as a stove top or a broiler, is required to have a range-hood and ventilation system installed. The range hood sits over the top of stove-tops and broilers, and uses fans to pull carcinogenic materials and heat through carbon filters up and out of the building. A range hood can be custom built to fit any location. <figure rend="Set Up a Commercial Kitchen Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Purchase or lease a broiler, a gas range and oven, and an industrial salamander. A broiler or an open flame grill is primarily used to cook grilled meats. Commercial broiling units come in many sizes. <figure rend="Set Up a Commercial Kitchen Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Lease or purchase a combination gas range and oven unit. These units, which are standard equipment in the majority of commercial food service operations, are available in multiple sizes and are typically categorized by the number of burners.</item>
<item>Consider purchasing or leasing a salamander. A salamander typically sits over the range burners and is primarily used to keep plated foods hot prior to service.</item></list></item>
<item>Purchase optional equipment depending on the type and the size of the food service operation. Some commercial kitchens will need to purchase or lease additional items, such as a deep fat fryer, a flat grill or a convection oven. <figure rend="Set Up a Commercial Kitchen Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Purchase Food Preparation Stations and Small Wares</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Purchase prep tables and approved cutting surfaces for food preparation. Stainless steel prep tables come in several sizes, and are essential in the commercial kitchen. Plastic cutting boards can be cut to fit any size table. <figure rend="Set Up a Commercial Kitchen Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Purchase specialty equipment as needed. Specialty equipment may include meat slicers, food processors or industrial-size mixers. <figure rend="Set Up a Commercial Kitchen Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Purchase and Install Fire, Safety and Sanitation Equipment</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Install a sprinkler system and fire extinguishers as required by local fire department regulations. Check with local industrial fire suppression system installers for price quotes. <figure rend="Set Up a Commercial Kitchen Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Install a triple-sink wash station and commercial dish washing unit. Municipal health department authorities typically require a commercial kitchen to have triple-sink wash station and commercial dish washing unit installed. <figure rend="Set Up a Commercial Kitchen Step 11.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>When purchasing equipment, research local restaurant equipment suppliers and compare prices or possible leasing options.</item>
<item>Some municipal health department authorities require that floor-drains be installed in commercial food service facilities. Check with local plumbing and heating contractors for price quotes on installing floor drains.</item>
<item>Some municipal workplace safety authorities require rubber floor mats at all work stations. Rubber floor mats reduce the risk of injury from falling, and also reduce occurrences of certain injuries caused by repetitive stress.</item>
<item>If you are still not quite sure whether you can manage it, contact an expert to help you. You can find those commercial kitchen consultants at any restaurant equipment dealers, and most of the time it is free service!</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
