<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc120" title="Adjust Yourself with the Matriculation After Switching from CBSE" shortTile="adjust-yourself-matriculation" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-05-13" dateModified="2019-10-07" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Adjust_Yourself_with_the_Matriculation_After_Switching_from_CBSE" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Adjust Yourself with the Matriculation After Switching from CBSE</head><p>It is a big confusion for every  student who has completed class 10, whether to switch from CBSE to matriculation? Will the new education system be comfortable? This article will help you to solve the confusion, and answer these questions among others.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Mingle among students. Socialize yourself among the new people you will be surrounded by. Though studies means a lot, it is very important to mingle among the students. This helps you freshen your brain, so that you are mentally and socially strong. When you have a group of friends you will have a helping hand to guide and help you in studies and everything. This step offers great many advantages.</item>
<item>Read and learn but in a new method. Though mugging up of portions will be the first aim in matriculation, don’t force yourself in the first go. In CBSE you will have to read the whole page for once and have repeated the concepts in your mind.
<list type="unordered"><item>A bit difference is what you will be required to do is read the whole page line by line slowly and repeat it in your mind after every line. This is not mugging up. You are understanding the concepts slowly line by line. Try this and you will surely have a better result without forcing yourself.</item></list></item>
<item>Manage your time well. Another big difficulty after switching to matriculation is the time management during examinations. In CBSE you would have written for 100 marks in two and half hours but in matriculation you would be required to write for 200 marks in three hours. This calls for  time management during exams as well as while reading as you will face a huge junk of portions.</item>
<item>Maintain your handwriting. Sometimes in a hurry to complete the paper within time, you often scribble. So try to maintain your handwriting. This will attract the examiner and will give better results.</item>
<item>Join special coaching classes. Make sure you join in special coaching classes such as IIT. As you are an alumnus of a CBSE School you have more chances to shine in IIT, IBM and other such institutions.</item>
<item>Don't rush yourself. Do not force yourself in the new circumstances. Maintain a schedule for reading and ensure regular intervals in between. Do not rage and hurry to win in the race you will be facing. Rather try to maintain a steady growth in your activities.</item>
<item>Engage yourself in sports and other activities. Sports is a better way to shine yourself in your new school. Do not hesitate to join in any sports and other activities such as leaderships. Through this, you will get a better chance to shine yourself and once done you will feel comfortable and satisfied.</item>
<item>Feel free to ask doubts. Do not fear to ask doubts to your teachers and friends. Feel free and be clear with your subjects. Maintain a habit of reading regularly every evening and morning, so that you are thoroughly acquainted with that day’s lessons.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be cool and be free. Don’t be shy, rise and shine not only in studies also in other activities.</item>
<item>Don’t give up in the first go itself. Keep doing and keep trying.</item></list>
</text>
