<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc34" title="Blog About Football" shortTile="blog-football" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2016-01-19" dateModified="2018-03-30" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Blog_About_Football" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Blog About Football</head><p>Blogging about football is rather easy and can be done by anyone with an interest in the sport who wishes to put their thoughts into words and share these with a wider audience. Read on to see just how straightforward it is to start and maintain your own football blog.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find a hosting website. If you're very proficient at IT you could have a go at creating a web page from scratch and personalising it as you wish. However, if you're simply interested in the content rather than the design, it's best to just set up an account on a hosting website such as Blogger, Tumblr, or WordPress. It only takes a matter of minutes to do this before your blog is ready to be written! <figure rend="Start a Blog Step 6 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Decide what you want to cover. Is it going to be a general football blog or will it be focused on a particular team or competition? If your interest is wide ranging and you have opinions on the sport as a whole, then cover a broad spectrum. However, if you have a burning passion for a specific team, hone in on this. A blog targeted towards a team will have a narrower range of interest but those with an interest will be very interested, more so than with a 'catch-all' blog. <figure rend="Be Determined Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Update it regularly. There's plenty going on in the world of football to keep your blog fresh all year round. You should aim to write at least one post a month, but if you can manage it more frequently, all the better. Just be careful that if you're writing more regularly than once a month, the content doesn't become stale or that you're not struggling to find a topic to write about. You're far better off having a strong piece once a month than writing for the sake of it every week. <figure rend="Start a Sports Blog Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Write competently. If you're going to write a regular blog and want people to read it, you should at the very least have the fundamentals of writing. Make sure that your spellings are correct, particularly for tricky player names, and that it reads well. When you're finished writing a blog post, take a five-minute break and then read it back to see if you've made any mistakes. This is time very well spent in order to have a professional-looking, flawless blog post. <figure rend="Become a Sports Journalist Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do your <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Do_Internet_Research">research</ref>. No matter how much you might know about football, it's probable that you will need to double check a fact or statistic that you've mentioned in your blog. Making an assumption and being subsequently corrected for its inaccuracy is not a nice feeling, so put in the effort beforehand and have your facts right before you click Publish. Readers will know when a piece has been researched thoroughly and when one has been hastily tacked together, and if it's the latter, they won't be in a hurry to read your blog in future. <figure rend="Become a Sports Journalist Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Exercise your social media potential. It's more likely than not that, in addition to your blog, you will have a multitude of social media profiles. You don't want your excellent blog to exist in a vacuum, so drum up readership by sharing it on Facebook, Twitter, LinkedIn, Pinterest, etc. If your friends, followers or connections have an interest in football, they'll want to read it and if they're impressed, they'll want to read your blog again and again, and could even share it to their profiles to further expand your blog's reach. <figure rend="Start a Sports Blog Step 20.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Enjoy your writing! Writing about football is a wonderful thing, especially when you can do it to a skilled level, so have a passion for what you're writing about. If you can get that passion across in a coherent, well-constructed blog post, that will be picked up by readers and they will engage with your content. <figure rend="Begin a Persuasive Essay Step 16.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
