<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc100" title="Create a Microatx Computer" shortTile="create-microatx-computer" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2016-10-12" dateModified="2017-02-16" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Create_a_Microatx_Computer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Create a Microatx Computer</head><p>Are you interested in building a MicroATX computer, but are intimidated or uncomfortable with the idea of putting together a complex machine in such little space? If so, this guide will tell you exactly what you need to know in order to put all your parts together into a coherent whole.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Building the Computer</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Put CPU in the motherboard. There is a golden arrow indicator in one of the corners on both the CPU slot and the CPU itself. Make sure that these arrows are aligned in the same corner, otherwise your CPU is not properly orientated. <figure rend="IMG_1837.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Place RAM into RAM socket. The ram should be aligned so that it fits properly in the gap in the socket. (RAM socket located on the right next to CPU socket)  <figure rend="20161012_122240_HDR.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Unscrew side panel from the back of the pc case. Typically, the left hand side is the one that's screwed open.</item>
<item>Screw the standoffs into the case. Standoffs are small, brass colored separators that stop the motherboard from directly touching the case. The case should have several holes for them to be screwed in.</item>
<item>Place the motherboard into the pc case. Line up the holes in the motherboard with the standoffs, and screw the motherboard to the standoffs.</item>
<item>Put the CPU fan on top of the CPU. If you're using the CPU fan that came with the CPU, then you typically only need to latch it or press it on. If you're using a third party cooler, you will likely need to consult their manual, as the process is more complicated. <figure rend="20161012_122311_HDR.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Put the hard drive inside of the hard drive tray. <figure rend="20161012_122355_HDR.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Insert the cd/dvd/blueray ROM/RW from a lot in the front of the PC case. <figure rend="Untitled123 122145.png"></figure></item>
<item>Put PSU in the case, usually on the bottom. Screws will be screwed in from the back. <figure rend="20161012_122300_HDR.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Connect the Motherboard Power Cable to the 24 pin connector. <figure rend="Motherboardpowerzoom.png"></figure></item>
<item>Connect the CPU power to the 4 pin or 8 pin connector.(usually on the top left corner of CPU)</item>
<item>Connect the CPU Fan.(There will be label on a connector say CPU_Fan) <figure rend="Fanpowerzoom.png"></figure></item>
<item>Connect the data and power cables for the hard drive <figure figure🎃👻="" rend="IMG_1840 1123.jpg" 🎃👻<="" 👻🎃figure="">👻🎃/figure&gt;</figure></item>
<item>Connect the data and power for ROM/RW <figure rend="IMG_1840 1321.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Connect the power/reset/USB/LED cables from the case to the motherboard. (connector usually located on bottom right corner) How this is done depends on the case/motherboard manufacturers, check their manual for further instruction. <figure rend="IMG_1838 27854.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>(Optional) Put GPU ON PCI slot, and plug in the PCI power cables.  <figure rend="Gpu.png"></figure></item>
<item>Screw back the side panel.</item>
<item>Connect the PC to an outlet and turn it on.</item>
<item>Put in a disc or USB of your preferred operating system and install it. The specific method of installation depends on the operating system you're using.</item>
<item>Install any motherboard drivers you may need.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>CPU (Central Processing Unit)</item>
<item>CPU Fan</item>
<item>Micro ATX Motherboard</item>
<item>RAM (Random Access Memory)</item>
<item>MicroATX computer case</item>
<item>PSU (Power Supply Unit)</item>
<item>CD/DVD ROM/RAM Drive</item>
<item>Screws (Should come with case)</item>
<item>Screw Driver</item>
<item>Windows OS CD or USB</item>
<item>Standoffs</item>
<item>GPU (Graphics Card) (This is considered optional)</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Make sure all parts are properly connected</item>
<item>For Step 13 and 14 make sure it’s the correct one.</item>
<item>Make sure all cables are properly connected</item></list>
</text>
