<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc147" title="Establish Boundaries with Family" shortTile="establish-boundaries" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-11-01" dateModified="2018-11-01" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Establish_Boundaries_with_Family" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Establish Boundaries with Family</head><p>Boundaries are good and healthy if they are set right. In this article you may find tips for establishing boundaries with your family.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Analyse the situation</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Before you can set healthy boundaries to someone of your family you have to be clear about what you want. Observe the situation and think about what specific behaviour bothers you. Get a notebook and write down what you would like to change and what your goals are.</item>
<item>You have to view the situation from the other persons eyes. Maybe the other person has a complete different view to the situation. The reason for someone to cross your boundaries may be legit from their point of view. If a person has a legit reason to act as he or she does, it's a completely different story than they simply like to push your buttons. Include this reason to your self reflection.</item>
<item>Prepare yourself for a dialogue. Be sure to do the following:
<list type="unordered"><item>Make yourself notes (objective infos are more useful than emotional accusations)</item>
<item>Prepare for the dialogue emotionally (ask yourself how they could possibly react, be prepared)</item>
<item>Make a specific moment to talk about your boundaries with your family member. Be sure you are alone, have time and do not get disturbed.</item></list></item></list>
<head>The Confrontation - Dialogue</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Adress your concerns, talk about how you feel in the situation and what boundaries you'd like to set. Always be patient and objective. Don't let your hurt feelings dominate the dialogue, because if they take the lead, it's possible that you are not able to control the situation anymore.</item>
<item>Give the person the space to explain their behaviour. Try to consider their feelings and reasons.</item>
<item>If the situation gets emotional: Stay cool. Don't get involved in an argument. It's about how you feel and how you'd like to be treated. It's your right to tell other people what is okay or not okay for you. The other person has to reflect his or her behaviour which can be hard for some people.</item>
<item>Talk about your wishes and boundaries as long as necessary, make sure everyone has the same view upon the situation. Set a precise rule who has to be followed by both.</item></list>
<head>After the dialogue</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Take a few weeks time to observe if your boundaries are now respected. If so: good for you, enjoy. If not: adress your concerns as fast and as objective as possible. Be polite if possible.</item>
<item>If nothing changes after a few weeks, you may have to talk about it again.</item></list>
<head>It still didn't work</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Think about the consequences you are willing to deal with. Reflect the situation and think about a solution, if your boundaries are still not being respected.You may seek professional help by a psychotherapist to go to with the other person or involve an official person.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>The other person may react angry. Try to stay as calm as possible. You do reach more if the other person actually understands your point instead of getting emotionally involved.</item>
<item>Try to find an objective view on your own behavior before setting boundaries. If you are a bully to others, chances are that they do not want to change a single thing.</item>
<item>Other people may have a good reason. Be sure you do not have a blind spot there.</item>
<item>You are allowed to end the contact to the other person. But be aware, you will have to face the consequences if you do so.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are being abused sexually or physically, go and get help! You do not have to live with this.</item></list>
</text>
