<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc26" title="Perform 3 of the 5 Compound Movements" shortTile="perform---compound" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-02-12" dateModified="2018-03-05" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Perform_3_of_the_5_Compound_Movements" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Perform 3 of the 5 Compound Movements</head><p>The three main compound movements: the squat, bench press, and deadlift are all described below, for avid gym goers and serious athletes alike. Intended for those who have a general understanding of the movements, as well as the physical demand they require to perform safely. Let's begin, shall we?</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Consult a physician
<list type="unordered"><item>It is important to check with a doctor before starting any exercise program. Any questions about finding a physician/specific health concerns are answered here: <ref target="http://www.fitnesshealth101.com/fitness/cardio/tips/consult-physician">http://www.fitnesshealth101.com/fitness/cardio/tips/consult-physician</ref></item></list></item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Squat</hi>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">The Set Up:</hi>
<list type="unordered"><item>The bar should be in line with your spine with your core, legs, and back tight in place. Inhale as you prepare to lift the bar and squat.</item>
<item>Your feet should be shoulder width apart, turned slightly outwards.</item></list></item>
<item><hi rend="bold">The Process:</hi>
<list type="unordered"><item>Lift Down
<list type="unordered"><item>Squats are similar to sitting in a chair. Bend at the hips, not at the knees. Keep your weight in your heels instead of leaning forward onto your toes.</item>
<item>Continue downward until a 90 degree angle is formed between your hamstring and calf muscles.</item></list></item>
<item>Lift Up
<list type="unordered"><item>The push upwards should come from your heels, legs, and hips. Watch your knees to make sure they don't begin to cave inwards.</item>
<item>Keep your balance until you have returned to your starting position.</item></list></item></list></item></list></item>
<item>Know what to avoid
<list type="unordered"><item>Leaning too far forward</item>
<item>Pushing from your toes</item>
<item>Bending at the waist instead of the hips</item>
<item>Squatting with an 'uneven' bar</item></list></item>
<item>Do the bench press
<list type="unordered"><item>The set up. With your hands shoulder width, grip the bar with your feet flat on the ground. Your wrists should be in line with your arm. Retracting your shoulders will also help protect your shoulder joints as you progress.</item>
<item>Lift down. As you breathe inward, slowly and evenly lower the weight until it touches your chest.  Keeping your elbows close to your body will also protect your shoulders; don't let them fan outwards.</item>
<item>Lift up. Using your feet for stability, raise the bar in a straight line back to the starting position, with arms fully extended.</item></list></item>
<item>Know what to avoid
<list type="unordered"><item>Pressing unevenly or without control</item>
<item>Pressing too high above the chest</item>
<item>Elbows flaring outward</item>
<item>Benching with a flat back</item>
<item>Benching without using your feet</item></list></item>
<item>Do the deadlift</item>
<item>Do the set up.  Feet shoulder width apart, with hands closely outside of your legs.
<list type="unordered"><item>Your back should form a straight line from tailbone to shoulders, with your head upwards.</item>
<item>Shoulders should be over the bar, with the bar midway over the foot.</item>
<item>Lift down. As with the squat, you want to push from the heels. Hamstrings, glutes, and hips will drive the weight in this movement, as your arms follow upwards with the bar.</item>
<item>Lift up. As you begin to lower the weight, take note of your shins. Make sure to avoid hitting them, as they are no match for a barbell. Slowly bend at the hips, bend at the hips, and return the weight to the floor.</item></list></item>
<item>Know what to avoid
<list type="unordered"><item>Excessive Rounding of the spine</item>
<item>Bending at the waist instead of the hips</item>
<item>Letting your hips hinge too high</item>
<item>Over emphasizing the lock out</item>
<item>Pushing from your toes</item>
<item>Lifting with bent arms</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Quality over quantity. Rushing reps compromises form and safety.</item>
<item>Filming lifts or having a partner critique them can be helpful.</item>
<item>If you jump to weight lifting equipment too early, It will hinder further progress.</item>
<item>Keep a reasonable frequency with these movements. They tax your body heavily.</item>
<item>Including the right accessory work can help avoid imbalances and improve future lifts.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>These movements can lead to injury if performed incorrectly. Utilize extreme caution whenever you squat, bench, or deadlift.</item>
<item>Each of these compound movements recruits the entire body. Give yourself proper time to recover.</item>
<item>Be patient with your progressions. This is the best way to make improvement and avoid injury.</item>
</list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Weight Belt/Lifting Straps/Chalk (for heavier weights only)</item>
<item>Thin soled gym shoes</item>
<item>Access to:  a) Squat Rack   b) Bench Press   c) Deadlift Platform</item></list>
</text>
