<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc282" title="Stay Healthy During the Summer" shortTile="stay-healthy-during" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-06-07" dateModified="2018-10-04" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Stay_Healthy_During_the_Summer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Stay Healthy During the Summer</head><p>Well, its that time of year again! Summer! It can be hard to stay motivated and fit during the warm weather. But a change in the season also brings lots of opportunities for outdoor activities. As long as you follow these simple steps it will be easy peasy to stay healthy.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Eat fruits and vegetables. They are very important. Even though it is summer doesn't mean you don't eat healthy!
<list type="unordered"><item>Eating healthy is important as fruits and vegetables have increased fluids and vitamins in them which helps keep you hydrated and strong to enjoy the summer days.</item></list></item>
<item>Don't spend to much time on electronics. Its nice and warm; go get some outside time!</item>
<item>Take walks! Taking walks is both fun and relaxing! Even if you go and take a five minute walk around the neighbourhood, it is still better than being a couch potato!
<list type="unordered"><item>Walks can help you get the beneficial sunlight and exercise. As vitamin D from sun exposure can help with the absorption of nutrients like Calcium, just remember to apply sunscreen.</item></list></item>
<item>Make sure to stay hydrated! You definitely need to drink a LOT of water in order to stay healthy, otherwise you will get sick.</item>
<item>Don't skip any meals. If you're on summer vacation, you might be sleeping in, but make sure you don't skip breakfast! Otherwise you will be hungry, and you don't want to be left with an empty stomach!</item>
<item>Get lots of sleep! Even though you don't need to wake up early the next morning doesn't mean you don't need to get lots of sleep! Because if you don't, you will be very drowsy the next day!</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Even if it is not summer it is still a good idea to follow these steps!</item>
<item>Dress appropriately, dressing to heavy can cause you to be to hot and possibly get heat stroke or exhaustion and to dressing to light without proper precautions such as sunscreen can cause extensive, painful burns.</item>
<item>Avoid the hottest parts of the day. Know when its the hottest and avoid them, in some areas its hottest between 10a and 2p, this can stop you from burning and developing things such as heat stroke.</item>
<item>Utilizing a SPF of at least 15 is important, although some say you do not have to spend excessive money on sunscreens of 100 or more as the benefits are not that increased.</item>
<item>Wear sunglasses to protect your eyes from excessive sun, just because it may not seem like it excessive sun can damage your eyes and cause cancer years later.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't walk to long on a hot day without enough water.</item>
<item>Avoid excessive exercise in extreme heat.</item>
<item>Test sunscreens and sun protectants on your skin in small patches, before utilizing a larger area to avoid allergic reactions and any skin irritations.</item></list>
</text>
