<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc222" title="Make Mostaccioli" shortTile="make-mostaccioli" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2019-09-30" dateModified="2019-10-24" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make_Mostaccioli" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make Mostaccioli</head><p>For all the pasta lovers out there, this recipe is for you! This cheesy pasta recipe is easy to create, and is not time consuming whatsoever. Whether you're cooking dinner, having a get-together, or even family game night, this delicious recipe will have your guests craving more! This tasteful recipe is guaranteed to keep you and your guests full for the rest of the night. This recipe serves 10-12 people. Need more? No problem just double the ingredients! This recipe can be made with meat as well for all the meat lovers! All it takes is one extra and easy step!</p>
<head>Ingredients</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>2 boxes of penne pasta (you may choose any type of pasta except spaghetti and linguine)</item>
<item>2 64. oz bottles of Prego Traditional Pasta Sauce</item>
<item>Four tomatoes diced</item>
<item>Two onions diced</item>
<item>1/2 head of celery diced</item>
<item>OPTIONAL: Two pounds of ground beef (Add 1/2 tsp of salt, black pepper, paprika, and garlic powder)</item>
<item>Five garlic cloves diced</item>
<item>1/2 Tbsp vegetable oil</item>
<item>2 Tbsp Garlic Powder</item>
<item>1 Tbsp Onion Powder</item>
<item>1/2 Tbsp Black Pepper</item>
<item>1/2 Tbsp Salt</item>
<item>Dash of oregano</item>
<item>One pound of mozzarella (make sure it is not frozen)</item>
<item>One large aluminum tray 21X13</item></list>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Preheat the oven to 350 degrees. Boil 12 cups of water in a large pot on medium heat.
<list type="unordered"><item>Optional: Add a pinch of salt and 1/2 Tbsp of vegetable oil. After 15 minutes, the water should be boiling.</item></list></item>
<item>Place both boxes of pasta into the boiling water for 12 minutes.</item>
<item>Drain the pasta in a strainer. Allow all the water to be removed. Rinse pasta out with warm water.</item>
<item>Cook the ground beef with the necessary seasonings. The meat must be well done. This step is optional</item>
<item>Take your diced onions and cook them. Add 1/2 Tbsp of vegetable oil. Cook until the onions are golden.</item>
<item>Add the celery, garlic cloves, and the diced tomatoes. Allow them to cook with the cover on the pot so they can cook evenly.</item>
<item>Add your two jars of pasta sauce into the pot. Add the garlic powder, onion, powder, black pepper and salt to the sauce as well. Let the sauce boil.</item>
<item>Add your noodles. Allow them to cook together for 2-5 minutes.</item>
<item>Add the pasta into the aluminium trays. Distribute the pasta evenly in the tray and add half a pound of mozzarella cheese. Mix the cheese together with the pasta</item>
<item>Take another half pound of cheese. Add that on top of the pasta mixture. Do not mix this into the pasta</item>
<item>Add a dash of oregano on top of the cheese.</item>
<item>Put the tray into the oven. Allow the pasta to cook for 40-45 minutes. OPTIONAL: Broil for another 5 minutes on HIGH heat for a crispy cheese topping</item>
<item>Take the tray out of the oven. Allow it to sit for at least five minutes to prevent sloppy servings.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Penne noodles work the best and are much more ascetically pleasing!</item>
<item>Make sure mozzarella cheese is not frozen when added to the pasta mixture</item>
<item>You may use any kind of sauce. Prego is the most flavorful</item>
<item>Do not grease up your trays</item>
<item>Best served with garlic bread</item>
<item>Best to use ground beef with some fat for more flavor</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not over bake. This will cause the pasta to become dry and take away the flavor</item></list>
</text>
