<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc129" title="Have a Senior Year of High School Full of Electives" shortTile="senior-year-high" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-02-03" dateModified="2016-08-18" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Have_a_Senior_Year_of_High_School_Full_of_Electives" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Have a Senior Year of High School Full of Electives</head><p>If your senior year of high school is filled with electives, you may find it hard to balance this with your studies, social life and need for downtime. In order to fit it all in, you'll need to consider how to schedule everything well, including setting aside standard coursework, and be ready to work even harder than many of the other students around you.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be prepared to work hard. To have the joy of having your entire senior year of high school full of electives you must be a hard worker. It will take you lots of possible work overloads and stressful situations where everything's seems chaotic (this is because you would have to take all your required academic courses in earlier years in high school).</item>
<item>Make the right decisions when choosing coursework. When doing course selection, if you'd like an entire year of electives, your decisions are crucial because they can impact your plan to have an academic-free school year. If would be a good idea to check up on all your required courses for your high school to graduate. This will give you a better understanding of the courses you should take in your grade 9-11 years.</item>
<item>Aim to have electives only. With all the required courses taken already in grades 9-11, you will be able to have an entire year dedicated to just electives. Be warned, though, most people will try to discourage you from this idea of saving all your electives until your senior year because your workload in your earlier years may be completely out of hand, as you don't know what your years of schedules will be like ahead of time.</item>
<item>Consider the opposite. If you were to take your electives as planned, with a limited amount each year to go along with your academics, it would give you quite the ease because electives are often considered easier than academics and a relief when you already have lots of homework coming from other classes.</item>
<item>Graduate before others. Lastly, if you would really like to go down this path of waiting till your senior year to take your electives, you can also ponder the idea of possibly even graduating early! If you'd really like to just get all your academics done with and are only saving your electives until last because you think they'll be easier but don't really want to do them, graduating early might be a possibility for you. Of course, you'd have to talk to your advisor first because that kind of stuff differs depending on where you live.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>It'd be a good idea to think about what you are going to do post-secondary as well. Are you going to go to university or college? All these aspects contribute to your decisions for choosing academics in your later years in high school. To get into your post-secondary school you must also read up on what it takes to qualify to be accepted by that school (some require that you have taken certain courses, and some require your grades to be at a certain point to be accepted).</item></list>
</text>
