<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc57" title="Be a Good Guest Track Announcer" shortTile="good-guest-track" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2013-01-31" dateModified="2018-03-22" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_a_Good_Guest_Track_Announcer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be a Good Guest Track Announcer</head><p>Imagine, my friends, you are watching the Kentucky Derby. All of a sudden, the "bugle player" plays "Boots and Saddles" gathering up the horses. They soon head into the starting gate and before you know it, they're off and racing with the track announcer giving all the race details over the PA system. If you get the opportunity to call a race, then here is what you need to do in order to make the happen. Good luck at calling you first race.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Before this, go to a race and experience it for yourself. That way, you can see how the race is done and how they call them <figure rend="Be a Good Guest Track Announcer Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Next, when the opportunity arrives, get to the track early and ask to meet with the announcer <figure rend="Be a Good Guest Track Announcer Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Go over the horses names that will be racing in each race and write down their pronunciation, though many are fairly easy to say. <figure rend="Be a Good Guest Track Announcer Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Practice, practice, practice. Yes, have that old phrase stuck in you head. Just pretend to call a race either watching an old race on the television or write down your own race calls. Now is the time to make mistakes, not when you are talking live to the spectators. Your job is to accurately describe what's going on in the race. <figure rend="Be a Good Guest Track Announcer Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If the original announcer is with you, get your cues from him on when to say different things before the actual race. Obviously, during the race itself, you will have to say what's happening then <figure rend="Be a Good Guest Track Announcer Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Adjust the binoculars; all track announcers will use binoculars, whether they hold them in their hands or if they are on a tripod. Also, check your headset microphone, obviously, it has to be a headset so you can talk and handle the binoculars. <figure rend="Be a Good Guest Track Announcer Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Stay calm. It's not going to help your announcing if you start to panic. Just relax, breath slowly in and out a couple of times and say "I could make a mistake, but I'll move on and overall just do my best" the actual announcer will be will you the entire race giving you support. <figure rend="Be a Good Guest Track Announcer Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>During the race read quickly, (not like an auctioneer) but clearly so the people can understand what's happening. <figure rend="Be a Good Guest Track Announcer Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>In between races, stay hydrated. It's good for you to drink water so that 1) you have a good clear voice and 2) it'll also relax you and not feel as tense. <figure rend="Be a Good Guest Track Announcer Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>At the end of all the races, thank the people for coming and to drive safely. Turn off your wireless headset Microphone and thank the actual announcer for letting you do the races. Good luck, as this may be a huge step in your broadcasting career. <figure rend="Be a Good Guest Track Announcer Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Again to recap; read quick but clearly, stay hydrated, stay calm and practice</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Keep liquids well away from any electronics</item></list>
</text>
