<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc157" title="Manage a Family Life" shortTile="manage-family-life" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-12-11" dateModified="2018-10-12" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Manage_a_Family_Life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Manage a Family Life</head><p>Families come in all shapes and sizes. It doesn't matter what your family looks like, so long as it provides a solid and loving base for your children. But a happy, well-functioning family doesn't just happen, it takes a bit of effort.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Communication: It’s important to talk through family issues with all family members, including children.</item>
<item>Sharing tasks: Think about how you can divide up jobs so everyone is happy.</item>
<item>Social life: Think about ways everyone in the family can meet their needs for a social life.</item>
<item>Routines: Consider your daily routines and figure out what system works best for all members of the family. Routines make children feel safe and secure, and can make the busy times of day less stressful for everyone.</item>
<item>Preferred reactions: Talk about how you would like everyone to respond to difficult or challenging situations like tiredness, an upset child or financial pressures.</item>
<item>Create awareness. Notice when you make decision that puts the needs of others before your own. Pay attention to when your energy gets drained. Witness yourself. How does it feel if you ditch your dreams? What’s it like for you to feel disapproved of?</item>
<item>Affection, positive attention and family time: everyone in the family needs to feel loved and valued. Make sure your children and your partner receive lots of encouragement, positive feedback and signs of affection. It’s also important to make time every week to do things as a family, even a short walk or a visit to the park can help bring you together.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Begin to implement one small boundary at a time:You have every right to create the life you desire, so begin to carve out small spaces for your true self to shine through. For example, answer the phone a little bit less often or say that you will have to call someone back when you have more time. Quit being available 24/7. Once you become comfortable with that, create a slightly bigger boundary. For example, resist the urge to ask others what they think you should do and instead tell them what you have planned. Begin to take more ownership over the life you want to create for yourself.</item>
<item>Shift your mindset::The intention behind your boundaries is not to keep your family out. The intention is to live the life of your dreams and be who you really are. In everything we do, it is incredibly important that the motivation behind our actions is rooted in positive and in our authentic desires rather than in negativity or fear!</item>
<item>Stop being apologetic about yourself and your dreams. If you act as if your decisions are offensive, wrong in other people’s eyes or will draw disapproval, that is what you will get. Instead, practice saying what you have planned for yourself with confidence and passion in your voice and body language.</item></list>
</text>
