<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc208" title="Understand the Five Foundations of Personal Finance" shortTile="understand-five-foundations" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-01-07" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Understand_the_Five_Foundations_of_Personal_Finance" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Understand the Five Foundations of Personal Finance</head><p>When it comes to personal finance, understanding what you should do can be quite difficult. By following the basic foundations of personal finance, you'll be able to live a happy and debt free life and retire with financial confidence.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>The First Foundation: Save a $500 Emergency Fund</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Build an adequately stocked emergency fund for any <hi rend="italic">unexpected</hi> emergencies.  <figure rend="The First Foundation Step 1 Version 1.png"></figure></item>
<item>Keep your Emergency Fund separate from your spending money. <figure rend="5 Foundations Step 2 Versionn 3.png"></figure></item>
<item>After you're out of school/older, you'll need to grow your Emergency Fund. <figure rend="5 Foundations Step 2 Version 4.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>A good three to six months' worth of expenses should do.</item></list></item>
<item>Make your Emergency Fund your first savings priority. <figure rend="5 Foundations Step 3 Version 2.png"></figure></item></list>
<head>The Second Foundation: Get out of Debt</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Our society today believes <hi rend="bold">debt is a normal part of life.</hi> Really, "<hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Debt is dumb!</hi></hi>" <figure rend="The Second Foundation Step 1 Version 1.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Debt is everywhere. It should be considered as a <hi rend="italic">product</hi>, not a <hi rend="italic">privilege</hi>.
<list type="unordered"><item>Nearly 70% of Americans are living paycheck to paycheck. Cause? Overspending and too much debt.</item></list></item></list></item>
<item>Don't be fooled by what the public tells you about debt. <figure rend="5 Foundations Step 2 Version 2.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>"The world wants us to believe that debt is a <hi rend="italic">service</hi> or <hi rend="italic">reward</hi> that is offered to help consumers."</item></list></item>
<item>Keep this in mind: "When it comes to debt, if you tell a lie or spread a myth long enough, eventually it becomes accepted as the truth. <hi rend="bold">The truth is, debt is a product - <hi rend="italic">the most successfully marketed product in history</hi></hi>"</item></list>
<head>The Third Foundation: Pay Cash for your Car</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>By paying cash for your car you will lower the risk of falling into substantial debt. <figure rend="The Third Foundation Step 1 Version 1.png"></figure></item>
<item>Don't get lured in by the claim that "car payments area a way of life, and you'll always have one."
<list type="unordered"><item>By staying away from car payments you will save money and be financially independent.</item></list></item>
<item>Watch out for the following tricks that can cause you to lose when you buy a new car: <figure rend="5 Foundations Step 2 Version 5.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>"<hi rend="bold">1. Payments.</hi> Spreading the purchase of an automobile over four or five years hinders your ability to pay off debt or save money for that time.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">2. Interest.</hi> Included in the payment, of course, are the interest charges. That means you pay more than the sticker price. It's like buying a $20,000 vehicle for $23,000.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">3. Depreciation.</hi> This is the biggest one. If you purchase a $20,000 car, it will be worth about $8,000 in four years. That's in addition to all the gasoline, maintenance and other stuff. You could buy a $20,000 beater and get the same use out of it for those same four years without taking a $12,000 hit."</item></list></item>
<item>Don't be fooled by car loan myths. Two of these are given below: <figure rend="5 Foundations Step 4 Version 2.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>"<hi rend="bold">Myth [1]:</hi>
<list type="unordered"><item>Leasing your car is what sophisticated financial people do. You should always lease things that go down in value. There are tax advantages.</item></list></item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Truth [1]:</hi>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">Consumer Reports, Smart Money</hi> magazine and a good calculator will tell you that a car lease is the <hi rend="bold">most expensive</hi> way to finance and operate a vehicle.</item>
<item>If you own a business, you can write off your paid-for car on taxes without making payments for the privilege.</item>
<item>The way to minimize the money lost on things that go down in value is to <hi rend="bold">buy slightly used.</hi></item></list></item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Myth [2]:</hi>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can get a <hi rend="italic">good deal</hi> on a <hi rend="italic">new</hi> car.</item></list></item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Truth [2]:</hi>
<list type="unordered"><item>A new car loses <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">70%</hi></hi> of its value in the first four years. This is the largest purchase most consumers make that goes down in value."</item></list></item></list></item></list>
<head>The Fourth Foundation: Pay Cash for College</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Today, people feel that student loan debt is normal or unavoidable. Some even call it <hi rend="italic">good debt</hi>. <figure rend="The Fourth Foundation Step 1 Version 1.png"></figure></item>
<item>"<hi rend="bold">Be Aware:</hi> Student loans will be listed in your financial aid award package as well." <figure rend="5 Foundations Step 3 Version 3.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Student loans are not to be seen as awards. It could take up to 20 years just to pay them all back; not to mention you'll also have to pay interest.</item></list></item>
<item>When it comes to student loans, the money can begin to rack up quick.
<list type="unordered"><item>"The total estimated student loan debt in [the United States] is one <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">trillion</hi></hi> dollars."
<list type="unordered"><item>$85 billion of this debt is unpaid. Do you really think it should be considered <hi rend="italic">good debt</hi>?</item></list></item></list></item></list>
<head>The Fifth Foundation: Build Wealth and Give</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Watch out for false perceptions. An example of this would be the idea "I am just <hi rend="bold">one</hi> person." <figure rend="The Fifth Foundation Step 1 Version 1.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Your goal should be to build wealth in the long run, but giving to others in need will not only improve your well being but can also better your future long after you're gone.</item></list></item>
<item>Identify your core values. <figure rend="The Fifth Foundation Step 2 Version 1.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>"Begin the process of discovering the real you! We;re talking about your values, your interests and your passions. The things that make you, YOU."</item></list></item>
<item>Make an impact. Use your money, time, and/or talents to help others and change your community for the better.
<list type="unordered"><item>Just because you don't have a lot of cash right now doesn't mean you can't give. You have a lot to give that doesn't have a monetary value.</item></list></item>
<item>Remember: "<hi rend="bold">Open Hands Build Wealth</hi>"
<list type="unordered"><item>"When you hold your money in an open hand, life looks a lot different.</item>
<item>It may take a little longer to reach your financial goals, but you're investing in something far more valuable.</item>
<item>When you give, you impact a person's life permanently.</item>
<item>The joy of giving lasts longer than the happy feeling you get when you spend money on yourself.</item>
<item>It's okay to spend money on yourself. Just make sure you spend money to help other people as well.</item>
<item>Need another reason to give? It's just plain fun."</item></list></item>
<item>Create your legacy.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Use what is called an <hi rend="italic">envelope system</hi> to properly budget out your expenses at the beginning of every month.
<list type="unordered"><item>The envelope system works as follows: "Decide how much you have to spend on each specific category and place that amount in an envelope. [Don't forget to label your envelopes.] When the envelope the envelope for a specific area of spending - like clothing or entertainment - is empty, you are done spending in that area for the month."</item></list></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not give in to impulse buys. These can damage your financial well-being and postpone your goals for the future.</item></list>
</text>
