<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc272" title="Use Biofeedback Therapy" shortTile="use-biofeedback-therapy" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2017-06-05" dateModified="2019-06-05" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Use_Biofeedback_Therapy" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Use Biofeedback Therapy</head><p>Biofeedback therapy is a technique used by many to help alleviate or prevent a variety of conditions, such as but not limited to high blood pressure, chronic pain, migraines, and certain psychological disorders .  In this therapy, sensors are placed on the body and body conditions such as heart rate are monitored.  The therapy allows one to control normally involuntary physiological processes of the body such as heart rate, muscle tone, and pain perception. There are no drugs involved in this treatment and it is a noninvasive procedure, reducing the rick for complications as well as reducing side effects.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Visit your primary care physician and determine if biofeedback therapy is the right fit for you.  Based on your health, biofeedback therapy may be the best option for you.  Talk to your health care provider and see if it is the best option for you.  Often times, this type of therapy is recommended for those who can't take medications for their specific conditions or would prefer not to.</item>
<item>Find a therapist. If it is the right fit for you, talk to your health care provider about finding a therapist a therapist in your area. Look at reviews and customer satisfaction to find a reputable one.</item>
<item>Schedule an initial appointment with your therapist.  During this appointment you will discuss your health conditions and concerns with the therapist and determine the best biofeedback method for you.
<list type="unordered"><item>Figure out approximately how many sessions you'll need and how long they will be.</item>
<item>Make sure to ask them any other questions you may have general or specific to your therapy.</item></list></item>
<item>Start therapy.You should be seated comfortably as your therapist attaches sensors onto the appropriate part of your body which it to be monitored (based on the method determination).  The sensors will detect and record physiological signs.  You will receive these via cues such as a beeping noise.</item>
<item>Pay attention to the cues and register them.Doing so will allow you to be truly aware of your physiological state.  Make sure to pay attention to your thoughts and emotions while you receive cues as these are indicative of what is going on in your head that is causing your current physiological condition.</item>
<item>Perform your first exercise.  Your therapist will help you control the state through a variety of relaxation exercises.  These will allow you to indirectly control physiological properties, such as heart rate  The exercises include deep breathing, muscle relaxation, guided imagery, and mindfulness meditation.</item>
<item>Focus on the second set of cues during and post-exercise. As you perform the exercise, you will see a change in your body functions, such as heart rate or breathing.  The sensors on your body will detect these changes and transmit them onto the monitor so that you can see these changes for your self.  For example, if you will be able to see that your heart rate has lowered after an exercise on the monitor.</item>
<item>Try out various exercises and see which one(s) work best for you.  Certain exercises may work best for certain conditions, so going through all the exercises to the best of your ability will ensure successful therapy!</item>
<item>Take notes. Doing so will allow you to keep track of your progress.  Your notes may include a list of the best exercises for you, you thoughts while in therapy, any suggestions your therapist makes, etc.</item>
<item>Practice the exercises at home.  These should be the exercises your therapist recommends you use for your particular condition.  Practice should be 5 to 10 minutes of your day.</item>
<item>Go to all of your scheduled sessions. Consistency is key so it is essential that you don't miss a sessions.  Make sure to plan out all your sessions ahead of time if possible.   If you absolutely must miss a sessions, make sure to contact your therapist ahead of time and reschedule.</item>
<item>If necessary, purchase equipment and programs for use at home.  If you want to see the changes in your body functions while practicing your relaxation techniques at home, you may purchase the programs used in therapy.  Ask your therapist about where you can purchase such programs.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Biofeedback therapy requires no drugs and in non-invasive, so therefore, it is unlikely that something would go wrong in the procedure. However, problems may arise with the technology and machines being used in the process.  If the technology malfunctions while in therapy, your therapist should be able to get other equipment to keep the session going.  If not, make sure to reschedule the appointment.  If decide to buy the technology,  call the manufacturer if you encounter issues.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<p>Certain machines will be used based on your condition and will be provided to you during your sessions. These machines include, but are not limited to:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>electromyograph (analyzes muscle activity)</item>
<item>feedback thermometer (analyzes body temperature)</item>
<item>electrodermograph (analyzes skin electrical activity)</item>
<item>electroencephalograph (analyzes electrical activity of the brain)</item></list>
</text>
