<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc84" title="Remove E Clips" shortTile="remove-e-clips" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-06-01" dateModified="2019-09-23" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Remove_E_Clips" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Remove E Clips</head><p>E-clips are a type of tool used for projects including car engines and locking mechanisms. They resemble an "E" shape, and they have 1 side with an opening. E-clips are large retaining rings, and retaining rings hold parts onto a shaft when installed into a groove. To remove an E-clip, use either a remover tool, needle-nose pliers, or a small, flathead screwdriver. Grasp the E-clip with your tool and push it upwards using moderate pressure. You can easily remove E-clips with another household tool.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Using an E-Clip Remover</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Align your remover tool with the edge of the E-clip. Most E-clip removers have a smooth, curved edge. Line up the curved edge on your tool with the curve of the E-clip, and place your tool just below the E-clip.
<list type="unordered"><item>There are several different types of E-clip removers, and you can use them all in a similar way.</item></list></item>
<item>Push upwards and apply steady, moderate pressure. Once your tool is aligned with the E-clip, simply press up on the tool to remove it from its position.
<list type="unordered"><item>Be careful not to use too much pressure, or the E-clip may go flying!</item></list></item>
<item>Store your E-clip in a dry location until you use it next. Place your E-clip in a storage jar, bin, or container. You can easily use them again and again for other projects involving tools.
<list type="unordered"><item>You can store these in your shop or in a tool box, for instance.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Removing an E-Clip with Pliers</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Move the middle of the E-clip toward the side so you can grasp it. To easily remove the E-clip,  you want the curved side of the E-clip facing you. If necessary, use your fingers or a pair of needle-nose pliers to twist it around. The E-clip should slide easily with moderate pressure.</item>
<item>Grab the center of the E-clip with needle-nose pliers. Pinch the middle of your E-clip with the tip of your needle-nose pliers. Hold the pliers securely so you can remove the clip.
<list type="unordered"><item>Needle-nose pliers work the best to easily remove the E-clips. However, you can use other types of pliers as well, like slip-joint pliers or locking pliers.</item></list></item>
<item>Pull the E-clip toward you with moderate pressure. While grasping the E-clip, pull back on your pliers to take the clip out of its position.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are having trouble gripping the E-clip, adjust your pliers so the tip is closer to the middle.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Using a Flathead Screwdriver</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Align the screwdriver with 1 of the small grooves in the middle. Place the tip of your screwdriver inside the groove on the clip. Each E-clip has 2 small grooves in the middle, 1 for the left side and 1 for the right side. You can use either groove to help remove the E-clip.
<list type="unordered"><item>For best results, use a screwdriver that is proportionate to the size of the E-clip.</item></list></item>
<item>Place your finger directly next to the E-clip to catch it when it moves. Hold your index finger of your non-dominant hand up to the E-clip along the top edge.
<list type="unordered"><item>This way, you can prevent the E-clip from flying far away when you remove it.</item></list></item>
<item>Push up on the screwdriver with moderate pressure. Hold your screwdriver with your dominant hand, and push the tool upwards consistently.
<list type="unordered"><item>The E-clip should easily come out. If it doesn’t, apply a bit more pressure.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>E-clips come in various sizes, from  to .</item>
<item>E-clips are commonly used in  repair and maintenance shops.</item>
<item>You can choose from black or silver E-clips.</item>
<item>Purchase E-clips at most home supply or auto supply stores.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Put on safety glasses before you start. This way, your eyes are protected in case an E-clip shoots upwards.</item></list>
</text>
