<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc223" title="Make Potato Pierogi" shortTile="make-potato-pierogi" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2019-10-19" dateModified="2019-10-21" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make_Potato_Pierogi" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make Potato Pierogi</head>This delightful comfort food has been a staple to polish people for centuries. It is almost sufficient to say the entire country is known for their food, specifically pierogi. This is the type of food you want to eat after having a really bad day and you just want to brighten up your mood. And the best part is, you can fill them with anything! Just swap out the filling instructions and fill it with your own preference! Every polish child grew up with their grandma in the kitchen making the weekly batch of pierogi while also learning how to do so. This is my grandmother’s special perfected recipe that I am glad to share with anyone truly looking for a great pierogi experience. Everyone always thinks that pierogi are so difficult to make so it is best to always just buy them. This is probably the worst assumption one can make. They are not hard to make at all. This recipe will take you approximately 3 hours total to complete, not including the best part of eating them. Once you have tasted the difference between store bought and homemade pierogi, you can never go back. That is why you must try this recipe for yourself.
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Ingredients List</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>This is everything you will need to make these delightful pierogi.
<list type="unordered"><item>5 lbs Idaho potatoes</item>
<item>3 yellow onions</item>
<item>3 blocks of cream cheese (or 3 cups of any cheese desired)</item>
<item>Salt and pepper to taste</item>
<item>3 1/2 cups of all-purpose flour</item>
<item>2 eggs</item>
<item>1/2 stick of butter</item>
<item>1 tbsp of sour cream</item>
<item>1 cup of hot water</item></list></item></list>
<head>Make the Dough</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Combine all of the wet ingredients. Take a cup of hot water (warm in microwave) &amp; place stick of butter in water &amp; mix it slowly until it melts so that the liquid is uniform. Combine all of the dry ingredients. Place all of the flour in a big mixing bowl. Break the eggs open and add to bowl with flour. Mix all of the wet and dry ingredients together. Add hot water with butter to bowl of flour and egg mixture. Add the sour cream to the dough mixture. Add sour cream to dough mixture and mix thoroughly so that there are no big clumps of flour left. Put dough aside for later.</item></list>
<head>Make the Filling</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Cook the potatoes. Peel &amp; cut each potato in the bag of potatoes into 4 or 5 pieces. Place all the potatoes in a pot of water with a pinch of salt &amp; bring to a boil. Let boil for about 30 minutes. Cook the onions. Peel &amp; chop onions and place in frying pan with some oil. Fry onions until caramelized, slightly brown in color. Combine the ingredients. Place potatoes, onions &amp; cream cheese in large mixing bowl &amp; mash &amp; mix together. Add salt &amp; pepper to taste.</item></list>
<head>Assembling the Pierogi</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Prepare your pierogi making station. You will need a large surface at least 3 feet by 4 feet to assemble the pierogi on. This can even be a clean countertop or table. Use a large cutting board if accessible. Make sure to clean the surface and then let it dry completely so none of the flour sticks. After it dries, pour a thin layer of flour over the whole surface.</item>
<item>Separate the dough. Separate the dough into 4 batches so that you can cook some pierogi in one batch while assembling the other batch.</item>
<item>Roll out the dough. Take one of the 4 pieces of dough out of the bowl &amp; place on wooden board. With a rolling pin, roll out the dough until it is about 1/8 inch thick.</item>
<item>Cut the dough for individual pierogi. Press the rim of a circular glass into the dough, cutting out a circle, until all of the dough is used. You will need to ball up the dough and roll it out again when you cannot cut another circle out of it anymore. Reference photo above (Perogy Project, 2010). <figure rend="Abarto.png"></figure></item>
<item>Shape the filling for the pierogi. Take 1 tablespoon of the filling out of the bowl and roll it in between your hands until it forms the shape of a golf ball. Do this with all of the filling until there is no more filling to form.</item>
<item>Assemble the pierogi. Put one ball of filling in the center of one circle of dough and fold the dough into a half-circle. You will pinch the ends of the dough together so that the filling does not fall out. They should look like this after assembly (The Black Peppercorn, 2019).  <figure figure🎃👻="" rend="Abarto3.jpg" 🎃👻<="" 👻🎃figure="">👻🎃/figure&gt;</figure></item></list>
<head>Start Cooking!</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>You will be boiling the assembled pierogi in a big pot of water. Take a large pot &amp; fill it with water &amp; a pinch of salt &amp; bring to a low boil. Continue forming pierogi while you wait for the water to boil.</item>
<item>Watch until the pierogi are done boiling. Once you have about 15-20 pierogi ready, place them in the pot of boiling water to cook. The pierogi are finished cooking when they float to the top of the water. Continue forming pierogi while this batch is cooking.</item></list>
<head>Enjoy or Store!</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Fry up your boiled pierogi! If you want to eat them right away, you can heat up a little bit of vegetable oil in a pan and fry them until each side is slightly browned. See photo below (Jenny Can Cook, 2013). <figure rend="Abarto2.png"></figure></item>
<item>Store your pierogi for an easily thawed dinner! Place the boiled pierogi in a baking sheet or large pan. You will want to separate each layer of pierogi with a sheet of wax paper because the dough tends to stick together between pierogi. If you don’t have wax paper, place in freezer for the pierogi to slightly freeze so that they can be put in a Ziploc bag without sticking together.</item></list>
</text>
