<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc29" title="Have a Fit Body with TRX" shortTile="fit-body-trx" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2016-06-28" dateModified="2016-08-20" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Have_a_Fit_Body_with_TRX" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Have a Fit Body with TRX</head><p>Many people want to get fit with TRX but don't know how. TRX is a sport that can make you feel both strong and flexible at the same time, and it can be very helpful. The abbreviation "TRX" actually stands for "Total Body Resistance Exercise". If you are interested in learning TRX, then this article can help you. Here are some steps you can easily take to get fit just by using a TRX.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><figure rend="Maria Ly from skimble.com completing the TRX Suspension Training System 40_40 Challenge.jpg"></figure> Start simple and easy. Start with 30-45 seconds of work along with every 20 seconds of rest. Don't rush! You're not going to be a professional TRX trainer overnight; instead, try to do these simple exercises as well as possible.</item>
<item><figure rend="TRX_Tricep Pushup.jpg"></figure> Do TRX Push-Ups. This is a very good work for your abdominal muscles and elbows. Hook your toes through the TRX as the tops of your feet face the floor. Then, lift your body up and apply the rest your weight on the palms of your hands. Afterwards, bend your elbows to lower your chest between your hands. Your body should be at the same height with the floor in every part.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you're a beginner, you can also place your toes on the floor (so that the top of your feet face the floor) instead of hooking them through the TRX.</item>
<item>Perform this process in sets of 3. Each set should last around 35 seconds with 10-15 second rests in between.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="DSCF1764.jpg"></figure> Try squatting. Squatting is a general exercise that can even be done without the TRX. First, hold the handles in front of your waist, and bend your elbows by your sides. Hold the TRX in front of your body as the palms of your hands keep the TRX in front of each other. Then, gently bend your knees but don't move them forward. Squat like you're sitting on a chair by using the TRX!
<list type="unordered"><item>Do regular squats as they are necessary and can build a strong body.</item></list></item>
<item>Do the TRX Y and T Deltoid Fly. First, begin the right position stand by keeping TRX. Lift your hands as your elbows and head can make a position like the letter "Y". Then, go backward but don't move your feet; just gently move your whole body to the back. Meanwhile, close the letter "Y" made by your hands to the front. Do the same thing by making letter "T". and repeat this 30 times.</item>
<item>Do the TRX Power Pull. First, make your TRX single by putting one into another twice. Then hold onto a single TRX handle with one of your hands. After that, open your other hand as a T-shape, slightly rotating your torso and your extended hand to the same side and touch the floor. Your feet should be wider than hip-width apart. Then, drive your elbow (which is holding the TRX) back and touch the top of the TRX with the other hand while you're hand is still extended. After doing this 15 times, repeat the workout with the other hand.
<list type="unordered"><item>This is good workout that can add power to your upper back and arms.</item>
<item>It's important to look at the pivot point you're rotating your body to.</item></list></item>
<item>Exercise at least 3 times a week. To reach the results you want, exercise at least 3 sessions a week, with each session lasting 1 and a half hours. Don't make last-minute decisions — set a plan and write it down and promise yourself to follow it carefully. Remember, people with good plans can reach whatever they want!</item>
<item>Do a variety of workouts. Don't just follow the same workouts every single session. Try to make a difference in every session. For example, add a 10 minute dance practice to your sessions once a week. By doing this, you'll also encourage yourself to do the workouts better.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Have balance. Most people don't have balance. The TRX will increase strength and balance. The more balance you'll have, the more successful you'll be.</item>
<item>To make a workout easier, you can gently decrease your incline.</item>
<item>If a workout is too easy, then you can increase your incline.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always remember that before doing any physical activity, you should warm up sufficiently.</item>
<item>Make sure that your TRX is set up currently. Test the TRX and be sure that it can support all your full body weight or you may fall down and hurt yourself!</item>
<item>It's essential to know if the two yellow adjustment lines on your TRX are aligned. If you don't check them after every exercise, you may easily hurt your body and this won't sound good for a trainer.</item>
<item>Remember that TRX is not an easy sport. Recognizing that you have to do everything as well as possible is so important. If you're a beginner and you never had the exercising experience in your life, you may have some aches in your waist and legs for the first sessions. But don't be afraid; that just means that you've done the workouts well!</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>TRX</item>
<item>A place to hold the TRX</item>
<item>Sneakers</item>
<item>Stopwatch (for recording workout times and sets you have to do)</item></list>
</text>
