<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc117" title="Open XPS Files" shortTile="open-xps-files" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-09-05" dateModified="2018-12-10" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Open_XPS_Files" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Open XPS Files</head><p>This wikiHow teaches you how to open an XPS file on your Windows or Mac computer. XPS files are Windows' response to the more popular PDF file format. While Windows computers have a built-in program that allows them to open XPS files, Mac users will have to convert their XPS files into PDFs before being able to view them.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>On Windows</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Add XPS Viewer to your computer if necessary. XPS Viewer is installed on Windows 10 computers by default, but you'll need to reinstall it if you've cleared your computer's optional features in the past: <figure rend="Open XPS Files Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Open <hi rend="bold">Start</hi> , then click <hi rend="bold">Settings</hi> .</item>
<item>Click <hi rend="bold">Apps</hi>, then click the <hi rend="bold">Manage optional features</hi> link.</item>
<item>Click <hi rend="bold">Add a feature</hi> at the top of the page.</item>
<item>Find and click <hi rend="bold">XPS Viewer</hi>, then click <hi rend="bold">Install</hi>.</item>
<item>Restart your computer once XPS Viewer finishes installing.</item></list></item>
<item>Find the XPS document. Go to the location of the XPS document you want to open. <figure rend="Open XPS Files Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Double-click the XPS document. Doing so will prompt the XPS document to begin opening in your computer's XPS Viewer app. <figure rend="Open XPS Files Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wait for the document to open. This may take a few seconds depending on the document's size. Once the document finishes loading, you should see it in the XPS Viewer window. <figure rend="Open XPS Files Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Open XPS Viewer by itself. If you want to open the program you use to view XPS documents, do the following: <figure rend="Open XPS Files Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Open <hi rend="bold">Start</hi> .</item>
<item>Type in .</item>
<item>Click <hi rend="bold">XPS Viewer</hi> in the list of search results.</item></list></item>
<item>Click . It's in the XPS viewer window at the top. This will open a drop-down menu. <figure rend="Open XPS Files Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . It's the first option at the top of the drop-down menu. This will open a new file explorer window for you to choose the XPS file you want to open. <figure rend="Open XPS Files Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select your XPS file and click . Select the location of your XPS file on the left side of the file explorer window (such as *Documents* or *Downloads*) and then click on the XPS file to select. Then click the <hi rend="bold">Open</hi> button on the bottom-right corner of the file explorer window. This opens your XPS file in the XPS viewer. <figure rend="Open XPS Files Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>On Mac</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open the XPS to PDF website. Go to <ref target="https://xpstopdf.com/">https://xpstopdf.com/</ref> in your computer's web browser. While you can't open XPS files on a Mac without purchasing software, you can convert the XPS files into PDF files which can be opened with your Mac's default PDF viewer. <figure rend="Open XPS Files Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>XPS files are fundamentally no different from PDFs in terms of presentation.</item></list></item>
<item>Click . It's a teal button in the middle of the page. A Finder window will open. <figure rend="Open XPS Files Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select your XPS file. Go to the location of the XPS file you want to open, then click it once to select it. <figure rend="Open XPS Files Step 11 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . This blue button is in the bottom-right corner of the window. Doing so uploads the XPS file to the XPS to PDF website. <figure rend="Open XPS Files Step 12 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You may click <hi rend="bold">Open</hi> here instead.</item></list></item>
<item>Click . This yellow button will appear below your XPS document's name in the middle of the page once it finishes converting. Clicking it prompts your converted PDF to download. <figure rend="Open XPS Files Step 13 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You may be prompted to confirm the download or select a save location before the PDF will download.</item></list></item>
<item>Double-click the downloaded PDF. Doing so will open it in your Mac's default PDF viewer (usually the Preview application). <figure rend="Open XPS Files Step 14 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>There are paid programs, such as the Cisdem Document Reader, that can be used to open XPS files without converting them on a Mac.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You cannot use XPS Viewer on a pre-Vista Windows computer.</item></list>
</text>
