<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc189" title="Settle an Argument Between Children" shortTile="settle-argument-between" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-04-18" dateModified="2019-09-13" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Settle_an_Argument_Between_Children" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Settle an Argument Between Children</head><p>If you've ever worked with kids, then you know how difficult it can be to deal with a dispute that has led to tears or yelling, especially when each child is telling you something different happened. Knowing how to settle these disputes is a vital skill to have if you are a parent, teacher, babysitter, or camp counselor.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Calm down the children so you can help them. You might need to seperate them for a while or they'll just continue the fight. Once both of your children have calmed down bring them out to the table, sofa or other area and talk to them.  <figure rend="Reduce-Sibling-Rivalry-(for-Parents)-Step-5-Version-3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Reassure both children that you are listening, and will do your best to make things right.</item>
<item>If children are crying or angry, make sure you spend extra time on this step. Once children feel that they are being listened to, they will usually calm down.</item>
<item>If children are still crying, yelling, or talking over each other, tell them that you can't help them if they can't calm down enough for you to be able to understand them.</item></list></item>
<item>Listen. Ask each child to tell their side of the story and try to understand what happened, don't interrupt them or ask questions, you can do this once they are done.  <figure rend="Reduce-Sibling-Rivalry-(for-Parents)-Step-8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If one child tries to interrupt, tell them that they will get their turn and that you can only listen to one person at a time.</item>
<item>Be unbiased. Even if you feel it is one child at fault its important to remain unbiased, otherwise the other child will feel less respected and not listened to.</item>
<item>If it's a he-said-she-said dispute, and you can't tell who is lying, ask another child or adult who was watching what they saw.</item></list></item>
<item>Make a judgement. Decide who was at fault for starting the dispute, and what they did that was wrong. Don't put all the blame on one child, the other should still receive some blame for participating in the arguing or fighting, Usually both children are at fault in some way.   <figure rend="Reduce-Sibling-Rivalry-(for-Parents)-Step-6-Version-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tell the children what you think happened, and ask if they agree, give them a chance to correct any details you missed or got wrong.  <figure rend="Handle-a-Preteen's-Tantrums-Step-12.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If only one child is disagreeing, explain to them why you think they are wrong, and describe your evidence.</item>
<item>If both children and/or bystanders are disagreeing, go back to step 2.</item>
<item>If you are unsure, say so. Tell the children that you are trying your best, but need more information.</item></list></item>
<item>Dismiss the children or enact consequences. If you feel the behaviour has been solved and wasn't bad enough to deserve any consequences dismiss your children, it can be helpful to ask them to spend some time alone to reflect on things or if the talk was very emotional. If you think that the behaviour needs a consequence give each child the same punishment. It should be can be something that involves working together, such as doing extra chores together. Make sure to talk to your children about the consequence, if they ask why explain it was because of their behaviour.  <figure rend="Handle-a-Preteen's-Tantrums-Step-7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If both children are at fault, but one was trying to fight back, tell them to go immediately to you next time before the dispute escalates.</item>
<item>If the argument was caused because there was only one of something (for example one cookie left) take the item away.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always be willing to listen, and give the children your full attention.</item>
<item>Use reflective listening techniques to help the children feel that they are being listened to, by repeating back simplified version of what they are saying.</item>
<item>Make eye contact with children at all times while they are talking.</item>
<item>Be unbiased, and don't shy away from uncertainty.</item>
<item>If you are feeling completely overwhelmed, it might be a good idea to get a supervisor, parent, or other more experienced adult to help you.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Never tell children to "get over it" or that it "isn't a big deal", especially if they are very upset. Although this may be true, it invalidates the child's feelings and will make them more angry and more difficult to work with.</item>
<item>If you don't care, try not to show it. Kids can tell when they aren't being listened to, and will be more likely to try to take justice into their own hands next time if they perceive that there isn't someone who is listening and who will try their best to make sure things are fair.</item></list>
</text>
