<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc241" title="Order at Philz" shortTile="order-philz" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2013-05-15" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Order_at_Philz" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Order at Philz</head><p>Philz is a coffee shop native to Northern California, and their dedication to quality coffee has gotten them a devoted and rabid fan base. Founded by Phil Jaber, Philz prides itself on hand crafting every cup to every customer's specifications. They have some very unique custom blends that often overwhelm first-time visitors and regulars alike, so if you've ever been tempted by Philz but discouraged by the menu or the ordering process, this article will tell you how it's done.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Order In Person</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find a Philz near you. Unfortunately for you non-Californians out there, Philz only has locations in San Francisco and East Bay areas. <figure rend="Order at Philz Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Locate the order line. At Philz, you order first and pay second, which is opposite most traditional coffee shops. There will usually be a big sign directing you to the proper place. <figure rend="Order at Philz Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wait to be called up. Your coffee is made-to-order by the baristas, and they can only handle 4 cups at a time. Wait in line until you hear someone say they can take the next person. <figure rend="Order at Philz Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Choose your drink. If you're new to Philz, ask the barista for a recommendation. They'll figure out what kinds of flavors you prefer and find you the perfect blend. If you're feeling a bit more adventurous, you can also experiment with their extensive menu: <figure rend="Order at Philz Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Dark roasts
<list type="unordered"><item>Jacob's Wonderbar Brew: Nutty and chocolatey, without bitterness</item>
<item>Tantalizing Turkish: Rich and dark, with a touch of cardamom</item>
<item>Ether: Dark and oily, with a hint of charcoal</item>
<item>Julie's Ultimate: Classy and floral</item>
<item>Aromatic Arabic: A full-bodied Arabian coffee</item>
<item>Code 33: Strong, rich, and oily</item></list></item>
<item>Medium roasts
<list type="unordered"><item>Tesora: The classic Philz blend, and strongly recommended for beginners</item>
<item>Philharmonic: Warm, with a hint of cardamom</item>
<item>Ambrosia Coffee of God: Warm and sweet, with nutty undertones</item>
<item>Anesthesia to the Upside: Oaky and sharp, with a caramel finish</item>
<item>Silken Splendor: Warm nutty tones</item>
<item>Filtered Soul: Sweet and chocolatey, with traces of hazelnut</item>
<item>It's the Best: Soft and smooth</item>
<item>Dancing Water: Smooth and delicate</item>
<item>Half-Caff: Half Tesora, half decaf Sumatra</item></list></item>
<item>Light roasts
<list type="unordered"><item>Sooo Good: Smoky and sweet</item>
<item>Greater Alarm: Strong, sweet, and highly caffeinated</item>
<item>Canopy of Heaven: Complex flavors</item>
<item>New Manhattan: Earthy and distinctive</item></list></item>
<item>Decaf
<list type="unordered"><item>Decaf Dark French: Bittersweet and full-bodied</item>
<item>Decaf Ethiopian: Rich and silky smooth</item>
<item>Decaf Sumatra: Sweet and earthy</item>
<item>Decaf Organic Swiss Water Peru: Sweet, silky, and decaffeinated using the Swiss water method</item></list></item>
<item>Specialty drinks
<list type="unordered"><item>Ecstatic Iced Coffee</item>
<item>Mint Mojito Iced Coffee</item>
<item>Gingersnap Iced Coffee</item>
<item>Mocha Tesora: A chocolate lover's dream</item>
<item>Jamaican Blue Mountain: Full-bodied and smooth</item>
<item>Hot chocolate</item></list></item>
<item>Teas
<list type="unordered"><item>Black Tea: Strong, but not too acidic</item>
<item>Green Tea: Floral and nutty notes</item>
<item>Chamomile Tea</item>
<item>Yerba Mate Tea: Smoky</item>
<item>Istanbul Treat</item>
<item>Mint Tea</item>
<item>Herbal Mint Tea</item>
<item>Chai</item></list></item></list></item>
<item>Pick a size. You have two options: small or large. <figure rend="Order at Philz Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Decide whether you'd like your drink hot or iced. <figure rend="Order at Philz Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pick a sweetener. Your options are sugar, Splenda, Equal, Sweet'n Low, stevia, or honey. <figure rend="Order at Philz Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Tell the barista how sweet you want your drink: not sweet, light, medium, or extra.</item></list></item>
<item>Pick your cream or milk. Your options are cream, whole milk, 2% milk, 1% milk, low-fat milk, almond milk, non-fat milk, soy milk, or vanilla soy milk. <figure rend="Order at Philz Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Tell the barista how creamy you'd like your drink: light, medium, or extra.</item></list></item>
<item>Pay for your coffee. Let the person at the register know what blend you ordered and what size. Most blends range from $3 to $4 a cup. <figure rend="Order at Philz Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wait for your order to be called. It's important to remember which barista you ordered from and what you got because they'll call out your order and not your name. <figure rend="Order at Philz Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Give it a taste. Most baristas will ask you to taste your drink while you're at their station—just so they can make sure they got everything perfect. <figure rend="Order at Philz Step 11 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't hesitate to ask your barista if your drink isn't quite to your liking. They can tweak your drink until it's just right.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Use OrderAhead</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open the OrderAhead app or navigate to their <ref target="https://www.orderaheadapp.com/learn-more">website</ref>. <figure rend="Order at Philz Step 12 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you're new to OrderAhead, you will need to first create an account and enter  your credit card information.</item></list></item>
<item>Choose your location to find a Philz near you, or just search for "Philz." <figure rend="Order at Philz Step 13 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on your desired beverage. <figure rend="Order at Philz Step 14 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Choose your size. You have two options: small or large. <figure rend="Order at Philz Step 15 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Decide whether you'd like your drink hot or iced. <figure rend="Order at Philz Step 16 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Choose your sweetener. You can choose between sugar, Splenda, Equal, Sweet'n Low, stevia, or honey. <figure rend="Order at Philz Step 17 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pick how sweet you would like your beverage. Your options are not sweet, not too sweet, medium sweet, or sweet. <figure rend="Order at Philz Step 18 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pick your cream or milk. Your options are cream, whole milk, 2% milk, 1% milk, low-fat milk, almond milk, non-fat milk, soy milk, or vanilla soy milk. <figure rend="Order at Philz Step 19 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Decide how creamy you'd like your drink. Your options are light, normal, extra. <figure rend="Order at Philz Step 20 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Add any special instructions. <figure rend="Order at Philz Step 21 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Place your order. OrderAhead will tell you when your beverage will be ready. <figure rend="Order at Philz Step 22 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pick up your order. The pick-up locations are different at every Philz store, but either look for the OrderAhead table or give your name to the person at the register and say you placed an order. <figure rend="Order at Philz Step 23 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Philz Drink List</head>
<p><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Doc:Philz_Drinks_List">Doc:Philz Drinks List</ref></p>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Consider taking a buddy—preferably a Philz veteran—especially if you're heading to Philz for the first time.</item>
<item>If you're brand new to Philz, most baristas will suggest you try a Tesora "medium medium" (medium cream, medium sugar).</item>
<item>Desperate for Philz but not in the San Francisco area? Virgin America offers Philz coffee on their flights.</item>
<item>If you want to sound like a real regular, try ordering your coffee "Philz way," which is medium sugar, medium cream.</item></list>
</text>
