<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc263" title="Take an Internal Bath" shortTile="take-internal-bath" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-04-13" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Take_an_Internal_Bath" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Take an Internal Bath</head><p>An internal bath cleanses the colon and rids the body of toxins. By learning how to take an internal bath, you can reap the health benefits of this alternative healing modality and help keep your body's toxicity levels at a minimum. Also known as colon cleansing or detoxification, internal baths additionally help the body expel undigested food and waste products that sit in the colon.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Determine what type of internal bath cleanse best suits your needs. You can choose from a standard detoxification cleanse, which utilizes baking soda and sea salt, or an herbal one, which typically entails the usage of such ingredients as coffee. Coffee is known for its laxative properties, and when used in an internal bath, offers an ideal alternative to the baking soda/sea salt option. <figure rend="Take an Internal Bath Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Gather the necessary materials. You will need an enema kit to conduct your cleanse. This is an essential component of learning how to take an internal bath. Enema bags, hoses, and nozzles are available in a variety of price ranges and quality levels. Find one that best matches the goals of your cleanse. For instance, if you plan on taking an internal bath regularly, you may want to invest in a higher quality enema kit than if you were planning on conducting the cleanse once or twice or to treat an intermittent health problem. <figure rend="Take an Internal Bath Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Mix the ingredients of your cleanse. The recipe for a standard cleanse is 1 tsp. baking soda, 1 tsp. sea salt, and 4 cups (32 oz.) water. Make sure the water is warm as this will create the most comfortable internal bath. If you're opting for a more alternative option, follow your recipe carefully and, again, be sure the water is lukewarm and comfortable in temperature. <figure rend="Take an Internal Bath Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Fill the enema bag with the cleansing concoction and insert into your colon. This can best be achieved by bending over and sliding the nozzle of the enema bag into your rectum. Gently apply pressure to the bag so the cleansing mixture flows slowly and smoothly into your body. When the bag is empty or you feel full, remove it and set it aside. <figure rend="Take an Internal Bath Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Massage your belly and move gently back and forth from the bent-over position. This will help the cleansing ingredients properly disperse around the colon and bathe the entire area. Stay in the bent-over position for a few minutes or until the need to expel the mixture is strong. After you release the contents, you can repeat this process as necessary. <figure rend="Take an Internal Bath Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>The use of lubricating jelly will help make the process more comfortable. When inserting the enema nozzle into the rectum, apply lubricant to both the nozzle and to your rectal area. This will help the nozzle slip into the body with ease. An important step in learning how to take an internal bath is understanding that this is not meant to be a painful procedure, but rather a therapeutic way to cleanse the internal organs.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Though you can repeat the internal bath process as necessary for your body, most experts recommend stopping after 5 or 6 continuous cleanses. This gives your organs and muscles a chance to relax and harness the benefits of the internal bath. Don't overdue it, especially on your first attempt, as the body may need to adjust to the entire process.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Enema kit</item>
<item>Baking soda</item>
<item>Sea salt</item>
<item>Water</item></list>
</text>
