<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc131" title="Tell if Your Academic Advisor Is Repressing Sexual Feelings Toward You" shortTile="tell-academic-advisor" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-11-13" dateModified="2015-07-02" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Tell_if_Your_Academic_Advisor_Is_Repressing_Sexual_Feelings_Toward_You" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Tell if Your Academic Advisor Is Repressing Sexual Feelings Toward You</head><p>In life, we have many different types of relationships. Some are romantic and some are just friends. But what do you do when someone who you THINK you are in a just friends relationship with shows signs of wanting something more? This can get more complicated when that person is your teacher or academic advisor at high school or University. In order to deal with this, though, first you have to figure out if your academic advisor really is repressing sexual feelings toward you.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Think about the way your academic advisor interacts with you. Does he pay special attention to you in class or in his or her office? Does he or she offer to do special projects with you, or encourage you to study the material he or she knows best? These could be signs that your advisor is taking a special interest in you, more than other students, and that interest could be sexual.</item>
<item>Look into your advisor's personal history. Has he or she ever had an inappropriate or romantic relationship with another student in the past? If so, who is to say he would not want to do the same thing again!</item>
<item>What is your advisor's personal life like outside of school? Is his family life happy or unhappy? Does he have a lot of hobbies or is he more of a loner? If he is an unhappy loner, these are more risk factors that show that he could have inappropriate sexual feelings toward you as a student.</item>
<item>What type of person is your academic advisor? Is he well regarded in the school community, or are people intimidated by him? If your advisor has a friendly, happy demeanor, this shows that he has a good attitude and would not likely engage in inappropriate behavior. But, if he is more of a surly person, and does not show a lot of emotions, this could mean that he is repressing his real feelings for you.</item>
<item>Look into his eyes. If your advisor really loves you, you will be able to tell when he looks at you.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you think your advisor is repressing his feelings for you, DO NOT spend a lot of time around him, because this could give him the impression that you also want to have a sexual relationship.</item>
<item>If you really do like your advisor as more than a friend, though, there are a few ways you can try to let him or her know. For example, you can put in extra work for your advisors class, and do things such as doing extra credit or writing extra-long essays. This will help your advisor know that you like him too.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Look out for invisible signs! Things such as vibes or feelings might not be obvious, but help you know if your academic advisor is repressing sexual feelings for you.</item></list>
</text>
