<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc167" title="Be a Pleasure to Have at Home" shortTile="pleasure-home" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2009-09-09" dateModified="2019-05-18" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_a_Pleasure_to_Have_at_Home" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be a Pleasure to Have at Home</head><p>Being a pleasure at home can make life a lot smoother between you and your family, and also have the positive side effect of getting more freedom.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Ask what you can do to help out day to day, and do it. There's nothing more annoying than someone asking to do something and it not get done, as it would be less annoying to just do it yourself. <figure rend="Be a Pleasure to Have at Home Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you have younger siblings, play with them, help them with homework, take them to the park or read with them. This will get them off your parents back. Your parents will appreciate it and you will build up a strong relationship with all of them. <figure rend="Be a Pleasure to Have at Home Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you have pets, do things for them that otherwise your parents would have to do, like walking the dog, cleaning out the pets' area, etc. <figure rend="Be a Pleasure to Have at Home Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have really good manners because it helps a lot. Just saying "sorry" for turning a light off accidentally when someone is in the room and switching it back on for them can immediately diffuse a confrontation. <figure rend="Be a Pleasure to Have at Home Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Spend time with your parents on your own. This makes your relationship better, and there are many different ways of achieving this. If you are the oldest, stay up later and chat with them. If you aren't the last to go to bed, do the weekly shop with them, suggest you both go for a walk together or suggest something like a kick around, but DON'T insist on anything they don't want to do.  <figure rend="Be a Pleasure to Have at Home Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Ask for things nicely, for example "would it be OK with you..." or "I've wanted X for a while now, please would you buy it for me if I did some extra stuff around the house". If you followed steps 1, 2 and 3, they might agree right away. Win!!! <figure rend="Be a Pleasure to Have at Home Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be tidy <figure rend="Be a Pleasure to Have at Home Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't insist everything is to be done your way <figure rend="Be a Pleasure to Have at Home Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you're on the computer, or watching TV and somebody wants you to change the channel, or go on the computer themselves, ask politely for 5 minutes longer on the computer if you're just chatting, 30 minutes for homework (If it is a big homework, ask what they want to do, if its just checking email or something, ask can you go back on in 10 minutes) If its TV, change to what they want to watch, or be reasonable, so say you've wanted to watch this for a while. You could also see if their or your program is repeated in the next hour (on E4+1 etc) <figure rend="Be a Pleasure to Have at Home Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Look for wikiHows on how to be polite, how to walk a dog, how to entertain young children etc</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't whine about how much you've done already if you ask for something.</item>
<item>It's OK to say that you've done something, but it shows a hidden agenda if you do something voluntarily and ask for payment later</item>
<item>Ask to do things for your pet. If you never normally walk your dog, if the dog goes missing, people will get worried</item></list>
</text>
