<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc181" title="Hide Things from Siblings and Parents" shortTile="hide-things-siblings" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2016-10-07" dateModified="2016-10-07" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Hide_Things_from_Siblings_and_Parents" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Hide Things from Siblings and Parents</head><p>Do your siblings and/or parents keep finding your hidden things? Do you want this to stop? If you answered yes to both questions, you're reading the correct article. Read on for some cool hiding spots..</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>How to hide small things</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Hiding small things can be easy and hard. To hide small things properly you might want to read my ideas...
<list type="unordered"><item>Try hiding small things in someone else's bedroom</item>
<item>Hide small things in at least 3 different places. Why? Because if someone finds ONE of your hiding places, the other ones will be safe and untouched!</item>
<item>If you can't find a good hiding place for your small things, go into someone else's bedroom and pretend that you're looking for small objects. Look in the strangest and unobvious places. That's where you can hide your small things (In your bedroom or someone else's).</item>
<item>As a last resort, you can hide small things in boxes under your bed. In front of those boxes, put piles of old, unwanted clothes or toys to hide the boxes.</item>
<item>And lastly, build a LEGO construction to hold your small things. But be careful, for someone might decide to take it apart and, Bingo!, find your small things!</item></list></item></list>
<head>How to hide big things</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Hiding big things can be tricky, so follow my advice carefully. Here are some ideas to help you out...
<list type="unordered"><item>Get a mini fridge, locker, or something similar. You could put your big things in there.</item>
<item>If your big things are very big, try hiding them outside in some big, thick bushes.</item>
<item>If you have a hidden room, basement, or attic, hide your big things there.</item>
<item>As a last resort, hand your big things over to a trusted friend and let him/her look after them.</item>
<item>And lastly, find a big cardboard box and put your big things in there. Don't forget to tape the box shut a lot of times with sticky tape before you leave it. It will be much harder for someone to excavate your big things with lots of sticky tape as a protective barrier!</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Hide your big or small things when everyone is asleep or away to minimise the chances of you getting caught while hiding your things!</item>
<item>If you decide to hide your big things in a cardboard box, be prepared to buy extra sticky tape to make up for using a lot of it on taping your box shut.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>No matter how well you hide things, big or small, you always have a chance of getting caught using or hiding them.</item>
<item>NEVER attempt to hide cigarettes, tobacco, alcohol, drugs, medicine, or ANY weapons. You could be sent to jail. And you may be risking your life.</item></list>
</text>
