<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc170" title="Avoid Network Marketing Relatives" shortTile="avoid-network-marketing" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-09-18" dateModified="2017-07-24" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Avoid_Network_Marketing_Relatives" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Avoid Network Marketing Relatives</head><p>"Network Marketing" working outside the rat race, this is what exactly what  they think but it is just the same as our work. Our relatives working with so called 'money making companies' believes that they are doing great and are sometimes even told that they are. We just want to ignore them just because we don't need or want their products. Sometimes we are not impressed by them and mainly our reasons are the investments before starting. Whatever your reason is here are some steps by which you can simply avoid them without showing them. This is meant for those people who really like their relatives but started feeling differently after they joined this business.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Never Show Them You Are Avoiding Them</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Whenever one network marketer feels that they are avoided by the guest or the person they have shown their project they use their special gadgets called "UPLINES". When they see that the guest is ignoring them they will just call you for another coffee some other day. That same day they will call you and tell you the day for the next meeting. And on the next meeting there will be a person with him or her. "Meet my senior, he will tell you something about our project". He knows that you can ignore him but not the third person with him, and the senior will be so impressive that you just can't resist talking to him. You will definitely like the way he will convince you, and if you ignore him a third, fourth, or seventh meeting will be called.</item></list>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Always show them that you are taking interest in their work and products. When they see a guest who takes them seriously and show interest in the project, they take them for granted. They think that you are already interested in the work and will definitely buy the products. And that is the best thing for you, you just don't want them to convince you.Your interest is the best tool to ignore them. You will be on their favorite list and they will not disturb you much.</item>
<item>Simply listen to your relative then tell them you don't have money. All network marketers try to convince you but now you have to convince them that you really don't have money. if they are convinced they will never come back to you again.</item>
<item>Just tell them that you will do it one day, which day, you really don't know. Give them your words. "See brother, I really don't have money today, but I'll definitely join you." These word will hit their heart and will help you a lot,  but don't forget to ask them occasionally about their business. and whenever he ask you about it just say it again "I'll do it one day".</item>
<item>These people are in search of true dreamers. They will ask you about your dreams, tell them you don't have any. They will say "Don't you want to live a life of luxury", tell them no. Never go against them just say no to riches and luxuries in front of them. They will never come back to you.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always remember they are one step ahead from you. What you are thinking to do is already done by many. They have a solution for nearly every person on the earth.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">Never</hi> talk against them.</item></list>
</text>
