<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc289" title="Have a Healthy Year" shortTile="healthy-year" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-07-15" dateModified="2017-12-09" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Have_a_Healthy_Year" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Have a Healthy Year</head><p>The new year gives us an opportunity to reflect on our life and what we have learned during the previous year. With the recession of 2009 still upon us, perhaps you’ve become more attuned to what is most important to you. We hope this list offers you an opportunity for greater reflection on how to make the most of the upcoming year.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Remember that your net worth is not the same as your self-worth. In a time when layoffs are common and job opportunities limited, this is an important bit to keep in mind. Think about it: What do your loved ones value about you? Chances are it’s not your income. <figure rend="Have a Healthy Year Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make yourself your highest priority. When you put your own well-being first, you have more time, attention, and love to give to others. Sacrificing your own needs for others leaves little energy for you or for those you’re tending to. The more you offer to yourself, the more you have to offer to others. <figure rend="Have a Healthy Year Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don’t forget to schedule time for fun. Too often we are run by our to-do list of things we believe must get completed, or else…what? Trust us, the laundry will wait for you! Creating time for laughter and fun is vital for decreasing feelings of deprivation and resentment. Who knows—maybe someone else will throw in a load or two for you! <figure rend="Have a Healthy Year Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take time each day to give yourself a pat on the back. How many times do you end the day reviewing what you didn’t get to or what you should have done differently? Positive reinforcement is a much better motivator—so go ahead, congratulate yourself for what you did right today! Everyone wants to be recognized for a job well done, and we have a right and need to do so for ourselves. <figure rend="Have a Healthy Year Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Live in the present moment. This is not as easy as it sounds. When we are regretting the past or worrying about the future, we lose the only moment that we actually have—which is the one right now. Need help? Sign up for a local meditation course or visit your local yoga studio to discover opportunities to learn about how to live in the moment. <figure rend="Have a Healthy Year Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Cultivate a connection to something larger than yourself. It may be God, nature, poetry, art, or a charity that has meaning to you. These connections often give us an opportunity to feel connected to the world around us, strengthening the connection we have with ourselves. <figure rend="Have a Healthy Year Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remember that you already have everything you need. Viewing our lives from an abundant perspective allows us to recognize our own capabilities rather than falling under an illusion that someone or something else will make our lives better. <figure rend="Have a Healthy Year Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Experience the world with awe and curiosity. Did you ever see a baby find his foot for the first time? He’s amazed! Try looking at the ordinary through a baby’s perspective—as if you were experiencing it for the very first time. This will work with anything that you experience using your senses—taste, touch, vision, hearing. <figure rend="Have a Healthy Year Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Welcome your mistakes. Mistakes give us the opportunity to learn and grow. Expecting to go through life without a bump or two in the road is a set-up for chronic frustration and disappointment. <figure rend="Have a Healthy Year Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Practice, practice, practice. All of the tips mentioned require an ongoing practice, particularly if you’re prone to seeing what’s wrong instead of what’s right in your life. However, there’s nothing magical about acquiring these skills other than an ongoing commitment to keep practicing. GOOD LUCK! <figure rend="Have a Healthy Year Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
</text>
