<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc180" title="Remember You Are Still Your Parents' Grown Child" shortTile="remember-still-parents" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-06-10" dateModified="2016-11-14" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Remember_You_Are_Still_Your_Parents%27_Grown_Child" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Remember You Are Still Your Parents' Grown Child</head>You might often forget that parents will always look at you as their children whether you are 10 years old or 100 years old. Many of you might think, "Why are they talking to me like I am a kid again?" Well, in their eyes you are always their little Johnny or Jane. Read on to remember that you're still your parent's child even grown.
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Show thanks to your parents because they are your parents-they raised you. For example, when you go to the store bringing them their favorite candy bar back lets them know you were thinking about them. You might say, "Here is a little treat I brought for you from the store." Watch their expression, they just want to know you have not forgotten about them.</item>
<item>A daily phone call to check on or just to talk with them is a nice call to get. Especially in the morning. They look forward to that call and now you have set an expectation so when they don't get the call, they know something has come up and now they will check on you. But in their minds, they know to expect that call on a daily basis.</item>
<item>They worry about you forever. You don't need to think that once you are grown, they don't worry. Most of your parents want to know that you are happy and that you care about them. Holding your tongue is another way to keep the peace. You can't always say what you are feeling when it comes to parents--especially older. So, choose your words carefully and wisely. Just try saying, "Okay mom (or dad), I disagree but you are the parent." Walk away and find something more positive to reflect on.</item>
<item>Always think about the sacrifices they made for you as children. Although you might have been more fortunate than some others around us. Say it and do the right thing now. Have no regrets later.</item>
<item>Show kindness to those elderly people. Be patient and willing to help when it's needed. Take turns as siblings when things get tough. Call on relatives and close friends when you need a break. Order out when you are tired of cooking. They love a different flavor of a meal every now and then. Make them a priority and they will live long. We must keep their minds stimulated. Keep the grandchildren in the loop and let them know what your expectations are when it comes to the grandparents. Don't just have them come around when they want money or a gift. We set the standard for them to follow.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Just show appreciation and forgiveness. Let the small stuff go and keep it all positive no matter how negative they are sometimes. You will feel better in your conscience when it's all said and done. Make sure you check on them daily no matter how busy you are.</item></list>
</text>
