<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc17" title="Use Wrist Wraps" shortTile="use-wrist-wraps" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2017-11-02" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Use_Wrist_Wraps" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Use Wrist Wraps</head><p>Wrist wraps are used to support your wrist joints during weight lifting. Bodybuilders typically use wrist wraps when performing pressing or pushing exercises. Exercises like the bench press force the wrists to bear a lot of weight, and wrist wraps will support the wrists and reduce strain. To use wrist wraps correctly, you’ll need to put them on snugly so they fully support your wrists. Then, perform pushing or lifting exercises that require a straight wrist. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Putting on Wrist Wraps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find the thumb loop. The wrist wraps will look like pieces of sturdy fabric, each of which is about  long. One of the ends will have a thumb loop: a looped piece of string sticking upwards from the wrist wrap. Find this end, and hold the wrist wrap with the thumb loop pointing upwards. <figure rend="Use Wrist Wraps Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can start with either hand, since the process of putting on a wrist wrap will be the same for both hands.</item>
<item>The two wrist wraps that come in a package are interchangeable, so either wrist wrap could go on either wrist.</item></list></item>
<item>Line the thumb loop up with the inside of your wrist. Hold the wrist wrap alongside your wrist so that the thumb loop aligns with your thumb. The fabric portion of the wrist wrap (below the thumb loop) should align with the lower portion of your hand, just below your thumb. <figure rend="Use Wrist Wraps Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Put your thumb through the thumb loop. This will hold the wrist wrap in place on your hand.  <figure rend="Use Wrist Wraps Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wrap the wrist wrap around your arm. Before you begin, check both sides of the wrist wrap fabric and find the side that doesn’t have Velcro.  The Velcro will need to end up on the outside of your wrist once you’re done wrapping, so wrap your wrist with the Velcro-free side facing in. <figure rend="Use Wrist Wraps Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Typically, the side with Velcro will also have a large brand logo.</item>
<item>Be sure to keep the edges of the wrist wrap aligned while you’re wrapping. The wrist wrap should not spiral down your arm.</item></list></item>
<item>Wrap until the wrist wrap is comfortably tight, then secure it with the Velcro. The tightness of the wrist wrap is partially a matter of preference. It should be tight enough to put pressure on your wrist and keep the joint stable, but not so tight that it causes discomfort. <figure rend="Use Wrist Wraps Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Tighten the wrist wrap for heavier lifts, since your wrist will need more stability and support.</item></list></item>
<item>Repeat the process with the other wrist wrap. You’ll use the same sequence of steps to put a wrist wrap on your other hand. Try to put the wrist wraps on so that they’re tightened to the same degree on both hands. <figure rend="Use Wrist Wraps Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Lifting with Wrist Wraps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Perform pushing or pressing exercises. Wrist wraps will provide little or no benefit when you perform exercises that involve pulling a weight towards yourself, or exercises that do not require a straight wrist (such as lateral pull-downs and curls, respectively). To benefit from your wrist wraps, try exercises like: <figure rend="Use Wrist Wraps Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Bench_Press">Bench press</ref>.</item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Do_Renegade_Rows">Dumbbell rows</ref>.</item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Do_a_Deadlift">Deadlifts</ref>.</item>
<item>Rack pulls.</item></list></item>
<item>Put wrist wraps on when your wrists begin to fatigue. Experienced weightlifters do not put on wrist wraps as soon as they begin a workout. Start your workout without wrist wraps, and let your muscles (including wrists) fatigue naturally. If your wrists tire before your arm, back, and shoulder muscles, put your wrist wraps on then. <figure rend="Use Wrist Wraps Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This will allow the flexor and extensor muscles in your wrists to develop. If you keep your wrists wrapped constantly, the muscles will weaken.</item></list></item>
<item>Select Velcro-bound wraps for better wrist support. There are two main varieties of wrist wrap: thin, cotton wraps, and thicker Velcro-bound wraps. The Velcro-bound style wraps are thicker and will provide more support for your wrists, making them a better choice overall. <figure rend="Use Wrist Wraps Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Use these if you’re planning to focus on lifts like the bench press, dumbbell rows, or the deadlift.</item></list></item>
<item>Choose cotton wraps for increased flexibility. Thin cotton wrist wraps are useful if you’re performing exercises that require more wrist flexibility. This includes the snatch or the clean and jerk powerlifting moves. <figure rend="Use Wrist Wraps Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The snatch is one of the primary moves of Olympic lifting. Weightlifters pick up the barbell from the floor while in a crouched position, lift the barbell over their head in a single, fluid movement, and then stand up.</item>
<item>Similarly, the clean and jerk requires weightlifters to lift the barbell up to their shoulders, pause, and then heft the barbell up over their head.</item></list></item>
<item>Avoid using “hook straps” when lifting. Certain companies also produce a type of wrist wraps called hook straps, which sport a built-in hook to loop around the bar when performing a bench press or squats. You’re better off avoiding this type of wrist wrap, though, since they can impede your grip. <figure rend="Use Wrist Wraps Step 11.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Only Velcro-bound wraps tend to have hooks on them. Cotton straps aren’t sturdy enough to support a hook.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't rely on wrist wraps to lift heavier weights unless you're an experienced weightlifter. Instead, gradually increase how much weight you're lifting until your wrists are able to adapt.</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
