<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc89" title="Type in Korean on a Computer" shortTile="type-korean-computer" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-05-10" dateModified="2019-06-05" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Type_in_Korean_on_a_Computer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Type in Korean on a Computer</head><p>This wikiHow teaches you how to install the Korean/Hangul language input on your Windows, macOS or Linux computer.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Windows</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open the Windows search bar. You can usually do this by clicking the circle or magnifying glass at the bottom-left corner of the screen. <figure rend="Type in Korean on PC or Mac Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Type . A list of matching search results will appear. <figure rend="Type in Korean on PC or Mac Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . <figure rend="Type in Korean on PC or Mac Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . It’s under the “Languages” header in the right panel. A list of languages will appear. <figure rend="Type in Korean on PC or Mac Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the Korean language. This returns you to the previous screen. Korean now appears in the language list. <figure rend="Type in Korean on PC or Mac Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the Korean language and select . <figure rend="Type in Korean on PC or Mac Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . This installs the language pack. You’ll be prompted to restart your computer once its installed. <figure rend="Type in Korean on PC or Mac Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . The computer will shut down and restart. Continue to the next step once you’ve returned to the desktop. <figure rend="Type in Korean on PC or Mac Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Press and hold the Windows  key and the spacebar. A list of installed languages will appear. <figure rend="Type in Korean on PC or Mac Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select the Korean language. To do this, continue holding the Windows key and press the spacebar until the language is selected. <figure rend="Type in Korean on PC or Mac Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the . It’s at the bottom-right corner of the screen. This switches the keyboard to Hangul (한글). <figure rend="Type in Korean on PC or Mac Step 11.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>macOS</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Click the  menu. It’s at the top-left corner of the screen. <figure rend="Type in Korean on PC or Mac Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . <figure rend="Type in Korean on PC or Mac Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . It’s the blue flag with a white map inside. <figure rend="Type in Korean on PC or Mac Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the  tab. It’s at the top of the window. A list of language inputs will appear. <figure rend="Type in Korean on PC or Mac Step 15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Scroll down and check the box next to “Hangul.” You’ll see several options beneath it. <figure rend="Type in Korean on PC or Mac Step 16.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Check the box next to “2-Set Korean.” You won’t need to select the other options to type in Korean. <figure rend="Type in Korean on PC or Mac Step 17.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Switch to the Korean keyboard/input. When you’re ready to start typing, click your country’s flag icon at the top-right corner of the screen, then select <hi rend="bold">2-Set Korean</hi>. <figure rend="Type in Korean on PC or Mac Step 18.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Linux</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open the <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Work_in_Linux_at_the_Command_Line">command Line</ref>. It is needed to install the ibus-hangul package. On most Linux platforms, the icon of the command line is a black screen icon, labeled Terminal. <figure rend="OpenCmdLine.png"></figure></item>
<item>Install the ibus-hangul package. This is done from the package manager, which is apt on Debian and Ubuntu, and yum on some other platforms. On Ubuntu or Debian, type . This will install the package and the necessary dependencies. Type  (for "Yes") when it asks you whether you want to proceed. <figure rend="Install ibus corrected.png"></figure></item>
<item>Run im-config. Type  into the command line. On the window that opens, always click  and click  when it asks you "Do you explicitly select the user configuration?". This will configure the computer to actually notice that you have a new input method. <figure rend="Im config configuration.png"></figure></item>
<item>Restart the computer. For whatever reason, it won't notice the change if you don't.</item>
<item>Open the (system) settings (usually has a picture of a gear or wrench or some other tools) and go to the section where you can select input sources. Depending on the platform, it is called something like ,  or just . <figure rend="Open settings inpsourc.png"></figure></item>
<item>Add the Hangul input source. To do this, click on the  symbol or  under the list of input sources. A new window which shows all possible input sources will appear. Search for "Korean". Select the  option, which was not there before you installed the ibus-hangul package, and add it. <figure rend="Add hangul settings linux.png"></figure></item>
<item>Remember to activate "Hangul mode". When you switch to the Korean keyboard and type something, you will first see Latin letters. To actually type in Hangul, click on the input source selection menu (which you used to switch to the Korean keyboard) and click on . Now, you can type in Hangul. <figure rend="Enable hangul mode linux.png"></figure></item></list>
</text>
