<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc149" title="Help a Troubled Friend or Family Member" shortTile="help-troubled-friend" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-04-29" dateModified="2018-10-12" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Help_a_Troubled_Friend_or_Family_Member" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Help a Troubled Friend or Family Member</head><p>This article will offer basic strategies for helping a family member or friend who is distressed.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Listen and be supportive.  Active listening means giving your full attention to the other person.  You may be able to help your friend/family member clarify their thinking and to see their situation or problem in a new light. <figure rend="Help a Troubled Friend or Family Member Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="ordered"><item>Encourage your friend to talk; show interest with your body language and don’t interrupt.</item>
<item>Clarify what your friend is saying; restate the basic message and request confirmation that you’ve heard them correctly.  Use open-ended questions (can’t be answered with yes or no).</item>
<item>Reflect your friend’s feelings.  Mirror back what you hear and understand, noting the underlying emotions even if these feelings are not stated directly.</item>
<item>Keep your own feelings, advice, and judgment in check.</item>
<item>Validate your friend’s work on the problem; be compassionate and respectful.</item></list></item>
<item>Brainstorm and problem-solve potential solutions.  Sometimes the person in trouble may just need to bounce ideas off a supportive other.  By talking through possible solutions, you can help your friend/family member recognize and address the problem. <figure rend="Help a Troubled Friend or Family Member Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="ordered"><item>Begin by brainstorming possible solutions; come up with as many ideas as possible.  Be careful to do this without judgment or critique.</item>
<item>Analyze the idea list.  Look at the pros and cons, what would be realistic, what would work.</item>
<item>Offer to role play a solution to help the person see how it might work.</item>
<item>Help the person decide a course of action and offer support to carry out this plan.</item></list></item>
<item>Direct the person to other resources.  You may not feel qualified to help your friend/family member with all problems.  When this is the case, be honest with the person and offer to help them to connect with other resources. <figure rend="Help a Troubled Friend or Family Member Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="ordered"><item>Don’t ignore the problem just because you don’t feel qualified to handle it; share your concern with the person.</item>
<item>Use I-statements to express your own feelings to your friend.</item>
<item>Give specific examples of the behaviors which you are concerned about.</item>
<item>Try using the language formula I feel _____ [worried, scared, etc.] when you _____ [specific behavior which you have observed].</item>
<item>Ask the person if s/he has considered seeking professional help.  Say something like "I can see that you are distressed; have you thought about talking to a counselor?"</item>
<item>See the web site link below for resources on finding a counselor.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Talk to a counselor about your friend or family member. Tell them about your friend doing drugs, getting drunk (under 21), doing anything illegal or thinking about suicide. It will be scary, but know that you are helping your friend and it can save him/her from going down the wrong path in the future.  The counselor won't tell them you came to him/her. The decision to tell them you went is completely up to you.</item>
<item>Here are some strategies that you can use for finding a therapist:
<list type="unordered"><item>Ask your family doctor/primary care physician for recommendations.</item>
<item>Solicit recommendations from family members and friends.</item>
<item>Look in your local yellow pages under “Counselors - Personal,” “Counselors – Marriage and Family,” “Psychotherapists,” “Psychologists,” or "Physicians - Psychiatrists" (for medication).</item>
<item>Visit the American Psychological Association's psychologist locator page: <ref target="http://locator.apa.org/">http://locator.apa.org/</ref>.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
