<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc232" title="Use Pesto" shortTile="use-pesto" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2017-11-26" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Use_Pesto" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Use Pesto</head><p>Pesto is most well known as a flavorful addition to pastas and other Italian dishes. However, it can be tricky to figure out how else you can use it in different meals. Add a spoonful of pesto to a bowl of pasta, on top of your scrambled eggs, or even over a bag of popcorn to add a distinct, earthy flavor. You’ll love just how delicious pesto can be!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Blending Pesto with Breakfast</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Top scrambled eggs with a spoonful of pesto. Instead of salt and pepper, season your scrambled eggs with a touch of pesto and cheese for a unique, but flavorful breakfast. If the pesto is too thick to drizzle, add a tablespoon of olive oil or water to make it thinner. Add the pesto to your eggs while they’re still hot to maximize the flavor. <figure rend="Use Pesto Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Mix pesto into an omelette or frittata. For a stronger pesto flavor, add in a spoonful of pesto to the raw eggs before whisking them. Blend until the pesto has completely combined with the rest of the mixture, with no chunks or dollops. Then cook your omelette or frittata as normal. <figure rend="Use Pesto Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For only a light hint of pesto, pour a small amount of pesto on top of your omelette before serving.</item></list></item>
<item>Spread pesto over your morning toast. Pesto can be a tasty (and healthier) alternative to butter or jelly on your toast. Just scoop out a small dollop of pesto with your butter knife and smear it onto your slice of morning toast. You can do the same thing with a bagel, swapping out the cream cheese for pesto. <figure rend="Use Pesto Step 3.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Incorporating Pesto into Lunch and Dinner</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Add pesto to freshly cooked pasta. Cook a fresh bowl of pasta (preferably al dente) and drain it of any water. Do not allow the pasta to cool. Instead, move it to a clean bowl and add a generous amount (around ) of pesto, then toss the pasta until the pesto is thoroughly coating the pasta. You should notice the pasta taking on a green color once the pesto is mixed in. Serve and eat immediately. <figure rend="Use Pesto Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Mix pesto into a bowl of soup. Tomato soup, potato soup, and many other vegetable soups are prime dishes to enhance with pesto. Scoop up a spoonful of pesto and stir it into a bowl of soup, or pour a tablespoon of freshly made pesto onto your soup as a topping. Alternatively, you can add pesto to your soup base to infuse pesto flavor into every bite. <figure rend="Use Pesto Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Spread diluted pesto over cooked chicken or steak for a delicious sauce. Add a tablespoon or 2 of water to the pesto to dilute it. Slice and plate your chicken or steak however you’d like. Then pour the pesto over the meat before serving. The pesto will create a refreshing sauce that enhances the flavor of the meat. <figure rend="Use Pesto Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Use pesto as a topping for freshly cooked meats for extra flavor.</item></list></item>
<item>Use pesto as a vegetable topping or dressing. Pesto mixes nicely with all sorts of vegetables, from potatoes to broccoli. Dump a generous spoonful into freshly steamed or roasted vegetables as a healthy alternative to butter. The pesto will still keep your vegetables flavorful, but in a more nutritious way. <figure rend="Use Pesto Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Spread a dollop of pesto onto your sandwich. Pesto adds a zesty kick to even the plainest of sandwiches. You can spread pesto directly onto your sandwich bread, or combine it with another condiment, such as mayonnaise. Add your favorite fillings (such as ham or prosciutto) and put your sandwich together. <figure rend="Use Pesto Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Replace tomato sauce with pesto on your <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_Pesto_Pizza">pizza</ref>. Pesto is naturally stronger in flavor, so use only a couple of spoonfuls to start out with and adjust as needed. Spread it out evenly over raw pizza dough, then add the rest of your toppings. Parmesan cheese and chicken or sliced tomatoes make excellent toppings for pesto pizza. Bake your pizza, then let it cool before you slice it and enjoy! <figure rend="Use Pesto Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Using Pesto in Appetizers and Snacks</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Blend pesto into bread dough before <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_Bread_from_Scratch">baking</ref>. If you prefer making your own bread at home, incorporating  of pesto into your homemade bread dough can add a wonderful touch to its flavor. Simply add in the pesto alongside the dry ingredients of your bread dough before letting the dough rest and rise. Pesto-infused bread makes a wonderful side item for pasta and comfort food dinners! <figure rend="Use Pesto Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Combine pesto with your favorite dipping sauce. Pesto can add a noticeable flavor boost to guacamole, sour cream, and hummus. Simply stir a spoonful into your readymade dip and enjoy with crackers or mini toasts! <figure rend="Use Pesto Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Drop a spoonful of pesto over unbuttered popcorn. Pesto can not only give your popcorn extra flavor, but it also supplies an additional healthy fat to your diet. Measure out  of pesto and add it to a bag or bowl of popcorn, alongside a generous serving of Parmesan cheese. Shake up the popcorn and enjoy it while it’s fresh! <figure rend="Use Pesto Step 12.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you find your pesto is too thick to use, blend in a teaspoon of olive oil or water one at a time until it is thin enough for you to pour or mix in.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Pesto is stronger in flavor due to its ingredients. Add your pesto in small amounts (tablespoon or  increments) until the taste is to your liking.</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
