<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc95" title="Organize Digital Files on PC or Mac" shortTile="organize-digital" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-03-04" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Organize_Digital_Files_on_PC_or_Mac" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Organize Digital Files on PC or Mac</head><p>This wikiHow teaches you how to organize your files into folders using the Windows File Explorer or the Finder app for macOS.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Using Windows File Explorer</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Press . This opens the File Explorer, a tool that’s invaluable for keeping your files organized. <figure rend="Organize Digital Files on PC or Mac Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . It’s in the left panel. You may have to scroll down to find it. Now you’ll see several folders in the main (right) panel, as well as a list of connected drives. <figure rend="Organize Digital Files on PC or Mac Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Browse the folders in the right panel. Before you start creating folders and moving documents around, take a look at how Windows is already keeping your files organized. <figure rend="Organize Digital Files on PC or Mac Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Desktop:</hi> Anything in this folder also appears on your Windows desktop.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Documents:</hi> This is the default saving location for most applications, such as Microsoft Office products (Word, Excel, etc.), Notepad/Wordpad, etc.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Downloads:</hi> This is where internet downloads are saved by default. You’ll probably have a lot of files in this folder that could be moved elsewhere.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Music:</hi> The default location for music and sound files.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Pictures:</hi> Windows adds your photos to this folder, as well as videos created with your webcam.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Videos:</hi> You’ll find video files here.</item>
<item>You can also double-click any of the drives under “Devices and drives” to find other places to store and save files.</item></list></item>
<item>Create a new folder. You can add your own folders to any of those under This PC, including any of the drives under “Devices and drives.” Here’s how to create a folder: <figure rend="Organize Digital Files on PC or Mac Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Double-click the folder in which you want to create a new folder.</item>
<item>Press . A new folder called “New Folder” will appear.</item>
<item>Right-click the highlighted “New Folder” and click <hi rend="bold">Delete</hi>.</item>
<item>Type a name for the new folder (e.g. Baby Pictures, Private). Give the folder a name that describes the type of content it will hold.</item>
<item>Press .</item></list></item>
<item>Move files between folders. Now that you’ve found folders and learned how to create new ones, it’s time to organize your files. You can move files from any folder into the new one you created (or any other folder). Here’s how: <figure rend="Organize Digital Files on PC or Mac Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Open the folder that contains the files you want to move.</item>
<item>Hold  as you click each file you want to move. If you only want to move one file, you can click its name without pressing .</item>
<item>Right-click the selected files to expand the menu.</item>
<item>Click <hi rend="bold">Cut</hi>.</item>
<item>Go to the folder where you want to move the files.</item>
<item>Right-click a blank area of the folder.</item>
<item>Click <hi rend="bold">Paste</hi>. The files will move to their new location.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Using Mac Finder</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Click the Finder icon in the Dock. It’s the two-toned smiling Mac logo. This opens your computer’s file browser, which is where you can keep your files organized. <figure rend="Organize Digital Files on PC or Mac Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you don’t see a left column with a “Favorites” section, click the <hi rend="bold">View</hi> menu at the top of the screen, then click <hi rend="bold">Show Sidebar</hi>.</item></list></item>
<item>Click your username under the “Favorites” header. It’s in the left column of Finder. This opens your home folder. <figure rend="Organize Digital Files on PC or Mac Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you don’t see your username, click the <hi rend="bold">Finder</hi> menu at the top of the screen, select <hi rend="bold">Preferences</hi>, click <hi rend="bold">Sidebar</hi>, then check the box next to your username.</item></list></item>
<item>Browse the folders in your home folder. These are the folders that already exist to help keep your files organized: <figure rend="Organize Digital Files on PC or Mac Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Applications:</hi> This is where your programs are installed.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Desktop:</hi> Anything in this folder appears on the desktop.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Documents:</hi> Most apps will save new documents to this folder by default.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Downloads:</hi> Safari and other internet apps save downloaded files to this folder by default. If you’ve downloaded things from Safari, you may want to move those things to more relevant folders (e.g. Documents, Music).</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Music, Pictures, Movies:</hi> Many apps add files to these folders. For example, if you’ve created movies with iMovie, they’ll appear in Movies.</item></list></item>
<item>Create a new folder. You can create your own folders under any of those in Finder. Here’s how: <figure rend="Organize Digital Files on PC or Mac Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Open the folder in which you want to create a new folder.</item>
<item>Click the <hi rend="bold">File</hi> menu at the top-left corner of the screen.</item>
<item>Click <hi rend="bold">New Folder</hi>.</item>
<item>Type a name for the folder that describes the types of files it will contain (e.g. Work, Writing).</item>
<item>Press . Your new folder is ready for use.</item></list></item>
<item>Move files to another folder. The trick to keeping your files organized is to move files into relevant folders. Here’s how to move files to the new folder (or any other folder in Finder): <figure rend="Organize Digital Files on PC or Mac Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Open the folder that contains the files you want to move.</item>
<item>Select the file you want to move. To select more than one file, hold  as you click additional files.</item>
<item>Drag the selected file(s) to the folder. If you selected more than one file, this will drag all of the selected files to the new location.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
