<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc311" title="Cap Off a Sprinkler Head" shortTile="cap-sprinkler-head" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-10-19" dateModified="2019-09-15" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Cap_Off_a_Sprinkler_Head" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Cap Off a Sprinkler Head</head><p>If you have sprinkler heads that are too close together or want to prevent overwatering in a certain area, you may want to cap a specific sprinkler head. To cap a sprinkler head, you'll have to remove the existing sprinkler cap and replace it with a flat cap that will prevent water from flowing into that head. You can also completely remove the sprinkler head and cap it with a PVC pipe cap.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Installing a Flat Sprinkler Cap</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find or purchase a sprinkler cap or plug that is compatible with your system. Your sprinkler system should have originally come with the flat plastic caps or plugs that fit over your sprinkler head. These caps plug up the water and prevent it from being dispersed on your lawn or garden. If you can’t find the cap that came with your system, you may be able to purchase it on the manufacturer's website or at a hardware store. <figure rend="Cap Off a Sprinkler Head Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Each sprinkler system will use a different sized cap, so it's best to find one made specifically for your system.</item></list></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Turn-Off-Your-Water-Supply-Quick-and-Easy">Turn off the water</ref> to the sprinkler system. Locate the valve that controls the water that pumps through your sprinkler system and turn the valve clockwise to turn off the water. This will prevent water from flowing out of the system while you cap the sprinkler head. <figure rend="Cap Off a Sprinkler Head Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The shut-off valve for your sprinkler system is typically on the side of your house.</item>
<item>Shut-off valves on sprinkler systems are usually blue.</item></list></item>
<item>Clear the dirt around the sprinkler head. Use a gardening shovel to dig a  hole around the sprinkler head. Set the dirt on the side so that you can use it later to refill the hole. <figure rend="Cap Off a Sprinkler Head Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Clearing the dirt from the top of the sprinkler head will ensure that it doesn’t enter your system when you unscrew the head’s cap.</item></list></item>
<item>Remove the cap from the sprinkler head. Turn the top of the head counterclockwise to remove the cap. If you can’t remove the cap, use a pair of pliers to loosen it. Continue unthreading the top of the sprinkler head until it’s removed. <figure rend="Cap Off a Sprinkler Head Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Screw the new cap onto the sprinkler head. Place the flat plastic cap made for your system over the threads on the top of your sprinkler head. Turn the cap clockwise to tighten it. <figure rend="Cap Off a Sprinkler Head Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Refill the hole and turn on the system. Turn the water supply valve counterclockwise to turn the water back on. Turn on your irrigation or sprinkler system and examine the sprinkler head you capped. No water should be coming out of it. <figure rend="Cap Off a Sprinkler Head Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Capping with PVC Pipe</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Turn off the valve to the system's water source. Turn the water valve connected to your sprinkler system clockwise to turn it off and cut off water flow. Typically, this valve will be blue and located on the side or back of your home. <figure rend="Cap Off a Sprinkler Head Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you don’t turn off your water, it may spray out of the system when you remove the sprinkler head.</item></list></item>
<item>Dig a  deep hole around the sprinkler head. Use a gardening shovel to create a hole around the sprinkler head. Set the dirt on the side so that you can use it later to refill the hole. <figure rend="Cap Off a Sprinkler Head Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Removing the dirt around the head allows you to access and remove the sprinkler head easier.</item></list></item>
<item>Unscrew the sprinkler head. Make sure your hole is deep enough so that you can see the base of the sprinkler head. Grab the long stem of the sprinkler head and turn it counterclockwise to loosen it from your sprinkler system tubing. <figure rend="Cap Off a Sprinkler Head Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can use the extra sprinkler head to replace a broken sprinkler head or use it in another location along your system.</item></list></item>
<item>Screw a PVC pipe cap directly onto the system. Purchase a PVC pipe cap that is the same size as the pipe in your sprinkler system. Place the cap on the threads that the sprinkler head was screwed into. Rotate the PVC pipe cap counterclockwise to secure it onto the system. <figure rend="Cap Off a Sprinkler Head Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Screwing a PVC pipe cap onto your sprinkler system will turn off that specific sprinkler head.</item>
<item>Typically, sprinkler systems use  pipe.</item></list></item>
<item>Fill the hole with dirt and turn on the system. Go back to the valve and rotate it counterclockwise to turn the water supply back on. Access your sprinkler system controller to turn the system. No water should be coming out of the sprinkler head that you capped. <figure rend="Cap Off a Sprinkler Head Step 11.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Things You’ll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Gardening shovel</item>
<item>Sprinkler head cap or  PVC pipe cap</item>
<item>Wrench (optional)</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
