<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc166" title="Survive Family" shortTile="survive-family" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2017-11-27" dateModified="2019-09-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Survive_Family" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Survive Family</head><p>Disagreeing, arguments and flat out fighting with family members is a common occurrence in a household. Be it big arguments or little disputes, either way, it is no fun.. Many people do not know how to calm down or how to proceed when in a situation like this occurs. Though we may be tempted to scream and yell, that is never the right way to go. Here are some tips on the do's and don'ts in such situations.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Stay calm. When in the middle of an argument with a family member, stop yelling. Try saying with a nice/soft voice, "This argument isn't getting us anywhere. Let's take a break, have some alone time and come back with calmer heads and talk it out.” If the argument seems to be getting out of hand again, try taking another break.
<list type="unordered"><item>Allowing a break will give both sides a chance to think what about what the argument is actually about and possibly how to come to a solution.</item></list></item>
<item>Control your emotions. After an argument everyone is left upset or mad. Usually we lock ourselves in our rooms. Worse yet, we might try to take out our anger on other people or objects. A few hours later, you will likely think back on your actions with regret. One way to keep your anger controlled is do something that to distract yourself.
<list type="unordered"><item>Try things like colouring, drawing, or listening to music. Taking a nap or even going on a walk can help. These are all stress and anger relief tactics.</item></list></item>
<item>Take control of your actions. Sometimes when an argument is really heated it can get out of hand. Things will be said or done that are later regretted. Here are a few tips on <hi rend="italic">what not to do</hi>.
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not scream or yell. Try to keep your voice clear and gentle, even if the other person is not listening.</item>
<item>Never get violent. Do not hit anything or anyone. This will only make the situation worse.</item>
<item>Do not play the blame game. Instead, try and point out how both of you let the conversation get out of control.</item>
<item>If you are arguing about something the other has done, do not accuse them unless you are 100% sure they did it.</item></list></item>
<item>Try to avoid arguments. You could do this by:
<list type="unordered"><item>Agreeing with the other person, even if they are not right.</item>
<item>Keep the lines of communication open.</item>
<item>Consider that you may be having a bad day and just don't feel like talking to anyone. Make sure to tell them beforehand, so that you can perhaps avoid the argument in the first place.</item>
<item>Never start arguing with a family member just for fun.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
