<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc69" title="Rebuild a Dewalt 14.4V Battery Pack" shortTile="rebuild-dewalt-v" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-11-11" dateModified="2019-03-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Rebuild_a_Dewalt_14.4V_Battery_Pack" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Rebuild a Dewalt 14.4V Battery Pack</head><p>This short but sweet article will teach you to rebuild a dewalt 14.4V battery. This steps in this article are easy to follow, so you should be able to follow it fairly easily.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Taking Apart The Battery Pack</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Remove the six screws that hold the pack together.</item>
<item>Carefully pull apart the two halves.
<list type="unordered"><item>Take notes as to where things are and how they go back together.</item>
<item>Have a digital camera on hand for documenting dis-assembly</item></list></item>
<item>Remove the battery pack. Carefully pull the battery pack out of the holder.</item>
<item>Document everything. As you pull the battery "pack" apart take pictures and draw pictures of how the 12 batteries are packed and connected so tightly.</item>
<item>Buy replacement batteries.
<list type="unordered"><item>Google 1.2v subC batteries</item>
<item>(1.2 * 12 = 14.4)</item>
<item>Find your best price for 12 batteries.</item>
<item>When you place your order make sure you have measured your battery cells and are getting the correct "physical" size.</item>
<item>Buy with or without tabs.</item>
<item>Without tabs is less expensive and the following steps will show you how to make your own tabs.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Diagram the Connections</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Notice after folding and unfolding the string of batters that the 12 batteries are wired in series pos-to-neg, neg-to-pos and so on.</item>
<item>Use the gummy insulator that you pried away from the top and bottom of the batteries to draw a template.</item>
<item>Use a coin to complete the circles representing the batteries.</item>
<item>Draw a diagram looking at the batteries from the bottom.</item>
<item>Draw a diagram of the batteries from the top.</item>
<item>Note each connection and how the battery tab is oriented.</item>
<item>Number the batteries on your diagram.
<list type="unordered"><item>While you are waiting on your new batteries to arrive in the mail practice refolding the old battery string and placing it back into the holder.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Making Battery Tabs</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><list type="unordered"><item>The battery tabs, as you can see, need to be flexible.</item>
<item>One very good source of material for making battery tabs is an old computer cable with an outer mesh.</item>
<item>This is an old Firewire cable cut into small strips with the innards removed.</item>
<item>The mesh can be squashed flat and take on solder very well.</item>
<item>You will need eleven strips.</item>
<item>Cut extra just in case.</item>
<item>Put some flux on both ends and tin the ends with solder in preparation for soldering to your new batteries.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Preparing The New Batteries</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><list type="unordered"><item>When your new batteries arrive, flux and tin both ends with solder.</item>
<item>Use a small iron with a nice large flat head.</item>
<item>Do not hold the iron on the battery for more than a second or two.</item>
<item>Wait.</item>
<item>Try it again until the solder melts and adheres to the battery.</item>
<item>Wear eye protection and use common sense.</item>
<item>Common sense says "overheat . . . and BOOM!".</item>
<item>Take your time tinning the ends.</item>
<item>One or two seconds at a time.</item>
<item>Flux is a must!</item></list></item></list>
<head>Build Your New Battery Pack</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><list type="unordered"><item>Arrange your new batteries on one of your template drawings.</item>
<item>Solder your homemade battery tabs to the batteries following your diagram for the bottom view.</item>
<item>Slowly, not overheating the batteries.</item>
<item>Since you have tinned both the battery and the tab, soldering will go quickly.</item>
<item>Once you have the tabs on by following your "bottom view" drawing.</item>
<item>Flip the batteries over.</item>
<item>Set them on the gummy insulator you saved.</item>
<item>And put the whole bundle in the battery holder.</item>
<item>Now solder the remainder of your tabs following your "top view" drawing.</item>
<item>The first battery in the string of batteries has a special connector that is spot welded in place.</item>
<item>Use an old wood chisel to pry it away from the old battery, it pops off easily.</item>
<item>Tin that connector with flux and solder and solder it to your last new battery.</item>
<item>The bottom of this battery may need a longer battery tab to get to the next battery in series.</item>
<item>And the wire coming from this special connector goes to the last battery in your series of batteries.</item>
<item>If you saved the gummy insulator from your earlier steps, place it on top of the batteries.</item>
<item>Otherwise cut a new template from some sort of nonconducting material and put it in place.</item>
<item>Now reassemble the two halves of your battery housing and screw them together.</item>
<item>Having total confidence in yourself drop your new battery pack into the charger.</item>
<item>A steady red light means everything is good and the battery is charging.</item>
<item>Wait 5 minutes and try your drill.</item>
<item>If all is good give it a full charge.</item>
<item>But just to be safe keep an eye out for smoke.</item></list></item>
<item>Charge Your New Battery Pack.
<list type="unordered"><item>Steady red light means all is good and the battery pack is charging.</item>
<item>If you end up not calling the fire department.</item>
<item>Take yourself out for a beer.</item>
<item>Brag about your experience!</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Welcome to online Cordless Drill Batteries Store, www.drill-batteries.com.au offers a complete line of power tool batteries and cordless drill chargers for most cordless tools: Bosch Cordless Drill Batteries, Makita Power Tool Batteries, Dewalt Batteries, Panasonic Drill Batteries, Hitachi Tool Batteries, Ryobi Batteries and Vacuum Cleaner Battery. All drill batteries are specifically designed for the right power tool brand models.</item></list>
</text>
