<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc111" title="Use Microsoft Publisher" shortTile="use-microsoft-publisher" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-12-08" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Use_Microsoft_Publisher" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Use Microsoft Publisher</head><p>Microsoft Publisher is an Office application that allows you to create professional documents such as newsletters, postcards, flyers, invitations, brochures, and more using built-in templates. After selecting one of Publisher’s built-in templates, you can add text and pictures as desired before saving and printing your document.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Selecting a Template</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Launch Microsoft Publisher. Upon opening the application, the Catalog window will display on-screen. The Catalog window features a number of different publication types and templates you can use to design your document, including newsletters, brochures, signs, greeting cards, letterheads, envelopes, banners, advertisements, and more. <figure rend="Use Microsoft Publisher Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on the publication type you want to create in the left column. A number of different templates for the chosen publication type will display in the pane on the right. <figure rend="Use Microsoft Publisher Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Scroll through the templates in the right pane to find the template you want to use. For example, if you chose “Newsletter” as the publication type and your newsletter is geared toward children, you may want to use the “Kid Stuff Newsletter” template. <figure rend="Use Microsoft Publisher Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select your template, then click on “Start Wizard” at the bottom right corner of the Catalog window. The Catalog window will disappear, and display your template in the main Publisher window. <figure rend="Use Microsoft Publisher Step 4.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Creating Your Document</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Click on “Next” in the left pane after starting the wizard for your Publisher template. The wizard will guide you through the process of formatting your document. <figure rend="Use Microsoft Publisher Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Follow the instructions provided by the Publisher wizard to create your document. The steps will vary for each document based on your publication type. For example, if creating a newsletter, the wizard will ask you to select a color scheme, and indicate whether you want the recipient’s address printed on the document. <figure rend="Use Microsoft Publisher Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on “Finish” on the last tab of the Publisher wizard. The wizard will be minimized, and you can now begin adding text and pictures to your document. <figure rend="Use Microsoft Publisher Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on the section of the document to which you want content added. Your document will feature multiple frames, into which text or pictures can be added. In most cases, Publisher places example text and photos in each template to provide you with a general idea of how to write and format your document. For example, if creating an envelope, Publisher inserts dummy addresses in the appropriate text frames on the document so you can replace the text with your own information. <figure rend="Use Microsoft Publisher Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Type content or insert images into each frame in the document as desired. You can also insert additional frames into the document as needed. <figure rend="Use Microsoft Publisher Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Inserting Additional Frames</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Click on the “Insert” tab and select “Draw Text Box.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> <figure rend="Use Microsoft Publisher Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Position your cursor where you want the top left corner of the frame to begin. <figure rend="Use Microsoft Publisher Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Drag your cursor diagonally down and to the right until the frame is in the size desired. <figure rend="Use Microsoft Publisher Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click inside the frame and start typing text. <figure rend="Use Microsoft Publisher Step 13.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Inserting an Image</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Position your cursor where you want the image added to your document. <figure rend="Use Microsoft Publisher Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on the “Insert” tab and select “Picture” under the Illustrations group. This opens the “Insert Picture” dialog box. <figure rend="Use Microsoft Publisher Step 15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on the folder in the left pane that contains the image you want added to your document. <figure rend="Use Microsoft Publisher Step 16.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Open the same folder in the right pane of the dialog box. <figure rend="Use Microsoft Publisher Step 17.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select the picture you want added to your document, then click “Insert.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> The image will be added to your document. <figure rend="Use Microsoft Publisher Step 18.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Cropping an Image</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Click on the picture in your document you want cropped. The outline of a box will appear around the image. <figure rend="Use Microsoft Publisher Step 19.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on the “Format” tab and select “Crop” under Picture Tools. <figure rend="Use Microsoft Publisher Step 20.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Position the cropping handle over the edge or corner of your picture as desired. <figure rend="Use Microsoft Publisher Step 21.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Drag the cropping handle over the portion of picture you want cropped, or removed. <figure rend="Use Microsoft Publisher Step 22.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Hold down CTRL when dragging a center handle to crop both sides evenly.</item>
<item>Hold down CTRL + Shift when dragging a corner handle to crop all four sides evenly while maintaining the proportions of your image.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Saving Your Document</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Click on “File” and select “Save.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> <figure rend="Use Microsoft Publisher Step 23.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Type a name for your document in the “Save As” dialog box. <figure rend="Use Microsoft Publisher Step 24.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Specify the location to which you want your document saved. Otherwise, Publisher will save your file to the default working folder. <figure rend="Use Microsoft Publisher Step 25.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on “Save.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> Your document will now be saved. <figure rend="Use Microsoft Publisher Step 26.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Printing Your Document</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Click on “File” and select “Print.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> <figure rend="Use Microsoft Publisher Step 27.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Enter the number of copies you want printed next to “Copies of print job.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> <figure rend="Use Microsoft Publisher Step 28.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Verify your printer is selected next to “Printer.” In most cases, the properties of your default printer will automatically display in this field. <figure rend="Use Microsoft Publisher Step 29.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Indicate the paper size you’re using to print your document under “Settings.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> <figure rend="Use Microsoft Publisher Step 30.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select your print color preferences, then click “Print.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> Your document will now be sent to the printer. <figure rend="Use Microsoft Publisher Step 31.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
