<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc98" title="Teach a Senior to Use a Computer" shortTile="teach-senior-use" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-06-17" dateModified="2019-10-27" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Teach_a_Senior_to_Use_a_Computer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Teach a Senior to Use a Computer</head><p>Teaching  Seniors how to use a computer is the same as teaching anyone who has had no prior training in computers. Computer keys are in essence pretty much the same as typewriters, and typewriters have been around longer than most people living today. Most Senior centers have been teaching the usage of computers in their classes for many many years, and if you happen to meet a Senior who has not as yet had the opportunity to take the class, or to buy a computer and teach themselves, you will find it extremely easy  explain. Seniors have gone to college, are Doctors, Lawyers, and Supreme Court Justices, and most are quite Computer literate. Just because they have lived longer than many, does not mean that they are totally computer illiterate.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Volunteer to teach Computer courses at the Adult Education Classes held at most colleges. These classes are equipped with every thing that you need to teach.</item>
<item>Let them show you what they can already do on a computer, you might be completely surprised at how much they already do know.  Teach them how to access games, email, search for information. <figure rend="Teach a Senior to Use a Computer Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Understand that most <hi rend="bold">seniors</hi> today have college degrees. Teach them privately and expect that they will need only one three hour lesson. <figure rend="Teach a Senior to Use a Computer Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Explain how to turn on a computer, if they do not already know how. Explain that they should never just shut off the computer without first shutting down the programs. <figure rend="Teach a Senior to Use a Computer Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Show them the basics of getting around, and how to use the Search Bar by using  words only that they want to search for. There is no longer a need to use a html address. <figure rend="Teach a Senior to Use a Computer Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Seniors might also be  authors and some would want to use the computer for writing and would need to know how to save their work often or they might lose it, as a result of a power outage. of their typewriter. Do not talk down to them, as this is extremely insulting. <figure rend="Teach a Senior to Use a Computer Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make them understand, that once they learn the few basics that you are going to teach them, that they can get help for any problem or question that they might need. Show them where to find help sites, how to use the Search Bar, and explain once again that all they have to do is type in the word only that they want to search for. <figure rend="Teach a Senior to Use a Computer Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Allow them to sit at the computer while you ask  them to hit the Start button on the lower left. Then show them the Control panel, and everything else on the Start up program. Once they become familiar with the workings of the computer, accept your fee, and ask them to phone you if they have any further questions. <figure rend="Teach a Senior to Use a Computer Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Seniors may have lived longer than you, but they have experience so much more than you have so be prepared to learn more from them.</item>
<item>Listen to <hi rend="bold">seniors</hi> and learn about life when they were young. They have much to teach you.</item>
<item>Seniors in nursing homes are sick and need treatment, but that does not mean that they do not have their mental facilities.</item>
<item>The most important thing to teach anyone just learning how to use a computer, is that there is nothing that they can do to break it.</item>
<item>Donate to senior citizen centers. Some cities don't have one or fund a staff.</item>
<item>Get to know more <hi rend="bold">seniors</hi>, hold a computer class at a Senior Center and get to realize how sharp, how much fun they are, and how quickly they learn</item>
<item>Make sure that they know that when there is a question in front of the monitor screen, <hi rend="italic">Are you sure you want to do this</hi> that if they are not sure, to just click on <hi rend="bold">no</hi>.  Then they are sure that nothing will happen to harm the computer or the program that they might be working on.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not refer to <hi rend="bold">seniors</hi> as being <hi rend="italic">old</hi>, as if you were using the word as an insult, because in fact you are. Being old does not go hand in hand with them being incapable of learning how to use a computer.</item>
<item>Never or treat them as if they were incompetent or ignorant because they have lived longer than you.</item></list>
</text>
