<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc18" title="Perform a Leg Press Safely" shortTile="perform-leg-press" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2017-10-12" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Perform_a_Leg_Press_Safely" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Perform a Leg Press Safely</head><p>The leg press is a helpful gym equipment to use for developing muscles in the legs. As with all exercises, performing them correctly and safely brings the best results. The following instructions will help people who want to start performing the leg press complete this exercise safely.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Consult your primary care doctor to be sure if you can perform a leg press.  <figure rend="Increase Blood Volume Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Performing a leg press may look simple, but can be dangerous if not performed correctly. Check with your physician to make sure that you are healthy enough to perform one.</item></list></item>
<item>Wear the right attire.  <figure rend="IMG_2750.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>When performing any type of exercise, you should make sure that you are wearing the right attire for that particular exercise. For the leg press, you should look for flat sneakers or gym shoes as well as shorts or sweatpants.</item></list></item>
<item>Find a spotter. <figure rend="Feel Comfortable at a New Gym Step 6 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You should make sure there is someone around you to help you if the weight is too heavy or if you are having trouble racking it.</item></list></item>
<item>Choose a workout regimen.
<list type="unordered"><item>There are many workout regimens and plans that you could follow. For example, if you want to get stronger, you should use heavier weights, but perform the action less times.</item>
<item>If you want to build muscle, you should use lower weights and aim for about 8-12 repetitions.</item>
<item>wikiHow has an excellent instruction set on how to choose a workout regimen here <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/Design-a-Fitness-Training-Plan">https://www.wikihow.com/Design-a-Fitness-Training-Plan</ref></item></list></item>
<item>Adjust the height of the chair and the range motion so that you're comfortable. <figure rend="IMG_12754.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Being comfortable is essential to any exercise, if you are uncomfortable you could increase your risk of performing the movement incorrectly and potentially injure yourself.</item></list></item>
<item>Sit with your back flat on the seat.  <figure rend="Yourbackflat.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>It should be pressed firmly against the chair.</item>
<item>Keeping your back flat is important because it acts as a stable base that you can push off of.</item></list></item>
<item>Place your feet flat on the platform about shoulder width apart.  <figure rend="IMG_2751.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>There are many variations of foot placement which allow you to exercise different groups of leg muscles. For beginners, shoulder width is optimal for all round muscle development.</item></list></item>
<item>Push safety bars to the side and hold on to them throughout the exercise. <figure rend="A34E7387 22A9 434F A3EF 4538D806E50B.jpeg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This allows you to stay safe and feel secure, in case you can't handle the weight.</item></list></item>
<item>Lower the platform towards you by slowly bringing your knees towards your face.  <figure rend="1IMG_2752.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>As far as you can go depending on flexibility. For beginners, you should aim to reach a 90 degree angle at your knees.</item></list></item>
<item>Push back the platform and focus on keeping your feet flat. <figure rend="Notalltheway.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure not to push the platform all the way like shown above so that your knees do not lock and your knees don’t bend outwards.</item>
<item>Make sure to push with your heels to prevent any injuries.</item>
<item>Repeat steps 9 and 10 based on the number of repetitions you’ve decided upon within your workout regimen. (Step 4)</item></list></item>
<item>Pull back the safety bars to rack the weight.  <figure rend="IMG_2756.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure the platform is extended far enough for the safety bars to rack.</item></list></item>
<item>When you’re done with the exercise, unrack the weight and wipe down the equipment. <figure rend="Use Gym Equipment Step 13.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This last step is a rule of thumb for any exercise at the gym, out of courtesy for the following person. The next person does not want to re rack your weights or sit on your sweat.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>For beginners, it is best you start off with smaller weights and lower repetitions, then slowly increase over time as you get used to the workout.</item></list>
</text>
