<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc101" title="Change your Reuleaux RX200S Screen Colour" shortTile="change-reuleaux-rxs" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2016-09-11" dateModified="2017-01-20" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Change_your_Reuleaux_RX200S_Screen_Colour" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Change your Reuleaux RX200S Screen Colour</head><p>Follow this tutorial to learn how to change the Reuleaux RX200S screen color.  As a note, you can also change the screen color on the Reuleaux RX200 and DNA200 as well.  Changing the screen color can be done by using red lens repair tape in a jiffy.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Philips Terminal Screwdriver</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Remove all three of your batteries from your device.</item>
<item>You’ll notice 4 screws towards the middle and bottom.  You’ll need to unscrew those 4 screws, which will allow you to detach the face plate.</item></list>
<head>Car Rear Lens Repair Tape</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Put the lens repair tape over the OLED screen without removing the backing paper and see how long it needs to be. Once you see how much it will take to fit over the OLED screen area, then make your cut.  Remember, the screen covering on the faceplace will tidy up any over hand so it doesn't matter if it is slightly a bit larger than that of the OLED screen.</item>
<item>Next you’ll want to place the lens tape over the OLED screen, remove the paper backing to reveal the sticky back of the tape then place the tape over the OLED screen and gently hold stick it down.  Be sure that your tape stays in place by gently smothing it down. Beware not to leave any air bubbles. Be very gentle as we don't want to crack of damage the OLED screen. Only apply very light pressure not being heavy handed is the key to getting this right.</item>
<item>Chances are when you took off the face plate, the buttons may have fallen out.  Those buttons are your adjustment buttons to control your device. If those fell out by chance, use this step to ensure that you’ve put the button back into the holes they fell out of.</item>
<item>In this step you’ll want to reattach the face plate back onto the device.  Just line it up with the conformity of the device, then screw the screws back in previously removed while holding the plate in position. Be gentle and carefull not to over tighten the screws. Just nip them up gently.</item>
<item>Now you can finally insert your batteries back into the device and enjoy your screen color change on the device!</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be gentle and pay attention as not to be to heavy handed. The OLED screen is very delicate.</item>
<item>Be careful not to loose the screws as they are extremely small.</item>
<item>For a darker color change cut two exact pieces of the tape and add one piece on top of the other tape before applying to your OLED screen.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Air bubbles will be difficult if not impossible to remove once they occur so pay attention when sticking the tape to minimize these.</item>
<item>Once you have added this color change to the OLED screen you cannot undo it. Try adding it to the face plates lens cover instead. This way if you don't like your color changes you can replace the face plate (sold separately) to undo any color changes.</item></list>
</text>
