<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc156" title="Make Family Mealtime Cheerful" shortTile="make-family-mealtime" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-04-16" dateModified="2018-10-12" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make_Family_Mealtime_Cheerful" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make Family Mealtime Cheerful</head><p>Nowadays kids are always on their electronics or watching TV during meal time. There’s never any real conversation at the table isn't there? If you want to make family mealtime more cheerful read these quick and easy steps.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Preparing for Dinner</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Set up the table. Place the dinner plates, drinking glasses and knives and forks or spoons. You could even set napkins if you wish or use candles or a nice vase of flowers.
<list type="unordered"><item>Try letting your children set up the table. Setting the table is an easy task and can give your children the feeling of responsibility, why not let them set the table for once? It may even be fun for them.</item></list></item>
<item>Cook the meal. Try cooking your own meal that isn't too hard to make and is something everyone loves. If you want you could even make desert! Desert doesn't have to be something hard either, maybe just a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_a_Simple_Chocolate_Cake">simple chocolate cake</ref> or some <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_Biscuits">biscuits</ref>.
<list type="unordered"><item>Again, try to get the kids to help out with cooking as well. Give them easy tasks such as mixing batter, sifting flour, icing cupcakes and adding ingredients to a mixture. Leave the dangerous tasks to yourself and if your child is struggling help them.</item></list></item>
<item>Serve the meal. Serve the meal on the plates, provide bread in a bowl, fill the glasses with a drink, etc.</item></list>
<head>Fun During Mealtime</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Turn off any electronics. Turn the TV off and tell the children that there should be no electronics at the table. If everyone is distracted by an electronic then there will be no interacting.
<list type="unordered"><item>You could consider playing quiet music in the background. This makes the mealtime more peaceful and when everything’s awkwardly silent at least you will have music running in the background to listen to.</item></list></item>
<item>Start a conversation. Starting a conversation is easy, if you don’t know any good conversation starters you could look some up on a computer, there are plenty! Some good conversation starters are:
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are eating dinner after a school day, ask the children what they did in school.</item>
<item>If it is close to the weekend, school holidays or a public holiday, talk about your plans for them.</item>
<item>Talk about the meal! Get your children to judge how good the meal is or tell them they did a great job at helping to cook.</item></list></item>
<item>Be silly and have fun. This doesn't mean you have to make a mess and play with your food, you can tell jokes and riddles and see if anyone can guess them. You could even start a competition on who can finish their whole meal or eat all their vegetables.</item></list>
<head>Serving Dessert</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Take away the cutlery and food. Then set the table again so everyone is prepared for dessert. Don’t skip this step and pack the table with lots of plates around.</item>
<item>Serve the dessert. Ask if everyone wants dessert and serve some. Remember to only serve a little amount as they have just eaten a full meal and might not be that hungry. Besides there’s always more after they've finished their first serving.
<list type="unordered"><item>Try to set some rules such as the children have to eat most of their meal to get dessert or they have to eat all their vegetables to get dessert. No one likes a good meal going to waste just to save room for dessert!</item></list></item>
<item>Repeat the steps during mealtime. Start a conversation, tell jokes and riddles, start a game or competition or play music. Get everyone talking and make sure they’re having a good time.</item>
<item>Clean up. Consider giving your children some chores such as washing the dishes or putting away leftovers. The children will surely learn some responsibility.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don’t prepare a cheerful mealtime day after day, you and the children will soon get bored of it and go back to watching TV or being on their electronics.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Keep your children away from the oven and very sharp knives. Accidents can happen if you’re not careful.</item></list>
</text>
