<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc308" title="Celebrate the Day of the Kings (El Día de los Reyes)" shortTile="celebrate-day-kings" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2009-12-31" dateModified="2019-09-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Celebrate_the_Day_of_the_Kings_%28El_D%C3%ADa_de_los_Reyes%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Celebrate the Day of the Kings (El Día de los Reyes)</head><p>On the 6th of January, most Christians and Catholics of Hispanic descent celebrate Three Kings Day or <hi rend="italic">El Día de los Reyes</hi>. The Christian tradition calls this day Epiphany Day, when three kings (Melchior from Europe, Gaspar from Arabia, and Balthazar from Africa) arrived on the backs of animals bearing gifts of gold, frankincense and myrrh for the baby Jesus. Celebrate this holiday with attending a parade, giving gifts, and enjoying delicious food including a Rosca de Reyes!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Creating Excitement for the Day of Kings</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Write letters to the kings requesting gifts. In the days leading up to Three Kings Day, children write letters to the Three Kings about what gifts they would like to receive. Make sure that they are reasonable gifts, as you will be fulfilling their wishes! Keep the letters, but say you'll give them to the Three Kings for them. They can use the same letters for Santa Claus if they want, but those are mailed to the North Pole instead. <figure rend="Celebrate the Day of the Kings (El Día de los Reyes) Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make crowns for the kids to wear. You can either purchase a crown for a costume shop, or <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make-a-Crown">make one yourself</ref>. Cut a long piece of construction paper about  wide with triangular points at the top. Tape the edges together so that the crown is tight enough around their head, and decorate with flowers, jewels, and stickers. Have the kids wear them during the parade and the next day's festivities. <figure rend="Celebrate the Day of the Kings (El Día de los Reyes) Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Go to a parade. You can find a local parade by searching online for "Three Kings Day events near me" or asking your friends and neighbors. Release the letters to the kings into the air using helium-filled balloons, or give the letters to the men dressed as the Kings at the parade.You can also pose with the Three Kings and take pictures. <figure rend="Celebrate the Day of the Kings (El Día de los Reyes) Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Disney World in Anaheim, California has a three-day-long celebration for Three Kings Day that includes parades, performances, and Mickey Mouse himself!</item></list></item>
<item>Fill shoes with grass, hay, or milk and place them under the tree. Have everyone who will be receiving gifts polish a pair of their shoes and place them under the Christmas tree or near the bed of an older relative. These are gifts for the kings' animals! The animals were a horse, a camel, and an elephant, so make sure the offerings are something those animals would eat! <figure rend="Celebrate the Day of the Kings (El Día de los Reyes) Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can also use a shoe box instead of pair of shoes, but make sure it's beautifully decorated. Kids have a great time using their arts and craft skills whenever they can!</item></list></item></list>
<head>Celebrating on January 6th</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Swap out the gifts for the animals with the real presents overnight. Fill the shoes or box with toys, sweets, or the gifts they requested from the kings. Place the offerings for the animals somewhere out of sight, since the fun part is that the kings brought the gifts, not you! <figure rend="Celebrate the Day of the Kings (El Día de los Reyes) Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Stage a parranda. A parranda is a Puerto Rican tradition where a small group gathers to surprise a friend at their house with songs and dancing. It's a lot like Christmas caroling! The parranda will start after dark and will continue from house to house until the party ends at dawn on January 6th. <figure rend="Celebrate the Day of the Kings (El Día de los Reyes) Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Hint to the person you're surprising that you're making a parranda, but don't make it obvious. They may want to serve a traditional meal of soup or asopao de pollo (chicken and rice gumbo) before joining the group for another parranda.</item></list></item>
<item>Bake or order a Rosca de Reyes. It is a round pastry meant to symbolize the crowns the kings wore, since "rosca" means “wreath” and "reyes" means “kings”. Top the cake with caramel frosting and dried fruit to represent the gold and jewels of the crown. <figure rend="Celebrate the Day of the Kings (El Día de los Reyes) Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Hide a “baby Jesus” figurine inside the cake to symbolize Jesus in hiding from King Herod. Whoever finds the figurine in their slice is considered to have good luck and must prepare tamales for everyone on February 2nd, the Day of the Candles (Día de la Candelaria)!</item>
<item>After dinner, have each person cut their slice of the cake, as the knife symbolizes the danger of being found by King Herod's men on his birthday. Each person will then inspect their slice for the figurine (if it wasn't already found during the cutting).</item>
<item>Enjoy the cake with some <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_Homemade_Hot_Chocolate">hot chocolate</ref> or atole, a creamy cinnamon cider.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Tell everyone to look for a small figurine in the Rosca de Reyes before everyone starts eating to avoid choking.</item>
<item>Use child safety scissors and non-toxic craft supplies for any projects, including decorating a shoebox or making a crown to wear at dinner.</item></list>
</text>
