<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc130" title="Make an Altar to Knowledge" shortTile="make-altar-knowledge" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-12-15" dateModified="2015-07-08" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make_an_Altar_to_Knowledge" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make an Altar to Knowledge</head><p>Making an altar to knowledge is a very contradictory statement because a human mind is not naturalized to have access to absolute knowledge. However humans can get a glimpse of it.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>CONSIDER THIS FIRST.</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>The human, being conscious of his own ignorance tries to find patterns of rationality and justifies his actions by his believes, thus a belief that gives more pleasure to a human is more powerful than a rational belief that makes him feel what he doesn't want to feel or that puts him in a position he dislikes.</item>
<item>Knowledge is power and power is the bases for free-will and discovery, but the word power has different uses in different categories, power is associated with the word strong but the word strong as any other word is just a symbol of grammar characters of a linguistic communication.</item>
<item>The same linguistic symbol "words" have different meanings for humans because they were introduced to it by different experiences. To make an altar to knowledge is to get out of your perspective and point of view, which is very hard for the average human.</item>
<item>If you still want to make an altar to knowledge first define to your self what is an Altar and what is its function. Once you have given this concepts to your self start reading the second part.</item></list>
<head>The making of an Altar</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>We'll use "U" as a variable for Unknown An altar is a point in which some kind of admiration or respect or both is done by an action in order to attract the attention of the respective idea, entity, being or concept, or all, so that the "U" can dwell upon the altar for some time or for eternity. Once the humans feel the "U" has their attention they will perform another or the same action in order to get the benefits of having made the altar.</item>
<item>An Altar to the concept and idea of Knowledge varies because some humans find knowledge according to their perspectives. Some find it in Gods and Goddesses others in a single God others in nature or supernatural but, a pattern can be seen that Knowledge is being searched in unknown places.</item>
<item>If an Altar to knowledge is created the rational assumption is because the creator of the Altar wants to be the Recipient of it. The idea of reciprocity is persistent here.</item>
<item>The less knowledge you have the better and easiest way to acquire it.There are no learning curves in the acquisition of knowledge, they are called learning corners which are in definition are more harder to surpass than learning curves. Egos create the learning corners that's why the more knowledge you acquire the harder it is to keep getting it. This is becuase Egos grow as a self validation often generalized as the word "better" than its surroundings, this is what closes the path to knowledge for humans. Hey don't feel sorry for yourself the answer to repelled the ego is in the next step.</item>
<item>!!THIS IS THE MOST IMPORTANT STEP IN THE ARTICLE!!                                                                                A man was the best at his job, no one could do better than him which gave him alot of Ego.Things started to get worse in the workplace for everybody and he still did better than the others but everytime things got harder. He very confident of himself thanks to his inflated ego began to think he was the best of the world at that particular thing. He felt he knew alot at that because he was the best, he felt he could see things nobody could see, he started to belive in his ego, months later he lost his job becuase he couldn't keep up learning new things. Why? While the others admitted that they needed help to understand the new challenges he instead started to make his own explanations, the others were open to new ideas but he felt that he could understand them because he was the best, this closed his mind from new and simple perspectives.Being confident is good but at a certain intensity once somebody becomes overconfident he does everything at less capacity that what he could do because he doesn't focus as much because now he is confident and thinks that 50% of his focus would do the job.</item>
<item>The Altar to Knowledge is the self and the Sacrifices are the way you feel or in other words not inflated egos, once this mentality is expressed daily, you'll start to notice that you are learning new things everyday because you don't feel like you know everything at that subject(Even if you know everything don't feel like you do) making your mind the recipient of inputs by existence.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>One thing is to know what to do, the other and the important is to live it and express it.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not feel confident instead feel "curious".</item></list>
</text>
