<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc59" title="Set up a Heavy Bag" shortTile="set-up-heavy-bag" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-03-20" dateModified="2016-05-12" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Set_up_a_Heavy_Bag" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Set up a Heavy Bag</head><p>If you're going on a hike such as Duke of Edinburgh expedition, you're going to need to pack a lot of things into your rucksack and carry it for a few days so you want it to be as comfortable and practical as possible. This article gives you some advice on packing your rucksack effectively.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Get a kit list from your expedition leader so you know what to bring. Don't pack anything that's not on the list otherwise your bag will be too heavy, but make sure that you have got everything you need. <figure rend="Set up a Heavy Bag Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Lay everything on the kit list out so you can see exactly what you're taking and how much space it might take up. This helps you to plan how to pack your bag. <figure rend="Set up a Heavy Bag Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Put items into groups (e.g. day clothes, spare clothes, emergency items, food, campsite kit) and put each group of items into separate carrier bags. It helps when trying to find something in your rucksack quickly if you know what colour bag it is in. <figure rend="Set up a Heavy Bag Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Put a rucksack liner or bin liner in your rucksack to make it more waterproof. <figure rend="Set up a Heavy Bag Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>When putting the items in the rucksack, think about their weight, bulkiness and when you might need them. For example, your sleeping bag should go at the bottom of your rucksack because it's quite bulky and it's not something that you will have to access during the day. On the other hand, the first aid kit, phone, whistle, torch and food and water for the day should be near the top of the bag or in side pockets so that they are quick and easy to get to. <figure rend="Set up a Heavy Bag Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Load heavy items in your rucksack as close to your back as possible to make it feel lighter and easier to carry. <figure rend="Set up a Heavy Bag Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Once you've worked out where the best place for everything is in your rucksack, pack and unpack it until you know exactly where everything goes. This means that you can access anything quickly and you won't have to empty out your whole rucksack every time you need something. <figure rend="Set up a Heavy Bag Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try packing your bag in different ways and then walk around carrying it. This should give you an idea of how it is most comfortable.</item>
<item>It's best if everyone knows where all the other team members keep essential items like the first aid kit. If only the person carrying the first aid kit knows where in their bag it is packed and they get injured or are unconscious, the rest of the group could be wasting a lot of time looking for the kit.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Where possible, separate food, cooking fuel and matches. It's best to put these in different rucksacks if walking as a group to avoid the fuel catching fire or leaking over the food. Wrap the fuel securely in a couple of carrier bags and carry it on the outside of the rucksack so if it does leak, it won't get all over your clothes or sleeping bag.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Rucksack (50-65 litres depending on the expedition)</item>
<item>Waterproof liner e.g. bin bag</item>
<item>Everything on your kit list, but no extra kit</item>
<item>Spare carrier bags, ideally different colours or designs</item></list>
</text>
