<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc283" title="Do Pranic Healing" shortTile="pranic-healing" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-01-05" dateModified="2015-11-24" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Do_Pranic_Healing" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Do Pranic Healing</head><p>First of all, there is actually no how to Pranic Healing without formal training. It is a highly specialized science and art, and no one, absolutely no one teaches without a valid license from the Institute for Inner Studies to do so. Anyone professing to do this without enrolling you in a class is suspect. There are plenty of resources available that tell you about Pranic Healing, its origins, the Modern Founder and various organisations around the world.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Learn. Take a Basic Pranic Healing Course from a Licensed Instructor in your area. The Basic course usually entails 16 to 20 hours of classes, which is equivalent to two working days. This empowers YOU to heal yourself and your loved ones of simple ailments. Sometimes trainers split them over 5 hours each for three days. Among the benefits of learning Pranic Healing through the entry level Basic Pranic Healing course, is the distinct healing technique that you are taught. You could heal a loved one no matter how far they maybe physically. <figure rend="Do Pranic Healing Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>What after Basic Course? There is a step by step progression as you are led through higher courses like Advance Pranic Healing, And Pranic Psychotherapy. As a trainer puts it, Basic is like learning to be on a trolley. Advanced is like learning all about the accelerator and the breaks. Psychotherapy is to be able to fix the engine.</item></list></item>
<item>Search The Net. There are plenty of testimonials attesting benefits accrued by people from different walks of life, and from simple to chronic ailments. These range from simple headaches and migraines to complex phobias, traumas and addictions. <figure rend="Do Pranic Healing Step 2 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Know that you don't HAVE to physically be with the healer during the session. It helps, but exceptions are made all the time. <figure rend="Do Pranic Healing Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be Warned. It is rare that ONE healing session may relieve you of all the symptoms completely, or prevent the recurrence of symptoms sometime later. Such miracles happen, but normally healers witness the requirement of more sessions than one. Seldom can a healer predict the number of healings required,except that in chronic cases, repeated healings during the first week or two three weeks may be advised. Depending upon the proficiency of the healer,symptoms show alleviation on the physical level after the first session itself. <figure rend="Do Pranic Healing Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Learn about the Founder. A Filipino of Chinese descent, Master Choa Kok Sui is the founder of modern Pranic Healing and author of the book, THE ANCIENT SCIENCE AND ART OF PRANIC HEALING, which was later retitled MIRACLES THROUGH PRANIC HEALING . From humble beginnings in Manila, today Pranic Healing spans across 80 countries and people of diverse cultures, religions and languages find their lives transformed once they encounter Pranic Healing. <figure rend="Do Pranic Healing Step 5 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>There is more than just healing to Pranic Healing. While the scope extends beyond physical ailments, aches, pains, colds, coughs, allergies, etc. it encompasses psychological healing,relationship/s healing, and advanced Meditation techniques.</item></list></item>
<item>Learn the principles. The principle of Pranic Healing sounds simplistic. Pranic comes form Prana, which means vital energy or life force. This is an energy healing system; and an entirely no touch no drugs therapy. It does NOT  throw out orthodox medicine; and is meant to be complementary to Modern Science. <figure rend="Do Pranic Healing Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Not only do you learn to heal yourself and others, you also learn about maintaining personal health and balance at optimum levels, stress busting, powerful breathing techniques, super-brain yoga, meditate for world peace, spread goodwill, and link to a whole community of people working towards personal and world peace, being light-workers for Divine Light, Divine Love and Divine Power.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If symptoms persist or the ailment is severe, consult your physician, and at the same time appraise your healer of your conditions.</item></list>
</text>
