<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc216" title="Rate Financial Writers" shortTile="rate-financial-writers" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-05-21" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Rate_Financial_Writers" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Rate Financial Writers</head><p>Financial writers provide a great deal of valuable information to investors who are seeking a good deal as well as individuals and companies that wish to get some insights into what is happening with the economy. In order to focus attention on writers who are likely to provide information that will help rather than hinder efforts to manage financial resources to best effect, it is important to qualify or rate financial writers. Fortunately, this process can be accomplished by taking into consideration the background and experience of the writer, the quality of information provided in the past, and the level of respect that the writer commands from his or her peers.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Look into the educational background of the financial writer. Identify college courses taken, degrees held, and continuing education seminars attended to get some idea of the knowledge base that the writer brings to the task of financial writing. A solid education in a related field is a strong sign that the writer will know how to properly interpret economic indicators and report information in a manner that will be helpful to readers. <figure rend="Rate Financial Writers Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Consider the past experience of the writer. While newer financial writers may have solid educational credentials, they lack the background that can only come from experience. Think in terms of how useful the work of the writer has been to investors, financial planners and others over the last several years. This will provide some insight into how much experience the writer has absorbed and can bring to the task of providing thoughtful and timely information today. <figure rend="Rate Financial Writers Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Check the writer's track record and assess the degree of success. Financial writers often include projections or predictions of what will happen in some sector of the marketplace and how those events will impact companies, investors and even consumers in general. Looking back at past predictions and getting some idea of how often the writer was right and how many projections turned out to be flawed will provide some perspective when determining if the word of the writer is reliable. <figure rend="Rate Financial Writers Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Identify any memberships that the writer may hold in professional organizations. This may include a state or national financial writers association or an organization that is directly related to the sector of the economy that the writer routinely covers. Professional memberships indicate that the writer takes the profession seriously and is engaged in networking with others who labor in the field. <figure rend="Rate Financial Writers Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Evaluate the place of the financial writer among his or her peers. Should others quote freely from the articles and columns that the writer prepares and publishes, this indicates a degree of trust on the part of others. When other writers tend to ignore the projections or thoughts of the writer, this may indicate that he or she is not particularly esteemed in the profession, and the writings should be approached with some degree of hesitancy. <figure rend="Rate Financial Writers Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't disregard your own hunches when rating financial writers. Even if the writer in question is relatively new to the field and has not yet established a widely recognized reputation, there may be some gems in the articles or columns published under his or her byline.</item>
<item>Should a seasoned writer present a point of view that strikes you as being untenable, don't assume the writer is correct and you are wrong; look for other evidence that will affirm 1 of the 2 positions before making a final decision.</item></list>
</text>
