<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc107" title="Extract and Edit an Image from Dalet (C SPAN)" shortTile="extract-edit-image" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2016-05-24" dateModified="2018-01-10" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Extract_and_Edit_an_Image_from_Dalet_%28C_SPAN%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Extract and Edit an Image from Dalet (C SPAN)</head><p>Start with step one below to learn how to extract, edit, and upload images from the Dalet program onto the C-SPAN website.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open up Dalet. <figure rend="Extract and Edit an Image from Dalet (C SPAN) Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Open up the Dalet icon on your homepage by double clicking on the orange icon with the "play" symbol.</item>
<item>Sign in with your computer login username and password.</item></list></item>
<item>Find media feeds. <figure rend="Extract and Edit an Image from Dalet (C SPAN) Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Select the Media tab inside of the Dalet program.</item>
<item>Click on "Incoming" then "Feeds" and select the current date.</item>
<item>Double click on the event you would like to find an image for. If there are two versions of the event (i.e. Keyed and Unkeyed) choose the Unkeyed Raw version.</item></list></item>
<item>Select your extraction image. <figure rend="Extract and Edit an Image from Dalet (C SPAN) Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Once you have double clicked on the event, a video trimmer tool should come up on the screen.</item>
<item>Scroll through the video roll by dragging your mouse across the trimmer.</item>
<item>You can also use the space bar to navigate the video in real time.</item>
<item>Use the J key on the keyboard to rewind the video content.</item>
<item>Use the L key on the keyboard to fast forward the video content.</item>
<item>The space bar can also be used to pause video.</item>
<item>Use numbers 1 and 2 on the number key pad to move forward or backward in smaller time increments.</item>
<item>When you have selected a spot on the video you want to save go to "Preview Window" at the top of the Dalet browser.</item>
<item>Scroll down to "Extract Image".</item></list></item>
<item>Save your extracted image. A "Save As" Screen should come up. <figure rend="Extract and Edit an Image from Dalet (C SPAN) Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Save all photos in the following format: first and last name of person or event-the current date in numerical format_C-SPAN.</item>
<item>Change the format of the file from BMP to JPEG.</item></list></item>
<item>Prepare the image for edit. <figure rend="Extract and Edit an Image from Dalet (C SPAN) Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>With the "Media" tab still selected scroll down to "Clip Bins".</item>
<item>Double click on "Clip Bins" and select the clip bin with your name.</item>
<item>Find the image you just saved.</item>
<item>Click on the Windows Icon in the bottom left hand corner and select Computer.</item>
<item>Select the (W:) drive.</item>
<item>Open the Raw Folder.</item>
<item>Select the category that best represents the event you extracted your picture from.</item>
<item>Drag and drop the image file from your Dalet ClipBin into the folder.</item></list></item>
<item>Use Photoshop to edit the selected image file <figure rend="Extract and Edit an Image from Dalet (C SPAN) Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Open up Photoshop.</item>
<item>Select "File" and "Open".</item>
<item>Go to the (W:) drive and open the raw folder and select the image you pulled from Dalet.</item>
<item>Select "View" and uncheck "Pixel Aspect Ratio Correction".</item>
<item>Select "Image" and scroll down to "Image Size".</item>
<item>Make the Pixel Dimension width of the image 1440 and the height 810.</item>
<item>For basic editing select the "Image" drop down bar and use "Auto Tone" and "Auto Contrast".</item>
<item>For more image edits use the "Adjustments" tab on the "Image" drop down bar.</item></list></item>
<item>Save the final image edits for use on the C-SPAN website. <figure rend="Extract and Edit an Image from Dalet (C SPAN) Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Select "File" in the top left hand corner of Photoshop.</item>
<item>Scroll down to save for web.</item>
<item>Save the image in standard file format and save to the "Edit" file folder under the appropriate event category.</item></list></item>
<item>Upload the image to the C-SPAN Website. <figure rend="Extract and Edit an Image from Dalet (C SPAN) Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Go to the C-SPAN website and click on the event you would like to upload a promo picture for.</item>
<item>Make sure you are logged into your "My C-SPAN" account using your C-SPAN email address.</item>
<item>Click on the link to the "Internal Page" located just under the C-SPAN logo on the left hand side.</item>
<item>Select "Promo Picture" on the far right side of the internal page.</item>
<item>Click on "Upload a new promo image".</item>
<item>Select "Choose File" and then upload the edited version of your Dalet Image</item>
<item>Before clicking "Upload" make sure you type "C-SPAN" into the "Image Attribution" space.</item>
<item>Your edited image should appear on the program screen.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
