<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc209" title="Succeed at Retail Arbitrage" shortTile="succeed-retail-arbitrage" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-06-24" dateModified="2017-06-04" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Succeed_at_Retail_Arbitrage" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Succeed at Retail Arbitrage</head><p>In economics, arbitrage is defined as a market inefficiency that can be exploited for profit by discovering a condition where an asset can be purchased for a lower price in one market, and instantaneously sold for a higher price in a different market.  The arbitrage profit is the difference between the two prices.   Retail arbitrage can be risky and difficult to execute because of the time factor associated with the lifecycle of the transaction.  Retail arbitrage involves real, tangible assets which must be purchased, stored, and transported.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Understand what arbitrage means. This term is usually used in dealing with non-tangible goods. For example, stock A is listed at the New York Stock Exchange (NYSE) for $50 per share.  At the same time, the same stock is listed at the Tokyo stock exchange for $51 per share.  An arbitrageur would place a buy order at the NYSE while simultaneously placing a sell order at the Tokyo stock exchange thereby executing a risk free arbitrage trade and profiting $1 not including transaction costs, taxes, or any other fees.   <figure rend="Get a Job Fast Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The above example occurs in an entirely electronic world where no possession of the asset takes place, and it occurs almost instantaneously.  It is this instant that makes arbitrage more or less of a risk and attractive because there is a high degree of certainty that the asset purchased will be a successful sale transaction thus avoiding the risk of owning an unwanted asset. Retail arbitrage is a bit riskier and more time consuming, since you actually have to handle and transport the good you've bought before selling it on.</item></list></item>
<item>Visit a Walmart, Target or any other store to find an asset to purchase. Estimate its viability as a trade including potential profit.  Physically drive to the store and look for merchandise that you perceive holds an opportunity for arbitrage.  <figure rend="Become-a-Millionaire-Step-19.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You should have your smartphone handy to do a price comparison and develop an idea of what the item you are considering sells for in other markets.  You should know your bottom line for the item to be profitable.</item></list></item>
<item>Make the purchase using cash or credit.  If you use credit, you will have to factor in the cost of credit to determine if the transaction will be profitable.  If you use cash, the math is simpler but there are opportunity costs for the cash so choose wisely. <figure rend="Change-Your-Name-Step-10-Version-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Store the asset and possibly pay storage fees.  If you have a large Retail Arbitrage practice, you may have a warehouse to store your merchandise.  Your garage is a good alternative as long as you implement a good inventory system <figure rend="Change-Your-Name-in-Texas-Step-20.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Locate a secondary market, such as Amazon, to unload the asset.  Listing your item at a secondary market is the easiest way to sell it, but it is by no means the only distribution channel available to you.  You can use your sales skills in anyway your imagination and grit allow you to.   Amazon is the most common way to sell for Retail Arbitrageurs. <figure rend="Market-a-Product-Step-1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wait for the item to sell.  If you listed your item through Amazon, then you will be notified to ship to the buyer unless you shipped to Amazon.  Your reputation as a seller matters, so be diligent about shipping times, methods, and packaging.  If you committed to standard shipping, do not ship overnight.  Amazon will ding you for it.  Likewise, if you committed to overnight shipments, comply with expectations.   <figure rend="Apply-for-an-Entrepreneurial-Grant-Step-2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>There will be shipping costs associated with the merchandise, so be sure to factor those in while you are selecting items for purchase for resale.  You can get an idea of how much it will cost to ship an item when you do price comparisons with your smartphone at the store before you buy the item.</item></list></item>
<item>Collect payment, minus transaction fees! <figure rend="File-Bankruptcy-in-the-United-States-Step-19.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>For retail arbitrage to be profitable, keep the following in mind:
<list type="unordered"><item>Large margins are the key to being successful.  The wider the spread between your cost, and your estimated resale price, the better.  Look for high price discrepancies between your cost, and the going price at other markets.</item>
<item>Be cognizant that size matters because of shipping costs.</item>
<item>Consider the availability of the item.  The item cannot be a commodity because they are widely available. Specialty items work best.</item>
<item>Seasons matter for certain items.</item>
<item>Time is of the essence.</item>
<item>A sophisticated retail arbitrageur will have profit and loss financial models in an Excel or other software package, and bring those models in a tablet or other mobile device to the retail location where purchases are to be made so that more accurate decisions can be made when making inventory selections.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>A lot can happen to the price of the asset from the time it is purchased, to the time it is sold.  The biggest risk to the retail arbitrageur is that he/she will not be able to price the asset competitively enough to make a profit, and that he/she will be stuck with the "hot potato".   If market prices move against you, you will be stuck with an asset that you neither want, nor need. On the contrary, if the asset increases in value from your original assumption, then you will profit more than forecasted.</item></list>
</text>
