<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc269" title="Stay Healthy With Busy Schedules" shortTile="stay-healthy-busy" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-02-08" dateModified="2019-09-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Stay_Healthy_With_Busy_Schedules" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Stay Healthy With Busy Schedules</head><p>When you're balancing a demanding schedule, it can be hard to maintain healthy habits. It's so easy to just grab a fast food lunch or sleep in until the last possible minute when you're stressed and busy all the time. By preparing food ahead of time, exercising whenever you have the opportunity, and rewarding yourself for healthy living, you can have a fit, healthy lifestyle no matter what your schedule looks like.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Eating Healthy</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Cook your meals ahead of time. Having healthy meals like lean chicken breast, light stir-fry, or pork loin ready to eat at all times will help you resist the temptation to just order a pizza after a hard day at work or school. There are several ways to ensure that you always have a few healthy, fast meals ready to go.  <figure rend="Stay Healthy With Busy Schedules Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Buy a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Use_a_Slow_Cooker">slow cooker</ref>. You can fill it up in the morning and enjoy a hot, savory meal at night.</item>
<item>Cook a week's worth of meals at once.  Divide the food into portions so you'll be able to quickly reheat and enjoy on busy weeknights.</item>
<item>Consider a meal delivery service. Some companies such as Freshly and Green Chef specialize in delivering fresh, healthy, ready-to-cook meals designed for busy people who want to eat healthy. </item></list></item>
<item>Pack lunches the night before. If you already have a healthy lunch with you right at your desk, you won't be tempted to eat an unhealthy vending-machine lunch! Lean turkey sandwiches, grilled or boiled chicken breast, and tuna salad with light mayonnaise are healthy options you can prepare quickly after dinner the night before. <figure rend="Stay Healthy With Busy Schedules Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Eat a healthy breakfast. Never skip breakfast, no matter how busy you are! Skipping breakfast will decrease your productivity by making you tired, lethargic, and prone to stress. Buy quick, healthy breakfast options like fresh fruit, granola, or instant oatmeal.  <figure rend="Stay Healthy With Busy Schedules Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Bring snacks with you to work. Having a variety of healthy snacks on hand will prevent you from indulging in junk food when you need an energy boost. Granola bars, nuts, fresh fruit, trail mix, baby carrots, and baked chips are good options. <figure rend="Stay Healthy With Busy Schedules Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Avoid drinking or eating out too often. Alcohol and restaurant food are both high in calories, low in nutritional content, and can make you tired and sluggish. If you still want to go out with your friends, consider bringing a healthy snack along, drinking seltzer instead of alcohol, or limiting yourself to one drink or one half-portion of a meal.  <figure rend="Stay Healthy With Busy Schedules Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Drink lots of water. You will save a lot of calories and feel better physically by switching to water for most of your liquid intake. Too much caffeine and sugar in your drinks can increase your exhaustion and decrease your energy levels. <figure rend="Stay Healthy With Busy Schedules Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try sugar-free water flavorings.</item>
<item>Buy a reusable water bottle and keep it filled. If you always have water nearby, you're much more likely to drink it.</item>
<item>Avoid sodas and other unhealthy drinks.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Finding Time to Exercise</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Schedule an appointment at the gym. It might seem impossible to find the time to make regular gym visits, but setting a specific appointment at the gym can motivate you to go. By making a formal appointment at your gym and putting it in your planner, you are much more likely to attend. <figure rend="Stay Healthy With Busy Schedules Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wake up early to exercise. Set your alarm for a half-hour earlier and use that time to get in a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Do_a_Full_Body_Workout_in_Less_Than_5_Minutes">quick workout</ref>. If you get your workout done early in the day rather than saving it for the end, you are less likely to put it off or cancel it altogether.  <figure rend="Stay Healthy With Busy Schedules Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Look for hidden opportunities to exercise. If you are completely unable to schedule specific workout times, look at your routine and see how you can add exercising to the schedule you already have. You don't need to block out an hour at the gym every day to add more fitness to your routine! <figure rend="Stay Healthy With Busy Schedules Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Park your car at the back of the lot and walk into the building.</item>
<item>Take the stairs instead of the elevator.</item>
<item>Get up every half hour and take a quick walk around the office.</item>
<item>Do chores like folding laundry or organizing your desk while standing up.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Managing Your Stress Levels</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Reevaluate your priorities. Take some time to think about all of your obligations. Are some of them not actually productive or helpful? Have you taken on too much responsibility? If so, consider cutting back on your obligations in favor of spending more time focused on your health. <figure rend="Stay Healthy With Busy Schedules Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, if you work full-time, attend night classes, and belong to three clubs, take a break from one of the clubs until school is out of session.</item></list></item>
<item>Think positive, helpful thoughts. Staying positive will decrease your stress and exhaustion levels, making it easier to maintain a healthy lifestyle despite a busy schedule. When you become tired or irritated at work or school, think about things that you enjoy. <figure rend="Stay Healthy With Busy Schedules Step 11.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Imagine yourself enjoying your next day off.</item>
<item>Think about how much healthier your lifestyle is now.</item>
<item>Think about the money you save by not eating out or getting pizza delivered.</item></list></item>
<item>Give yourself rewards. You will be less stressed and more motivated to continue eating healthy and exercising if you have a goal to work towards. Rewards can be anything you enjoy, but be careful to avoid giving yourself junk food rewards! <figure rend="Stay Healthy With Busy Schedules Step 12.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Use the money you save eating in to buy a specific item you want, like a new shirt or video game.</item>
<item>Reward exercise with a fun outdoors activity. If you've been parking your car a little further out every day for two weeks, plan a short hike to test your new fitness regimen.</item>
<item>Watch a new TV show in the evening on days when you get up early and exercise.</item></list></item>
<item>Get plenty of sleep. When you're juggling a busy schedule, cutting back on sleep can seem  like a good idea, but it will actually make you less healthy and more stressed out! Most adults need between 7 and 9 hours of sleep, so take a look at your schedule and see what you can change to ensure that you get into bed at a reasonable hour.  <figure rend="Stay Healthy With Busy Schedules Step 13.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
