<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc127" title="Start Studying for IIT in Class 11" shortTile="start-studying-iit" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-03-25" dateModified="2015-08-10" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Start_Studying_for_IIT_in_Class_11" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Start Studying for IIT in Class 11</head><p>Although students think that they need a break after their class 10 board exams, this is the best time to start preparing for IIT-JEE. Here are some tips which will surely help you to start your preparation for JEE-Mains &amp; Advanced.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>The First Step.</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>JOIN ANY COACHING INSTITUTE-This should be the first step to start your preparation. It is very helpful to join any coaching institute. This helps you to get clear guidance in your starting preparation and also helps in clearing your basics too;</item></list>
<head>Revise your notes thoroughly.</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>These are the best methods to excel in your weekly subjective and objective examinations.
<list type="unordered"><item>Revising notes not only helps to build a strong understanding of the topic, but also helps in building confidence in the present topic,. which in turn is very important.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Practice assignments</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Practicing assignments everyday is a very important task concerning preparation.
<list type="unordered"><item>The assignments of your coaching institute should be preferred most. They help you in getting confidence in that particular topic.</item>
<item>Also, there are many local books available in the market which help you in providing the latest study material and assignments.</item>
<item>Also try to complete the assignments of the present topic as soon as possible.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Plan your coaching and school.</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Although your coaching is very important for your goal, but don't neglect your school's.
<list type="unordered"><item>Remember the school only provides marks to you to qualify for the next class.</item>
<item>You can manage it , --by planning 4-6hrs for your coaching and then doing the school work on your coaching institute holidays.</item>
<item>Remember, pay the same amount of attention to your school as your coaching.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Practice model papers</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>This is the best method to keep a check on your performance in your academics. Practicing model papers will give you an idea of the questions being asked in the exams.
<list type="unordered"><item>Practice papers, giving yourself 3 hrs for each test paper.</item>
<item>Always try to finish a model paper, the same day you finished a topic.</item>
<item>Always try to finish the model paper of a particular topic as soon as possible.</item>
<item>This will help you in clearing your basics and building your confidence.</item>
<item>There are many local books present in market which you can take help of.</item></list></item></list>
<head>No Shortcuts and Tricks to hard work</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Have all of us have heard that "Hard work is the key to Success". This is always true.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are planning to secure a good rank in Jee mains and advanced, there are no shortcuts for hard work.</item>
<item>You have to study at least 5-6 hrs in your school days with a fresh mind to score good in your entrance exams.</item>
<item>Eat a healthy diet and try to exercise at least half an hour a day. This will help your brain to work more efficiently</item></list></item></list>
<head>Avoid entertainment</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>When I stated about entertainment i mean - T.V. , social networking sites and all that time wasting things.
<list type="unordered"><item>At some point you will feel that you just cannot resist, but then think of your dream for which you are working so hard for.</item>
<item>If you want you can watch television for sometime.</item>
<item>Try to make the best use of the internet. Apart from Facebook and Twitter, there are many useful things on internet which can help you to increase your knowledge beyond books.</item>
<item>This can decrease your efficiency which will ultimately lead to a huge loss.</item>
<item>Make the best use of internet. Apart from Facebook  and Twitter, there are many useful materials in the internet which can help you in increasing your knowledge out from your books.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Be confident</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Don't think about what will happen after 2 years; just work hard and you will get it, surely.
<list type="unordered"><item>At some point of time you will feel tired and will want to resist studying for sometime, but remember that time can help you secure 10 rank higher than you were expecting.</item>
<item>You should surely take breaks at least once in two weeks, this will help in refreshing your mind. This will impact on motivation and concentration levels afterwards.</item>
<item>Finally, don't feel alone. Always remember "God helps those who help themselves".</item></list></item></list>
</text>
