<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc248" title="Prepare a Sea Salt Soak" shortTile="prepare-sea-salt" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-06-17" dateModified="2019-05-15" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Prepare_a_Sea_Salt_Soak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Prepare a Sea Salt Soak</head><p>Sea salt is known mostly for being a tastier alternative to table salt, but it also has medicinal and relaxing qualities as well. A sea salt soak can be used to treat minor infections and wounds as well as sterilize piercings and tattoos, whereas a sea salt bath soak can be as relaxing as taking a dip in the ocean. Sea salt contains no iodine, which makes it a perfect for creating saline solutions for keeping wounds clean. It mixes with scented oils easily and can be stored in the bathroom to add to calming baths as well.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Making a Medicinal Sea Salt Soak</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Purchase  of purified water, or purify tap water at home. You can pour tap water through a water filter, or purchase purified water if you don't have access to one — just make sure the bottle is labelled as purified. You can find filter pitchers or faucet filters at most grocery and specialty stores. The filter removes chemicals that are added to normal tap water, which can affect the salinity of the solution. <figure rend="Prepare a Sea Salt Soak Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pour the purified water into a saucepan and boil it to sterilize it. The boiling process will kill any living organisms, leaving you with sterile purified water. If you bought distilled water instead of purifying tap water, it should already be sterilized. <figure rend="Prepare a Sea Salt Soak Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Allow the water to cool, and add 9 g (1.8 tbsp) of sea salt. After letting the water cool slightly, add sea salt and let it dissolve completely. If you need to prepare more medicinal sea salt soak, add another 9 g (1.8 tbsp) of sea salt for every extra  of distilled water you will use. <figure rend="Prepare a Sea Salt Soak Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>A typical saline solution contains 0.9% salt content, similar to levels of salt in the human body. If your water has large chunks of salt left over, you need to either strain it out or add more water.</item></list></item>
<item>Pour the solution into a shallow cup or soak a clean cloth with it. Fill the shallow cup just enough to submerge the area you want to treat, such as a finger wound, or soak a clean cloth completely to dab over a larger area, such as a leg or an arm. <figure rend="Prepare a Sea Salt Soak Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Apply the soak to the affected area 2 to 3 times a day until it heals. You should expose the affected area to the soak for about 5 to 10 minutes, either by dipping the area in a shallow cup of the solution or dabbing the area with a soaked cloth. A good rule of thumb is to do it once in the morning, once around lunch, and once before you go to sleep. This helps to ensure that you break up treatment equally throughout the day. <figure rend="Prepare a Sea Salt Soak Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Saline solutions are recommended for post-tattoo treatment, to reduce the chance of infection. Dab a clean cloth soaked in the solution onto the area to keep a fresh tattoo sterile.</item>
<item>Saline solutions have also been known to help sterilize small wounds, such as piercings and minor infections on the hands, which may be easier to treat by dipping the affected area into a shallow cup.</item>
<item>You can store the excess solution at room temperature in a sealed container to use for repeat treatments or for the future. The solution should last indefinitely as long as it remains in a sealed container.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Preparing a Sea Salt Bath Soak</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Pour 453 g (1.9 cups) of fine grain sea salt into a bowl. Be sure to use fine grain sea salt or it may take a much longer time for the salt crystals to fully dissolve into the bath water when the time comes. <figure rend="Prepare a Sea Salt Soak Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Consider adding 15 to 30 drops of scented or essential oil to the sea salt. While not a required step, essential oils can make the soak feel more relaxing and comforting. Lavender and peppermint are popular oils to use for their calming effect, but feel free to use 15 to 30 drops of whichever scents are soothing to you and blend them together to your liking, if you so choose. <figure rend="Prepare a Sea Salt Soak Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can try using essential jojoba oil to add a mild anti-fungal effect to the soak, or use essential almond oil to add a skin softening effect.</item></list></item>
<item>Mix the salts and oils thoroughly then store the mix in a glass container. The salts and oils should mix together pretty easily, but don't expect much, if any, salt to dissolve into the oil — the mixture will dissolve into bath water when you decide to use the soak. It should stay good forever in a sealed glass container, which you can keep in a bathroom closet.  <figure rend="Prepare a Sea Salt Soak Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The mix will only go "bad" when outside objects, such as grass and dirt, get into the container, but otherwise should be free of mold and contaminants forever.</item></list></item>
<item>Add 120 g (1/2 cup) of the salt soak to a warm bath and let it dissolve. You should let it sit for around 10 to 20 minutes until the bathwater begins to smell like your oils and the salt has dissolved. If you decided not to use any oils, just look for the salt to have mostly dissolved before stepping into the water. <figure rend="Prepare a Sea Salt Soak Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you would like to make your soak into a foot soak, simply pour 120 g (1/2 cup) of the salt soak mix in a hot foot bath and allow it to dissolve. It may take a few minutes as there is less water for the salt to dissolve into.</item></list></item>
<item>Take a bath with the sea salt soak when you need to relax and unwind. While the saline solution is intended for medical treatment, the sea salt bath soak is used for its calming effect and its medicinal effects, especially with jojoba or almond essential oil. Stressful days, sick days, or days when you just want to unwind are perfect for whipping out the sea salt soak and making your bath a little more comforting. <figure rend="Prepare a Sea Salt Soak Step 10.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always wash your hands before handling the saline sea salt solution. The bacteria and dirt from your hands can contaminate the solution if you aren't careful, and can raise your risk of infection in your wounds.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<head>Making Medicinal Sea Salt Soak</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>9 g (1.8 tbsp) of sea salt</item>
<item> of purified water</item>
<item>Saucepan</item>
<item>Clean cloth</item>
<item>Bowl</item>
<item>Sealable container</item></list>
<head>Preparing a Sea Salt Bath Soak</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>453 g (1.9 cups) of sea salt</item>
<item>Scented or essential oil (lavender, peppermint, etc.)</item>
<item>Sealable glass jars</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
