<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc25" title="Improve Your Workout in Two Ways" shortTile="improve-workout-two" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2016-10-12" dateModified="2017-01-03" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Improve_Your_Workout_in_Two_Ways" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Improve Your Workout in Two Ways</head><p>People who are particularly new to working out or workout maybe just a few times a week should benefit from these steps. One way is to improve your mind to muscle connection. This step will improve the effectiveness of muscle gain. The other step is to contract (or vacuum) your abs while working out.This will not only help you have a slimmer belly, but also increase the strength of your core. This will help avoid potential back problems in the future.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Mind to Muscle Connection</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Warm up sets are important to any exercise. Practicing mind to muscle connection is easiest with light weight.
<list type="unordered"><item>Do light weights with 15-20 repetitions.</item>
<item>Try closing your eyes and focus on the target muscles.</item>
<item>Contract at the maximum point of contraction. For example, if doing bench press, really squeeze the chest when the weight is near the chest. When doing leg press, squeeze the quad muscle when the weight is closer to your body.</item></list></item>
<item>Do your exercise slow! Doing them slower will allow you to focus on your target muscles.
<list type="unordered"><item>Take about 4-5 seconds for each repetition.</item>
<item>Pause at the point of contraction. Pausing at the point of contraction will force your target muscle to be used.</item></list></item>
<item>Flex your target muscles in between every set. This might sound useless and uncomfortable, but this forces blood into your muscles. This in turn, pumps them even further. When the muscles are pumped, it is easier to isolate them during the exercise.
<list type="unordered"><item>Try squeezing your muscle for five seconds after you complete your set.</item>
<item>Do this twice in between every set to keep your muscles pumped.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Contracting your Abs</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Ab contraction exercise. This exercise will help you practice vacuuming.
<list type="unordered"><item>Lay on your back while bending your knees and having your knees flat against the floor.</item>
<item>Keep your arms extended along your body with palms facing down.</item>
<item>Have your lower back touch the floor as much as possible. This will raise your pelvis. Inhale.</item>
<item>Now exhale. While exhaling all the air out of your belly, pull your belly button towards your spine to achieve the contraction. Retain this position for three seconds.</item>
<item>Inhale with your belly again while keeping this contaction.</item>
<item>Repeat to achieve twenty repitions.</item></list></item>
<item>Vacuum while lifting! You want to try to contract your abs during workouts, but not as much as in step one. The ab contraction exercise is an exaggerated version of what you want to do while working out. Try something you are comfortable with. In example of this is for benchpressing:
<list type="unordered"><item>When bringing the weight down to your chest, you should be inhaling. Try contracting your abs while doing this. You don't want to do as much as with the ab contraction exercise, just enough to feel the contraction.</item>
<item>When you push the weight back up, you should be exhaling. Try pulling your belly button to your spine slightly. Again, not as much as the ab contraction exercise, but just enough to feel it.</item>
<item>Always keep your abs contracting slightly!</item></list></item>
<item>Combine mind to muscle connection and the vacuum. Once you are comfortable doing each, try doing both at the same time!</item></list>
</text>
