<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc237" title="Stash Snacks in Your Room" shortTile="stash-snacks-room" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-09-04" dateModified="2018-12-25" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Stash_Snacks_in_Your_Room" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Stash Snacks in Your Room</head><p>If you like to stay up late secretly in to your room, read this to stash food if you get hungry.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Wait until your parents aren't home, are asleep, or are in their room. Or, alternatively, you could try to sneak them up while they are awake and moving about. This is more challenging, and a bag (ex: a purse) or hoodie (with pockets) may be needed. <figure rend="Stash Snacks in Your Room Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Go to the kitchen, or wherever the snacks are. (ex: a pantry not in the kitchen.) <figure rend="Stash Snacks in Your Room Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get the snacks you want. Make sure they do not require water or the use of a microwave, stove, etc. Refrigerated snacks are fine on one condition: that you have something to put them in (like a cooler.) <figure rend="Stash Snacks in Your Room Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Sneak them up to your room. You can do this by, if the item is small enough, putting it under your armpit, and walking nonchalantly to your room. If your parents or somebody else is awake and you walk by them, don't walk funny. That might give it away. If it's a bigger item, hold it in purse or jacket, or whatever you have that's available, so that you or anyone else are able to see the item. <figure rend="Stash Snacks in Your Room Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Put them in a drawer or a place where your parents won't find them. Do not simply toss them in an innocent cardboard box. This doesn't work, and if you leave the box open, you're done for. <figure rend="Stash Snacks in Your Room Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Save them for a time you need them, like staying up late at night. If you're going to stay up for a while, don't eat it very fast. You want to make it last. <figure rend="Stash Snacks in Your Room Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Always vacuum or sweep up any crumbs or leftovers from your snacks, otherwise it will attract insects and rodents. The worst way to get caught, is by bugs. Your parents will know something's up if you have some new pet mice. <figure rend="Stash Snacks in Your Room Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure the snack is not something that'll make too much noise when you eat or open it.</item>
<item>If you can keep a bottle of water in your room, that will help if you get thirsty.</item>
<item>Soda cans are okay to keep but make sure they don't spill. Using bottles with screw-on tops (like the ones in vending machines) is recommended.</item>
<item>Keep something along the lines of a drawer, for your stash. Try stashing little bits around your room (but remember where everything is!) so that if your parents or anyone else finds out they won't find out about all of it.</item>
<item>Clear your browsing history after reading this so you don't get caught.</item>
<item>If you need to dispose of the wrappers, wrap them in a tissue and throw them away.</item>
<item>Tell your parents they pack your lunch if you still go to school.</item>
<item>If you have a hollow plastic toy, such as a pony, you can hide small snacks in there. Just twist the head off, place the food inside, and close it again. Be warned, it is often very difficult to open and close a plastic toy's head.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Throw out the wrappers/bottles in the normal trash. If your parents find a lot of potato chip bags on your floor, they'll know that you're sneaking food.</item>
<item>Try not to crunch loud if you're eating in the night if you stash.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Food non perishable to sneak and store in you room</item>
<item>Secret place in your room</item>
<item>Bottle of water (optional)</item></list>
</text>
