<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc173" title="Keep Your Family Happy" shortTile="keep-family-happy" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2017-04-10" dateModified="2017-04-11" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Keep_Your_Family_Happy" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Keep Your Family Happy</head><p>A happy family is the one without conflicts or any misunderstandings. However, keeping your family happy is not as easy as it seems. Here are a few tips you can use to create a feeling of togetherness.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Listen to them. It means listen to ALL of them. Sometimes, the elderly or the parents start neglecting a child right after having another baby or getting a new job etc. As they stay busy, they are not aware of what the ignored child might be going through. Try to spend equal time with each of them, whether they be the children or the elderly and get them to confide in you and let you know what they want or what they are thinking. Try asking them the following questions:
<list type="unordered"><item>How was your day at school/the office?</item>
<item>Talk about some abnormality in the routine like, "Why did you come home late today?"</item>
<item>Try admiring them, "I loved the cake you made that day."</item>
<item>Try telling your own day's story even if they don't ask.</item></list></item>
<item>Observer the people at home. Sometimes, people tend to keep things to themselves. It may be a child who is getting bullied at school or an elderly who is experiencing a pain in the kidney. But they do not let you know because they do not want to trouble you.
<list type="unordered"><item>Observe their facial expressions or their body language. If your child seems down or your mother walks while holding on to her left side, go up to them and ask them what is up.</item>
<item>If they tell you something is wrong, tell them you can help them but only if they want it. because sometimes children like dealing with bullies themselves instead of involving parents. So ask them what they want.</item></list></item>
<item>Never make decisions yourself. Always try to involve all the members of the family. If you tell them something after you make the decision they might get offended. So try to talk to all of them and welcome their suggestions and their votes and then come up with a solution.
<list type="unordered"><item>Its best if you do this with them at the same time rather than talking to each person separately.You can do this on the dinner table. If a mutual discussion is held this way, everyone will be satisfied.</item></list></item>
<item>Do something together. It could be anything. You can plan a picnic of the month. Or a day out at least once in a month or two. Go out together to an art gallery. Decide the place together a week before. Or any one person gets to decide each time you go and all of them have to agree. It could be a famous monument, a park or an art gallery. And you can have dinner at a restaurant.
<list type="unordered"><item>It may also involve some other activity like baking a cake together or making a nice dinner.</item></list></item>
<item>Be equal. Nobody gets to have a higher power. Sometimes, when people have a maid at their homes, they never consider her opinion because they think she is an outsider. But that is not fair. She lives with you so she is a part of your home. Try to involve her to some extent as well. She might actually give better ideas for something.</item>
<item>Encourage them. If you feel like your children might be misbehaving, or the elderly might be too irritating, try encouraging them to not do so.
<list type="unordered"><item>You can have an award for the month for a housemember who is the most well behaved or never did anything wrong that very month. And the award will be decided through votes. The one who wins can get a prize like 10 dollars or a nice dinner. This will keep them from misbehaving in an effort to fight for the prize.</item></list></item>
<item>Divide your time. Job may be an important thing and sometimes when you cannot support your family you do overtime. But this may cause you to be negligent and you might end up getting ignored and not being a part of family discussions.
<list type="unordered"><item>You can still do overtime, but do it for alternative days instead so you get to stay updated with the family matters.</item></list></item>
<item>Use technology. If someone leaves the town for work for a couple of days or months even, never leave them ignored and wait for them to come back. Instead, stay connected.
<list type="unordered"><item>You can have a video chat on a daily basis during important family meetings.</item>
<item>Call them daily by the end of the day to ask them how their day was</item></list></item></list>
</text>
