<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc197" title="Cope with Twins" shortTile="cope-twins" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-01-05" dateModified="2016-04-03" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Cope_with_Twins" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Cope with Twins</head><p>Caring for twins can be a difficult process since you have to deal with two babies at once. Although it can be a rewarding time, it also has the potential to cause stress and worries. If you're not sure how to cope with twins, this article will give you tips to help you care for them during the first few weeks as they grow up. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Take note of your twins' routine. During the first few weeks, it's best to write down the times that they wake up, demand food, need to be changed, etc. That way, you have an idea of their routines and whether you'll need to change it a bit so that they both have a similar one. Although you might believe that you can remember all this information, your mind may be too tired to grasp every detail. Therefore, it's best that you write it down before you forget. There are also apps that can help you keep track.</item>
<item>Ask for help. Caring for one baby can be a difficult, time-consuming process, but taking care of two at the same time may be overwhelming. During the first few weeks as you try to establish a routine, ask your spouse or a relative for help, which can take a huge load off of your shoulder. Make sure that the person is available to frequently assist you for a while. Be sure to communicate with each other and agree on feeding and sleeping times.</item>
<item>Establish a sleep routine. Rock them and sing them lullabies until they are nearly asleep before gently setting them down. Parents may want to keep their babies in their arms until they have completely drifted off, but since you have twins, it's best if your babies learn to fall asleep on their own. Make sure that they go to sleep at the same time. Keep them in the same room but in separate cribs (which reduces the risk of SIDS), as they'll learn to sleep well together. Be sure to place them on their backs, and consider tucking them in sleep sacks to help them feel warm and safe.</item>
<item>Feed your twins. Getting used to a feeding routine can be hard since you have two mouths to satisfy, but it's best that you start with feeding them every two or three hours. Make sure that they both eat at the same time, even if it means that you have to wake them up from naps. To make the process easier, you can invest in a twin-feeding pillow, which allows you to simultaneously nurse or bottle-feed your babies. Be sure that you position yourself and your newborns properly to prevent aches or discomfort. Although it may take a while to grow accustomed to this, it's important that you establish this routine while they're young so that you have an easier time caring for them.
<list type="unordered"><item>Encourage your babies to feed themselves. Although this may be impossible while they're so young, you can begin establishing this habit by placing their hands on the bottle as you feed them.</item>
<item>Ask your spouse or someone else for help. If you have trouble feeding the twins simultaneously, you can request for assistance so that you have one less baby to worry about. This will also give others the opportunity to bond with your children.</item></list></item>
<item>Bond with your babies. It's important to develop a connection with them while they're young, so make sure that you use every bit of time to bond with them. For instance, while you're changing a baby's diaper, take the opportunity to make her smile and talk to her in a gentle voice. Spend time cuddling with your babies, and learn how to give them massages and rubs to soothe them and prevent fussiness. Don't forget to give your spouse the chance to bond with the twins as well.  <figure rend="Playing with our legos.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take care of yourself. Caring for two babies at once can be taxing and cause large amounts of stress. To prevent physical, mental, or emotional issues from arising, it's best to care for your own needs and remember that you're important too. You should also maintain a healthy diet and get regular exercise to release pent-up frustration and get your body moving. Sleep whenever you can, even if it means taking a nap in the middle of the day.  Ask someone else - such as a relative, trusted friend, or babysitter - to care for your twins while you relax and give yourself time. If the need arises, speak with a parenting counselor or join a club that focuses on twins. That way, you can release your stress and also gain valuable tips that may ease the process of raising babies.
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't hesitate to ask for advice or assistance if it's necessary.</item>
<item>Avoid carrying out errands and tasks during your break time. It's important that you focus on yourself and remember to care for your own personal needs. Otherwise, this may lead to a breakdown and cause potential problems.</item></list></item>
<item>Treat your twins as individuals. Make sure to give them the love and care that they deserve while meeting any necessary needs. It may be easy to forget that your twins aren't a unit or the same person, so do your best to separate them in your head. Remember that they are both different and have unique personalities. Avoid punishing both of them for an action that one of them performed. Make sure that they know they should never pretend to be each other, as it will wreak havoc.  <figure rend="Silly Faces and Giggles.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
