<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc155" title="Reconnect With Your Kids" shortTile="reconnect-kids" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-06-29" dateModified="2018-10-12" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Reconnect_With_Your_Kids" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Reconnect With Your Kids</head><p>So you want to try to reconnect with your kids? This wikiHow will try to help you do just that!
[[Category:Raising Children]</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Ask them how they are. The first essential step is giving them attention. If they know they're important to you, you'll become important to them. And remember, listen to what they have to say. Make conversation, don't let them do all the talking. <figure rend="Reconnect With Your Kids Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure they aren't having to deal with any issues. If they seem down, ask them what's the matter. try to give the most helpful advice you possibly can. <figure rend="Reconnect With Your Kids Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make specific nights special. For example, 'Snack Saturday', where you give them each £3 and let them buy whatever treat they want in the store. Or a special Family Fun Night, with board games. However, if you make a big deal to start these and can't keep them going, then they'll become even more of a reason for your kids to drift away. You don't want them thinking you constantly miss their designated special day. It'll seem like you have something more important than them. If you really have to miss a week, change the day. Don't say, 'oh it'll definitely happen next week'. <figure rend="Reconnect With Your Kids Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure you have a pleasant home. When they're coming home from school, make sure they're coming to a clean home, with preparations for dinner beginning. Maybe play some music, make sure the house is warm. If you don't mind maybe a few candles. Try to make sure your home isn't a total bachelor pad. It's not good for children. <figure rend="Reconnect With Your Kids Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Share interests. This doesn't mean become immersed in your kids interests. It means show an interest in what they like, but don't copy it. And share some of yours too. Maybe say, 'oh you like that band? Funny I like one just like them' or something to that effect. <figure rend="Reconnect With Your Kids Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Calm down. If you are an angry, punishing parent, don't go overboard! Punish them if you need to, but there's never any reason to scream or shout. Your kids need to believe you're a nice person if you want to reconnect. <figure rend="Reconnect With Your Kids Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you're divorced, don't talk badly of the other parent. It doesn't put them in a bad light, it puts you in a bad light. Even if your ex is talking horribly about you, by not talking about them you seem much nicer to the kids. Not that you want them to hate their other parent. <figure rend="Reconnect With Your Kids Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure you get along with their other parent. Whether you're together or not, you're kids don't want tensions between you two. <figure rend="Reconnect With Your Kids Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Ask the other parent what you can do. If you are far from your kids, likelihood is their other parent is closer to them. Even if they hate you, they're likely to tell the truth. <figure rend="Reconnect With Your Kids Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If the other parent died, try to finish you're grieving. Maybe you became distant after your spouse died. Remember your kids have been hurt from it too, and they won't fully recover until you have.  Try to start dating again. <figure rend="Reconnect With Your Kids Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If your family complain about issues you have, fix them. Let's say they always tell you to stop smoking, or drinking. try to cut it down. It could be the reason you and your children have drifted apart. Children see it as though you are replacing them with your addiction. <figure rend="Reconnect With Your Kids Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Hopefully these tips help! Remember, be nice, interested and not to busy! Make your kids the most important part of your life! <figure rend="Reconnect With Your Kids Step 12.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Kids like organisation. If you have designated days and times, then they have definite things to look forward to.</item>
<item>Maybe you could help your kids revise. Even if you're no good at a topic, a laptop and a helper to keep focused is what a kid needs to do well.</item></list>
</text>
