<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc86" title="Reset an Echo Dot" shortTile="reset-echo-dot" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-05-23" dateModified="2019-10-19" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Reset_an_Echo_Dot" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Reset an Echo Dot</head><p>This wikiHow teaches you how to reset an Echo Dot.  You can reset your Echo Dot if your device is unresponsive, or you want to give it to someone else.  The way you reset your Echo Dot depends on if it's a first or second generation device.  If you are planning on selling an Amazon Echo, you'll need to deregister it from your Amazon  account.  After you reset your Amazon Echo, you'll need to reconnect it to your Wi-Fi.  </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Deregister an Amazon Echo on Mobile</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open the Alexa app.  It's the app that has a blue icon that says "Amazon Alexa" in white text.</item>
<item>Tap .  The menu button is the button with three horizontal lines in the upper-right corner.</item>
<item>Tap .  It's towards the bottom of the menu in the Alexa app.</item>
<item>Tap the device you want to deregister.   All connected devices are listed under the "Devices" header at the top of the Settings menu.</item>
<item>Scroll down and tap .  It's near the bottom of the device settings menu.  This displays a confirmation popup window.</item>
<item>Tap .  It's the blue button in the popup screen.  This confirms that you want to deregister your Amazon Echo device.  Your Amazon Echo device is now removed from your Amazon account.  You can now reset the Amazon Echo device.</item></list>
<head>Deregister an Amazon Echo on a Computer</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Go to <ref target="https://www.amazon.com/">https://www.amazon.com/</ref> in a web browser.  You can use any web browser on PC or Mac.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are not signed in, click "Accounts &amp; Lists" in the upper-right corner and click the yellow "Sign In" button.  Sign in with the email and password associated with your Amazon account.</item></list></item>
<item>Click .  It's in the upper-right corner of the website.  This displays a drop-down menu.</item>
<item>Click .  It's about halfway down the "Accounts &amp; Lists" drop-down menu.</item>
<item>Click the  tab.  It's the second tab at the top of the page below "Manage Your Content and Devices".  This tab displays a list of all the devices registered to your Amazon account.</item>
<item>Tap  next to the Amazon Echo.  This button is to the right of all the devices listed on your account.  Clicking this button displays a small popup window.</item>
<item>Click .  It's the blue text below the device type in the popup window.  This displays a confirmation popup window.</item>
<item>Click .  It's the yellow button in the lower-right corner of the confirmation popup menu.  This deregisters the Amazon Echo device from your Amazon account.</item></list>
<head>Reset an Amazon Echo</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Press and hold the Reset button.  The light ring turns orange and then blue. The reset button is different on first and second generation Echo Dot models.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are using a first generation Echo Dot, use a pin or a paperclip to press and hold the <hi rend="bold">Reset</hi> button on the base of the device.</item>
<item>If you are using a second generation Echo Dot, press and hold the <hi rend="bold">Microphone off</hi> and <hi rend="bold">volume down</hi> buttons at the same time and hold them for about 20 seconds.</item></list></item>
<item>Wait for the light ring to turn off and then back on.  After the light ring turns orange, the device goes into setup mode.  The device is now ready to sell.  If you still plan on using it, you will need to reconnect it to your Wi-Fi and Amazon account.</item></list>
<head>Reconnect Amazon Echo to Your Account</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open the Alexa app on your smartphone.  It's the app that has a blue icon with a white "O".
<list type="unordered"><item>If need be, sign in to the Alexa app with the email address and password associated with your Amazon account.</item></list></item>
<item>Tap .  It's in the upper-left corner of the app.</item>
<item>Tap .  This displays a list of Amazon Alexa devices and has an option to add Alexa devices.</item>
<item>Tap .  It's at the top of the list of Alexa devices on the smartphone app.</item>
<item>Press and hold the  on the Echo Dot.  Hold the action button until the light ring turns orange.  A list of Wi-Fi networks appears on the Alexa smartphone app.</item>
<item>Tap your Wi-Fi network.  Select the Wi-Fi network you want to connect the Echo Dot to.  If needed, type the password for the Wi-Fi network.</item>
<item>Tap  on the Alexa app.  A confirmation message appears in the Alexa app once the Echo Dot is connected.  The Echo Dot has been reset and reconnected to Wi-Fi.  It is now ready to use.</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
