<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc239" title="Pack Food Items Using Air Cushions" shortTile="pack-food-items-using" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-05-08" dateModified="2015-07-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Pack_Food_Items_Using_Air_Cushions" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Pack Food Items Using Air Cushions</head><p>Food and drink items such as fruits, vegetables, bottled water, or even cheese and alcohol require a special type of packaging for convenient transportation and client delivery. Many transport companies use different types of packaging for transporting items.</p>
<p>The air cushion is a bag made out of biodegradable fabric or plastic. It is designed to cover and protect a product; as well as act as box filler for products that do not use the entire space within a box. The act of box filling also prevents the product from moving inside the box.</p>
<p>When it comes to food and drink items, the air cushion can be used in a number of ways – interleaving, void fill, cross layering, corner protection, and wrapping. All these methods involve the packaging box, air cushions, and the items you wish to pack.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Interleaving</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Create a base. Interleaving allows you to pack several items in 1 box. This is particularly useful for large items like beer and champagne bottles, therefore you should insert one air cushion into the base layer of the box. <figure rend="Pack Food Items Using Air Cushions Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Place the item(s) onto the air cushion. You may find that organizing it in a particular way will help you fit more into it. Rather than stacking, insert a thin layer of items. <figure rend="Pack Food Items Using Air Cushions Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Add another air cushion, and fit it snugly within the box. <figure rend="Pack Food Items Using Air Cushions Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Add more products. Whether it be food, furniture, jewelry, you may end up with void space, therefore you can fill it by <hi rend="italic">layering</hi>. <figure rend="Pack Food Items Using Air Cushions Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take a second air cushion and cover the item(s) completely. When small items are placed in a large box, there is usually void space. The air cushion is used as a filler to fill the gap. It is useful for item like cheese tins and packets. <figure rend="Pack Food Items Using Air Cushions Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Repeat steps 3 and 4 until the box is completely full. <figure rend="Pack Food Items Using Air Cushions Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Close and secure the box with cellophane tape on it, and it’s ready for transport. <figure rend="Pack Food Items Using Air Cushions Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Cross Layering</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open the box. Open up the box and keep the flaps in a horizontal position. This will provide support when you add the air cushions. Cross layering is s quick and easy solution when you need to protect the product from all sides. This usually involves using two air cushions. <figure rend="Pack Food Items Using Air Cushions Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Place the first air cushion into the box. Take the first air cushion and place it at a diagonal angle over the flaps. <figure rend="Pack Food Items Using Air Cushions Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Add a second air cushion. Place another air cushion layer in the opposite diagonal angle. <figure rend="Pack Food Items Using Air Cushions Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Place the product. Take the product and place in the middle of the layers. Push all three items down into the box. <figure rend="Pack Food Items Using Air Cushions Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pack the box. Use the ends of the air cushion to completely cover the item and close the box. <figure rend="Pack Food Items Using Air Cushions Step 12.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Corner Protection</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Place the product. Take the product and place it into the box. Make sure that item is placed in the center of the box. Corner protection involves using air cushions to protect the corners of your product from damage. This is useful when packing large items like humidors. <figure rend="Pack Food Items Using Air Cushions Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Add the air cushions. Use two air cushions and place them in the two corners of the box. The cushions have two chambers that allow them to be bent in certain places. <figure rend="Pack Food Items Using Air Cushions Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pack the box. Once the product is completely secure and cannot move, close and pack the box. <figure rend="Pack Food Items Using Air Cushions Step 15.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Wrapping</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Lay out the cushion. Take one air cushions, open it out and lay it flat on the floor. This Method is particularly useful for fragile products that require overall protection. <figure rend="Pack Food Items Using Air Cushions Step 16.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Add the product. Take the product and place in the center of the air cushion. <figure rend="Pack Food Items Using Air Cushions Step 17.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wrap the product. Fold the four ends of the air cushion inwards to completely wrap the product. <figure rend="Pack Food Items Using Air Cushions Step 18.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Box pack the product by placing it into the product into the box. <figure rend="Pack Food Items Using Air Cushions Step 19.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
