<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc198" title="Impress Family Members" shortTile="impress-family-members" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-12-12" dateModified="2015-07-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Impress_Family_Members" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Impress Family Members</head><p>Have you ever wanted to impress your family members? Have you ever wanted to show them that you are good enough? Read on to know more!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Intelligence</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>The first and most important way to impress your family members is intelligence. Your parents always have impressions on what you will be in future; a famous businessman, an intelligent scientist or a powerful police officer. So its in your hands to show them that you can fulfill their wishes. <figure rend="TeslaMotors_HQ_PaloAlto.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Study. Make yourself busy during free time with your studies. Read and understand everything so that it will be easy for you when a pop-up quiz is there. Science, Mathematics and English are the most important subjects in the whole world as general so concentrate more on these subjects. <figure rend="POL_Books.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Participate. Get bold and ready to face some challenges. Participate in quiz, debates, spelling-B and other educational sports. Try all your best in them, prepare for it and win! Winning is what your parents and other family members want. This will help to boost your family reputation which you are indirectly impressing them. <figure rend="Quiz NM 2014.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get good grades. Getting good grades also help to impress them as now they will have the impression that you are intelligent and clever. Through this, you can easily impress them. <figure rend="Exam results.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Behavior</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Behave properly. Do not be rude to your elders and young ones. Always be polite and helping. Make an impression that you are kind not harsh or rude. <figure rend="His Holiness Jigdal Dagchen Sakya walking under a white umbrella held by his son, sangha, pilgrimage, Vulture Peak, India.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Listen to your parents. Listening to your parents helps to make them proud and impressed. Do not object what they are doing or reject their views and ideas. Be happy to whatever they give you and have for you in mind because your parents will always wish for the best for you wherever you are.</item>
<item>Deny wrong. Always be right and justice in your actions. Support the right and advise the wrong. Don't support wrong just because they are your friend or family member or your dear ones. If they need to rectify for their mistakes, tell them to do so.</item></list>
<head>Sports</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Play. Develop your body. Participate in sports and other games to show that you can do great in any thing.</item>
<item>Win. Try to win in whatever you do. If its teamwork, then make sure that you are the leading role.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You could crack some good jokes to lighten up the mood.</item>
<item>Enter in to music class, art class and other classes to increase your ability</item>
<item>Don't be too kind or your own family will think you're a creep</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't boast</item>
<item>Don't make jokes which just leave an strange silence</item>
<item>Don't be forced into anything you don't want to do</item></list>
</text>
