<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc114" title="Use a PS4 Controller on Your PC That Has Windows 7, 8, or 8.1" shortTile="use-ps-controller" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-10-08" dateModified="2015-10-25" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Use_a_PS4_Controller_on_Your_PC_That_Has_Windows_7%2C_8%2C_or_8.1" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Use a PS4 Controller on Your PC That Has Windows 7, 8, or 8.1</head>
<p>Having a tough time playing games on your PC with a mouse and keyboard? Are you more used to playing games with your PS4 controller? Or do you just not like playing games with a mouse and keyboard? While any controller other than a Microsoft controller does not work natively in a Windows environment, you can "trick" your computer into thinking your PS4 controller is an Xbox controller thus allowing you to play any game on your PC with your PS4 controller.</p>
<head>Disclaimer</head>
The software tool that we will be using to trick your PC into thinking your PS4 controller is an Xbox 360 controller is not made by, designed, or thought of by me. As the website <ref target="http://ds4windows.com/">http://ds4windows.com/</ref>  will tell you "DS4Windows was a project originally started by InhexSTER by the name of DS4 Tool. The tool was later branched off by electrobrains."  The one who currently updates and maintains the software is Jays2Kings.
<head>Warnings</head>
While downloading anything from the internet, there are always chances of you picking up a virus or malware along the way. To minimize the risks of downloading a virus onto your computer, please follow the steps as listed to the letter. Neither downloads will come with any virus/malware but a stray click on an add here or there could result in unwanted software being installed onto your machine. Download the programs needed to complete this guide at your own discretion.
<head>What you will need</head>
<p>The software and drivers that are listed here are going to be explained on how to get/ install them on your computer. What you will really need at hand is your PS4 controller, the micro USB cable, and your PC.</p>
<list type="ordered"><item>A PS4 controller</item>
<item>A micro USB cable ( the cable that came with your controller will do just fine )</item>
<item>A PC</item>
<item>Microsoft 360 Driver ( already installed on Windows 7 SP1 and higher or if you've used a 360 controller before)</item>
<item>DS4 Driver (Downloaded &amp; Installed with DS4Windows)</item>
<item>Microsoft .NET 4.5 or higher (needed to unzip the driver and for macros to work properly)</item></list>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Downloading and Installing drivers and software</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>We will be downloading the necessary Xbox 360 controller drivers. We will be downloading the drivers forWindows 7 (64-bit only). This will be used for people that have Windows 7, 8, or 8.1 operating systems.
<list type="unordered"><item>Open this link in a new tab <ref target="http://www.microsoft.com/hardware/en-us/d/xbox-360-controller-for-windows">http://www.microsoft.com/hardware/en-us/d/xbox-360-controller-for-windows</ref></item>
<item>Select “Windows 7 (64-bit only)”. After selecting this operating system, a download button will appear on the web page.</item>
<item>Click on the download button</item></list></item></list>
<list type="ordered"><item>We will now install the newly downloaded drivers onto your computer through the installation wizard that comes with it.
<list type="unordered"><item>Click on the newly downloaded exe. File and you will be taken through the installation wizard</item>
<item>Check the “I accept this agreement” box and hit next. The files take less than 30 seconds to install. You will now be shown a screen that says “Installation complete”</item>
<item>Click the finish button when it appears</item></list></item>
<item>We will now download the tool that we will use to mimic an Xbox controller to use our PS4 Controller
<list type="unordered"><item>Open this link in a new tab <ref target="http://ds4windows.com/">http://ds4windows.com/</ref> You will be led to a webpage that immediately has a button that says “Download Now”</item>
<item>Click the “Download Now” button</item></list></item></list>
<list type="ordered"><item>We will install the DS4Tool that allows us to use the PS4 as an Xbox 360 controller.
<list type="unordered"><item>Click on the file that was downloaded below (or find the file in your PC under Downloads and click on it there) to begin installation</item></list></item></list>
<list type="ordered"><item><list type="unordered"><item>Select an area where you can easily find the DS4Tool files later. The default location that the software selects is a good place to choose if you are indifferent as to where it will be located.</item>
<item>Check the “I agree to the License terms and conditions” box. The install button will now be able to be selected</item>
<item>Click the install button. A window will now appear asking if you “Would like to install this device software?”</item>
<item>Click the install button. The program will take a bit to install</item>
<item>Click the finish button as it appears on the screen</item></list></item></list>
<head>Opening your DS4Tool Program</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>We will now open DS4Tool program that allows us to use our PS4 controller as a Xbox controller. Locate the files titled “DS4Windows” where you installed them from the previous steps.
<list type="unordered"><item>Open the folder named “DS4Windows”</item>
<item>Double click on the application file named “DS4Windows”</item>
<item>Select “run”</item>
<item>Select to install the files on “app data”. Your DS4Tool will now launch. Go back to the “DS4Windows” folder.</item>
<item>Double click the application file “DS4 Updater”. This will give you the most up to date version of the DS4Tool</item></list></item></list>
<head>Using your DS4Tool Program</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>We will now connect your controller to the PC. There are some neat features you can play with here for the PS4 controller.</item></list>
<p>The program itself is abundant with settings for the color of the light of the PS4 controller as well as profile you would like to set for the controller based on what games you play. A profile with more sensitivity on a push of the joystick might be set for first person shooter games for example.</p>
<p>Connect the PS4 Controller with the micro USB cable and the PC with the other end of the cable. You should now see that the PS4 controller is connected to your PC and no other settings need to be changed to make it work as an Xbox controller. Congratulations!!!!</p>
</text>
