<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc148" title="Cope With Your Mother Being a Prostitute" shortTile="cope-mother-being" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-07-01" dateModified="2018-10-12" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Cope_With_Your_Mother_Being_a_Prostitute" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Cope With Your Mother Being a Prostitute</head><p>To cope with a thing such as this, is emotionally stressing. It is a big thing to worry about, and if so - you have the right to get mad. But, if the community is severely distrustful, and it's hard to find a job. The only option is to sell your body, for instance, a mother wants her children to live, to experience life. But not live her life how it turned out to be, and your emotions will be twisted, confusing, righteously angry, but you should know that love is needed. </p>
<p>She would want you to have a home over your head, she wouldn't want you to be homeless and having to resort to what she did, so she's taking that risk. But, it depends if she was living on her own and decided to change her life, spice it up with chances. You found out, but it is her life, your have your own social problems. Concerning your mother, it is a prominent thing to address.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Portrayal. You have to understand that her view is different from yours, that she thinks this is the best way to get support, and money, or for a different life to experience instead of the usual routines. There are times where men are curious about being gay, and women curious about the feelings of physical attraction towards other women. Being a prostitute does mean selling your body for release, but it's also for money. <figure rend="Cope With Your Mother Being a Prostitute Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Think about it.  You must have thought: 'Why?' A mother to sell her body for money or what-else, is something to concern yourself over. Even if you don't want to, even if you have a grudge, you still have to ask her that question yourself. <figure rend="Cope With Your Mother Being a Prostitute Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Know that you were once her daughter/or son. She raised you if she was single. That even if she gave you the 'cold shoulder', you wouldn't be in this world if it weren't for your mother. Never be afraid, don't run, it doesn't solve any problems; it only cause that gap to expand more and deepen those scars. <figure rend="Cope With Your Mother Being a Prostitute Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have no regrets on the table.  This is an idiomatic expression meaning that you shouldn't hold a grudge too long, or your life will be sad, knowing you didn't give out no chances when you should have. That your cold relationship with your mother diminished slowly, leaving you alone without a mother to be by your side, to comfort you, or at least, live with you. <figure rend="Cope With Your Mother Being a Prostitute Step 4.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Dealing with a situation like this will take its toll on you, and her if she just want to explain her behavior. Give her a chance.</item>
<item>Think over what you are going to do: run away or confront your mother about why she changed.</item>
<item>Scars will remain, but don't always ignore what your heart feels.</item>
<item>Give it time to cope with what changed so suddenly in your life.</item>
<item>Write a letter of your feelings, send it to her when you felt that you were insecure. The feelings, or thoughts you wrote should be perceived, and thus, your answer will come.</item>
<item>Seek professional help on this matter.Dealing with this,you need to sit face to face with a professional,it will be more personal,they will be able to see your emotions and help you as well.</item></list>
</text>
