<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc139" title="Know When You Need To Further Your Education" shortTile="know-need-further" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-03-23" dateModified="2019-02-17" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Know_When_You_Need_To_Further_Your_Education" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Know When You Need To Further Your Education</head><p>Whether you are looking for a specific job that requires specialty skills or you are looking to build upon your current work skills, furthering your education will help you in your endeavor. But in a slow economy, how do you know when your need to further your education so that your investment will pay off? There are steps that you should take into account if you're considering going back to school to further your education.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Opt to further your education if you feel that you can increase your salary by doing so. Those with degrees can expect to earn higher salaries, and the level of the degree is a determining factor as to how much. If you want to make more money, then you have to have something to offer in return. Check with your company regarding reimbursement programs that may assist you in your ongoing education efforts. <figure rend="Come up With a Thesis Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Evaluate your current profession, and determine whether you need a change. Maybe you are looking for more of a challenge, or maybe you are not happy with the politics in your current work situation. Whatever the reason, your need to continue your schooling may be a necessity, even if you are looking for a similar position but at a different company. Company requirements may have evolved since you last looked for a job, and positions that may not have required a degree, or certain qualifications, in the past, may be asking for them now. Even the job that you are in today may have higher expectations should you apply for the position today. <figure rend="Ask Survey Questions Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Become more marketable to future employers by furthering your education and enhancing your value. By arming yourself with newer skills and making yourself more valuable, you are more likely to be eligible for a promotion. If this is your intention, then opt to enhance your qualifications and gain more knowledge so that you are the better choice when the time comes to promote within your company. <figure rend="Know When You Need To Further Your Education Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Save your job by building upon your existing knowledge and sharpening your current skills. In a fragile economy, nobody's job is safe. If there are concerns at your company about lay offs, then you should enhance your skills so that you are more of a valuable asset to your employers and less likely to lose your position there.  Even if your investment in such education does not save your current job, it should make you more marketable in a job search. <figure rend="Become a Publicist Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Stay abreast of the latest and greatest in your industry. Your job may be ever evolving, as is technology, and so you should always be ahead of the game. Understanding newer technology will set you apart from your peers who may prefer to remain stagnant in their knowledge base. <figure rend="Analyse Literature in an Essay Step 11.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
