<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc243" title="Make Whipple Cream" shortTile="make-whipple-cream" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-12-09" dateModified="2019-10-23" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make_Whipple_Cream" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make Whipple Cream</head><p>Whipple cream is a type of clay that you use to make toy and decorative baked goods. Whipple cream is meant to resemble whipped cream and is not edible. All you need to make whipple cream is some art clay, glue, and supplies like a spray bottle and ruler. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Preparing the Clay</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Break your clay into small pieces and place them in the bag. In order to get your clay to a mixable consistency, you should break it into small pieces. Take out a large chunk of art clay and break it apart. Place the pieces in your plastic bag. <figure rend="Make Whipple Cream Step 1 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>There is no set amount of art clay to use. Take out as much as you need for your whipple cream. More art clay will make more cream.</item>
<item>If your clay is very thick or dry, it can help to work your clay with your fingers to soften it before breaking it into pieces.</item></list></item>
<item>Add water in small amounts until you reach the right consistency. Put some tap water in your spritzer bottle. Spray in a small amount to start. For example, spritz the water 10 times. Then, seal your bag, leaving a small amount of air in the bag, and work the clay with your fingers through the bag. Keep adding small amounts of water at a time until you reach the right consistency. <figure rend="Make Whipple Cream Step 2 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The consistency should be similar to marshmallow fluff. If you've never had marshmallow fluff, this feels like slightly hardened whipped cream.</item></list></item>
<item>Push the clay to one side of the bag. Seal the bag and use your fingers to push the clay through the bag. You want all your clay concentrated in one side of the bag. Once the clay is in one side of the bag, cut a hole in the corner where the clay sits. <figure rend="Make Whipple Cream Step 3 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Mixing in the Other Ingredients</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Add glue to soften the whipple cream. Open the bag again and pour in some school glue. As with the water, add a small amount at first and then more as necessary. You do not want the whipple cream to be too runny, but the glue should loosen it slightly. Add enough glue that the whipple cream is easily squeezed out of the bag. <figure rend="Make Whipple Cream Step 4 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Pinch the open side of the bag closed while you do this to keep glue from running out of the bag.</item></list></item>
<item>Add food coloring if you want a specific color. You can add a small bit of food coloring the  the whipple cream. Then, work the cream together using your fingers until the color is dispersed throughout. If you want a darker color after adding your initial coloring, add a bit more food coloring. <figure rend="Make Whipple Cream Step 5 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Like the other ingredients, there is no set amount to add. You can add a small amount at first and add more if the color is too light.</item></list></item>
<item>Place the bag in a pastry bag. Insert the nozzle into the pastry bag by putting it in the bag and pushing it through the opening in the corner. Then, put your plastic bag with the whipple cream in the pastry bag. Push the corner of the plastic bag with the opening into the nozzle in the pastry bag. <figure rend="Make Whipple Cream Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Avoiding Common Mistakes</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Do not substitute different types of glue. Things like superglue, industrial glue, or rubber cement should not be used to make whipple cream. You should only use school glue, such as Elmer's glue, as this has the right consistency for whipple cream. <figure rend="Make Whipple Cream Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Store the whipple cream carefully. Remove the whipple cream from the pastry bag when you're done using it. Twist the end of the plastic bag, removing most of the air, and use a rubber band to secure it in place. You can store your whipple cream in a cabinet until you want to use it again. <figure rend="Make Whipple Cream Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If your whipple cream dries out between uses, add more water. It should last awhile as long as you keep adding water, but will dry out in a few months. How long whipple cream lasts depends on how often you use it and the temperature of your home.</item></list></item>
<item>Make sure children know not to eat the cream. If you're using whipple cream for crafts with young children, make sure to make it clear the cream is not to be eaten. Children may mistake whipple cream for food, but it does not contain edible ingredients. Tell children something like, "I know the whipple cream looks like food, but it's bad for you to eat. Just use it for decoration." <figure rend="Make Whipple Cream Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If glue isn't providing the right consistency, use corn starch to make your cream more stable and thicker. The thicker the cream, the better details you can get.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be careful when mixing in the food coloring. Try wearing gloves because it can sometimes stain your hands and it will take quite long to really get the stain off.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Art clay</item>
<item>Spray bottle</item>
<item>Plastic bag</item>
<item>School glue</item>
<item>Ruler</item>
<item>Pastry bag</item></list>
</text>
