<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc14" title="Measure Hockey Gloves" shortTile="measure-hockey-gloves" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-01-29" dateModified="2019-04-20" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Measure_Hockey_Gloves" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Measure Hockey Gloves</head><p>If you want to play hockey, you're definitely going to need well-fitting gloves. You can easily find the right size gloves by measuring your arm from your elbow to the base of your middle finger. Then, try on a few different pairs and choose the ones that are most comfortable.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Taking Your Measurements</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Bend your arm at the elbow. The measurement for a glove is based on the distance from the crook, or crease, of your elbow to your middle finger. Bend your elbow slightly. <figure rend="Measure Hockey Gloves Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Measure from the bend in your elbow to the base of your middle finger. Place the end of a soft measuring tape where the crease in your elbow begins. Then measure along the underside of your forearm, stopping at the base of your middle finger. <figure rend="Measure Hockey Gloves Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Round to the nearest inch to find your size. Hockey gloves are sized according to whole inches. Once you have your measurement, you'll have to round to the nearest inch. So if your measurement has less than  over a whole inch, round down. If it has more than  over a whole inch, round up. That measurement in inches is your glove size. <figure rend="Measure Hockey Gloves Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, if your measurement is , round up to .</item>
<item>If your measurement is , you would round down to .</item></list></item></list>
<head>Trying on Gloves to Choose Your Fit</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Choose youth, junior, or adult size gloves. Hockey gloves are classified into different categories according to size. Make sure you're checking the size and the classification as you choose gloves. <figure rend="Measure Hockey Gloves Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Youth hockey glove sizes are between  and .</item>
<item>Junior hockey glove sizes are between  and .</item>
<item>Adult sizes are anything over .</item></list></item>
<item>Try both loose and tight-fitting gloves. Depending on the brand of glove, some will fit more loosely—a more traditional fit—and others will be a little tighter. Once you know your size, try on gloves that fit both ways and see which feels more comfortable to you. <figure rend="Measure Hockey Gloves Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Bauer, Easton, CCM, and Reebok all have snug or mid-fit gloves.</item>
<item>Sherwood, Easton Pro, and Eagle all have looser-fitting gloves.</item></list></item>
<item>Go for short cuffs if you want increased mobility. Short cuffs will leave part of your forearm exposed, but will also allow you more mobility while you play. Try the gloves on and flex your wrist back and forth to test the fit. <figure rend="Measure Hockey Gloves Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you choose short cuffs, consider getting wrist guards to give your full arm the protection it needs.</item></list></item>
<item>Opt for long cuffs for more protection. Regular cuffs will cover more, but limit your mobility. If you're playing in a school or professional league, regular cuffs will protect you better. <figure rend="Measure Hockey Gloves Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get gloves with foam padding if you're on a budget. Most entry-level gloves have just a thin layer of foam padding to protect your hands. If you're on a budget or just beginning to play, these gloves are a great choice. <figure rend="Measure Hockey Gloves Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Choose mid or high-range gloves for extra protection. Mid-range gloves usually have plastic inserts in addition to the padding. The plastic offers extra protection to the most vulnerable parts of your hand — especially your fingers. All hockey gloves come with protective padding. However, gloves with more padding tend to be more expensive. <figure rend="Measure Hockey Gloves Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you're in a serious league consider getting gloves with a little extra padding.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Testing the Fit</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Make sure there's enough space in your fingertips. Once your gloves are on, you should have about  of space between the tips of your fingers and the tips of your gloves. If your fingers butt up against the tips of your gloves, they're too small. <figure rend="Measure Hockey Gloves Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Check the alignment of your knuckles. Your gloves will have breaks in the fingers, allowing you to curl your hands around your stick. In a good-fitting glove, your knuckles should roughly line up with those breaks, making it easy to move and curl your hand. <figure rend="Measure Hockey Gloves Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make a fist to test the stretch of the material. When you make a fist in your glove, the material connecting the palm of your glove to the fingertips shouldn't stretch too far. You'll feel some give, but the material shouldn't become taught against your palm. <figure rend="Measure Hockey Gloves Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Line up the wrist break with the underside of your wrist. Regardless of the length of the cuffs, the wrist break should line up with the underside of your wrist. The wrist break is where the palm of the glove ends and the cuff begins — there should be a line of stitching there. <figure rend="Measure Hockey Gloves Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Spend some time shooting and stick handling to test your gloves. Once you're fairly certain you've got gloves that fit correctly, test them out a little bit. Wear them to shoot a few goals and handle your stick in standard drills. If they feel uncomfortable at all, exchange them. <figure rend="Measure Hockey Gloves Step 14.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Before you buy the gloves, check with the seller about their return policy. If the gloves can't be returned, bring your stick to the store and test them out before you buy them.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you're unsure about the fit of your gloves, talk to a salesperson where you're buying the gloves. They can help you find gloves that fit.</item></list>
</text>
