<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc20" title="Kick a High Ball" shortTile="kick-high-ball" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2017-05-02" dateModified="2017-05-02" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Kick_a_High_Ball" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Kick a High Ball</head><p>Hello! And today, I'm going to tell you the two important steps of kicking a high ball! And I am going to use my own words. Otherwise I won't steal other articles, or maybe something I wrote just seems so similar to another article you just read. So enjoy!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Practicing Your Position Of High Kicks</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>KNOW WHERE YOU ARE GOING TO KICK. This explains to yourself which direction you want to kick at. left, of right, or center. Maybe even somewhere high. If you are kicking to the right side, you are walking back to the right of the soccer ball. It would mean you are left footed
<list type="unordered"><item>Know which foot you are comfortable or born with to kick. A bunch of people are right footed. So they might have a better chance of kick the ball the your left side of the goal.</item></list></item>
<item>INSIDE KICK OR STRAIGHT KICK. Most people may feel comfortable with the inside kick, which is kicking with their foot, for example, if you were right footed, you would use your foot to your hip to twist your body and kick the ball to the left of the goal. Opposite with left footers. Kicking it straight doesn't involve much with your body. You're just kicking it straight. The only force you are using is the foot, which kicks the ball, and legs, which support the use of a high kick. This also happens with the inside kick.</item>
<item>TAKE SOME STEPS BACK. Always, professional players sometimes take 2-3 steps back to use power into kicking the ball. You know if you stay there and kick it, it doesn't involve to much power, and the ball will to high just like a pass above a player. But be warned, taking too much steps 6-9 won't change anything. Seriously, do a 2-3 step kick and a 6-9 step kick. No difference because you can't generate TOO much power.</item>
<item>MAKE SURE YOUR FOOT IS INSIDE THE BALL. when you put your foot inside the ball, it will make you do the high kick. Kicking with your toes will not only make the ball go straight on the ground, it could make your toes hurt in pain for a couple of seconds. When you combine the inside foot and power can result to a high kick. Kick the ball with your foot under the ball and lift your leg, and foot up. With the power. It matters how high the ball is kicked. If really high, lift your foot and leg high, middle, kick the ball with the foot and leg to kick the middle.</item>
<item>RUNNING UP TO THE BALL. When you run, you usually want to be in a sprinting position so the foot can gain power. Feet kicked up high to gain power. Usually medium steps, then spread your feet wider to get more power to kick the ball ASAP.</item></list>
<head>Kicking The Ball</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>KICKING CORRECTLY. When you are high kicking a ball, there is a correct position to kick it. Too close to your top foot will to a high kick to nowhere. If you don't kick correctly, you foot will get hurt in big pain. Below your toes is the best place to kick a ball.</item>
<item>I WILL CONTINUE EDITING SOON OR LATER</item></list>
</text>
