<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc62" title="Find Creative Commons Images" shortTile="find-creative-commons" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2019-07-27" dateModified="2019-09-14" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Find_Creative_Commons_Images" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Find Creative Commons Images</head><p>Whether if you are looking for free images to use in a PowerPoint or if you are seeking to transfer photos to Wikimedia Commons, Creative Commons images are free and convenient to use, provided that you follow the license terms.  This wikiHow will show you how to find CC images using Bing or Google, as well as the Creative Commons search engine.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>On Bing</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open Bing Image search.  To do so, navigate to the following URL:  <ref target="https://images.bing.com/">https://images.bing.com/</ref>.</item>
<item>Type in a keyword for the image you are looking for in the search box.  For example, if you are looking for images of cars, type .  Then press the search button.</item>
<item>Choose the filter button.  This button has an upside down funnel.  This will give you tools to filter the images.</item>
<item>Choose "License".  This will open a drop down showing the different licenses.</item>
<item>Choose a license below "All Creative Commons".  These licenses are all free.  Choosing "All" will also load copyrighted images.</item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Copy_and_Paste">Copy and paste</ref> the desired image.  To make the image larger, click on it.  Then you can copy the image to your clipboard.</item></list>
<head>On Google</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open Google Image search.  To do so, navigate to the following URL:  <ref target="https://images.google.com/">https://images.google.com/</ref>.</item>
<item>Type in a keyword for the image you are looking for in the search box.  For example, if you are looking for images of cars, type .  Then press the search button.</item>
<item>Choose "Tools".  This will give you tools to filter the images.</item>
<item>Choose "Usage rights".  This will open a drop down showing different types of licenses.</item>
<item>Choose a license type.  These licenses are all free.  Choosing "Not filtered by license" will also load copyrighted images.</item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Copy_and_Paste">Copy and paste</ref> the desired image.  To make the image larger, click on it.  Then you can copy the image to your clipboard.</item></list>
<head>Using Creative Commons Search</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Go to <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/">https://creativecommons.org/</ref>.  This site is the official site for the CC licenses.</item>
<item>Choose "Search for CC Images".  This will open up an image search that only searches CC images.</item>
<item>Determine the license type.  You can search for images that can be used commercially or modify.</item>
<item>Type in a keyword for the image you are looking for in the search box.  For example, if you are looking for images of cars, type .  Then press the search button.</item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Copy_and_Paste">Copy and paste</ref> the desired image.  To make the image larger, click on it.  Then you can copy the image to your clipboard.</item></list>
<head>Knowing the Restrictions of CC Licenses</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Know that not all CC images are actually CC licensed.  Some uploaders steal and make a false CC claim.  These images are not free to use, even if the uploader alleges a CC license.
<list type="unordered"><item>To be sure of this, you may want to perform an image search using Bing's or Google's image search.  Drag an image into the search box to find matches.  If there are more than two identical matches, and one of them is not licensed CC, then it is likely that the image was stolen.</item></list></item>
<item>Note that you must provide attribution for all BY licenses.  Any license which has short code "BY" (attribution) means that attribution is required.  This could be a plain URL along with details about who the author is.</item>
<item>Be aware that you cannot modify the license for copies of works.  Any license which has short code "SA" (share alike) means that you may copy and redistribute the image without permission.  However, to change the license, you need to get permission from the original copyright holder.</item>
<item>Be careful when using certain CC images commercially.  If you use a noncommercial "NC" image commercially, then you are breaking the terms of the license, and could get in legal trouble for copyright infringement.</item>
<item>Know that some images cannot be modified.  Any license with code "ND" (no derivatives) cannot be modified without permission from the copyright holder.</item></list>
<head>List of Creative Commons Licenses</head>
License NameLicense CodeLicense Summary
AttributionCC BYRedistribution and adaptation is allowed as long as attribution is provided.
Attribution ShareAlikeCC BY-SAIn addition to attribution, the license terms cannot be modified without permission.
Attribution-NoDerivsCC BY-NDIn addition to attribution, the image cannot be modified.
Attribution-NonCommercialCC BY-NCIn addition to attribution, the image cannot be used commercially.
Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlikeCC BY-NC-SACombination of CC BY-NC and CC BY-SA.  The image can be used noncommercially and the license terms cannot be modified without permission.
Attribution-NonCommerical-NoDerivsCC BY-NC-NDCombination of CC BY-NC and CC BY-ND.  The image can be used noncommercially and there can be no derivative works.
No Rights ReservedCC0Public domain.  The copyrights have been waived by the copyright holder and the image may be used without any restrictions.
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Creative Commons images may still be subject to protections, including trademark and personality rights.</item></list>
</text>
