<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc19" title="Always Make Your Layups in Basketball" shortTile="always-make-layups" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2013-06-14" dateModified="2019-06-19" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Always_Make_Your_Layups_in_Basketball" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Always Make Your Layups in Basketball</head><p>Layups can be pretty hard to pull off, but if you work on your technique of laying the ball up to the sweet spot of the backboard, you'll slowly improve your performance. Making your layups is not about being fancy, rather, its about practice and skill. It’s about setting goals and being confident. Don't give up, commit plenty of time to practicing on your own and with others, and soon enough your technique will improve, your skill level will rise, and you'll be making your layups regularly.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Shooting a Layup</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Consider the underhand layup. You lay the ball with your hand under it. The ball leaves your hand gently and it causes a nice and smooth touch on the backboard. This is useful if you are driving your way towards the basket and are unable to slow down and take the time to aim. <figure rend="Always Make Your Layups in Basketball Step 1 Version 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use the overhand layup, if you prefer. The overhand layup is a great alternative to the underhand layup. You hold the ball on top of it as if you will be dunking, it produces more power to touch the backboard roughly. It is useful when you are on the low post. <figure rend="Always Make Your Layups in Basketball Step 2 Version 4.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Run into the shot, if you're using an underhand layup. Make sure you’re running into the shot. This is the key to the underhand layup, as during the game you’ll be dodging other players and running toward the basket. Don’t run too fast. When you’re practicing take it easy and try to perfect your skill. <figure rend="Always Make Your Layups in Basketball Step 3 Version 4.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Perform a one foot layup, if appropriate. A one foot layup is what most people commonly do. It’s used when you’re moving toward the basket from far away with the ball, or when you’re moving toward the basket and you expect someone to throw you the ball to take a shot. <figure rend="Always Make Your Layups in Basketball Step 4 Version 3.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Run toward the basket.</item>
<item>Once you’re near, jump off one of your feet up toward the basket. You’ll probably jump with one foot (the left) and shoot with the other hand (the right).</item>
<item>Practice this until you’re comfortable running toward the basket and jumping with one foot.</item></list></item>
<item>Consider a two foot layup. Sometimes it’s more appropriate to do a two foot layup. This is often when you’re positioned near the basket and someone passes the ball to you. When doing this layup, you’ll have to be prepared to catch a ball quickly and to shoot at a moment’s notice. <figure rend="Always Make Your Layups in Basketball Step 5 Version 3.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be aware, the ball could come from a teammate at any moment.</item>
<item>Be ready to jump and aim the second you get the ball.</item>
<item>Don’t let distractions or nervousness break your concentration. </item></list></item>
<item>Aim and shoot the ball gently at the "sweet spot.” After you’re positioned and have the ball, aim and shoot for the sweet spot. The sweet spot is the two corners of the square on the backboard which sits just above the basket. Laying the ball on this spot will assure you to make the shot. <figure rend="Always Make Your Layups in Basketball Step 6 Version 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you’re tall enough, you won’t have to aim for the sweet spot and can just shoot the ball directly into the basket.</item>
<item>If you’re younger or just starting out, try to hit the sweet spot.</item>
<item>Don’t shoot the ball with too much force, as it’ll probably bounce off and won’t go into the basket.</item>
<item>Feel free to experiment without aiming for the sweet spot, if you are confident.</item>
<item>Watch others who are more experienced shoot the ball and emulate their technique.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Practicing Your Layups</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Try layups on your own, without a ball. Before you hit the court with a ball and with other players, make sure to try doing your layups without a ball. Practice your running and jumping technique until you feel comfortable with it. This should help you build your own technique. <figure rend="Always Make Your Layups in Basketball Step 7 Version 4.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Practice your layups on your own, with a ball. Practice makes perfect, at least most of the time. When it comes to layups, this is true, too. Make sure to practice your layups with a ball on your own as much as you can. <figure rend="Always Make Your Layups in Basketball Step 8 Version 4.360p.mp4"></figure></item>
<item>Add variation to your practice. Now that you’ve practiced a bit, add some variations to your approach. Variations will simulate the many situations you might find yourself in during an actual game. Try as many as possible, as you'll never really know what to expect in the heat of the moment. <figure rend="Always Make Your Layups in Basketball Step 9 Version 4.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Practice coming at the basket from different angles.</item>
<item>Practice coming at the basket from different speeds.</item>
<item>Use cones or other obstacles on the court to simulate opposing players who will try to contest your layup.</item></list></item>
<item>Get some good competition to practice, before you play a full game. When you’re practicing your layups, you need to make sure you’ve got some pretty solid competition who is going to contest your layups. Find some friends who are pretty good on the court, and practice with them. Remember, though, you need to play against people who are as good as or better than you in order to improve your skill. <figure rend="Always Make Your Layups in Basketball Step 10 Version 4.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Play full games and go out of your way to practice your layups against a skillful opponent.</item>
<item>Ask skilled friends to let you practice layups against them.</item>
<item>Realize that skillful competition is key.</item></list></item>
<item>Jump into a game and try your layup. Now that you’ve perfected your layups and practiced, find some friends and play a game. Take it easy, though. Try to find a few friends who want to play a low-stress game. This’ll be the best way for you to test your skills without the stress of a normal match. Don’t worry if you miss some layups, that’s part of learning. <figure rend="Always Make Your Layups in Basketball Step 11 Version 3.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Keep practicing on your own after the game.</item>
<item>Keep practicing with friends.</item>
<item>Keep finding games to play in order to perfect your skills.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't do fancy tricks. Doing tricks won't just get your coach angry but also you'll have a hard time getting the ball in.</item>
<item>Once you’ve mastered the one and two foot layup, move on and try to master the jump stop and reverse layup.</item></list>
</text>
