<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc300" title="Start a Hobby" shortTile="start-hobby" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-05-23" dateModified="2018-10-12" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Start_a_Hobby" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Start a Hobby</head><p>Have you been wanting to start a new hobby for a while? Have you been in awe at what some people have made, or done as a result of their hobby? Starting one can often be hard, take a lot of work, and can be expensive. Use these steps to get you started.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Start saving. Before you even think about what you want to do, start saving up your money. If you start a hobby that is expensive, and are already halfway to your cash goal, things get that much easier. Make sure once you've paid for your hobby's cost don't stop saving because you might want to make purchases to expand your hobby.  <figure rend="Start a Hobby Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Figure out what you want to do.Think what you really want to do, research about your interest online. Try to get yourself out there, go to your local workshop, talk with other hobbyist or just try new things. <figure rend="Start a Hobby Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make the decision to proceed. Now that you know what you want to do, ask yourself, "Am I ready to spend a lot of time on this, a lot of money, and do I enjoy what I am about to do." If the answer is no to any of these questions, then find something else to do. Dont waste your time trying everything. Do it only if you want to.  <figure rend="Start a Hobby Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Plan, draft down ideas, think about it in bed at night, talk to your friends to ideas, and research ideas on the Internet. <figure rend="Start a Hobby Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Buy any equipment you need and, if your hobby requires it, set up dedicated space just for your hobby. <figure rend="Start a Hobby Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Read the instruction manual.  This may sound like a no-brainer, but not a lot of people do it. Read the instruction manual! Or at least the safety warnings. You may learn something that you would never otherwise know. <figure rend="Start a Hobby Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Start your hobby! And keep dedicated to it, try to allocate X amount of time every day, or week or month to spend on it. <figure rend="Start a Hobby Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Start small. If your hobby is collecting stamps don't start by buying expensive stamps. Your new to the field. Try gathering as much information as you can and start small.</item>
<item>Never give up, you will run into issues, but you will never get better at your hobby if you  don't try to overcome them. <figure rend="Start a Hobby Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>When you finish your first project, show off! Brag about it and make sure the world sees it! <figure rend="Start a Hobby Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Start another project, and enjoy doing what you now do best! <figure rend="Start a Hobby Step 10.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Take constructive criticism, your work will only get better that way! </item>
<item>If your hobby is photography, or art, try publishing your work online.</item>
<item>Make sure you actually like doing it,  don't just do it because your friends are doing it..</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If your hobby has anything to do with woodwork, or soldering etc., make sure to have the proper safety gear.</item>
<item>Don't just go trying everything because everything may seem fun at first but soon you'll lose interest if you don't really have a passion for it. Use your time and resources well.</item></list>
</text>
