<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc187" title="Help Your Family to Change by Your Example" shortTile="help-family-change" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-06-26" dateModified="2017-07-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Help_Your_Family_to_Change_by_Your_Example" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Help Your Family to Change by Your Example</head><p>Sometimes when people start falling apart in your family for some reason or the other and you cannot bear it anymore, maybe it is time for you to set forth some positive examples and change your family.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be stable before you try to initiate changes in others. In stressful situations, to be mentally stable might sound like impossible, but it is not very difficult. Just a simple reminder about a few things can do the trick!</item>
<item>Control your temper. No matter how tempting the situations might be for you to get up and shout back, control yourself! Close your eyes and take deep breaths. Remind yourself that the one who is angry is in more pain and they need love and affection at this time to calm down. If you react with equal fury, the hatred will build up. React with an equal amount of love and peace and you will see that the other person's temper fade off.</item>
<item>Remind yourself to be not angry. Often, you can be used to become upset or hurt or furious about small things in our lives that it becomes difficult at times to forget anger. Put up an hourly reminder on your phone, congratulating yourself for having controlled your temper for 60 minutes. This will boost your confidence in yourself and your ability to control anger. If you have made an unnecessary comment while at home, you will be reminded of it within an hour! And there are many chances that you won't repeat the same mistake!</item>
<item>Smile at the people you love. It might look odd at first, but gradually everyone will start noticing and they may also smile back in return. Smiling would not only make you feel better but also others around you.</item>
<item>Compliment your family members whenever they deserve it. Also, greet them when they are home or leaving for work. Make it a habit. Avoid watching negative news or movie when everyone is together, this will help in spreading the positivity you're trying to bring home for all. Sooner or later, your family will notice the changes happening around and will gracefully not only acknowledge them but also join you in it. Be patient with everyone and everything. A family which stands together can face any challenge and so it's always worth taking some efforts for our families if they are falling apart.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't hesitate to apologize if you've reacted in a wrong way about something. There is no harm in accepting your mistake.</item>
<item>You will have to follow what you want your family to follow. Try and inculcate good habits in yourself.</item>
<item>Watch your food too! Healthy food has been scientifically proven for bringing mental stability and peace. So good luck!</item></list>
</text>
