<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc313" title="Choose the Right Laminate Surface" shortTile="choose-right-laminate" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-03-23" dateModified="2019-09-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Choose_the_Right_Laminate_Surface" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Choose the Right Laminate Surface</head><p>Regardless of whether you are an architect looking to design a new building or someone who just wants to replace their kitchen worktop, you will have heard about the wonders of laminate. From commercial buildings to residential homes, these wonderful surface solutions have the ability to save you money, whilst providing thousands of different styles to choose from. If you are looking to use laminate sheets, there are many things to consider. This guide will walk you through all the necessary steps, to ensure you choose the right one for you.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Picking the Colour</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Figure out where to start. There are so many different colours to choose from that it's crucial you choose the right one for your home. Colours can create mood, bring back memories and stir up emotions. There are 4 key factors when choosing a colour scheme:
<list type="unordered"><item>The size of the room: The first thing to consider when looking at what colour scheme to go for is how big the room is. Colours have the ability to provide a room with a sense of space but can also make a room seem smaller and more intimate.</item>
<item>The <hi rend="italic">effect</hi> of colours: The purpose of the room will determine the colour you choose, but it's worth knowing that light colours like yellow and cream provide a sense of happiness, optimism and fun. Whereas darker colours, like red and burgundy, deliver a feeling of love, comfort and warmth which could be perfect for a cosy coffee shop or romantic bar.</item>
<item>Lighting: The lighting throughout the day will change constantly so checking a laminate sample in the morning when the sun is shining will look very different to when compared at night lit through artificial lighting. Consider how much natural light floods into the room, how strong the artificial lighting is and whether or not you want the laminate material to reflect this or not.</item></list></item>
<item>Consider the bigger picture. Never choose the laminate without thinking of what colour and style the furniture will be as these should work together, complement each other and create a sense of flow and style.</item></list>
<p>===Establishing Your Budget=== </p>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be realistic as to what you can afford. This will usually determine the scale of the project, the type of materials you can and can't use as well as the style. You may not think that the budget would have such a large impact on the style but it really can.</item>
<item>Realize the impact of style to your budget. Many people prefer the retro, vintage style wooden surfaces, to reflect the old and rustic trend but simply can't afford it. This then means they have to opt for a different style altogether in order to stay within budget. The good news is that due to the vast and diverse selection of laminates available there are plenty of options that are suitable for all types of budgets.</item>
<item>Enjoy the variety of choices at various price ranges. From inexpensive, high pressure laminate to expensive Lami Gloss melamine board, laminate sheets provide you with the freedom and ability to create any type of style and design you want. Perfect for bathrooms, kitchens and commercial buildings.</item></list>
<head>Choosing a Style</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Contemplate the look you are trying to achieve. Laminate sheets come in a vast array of styles and designs. Look into what type of laminate will suit your room.</item>
<item>Evaluate what would suit the room. For example, if you are looking to update your kitchen, then a wooden or stone effect laminate would work really well. If it is a bathroom, perhaps marble or tile effect laminate might be the best option. You can choose from:
<list type="unordered"><item>Stone</item>
<item>Marble</item>
<item>Wood</item>
<item>Metal</item>
<item>Bright Colours</item>
<item>Dark Colours</item>
<item>Pastel Colours</item>
<item>Tile</item>
<item>Pattern</item>
<item>Plain</item></list></item></list>
<head>Adding Light</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Reflect on lighting in the space. This is a crucial aspect of interior design, as it can make or break a room. Try and work with natural light for the best results. When looking to add laminates into a room consider how much daylight flows through into the space throughout the day.
<list type="unordered"><item>If it is a very bright room, then you might not want a shiny surface, as it could be a bit too bright. A plain colour or wooden laminate sheet would be the better option.</item></list></item></list>
<p>===Evaluate the Design=== </p>
<list type="ordered"><item>Define your taste preference. Are you thinking modern and minimalist or do you prefer the retro chic? Both design styles are easily achieved with laminates and will cost you a lot less than other materials.[</item>
<item>Consider the size of your room. When determining your choice of laminate, consider the furniture you already have and the colour scheme. Modern minimalism works really well with large rooms that have a pale or washed out colour scheme.</item></list>
<head>Finishing the Laminate</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Think about what would look best. There many different types of finishes for laminate worktops. As mentioned earlier, if you have a very bright room then avoid a shiny surface as this might be a bit too much. However, if your room is dark then this could really help brighten it up.</item>
<item>Assess what is best for your household. If you have a family with children, then you want a finish that will hide any possible scratches. A glossy finish would work well. Laminates are incredibly strong and durable, however, so this shouldn't be much of an issue.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Laminates are a great way of achieving the natural style you always wanted without having to pay the huge price tags. Look into how these are being used now and you'll be shocked to see how real they look.</item>
<item>Always get laminates professionally fitted. If they are not fitted correctly then water can get through the gaps causing them to warp over time, which will be very expensive to replace.</item></list>
</text>
