<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc163" title="Cope with Having Your Entire Family Bullied" shortTile="cope-having-entire" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-09-26" dateModified="2018-08-01" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Cope_with_Having_Your_Entire_Family_Bullied" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Cope with Having Your Entire Family Bullied</head><p>Sadly, many families experience severe bullying. There are ways to prevent this from happening and many ways to stop family bullying. This captivating article will help you learn about what you can do if you ever experience such a thing.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>If You Notice the Bullying</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>If you see any change in the behavior of your child and if they start to act weirdly in social areas or not want to attend any social event or come across a certain person, sit down and talk with them. They might just need someone to talk with and share their worries or fears. Remember adults aren't the only ones with problems!</item>
<item>Go in and talk with the child's class teacher. <hi rend="italic">Do not</hi> go and start an argument with the bully's parents, because this will only make matters worse. The teacher will inform the parents of the child's actions and hopefully, your child will be relieved from this bullying.</item>
<item>If this step doesn't work, take the matter to the headteacher or a senior member of staff who will hopefully take this on a more serious level. Request for the bullied child to not be seated next to or partnered with the bully as this will make matters worse for your child. If this request is denied try and start looking for a new school for your child.</item>
<item>Now this may sound like an unreasonable and silly answer but sometimes this method is the one to follow. If your child continues to be bullied they will be very low in self-confidence and this will cause to depression and self-harm in the future. This is not a road you want your child to go down, so when all the tips don't work finding a new school for this child can be ideal. It will improve and boost their self-confidence and make them feel good about themselves.</item>
<item>Another good thing would be to report this school or give a bad review about it somewhere if they don't take bullying seriously.</item></list>
<head>If the Child Tells You About the Bullying</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>If the child tells you about the bullying it's an obvious sign that they don't know what to do about it and that they need you to go do something about it.</item>
<item>Go and talk with the class teacher and ask her/him to explain to the bully about the severe consequences of bullying and how it can affect the victim very badly.</item>
<item>If the bullying carries on from there go and report it to a headteacher or a senior member of staff and they should hopefully take care of the matter straight away and punish the bully for his/her wrong actions.</item>
<item>Remember to never try to take the matters into your own hands because this can lead to a lot of unnecessary trouble.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Never take the matter into your own hands. Always make sure you know the full story on why your child is being bullied. It could be because of something they have previously done.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Even if the entire family was bullied, their behaviour and reaction need not be identical. Respect the differences and let go if one tends to be difficult with you.</item></list>
</text>
