<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc227" title="Make Ginger Paste" shortTile="make-ginger-paste" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-10-21" dateModified="2019-08-07" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make_Ginger_Paste" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make Ginger Paste</head><p>Fresh ginger is an essential ingredient in many recipes, but you may get tired of peeling and grating small amounts of ginger over and over. Instead, you can chop up a much larger amount of ginger, puree it into a paste, and store it in the fridge or freezer for use as needed in recipes. Once you have fresh ginger ready-to-go, you’ll be using it in everything from sushi to ice cream to cocktails!</p>
<head>Ingredients</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>1 c (225 g) ginger, peeled and coarsely chopped</item>
<item> water</item>
<item>1 tsp (5 g) citric acid powder (optional)</item>
<item> vegetable oil (optional)</item></list>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Choosing and Chopping Ginger</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Pick hands of ginger that are firm and have smooth skin. You’ll find ginger at the market in oddly-shaped pieces called “hands” (the protruding sections are called “fingers”). Avoid hands that feel light for their size, have wrinkly skin, and are soft to the touch—those ones have lost too much of their water content. Instead, look for hands that have smooth, brown skin, and that feel both heavy for their size and firm to the touch. <figure rend="Make Ginger Paste Step 1 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Most people call ginger a root, but it’s actually a rhizome.</item></list></item>
<item>Store the ginger in the fridge until you’re ready to use it. Wrap the ginger loosely in plastic wrap and place a rubber band over it, or put it in a zip-close bag with the zipper kept partly open. Stash it in the vegetable drawer of your refrigerator for up to 1 week before using it. <figure rend="Make Ginger Paste Step 2 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The ginger will go bad more quickly if you seal it up tight.</item>
<item>Even if the ginger hasn’t gotten moldy or mushy after a week, it will start to lose the brightness of its flavor quickly.</item></list></item>
<item>Wash and peel the ginger. If you’re not using the whole hand, cut or snap off a finger or two of the ginger. Rinse it under running water and rub off any dirt, then dry it with paper towels. Peel off the skin with a vegetable peeler or a paring knife. <figure rend="Make Ginger Paste Step 3 Version 3.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Work carefully with the peeler or paring knife—they’re sharp!</item>
<item>If the ginger has thin, smooth skin, you don’t necessarily have to peel it. However, peeling it may make your ginger paste come out a little bit smoother.</item></list></item>
<item>Chop the ginger coarsely and measure out 1 c (225 g). Use a sharp knife to cut up the ginger. The pieces don’t have to be uniform in size, but try to make them no more than  thick. Keep chopping until you have your desired amount. <figure rend="Make Ginger Paste Step 4 Version 3.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you’ve cleaned and peeled too much ginger, simply double the recipe to 2 c (450 g)!</item></list></item></list>
<head>Creating a Smooth Paste</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Add  of water to a blender or food processor. Use room temperature or cold water. You may need up to  to make a paste out of 1 c (225 g) of chopped ginger, so be ready to add more water as needed while you work. <figure rend="Make Ginger Paste Step 5 Version 3.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Adding the water first makes the pureeing go a little faster.</item></list></item>
<item>Add the ginger and, if desired, oil or citric acid as a preservative. If you want to ensure the full flavor profile of the ginger, don’t use anything but it and water to make your paste. However, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Preserve_Ginger_Paste">the paste will last longer</ref> in the fridge or freezer if you add either  of vegetable oil or 1 tsp (5 g) of citric acid. <figure rend="Make Ginger Paste Step 6 Version 3.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You’ll find citric acid in powdered form at health stores and many grocery stores.</item>
<item>These preservatives will extend the storage time in the fridge from about 1 week to 1 month, and in the freezer from 1 month to 3 months.</item>
<item>You can add both vegetable oil and citric acid, but this won’t further extend the storage time.</item></list></item>
<item>Puree the mixture until it forms a smooth paste. Depending on your blender or food processor, you may need to occasionally scrape down the inside of the container with a silicone spatula to help fully incorporate the chunks of ginger. You can also add up to  of additional water as needed to help break down the ginger pieces. Stop pureeing when the entire mixture has a consistent, slightly lumpy texture. <figure rend="Make Ginger Paste Step 7 Version 3.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>In regards to consistency, the mixture should look more like grits than oatmeal.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Storing the Ginger Paste</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Keep the puree in a tightly sealed container in the fridge or freezer. Immediately transfer your puree to one or more containers with tight-fitting lids, then stash it in the refrigerator or freezer. Without any added preservatives, the paste will keep in the fridge for 1 week and in the freezer for 1 month. <figure rend="Make Ginger Paste Step 8 Version 3.360p.mp4"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you added vegetable oil or citric acid to the paste, it should keep for up to 1 month in the fridge and up to 3 months in the freezer.</item></list></item>
<item>Use ice cube trays to freeze mini-doses of paste instead. If you consistently use the same amount of ginger paste in your go-to recipes, you can freeze pre-measured amounts by using ice cube trays. Spoon your preferred amount—up to —into each cup in an ice cube tray, then freeze the paste solid. After that, pop out the ginger paste cubes and store them in a labeled zip-close freezer bag. <figure rend="Make Ginger Paste Step 9 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This way, you can grab just the amount you need while you’re cooking without having to measure!</item></list></item>
<item>Use the paste chilled, frozen, or slightly thawed. Refrigerated ginger paste can be added as-is to any recipe. You can also add frozen cubes straight to a skillet. However, if you’re using frozen cubes for baking, thaw them for 5-10 minutes on the counter first—by then, they should be softened enough to incorporate into your batter or mix. <figure rend="Make Ginger Paste Step 10 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can substitute ginger paste for fresh grated ginger at an equal ratio. If your recipe calls for a length of ginger—for instance, a “1-inch finger”—use  of paste per 1 inch.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Steep  of ginger paste in  of hot water for 5-10 minutes, then add honey and lemon to taste to make a tasty ginger tea.</item>
<item>With only minor adjustments, you can also make <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_Ginger_Garlic_Paste">ginger garlic paste</ref>, which is particularly useful if you like to cook Indian cuisine.</item></list>
</text>
