<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc192" title="Overcome Sibling Rivalry in Adulthood" shortTile="overcome-sibling" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-03-11" dateModified="2019-09-08" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Overcome_Sibling_Rivalry_in_Adulthood" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Overcome Sibling Rivalry in Adulthood</head><p>Years of sibling rivalry can be remedied even if it comes later in life. It takes effort on both parts but it can be done with determination and will power. Life is short! Have no regrets and feel good knowing that you have done all you can do to mend relationships with your siblings.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Try to see things from your sibling's perspective. Maybe your parents really did show favoritism or perhaps your sibling can't get past a certain issue that happened during childhood. Understanding things from someone else's point of view is the first step in repairing any relationship, and it's no different when it comes to your brother or sister.</item>
<item>Respect the beliefs that your sibling adheres to. You can agree to disagree on issues that will allow you to have a loving relationship with someone who shares so much with you. At the end of the day, think about what is most important to you: arguing about something that you could probably get past, or letting go and opening your mind to the idea that you may not be right all of the time. Even if you know you are...let it go!</item>
<item>Apologize for any big incidents you both might still be holding onto. Maybe you broke their x box when you were younger and never apologized, now is the perfect time to do it.</item>
<item>Find something common. It can be as simple as a television series that you both enjoy. Anything that will allow you to be able to talk and communicate freely may be the common ground that you both need to remember the things that you love about each other. Laughing over a character's goofy personality or crying together because someone on the show "died" can create a sense of unity that may surprise you.</item>
<item>Proceed with caution. Take things slowly. Things probably didn't turn sour overnight and you will not be able to make things lollipops and rainbows overnight. It takes time..so give it time. It will be worth it in the end. Just keep being yourself and letting your sibling know they are loved and you value their opinion.
<list type="unordered"><item>Do little things to let them know how much they mean to you. It could be a funny card in the mail with an inside joke that only you two would understand, or maybe surprise them with lunch at their workplace. No matter what, allow the relationship time to heal.</item></list></item>
<item>Once things have improved a bit joke about the old times. As long as your siblings doesn't get hurt by this you can laugh about your childhood together instead of arguing.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't be pushy. Give your sibling space. Don't try to force them to see things the way you do. Explain your view points, but let them know you are open to listening to what they have to say.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Your sibling may be suspicious of your intent. Be careful not to expect too much too soon, and don't get frustrated when you put forth effort a few times and don't see instant results. If that happens, your sibling will develop a "What exactly do you want from me?!" attitude. Be real. Be honest. Be you. That doesn't mean you have to conform to or agree with everything they say, but you can stand your ground in a loving way while expressing thoughts of love at the same time.</item></list>
</text>
