<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc193" title="Deal with a Member of Your Family Leaving" shortTile="deal-member-family" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-02-15" dateModified="2016-08-18" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Deal_with_a_Member_of_Your_Family_Leaving" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Deal with a Member of Your Family Leaving</head><p>It's tough when a family member leaves home. It might be a sibling moving interstate for a new job, a daughter going overseas to study, a son moving out after marrying, and so forth. Whatever the reason, and whichever the family member, it can be sad and joyous at once, but you may be left with a sense of emptiness when they have actually gone.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Talk to one another. Encourage all family members to let out their feelings about the person leaving and how it affects them. Everyone will have their own things to say, so let each person talk openly, without interruption or judgment.
<list type="unordered"><item>Be especially careful of children's feelings, to ensure that they don't feel left out and have a chance to express themselves too. Letting them talk can help them to express how they miss the family member and what they'd like to happen.</item></list></item>
<item>Organize constant communication with the person who has left. There are many ways to stay in touch, including Skype, talking on the phone, texting, messaging on Instagram, using Twitter, emailing, even snail mail (especially for care packages).</item>
<item>Deal with ongoing sadness or feeling down. If you feel that you, or anyone else in the family, might be experiencing depression as a result of the family member leaving, get some help. Begin by talking to a trusted family member who is strong and caring. If this doesn't help, consider talking to your doctor about ways to cope with the sadness.
<list type="unordered"><item>Try not to feel down all the time. If the absence is for a set period of time, it'll pass soon enough. If the absence is permanent, such as in the case of a marriage or moving overseas, realize that you can still stay in touch and see each other. In the instance of a family member leaving under a dark cloud, remember that time heals all wounds and perhaps there is a chance that someday this family member will come back.</item></list></item>
<item>Ensure that the remaining family members are pursuing the activities and interests that they care about. Check that everyone is coping and moving forward, accepting of the change that has occurred in the family structure. Even though it is wonderful for family to remain close together, life is full of opportunities and the form of family shifts and changes with time, which is as it should be. Remember too, that your sadness should not impinge on the wonderful new opportunities that the family member leaving may be pursuing or the new life that they are carving out for themselves.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be especially vigilant of how children are coping when a treasured member of the family leaves. Be open about the person's reasons for leaving, unless it is not appropriate for the child's age. Understanding the reason can help the child to cope better.</item>
<item>Be sure to take plenty of photos of the family back at home to send to the family member who has gone away. They'll most likely want to keep up with all the happenings as the time goes on.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Contact methods, such as Skype account, email, phone numbers, etc.</item>
<item>Snail mail address for those wonderful care packages</item>
<item>Camera for taking photos as the family grows and changes</item></list>
</text>
