<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc72" title="Set Up Dfp" shortTile="set-up-dfp" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2017-03-17" dateModified="2019-10-18" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Set_Up_Dfp" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Set Up Dfp</head><head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Before getting into introducing how to set up DFP with your Google Account, let’s talk about what DFP actually is. DFP stands for DoubleClick for Publishers. That is a server, a host for ads. There are two types of DFP. The first one is DFP Small Business and the other is DFP Premium. The difference between these two is that DFP Small business is the free product, and you will have to have a Google AdSense account. However you will not have to use AdSense on your site. DFP Premium is the paid product and it is meant for bigger and massive sites. You have to reach impressions of 90 million per month in order to have access to DFP Premium. Until then, DFP will tell you that you need DFP Small Business.</item>
<item>STEP ONE Register a Google AdSense Account. You will have to have that account in order to use DFP Small Business.</item>
<item>STEP TWO In another tab, go to DFP main page. But first, you will have to verify your account. Follow the instructions. Then you will have to choose the display language, country, time zone, currency.</item>
<item>STEP THREE Accept the terms and local settings</item>
<item>STEP FOUR After you are logged in to your DFP there you might see three tabs. They are: ORDERS INVENTORY REPORTS  What are ORDERS? In that tab you will see two categories: ORDERS LINE ITEMS Orders are those advertisers you are buying or have already bought ads on your site. For every single customer you may create a separate order. Every single Order or Customer may have as many Line items /campaigns/ as you would like them to. Line Items/Campaign may have many Creatives AKA ads and banners. But Before that we will have to do</item>
<item>STEP FIVE Go to Inventory in the main navigations  In Inventory tab you will have two categories: Ad Units Placements Ad units are the actual ad units on the page. Placements are the booking option for the ad Unit. You may have one Ad Unit as Placement or you may have many ad Units in one Placement. You won't have to set up Placements to start Ad Campaigns on the web-site, however the more interesting your Ad Inventory becomes the more useful placements will be.</item>
<item>STEP SIX At this point you are ready to define your inventory in DFP. Create an Ad unit create one Ad Unit for every item on your list giving them different names. Every single Ad Unit will need an original block of HTML that will have to be pasted on the site at the very place, where that ad unit has to be shown. Your inventory is already active. You will see empty white boxes. That means that you have integrated DFP.</item>
<item>STEP SEVEN Get ad content that will be displaying on the site. To do that you will have to create an order. You can create an order in two ways: By running an inventory forecast For this you have to run an inventory forecast, then put in the name of the order in the field Save to an Order and click Continue. All your info will be imported to your new order. Manually In DFP, you should click Delivery tab → Click New Order→ Enter Order info in the appropriate fields→ Order names have to be unique in the network→ put in line Item info → Press Check inventory to make sure that your Order will get available impressions→ Click SAVE. Once you do that, you will be able to add many Line Items. The latter can be content that you upload or a link. It can also be 3rd party content like AdSense etc.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>After you do all of these, you are good to go. Hopefully this article helped you.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>NOTE. YOU CAN NO LONGER CHANGE THE SETTINGS ONCE YOU HAVE CHOSEN THEM. Be very attentive.*</item></list>
</text>
