<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc158" title="Be Great Company When Out with Your Mother" shortTile="great-company-out" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2009-09-03" dateModified="2018-10-12" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_Great_Company_When_Out_with_Your_Mother" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be Great Company When Out with Your Mother</head><p>Going out with your mother when you're a teen can be embarrassing at times, or it can just feel like a chore. As an adult, you might feel compelled to be argumentative or to just put up with things being "the way they always have" and end up not enjoying the occasion. Why not make up your mind to enjoy being out with your mother instead?</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Listen to her for real. Instead of hearing the "usual stories" or "typical whining", view her in a new light and really listen to what she has to say. Go on - it might just be interesting! You will get to know each other even more, and therefore, have a real emotional relationship. <figure rend="Be Great Company When Out with Your Mother Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Help her. Be courteous and thoughtful by opening doors, picking up dropped items, and paying for things before she has a chance to do so. Show her that she matters and she will find the occasion enjoyable. Then maybe you will feel the same! <figure rend="Be Great Company When Out with Your Mother Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Share secrets. Remind her of times that the two of you have done things together or said things together that were special just to the two of you. Only bring up happy memories and things that both of you relate to fondly. Tell her about everything that happens to you lately, and maybe ask her for advice. After all, she is older than you and has more life experience than you. There is a chance that she has already been in the same situation as you, so ask her for solution. She will feel she is really special to you, and the fact that, she is. Just you don't show it much often. <figure rend="Be Great Company When Out with Your Mother Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make her feel special. Let her know that she's a mom in a million and that you care for her a great deal. Tell her so. Give her flowers. Pay for her meal or movie. Let her know that you think she is irreplaceable. Always say 'I love you' no matter the occasion is. And yes, love is not something temporary, especially when it comes to motherhood.  <figure rend="Be Great Company When Out with Your Mother Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Put your negative feelings to one side. Don't let past behavior and irritations get to you. When these feelings rise, put a hold them and remind yourself that the time spent with your mother is short and you must make it as special as possible. Stop yourself from saying anything negative. Except for when you ask her for advice, of course.  <figure rend="Be Great Company When Out with Your Mother Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't be embarrassed by her. She's your mom and you ought to be proud of her. Don't snicker, sigh, or look away wishing you were somewhere else. That's disrespectful and hurtful. Be proud to be with her. She is the one who gave birth to you and has brought you up, taken care of you for years and years. All the money you give her will never compensate for what she has sacrificed for you. <figure rend="Be Great Company When Out with Your Mother Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Love her. You will do whatever for the one you love, that is one thing we know for sure.</item></list>
</text>
