<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc108" title="Speed Up Acer Aspire One" shortTile="speed-up-acer-aspire" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2016-02-21" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Speed_Up_Acer_Aspire_One" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Speed Up Acer Aspire One</head><p>The Acer Aspire One is a small Windows notebook designed for users who primarily browse the Internet. When your Aspire One starts lagging or running slowly, speed its performance and efficiency by disabling unneeded features, installing more RAM, replacing outdated software, and more.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Disabling Startup Applications</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Click the Start menu and type “system configuration” into the search box. <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select “System Configuration” from search results. <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on the “Startup” tab, then remove checkmarks next to processes you don’t want running after startup. This prevents applications you don’t use from automatically running in the background after your computer starts up, leading to slowness and lagging. <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click “OK.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> Going forward, these processes will no longer run automatically following startup. <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 4.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Disabling Performance Options</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Click the Start menu and type “system” into the search box. <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select “System” from search results, then click on “Advanced system settings.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on the “Advanced” tab, then click “Settings” under Performance. These options control visual effects and performance features, some of which could be clogging your system. <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remove checkmarks next to options as desired, then click “OK.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> For example, disable the feature labeled “Animate windows when minimizing and maximizing” if you don’t wish to see animations when minimizing windows. <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Enabling Manual Services</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Click the Start menu and type “services” into the search box. <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select “Services” from search results. Windows automatically starts services such as IP Helper and Print Spooler upon startup, even when not needed. <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Double-click on each service in the Services window and change its Startup Type to “Manual.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> Going forward, these services will only start at your command. Examples of services you can disable are Diagnostic Policy Service, Print Spooler, and Distributed Link Tracking Client. <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 11.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Disabling McAfee</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Click the “Start” menu and select “Program and Features.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Right-click on the installed McAfee software and select “Uninstall.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> Most Aspire One models come pre-loaded with McAfee antivirus software, which runs in the background at all times to keep your system protected from malware and viruses. <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 13.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Consider installing another security program that consumes fewer resources, or stick to visiting websites you trust to avoid malware and viruses. Disabling McAfee antivirus security software makes your computer more vulnerable to malicious software and third parties.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Turning Off Sounds</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Click the Start menu and type “sound” into the search box. <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on “Sound” in search results. This opens the Sounds menu. By default, Windows plays sound effects that use system resources when performing actions such as closing programs and restarting. <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on the “Sounds” tab, then select “No Sounds” next to Sound Scheme. <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 16.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remove the checkmark next to “Play Windows Startup sound,” then click “OK.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 17.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Installing More RAM</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Click the Start menu and type “system” into the search box. <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 18.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select “System” from search results. <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 19.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Note the value next to “Installed memory (RAM).<hi rend="bold">”</hi> This tells you how much RAM is already installed in your computer. <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 20.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Refer to the user’s manual for your Acer Aspire One to determine the maximum amount of RAM it takes. Alternately, visit Acer’s official website at <ref target="http://www.acer.com/ac/en/US/content/drivers">http://www.acer.com/ac/en/US/content/drivers</ref> to access the manual. For example, if your computer supports up to 3.5 GB RAM and one GB is already installed, you can install 2.5 GB additional RAM. <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 21.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Install_RAM">Install extra RAM on your own</ref>, or hire a computer technician to install it for you. Following installation, your computer will run faster and more efficiently. <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 22.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Installing Windows Updates</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Click the Start menu and select “All Programs.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 23.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select “Windows Update.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> This opens the Windows Update menu. Windows automatically installs updates as they become available, unless you disabled this feature at an earlier date. <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 24.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click “Check for updates” in the left pane. Windows will search for the newest software updates from Microsoft. <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 25.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click “Install updates,” then type the administrator password if prompted. Your computer will download and install available updates. <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 26.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Replacing Outdated Software</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Replace slower Internet browsers with Google Chrome. Chrome is currently the fastest browser available on Windows computers, and speeds up loading time. <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Uninstall_Internet_Explorer_Completely">Uninstall Internet Explorer</ref>, Safari, Firefox, and other browsers, and start using Chrome. <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 27.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Replace software packages with Web-based applications. Applications that rival Microsoft Office Suite are now available online and free of charge so you can avoid installing extra software. For example, use your search engine to find photo editing software to replace Microsoft Photo Editor, and consider using Google Sheets instead of Microsoft Excel. <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 28.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Replace outdated programs with newer, more lightweight versions. If you’ve been using programs you installed on your computer several years ago, visit the developer’s website to locate newer versions of the same software that consume fewer memory and resources. <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 29.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Alternately, search for similar versions of the same program from other developers and manufacturers. For example, if using antivirus software that consumes too much memory, search for reviews of new antivirus software from another developer that consumes fewer resources.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Removing Pre-Installed Bloatware</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Click the Start menu and select “Control Panel.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> This opens the Control Panel window. <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 30.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select “Uninstall a Program.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> This displays a list of all programs installed on your system. Acer Aspire One models come pre-loaded with unneeded programs known as “bloatware” that cause lagging and slowness. <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 31.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click on each program you don’t use or recognize and select “Uninstall.<hi rend="bold">”</hi> This removes the program from your system. <figure rend="Speed Up Acer Aspire One Step 32.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Use antivirus security software to search your Acer Aspire One for malware and viruses before following any other steps to speed up your system. This helps identify whether your computer is running slowly due to security threats and malware.</item></list>
</text>
