<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc171" title="Save Money on Your Young Children's Needs" shortTile="save-money-young" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-07-20" dateModified="2019-09-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Save_Money_on_Your_Young_Children%27s_Needs" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Save Money on Your Young Children's Needs</head><p>In today's modern life, fashion and trends are always changing. As such saving money becomes a real task in its own. Read on to find out how to save on children's accessories.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Try to buy second hand clothes whenever possible. Whether it is your newborn baby or a 10 year old kid. Buying secondhand will most certainly save you money. A lot of the second hand clothes are actually in a better condition than you may imagine! You may find some of the charity shops in the market you go for shopping. Otherwise, you may find some on the Internet; however it is advised that you be careful while shopping online. <figure rend="Be-Stylish-Without-Spending-a-Lot-of-Money-Step-8-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Cut and glue cartoons or graphics from other older shirts to plain ones. You could also buy new shirts of 0 sizes, with your kid's favorite character on it and cut that to put it on their own shirts. Size 0 shirts are relatively low priced, thus can be bought to make your kids happy and save at the same time. <figure rend="Create-an-Awesome-Discovery-Girls-Star-Form-Step-10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Go to charity shops frequently. Perhaps you can find a toy that would otherwise cost you a shiny dime. You would need them in future too. When you have a newborn, you have lots of time to search for his/her toys. You can be picky at charity shops, although if you're lucky enough, you may just find the thing you were looking for! <figure rend="Keep-Toddlers-from-Fighting-over-Toys-Step-20-Version-2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Take your time, and find toys of your choice to give them to your kids when they reach that age.</item>
<item>Shop smartly from charity shops as they sometimes are dearer to the new ones! </item></list></item>
<item>Go for the books when you have no pennies left in your pocket. Your library will lend you many items for free. In charity shops, books are relatively low priced so go for it. Books are the best toys for kids; they are informational and are excellent boredom-busters. <figure rend="Change-Your-Child's-Attitude-Step-17.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can find some sites that offer a free exchange of items. Freecycle.org is one such site. You can also find cheap clothing on various other sites. Amazon and eBay also offer a secondhand section in their site list It is always advised that you exercise caution while shopping for secondhand products online. </item></list></item>
<item>Get a pack of cards. There are countless games that one can play with a set of 52 cards. You can play the classics such as <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Play_Hearts">Hearts</ref>, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Play_Blackjack">BlackJack</ref>, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Play_Gin_Rummy">Gin</ref> or <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Play_Solitaire">Solitaire</ref> or you can even make up your own card game! <figure rend="Cleanse-Yourself-of-Prejudices-and-Race-Based-Behaviors-Step-10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find origami sets. Origami sets are inexpensive and are a lot of fun. They are also good for your child's visual, tactile and mental development.  <figure rend="Play-Simple-Learning-Activities-with-Your-Child-at-Home-Step-12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find a good drawer for free or for sale and your kids will surely enjoy it. A good drawer is a necessity of the room and a toy for the kids to play with. <figure rend="Fake-Clean-Your-Bedroom-Step-5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>It will teach them the concept of tidy up and make them organized. </item></list></item>
<item>Cut your kid's hair by yourself. It is not rocket science and is fairly easy once you get the hang of it!  You can also find free offers from new hair dressers on Internet and in shops. This is worth finding!  <figure rend="Comb-a-Small-Child's-Hair-Without-Tears-Step-2-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take your kids to public parks outside. They are usually free all the time instead of spending a wholesome amount at leisure clubs. <figure rend="Make-a-Child-Feel-Valued-Step-1-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Teach them to cook. Cooking can be fun too! Experimenting with new ideas and recipes to make a mouth-watering dish is an art in itself. This will also help them in their lives ahead and make them more independent. <figure rend="Deal-With-Annoying-Kids-Step-16.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Give your kids spare household items to play with, as long as they're safe. Not every toy has to be an expensive robot or a RC car. Common household objects such as used up CD's can be a fun thing to play around with. <figure rend="Discipline-a-4-Year-Old-Step-2-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always check the prices at both ends: charity chop and new shop. Sometimes in new shops, clearance items are cheaper than charity items.</item>
<item>Always check your needed items from charity shops then go for the new one.</item>
<item>Buy things when you are sure you would need them in future. Try not to buy in a hurry unless it is really important for you to get something now.</item>
<item>Teach your children about the shops you can buy something for them. They will eventually understand your stance and be with you.</item>
<item>Some pound shops are better alternatives if your need is temporary in nature.</item>
<item>Re- use the old stuff in your own home and make something that interests your kids.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You must not use things that may cause health hazards for your kids. It is better to use a new thing if you are not sure about the hygiene of the old one.</item>
<item>Always wash your things coming from charity shops. They would never be the same like new. Be careful!</item></list>
</text>
