<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc186" title="Understand a Family Member's Physical Disability" shortTile="understand-family" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-05-06" dateModified="2017-05-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Understand_a_Family_Member%27s_Physical_Disability" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Understand a Family Member's Physical Disability</head><p>If your family member has a disability, it may be hard for you to understand. From just having bad eyes to not having use of their legs, you still have to respect them. Here's how.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Understanding Disability in General</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Try reading up on their disability. An online search can take you to articles about the disability, both written by medical professionals and people who have the disability. This can help you get a better understanding of exactly what your family member is dealing with.</item>
<item>Learn about the spoon theory. The spoon theory describes how some people with disabilities have limited energy, which they need to budget carefully. Your family member might not always have energy for different tasks, and might need more rest.
<list type="unordered"><item>Not all disabled people have trouble with energy. This will depend on the person.</item></list></item>
<item>Keep in mind that abilities can vary from day to day. Lack of sleep, how much they exerted themselves yesterday, how busy they are, and other factors can influence the person's disability.
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, maybe they used a wheelchair yesterday but are okay with just a cane today. It doesn't mean they're "getting better," just doing better today.</item></list></item>
<item>Recognize that many people with disabilities are used to it. They usually don't want to be pitied, treated like they're fragile, treated awkwardly, or left out. Your loved one is an ordinary person who just has slightly different needs and abilities.
<list type="unordered"><item>Newly disabled people may still be adjusting. It can take a while to figure out what their body can and can't do, often through trial and error.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Interacting with Them</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Follow the usual rules of politeness. It's normal to be a little confused about manners around a disabled person, because these things aren't usually taught like other rules of politeness are. Recognize that the manners you learned still apply, and be mindful of the person and their feelings.
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't touch or move them without permission. Just like you wouldn't grab someone's leg and move it, don't move someone's cane or wheelchair unless they're okay with it.</item>
<item>Respect their personal space. People with disabilities have personal space just like people without them.</item>
<item>Don't ask intrusive questions. "What happened?" or "Why are your eyes like that?" are usually questions that disabled people are tired of answering. Assume they'll tell you if they think it's important.</item></list></item>
<item>Offer help if they're struggling. Be polite and open-minded, the same way you might offer help to someone who's struggling to use something tricky or new. It may be that your loved one needs help, or maybe they want to do it themselves. This is a polite way to let them know that if they need help from you, you're there.</item>
<item>Ask instead of assuming. Avoid thinking that you know what you're family member can or can't do. (Remember that what they can do today might be different from what they could do yesterday.)
<list type="unordered"><item>Invite them to go places, even if you know they might not be able to come with. Sometimes they might be able to come.</item>
<item>If you don't know if they can do something, just ask.</item></list></item>
<item>Treat them like they're normal. Around 1 in 5 people are disabled, and your loved one is one of them. There's no need to treat them like they're weird, odd-looking, or from outer space. They're just a slightly different type of normal than what you're used to.
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't stare. You can look, but avoid making them uncomfortable.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>DO NOT do anything that might hurt them, or make them feel bad.</item></list>
</text>
