<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc75" title="Design a Land Parcel in AutoCAD Civil 3D" shortTile="design-land-parcel" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-10-03" dateModified="2019-09-15" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Design_a_Land_Parcel_in_AutoCAD_Civil_3D" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Design a Land Parcel in AutoCAD Civil 3D</head><p>A land parcel the technical term for a plot of land owned by an individual, organization, company, or otherwise. Civil Engineers and Land Surveyors routinely work with land parcels as they work on land development projects. This article describes how to use Autocad Civil 3D to design and depict those land parcels.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><figure rend="Step1Parcel.png"></figure>Establish a new drawing window
<list type="unordered"><item>On the top end of the civil 3D ribbon a new tab option is available for opening a new drawing. Be sure your settings are appropriate to your region.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Step2Parcel.png"></figure>Create a Parcel from Objects
<list type="unordered"><item>One way to design parcels in Civil 3D is to do so using existing objects. To demonstrate, use the polyline command to create a rectangular shape. This shape will be what you will ask Civil 3D to generate a parcel from. In designing a subdivision or cul-de-sac, this type of command is extremely useful as you will be able to convert objects drawn from legal descriptions to parcels recognized by Civil 3D.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Step3Parcel.png"></figure>Launch the parcel creation wizard
<list type="unordered"><item>Launch the parcel creation wizard by clicking on it from the ribbon on the top of left next to the toolspace icon. You will see three different options, including parcel creation tools, create parcel from objects, and create right of way. We want to select create parcel from objects.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Step4Parcel.png"></figure>Highlight the object
<list type="unordered"><item>Highlight the object you wish to convert to a parcel by clicking and dragging your mouse over the intended objects. This will select them. You should then press the enter key on your keyboard.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Step5Parcel.png"></figure>Use the Parcel Creation Wizard
<list type="unordered"><item>At this point you will see a pop up with a number of prompts. The site allows you to associate the objects with a particular grouping of parcels. This is helpful when making parcels for different subdivisions. The parcel style tab allows you to change the color and look of the parcel based on presets or your own custom created style. The area label style helps you select what to display on the parcel you create. On the bottom of the wizard, you have the option of adding segment labels to each of the individual lines and the option of erasing existing entities. The labels will display for you information like bearing and distance on each of the lines of the parcel, and erasing existing entities will simply erase the objects you created the parcel from and create the parcel instead.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Step6Parcel.png"></figure>Select the following for demonstration purposes:
<list type="unordered"><item>For demonstration purposes create a new site called subdivision, select a parcel style of single family, select an area label style of name, square foot, and acres, and leave remove existing entities checked.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Step7Parcel.png"></figure>You just created a parcel!
<list type="unordered"><item>Running your cursor over the parcel you will find that it shows you data related to the object no longer being a poly-line but a parcel recognized by Civil 3D. We can see that it displays name, square footage, and acres as per our area label specification and relates itself to the subdivision site.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Step8Parcel.png"></figure>Further Division
<list type="unordered"><item>The parcel creation wizard is a powerful tool in Civil 3D and can help divide the parcel further based on specifications you provide the system with. Highlight parcel creation tools under parcel near the toolspace tab and select it.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Step9Parcels.png"></figure>Select Slide Line Create
<list type="unordered"><item>The parcel creation wizard is able to subdivide parcels in a number of different ways but the most common one is the slide line create method. Select that command as shown above.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Steps10Parcel.png"></figure>Specify and Select
<list type="unordered"><item>The wizard will now ask you to give it criterion with which to subdivide the parcels. These are often based on zoning requirements. Among them are lot depth, width, and frontage. Adjusting these variables will tell Civil 3D what kind of parcels you wish to come out with. When finished selecting the specifications select the parcel you want to subdivide by clicking on the parcel text.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Step11Parcel.png"></figure>Specify your frontage
<list type="unordered"><item>Autocad will now ask you to draw a line to describe the front of the property. It will subdivide based on the direction of this vector. Here we wanted to divide from left to right so we indicated that.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Step12Parcel.png"></figure>Accept or decline the divisions
<list type="unordered"><item>Civil 3D just went ahead and subdivided your property per your specifications. If you accept the result on this screen it will go ahead and generate those divisions as parcels.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Step13Parcel.png"></figure>Parcels created!
<list type="unordered"><item>You just designed multiple parcels with Civil 3D’s powerful parcel creation wizard.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
