<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc126" title="Study and Make Friends in Canada" shortTile="study-make-friends" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-07-12" dateModified="2016-06-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Study_and_Make_Friends_in_Canada" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Study and Make Friends in Canada</head><p>Maybe you end up going to school in Canada. If you're from the U.S.or anywhere else in the world, you may find it hard to adjust to Canada. Especially if you live in a warm, sunny place all year round and you get to Canada in the winter and <hi rend="italic">bam</hi>, there's a snow storm and it's freezing.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Studying</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>If you're in Canada for college, then you have to study hard. One place you can go for some quietness is a local Starbucks. You can sit in a corner table, bring your computer and your books. Also if you want to be more alone, you could go to the closest library. Some libraries have large tables, so if you're like the only one in there you could spread your stuff out on the table so you have more room.</item>
<item>If your college has study groups or a club on what you're studying, then join it. Don't be shy; the faster you join the more friends you will make and the more you will learn. But if you're in a study group, some are more serious and focused and others are relaxed and everyone talks and has fun.</item>
<item>In your dorm, set up a little study corner. Maybe if you have a small desk or table and chair, a small table lamp, you could just set that up and make it all comfortable and cozy.</item></list>
<head>Making friends</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>That study group would be helpful for learning, but it's also extremely helpful for making friends. If you're in the more laid back one, find someone who you have stuff in common with or if you know nothing about anyone there, just strike up a conversation with anybody. Say "Hi, I'm {name here}, I just moved here from {place}". Then just continue on with the conversation.</item>
<item>Join lots of stuff out of school. Like join a gym, a walking club. That way you meet all sorts of people. The more people you meet, the more people they'll introduce you too.</item>
<item>Just be really nice to everyone and people will want to be your friend. Find some thing in common with someone and talk over that and you will have a connection in no time.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be friendly.</item>
<item>Don't let the conversation fall, try to keep it going.</item>
<item>Don't be to pushy and invite them somewhere right away.</item>
<item>Don't keep the conversation too long, then you get annoying. Keep it going to the other person looks bored. Signs of that are the person just keeps nodding, looks around and doesn't make eye contact.</item></list>
</text>
