<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc258" title="Spot Stunted Growth in Children" shortTile="spot-stunted-growth" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-12-02" dateModified="2019-06-05" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Spot_Stunted_Growth_in_Children" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Spot Stunted Growth in Children</head><p>Stunted growth in children is the impaired of growth and development in general. It's not simply about a child being shorter than other children their age. Stunted growth is caused by poor nutrition, repeated infections and inadequate psychosocial stimulation. Stunted growth can affect a child throughout their life, even impacting salary in adult life.. To spot signs of stunted growth in children, monitor the child's physical development and if a slowing is noted, consider the causes.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Take into account where the child is growing up. One in four children in the world are stunted. 80% of children who don't develop physically to their full potential, live in just 20 countries - This isn't to say that only only children in the developing world suffer from stunted growth. Any child consuming a diet that lacks sufficient nutrients can suffer their body adapting, long term, to this lack. Malnutrition leads to the body giving priority to the requirements of the vital organs and bodily functions, rather than to growth in height.</item>
<item>Understand what's to be expected in terms of the child's physical development. In a healthy, well-nourished population only around 2% of children would naturally be short enough to be classed as stunted.[2 how to a reference a pdf?]. Short parents often have short children. Genetics play a part in height too. Compare the height of a child to other children that he or she is on a level with, a child with Chinese heritage is likely to be shorter than a child with primarily Dutch ancestors for instance. There are of course always anomalies and heritage or cultural traditions are not a reason to dismiss especially small stature.</item>
<item>Start to record height regularly as soon as the child can stand up to be measured. Prior to this a baby's length should of been recorded regularly by a midwife or pediatrician performing scheduled check-ups. If a child cannot stand by 17 months old, consult a doctor, unless you are fully aware of the reason, eg the child has mobility issues or a medical condition that prevents them standing.
<list type="unordered"><item>If a child cannot stand, work with the medical professional caring for them to monitor the child's specific physical development rate.</item></list></item>
<item>Measure children's height every six to 12 months at least. If you suspect a child is a risk of malnutrition due to poor diet, frequent infectious or repeated parasitic infestation, measure monthly.</item>
<item>Record the height of the child when you measure them. Record it in the same book or document each time. Add the weight of the child. The key to spotting stunting is identifying a slowing or stopping of growth. Children don't grow at the same rate throughout their childhood, but incremental changes should be noted at each measure. A cessation of growth for three months in a child aged two or less is cause for concern. <figure rend="Spot Stunted Growth in Kids Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Compare recorded growth rates with children of the same age and  gender. If the child is consistently below the average height of children of the same age, stunted growth could be the cause.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Malnutrition is the leading cause of stunted growth. If your child has Avoidant/restrictive food intake disorder (ARFID), to prevent stunted growth, their diet must contain sufficient calories and nutrients for healthy development.</item>
<item>Stunted growth has irreversible detrimental effects. Act to prevent so that detecting it is not required.</item></list>
</text>
