<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc52" title="Make the JV Soccer Team As a Goalie" shortTile="make-jv-soccer-team" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2013-11-08" dateModified="2014-07-16" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make_the_JV_Soccer_Team_As_a_Goalie" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make the JV Soccer Team As a Goalie</head><p>Do you want to be on your schools JV soccer team as the goal keeper? Freshmen, Sophomore?  This article will teach you how to do just that!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Before tryouts, get all the materials listed down below in the "Things You'll Need" section.</item>
<item>Make sure you introduce yourself to the JV and Varsity coach at least a week before tryouts.</item>
<item>Be kind and understanding. The reason you meet both coaches is because you never know if you'll be asked to play Varsity instead of JV.</item>
<item>Work out if you aren't in shape. Some workout ideas would include a twenty minute run around the neighborhood. Be sure to time yourself.  Do 20 crunches and 30 jumping jacks with a two minute cool down between them. Jump as high as you can 10 times. You can also do some push ups. Don't forget to stretch before and after your workout.</item>
<item>Be very hydrated. Try 3-5 glasses of water and most definitely cut out soda.</item>
<item>Be 10 minutes early. Find the coach, say hello and ask if he or she would like you to carry the ball bags to the field. (If you are nervous, just ask if they need help with anything to prepare for tryouts.) If so, help. If not, find a group of older girls and introduce yourself. Be nice and ask questions, but don't interrogate. Simply act interested in whatever they are talking about. Show emotion, but don't be wildly interested.</item>
<item>Once you have been put in the goal, be fierce.</item>
<item>If a forward gets a lead off your defense, run out at her. This will hopefully scare her, which will put her aim off.</item>
<item>If she keeps charging, just jump on the ball. You WILL get hurt, but not too bad. Making the team will be worth this.  Plus, you will have to do it in games because diving is a part of your job description!</item>
<item>Be prepared to run (a lot). Find a girl who previously ran with the cross country team and STICK WITH HER. Keep a good pace and don't stop and walk, no matter what. If you start cramping up, slow down your pace and SLOW jog, but NEVER walk. This will for sure get you cut from the list. There will probably be another goalie trying out.   Figure out who is your main competition.</item>
<item>NEVER complain. Ever. Not inside or outside of tryouts. Not to the girls who are your friends; not to strangers. NO ONE. That is the MAIN reason the other freshmen got cut. Also, after you mess up do not talk bad about your performance.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Smile! Act like you love soccer! Play hard but laugh a little every now and then!</item>
<item>Learn some of the field players names so you can cheer them on during scrimmage games. Ex " There you go Sarah!" "Keep her to the left Sidney!" "Good job D!" (defense) ETC:)</item>
<item>Don't be afraid of the ball. Trust me, it doesn't hurt nearly as bad as it looks.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Again, no complaining</item>
<item>No trash talk</item>
<item>If you have asthma, remember to use your inhaler twenty minutes before tryouts!</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Goalie gloves</item>
<item>Comfortable shorts that aren't too short. They shouldn't be tight, or else you will have a major wedgie after every dive.</item>
<item>A comfortable sports bra</item>
<item>A t-shirt from your dresser that is a little baggy. Try not to wear black until it's cold outside though. It can be your youth shirt or the spirit shirt you bought from last years homecoming. Nothing special</item>
<item>Any kind of cleats</item>
<item>Socks of any color, pattern, or design that go up your calf, about two inches below your knee cap. These will need to be high to cover up the next item needed below!</item>
<item>SHIN GUARDS. These are extremely important. They keep you from being kicked in the shins when you run out of the goal towards a player who will potentially aim to score on you</item>
<item>Head bands are more important than you think.</item></list>
</text>
