<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc211" title="Argue Against the Gold Standard" shortTile="argue-against-gold" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-08-30" dateModified="2019-03-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Argue_Against_the_Gold_Standard" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Argue Against the Gold Standard</head><p><hi rend="italic">"As good as gold"</hi> - Anon
<hi rend="italic">"Anyone can mint gold. Anyone can issue gold receipts. With gold, control of the money is taken away from government. Gold is true. It is incorruptible. You can’t print it. It is a rare, useless, inanimate object, but it is constant, immutable and nobody else’s liability.  Gold imposes a discipline on people and governments which means they can’t spend it recklessly. Spending, no matter how well-intentioned, creates problems. Gold is a restrictive monetary system, but it is a fair, free and honest system."</hi> - Dominic Frisby, The Idler 42, February 2009</p>
<p>Bullionism is an argument that was demolished in the 19th Century but, thanks to the likes of Ron Paul, is making a return. Here's how to demolish it again.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Understand the terms. <figure rend="Become-a-Certified-Life-Coach-Step-2-Version-3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>fiat money</item>
<item>fiduciary money etc.</item></list></item>
<item>Study the proponents, Murray Rothbard, Ludwig von Mises, Lew Rockwell and Joseph Schumpeter. <figure rend="Become-President-of-the-United-States-Step-4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The Case for a Genuine Gold Dollar by Murray N. Rothbard.</item>
<item>The Gold Standard: Perspectives in the Austrian School. Edited with an Introduction by Llewellyn H. Rockwell, Jr. 1992. The Ludwig von Mises Institute.</item>
<item>What Has Government Done to Our Money? by Murray N. Rothbard.</item>
<item>Myth of the Gold Standard by Gary North.</item></list></item>
<item>Read the major economists who have criticized bullionism from the past and present.  <figure rend="Become-a-Millionaire-Step-6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Finance Capital by Rudolf Hilferding, Chapter 1.</item>
<item>The General Theory of Employment, Interest and Money by John Maynard Keynes, Chapter 23.<hi rend="italic">For in an economy subject to money contracts and customs more or less fixed over an appreciable period of time, where the quantity of the domestic circulation and the domestic rate of interest are primarily determined by the balance of payments, as they were in Great Britain before the war, there is no orthodox means open to the authorities for countering unemployment at home except by struggling for an export surplus and an import of the monetary metal at the expense of their neighbours. Never in history was there a method devised of such efficacy for setting each country’s advantage at variance with its neighbours’ as the international gold (or, formerly, silver) standard. For it made domestic prosperity directly dependent on a competitive pursuit of markets and a competitive appetite for the precious metals. When by happy accident the new supplies of gold and silver were comparatively abundant, the struggle might be somewhat abated. But with the growth of wealth and the diminishing marginal propensity to consume, it has tended to become increasingly internecine.</hi></item>
<item>Capital: Critique of Political Economy Volume I by Karl Marx, Chapter 3 Money, or the Circulation of Commodities.<hi rend="italic">The first chief function of money is to supply commodities with the material for the expression of their values, or to represent their values as magnitudes of the same denomination, qualitatively equal, and quantitatively comparable. It thus serves as a universal measure of value. And only by virtue of this function does gold, the equivalent commodity par excellence, become money.It is not money that renders commodities commensurable. Just the contrary. It is because all commodities, as values, are realised human labour, and therefore commensurable, that their values can be measured by one and the same special commodity, and the latter be converted into the common measure of their values, i.e., into money. Money as a measure of value, is the phenomenal form that must of necessity be assumed by that measure of value which is immanent in commodities, labour-time. </hi></item></list></item>
<item>Link up the causes of Deflation. <figure rend="Become-a-Software-Engineer-Step-10-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Explain the consequences. <figure rend="Become-a-Certified-Life-Coach-Step-12.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Recession is the consequence of deflation.</item>
<item>The Great Depression was the consequence of recession.</item></list></item>
<item>Look at why the gold standard was abandoned. The Nixon Shock was in 1971. <figure rend="Become-an-Accountant-Step-13.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
