<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc78" title="Connect a Macbook to an iMac" shortTile="connect-macbook-imac" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-09-30" dateModified="2019-09-01" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Connect_a_Macbook_to_an_iMac" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Connect a Macbook to an iMac</head><p>This wikiHow teaches you how to use your iMac as a monitor for a MacBook, as well as how to share files and printers between both computers.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Using your iMac as a Monitor</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Determine the cable you’ll need for your iMac. The type of cable you’ll need varies by model: <figure rend="Connect a Macbook to an iMac Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">iMac 27-inch (2009):</hi> Mini DisplayPort to Mini DisplayPort cable.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">iMac 27-inch (2010):</hi> Mini DisplayPort to Mini DisplayPort cable.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">iMac (2011- early 2014):</hi> Thunderbolt cable.</item>
<item>iMac models from late 2014 (the Retina 5k model) and later can’t be used as displays.</item></list></item>
<item>Locate the port on your MacBook. If both the MacBook and iMac have the same port (Mini DisplayPort or Thunderbolt), you won’t need to purchase an additional adapter. If your MacBook has a Thunderbolt 3 (USB-C) port, you’ll need a Thunderbolt 3 (USB-C) to Thunderbolt 2 adapter. <figure rend="Connect-Two-Monitors-Step-15-Version-2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>See Apple’s <ref target="https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT201736">Mac port guide</ref> to learn how to identify your ports.</item></list></item>
<item>Turn on both computers. If you haven’t yet logged in to either computer, you should do so now. <figure rend="Connect a Macbook to an iMac Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Connect the Mini DisplayPort or Thunderbolt cable to both computers. <figure rend="Connect-Two-Monitors-Step-18-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Press  on the iMac. The iMac’s display will now show the MacBook’s screen instead of its own. <figure rend="Connect a Macbook to an iMac Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Sharing Files Between Computers</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Connect both Macs to the same wireless network. If you don’t have a wireless network, you can use an Ethernet cable instead (just connect the cable to an Ethernet port on both computers, and then move to the next step). Here’s how to connect both computers to Wi-Fi: <figure rend="Connect a Macbook to an iMac Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you see  near the top-right corner of the screen, click it, and then select <hi rend="bold">Turn Wi-Fi On</hi>.</item>
<item>Click  at the top-right corner of the screen.</item>
<item>Select a network.</item>
<item>Enter the password and click <hi rend="bold">Join</hi>.</item></list></item>
<item>Click the  menu on the computer that has something to share. It’s at the top-left corner of the screen. <figure rend="Connect a Macbook to an iMac Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . <figure rend="Connect a Macbook to an iMac Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . A list of sharing services will appear. <figure rend="Connect a Macbook to an iMac Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Set up file sharing. Here’s how to allow users of the other computer to access the files on this one: <figure rend="Connect a Macbook to an iMac Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Click <hi rend="bold">File Sharing</hi>.</item>
<item>Click <hi rend="bold">+</hi> under the folder list.</item>
<item>Select a folder and click <hi rend="bold">Add</hi>.
<list type="unordered"><item>Anyone with account on this Mac can access it from the other computer. If you want to restrict access to certain users, select the folder, click <hi rend="bold">+</hi> under the user list, then select who should have access.</item>
<item>You can add users with local accounts (regular logins you set up on this Mac) or by Apple ID by selecting them from your contacts.</item></list></item>
<item>Make note of the IP address on the Sharing screen. It should look like ″afp://10.0.0.1″ or ″smb://10.0.0.1″.</item></list></item>
<item>Open Finder  on the other computer. It’ll be the first icon on the Dock, which is usually at the bottom of the screen. <figure rend="Connect a Macbook to an iMac Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the  menu. It’s at the top of the screen. <figure rend="Connect a Macbook to an iMac Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . <figure rend="Connect a Macbook to an iMac Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Enter the IP address for the other computer. This is the address you found on the other computer’s Sharing screen. <figure rend="Connect a Macbook to an iMac Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . <figure rend="Connect a Macbook to an iMac Step 15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Choose how to connect. <figure rend="Connect a Macbook to an iMac Step 16.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Select <hi rend="bold">Registered User</hi> if you want to log into a local account on the other computer.</item>
<item>Select <hi rend="bold">Apple ID</hi> to log in that way.</item>
<item>Select <hi rend="bold">Guest</hi> if the files don’t require a login.</item></list></item>
<item>Follow the on-screen instructions to log in. Once you’ve connected to the other computer, you can access its files. <figure rend="Connect a Macbook to an iMac Step 17.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Set up printer sharing (optional). If you’d like to share the printer from this computer, return to the Sharing settings, click <hi rend="bold">Printer Sharing</hi>, and choose a printer. Once shared, you’ll be able to print to it from any app on the other computer by selecting the printer (and logging in, if prompted to do so). <figure rend="Connect a Macbook to an iMac Step 18.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Anyone with an account on this computer can print by default. To select specific users, click <hi rend="bold">+</hi> under the user list, then choose who should be allowed to print.</item></list></item>
<item>Set up other types of sharing (optional). If you want users of the other computer to be able to connect to this one for remote administration or screen sharing, choose one of those options from the list, then follow the same instructions as you did for file and printer sharing. <figure rend="Connect a Macbook to an iMac Step 19.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
