<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc301" title="Help Your Child Find a Suitable Online Hobby" shortTile="help-child-find-suitable" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-10-31" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Help_Your_Child_Find_a_Suitable_Online_Hobby" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Help Your Child Find a Suitable Online Hobby</head><p>Today’s advanced technology may have made life easier, but finding an online hobby for your child is still so difficult. The many options available lead in paths that are both good and bad. So how do you make the (possibly) life-changing decision of choosing a suitable online hobby for your child?</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Prepare your computer. Set up proper filters to block any undesirable content. <figure rend="Help Your Child Find a Suitable Online Hobby Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Set strict rules. Using the computer for too long may be harmful to your child’s eyesight or may develop into a bad habit. It is important to set rules concerning how long your child is allowed to stay online and about which sites your child is allowed to access. <figure rend="Help Your Child Find a Suitable Online Hobby Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Determine your purpose. It helps to determine the reason why you want your child to find an online hobby. Do you want your child to learn something educational, learn how to use the internet better, keep them busy and out of trouble, or maybe you just want him/her to have some fun? <figure rend="Help Your Child Find a Suitable Online Hobby Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Understand your child. What are the things that your child is interested in? What does he like or dislike? Has your child expressed any particular ambition, like maybe being a pilot when he grows up? Find a site related to his interest which he can understand and enjoy. If he likes writing, making a blog for him to write stories in would be an example. <figure rend="Help Your Child Find a Suitable Online Hobby Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Think ahead. Will this hobby be harmful to my child in any way? How could this hobby benefit my child? Has this hobby been known to result in child problems? <figure rend="Help Your Child Find a Suitable Online Hobby Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Choose a hobby. After considering the various important points mentioned, you can make a good decision as to which hobby to introduce to your child. Do your research and find some good sites that you think will be appropriate and enjoyable for your child. <figure rend="Help Your Child Find a Suitable Online Hobby Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take responsibility for monitoring your child. After a certain period of time, you may tend to become used to your child’s activities and let them have some freedom in their new online hobby. Remember that it is important to teach your child proper discipline and responsibility before allowing them such freedom. Also keep in mind that no matter how disciplined or responsible your child is, a child is still a child. So, ensure that you still keep track of their activities from time to time. <figure rend="Help Your Child Find a Suitable Online Hobby Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Childhood is a time of both physical and mental growth. Find a hobby that involves physical exercise apart from your child’s online hobby.</item>
<item>The internet today is not as safe as it used to be, so setting up proper filters should not be overlooked.</item>
<item>Don't be overprotective by sitting next to your child and be a busybody in what are they doing AFTER you set up the filters. just relax</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Ensure that your child knows never to give away any personal information online.</item>
<item>Hobbies that may involve your child meeting or chatting with total strangers is not advisable.</item>
<item>Too much computer can damage your eyes. So be careful please.</item>
<item>Using the computer too much may be harmful to your child’s growth and development, so ensure that all things are done with moderation and discipline.</item></list>
</text>
