<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc284" title="Prioritise Your Health at 40 and 50" shortTile="prioritise-health" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-02-08" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Prioritise_Your_Health_at_40_and_50" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Prioritise Your Health at 40 and 50</head><p>Bodies age, it's a fact of life. Whilst many people may wish to be forever young, it's not possible. You can however take steps to stay healthy. What you need to do to prioritise your health changes as your body ages. These steps give some general guidance on prioritising your heath at the ages of 40 and 50 (chances are they will work if you're aged between 41 and 59 too)</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Your 40s and 50s really can be the best time of your life. You know yourself and are clear on your likes and dislikes. You should be feeling at your most confident and have probably already achieved a lot in your life, maybe having had children or an established career to feel proud of. For many of us during this period, our children will become more independent, leaving time to pursue hobbies and interests that you couldn’t find time for before. For those who are in relationships this may mean spending more quality time together. For those who are not, you can get out and meet others, including potential partners, with a real sense of self, and a freedom that you may not have experienced for years. Some of you may choose this time of life to begin a family. The truth is that these days, your 40s and 50s may bring a huge variety of experiences, and you are ready for them; with experience and wisdom on your side! <figure rend="Prioritise Your Health at 40 and 50 Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>You may find that you require more sleep over these years than you did in your 20s and 30s.  Try to aim for an early night, around 10pm, two to three times a week. Ensuring that you have had these extra hours sleep will not only increase energy levels during the day, but it will also help you to remain youthful looking. <figure rend="Prioritise Your Health at 40 and 50 Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For those of you with young children, power napping could be the answer.</item></list></item>
<item>Issues concerning inflammation, dehydration and cardiovascular health can become more common place as we get older so, as always, drink plenty of bottled or filtered water every day. Omega oils are thought to be helpful for cardiovascular health and inflammation, so it may be worth considering a supplement. Ginger and garlic can also be helpful and delicious inflammation fighting additions to the diet. <figure rend="Prioritise Your Health at 40 and 50 Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>As in your 20s and 30s, eat fresh foods wherever possible and include plenty of whole grains, pulses, lean meats, fish, fruit and vegetables. Try eating these items in four or five small meals a day rather than three larger portions, it will help to keep your metabolism ticking over at a healthy rate and your energy levels at an optimum. <figure rend="Prioritise Your Health at 40 and 50 Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For women, it may be worth increasing your calcium intake during these years, either by way of a supplement or by increasing (low fat) dairy intake.</item>
<item>For men, cut your cholesterol and help to keep blood pressure low with orange juice and beetroot as part of your regular diet.</item></list></item>
<item>Stay active with regular brisk walks, cycling, swimming, dancing or whatever else takes your fancy! <figure rend="Prioritise Your Health at 40 and 50 Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always consult a medical professional before embarking on a new exercise or health regime.</item></list>
</text>
