<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc273" title="Avoid Pseudoscientific Medicine" shortTile="avoid-pseudoscientific" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2016-03-27" dateModified="2019-08-09" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Avoid_Pseudoscientific_Medicine" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Avoid Pseudoscientific Medicine</head><p>The internet can provide helpful information on treating health conditions... but it can also be an excellent platform for scammers looking to take your money. Their pseudoscientific "remedies" may be useless or even dangerous to your health. Protect your health and your wallet by learning to avoid health-related scams.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Noticing Suspicious Rhetoric</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Stay away from cure-alls. Scammers want to maximize their audience, so they tend to claim that their product can cure just about anything. They may list many unrelated conditions with very different causes. Often, the only relationship between the conditions they claim to cure is that all of them are serious or scary in the public mind.
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, if a remedy supposedly can cure "cancer, asthma, autism, diabetes, and more," then it's likely it actually can't treat any of these.</item>
<item>Real medicines tend to have more scientific reasons for treating multiple conditions. For example, some medicines that treat high blood pressure can also help people with panic disorder, because they reduce spikes in blood pressure associated with panic attacks.</item></list></item>
<item>Notice "quick fix" claims for things that can't be removed quickly (or even at all). Quacks will say that their product can give results that seem impossible. If something could actually produce such miraculous results, the professional medical community would probably be incredibly excited about it. It's more likely that this product is useless.
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">They brag about quick results.</hi> For example, they may say "this can reverse diabetes in 2 weeks."</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">They say they can cure the incurable.</hi> Autism, for example, is a lifelong condition that is deeply interwoven into the brain. Autistic people can get support, but they can't be "cured" of autism.</item></list></item>
<item>Notice how they excuse a lack of results. When it comes to many legitimate medical treatments, experts will admit that the treatment won't fix every single case of the illness(es) it targets. But a scammer will try to avoid admitting this, because they don't want to risk making their product sound less reliable. Instead of saying that their product isn't a miracle cure, they'll blame the user for doing it wrong.
<list type="unordered"><item>Some scammers say that you have to believe in their product or it won't work. Thus, when you don't see any improvement, they'll blame you for not trying hard enough.</item>
<item>In the case of depression medication, for example, doctors will tell you that different pills work for different people, and it may take time to find the right one. A scammer, on the other hand, will say "this one pill can cure depression in anybody."</item></list></item>
<item>Watch out for conspiracy theories about mainstream medicine. Since mainstream organizations often publish warnings against fake medicines, peddlers of them may try to discredit criticism against themselves by saying that "mainstream medicine is conspiring against me."
<list type="unordered"><item>Charlatans may also try to scare you into buying their own medicine over mainstream medicine that has been proven to work by claiming that mainstream remedies, such as vaccines, may cause conditions like autism. Research these claims on reliable sources and ask about them with your doctor to see if they are true.</item></list></item>
<item>Consider whether the supposed way in which the "remedy" works makes sense. It may solely be pseudoscience. Beware of "remedies" that say they work because of some unexplained quantum mechanical process, and also beware of technobabble.</item></list>
<head>Digging Deeper</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Watch out for the so-called "quack Miranda warning". Peddlers of ineffective medicine may write in small print something along the lines of "these statements have not been evaluated by the Food and Drug Administration. This product is not intended to diagnose, treat, cure, or prevent any disease" on their products.</item>
<item>Look at the evidence. Safe remedies are ones that have been carefully tested by the medical community. You'll be able to find peer-reviewed studies from scientific journals testifying that the treatment is more effective than a placebo.
<list type="unordered"><item>It's not safe to conduct experiments on yourself, a family member, or a child. Leave it to the medical professionals.</item></list></item>
<item>Notice if there are warnings urging customers to avoid the "remedy."
<list type="unordered"><item>Quackwatch and Snopes offer fact-checking.</item></list></item>
<item>Beware products that have serious health consequences. When people discover that a product is dangerous, they may begin writing articles about it. See if you find any warnings that the product is damaging to people's health.
<list type="unordered"><item>"Miracle Mineral Solution," for example, involves feeding children bleach until their intestines begin to fall apart.</item></list></item>
<item>Consult a doctor if you are still unsure about these products. Check with your family doctor or specialist to see if they've heard about the product, and get their opinion.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Autism is lifelong, so if someone claims to cure it, they are not being honest. Look for <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Treat_Autism">more reliable treatments</ref>.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Using quack remedies can have serious consequences; if you use a fake drug peddled on the internet to cure a life-threatening disease in place of an actual remedy administered by an actual doctor, you may place your life in jeopardy.</item>
<item>Some fake drugs can be harmful to your body.</item></list>
</text>
