<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc176" title="Cope with Spiteful Family Members" shortTile="cope-spiteful-family" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2016-04-17" dateModified="2016-12-20" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Cope_with_Spiteful_Family_Members" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Cope with Spiteful Family Members</head><p>Family is an integral part of your life, one just can't deny that. The only trustworthy people around you are your family members ;not everybody is lucky to have other support systems in their lives. But sometimes, some of the people in your family develop spiteful nature, and nothing can be more harmful than a family member turning into an enemy. This could cause you real troubles as they know many of the things they should not know and then it backfires on you! And you just can't shut them away either!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>NEVER SPILL YOUR SECRETS UNTIL AND UNLESS YOU ARE SURE OF THEIR TRUSTWORTHINESS:-Talk about your private life only with those who matter and people you can trust. People living in joint families have to suffer in situations like this, when they tell one person something, and then the whole house knows it. It can be very embarrassing in many cases.So, try to avoid telling those family members about what is going on in your life in neat details.</item>
<item>KNOW WHO IS YOUR BEST FRIEND AND NEVER LET GO OF HIM/HER:-Not everybody is blessed to have real best friends, but those who do, they are some of the luckiest people on this earth.Blood relations don't always have to be better than friendships. You should have atleast one person who you can rely upon no matter what the situation rises.</item>
<item>DONT MAKE THEM JEALOUS:-This happens a lot in indian households. People live their lives thinking how it looks like to the world. They believe in showoff and brag about even the little things they've got. This is totally not what you should be doing. This will only make them envy you and they will leave no stone unturned to take you down. So, its better that you don't come in the limelight. This way you can enjoy doing your stuff without them knowing!</item>
<item>NUCLEAR FAMILIES ARE HAPPY FAMILIES:-Because they cut out on the daily drama.They are very close to each other, and most of all, they want to live together..this is what makes their bond strong.As long as your parents are together, their aren't any real troubles in your life on the family front. Because they will stick with you through thick and thin. You can tell them anything and everything.</item>
<item>DONT GET INTO ARGUMENTS:-Arguing with people who you are coping up with is a complete NO! NO!.Beacuse if you do so, it will only make things worse for you. Your own house will be a living hell. Don't lose your cool when they do something that you don't like. Try to make them understand very calmly. Don't be impatient.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>1.Stay out of their sight, for as much as you can do that will prove benificial.</item>
<item>2.Don't get irritated over petty things they do.</item>
<item>3.Avoid them in a way that they don't really realise that you're avoiding them, but doing so will save you a lot of headaches.</item>
<item>4.Lay low. Don't let them know about your stuff and plans, beacause you know they only hold ill-wills for you.</item>
<item>5.Stay in your own world. Think about what you want in life..make plans for it, and work your plans.</item>
<item>6.Stay happy. No matter what life throws at you..remember that everybody has its own struggles..you are not the only one..this is how the world works..</item>
<item>7.Stay satisfied in all that you have.</item></list>
</text>
