<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc15" title="Do Skull Crushers" shortTile="skull-crushers" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2017-11-18" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Do_Skull_Crushers" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Do Skull Crushers</head><p>If you're looking to work your triceps in particular, you'll find skull crushers are a good way to do it. This exercise uses gravity to specifically work this area, so start by learning the basic technique. You can switch things up a bit to work your lateral or long head muscle in your triceps. Once you've got the basics down, work on improving your technique by making a few small tweaks. Then you're ready to bulk up those triceps! </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Working on the Basic Technique</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Lie down on a bench or stability ball. Lie down on your back. Your feet should be flat on the floor and your legs should be bent at the knees. If you're on a bench, your head should be at one end of the bench so you have space to use your weights. On a stability ball, just balance in the middle of your back. <figure rend="Do Skull Crushers Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Hold weights straight out in front of you. Start with basic weights, such as dumbbells. If you haven't done this exercise before, start small, such as with 5-lb (2.3 kg) weights. Hold the weights straight out from your chest. Your wrists should face inwards. <figure rend="Do Skull Crushers Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Lower the weights towards the floor by bending your elbows. Slowly bend your elbows, lowering the weights down towards your face. Keep your upper arms perpendicular to the floor, while your forearms move. It can be hard at first, so just do your best. <figure rend="Do Skull Crushers Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Some people start in this position instead of with their arms straight. How you begin is up to you.</item></list></item>
<item>Move back to the starting position. Slowly bring your arms back up to a straightened position. Repeat the movement for a total of 12 reps. You can do another set or move on to another exercise. You can also work up to more sets over time. <figure rend="Do Skull Crushers Step 4.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Doing Variations</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Use different types of weights. Dumbbells are a good place to start, but really, you can use any type of weight for this exercise, including an EZ bar. You can also use cables or a barbell. Just use whatever is easiest for you. You can even just use canned goods as weights to start out. <figure rend="Do Skull Crushers Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Instead of having your wrists facing inward, you'll grasp the bar with the tops of your hands towards your face. Keep your hands at shoulder width or closer together.</item></list></item>
<item>Incline the bench up to work the triceps long head. Inclining the bench upwards will put more work on the long head because you're moving more toward an overhead position. If you're specifically wanting to work this muscle, increase the incline. <figure rend="Do Skull Crushers Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The triceps long head is the muscle at the back of the upper arm on the inner side.</item></list></item>
<item>Decline the bench to work the triceps lateral head. The other major muscle in the triceps is the lateral head. As you decline the bench, you'll work this muscle more, if that's your goal. You can also work the lateral head and the long head in turns by working at different inclines and declines. <figure rend="Do Skull Crushers Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The triceps lateral head is the muscle at the back of the upper arm on the outside.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Using Tricks to Make Skull Crushers More Effective</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Keep your upper arms still. With this exercise, you may be tempted to move your upper arms, too. However, that allows your shoulders to take some of the load. Since the goal of this exercise is mainly to work the triceps, try to keep those upper arms still. You can do it! <figure rend="Do Skull Crushers Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pull in your elbows. You may also be tempted to let your elbows pull away from your body, which reduces the work your triceps are doing. Keep your elbows in close to truly work your triceps as much as you can. <figure rend="Do Skull Crushers Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Aim to make your upper arms perpendicular with the floor, not your body. Gravity is your friend on this exercise. Gravity is what makes it difficult to lift the weights back up. However, if you're on an incline bench, you may be inclined to keep your upper arms perpendicular to your body. Always check to make sure your upper arms are perpendicular to the floor instead. <figure rend="Do Skull Crushers Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't go all the way up to the straightened position. If you straighten your arms completely, you likely get a little rest at the top, which feels good but doesn't work your triceps as much. However, if you stop just short, you're continuing the pressure on your arms, which helps work them that much harder. <figure rend="Do Skull Crushers Step 11.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Of course, if you need to, don't be afraid to take a break. You don't want to injure yourself.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
