<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc81" title="Disable Two Factor Authentication on PC or Mac" shortTile="disable-two-factor" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-08-27" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Disable_Two_Factor_Authentication_on_PC_or_Mac" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Disable Two Factor Authentication on PC or Mac</head><p>This wikiHow teaches you how to turn off two-step verification on your Microsoft and Google accounts, using a desktop internet browser. If you already use two-factor authentication on your Apple ID, you can no longer turn it off because certain features in macOS require it as an extra level of security.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Using a Microsoft Account</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open the <ref target="https://account.microsoft.com/account">Microsoft account</ref> page in your internet browser. Type <ref target="https://account.microsoft.com/account">account.microsoft.com/account</ref> into the address bar, and hit  or  on your keyboard. <figure rend="Disable Two Factor Authentication on PC or Mac Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the  button. It's in the upper-right corner of the page. This will open the sign-in form on a new page. <figure rend="Disable Two Factor Authentication on PC or Mac Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Sign in to your Microsoft account. Signing in will open your account dashboard. <figure rend="Disable Two Factor Authentication on PC or Mac Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Enter your email address, phone number or Skype ID.</item>
<item>Click <hi rend="bold">Next</hi>.</item>
<item>Enter your account password.</item>
<item>Click <hi rend="bold">Sign in</hi>.</item></list></item>
<item>Click the  button in the "Security" box. This will open your security options on a new page. <figure rend="Disable Two Factor Authentication on PC or Mac Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click  at the bottom. You can find this link at the bottom of the "Security basics" page. <figure rend="Disable Two Factor Authentication on PC or Mac Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Verify your identity. Depending on your account information, you can choose to get a verification code sent to your email, or texted to your phone. This will open your "Additional security options" on a new page. <figure rend="Disable Two Factor Authentication on PC or Mac Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Select a method if you're prompted.</item>
<item>Enter your code in the area provided.</item>
<item>Click <hi rend="bold">Verify</hi>.</item></list></item>
<item>Click the  link. You can find this option under the "Two-step verification" heading. <figure rend="Disable Two Factor Authentication on PC or Mac Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You will have to confirm your action in a new pop-up.</item></list></item>
<item>Click  in the confirmation pop-up. This will confirm your action, and disable two-step verification on your Microsoft account. <figure rend="Disable Two Factor Authentication on PC or Mac Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Using a Google Account</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open your <ref target="https://myaccount.google.com">Google account</ref> page in an internet browser. Type <ref target="https://myaccount.google.com">myaccount.google.com</ref> into the address bar, and hit  or  on your keyboard. <figure rend="Disable Two Factor Authentication on PC or Mac Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you're not automatically signed in, click the blue <hi rend="bold">Sign in</hi> button on the top-right, and log in with your email and password.</item></list></item>
<item>Click  under "Sign-in &amp; security.<hi rend="bold">"</hi> This will open your password and sign-in settings on a new page. <figure rend="Disable Two Factor Authentication on PC or Mac Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . You can find it in the "Password &amp; sign-in method" box. <figure rend="Disable Two Factor Authentication on PC or Mac Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Verify your account password. In order to change your security settings, you'll first have to verify it's you. <figure rend="Disable Two Factor Authentication on PC or Mac Step 12.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Enter your password.</item>
<item>Click <hi rend="bold">Next</hi>.</item></list></item>
<item>Complete the 2-step verification process. You can do this with Google prompt, or with a verification code via text message or phone call. <figure rend="Disable Two Factor Authentication on PC or Mac Step 13.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you have Google prompt, tap <hi rend="bold">Yes</hi> on your prompt device.</item>
<item>If you're using the verification code method, select whether you want to receive your code via text message or phone call, enter your code in the area provided, and click <hi rend="bold">Next</hi>.</item></list></item>
<item>Click the blue  button. You can find it near the top of the page. <figure rend="Disable Two Factor Authentication on PC or Mac Step 14.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You will have to confirm your action in a pop-up window.</item></list></item>
<item>Click  in the confirmation pop-up. This will disable 2-step verification on your Google account. <figure rend="Disable Two Factor Authentication on PC or Mac Step 15.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
