<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc97" title="Organize Apps on PC or Mac" shortTile="organize-apps-pc" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-02-16" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Organize_Apps_on_PC_or_Mac" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Organize Apps on PC or Mac</head><p>This wikiHow teaches you how to organize the apps in the Windows Start Menu and the macOS Launchpad.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Windows</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Click the  button. It’s usually at the bottom-left corner of the screen. You’ll see a list of tiles that can be organized into groups, as well as a list of apps installed on your PC. <figure rend="Organize Apps on PC or Mac Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you don’t see a list of apps to the left of the tiles, click <hi rend="bold">All Apps</hi> to display them.</item></list></item>
<item>Add a new tile to the Start menu. You can create tiles for any app on your computer. Here’s how: <figure rend="Organize Apps on PC or Mac Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Right-click an app you want to pin.</item>
<item>Click <hi rend="bold">Pin to Start</hi>. A new tile will appear for the app you’ve added.</item></list></item>
<item>Resize a tile. Tiles are large by default, but you can make them larger or smaller if you’d like. Here’s how: <figure rend="Organize Apps on PC or Mac Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Right-click the tile.</item>
<item>Click <hi rend="bold">Resize</hi>.</item>
<item>Select a size.</item></list></item>
<item>Group your apps. You can create groups of apps based on your desired criteria and then add tiles to that group. Here’s how: <figure rend="Organize Apps on PC or Mac Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Click and drag a tile up or down until a divider bar appears.</item>
<item>Release your finger.</item>
<item>Click the divider bar at the top of the group.</item>
<item>Type a name for the group (e.g. Productivity, Art).</item>
<item>Press .</item>
<item>Drag additional tiles to the group as needed.</item></list></item>
<item>Rearrange your groups. To move a group to another location, click and hold the title of the group, then drag it to a new location. <figure rend="Organize Apps on PC or Mac Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remove tiles you don’t need. Here’s how: <figure rend="Organize Apps on PC or Mac Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Right-click the tile.</item>
<item>Click <hi rend="bold">Unpin from Start</hi>.</item></list></item></list>
<head>macOS</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open your Mac’s Launchpad. You can do this by pressing the Launchpad key (6 squares in the top row of keys), or clicking the rocket icon in the dock. You’ll see a screen containing icons for many of the apps on your Mac. <figure rend="Organize Apps on PC or Mac Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you don’t see an app you know you’ve installed, you may just need to move that app to the Applications folder.</item></list></item>
<item>Move an app to a new location. To rearrange apps in the Launchpad, click and drag the app icon to the desired position. <figure rend="Organize Apps on PC or Mac Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Create a group folder. It may be helpful to organize your apps into different folders by category. Here’s how: <figure rend="Organize Apps on PC or Mac Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Drag one app icon to another icon. This creates a folder that contains just these two apps.</item>
<item>Click the folder to open it.</item>
<item>Click the name of the folder (above the app icons).</item>
<item>Type a new name for the folder (e.g. Office, Photography).</item>
<item>Press .</item>
<item>Click outside the folder to return to the main list of apps.</item>
<item>To add additional apps to the folder, drag and drop those apps onto the folder icon.</item></list></item>
<item>Delete an app from the Launchpad. This action will remove the app from your computer. Here’s how: <figure rend="Organize Apps on PC or Mac Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Open the Launchpad.</item>
<item>Press and hold .</item>
<item>Click the <hi rend="bold">X</hi> next to the app icon you want to delete. If you don’t see an X, it’s either a required Mac App or it didn’t come from the App Store.</item>
<item>Click <hi rend="bold">Delete</hi>.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
