<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc123" title="Become a Dual Enrollment Student" shortTile="become-dual-enrollment" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-06-24" dateModified="2018-06-25" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Become_a_Dual_Enrollment_Student" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Become a Dual Enrollment Student</head><p>Dual enrollment allows high school students to take college courses all while in high school. These college classes are offered to the high school students for free so it’s good to use this opportunity as much as you can. The classes you take can transfer to most universities and technical colleges in the state of Georgia and also many other colleges/universities outside of the state of Georgia. So dual enrollment is something high school students should consider.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Decide whether you're ready to take college classes. Taking on high school and college classes can be a big load to take on. It is very important to know whether you’re ready to take on these extra classes. If you’re a student that can hardly handle the regular high school classes then maybe taking both high school and college classes aren’t something you should consider. Once you start a class, you’re in the class for good unless you want to have “withdrew” under whatever the class was on your high school transcript. Having that on your transcript is not a good look so it’s important to know whether you’re ready to take on these classes beforehand.</item>
<item>Speak with your counselor to test and meet eligibility requirements. After you decide whether you’re ready to take college classes, your counselor is now your guide. Go to your counselor to test and see if you’re eligible to take college classes. The test is called the “ACCUPLACER”. You test over two different subjects which are math and reading but there are four tests. You would test on basic skills like reading comprehension, sentence skills, arithmetic/pre-algebra and elementary math. In order to meet requirements, you must score a 64 on arithmetic, 62 on the elementary math, 70 on the reading comprehension and a 72 on the sentence skills.</item>
<item>Complete dual enrollment application. The dual enrollment application or move on when ready application is basically the information the college needs on you in order for you to take the dual enrollment classes. It’s not a long application at all and only asks basic things like your name, address, school, graduation year, the college you will be taking the courses at and other basic information. Usually your counselor will give you this paper to fill out and you would return the paper back in to your counselor so it can then be passed on to the high school initiatives specialist to take back to the college.</item>
<item>Decide what classes you would like to take. When deciding on the classes you would like to take it is important to make sure you are ready to take on the responsibility of getting all your work done in each of the classes. For first timers, I would suggest you only take one classes to start off with and get a feel of it. After you have successfully passed that class then it’s okay to take on more than one class as long as you are sure you can handle the classes you take on. Your counselor can help with picking out which classes you should take.</item>
<item>Apply for financial aid. Last step on the journey to becoming a dual enrollment student is applying for financial aid. The counselor will also help with this last step. In order to apply for your financial aid you would have to go to Gafutures.com, click on the ‘Federal aid and scholarships’ tab, click ‘State financial aid applications’ on the right side, then dual enrollment funding application and it should take you to the application from there. After this application is done your counselor will finalize and approve of the class or classes you are going to take and that’s all to it!</item></list>
</text>
