<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc265" title="Get Online Health Advice" shortTile="online-health-advice" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-06-10" dateModified="2019-06-03" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get_Online_Health_Advice" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get Online Health Advice</head><p>These days, the Internet works a great medium to find the answers about the questions that you have in your mind regarding your health. But at the same time, this is also the minefield of questionable sources, outright fraud and misinformation. Therefore, before you visit any particular site to get health related questions, you must check a few tips to make sure that you are getting the best deal.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Always consider the source: While you are in search of some online health advice, it is quite obvious to get overwhelmed by the total number of sites. Besides, it is really hard to decide which site is actually reliable. Instead of conducting any random search, it is better to start with the trusted sources.
<list type="unordered"><item>The government sites are always a good alternative as these sites will inform you about numerous health topics. Additionally, you can check the medical school sites or the nationally recognized facilities for health and research.</item></list></item>
<item>Get details of the prescribed drugs from the licensed online pharmacies: The licensed online pharmacies can work like the front for the identity thief or a scammer. These sites look legitimate, include official logos and seals and offer money back guarantees. But not always. These can be fake too. So, you need to very careful while checking the details of any prescribed drugs from these stores. Otherwise, you can end up having fake, mislabeled, expired or the wrong dosage of medicines from these.
<list type="unordered"><item>Check the legitimacy of the sites first before making any purchase. Besides, the licensed sites should have one licensed pharmacist to answer the questions that you have and the sites should also have a physical address and a valid phone number. Therefore, be realistic while choosing the online pharmacy sites and choose the huge retailers as these offer lower prices due to the customer volume they serve.</item></list></item>
<item>Avoid the sites that seem to be good and true: Always avoid the sites that make huge promises about curing the serious diseases like diabetes, arthritis, multiple sclerosis, Alzheimer’s disease, HIV or cancer. Or, the sites that offer weight loss pills that help users to lose weight without eating less or without exercising. Often these sites try to fool their clients by using the terms like ancient remedies, natural, scientific remedies etc.
<list type="unordered"><item>But investing in these products are actually the wastage of money or flat-out dangerous to the health of the users. Never trust these sites only because these look professional or have several success stories. The success stories can be made up easily and models or actors can be hired to praise the products. So, before you seek the medical advice online or purchase any medication, consult with your doctor first.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
