<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc137" title="Request High School Transcripts" shortTile="request-high-school" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-11-25" dateModified="2019-10-26" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Request_High_School_Transcripts" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Request High School Transcripts</head><p>Why would you need to request copies of your high school transcripts? Colleges and universities require them as part of the application process. Some employers, particularly government agencies, require proof of all education and training of prospective employees. You may also just want to have a copy for yourself. You’ll need to do a little research, but getting a copy of your high school transcript usually isn’t too hard. (Note: this information applies only to US and Canadian schools.)</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Requesting Transcripts from a Public School (US)</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Contact your individual school. If you are currently enrolled in high school, the best way to request your transcripts is to request them from your school. <figure rend="Request High School Transcripts Step 1 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can usually request your transcripts from your high school’s registrar, student services, or student counseling office. If you aren’t sure who to contact, call your school’s main information line.</item></list></item>
<item>Contact your school district. If you have graduated recently from a public school, your records will likely be stored at your local school district office or county board of education. <figure rend="Request High School Transcripts Step 2 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Depending on your school, you may be able to request your transcripts online, over the phone, or through the mail.</item>
<item>You can search for your school district at the National Center for Education Statistics <ref target="http://nces.ed.gov/ccd/districtsearch/">website</ref>.</item></list></item>
<item>Contact your state’s Department of Education. If it’s been awhile since you graduated from high school, you may need to contact your state’s Department of Education to request your transcripts. <figure rend="Request High School Transcripts Step 3 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The US Department of Education has a searchable list by state, <ref target="http://www2.ed.gov/about/contacts/state/index.html">here</ref>.</item></list></item>
<item>Check online services. Many high schools now use services so that you can request your high school transcripts online. You can even request that your transcripts be delivered to a third party, such as a university or employer. <figure rend="Request High School Transcripts Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Over 3,400 high schools in the US use Parchment.com for transcript requests.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Requesting Transcripts from a Private School (US)</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Contact your school. Most private schools maintain student records at the individual school. <figure rend="Request High School Transcripts Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can search for your school at the National Center for Education Statistics website, <ref target="http://nces.ed.gov/surveys/pss/privateschoolsearch/">here</ref>.</item></list></item>
<item>Contact your school’s custodian of records. If your school is no longer in operation, contact the organization responsible for maintaining school accreditation in your area. This organization is usually the custodian of records for schools that close.  <figure rend="Request High School Transcripts Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, in Texas, you would contact the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools.</item></list></item>
<item>Contact your state Department of Education. If the private school you attended is no longer in operation, and you cannot contact the custodian of records for your school, contact your state’s Department of Education. Most states have a Private Schools Office that can handle your request. <figure rend="Request High School Transcripts Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Provide as much information as you can, including the school name, address, county, and your years of attendance.</item></list></item>
<item>Check online services. Many high schools now use services so that you can request your high school transcripts online. You can even request that your transcripts be delivered to a third party, such as a university or employer. <figure rend="Request High School Transcripts Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Requesting Transcripts from a School in Canada</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Check if your province allows online requests. Some provinces, such as Saskatchewan and Alberta, allow online transcript requests for secondary school (high school) transcripts. Check your province’s Ministry of Education website to see whether your province has this option. <figure rend="Request High School Transcripts Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can usually pay via credit card for online transcript requests.</item>
<item>Currently, British Columbia, Manitoba, Newfoundland and Labrador, Northwest Territories, Nunavut, Quebec, Saskatchewan, and Yukon provinces allow online requests.</item>
<item>New Brunswick, Nova Scotia, Ontario, and Prince Edward Island require you to contact your school.</item></list></item>
<item>Contact the school if you attended a public school within the past five years. In Canada, the individual provinces are responsible for public education. If you attended secondary school at a public school in Canada, you can contact the school to request your transcripts. <figure rend="Request High School Transcripts Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Most provinces have a school information finder on their Ministry of Education website that can help you find the contact information for public schools in that province. For example, Ontario’s school finder is <ref target="http://www.edu.gov.on.ca/eng/sift/">here</ref>.</item></list></item>
<item>Contact the school board. Sometimes, individual schools maintain their records in a central office, rather than keeping them at the school. You may be referred to the school board if this is the case for your school. <figure rend="Request High School Transcripts Step 11 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The Ministry of Education websites for each province usually also have a school board finder to help you find contact information. For example, Ontario’s school board finder is <ref target="http://www.edu.gov.on.ca/eng/sbinfo/boardList.html">here</ref>.</item>
<item>If you left school more than 5 years ago, you’ll need to contact the school board.</item>
<item>You’ll also need to contact the school board if you attended a public secondary school that is no longer in operation.</item></list></item>
<item>Contact the private school. Most private schools in Canada keep their transcript records on file at the school. If you attended a private school, contact your school to request a transcript. <figure rend="Request High School Transcripts Step 12 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you attended a private school that is no longer in operation, you will need to contact your province’s Ministry of Education with as much information as possible to request your transcripts.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
