<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc5" title="Tackle a Girl" shortTile="tackle-girl" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-10-21" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Tackle_a_Girl" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Tackle a Girl</head><p>The time may come when you must figure out how to tactfully tackle a girl. Odds are, it's in a playful context: rugby, football, or another contact sport. You don't want to hurt her, but you also don't want to be so gentle that you take away her agency to play the game. Do not tackle a girl without consent. Make sure that you share a common understanding of the rules. The most important thing is that you are respectful.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Reading the Situation</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Make sure you know her well enough to tackle her. You should never tackle a stranger, and you should avoid tackling someone that you've just met unless you're sure that she will be comfortable with it. If she is your sister, your relative, or your good friend, then she might feel more comfortable with you tackling her. Use your best judgment. <figure rend="Tackle a Girl Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tackle in the right setting. Tackling is a large part of many contact sports, including rugby and American football. If you are playing a contact sport with a mixed group of boys and girls, then the tackling issue will certainly come up. Consider playing flag football, two-hand touch football, or another less violent variation of the game. If you plan to tackle a girl in a non-sporting context, then you will need to be especially sure that she'll be okay with it. <figure rend="Tackle a Girl Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Play_Flag_Football">Flag football</ref> or two-hand touch football can be a great way to avoid the issue of tackling a girl. In regular football, you stop someone from running the ball by tackling them to the ground. In touch football, you only need to touch them with two hands at once. In flag football, you pull a "flag" from the runner's belt to signify that you have stopped them.</item></list></item>
<item>Make your intentions clear. Check in to be sure that the girl is comfortable with being tackled. It's better to ask ahead of time than to risk making someone feel violated. Get consent and establish a common understanding of the rules. <figure rend="Tackle a Girl Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are playing a contact sport like rugby or tackle football, make sure that everyone playing understands that he or she might get tackled. Explain the rules before you begin. If anyone is uncomfortable with being tackled, consider playing a less violent variation.</item>
<item>If you are going to tackle a sibling, a romantic interest, or a female friend, then you should be physically comfortable with one another. It's okay to play rough, but you need to make sure that you are not violating her personal space.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tackling Carefully</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Avoid touching sensitive areas. Even if the girl doesn't mind being tackled, she might not be so comfortable with you touching her breasts or her pelvic region. The legs and the midriff are usually safe. Wrap your arms around her waist, or aim low for her knees. <figure rend="Tackle a Girl Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try not to worry too much about inappropriate touching. Pretend that you are tackling a male friend, but be a bit gentler. If you obviously aren't aiming for her private areas, then there shouldn't be a problem.</item></list></item>
<item>Tackle gently. Once you wrap your arms around her for the tackle, try placing your arms on her back so that she won't be hurt when she hits the ground. If you make a diving tackle from a few steps behind, then you will tackle harder in your effort to catch up. If you are worried that you'll hurt her, try to catch up to her first, then bring her slowly to the ground – that is, if you can catch her! <figure rend="Tackle a Girl Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Respect her agency to play. Girls are tough, too. If she wants to play tackle football with you, then that is her choice. It is not necessarily your place to treat her like a delicate doll. Be careful, certainly, and treat her with respect – but do not assume that she is weak just because she is a girl! <figure rend="Tackle a Girl Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure you're only going to tackle her if it's friendly.</item>
<item>Don't hurt her.</item>
<item>Don't rush into the tackle when the mood is bad already. Let it cool down.</item>
<item>Laugh about the moment. Keep smiling.</item>
<item>Sexual tackling isn't suggested, unless she will consent</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be aware that if you tackle a girl without warning, she might be angry with you. Consider other ways to get close to her.</item>
<item>Don't tackle her unless you're sure that it's a good idea. Someone could get hurt.</item>
<item>Sexual tackling isn't suggested, unless she will consent</item></list>
</text>
