<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc145" title="Cope when a Family Member Is Diagnosed with Breast Cancer" shortTile="cope-family-member" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2019-10-26" dateModified="2019-10-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Cope_when_a_Family_Member_Is_Diagnosed_with_Breast_Cancer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Cope when a Family Member Is Diagnosed with Breast Cancer</head>Breast cancer is everywhere and it can be a very hard time for you and your family. Having a family member diagnosed with this cancer can cause stress and mental pain in a time where no matter what you need to push through, whether it is for you or someone else.
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Staying Positive</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Surround yourself with people who care about you. Keep friends, other relatives and most importantly your family. If it is your mum who gets diagnosed then make sure your there for her too. Don't separate yourself from people who you love and love you back, as when the time comes you will have no one to talk to about your feelings.</item>
<item>Ignore the haters. We all know they're out there ready to grab on to sadness and\or anger. If someone is trying to anger you or make you upset then just turn away from them and walk away. If this continues for a long time try to confront the bully and talk with a counselor or family member about it.</item>
<item>Start or continue with a hobby. Find something that you are interested in and nurture that interest. It could be something from painting, to taking a run, to reading. Just make sure that this hobby is ideal for you and you can find peace when doing this.</item>
<item>Sit down and breathe. This may sound so simple, but really if you are feeling overwhelmed, or just a bit stressed: breathe.</item></list>
<head>Maintaining Hygiene</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Shower every other day. Showers are also a way to relieve yourself of stress so enjoy your time in the shower. You can also have a bath if you prefer. If you need to you can shower every day, just be aware this can make your hair dry and brittle</item></list>
<list type="ordered"><item>Wash your face with a good cleanser. Try finding an exfoliating wash as well to clear any blocked pores. If you like to use creams try finding water-based ones so they don't clog your pores but allow your skin to breathe.
<list type="unordered"><item>A good brand of cleansers is Simple as it is made of 100% natural oils.</item></list></item>
<item>Brush your teeth twice or three times a day. It is as important to keep a healthy mouth, so remember to brush and floss.</item>
<item>Try different deodorants or body sprays. Make sure you always have some perfume or spray with you if you think you smell stinky. It also makes you nicer to be around.</item></list>
<head>Staying healthy</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Try to do at least 30 minutes of exercise a day. Even if this is just a quick walk to the shops that is enough to get your heart going and burn those calories. Plus you will have an energy boost for the rest of the day if you do this in the mornings.
<list type="unordered"><item>Exercise is also linked to being happier.</item></list></item>
<item>Try a more subtle exercise at night. It is always good to wind down before bed so try some yoga or meditation. Reading is an exercise for the mind so maybe try that as well</item>
<item>Eat healthy and balanced. Stress can lead to poor eating habits. Try to maintain a balanced diet. Try to find healthy snacks like fruit that are filling to help with stress eating.</item></list>
<head>Understand the Effects of Cancer</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>They will lose their hair if they choose to do Chemotherapy. It targets all fast-growing cells (eg. hair, nails, etc.) To avoid large chunks of hair everywhere, suggest that they try cutting their hair short or shave it off. They don't have to, but they can also use a cold cap instead of shaving their hair off.</item>
<item>Their mood will darken. Cancer lives off and feeds on a hormone called estrogen, which is the hormone that regulates the "feel-good" chemicals in the brain.</item></list>
<p>The chemotherapy targets this so cancer has nothing to feed on.</p>
<list type="ordered"><item>They will become very ill. White blood cells are fast-growing so they are destroyed with chemotherapy. This means they have no immune system, and therefore will get very ill quickly. There is an option to produce white blood cells but this could cause leg or muscle cramps. Other symptoms they could get include vomiting and headaches.</item>
<item>Chemotherapy, Surgery, and Radiotherapy. Chemotherapy is an 18-week long treatment, but after they will have the surgery. This surgery removes cancer cells, but also remove the breast. Soon after they could also decide to have breast reconstruction. Afterward, they will have radio-therapy which should eliminate cancer from coming back.</item></list>
<p>The one worst thing: Although it is very unlikely that this will happen, with all the medicine and technology doctors have now, there is a chance that they could die. This can also be because they have waited too long to have their cancer checked. If this happened the cancer cells could have reached the bloodstream causing it to travel around the body and develop into full-blown cancer. Alternatively, they could have decided they would rather die than have the treatment. Though this will be hard, you will need to push through. </p>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be aware of your body and immediately get screened for cancer if you are developing the symptoms of cancer. This applies throughout your life.</item>
<item>Cancer is not contagious.</item>
<item>Try online websites to help you get through, like the ones where people in similar situations as you can talk and help each other.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Even if the worst does come you need to stay positive or you could lead to life dangering thoughts, feelings, or conditions</item></list>
</text>
