<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc115" title="Create and Deploy a Java Web App to Google App Engine" shortTile="create-deploy-java" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-10-04" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Create_and_Deploy_a_Java_Web_App_to_Google_App_Engine" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Create and Deploy a Java Web App to Google App Engine</head><p>The Google App Engine is a Platform as a Service by Google. With App Engine, there are no servers for you to maintain. You simply upload your application and it’s ready to go. This article is for anyone who knows a little bit of web development and want to create a web application which is live and accessible to all. This tutorial uses Java Plugin of Google App Engine and Eclipse IDE.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Setting up the Environment</head>
<p>This procedure installs the Google Plugin for Eclipse and optionally the Android Developer Tools, the Google Web Toolkit SDK, and the Google App Engine SDK.</p>
<list type="ordered"><item>Start Eclipse, running JVM version 1.7.0 or later.</item>
<item>Select Help &gt; Install New Software.  <figure rend="P1s1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>In the dialog that appears, enter the update site URL into the Work with text box: "https://dl.google.com/eclipse/plugin/4.3". Press the  key. <figure rend="Gp1s2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select the checkbox next to Google Plugin for Eclipse (required). Click . <figure rend="Gp1s3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Review the features that you are about to install. Click .</item>
<item>Read the license agreements and then select "I accept the terms of the license agreements". Click . <figure rend="Gp1s4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click  on the Security Warning.</item>
<item>Click Restart Now to restart Eclipse.</item>
<item>Sign in to Google by clicking in bottom-right corner.  <figure rend="Gp1s5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Provide the Google Account Credentials and Click . <figure rend="Gp1s6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click ‘Accept’ after reading the required permissions. <figure rend="Gp1s7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Now you are logged in to your Google Account. <figure rend="Gp1s8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>You are ready to build App Engine web applications and mobile backends for your Android applications!</item></list></item></list>
<head>Creating the Application in GAE</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Go to appengine.google.com</item>
<item>Login to your account using google account credentials .A new page is opened where it displays all the  google app engine applications created by you. <figure rend="Gpstep (1) 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click ‘Google Developers Console’ link. A new window opens. <figure rend="Gpstep (2).jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Google Developers Console is opened. <figure rend="Gpstep (3).jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click ‘Create new Project’. <figure rend="Gpstep (4).jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Enter the project name and edit the app ID as desired but it must be unique. An error is shown if the app id is not available. <figure rend="Gpstep (5).jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . Your newly created app is ready. Now you can deploy the java web app code to this app id. <figure rend="Gpstep (6).jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Creating the Application in Eclipse</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open Eclipse. Go to File &gt; New &gt; Web Application Project. <figure rend="Gpstep (7).jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Enter the project name and package name. Uncheck the Google Web Toolkit. <figure rend="Gpstep (8).jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . <figure rend="Gpstep (9).jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Your project folder and its internal hierarchy will be created as shown in the figure. <figure rend="Gpstep (10).jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Open index.html which is present in the war folder of your project. <figure rend="Gpstep (11).jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Edit the HTML as desired. Currently we are not using any servlet hence remove the servlet link from the html. <figure rend="Gpstep (12).jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Open web.xml and make sure that index.html is set as the welcome file. <figure rend="Gpstep (13).jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Save the project.</item></list>
<head>Deploying the App to Google App Engine</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Right click on the project name in the package explorer. Go to Deploy &gt; Google #App Engine. A window will pop-up. <figure figure🎃👻="" rend="Gpstep (14).jpg" 🎃👻<="" 👻🎃figure="">👻🎃/figure&gt;</figure></item>
<item>Click on the 'Application Settings' link. A new window will pop-up. <figure rend="Gpstep (16).jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Enter the App ID which you previously created and click . Click .  <figure rend="Gpstep (17).jpg"></figure></item>
<item>After the app is deployed, it will open in the browser automatically. The app will be available at www.app-id.appspot.com. <figure figure🎃👻="" rend="Gpstep (18).jpg" 🎃👻<="" 👻🎃figure="">👻🎃/figure&gt;</figure></item></list>
</text>
