<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc191" title="Protect Your Family" shortTile="protect-family" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-03-23" dateModified="2019-09-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Protect_Your_Family" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Protect Your Family</head><p>Have you seen an individual without a family? or have you met someone having no family at all?  The answer could be a "Yes" or "No", any individual who has been separated or left by their immediate family member will say yes and those who are with their loved ones will say no. In this article, we will know what family is and why do we need to protect our family? Family came from the Latin word "familia" which means a group of people affiliated by consanguinity (recognized by birth), affinity (by marriage), and or co-residence and/or shared consumption. Members of the immediate family may include a spouse, parent, brother, sister, son and/or daughter. Members of the extended family may include grand-parents, aunts, uncles, cousins, nephews, nieces and/or siblings in law. It is said that family is the smallest unit composing the society but has the largest role in the success or failure of the society. Being the sole unit handled by parents, it is their responsibility to teach and guide children. This responsibility is not just a duty to their child but a duty to promote good and responsible children of the community. In order to protect the family each members has to do its responsibility from parents down to children. Parental responsibility is the legal rights and responsibilities as a parent known as "parental responsibility".</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Most important role of parental responsibility</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Provide a home for a child.</item>
<item>Protect and maintain the child.</item>
<item>Discipline the child.</item>
<item>Choosing and providing for the child's education.</item>
<item>Agreeing to the child's medical treatment.</item>
<item>Naming the child and agreeing to any change of name.</item>
<item>Looking after the child's property.</item>
<item>Parents have to ensure that their child is supported financially, whether they are of parental responsibility or not.</item></list>
<head>Child's Responsibilities to their parent and society</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Child's responsibilities to parents and family. A child has to respect his/her parent and guardians just as they have to respect their children.</item>
<item>Child's responsibility to society. A child is a full member of the society. His/her responsibility to society grow with age.</item>
<item>Child and fellow people. Children must regard respectfully to fellow people. Children cannot harm other children or adults legal interest and rights when using his/her rights.</item>
<item>Child and work. Age-appropriate and voluntary work is an important condition of a child's normal development. Child cares for him/herself, participates in the family's joint activities and work. The state and local governments create necessary conditions for children's work. Social services observe the children's work being in accordance to the requirements of work safety and healthcare and the principals of this law.</item>
<item>Child's school obligation. A child has the obligation to attend school according to the basic- and secondary education law.</item>
<item>Child's responsibility to keep his/her health. Every child has to keep his/her health and not ruin it, in order to fully proceed in life one day.</item>
<item>The limits of freedom of mobility for minors (1) A child is obliged to follow the public order.</item></list>
</text>
