<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc196" title="Find Relatives Abroad" shortTile="find-relatives-abroad" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-01-13" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Find_Relatives_Abroad" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Find Relatives Abroad</head><p>When a relative or friend goes missing abroad, it can be very distressing. You may be confused about what you should do. This article will explain first steps you can take, what you can do to help, and additional resources that can help in finding a missing relative abroad.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Establishing Whether or Not The Person is Missing</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Consider the possibilities. Before concluding that a person is missing, seek out a reasonable explanation for their behavior and whether or not you need to be concerned. Asking family and friends is an important step, as they will be most familiar with the person's routine and are often the first to notice when something is amiss. For instance, if the missing person normally contacts them but hasn't talked to them for a considerable amount of time, it may be reasonable to assume that something has happened.</item>
<item>Attempt to make contact. If you feel concerned about your relative's wellbeing, try to contact the potentially missing person before jumping to conclusions. It's best to call their personal or work number for a quicker response. If you receive no reply, leave a voicemail before sending an e-mail asking and checking any information from past correspondence. If there is no immediate response, you should ask friends and family if they have had any recent contact. Contact any traveling companions to see if they have information.</item>
<item>Check their last traces. Look into their social media for updates or information on their travel plans or last location. Use any recently tagged photographs to identify who they were recently with before contacting those people as well. If you know where they are staying, call their accommodations to see if they are still there or have left. You should also contact their financial institute and ask if they can release information on where their credit or debit card was last used. Don't forget to contact the airline they are traveling with and relay your concerns before seeking details about their traveling arrangements. They may also be able to put an alert on the missing persons reservation to contact you if someone checks into the reservation.</item></list>
<head>Contacting the Authorities</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Contact the local police. If you receive no reply from the person or believe they're in trouble, it's best to alert the authorities so that they can assist you. Once you have called them, they will take a missing persons report from you. From there, you can request that they notify your country's consular officials to begin the search. You may also wish to contact your government's consular services to make a report with them as well.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Have information about the missing person ready</hi>. When filling out the missing persons report with police, you will be asked specific information about the person, such as:
<list type="unordered"><item>Full name</item>
<item>Place and date of birth</item>
<item>Nationality, including any other citizenship they may have</item>
<item>Passport number (if known)</item>
<item>Height</item>
<item>Weight</item>
<item>Eye color</item>
<item>Hair color</item>
<item>Recent photograph</item>
<item>Blood type</item>
<item>Identifying features (marks, scars, glasses, tattoos, etc.)</item>
<item>Known travel details and plans, including itineraries</item>
<item>Names and contact details of employers and people they have been travelling with</item>
<item>Details about the last contact they made</item>
<item>When you were expecting them to contact you next</item>
<item>Any information you found while trying to make contact.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Understanding What Happens Next</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be patient. The government agency responsible for citizens abroad will determine whether or not the person is deemed missing. If they are considered missing, the consulate will establish contact with the authorities in the country they best believe the person is in. After that, the consulate will try to get in contact with local authorities in the last known country. They will attempt to establish when and where the missing person entered and exited the country.
<list type="unordered"><item>Due to certain factors such as varying privacy laws or government relations, accessibility and availability to information may be restricted. This will vary country to country.</item></list></item>
<item>Keep an eye out for messages. If the missing person contacts you, immediately notify your local police and consulate. They may be able to pinpoint the missing person's location and perhaps even rescue them faster.</item>
<item>Understand the person may have disappeared for a reason. In certain countries, if the consulate is able to contact the person, and they wish to disassociate themselves from friends and family for legitimate reasons such as removing themselves from a harmful environment, the consulate will be unable to pass along any information.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>There are many organizations that are ready and willing to help you expand your search. These organizations are usually classified as  Non-Government Organizations or <hi rend="italic">NGO's.</hi> They can be particularly helpful if your consulate is having trouble accessing information from the foreign country, as many have offices in different countries and are able to give local information.
<list type="unordered"><item>Examples are the <ref target="http://familylinks.icrc.org/en/Pages/home.aspx">International Committee for the Red Cross</ref>, the <ref target="http://www.lbtrust.org/#!somebody-is-missing/c1mfi">Lucy Blackman Trust</ref> which supports British people missing abroad, and the <ref target="http://missingpersons.asia/">Missing Persons in Asia</ref> which specifically focuses on finding travelers lost in Southeast Asia.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
