<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc150" title="Handle Evenings and Weekends with Your Family" shortTile="handle-evenings-weekends" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-10-09" dateModified="2018-10-12" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Handle_Evenings_and_Weekends_with_Your_Family" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Handle Evenings and Weekends with Your Family</head><p>For most families, nights and weekends are a big challenge. Hopefully this article will remove the stress and make the weekends easier.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Quick easy suppers</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Nighttime food is a life lesson no matter what the situation is. It is so scary but it is just people and groceries. <figure rend="Handle Evenings and Weekends with Your Family Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure your child(ren) have done all homework, this will make sure no one is rushing around doing homework in the morning. <figure rend="Handle Evenings and Weekends with Your Family Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Clean up the table and kitchen. <figure rend="Handle Evenings and Weekends with Your Family Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>During the above steps make sure there are no distractions, such as the telephone t.v.,or computer <figure rend="Handle Evenings and Weekends with Your Family Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Put on the washing after checking with everyone to see if there is a certain piece of clothing they just have to have for the next day. <figure rend="Handle Evenings and Weekends with Your Family Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>This is a good time to start baths and finish up lessons. <figure rend="Handle Evenings and Weekends with Your Family Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tend to the load of  of wash and see that all clothes are laid out for the next morning. This includes shoes and back-packs afterwards make sure all homework are in the backpack and brief cases are ready to go. <figure rend="Handle Evenings and Weekends with Your Family Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>You can now bring back phones &amp; TV. <figure rend="Handle Evenings and Weekends with Your Family Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Depending on the varying sleep schedules (if any) for all members of the house, it is wise to check any alarms as well as any charging of equipment needed for the morning.  <figure rend="Handle Evenings and Weekends with Your Family Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Getting Groceries &amp; Other Items</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>To make faster and better budgeted shopping, it is highly advisable to create a list of items needed for the household before setting out to the store. <figure rend="Handle Evenings and Weekends with Your Family Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>It is wise to keep a pen and paper in the kitchen to list items when you run out of them or simply when you think up of an item you wish to purchase on your next shopping trip. <figure rend="Handle Evenings and Weekends with Your Family Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>To avoid food wastage and overspending, it is recommended to make the list consisting of certain recipes for meals that you plan to make ahead of time. <figure rend="Handle Evenings and Weekends with Your Family Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Aside from food products, make sure you check any other household items that need replacing or additions such as, toiletries, laundry soap, trash bags etc. <figure rend="Handle Evenings and Weekends with Your Family Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Consulting family members for any items they might need or want is also key in avoiding any hassles or regrets afterwards. <figure rend="Handle Evenings and Weekends with Your Family Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>There is no "fixed" day of the week for optimal shopping time, it is up to the buyer to when such plans are to be made based on their free time and availability.  <figure rend="Handle Evenings and Weekends with Your Family Step 15.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Week-ends</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Depending on the schedules of each household member for a change of pace each week, a night out either for eating, watching a movie, or simply just some family time at home is advisable. <figure rend="Handle Evenings and Weekends with Your Family Step 16.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Depending on the cleaning schedules for the household as well as who performs the tasks, the week-ends are usually the free time when such tasks are implemented due to the lack of time during the start of the week.</item></list>
</text>
