<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc286" title="Be Mentally and Physically Healthy" shortTile="mentally-physically" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-06-24" dateModified="2019-10-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_Mentally_and_Physically_Healthy" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be Mentally and Physically Healthy</head><p>Do you want to feel and look healthy, physically and mentally? Well, here are some tips to help you out.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Drink water. Drinking water gives you energy and helps you through the day. Water also makes your skin look and feel great. So drinking 8 cups of water a day scattered throughout the day is great for your health. <figure rend="Be Mentally and Physically Healthy Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Follow the food pyramid. You need to follow the food pyramid and should get 6 or more servings of bread and cereals, 2-5 servings of fruits and veggies, 2 servings of dairy and meat, and only eat what it says to eat. Doing this will make sure you get as many servings as needed to get all the necessary vitamins. You can eat fats, oils, and sweets occasionally. <figure rend="Be Mentally and Physically Healthy Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get enough sleep. Make sure that you get at least 8 hours of sleep. If you are under the age of 13, get 10-11 hours of sleep each night. If you don't, you won't be able to function well mentally or physically throughout the day. <figure rend="Be Mentally and Physically Healthy Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take care of your hair. Washing your hair depends on your hair type. If your hair is really oily, wash it every day. However, if it's dry, wash it every other day, so that you don't develop dandruff. If your hair gets really frizzy when you wash it and you don't have the time to straighten it every day, and you don't have the money to get it professionally straightened then you should use dry shampoo. It's also important to brush your hair at least twice a day. This helps to distribute natural oils. <figure rend="Be Mentally and Physically Healthy Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wear clean clothes. It is important to wear clean clothes so that you don't smell and so that you aren't all sweaty. <figure rend="Be Mentally and Physically Healthy Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be clean. Shower at least once a day and wash your face twice a day for clean skin. <figure rend="Be Mentally and Physically Healthy Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take care of your teeth. Brush your teeth twice a day, floss, and use mouthwash. <figure rend="Be Mentally and Physically Healthy Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Read. Read at least once a day, especially on the weekends and during summer when you're not in school. It's also a good idea to read at least 20 minutes per night. You don't have to read a 500-page novel. Even reading things like your favorite magazine, or Yahoo news will keep your mind healthy and moving. <figure rend="Be Mentally and Physically Healthy Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Exercise. Keep a daily routine to exercise your mind as well as your body.</item>
<item>Relax. Make sure you have some time to spare for yourself every day. Use that time to engage in a relaxing technique to clear off your mind and body of the stress and fatigue received during the day.</item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Little 10 minute workouts at home or even just running around the hall with your friends is good exercise. As long as you're moving.</item>
<item>Don't just exercise your body. It's important to exercise your mind too.</item>
<item>Some fitness ideas are Windsor Pilates, treadmill running, step aerobics, and some gyms even offer free child care while you pump the iron.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure that you stick to being healthy. Don't just start and forget about it after. Being healthy can't be a little fad!</item>
<item>Following diet fads can be dangerous. You could lose key nutrients to being healthy.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>A good book</item>
<item>Treadmill (Optional)</item>
<item>Yoga Mat (Also optional)</item></list>
</text>
