<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc54" title="Become a Good Major League Baseball Player" shortTile="become-good-major" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2013-10-20" dateModified="2017-02-23" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Become_a_Good_Major_League_Baseball_Player" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Become a Good Major League Baseball Player</head> Lots of boys dream of playing baseball at the Major League level. You need two general qualities in order to become a Major Leaguer. First you need to be an exceptionally talented player. Major Leaguers make the game of baseball look easy to play. It's <hi rend="italic">not.</hi> It is an extremely difficult game to play <hi rend="italic">well.</hi> Secondly -- and just as important -- you need to be very motivated. A talented player who really doesn't care much about making it to the Majors probably won't. There's so much competition that only the most talented and motivated players will succeed at the Major League level. Here are a few tips.
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Learn every aspect of the game. The easiest way to learn the game is to <hi rend="italic">play</hi> it. The finer points of baseball are a bit complicated, but you can start out simply by joining in a pick-up game and just having fun. If you find you like what you see, start asking questions and learning the rules and the techniques inherent in the game. Ask coaches and other players for pointers. A good coach wants to help young people learn to play well.  <figure rend="Become a Good Major League Baseball Player Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Join a team. Once you've learned the basic rules and skills involved, look for a school or community team to join so you can practice the game. It takes a lot of practice -- a <hi rend="italic">lot</hi> of it -- to get to the point where higher-level teams will invite you to play with them. Playing with better teams will make <hi rend="italic">you</hi> better.   <figure rend="Become a Good Major League Baseball Player Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try different positions. Baseball teams consist of nine different defensive positions. Try them all. You'll find you're better at some positions than others. Once you find a position you like, concentrate on it, and practice playing that position a lot. Most Major Leaguers are very good at playing one or more defensive positions.  <figure rend="Become a Good Major League Baseball Player Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Learn to hit. Hitting (batting) a well-pitched ball is not easy. This takes a huge amount of practice to do well. Most Major League players are very good hitters. If you can learn to hit a baseball well, you will greatly increase your chances of making it to the Majors. Have someone throw balls to you. Practice making bat contact with the ball. Good hitters will make solid contact with the ball and as they get older and stronger will hit the ball longer distances. (The longer, the better.) If you hit well and can also play good defense, you'll attract attention, and teams will ask you to join them.</item>
<item>Consider pitching. Pitcher is the most specialized position on a team. For most people it's also the most difficult position to play. Let a coach see how you can throw a ball. A good coach will know if a young player has the potential to be a pitcher and will help guide such a player in developing appropriate skills safely. Pitching is not for everyone, but give it some thought.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't be afraid to join more competitive teams. If you play with others who are better players than you are, you'll become a better player yourself. If you have any hopes of being a Major Leaguer, you have to play with the best players possible.</item>
<item>The usual progression for Major Leaguers is to play Little League and higher levels of community ball, then high school and college play, followed by professional ball in the minor leagues. Success at any of these levels requires a huge commitment of time and energy.</item>
<item>Remember that motivation and dedication are essential to the success of any athlete in any sport.</item>
<item>Don't be afraid to strike out while hitting. Even good Major Leaguers strike out 6 times out of 10.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Baseball can be a dangerous game, particularly around home plate. Wear appropriate gear when batting (or playing catcher). You'll also have to get over your fear of being hit by a thrown ball. The only way to do that is to get hit a few times. It doesn't feel good, but it won't kill you either. No one who's afraid of the ball is going to make it to the Majors.</item>
<item>Don't get discouraged. Becoming a Major League player is quite difficult. Keep practicing. That is absolutely the only way to succeed.</item></list>
</text>
