<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc2" title="Incline Bench Press" shortTile="incline-bench-press" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2019-10-02" dateModified="2019-10-22" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Incline_Bench_Press" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Incline Bench Press</head><p>The incline bench press is a variation of the well known flat bench press. Like all variations of bench pressing the workout is done for strength training, gaining muscle mass, and for sports. The incline bench press focuses on the upper chest, and part of your shoulders. The workout can be done to increase flat bench press, and to have a fuller chest.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Stretch the upper body muscle groups to avoid injuries. <figure rend="Arm stretch.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>It is important to stretch the right muscle groups before any workout to reduce the risk of injuries or cramps.</item>
<item>For an incline bench press <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Stretch">stretching the arms, chest, and back</ref> is recommended.</item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Supplement_Your_Stretching_Routine_With_Dynamic_Stretching">Dynamic</ref> or static stretches are both okay to do.</item></list></item>
<item>Warmup using lighter weights before working up to the desired amount of weight.
<list type="unordered"><item>Warming up before working out is recommended just as much as stretching.</item>
<item>Prepare the joints and the core muscles that are going to be used to avoid any unnecessary injuries.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Deciding reps.jpg"></figure>Decide how many reps and sets you are going to do for the workout.
<list type="unordered"><item>Setting a goal for the workout may help with motivation.</item>
<item>Knowing your physical limit is important as to not overwork your muscles and cause injuries.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Putting weight.jpg"></figure> Put the desired weight on the bar.
<list type="unordered"><item>Add weight that you are comfortable lifting on your own if no one is available to be a spotter.</item>
<item>The bar itself is 45 pounds, so keep that in mind when adding weight.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Sitting bench .jpg"></figure>Sit on the bench.</item>
<item>Get a spotter if necessary.
<list type="unordered"><item>When lifting a heavy weight, or attempting a personal record, a spotter is helpful to avoid injuries in case of failure.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Proper postition.jpg"></figure> Get in the proper position.
<list type="unordered"><item>Sit back onto the incline bench, with feet firmly planted on the ground.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Bar grip.jpg"></figure>Grip the bar properly.
<list type="unordered"><item>Grip the bar an equal distance apart so the weight is equally distributed.</item>
<item>Make sure your grip is solid and your comfortable with the way you are gripping it.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Unrack.jpg"></figure> Unrack the weight and start the exercise.
<list type="unordered"><item>Push up the barbell, and lock your elbows this is the start position.</item>
<item>If a spotter is present, they may be able to help with the lift off.</item>
<item>Taking a deep breath before lifting off may help with unracking the weight.</item>
<item>Take a deep breath as you bring the bar down, and breathe out through your mouth as you're pushing up.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Resting on bench.jpg"></figure> Rest in between sets and do as many as desired.</item>
<item><figure rend="Wipe bench.jpg"></figure> Get off the bench and wipe it off, especially if it is sweaty.
<list type="unordered"><item>It is proper gym etiquette to wipe off whatever equipment that was used for the following person.</item></list></item>
<item><figure rend="Rerackingweights.jpg"></figure> Re-rack the weights for the next person to use
<list type="unordered"><item>It is common gym etiquette to put the weights away after you are done.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Stretch and lift some lighter weights to avoid injuries.</item>
<item>If you are working with a heavier weight, less reps would be best.</item>
<item>Focus on the chest, the anterior deltoids, and triceps.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you think the weight may be too much, get a spotter to make sure you don't get injured.</item></list>
</text>
