<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc94" title="Set an Alarm with Google Home" shortTile="set-alarm-google" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-03-15" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Set_an_Alarm_with_Google_Home" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Set an Alarm with Google Home</head><p>This wikiHow teaches you how to set an alarm using voice commands for a Google Home device or the Google Assistant. You can also do things like name alarms, make alarms recurring, ask about your active alarms, set an alarm to music or use the snooze function.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Say, "OK Google," to wake your Google Home device. If you're using a Google Home, Google Home Mini, or Google Max speaker, you can also say <hi rend="italic">"Hey, Google,"</hi> as the wake word instead. <figure rend="Set an Alarm with Google Home Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are using the Google Assistant on your phone you may need to turn on the screen or unlock the device first.</item>
<item>On the iPhone, you will need to open up the Google Assistant app first.</item></list></item>
<item>Ask Google to set a one-time alarm. Say, <hi rend="italic">"OK Google, set an alarm for 7:15 AM,"</hi> to have Google Assistant set an alarm that will sound when it turns the time you specified. <figure rend="Set an Alarm with Google Home Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can also ask, <hi rend="italic">"OK Google, set an alarm,"</hi> and Google will respond by asking <hi rend="italic">"Ok, when's the alarm?"</hi> You can respond by saying a time without needing to say <hi rend="italic">"OK Google."</hi></item></list></item>
<item>Ask Google to set a recurring alarm. Say, <hi rend="italic">"OK Google, set an alarm for 6 AM on Tuesdays and Thursdays."</hi> Google will create an alarm that will repeat every Tuesday and Thursday. <figure rend="Set an Alarm with Google Home Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can also say, <hi rend="italic">"OK Google, set a recurring alarm,"</hi> and Google Home will prompt you to say the time and days you would like the alarm to repeat.</item>
<item>Say, <hi rend="italic">"OK Google, set an alarm for 8 AM every day,"</hi> if you'd like the alarm to go off at the same time every day.</item></list></item>
<item>Name your alarms. This can be helpful when you have multiple alarms set and want to be able to tell them apart. You can simply say, <hi rend="italic">"OK Set an alarm for 7 AM called 'Medicine'"</hi>. <figure rend="Set an Alarm with Google Home Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Although Google Assistant doesn't tell you what alarm is ringing when it goes off, you can ask <hi rend="italic">"OK Google, what alarm is this?"</hi> and Google will respond with, <hi rend="italic">"You have an alarm called 'Medicine' that is going off right now."</hi></item></list></item>
<item>Ask Google to set a music alarm. You can easily set alarms to play with a specific artist, song, or genre of music. For example, you could say <hi rend="italic">"OK Google, set an alarm for 8 AM that plays the Beatles."</hi> If you just say the artist's name, the song will be chosen at random, but you can say the name of a specific song. If the song you want to play has a common name, you can specify the song by a specific artist. <figure rend="Set an Alarm with Google Home Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You must have access to the music you're requesting to play with a music streaming service that's connected to your Google Home, such as Spotify or Google Play Music before this will work.</item></list></item>
<item>Ask about your active alarms. You can ask Google what alarms are currently active, what time they are set for, or ask about a specific alarm by name. For example: <figure rend="Set an Alarm with Google Home Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">"OK Google, what alarms are set?"</hi></hi> Tells you about all the active alarms and what times they are set for.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">"OK Google, what time is my 'Medicine' alarm?"</hi></hi> Tells you about the specific alarm.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">"OK Google, what time is my alarm tomorrow?"</hi></hi> Tells you about all the alarms that are scheduled for tomorrow.</item></list></item>
<item>Snooze or stop an alarm. If you want to stop an alarm that is going off you can snooze it by saying, <hi rend="italic">"OK Google, snooze."</hi> The default snooze time is 5 minutes, but you can snooze for a specific time by saying, <hi rend="italic">"OK Google, snooze for 11 minutes."</hi> You can turn off any alarm that is going off by saying, <hi rend="italic">"OK Google, stop,"</hi> or you can tap touch controls at the top of of your Google Home speaker. <figure rend="Set an Alarm with Google Home Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Ask Google to cancel alarms. If you named your alarms, you can cancel them individually by saying, <hi rend="italic">"OK Google, cancel my 'Medicine' alarm."</hi> However, if you have multiple alarms that aren't labeled or you can't remember their names, you can simply say <hi rend="italic">"OK Google, cancel an alarm"</hi> and Google will tell which alarms are set and then ask you which one you want to cancel. <figure rend="Set an Alarm with Google Home Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can cancel all the alarms at once by simply saying, <hi rend="italic">"OK Google, cancel all the alarms."</hi></item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Remember, if you have an important event planned, be sure to set a backup alarm on your phone or a battery operated alarm clock. If your power or Internet goes out during the time the alarm is set to go off, it will not chime!</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
