<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc93" title="Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac" shortTile="record-skype-interview" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-04-04" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Record_a_Skype_Interview_on_PC_or_Mac" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac</head><p>This wikiHow teaches you how to record an audio or video interview in Skype for Windows or macOS.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Recording a Voice Interview (Windows)</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Install MP3 Skype Recorder for Windows. This free app is recommended by Skype for recording audio calls. You can get it for free from <hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://voipcallrecording.com">https://voipcallrecording.com</ref></hi>. <figure rend="Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Open MP3 Skype Recorder. It’s in the <hi rend="bold">All Apps</hi> area of the Start menu. The app will launch in “On” mode, meaning it’s waiting for your Skype call to begin. <figure rend="Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select your audio settings. The app will detect your microphone and speakers by default. If you want to select different devices, remove the check mark from the box, then select the appropriate options from the menus. <figure rend="Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select a recording destination. If the default folder under “Recordings destination folder” is alright with you, skip to the next step. If not, enter a different path into the field. <figure rend="Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Open Skype. You’ll find it in the <hi rend="bold">All Apps</hi> section of the Start menu. <figure rend="Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wait for your interview call. When the call comes in, a notification will appear on the screen. <figure rend="Pay-Taxes-in-the-UK-Step-16.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the phone receiver to answer the call. The Skype recorder will record your end of the call as well as the interviewer’s. <figure rend="Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>When the call is complete, you’ll see a notification that the call has ended. The recording will be saved to the specified folder as an .mp3 file.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Recording a Video Interview (Windows)</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Install Free Video Call Recorder for Skype. It's a free app by DVD Video Soft. <figure rend="Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Open Video Call Recorder. The app installs to the <hi rend="bold">All Apps</hi> area of the Start menu. A confirmation message will appear, reminding you to let the other party know you’ll be recording the call. <figure rend="Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . <figure rend="Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select  from the “Recording mode” menu. <figure rend="Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select a recording destination. If the default folder under “Output folder” is alright with you, skip to the next step. If not, click <hi rend="bold">Browse…</hi> to select a different folder now. <figure rend="Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Open Skype. You’ll find it in the <hi rend="bold">All Apps</hi> section of the Start menu. <figure rend="Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wait for your interview call. When the call comes in, a notification will appear on the screen. <figure rend="Remove-Late-Payments-from-Your-Credit-Report-Step-8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the video camera to answer the call. Though you’re connected to the call, the recorder is not yet recording. <figure rend="Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac Step 15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Return to Video Call Recorder and click the Record button. It’s the red circle button at the top of the window. This records the video call until you press stop. <figure rend="Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac Step 16.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the Stop button when you’re finished. It’s the blue square at the top of the window. <figure rend="Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac Step 17.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . This opens the folder to which the video was saved. To watch the video, double-click it to open it in your default video player. <figure rend="Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac Step 18.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Recording an Audio or Video Interview (macOS)</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Open Quicktime on your Mac. It’s in the <hi rend="bold">Applications</hi> folder. <figure rend="Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac Step 19.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If Quicktime prompts you to pick a file, click <hi rend="bold">Done</hi> to dismiss the window.</item></list></item>
<item>Click the  menu. It’s at the top-left corner of the screen. <figure rend="Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac Step 20.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click  or . <figure rend="Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac Step 21.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the down-arrow next to the record button. Some options will appear. <figure rend="Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac Step 22.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select an audio source. Choose the audio source you want to use in your recording such as the internal microphone or speaker output. <figure rend="Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac Step 23.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click red record button. It’s the red circle at the center of the window. This begins your recording. <figure rend="Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac Step 24.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are recording video, you will need to click the screen after clicking the record button to begin recording.</item></list></item>
<item>Open Skype on your Mac. It’s in the <hi rend="bold">Applications</hi> folder. <figure rend="Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac Step 25.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Answer the audio or video call. <figure rend="Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac Step 26.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Return to Quicktime and click Record. It’s the red circle at the center of the window. This begins your recording. <figure rend="Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac Step 27.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click Stop when the call is complete. If you were making an audio recording, it’s in the Quicktime window where the play button used to be. If you were doing a Screen recording, it’s in the menu bar at the top of the screen on the right-side. <figure rend="Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac Step 28.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click the  menu. It’s at the top-left corner of the screen. Now you must export the file to save it. <figure rend="Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac Step 29.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Click . Several saving options will appear. <figure rend="Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac Step 30.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Select your audio or video quality options. If you recorded video, select your desired file quality. If you recorded audio, select <hi rend="bold">Audio only</hi>. <figure rend="Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac Step 31.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Name the file and click . The file is now saved to your computer. <figure rend="Record a Skype Interview on PC or Mac Step 32.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
