<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc165" title="Convince Your Parents to Let You Grow Up" shortTile="convince-parents" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-05-29" dateModified="2018-07-09" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Convince_Your_Parents_to_Let_You_Grow_Up" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Convince Your Parents to Let You Grow Up</head><p>Parents can be very strict at times, or at points you may feel uncomfortable requesting permission to do certain activities or to purchase certain "new" items. This article will help you to understand how to easily do this, without having too much of the stress that comes with these problems.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Gaining privileges</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Begin to ask your parents for more privileges. For example, you may want to start drinking coffee, choose your own clothes, be more independent. The first thing to do is ask. Just push yourself to ask them, and if you feel afraid, ask yourself: "What's the worst that could happen? They could just say no."</item>
<item>Tell them why you wish to be able to do something. Explain the reasons for why they should allow you to do it, how it could positively affect you.</item>
<item>End by asking them to consider your request. Make sure to be respectful of their decision when speaking to them, and try to compromise. Remember, you most likely won't get exactly what you want on the first try. Just accept what you can receive, because once you show them you are responsible with the privilege, they will allow you to do more and eventually you will reach your original goal, and feel proud of yourself.</item></list>
<head>Dating</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Ask if you can begin dating. Yes, you have reached that point. You want to start looking for that special someone, after all life is short. Again, you must show your parents you will be responsible with the privilege, and if you make any mistakes you will learn from them.</item>
<item>Allow them to ask you questions about who you are considering to date, why you wish to date, and how far you will take it. Answer these questions honestly; after all, it will help you in the long run and you don't want them to have a lack of trust in you.
<list type="unordered"><item>Make it clear that you do not want a play-date but a date. But at the same time you don't want to take it too far.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Doing things alone</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Ask if it's okay to start going to places by yourself. We all have been there. You want to go to the movies, pool, bowling alley, anywhere really with your friends to get away from your parents.</item>
<item>Allow your parents to know that you are safe, giving reasons as to why you would be safe there. Explain that they will be able to contact you. Listen to any special requests they may desire. Again, the more they trust you, the more things they will allow you to do in the future.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't come home with no money left, (if they happen to give you any), high on caffeine (or drugs) and definitely no smoking or any of the sort if you wish to go anywhere in the near future, namely, none of these things until you are out of college and start paying your own bills.</item>
<item>Respect your parents requests, but at the same time let them know that you want them to respect yours in return.</item></list>
</text>
