<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc12" title="Throw a Ball Faster" shortTile="throw-ball-faster" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-05-31" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Throw_a_Ball_Faster" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Throw a Ball Faster</head><p>In several ball-based sports—including baseball, softball, and dodgeball—the speed of the throw is important. But throwing a ball quickly is about more than just whipping your arm forward. If you’d like to throw a ball faster—even if it’s just for a fun game of catch, not related to any organized sport—you’ll need to perfect your stance and body positioning, and use your wrist and fingers to put an extra burst of speed on the ball as you release it.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Getting into a Stance</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Hold your hands together at chest height. If you’re playing baseball or softball, this will be a familiar position. To begin a fast throw, cup your glove (if applicable) around the ball and hold both directly in front of your sternum. <figure rend="Throw a Ball Faster Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Hold a baseball or softball with your index finger, middle finger, and thumb. With the ball in your glove, use these 3 fingers to keep a tight grip on the ball. You’ll use these 3 fingers to throw the ball as well. It might feel tempting to hold the ball with all 5 fingers, but the extra fingers will only slow down the throw. <figure rend="Throw a Ball Faster Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you're playing with a larger ball, such as a dodgeball, you can use all 5 fingers to hold the ball.</item>
<item>Hold the ball in your dominant hand.</item></list></item>
<item>Stand with your feet about shoulder-width apart. Move your feet until they’re  apart. Standing with your feet shoulder-width apart will allow you to use your lower body strength to accelerate the speed of your throw. <figure rend="Throw a Ball Faster Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This stance will also give you plenty of mobility, so you can move if necessary without losing your balance.</item></list></item>
<item>Stand sideways, perpendicular to your target. Your shoulders should be pointing at your target, with your dominant arm further away from the target. Standing sideways to your target will allow your arm a fuller range of motion than if you were facing your target. It also allows you to bring your legs into the pitch and use their strength to throw the ball faster. Your shoulders and leading elbow should both point in the direction you want to throw the ball. <figure rend="Throw a Ball Faster Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Look down at your feet before you throw: they should be pointing ahead of you, perpendicular to the direction of your shoulders.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Beginning the Throw</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Draw your arm back and keep the ball facing the ground. As you start to wind up for a pitch, pull the ball out of your glove (if applicable) and extend your arm back behind you. Keep your 3-fingered grip on the ball, and make sure that your index and middle fingers stay on top. Your thumb and the bottom of the ball should face the ground. <figure rend="Throw a Ball Faster Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This will maximize your range of motion, which in turn maximizes the amount of speed you can give the throw.</item>
<item>Keep your front elbow close to your torso, with the glove extended about  in front of you.</item>
<item>If you're throwing a dodgeball, you'll need all 5 fingers to grip it.</item></list></item>
<item>Hold the ball behind you, at the same height as your shoulder. Wind up for the pitch by drawing your arm back behind you. Your arm should be fully outstretched at this point, and the ball should be at the same height as your shoulders. Keep your index and middle fingers on top of the ball the entire time. <figure rend="Throw a Ball Faster Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>When your arm is extended, hold the ball so that your thumb, index, and middle fingers are pointing away from you. Do not hold the ball so that your fingers point back towards your head.</item></list></item>
<item>Lean your torso forward. For added force, use your rear leg to push the weight of your body forward so most of your weight rests on your front leg. As you move forward, your hips will start to rotate as well. This is good; opening up your hips and generating torque with your torso will help you throw a fast ball. <figure rend="Throw a Ball Faster Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>As you lean forward, your throwing arm will start to come around. Let your elbow bend at about a 90° angle, and keep the ball facing the direction you want to throw.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Releasing the Ball</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Whip your throwing arm forward. As you continue to lean forward, use your shoulder muscles and bicep to whip your arm forward. Lean your body into the pitch, and let your arm fully extend itself. <figure rend="Throw a Ball Faster Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Even after the ball has left your hand, it’s important to continue this forward momentum. This will help you follow through on the pitch.</item></list></item>
<item>Snap your wrist forward as the ball moves past your face. Your wrist can add a great deal of speed to the ball as you throw it. Begin the snap when your arm is about 2/3 through the pitching motion. At this point, the ball should be roughly  in front of your face. <figure rend="Throw a Ball Faster Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Figuring out exactly when to snap your wrist will take some practice. If you snap your wrist forward too early, the ball will fly down towards the ground. Too late, and the snap will be ineffective.</item>
<item>Your wrist and fingers can also make fine-tuning adjustments to the direction the ball is heading.</item></list></item>
<item>Pull down on the ball with your fingers as you release. Release the ball when your arm is parallel to the ground and fully extended in front of you. Your fingers play an important role in a pitch: they can add an extra boost of speed to the ball before you release it from your hand. To add a little extra speed, press your fingers down on the ball at the exact moment of release. <figure rend="Throw a Ball Faster Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The added pressure will propel the ball slightly faster than it would’ve gone otherwise.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Learning to improve the speed of your throw takes time. Don’t give up if you don’t notice greater speed on your throws at first.</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
