<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc51" title="Train for Steeplechase" shortTile="train-steeplechase" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-01-01" dateModified="2017-04-10" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Train_for_Steeplechase" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Train for Steeplechase</head><p>Steeplechase is a grueling, difficult track and field event that takes a lot of preparation and willpower. However, if you train safely and correctly, it can be a rewarding and fun race.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Start training on flat courses. The first part of training for steeplechase is to build up your endurance. Whether you're running the 2000m or 3200, building up your endurance is the most important part of your training. <figure rend="Train for Steeplechase Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Start preparing early! Steeplechase is most popular in the spring, so start your distance/endurance training in early to mid winter.</item></list></item>
<item>Learn how to hurdle. There are 5 steeples (barriers) per lap that must be hurdled or jumped onto. Since these cannot be knocked over, it is easier to begin training with conventional hurdles. <figure rend="Train for Steeplechase Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Ask someone with experience for tips about doing drills and perfecting form.</item>
<item>There are many videos on YouTube that help people see what a good hurdling form is. It helps to record yourself hurdling and use it for comparison! <figure rend="Train for Steeplechase Step 2Bullet2.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Learn how to jump off of a barrier. Once per lap, the barrier will be in front of a water pit that you will try to clear. Although clearing the water pit every time takes many years of practice, having a strong leap off of the barrier in front of it will help tremendously. <figure rend="Train for Steeplechase Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Stride towards the barrier (on a track, turf field, sand pit, or other softer surface) and jump, landing on top with the heel of one foot. Roll your landing foot forward and spring off! Make sure your trail leg is still in correct hurdling form, or you'll hit the barrier and fall.</item></list></item>
<item>Practice longer runs on the track with hurdles. Do intervals of 400m, alternating hurdling and not hurdling. <figure rend="Train for Steeplechase Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Eventually, practice your race. Set up the barriers and water pit, and run as if you were in a race. Ideally, this should take place 1-2 weeks before your race. <figure rend="Train for Steeplechase Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Preparing for your race
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure you eat a proper 'distance runners' meal' the night before your race.</item>
<item>Have the proper gear: most runners prefer spandex shorts (as they provide flexibility), a well-fitting tank top shirt, a towel, a supportive sports bra (for females), and steeplechase spikes (regular track spikes work fine too, but steeplechase spikes allow water drainage). Most runners will avoid wearing socks, as they become weighed down with water, and will even leave behind their underwear for the same reason! <figure rend="Train for Steeplechase Step 6Bullet2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Since steeple is usually the first event at track and field meets, be sure to arrive early to begin your warmup. <figure rend="Train for Steeplechase Step 6Bullet3.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>After the race: be sure to cool down and eat carbs and protein! Keep training for your next race. <figure rend="Train for Steeplechase Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Endurance training is the most important part of your training. Be sure to have a strong foundation in distance running. Although the race is relatively short, it's immensely more difficult because of the barriers and water pit.</item>
<item>Set goals. The first time you race, do your best and see where you stand. Use your first time to set a goal for your second time, as you would in any other event. But remember to be realistic, as to not discourage yourself. Goals are meant to motivate!</item>
<item>If hurdling the barriers every time becomes too tiring or difficult, some runners find it easier to jump off of them as they would with the barrier in front of the water pit.</item>
<item>Do not become discouraged if you fall into the water pit or trip over a barrier! Everyone who races steeplechase will do that more than once. The best thing to do is pick yourself up and keep on running!</item>
<item>After your race, be sure to towel off and change out of your wet clothes!</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be sure to complete a concussion test online.</item>
<item>Make sure your shoes fit well and the spikes are screwed in tightly.</item>
<item>Be careful to get out of the way of other runners if you fall -- it wouldn't be fun to get trampled by people wearing spiked shoes.</item>
<item>Have a first aid kit ready in the event that you scrape your knee, elbow, or hand if you fall.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Training shoes. They should be well-fitting and cushioning, as most of your training will be distance.</item>
<item>Racing flats. These shoes have the minimal amount of material and often have spikes that can be screwed into the bottoms to aid in your stride. Steeplechase spikes have holes to allow water to drain out of them more quickly, but regular racing flats (worn without socks) will also suit the race.</item>
<item>Spandex shorts</item>
<item>Your team's jersey or a tank-top racing shirt</item>
<item>A supportive sports bra</item>
<item>A towel</item></list>
</text>
