<text id="autogum_wikihow_doc288" title="Keep a Health Journal" shortTile="keep-health-journal" type="wikihow" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-05-01" dateModified="2019-06-17" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Keep_a_Health_Journal" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Keep a Health Journal</head><p>A health journal or diary helps one keep track of any relevant information about his wellness in general. It is kept mostly by people who have chronic conditions to monitor the progression of the disease, to note the presence of new symptoms, and to keep track of medications. But a perfectly healthy person may wish to make a health journal as well, in preparation for unforeseen health crises that may arise.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Record basic health information. You should include: <figure rend="Keep a Health Journal Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Birthday. Sometimes age matters in the diagnosis and treatment of disease.</item>
<item>Height and Weight.</item>
<item>Blood Type.</item>
<item>Blood pressure, cardiac rate, and respiratory rate. Establish baseline data so you can identify sudden changes.</item>
<item>Allergies. This is important because upon admission to a hospital you won't normally be tested for allergies unless the physician feels the need to. Let your healthcare providers know what your allergies are to avoid accidents.</item>
<item>Smoking or alcohol-drinking habits.</item>
<item>Treatments for or rehabilitation from substance, alcohol, or other forms of addiction.</item>
<item>Past surgical procedures. Indicate also if you have prosthetics or bone pins.</item>
<item>Past and present medications.</item></list></item>
<item>Write about what you know of your family's medical history. Things like heart diseases, Alzheimer's, mental disorders, and other diseases should be noted. Try to be as detailed as possible- indicate the specific person who has or had the disease, which side of the family it is from, etc. <figure rend="Keep a Health Journal Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Identify what you are feeling and record it. And when you felt it, date, time, etc. You should write down things like recurring weakness or pain in a specific parts of the body, difficulty breathing when in a certain position, sudden changes in perception, and other things that you do not normally experience or those that are "not right" in your opinion. <figure rend="Keep a Health Journal Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be specific. For example, if you can pinpoint the specific location and characteristic (sharp, dull, constant, intermittent) of pain, record it.</item></list></item>
<item>Record whatever you did in response to what you felt. Did you take aspirin for the sudden headache you got? Write it down. Did you try out an herb you read about in the Internet? Mention it in  your health diary. <figure rend="Keep a Health Journal Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep track of your medical appointments. List the reasons for your trip to the doctor, what your healthcare provider did for you, the efficacy of the treatment or prescribed drug given, and any adverse reactions you had to the treatment or medication. <figure rend="Keep a Health Journal Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take your health diary with you if you are going to be admitted to a healthcare facility or if you are going on vacation somewhere you don't have friends or close relatives who know about your health history nearby. <figure rend="Keep a Health Journal Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be honest and accurate.</item>
<item>If you begin to see a downward trend and feel like your health is declining, seek medical attention.</item>
<item>A health diary is a great tool to monitor your health at home.</item>
<item>Write as if you were telling someone else the situation, you may not remember things later even if they seem very obvious now.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be cautious about self-treatment.</item></list>
</text>
